<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Declining Stars, In to Have Their Heads Shrunk</title>
    <meta content="18head" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/arts/television/18head.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841095"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Stephanopoulos, George</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Priestley, Jason</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Skye, Ione</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E6DE1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="654" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Declining Stars, In to Have Their Heads Shrunk</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Declining Stars, in to Have Their Heads Shrunk</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINIA BELLAFANTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bellafante, Ginia</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Head Case'' is a new comedy with a relatively languorous pace and no laugh track -- the kind of show that, like Larry David's or Ricky Gervais's, wants to remind you what a fount of abasement daily existence actually is. It stars Alexandra Wentworth, the actress and comedian (and wife of George Stephanopoulos), who also writes for the show. And it revolves around a therapist's office in Los Angeles, a premise fairly easy to imagine taking off in as many predictable directions as there are routes to the Staples Center.</p>
        <p>But ''Head Case,'' which begins tonight on Starz, is pretty funny even as it travels some obvious roads. Ms. Wentworth plays Dr. Elizabeth Goode, a therapist who possesses neither sympathy nor understanding, insisting instead on bamboozling her patients into believing that they have issues they actually don't. Ms. Wentworth works against her own potentially winsome appearance to look hard and vaguely deranged. She shares an office with a fellow clinician, Dr. Myron Finkelstein (Steve Landesberg), with whom she refuses to share her Diptyque candles in the waiting room. A giant art photograph of a screaming toddler hangs behind her receptionist's desk.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“Head Case,” which features Alexandra Wentworth as a shrink for the known but barely employed, reminds us that celebrities whose fortunes have dwindled seem to have an endless capacity to make fun of themselves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Head Case'' is a new comedy with a relatively languorous pace and no laugh track -- the kind of show that, like Larry David's or Ricky Gervais's, wants to remind you what a fount of abasement daily existence actually is. It stars Alexandra Wentworth, the actress and comedian (and wife of George Stephanopoulos), who also writes for the show. And it revolves around a therapist's office in Los Angeles, a premise fairly easy to imagine taking off in as many predictable directions as there are routes to the Staples Center.</p>
        <p>But ''Head Case,'' which begins tonight on Starz, is pretty funny even as it travels some obvious roads. Ms. Wentworth plays Dr. Elizabeth Goode, a therapist who possesses neither sympathy nor understanding, insisting instead on bamboozling her patients into believing that they have issues they actually don't. Ms. Wentworth works against her own potentially winsome appearance to look hard and vaguely deranged. She shares an office with a fellow clinician, Dr. Myron Finkelstein (Steve Landesberg), with whom she refuses to share her Diptyque candles in the waiting room. A giant art photograph of a screaming toddler hangs behind her receptionist's desk.</p>
        <p>Part of the idea here is that Finkelstein finds himself constantly in a jealous rage because he gets to see only losers -- aging nutcases who can't speak English and very small children -- while Goode sees famous losers. She is the ''it'' shrink for the known but barely employed. The patients (and this is where things become a bit too easy) are celebrities playing themselves, not Kate Winslet-level celebrities, but the fallen ones who might seem unfamiliar even to viewers of reality TV.</p>
        <p>Jason Priestley is among those, reduced in stature, who show up. He goes to see Goode to talk about his relatively happy marriage. But when he does, she responds by asking if he is gay, because that's the idea she got watching ''Beverly Hills 90210.''</p>
        <p>''How does it feel,'' she says, prompted by nothing, ''to be perceived as a homosexual?'' Taking the inquiry further, she has him dress up in women's clothes just to see what it would feel like.</p>
        <p>The best moment in the first few episodes comes during an exchange with Ione Skye, who talks to Goode about her repeated dreams about a rabbi, especially one in which the rabbi refuses her entry into a sale at Fred Segal, the West Hollywood clothing store favored by the industry's actively successful. ''Fred Segal is a Jewish man, right? Is he Daddy, maybe?'' Goode asks. ''And why do you think he chained the store?'' To this Ms. Skye deadpans, ''I think, I feel, I don't deserve, even, you know, things on sale.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Skye, who most recently appeared in a tiny role in the film ''Zodiac,'' looks beautiful. ''Head Case'' reminds us that while celebrities whose fortunes have dwindled seem to have an endless capacity to make fun of themselves, their circumstances are still generally enviable, or at least a lot more enviable than those of a laid-off Citigroup worker.</p>
        <p>If ''Head Case'' feels somehow less than what it ought to be, it is because Ms. Wentworth, unlike comedians trafficking in a similar vein, refuses to jump into the humiliation pool she keeps filling. She has built a show a lot more self-serving than, for instance, ''Extras,'' on which Mr. Gervais seems as eager to embrace his abjection as a runner is to win a race. Ms. Wentworth is not above her celebrity guests; they are her mirror.</p>
        <p>Head Case  Starz, tonight at 11, Eastern and Pacific times; 10, Central.</p>
        <p>Directed by Jason Farrand. A co-production of Starz Entertainment and UNCLE Film + Television. Robert Bauer, Eric Bonniot, Alexandra Wentworth and Mr. Farrand, executive producers for UNCLE. Stephan Shelanski, Michael Ruggiero and Robert Markovich, executive producers for Starz Entertainment.</p>
        <p>WITH: Ms. Wentworth (Dr. Elizabeth Goode); Steve Landesberg (Dr. Myron Finkelstein) and Michelle Arthur (Lola Buckingham).</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
