<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>N.H.L. Ratings Are All Over the Ice</title>
    <meta content="18sandomir" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841209"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TV SPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E4DB1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="568" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>N.H.L. Ratings Are All Over the Ice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is the time of year to contemplate National Hockey League viewership.</p>
        <p>It is time to wonder why Versus, in Year 2 of its N.H.L. deal, watched its viewership swell 31 percent over the 2005-6 regular season but has lost 6 percent of its postseason audience, reaching an average of 267,720 a game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is the time of year to contemplate National Hockey League viewership.</p>
        <p>It is time to wonder why Versus, in Year 2 of its N.H.L. deal, watched its viewership swell 31 percent over the 2005-6 regular season but has lost 6 percent of its postseason audience, reaching an average of 267,720 a game.</p>
        <p>And it is time to note how the National Heads-Up Poker Championship on NBC last Sunday (with matches won by Don Cheadle and Gabe Kaplan) drew better than the Calgary-Detroit playoff game immediately after.</p>
        <p>(Note to NBC: Drop intermission interviews and add speed stud.)</p>
        <p>The N.H.L. remains a league in recovery from the 2004-5 lockout and the miscalculations that led to the labor strife. So it is not surprising that it continues to struggle to rebuild its United States viewership. Nationally, for example, NBC's regular-season average viewership of 1.34 million is but 45 percent of the 2.9 million in more glorious days on Fox 11 years ago.</p>
        <p>''Is there a prospect for monumental growth in ratings? No,'' Bill Daly, the league's deputy commissioner, said yesterday in a telephone interview. ''Do we have what we consider good growth prospects in this environment? Yes.''</p>
        <p>There is some hope that more viewers will watch the playoffs than they have so far in the first round. Three New York-area teams are involved, and while the Islanders and the Devils mean little nationally, the presence of the Rangers, who are leading Atlanta, 3-0, in their series after last night's game, can be viewed only positively.</p>
        <p>''It's nice to have a revival in hockey in New York, in a market where the Rangers hadn't won a playoff game before this year in 10 years,'' Daly said.</p>
        <p>Still, it is odd that the Rangers' game on NBC on Saturday generated a rating in the New York market 38 percent less than that of the Samsung 500 at Texas Motor Speedway on Sunday. Are there really more Nascar lovers than Rangers fans around town?</p>
        <p>More positives: the Penguins, with Sidney Crosby, the league's best and best-known player, are in the playoffs, which they did not reach last year; and if Detroit wins its series against Calgary, the Red Wings will attract viewers from a reliably strong market (while Calgary doesn't count in United States viewership calculations). And one more thing: Don Cherry, the plaid-wearing, brawl-loving Canadian blabbermouth, will join NBC's studio show for the Stanley Cup finals.</p>
        <p>The league would be ecstatic if its TV audience grew from the regular season to the playoffs as it has with the New York area's three teams. The number of households watching Devils games on FSNY has soared from an average of only 17,000 in the regular season to 58,000; Islanders games on FSNY have been witnessed in the playoffs by an average of 51,000 homes, up from 10,000; and the one Ranger game on MSG was seen in 103,000 homes, up from a regular-season average of 48,000.</p>
        <p>Last month, the N.H.L. renewed its revenue-sharing deal with NBC for one season and wants to help Versus expand its subscriber base beyond 72 million. Daly said the league was also pushing non-TV options like videos streamed on YouTube and NHL.com to reach young, passionate fans -- even if they watch a bunch of bites instead of two-and-a-half-hour games.</p>
        <p>''Conventional TV is still a priority, but people are consuming our content in smaller pieces,'' he said.</p>
        <p>TV SPORTS E-mail: sportsbiz@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: sportsbiz@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
