<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Extra Practice for Jeter, But No Hint of Doubt</title>
    <meta content="18jeter" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/sports/baseball/18jeter.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841242"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cleveland Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Cleveland Indians</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Jeter, Derek</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03EEDB1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="867" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Extra Practice for Jeter, But No Hint of Doubt</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Few Errors for Jeter, but No Doubts</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Derek Jeter fielded a grounder and then another and then another. His movements were the same. His glove touched the dirt, his right hand was a few inches above his glove, his knees were bent and his eyes were focused on the approaching ball.</p>
        <p>This scene unfolded again and again yesterday at an empty Yankee Stadium. More than three hours before the Yankees played the Cleveland Indians and about an hour before the rest of the Yankees joined Jeter for batting practice, he put in extra work in front of the ushers and security guards.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Derek Jeter has committed six errors in the first 12 games. Yet he stressed that his pregame preparation was unrelated to the problems he has endured at shortstop.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Derek Jeter fielded a grounder and then another and then another. His movements were the same. His glove touched the dirt, his right hand was a few inches above his glove, his knees were bent and his eyes were focused on the approaching ball.</p>
        <p>This scene unfolded again and again yesterday at an empty Yankee Stadium. More than three hours before the Yankees played the Cleveland Indians and about an hour before the rest of the Yankees joined Jeter for batting practice, he put in extra work in front of the ushers and security guards.</p>
        <p>While Jeter's pregame preparation seemed purposeful, he insisted it was unrelated to the problems he has endured at shortstop. Jeter has committed six errors in the first 12 games, more than any major leaguer, but he stressed that he often participates in early workouts after a day off.</p>
        <p>''I'm just doing this because we haven't been out there,'' Jeter said.</p>
        <p>Still, even if Jeter depicted his actions as normal, there was something noteworthy about a three-time Gold Glove Award winner spearing grounders on a barren field and in wet, windy conditions. Third baseman Alex Rodriguez also worked with Larry Bowa, the third-base coach, but Jeter outlasted him by several minutes.</p>
        <p>Jeter, who is in his 12th season as a starting shortstop, knows there was speculation in his rookie season that he would eventually have to switch to third base or the outfield. But Jeter is still entrenched at short and still playing the most important infield position for the Yankees, who won, 10-3, last night.</p>
        <p>Three of Jeter's errors have been on throws and three have been on balls that he bobbled or flubbed. Jeter said he was not pleased with those results. But, as he recounted a throw that was almost scooped at first base and another errant throw that followed a difficult stop, Jeter emphasized that he did not feel trapped in a slump.</p>
        <p>''Do I believe you can be in a defensive slump?'' Jeter said. ''Yeah, you can. But do I think I'm in one? No.''</p>
        <p>Manager Joe Torre said there are some things that Jeter does as well or better than any shortstop. Torre said Jeter is adept at rushing in to snare slow rollers, and that Jeter is ''as good as I've seen'' at corralling pop flies behind him. Torre cringed while mentioning Jeter's solid yet scary jump throws from the hole.</p>
        <p>But, as athletic as Jeter is, he has flaws, too. Jeter does not have as much range to his left as he does to his right, and he can be streaky.</p>
        <p>''As I say, he may not be as fluid as other people when they make plays,'' Torre said. ''But Derek has a presence out there and, again, he seems to be in control all the time.''</p>
        <p>Almost on cue after Torre's remarks, Jeter was in total control on one stylish play in the third. Víctor Martínez hit a grounder to the left of the pitcher's mound. Jeter scooted over and grabbed the ball before it slithered into the outfield. He pivoted, did a 360-degree turn, jumped and made a nifty one-bounce throw to first. The lumbering Martínez was easily nabbed.</p>
        <p>So, on Martínez's ball, Jeter's range to his left was not suspect. On other plays, Jeter has doubters. In the 2007 ''Bill James Handbook,'' there is a statistic called range factor. It is defined as the number of successful chances (putouts plus assists) times nine and divided by the number of innings played. Jeter's range factor was 4.14 in 2006, which was 25th among the 30 regular shortstops in the major leagues. Not surprisingly, Jeter dismissed that analysis.</p>
        <p>''They think they have a mathematical equation that figures everything out,'' Jeter said. ''Like every single person is out there with the same runner and the same pitcher and the ball is hit in the same exact place. It seems like once somebody says one thing about you, people tend to run with it and we never hear the end of it.''</p>
        <p>Torre said he was not concerned with Jeter's defense and instead lauded the intangibles he offers.</p>
        <p>''The lack of fear and the lack of being afraid to fail is, to me, it works to his advantage,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>There was no pressure as Jeter, wearing a blue hooded sweat shirt, stood yesterday in the infield where the grass first touches the dirt yesterday. He fielded 12 grounders flawlessly, shouting, ''Ouch,'' after his initial throw.</p>
        <p>Then Jeter retreated to his normal depth and fielded 31 more grounders without a miscue. An hour later, Jeter rumbled through a set of 29 grounders, finally botching one that was to his left.</p>
        <p>Obviously, it was Bowa hitting the balls to Jeter, not a power hitter like Travis Hafner. There is no comparison between fielding predictable pregame grounders and fielding in a game. But, even though it was only a practice session, Jeter was out there for a reason.</p>
        <p>''There have been times when you feel uncomfortable, you make errors and you know you have something to work on,'' Jeter said. ''But I feel comfortable, believe it or not. It's just that I've had some errors.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
