<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Cup Bidding Is Brazil's to Lose</title>
    <meta content="18soccer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/sports/soccer/18soccer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841198"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER: EXTRA TIME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">World Cup (Soccer)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Cup (Soccer)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brazil</location>
        <org class="online_producer">FIFA</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E6DB1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1021" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Cup Bidding Is Brazil's to Lose</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">World Cup Bidding Is Brazil's to Lose</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK BELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bell, Jack</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Brazil has won five World Cup titles and exports hundreds of players to leagues around the world but has played host to only one World Cup tournament, in 1950 (losing in the final to Uruguay). If statements from FIFA headquarters in Zurich are credible, it will be awarded the 2014 World Cup later this year -- probably.</p>
        <p>''The concept of Brazil, or someone else from South America, is not a problem,'' Chuck Blazer, the only American member of FIFA's powerful executive committee and the general secretary of Concacaf, said during a telephone interview from Las Vegas, where he was attending the National Association of Broadcasters convention last weekend.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If statements from FIFA headquarters in Zurich are credible, Brazil will be awarded the 2014 World Cup later this year  probably.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Brazil has won five World Cup titles and exports hundreds of players to leagues around the world but has played host to only one World Cup tournament, in 1950 (losing in the final to Uruguay). If statements from FIFA headquarters in Zurich are credible, it will be awarded the 2014 World Cup later this year -- probably.</p>
        <p>''The concept of Brazil, or someone else from South America, is not a problem,'' Chuck Blazer, the only American member of FIFA's powerful executive committee and the general secretary of Concacaf, said during a telephone interview from Las Vegas, where he was attending the National Association of Broadcasters convention last weekend.</p>
        <p>Concacaf, based in Manhattan, represents 40 national associations in North and Central America and the Caribbean.</p>
        <p>''One of the reasons the World Cup has grown has been the level of competition in the bidding,'' Blazer said. ''It would have been better if the South Americans had not rushed in and made Brazil the singular bidder. It is unusual that there is no one to bid against them. It's my opinion that candidates often build on unsuccessful bids. Look at London and the Olympics, and South Africa, which had bid twice before getting the 2010 World Cup.''</p>
        <p>Colombia contemplated bidding for the World Cup but dropped out before last week's deadline. That left only Brazil from a 10-nation confederation that has not had the World Cup since Argentina in 1978. Brazil faces significant hurdles because most of its stadiums are in disrepair, and the costs of renovation or construction could be prohibitive. After an inspection in September, FIFA officials will meet in November (instead of the middle of next year) to approve Brazil's bid or consider alternative sites, which could include the United States, Mexico or perhaps Canada.</p>
        <p>''If things are not satisfactory, then the bidding would be opened up,'' Blazer said. ''But I don't expect that to be the case. I would be surprised if it's not in Brazil.</p>
        <p>''I was the one who initiated the earlier date. Rather than leaving the normal six-year window, this will give us a little more time. Our standards have risen, and presently it's recognized that their stadiums are not at the level needed for the World Cup.''</p>
        <p>As an advocate for Concacaf, Blazer has accepted the concept of rotating the World Cup among the six regional confederations of FIFA, the sport's world governing body. FIFA statutes preclude any confederation from playing host to consecutive World Cups, a situation that rankles Europeans. After a South American country in 2014, a North American nation would be expected to play host to the 2018 tournament, if the rotation system was maintained.</p>
        <p>In recent months, however, England has announced its intention to break the rotation and to bid for the 2018 tournament.</p>
        <p>''We had Asia in '02, Europe in '06, Africa in '10 and South America in '14,'' Blazer said. ''I think at this point that if you're going to make any changes, they should start in 2022, leaving '18 to the one confederation, Concacaf, that stood by quietly and allowed the process to go through and finish the complete cycle. All of a sudden there is this bid from England. We don't want to get sloshed over and see England simply jump in.''</p>
        <p>Copa Libertadores</p>
        <p>Two Brazilian teams -- Flamengo in Group 5 and Santos in Group 8 -- have clinched spots in the first knockout stage, with six more teams to be determined in matches in South America tonight and tomorrow night. The top two teams in each of the eight groups move to the Round of 16 in the continent's top club competition. (The remaining eight teams will be determined after games next week.)</p>
        <p>In Group 1, Libertad (Paraguay), Banfield (Argentina) and Club América (Mexico) are separated by a point. América has a good chance to win the group going into tonight's match against El Nacional (Ecuador), which is in last place. Banfield plays host to Libertad.</p>
        <p>In Group 4 tomorrow, Internacional (Brazil), the defending Copa and Club World Cup champion, has 7 points (minus-1 goal differential) and needs to beat group-leading Nacional (Uruguay), which has 10 points (plus-5 differential), by a significant margin to have a chance to advance. Second-place Vélez Sarsfield (Argentina), with 8 points, plays host to last-place Emelec (Ecuador).</p>
        <p>In Group 5, Bamin Real Potosí (Bolivia) and Paraná (Brazil) are tied for second behind Flamengo, even on goal differential. Flamengo plays host to Bamin and Paraná plays in Venezuela against last-place U.A. Maracaibo.</p>
        <p>In Group 8, Defensor Sporting (Uruguay) plays at Gimnasia (Argentina). Defensor has 9 points to Gimnasia's 6, and has a plus-4 differential to Gimnasia's minus-4.</p>
        <p>Notes</p>
        <p>The American billionaire Stan Kroenke, who recently bought a 9.9 percent interest in Arsenal of the English Premier League for $129 million from ITV, increased his stake last week to 11.26 percent. Kroenke's Colorado Rapids of Major League Soccer recently announced a partnership with Arsenal. Kroenke also owns the N.B.A.'s Denver Nuggets, the N.H.L.'s Colorado Avalanche, half of the N.F.L.'s St. Louis Rams, an Arena League football team and a professional lacrosse team.</p>
        <p>Manchester United has re-signed the Portuguese wing Cristiano Ronaldo, 22, to a new contract through 2012 that will pay him more than $12 million a year. Ronaldo had been pursued by Real Madrid.  United and Chelsea are competing for the same three titles. The clubs will play in the final of the English F.A. Cup on May 19 at the new Wembley Stadium, they have advanced to the semifinals of the European Champions League, and United leads Chelsea by 6 points in the Premier League (Chelsea has a game in hand).</p>
        <p>Coach Greg Ryan and the captain, Kristine Lilly, will represent the United States at the draw for the Women's World Cup on Sunday in Wuhan, China. The 16-team tournament will be Sept. 10-30 in five Chinese cities.</p>
        <p>Joseph Lapira, a striker for Notre Dame who won the Hermann Trophy last year, will travel to Scotland in August for a tryout with Aberdeen of the Scottish Premier League. Irish Coach Bobby Clarke was a goalkeeper for the club.</p>
        <p>SOCCER: EXTRA TIME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
