<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Builder of Sallie Mae Deal Has a Daring History</title>
    <meta content="18flowers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/business/18flowers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841136"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Slm Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Flowers, J C, Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Friedman Fleischer &amp; Lowe</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Morgan, J P, Chase &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bank of America</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">De La Merced, Michael J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edmonston, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flowers, J Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Sallie Mae</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Flowers, J Christopher</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E4DD1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="819" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Builder of Sallie Mae Deal Has a Daring History</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Builder of Sallie Mae Deal Has a Daring History</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL J. de la MERCED and PETER EDMONSTON</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>J Christopher Flowers, architect of $25 billion deal to take Sallie Mae private, has had history of daring financial challenges; Flowers's firm J C Flowers &amp; Co has engineered largest leveraged buyout of financial services company; Flowers and private equity firm Friedman Fleischer &amp; Lowe will invest $4.4 billion in Sallie Mae and control 50.2 percent of company, officially known as SLM Corp; J P Morgan Chase and Bank of America will acquire rest and provide financing for transaction; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As a financial company, and one that began as a government-created company, Sallie Mae was an unlikely candidate for a leveraged buyout.</p>
        <p>But the architect of this week's $25 billion deal to take Sallie Mae private, J. Christopher Flowers, has had a history of daring financial challenges.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>J. Christopher Flowers, the architect of the $25 billion deal to take Sallie Mae private, has had a history of daring financial challenges.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As a financial company, and one that began as a government-created company, Sallie Mae was an unlikely candidate for a leveraged buyout.</p>
        <p>But the architect of this week's $25 billion deal to take Sallie Mae private, J. Christopher Flowers, has had a history of daring financial challenges.</p>
        <p>His previous investments have included one of Japan's biggest banks, which had struggled with trillions of yen in bad loans, and a mobile-home lender whose parent was mired in one of the largest corporate bankruptcies in history.</p>
        <p>Now with Sallie Mae, the nation's largest student loan provider, his firm, J. C. Flowers &amp; Company, has engineered what would be the largest leveraged buyout of a financial services company.</p>
        <p>J. C. Flowers and another private equity firm, Friedman Fleischer &amp; Lowe, will invest $4.4 billion in Sallie Mae and control 50.2 percent of the company, officially known as the SLM Corporation. JPMorgan Chase and Bank of America will acquire the rest and will provide the financing for the transaction.</p>
        <p>''At least by our standards, this is a rapidly growing company serving an important demographic group, and we found that very attractive,'' Mr. Flowers said in an interview, adding that he took a victory lap on the running path around the Central Park Reservoir in New York on Monday.</p>
        <p>Sallie Mae faces challenges on several fronts, including threats by Congress and President Bush to cut the federal subsidies and guarantees that have fueled its 35-year growth. Mr. Flowers said that he looked forward to meeting with Congress in the coming months to assuage any concerns.</p>
        <p>Mr. Flowers, 49, who founded Goldman Sachs's lucrative financial services merger business, has built his fortune by investing in distressed financial firms.</p>
        <p>Yet he contends that he fell into financial services by chance. After joining the investment bank as a generalist in 1979, he was moved into the financial institutions group soon thereafter -- and soon it became too late to change.</p>
        <p>Timothy C. Collins, the chief executive of Ripplewood Holdings, said of Mr. Flowers: ''He probably knows more about financial services deals than just about anybody I ever met.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Collins should know. In 2000, he and Mr. Flowers led the group that acquired the Long-Term Credit Bank of Japan for $1.2 billion, after it collapsed. Ripplewood, Mr. Flowers and their partners became the first foreigners to take control of a Japanese bank.</p>
        <p>Shortly after Mr. Flowers left Goldman Sachs in 1998. Mr. Collins offered Mr. Flowers the office next to his in Ripplewood's headquarters in Rockefeller Plaza in Manhattan. The two began looking at potential targets in Japan before independently identifying Long-Term Credit as a possibility.</p>
        <p>Both profited handsomely when Long-Term Credit, rechristened Shinsei Bank, went public in 2004.</p>
        <p>While he acknowledged that the deal for Sallie Mae was complicated, Mr. Flowers said that it had one advantage over the Long-Term Credit transaction.</p>
        <p>''One thing about Sallie Mae is it's in the United States,'' he said. ''Not quite in New York, but at least it's in the same time zone.''</p>
        <p>J. C. Flowers will take a 49.2 percent stake, while Bank of America and JPMorgan will each take 24.9 percent. The other private equity firm, Friedman Fleischer &amp; Lowe of San Francisco, will take 1 percent; one of its founders is Tully M. Friedman, perhaps better known as the co-founder of the larger buyout firm Hellman &amp; Friedman.</p>
        <p>Mr. Flowers has made more headlines since the Shinsei deal. In 2005, J. C. Flowers led a group offering to buy the futures brokerage business of Refco out of bankruptcy. But the firm withdrew the $768 million bid after a bankruptcy judge said he would approve the deal only if fees were lowered.</p>
        <p>Mr. Flowers has had more success in other deals. In 2003, J. C. Flowers joined with two hedge funds to buy the lending arm of the insurance company Conseco out of bankruptcy for $850 million.</p>
        <p>Last year, the firm joined with the employees of a New York-based investment bank, Fox-Pitt, Kelton, a specialist in financial institutions, to buy it , from Swiss Re for an undisclosed price.</p>
        <p>At Goldman Sachs, Mr. Flowers had established himself as a pre-eminent banker; on his résumé are the $61.6 billion merger of Nationsbank and Bank America (now Bank of America, one of his partners in the Sallie Mae deal) and the $34.4 billion takeover of Wells Fargo by Norwest.</p>
        <p>His deal-making extends beyond financial services. Last year, Mr. Flowers was reported to be the buyer of the Harkness Mansion on the Upper East Side of Manhattan, a $53 million transaction that set a New York record for a single residential property.</p>
        <p>He also paid $19 million for another co-op in the same neighborhood.</p>
        <p>Mr. Flowers, a native of the Boston area, spends leisure time playing chess and squash, as well as sailing in the waters of Maine, where he has a house.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
