<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Iraq's Public Health Services Severely Strained, Group Says</title>
    <meta content="18health" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/world/middleeast/18health.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841133"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE REACH OF WAR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <org class="online_producer">World Health Organization</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E4DD1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="568" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Iraq's Public Health Services Severely Strained, Group Says</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Iraq’s Public Health Services Severely Strained, Group Says</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH ROSENTHAL</byline>
      <dateline>ROME, April 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It goes without saying that war is bad for your health. But a compendium of new public health statistics, released Tuesday by the World Health Organization, quantifies just how desperate the situation has become for Iraqis.</p>
        <p>There are the obvious risks of car bombs and other violence that now kill an average of 100 people a day, according to the report from the W.H.O.'s Health Action in Crises group. But beyond that, there are a host of other problems created by years of conflict: 70 percent of Iraqis lack regular access to clean water, and 80 percent lack toilets that do not contaminate water sources, according to the report.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New health statistics from the World Health Organization quantifies just how desperate the situation has become for Iraqis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It goes without saying that war is bad for your health. But a compendium of new public health statistics, released Tuesday by the World Health Organization, quantifies just how desperate the situation has become for Iraqis.</p>
        <p>There are the obvious risks of car bombs and other violence that now kill an average of 100 people a day, according to the report from the W.H.O.'s Health Action in Crises group. But beyond that, there are a host of other problems created by years of conflict: 70 percent of Iraqis lack regular access to clean water, and 80 percent lack toilets that do not contaminate water sources, according to the report.</p>
        <p>As a result of these multiple public-health failings, diarrhea and respiratory infections now account for two-thirds of the deaths of children under five, the report said. Twenty-one percent of Iraqi children are now chronically malnourished, according to a 2006 national survey conducted by Unicef, which puts them at risk for both stunted growth and mental development.</p>
        <p>The statistics are being presented by the W.H.O. at an international meeting on Iraq on Tuesday and Wednesday at the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees in Geneva.</p>
        <p>''There has been so much violence for so long that the result is inevitably this kind of complete social decay,'' said Dr. Les Roberts, a principal researcher in a series of public health surveys on mortality among Iraqi citizens whose controversial results have been published in the British journal Lancet.</p>
        <p>He says he believes that some of the new data vastly underestimates the human tragedy. ''The W.H.O. has done a great job in walking a tightrope,'' said Dr. Roberts, who was formerly at the Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health and now heads the program on forced migration and health at Columbia University. ''They are telling the world that the Iraqi health situation is really bad and likely to get worse, but doing it within the political constraints of respecting government numbers.''</p>
        <p>He said, for example, that the report of 100 deaths a day from violence was ''a gross underestimate,'' placing the probable tally at several times higher.</p>
        <p>Dr. Khalid Shibib, of the W.H.O., said that most of the public health figures were ''better a few years ago'' because ''loss of electricity and displacement of people have led to a deterioration of our public services and lack of access.''</p>
        <p>''If the environmental situation continues to deteriorate, there will be increased diarrheal diseases, such as cholera,'' he said. ''Also, if there continues to be so many displaced people who are crowded together -- maybe living with relatives -- there will be a great rise in respiratory diseases, maybe even tuberculosis.''</p>
        <p>The Health Action in Crises group said doctors and nurses were fleeing the violence and chaos of Iraq, although Dr. Shibib said there were no official numbers. As a result, clinics and hospitals are understaffed and undersupplied.</p>
        <p>The report cites the Iraqi government as saying that almost 70 percent of critically injured patients die in the hospital because of lack of staff, drugs and equipment.</p>
        <p>To make matters worse, pregnant women and the injured and ill in parts of Iraq, including Baghdad, are afraid to risk the trip to the hospital for security reasons, the report said. Dr. Shibib said the problem was complicated by divisions between Shiites and Sunnis that led Iraqis to fear that they would not be treated at certain facilities.</p>
        <p>THE REACH OF WAR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
