<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judge Is Called Robed Robber Or Just the Victim of a Setup</title>
    <meta content="18judge" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/nyregion/18judge.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070421T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841143"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Video)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garson, Gerald P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siminovsky, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brick, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3DD1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="772" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judge Is Called Robed Robber Or Just the Victim of a Setup</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Judge Is Called Robed Robber or Just the Victim of a Setup</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL BRICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brick, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prosecutors in Brooklyn conclude their case against Gerald B Garson, former State Supreme Court justice accused of taking cash and gifts to manipulate divorce cases; built case around surveillance recordings, financial records and testimony of onetime officers of court to show judge had accepted money, cigars, meals and drinks in exchange for giving legal assignments and unfair advantages to favored lawyers, including Paul Siminovsky, disbarred divorce lawyer, who was central witness for prosecution; defense lawyer says prosecutors set judge up by sending divorce lawyer to proffer cash and gifts (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nearly half a decade after their investigation began, prosecutors in Brooklyn concluded their case yesterday against a former State Supreme Court justice accused of taking cash and gifts to manipulate divorce cases.</p>
        <p>The case against the ex-judge, Gerald P. Garson, led to a broad inquiry into political and judicial corruption in the borough, drawing scrutiny to systems of campaigning, patronage and judicial selection.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gerald P. Garson, a former State Supreme Court justice, is accused of taking cash and gifts to manipulate divorce cases.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nearly half a decade after their investigation began, prosecutors in Brooklyn concluded their case yesterday against a former State Supreme Court justice accused of taking cash and gifts to manipulate divorce cases.</p>
        <p>The case against the ex-judge, Gerald P. Garson, led to a broad inquiry into political and judicial corruption in the borough, drawing scrutiny to systems of campaigning, patronage and judicial selection.</p>
        <p>The district attorney, Charles J. Hynes, has pledged to show that judgeships were for sale in Brooklyn, a claim that first emerged after Justice Garson was confronted with the bribery evidence against him in 2003.</p>
        <p>Justice Garson, 74, was suspended from the bench and later resigned. He has been charged with accepting bribes and taking rewards for official misconduct, crimes that could lead to a maximum sentence of 31 years in prison. His trial was delayed while he sought treatment for cancer and while a pretrial ruling was appealed.</p>
        <p>Since it opened four weeks ago in State Supreme Court in Brooklyn, the trial has drawn a sizable audience, including people whose cases were handled by Justice Garson and members of the borough's legal establishment. The defendant's wife, Rachel Garson, a Civil Court judge, has sat in the front row, handing notes to defense lawyers.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors built a case based on surveillance recordings, financial records and the testimony of onetime officers of the court to show that Justice Garson had accepted cigars, money, meals and drinks in exchange for giving legal assignments and unfair advantages to favored lawyers.</p>
        <p>''Gerald Garson turned matrimonial Part 5B into his private piggy bank,'' said the lead prosecutor, Michael F. Vecchione, in his closing remarks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vecchione, who has managed the broader corruption inquiry, added, ''That makes Gerald Garson no better than the health inspector who turns the other way for 20 bucks when the rats have infested the restaurant.''</p>
        <p>The defendant did not testify, and defense lawyers called no witnesses, instead adding stipulations to the court record and trying to impugn the credibility of prosecution witnesses. The central witness -- Paul Siminovsky, a disbarred divorce lawyer who has pleaded guilty to giving unlawful gratuities -- was questioned and cross-examined across a span of two weeks.</p>
        <p>The lead defense lawyer, Michael S. Washor, gave a rollicking, somewhat jovial, sometimes accusatory closing argument, announcing that yesterday was his birthday, warning jurors that he might speak all day long and calling the prosecution ''ridiculous.''</p>
        <p>He taunted Mr. Vecchione, who had yet to begin his own closing argument, by accusing his team of suborning perjury, then apologizing one by one to the other three prosecutors but not to their leader. In Mr. Washor's telling, the prosecutors had scripted a case by sending a divorce lawyer to proffer cash and gifts. He called Mr. Siminovsky a ''weasel.''</p>
        <p>''This case started with a lie,'' he said, ''and ended with the prosecution creating the illusion of criminality.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Washor argued that his client had probably violated ethical rules, but said he had never agreed to give out courtroom benefits for the largess he received.</p>
        <p>''That man, Gerry Garson, he's not a judge anymore; he'll never be a judge again,'' Mr. Washor said. He added that though it pained him to say so, ''maybe Gerry Garson should never have been a judge in the first place.''</p>
        <p>When his turn came to speak, Mr. Vecchione stood a few feet from the jury. He spoke for more than an hour before taking a break, using casual words like ''freeloader'' and legal terminology like ''dispositive.''</p>
        <p>For several minutes, he expounded on the responsibilities stitched into the judicial robes, calling the former justice ''nothing short of a disgrace.''</p>
        <p>''He took his robing room and turned it into a robbing room,'' Mr. Vecchione said, counting among the victims those who had appeared in Justice Garson's court and citizens of Brooklyn who expect justice at the courthouse. He said Mr. Garson had committed his crimes for ''expensive cigars and cheap wine.''</p>
        <p>Conceding that Mr. Siminovsky was a criminal, Mr. Vecchione argued that his testimony provided a credible window into the defendant's inner sanctum. Before the divorce lawyer began cooperating with prosecutors, Mr. Vecchione said, he had already entertained Justice Garson more than 40 times, spending $3,149.</p>
        <p>''The only script followed here was written by the defendant,'' Mr. Vecchione argued. ''And you know the part he played in the script? Himself. Unfortunately, himself.''</p>
        <p>Jurors, he said, could infer an agreement between Justice Garson and his patrons from the evidence of his behavior. The jury is scheduled to return today to begin deliberating.</p>
        <p>''Crimes like this,'' Mr. Vecchione told them, ''are perpetrated with winks, with nods, with unspoken understandings.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 21, 2007, Saturday  An article on Wednesday about closing arguments in a corruption case against Gerald P. Garson, a former State Supreme Court justice in Brooklyn, misstated the name of his wife, a Brooklyn Civil Court judge who was in the courtroom. She is Robin Garson, not Rachel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 21, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article on Wednesday about closing arguments in a corruption case against Gerald P. Garson, a former State Supreme Court justice in Brooklyn, misstated the name of his wife, a Brooklyn Civil Court judge who was in the courtroom. She is Robin Garson, not Rachel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
