<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>8-Armed Cephalopods, 2-Armed Cretins</title>
    <meta content="18vecsey" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/sports/hockey/18vecsey.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841239"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Atlanta Thrashers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stanley Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stanley Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Islanders</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Potvin, Denis</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bossy, Mike</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05EEDB1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="915" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>8-Armed Cephalopods, 2-Armed Cretins</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">8-Armed Cephalopods, 2-Armed Cretins</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Almost an entire decade had gone by since the sound echoed through Madison Square Garden for a Stanley Cup playoff game -- like the rush of a freight train.</p>
        <p>The positive energy of the Garden seemed to propel the Rangers to the 7-0 humiliation of Atlanta last night, to take a three-games-to-none lead in a first-round series that does not seem likely to go any further than tonight's fourth game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the Islanders, the classy touches of the early ’80s seem long gone  on both sides of the barricade.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Almost an entire decade had gone by since the sound echoed through Madison Square Garden for a Stanley Cup playoff game -- like the rush of a freight train.</p>
        <p>The positive energy of the Garden seemed to propel the Rangers to the 7-0 humiliation of Atlanta last night, to take a three-games-to-none lead in a first-round series that does not seem likely to go any further than tonight's fourth game.</p>
        <p>Faced with the one-sided debacle, the Thrashers did what broken teams do; they gooned it up, with their better players, no less.</p>
        <p>I confess, however, that I was still thinking about the ugly spectacle in Nassau Coliseum on Monday night. In an arena with glorious memories, these latter-day louts were heaving bottles -- plastic and glass -- onto the ice, prompting my facetious question: Why can't hockey be a nice safe sport like soccer? Just asking.</p>
        <p>The Stanley Cup playoffs, virtually a different sport than regular-season hockey, have a huge share of wonderful traditions -- the bristles on the mugs of the players, the handshake lines after each series, even the octopuses flung to the ice in Detroit.</p>
        <p>Tossing an eight-armed cephalopod from the stands may sound icky to anybody not indoctrinated into the glorious legends of Red Wings hockey, but it is a lot more wholesome than what some denizens of the Nassau Coliseum were doing Monday.</p>
        <p>Islanders fans wear faded jerseys honoring Denis Potvin and Mike Bossy and the rest of that sensational team that won four straight Cups from 1980 through 1983 (best team I ever covered), but some current fans do not act as if anything classy ever rubbed off.</p>
        <p>The referees made a couple of painful penalty calls while the Islanders were losing to Buffalo, 3-2, to fall behind, two games to one. A couple of the calls were borderline, particularly the double-minor high-sticking call on Tom Poti in the second period, but the fans, having ingested a huge amount of beer, took it as an insult.</p>
        <p>A few glass bottles had been smuggled into the Coliseum, and they exploded on the ice, spewing various colored liquids. The plastic bottles, sold in the arena, bounced on the surface. Other stuff was thrown overboard, but no octopuses were sacrificed to the nasty cause.</p>
        <p>The Islanders say the arena management will add security for tonight's game, and the club will display a message on the scoreboard from Coach Ted Nolan asking fans ''to be passionate but to stay cool,'' said Chris Botta, the Islanders' vice president for media.</p>
        <p>This spectacle made me sad because I associate the gloomy barn on Hempstead Turnpike with magical nights in April and May. I recently downloaded a copy of Queen singing ''We Are the Champions'' and pasted it into my workout playlist.</p>
        <p>Every time I hear the music and lyrics (''We are the champions my friends; And we'll keep on fighting till the end''), I envision Stefan Persson and John Tonelli and Anders Kallur celebrating after another Stanley Cup. The song and the dynasty and the age have become linked in my nostalgic little brain.</p>
        <p>Not that it was all so wonderful. I still remember heading down to the locker room late in a Stanley Cup finals game against the Oilers and hearing some of our Long Island rednecks heap racial abuse on Grant Fuhr. Unable to resist having a conversation with some vicious, drunken bigots, I asked them why they had to act that way.</p>
        <p>''We're trying to help our team,'' one of them blustered.</p>
        <p>Apparently, some of them have multiplied and gone forth onto the Island, with their descendants heaving refuse onto the ice, nearly a quarter of a century later. Not everybody, mind you. Just a handful. Just enough to make the whole Islander experience a little less pleasant.</p>
        <p>The Coliseum was even gussied up with orange and blue balloons -- the most festive I had seen it in a first-round game. In the austere regime of Bill Torrey, when the Isles were sweeping through the playoffs for four years, there was barely a trace of frivolity in the Coliseum. Business as usual. There's something to be said for that.</p>
        <p>It's a long haul, although it is unclear whether the New York area will have a glut of hockey in weeks to come. Penalties or not, the Islanders seem to have hit their level (eighth-best record in the East) after a surprising win in Buffalo in the second game. Their power play was abysmal Monday night and their expensive captain, Alexei Yashin, is playing on the fourth line, probably deservedly.</p>
        <p>The Devils are also in trouble, down by two games to one with the fourth game at Tampa Bay tonight. Martin Brodeur, one of the best goalies in N.H.L. history, has lost 10 straight playoff games outside the metropolitan area since 2003.</p>
        <p>The Rangers have been taking advantage of a team with no collective frame of reference for how to conduct itself in the playoffs. Just growing whiskers is not enough. The Rangers are hardly the embodiment of winning experience: they had not won a home game in the playoffs since May 8, 1997.</p>
        <p>Garden crowds can be ugly, but expectation and entitlement were in the air last night. Jed Ortmeyer set a tone by whacking everybody on his first shift. Coach Tom Renney's players skated patterns and found openings, while the Thrashers seemed essentially clueless. Some of that 1994 magic dust was back in the ozone. It was better than bottles flying in Nassau.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
