<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Bocks, It's All About the Malt</title>
    <meta content="18wine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/dining/18wine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841118"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BEERS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE2DE1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1583" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Bocks, It's All About the Malt</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With Bocks, It’s All About the Malt</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC ASIMOV</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Asimov, Eric</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR many Americans, bock beer once was simply a synonym for dark beer. In the early 1980s, before the craft beer revolution hit Austin, Tex., where I was a graduate student, we had the usual array of insipid mass-market lagers to choose from, and then we had Shiner Bock, a legacy of the huge wave of German immigrants who in the 19th century settled central Texas towns like Fredericksburg and New Braunfels.</p>
        <p>In truth, Shiner Bock was barely a cut above the other beers, darker for sure, and with just a touch of malty flavor to set it apart. But desperate for even a hint of character and eager to show disdain for lackluster brews, my friends and I flocked to the bock, which back then was kind of the unofficial beer of Austin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The tasting panel samples German and American versions of the dark brew called bock.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR many Americans, bock beer once was simply a synonym for dark beer. In the early 1980s, before the craft beer revolution hit Austin, Tex., where I was a graduate student, we had the usual array of insipid mass-market lagers to choose from, and then we had Shiner Bock, a legacy of the huge wave of German immigrants who in the 19th century settled central Texas towns like Fredericksburg and New Braunfels.</p>
        <p>In truth, Shiner Bock was barely a cut above the other beers, darker for sure, and with just a touch of malty flavor to set it apart. But desperate for even a hint of character and eager to show disdain for lackluster brews, my friends and I flocked to the bock, which back then was kind of the unofficial beer of Austin.</p>
        <p>Nowadays, as Americans have become accustomed to stouts, trappist ales, porters and all manner of dark brews, the talismanic appeal of Shiner Bock seems somewhat quaint. At the same time, as more bock beers have become available, to say nothing of doppelbocks, maibocks, weizenbocks and eisbocks, the blanket association of bock beer with dark beer fails miserably. In fact, most maibocks are not even dark but decidedly amber.</p>
        <p>For insight into the world of bocks, and to mark spring with a traditional Bavarian seasonal beverage, we recently tasted 25 bottles, primarily from Germany and the United States. For the tasting Florence Fabricant and I were joined by Richard Scholz, an owner of Bierkraft in Park Slope, Brooklyn, and Lew Bryson, a beer writer and the managing editor of Malt Advocate magazine.</p>
        <p>The term bock dates back centuries, at least toward the end of the Middle Ages, when the Hanseatic city of Einbeck became well know for its strong, malty lagers. In Bavaria, where the style was particularly valued and eventually duplicated, the beer was called Einbeck, rendered in the local dialect as Einbock, and later simply as bock.</p>
        <p>Bock also means billy goat, which became the symbol for this style of beer. That's how the story goes, anyhow, and we're sticking to it.</p>
        <p>Unlike pale ales and India pale ales, which emphasize lively bitter hop aromas and flavors, bock beers are all about the malt, which gives them a seductively sweet aroma.</p>
        <p>Anybody who has visited a brewery will recognize the malt aroma. While the hops are played down in the mix, they still have a crucial role. Their bitterness, while not obvious, balances the sweetness of the malt, making the beer clean and refreshing rather than cloying.</p>
        <p>That is the general theory behind bocks, but what about the variations on the theme, in particular, the doppelbocks, or double bocks, which we found the most consistently interesting of the brews?</p>
        <p>As with so many beer styles, we have monasteries to thank for doppelbock, in particular the devout monks of St. Francis of Paula.</p>
        <p>Forbidden to eat during the 40 days of Lent, they brewed a particularly rich and nutritious beer, a sort of liquid bread, to sustain them through Easter. The monks called their beer Salvator, for Savior, and to this day doppelbocks can be identified by the distinctive ''ator'' names they go by. The monks eventually secularized their brewery, Paulaner, which continues to make Salvator among many other beers.</p>
        <p>The term doppelbock has no literal meaning. The beers are thicker and fuller-bodied than ordinary bocks, but the difference is maybe 8 percent alcohol rather than 6.5 percent.</p>
        <p>Still, it raises the question of how the fasting monks maintained their sober equilibrium on a steady diet of doppelbock. Mr. Scholz pointed out that today's doppelbock is not exactly true to recipes the monks used.</p>
        <p>''It's fermented until dry, 7 or 8 percent,'' he said. ''It used to be 3 percent, with a lot of residual sugar.''</p>
        <p>While doppelbock in particular is associated with Lent and Easter, maibock is brewed to celebrate May Day. These beers tend to be more amber than dark, though there's no rule about it. They're very malty and, alone among bocks, they have a more pronounced hop bitterness.</p>
        <p>Weizenbock, sometimes called dunkler bock, is a dark wheat beer, still very malty and strong. In fact, our No. 1 beer, the Ettaler Curator, was termed a dunkler doppelbock, which is perhaps too twisted a label to decipher other than to say it combined the wonderful floral and spice aromas of a wheat beer with the malty crispness of a bock. Delicious!</p>
        <p>The only category we ruled out was eisbock, which, like ice wine, eliminates some of the water to produce a stronger, often sweeter, brew. In the end we had 13 bottles from Germany (one bock, nine doppelbocks, three maibocks), 9 from the United States (five bocks, three doppelbocks and one maibock), one doppelbock from Italy, one bock from Poland and one doppelbock from Austria.</p>
        <p>As I said, the doppelbocks were by far our favorites, taking eight slots in our top 10, with the other two going to maibocks. Why was this? I'm not sure, but I do have some theories. We tasted the bocks first so they wouldn't be overshadowed by comparison to the richer doppelbocks. But even on their own terms they tasted bland or subdued, even my once-beloved Shiner.</p>
        <p>Usually in a tasting that includes American craft brews and imports, the Americans do well because at the least they have the edge in freshness. But the bocks from Anchor, Clipper City, Rock Art and Abita did not show well at all. For that matter neither did the imported bocks.</p>
        <p>This suggests three things. First, doppelbocks are inherently more interesting than ordinary bocks. They combine the maltiness of a bock with the fruitiness of ales to make a beer more complex than most lagers.</p>
        <p>The Augustiner Maximator is fascinating: thick and sumptuous but not cloying. The Salvator, too, shows the genius of the monks. Only one of the three American doppelbocks made the list, the Sprecher, which oddly misspells the German term, calling itself Dopple Bock. It was creamy and a bit sweet, with some hop bitterness that was not classic but was distinctively American.</p>
        <p>The fact that the German doppelbocks were so good suggests a second point: The added richness and body in this style possibly act as preservatives, allowing these beers to withstand the rigors of travel better than more fragile styles.</p>
        <p>And it underscores a third point: American brewers have yet to embrace this style, or lagers in general. There is a widespread idea that lagers in general are dull and simple, an understandable reaction to American mass-market beers. But the doppelbocks at least show the intricate possibilities of lagers.</p>
        <p>Of the two maibocks that made the list the better was the Einbecker Mai-Ur-Bock, an amber beer that showed both the malt and the hops sides of this style.</p>
        <p>The last word goes to the Italian double bock, La Rossa from Moretti. Most people know Moretti as a fairly innocuous lager, but La Rossa is malty and full-flavored. I never would have guessed it was Italian. I guess I should have thought outside the bocks.</p>
        <p>Tasting Report: Rich and Complex Double Bocks Lead the Way</p>
        <p>Ettaler Curator Dunkler $3.50 *** 1/2 [Rating: Three and a Half Stars]  Doppelbock Germany 16.9 ounces  Wonderfully fragrant, with aromas of malt, flowers and spices; complex and delicious. (Importer: B. United International, Redding, Conn.)</p>
        <p>Augustiner Maximator $2.30 *** 1/2 [Rating: Three and a Half Stars]  Doppelbock Germany 12 ounces  Thick, rich and bottomless with flavors of coffee, malt and anise; balanced and dry. (Global Village Imports, King of Prussia, Pa.)</p>
        <p>Einbecker Mai-Ur-Bock Germany $1.90 *** [Rating: Three Stars]  11.2 ounces  Amber-colored, sedate and malty, balanced by refreshing bitterness from hops. (B. United International, Redding, Conn.)</p>
        <p>Hirsch Doppelbock Germany $3.75 *** [Rating: Three Stars]  16.9 ounces  Sweet, malty and earthy, yet lively, fresh and balanced. (HDT Importers, Portland, Ore.)</p>
        <p>Paulaner Salvator $1.75 *** [Rating: Three Stars]  Doppelbock Germany 12 ounces  Rich and spicy, with complex flavors of malt, coffee and caramel. (Star Brand Imports, White Plains, N.Y.)</p>
        <p>Ayinger Celebrator $3.85 *** [Rating: Three Stars]  Doppelbock Germany 11.2 ounces  Rich and malty with smoky, roasted flavors of coffee, spice and caramel. (Merchant du Vin, Tukwila, Wash.)</p>
        <p>Moretti La Rossa Double Italy $1.55 *** [Rating: Three Stars]  12 ounces  Richly flavored with caramel, smoke and anise; sweet malt turns dry at the end. (Star Brand Imports, White Plains, N.Y.)</p>
        <p>Weihenstephaner Korbinian $2.50 *** [Rating: Three Stars]  Doppelbock Germany 16.9 ounces  Sumptuous, balanced flavors of malt, fruit and caramel. (Bavaria House, Wilmington, N.C.)</p>
        <p>Sprecher Dopple Bock $8 *** [Rating: Three Stars]  Glendale, Wis. 22 ounces  Rich, sweet, creamy, complex and balanced with subtle hop flavors.</p>
        <p>Hofbrau Munchen $2 ** 1/2 [Rating: Two and a Half Stars]  Maibock Germany 16.9 ounces  Amber-colored with rich, malty sweetness balanced by a hoppy bitterness. (Hess Beer Importers, Moorestown, N.J.)</p>
        <p>WHAT THE STARS MEAN:  Ratings range from zero to four stars and reflect the panel's reaction to the beers, which were tasted with names concealed. The panelists this week are Eric Asimov; Florence Fabricant; Richard Scholz, an owner of Bierkraft in Brooklyn; and Lew Bryson, managing editor of Malt Advocate magazine. The tasted beers represent a selection generally available in groceries, supermarkets and beer distributorships. Prices are those paid in the New York region.</p>
        <p>Tasting Coordinator: Bernard Kirsch  nytimes.com</p>
        <p>Recent wine columns from The New York Times are online: nytimes.com/wine. This week members of the panel discuss their favorite bock beers.</p>
        <p>BEERS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
