<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For an Agency, Life After Wal-Mart Is Called Kmart</title>
    <meta content="18adco" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/business/media/18adco.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841137"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Account Changes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Draftfcb</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sears Holdings</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wal-Mart Stores Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Draft, Howard</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Kmart Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Wal-Mart Stores Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DD1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="944" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For an Agency, Life After Wal-Mart Is Called Kmart</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For an Agency, Life After Wal-Mart Is Called Kmart</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STUART ELLIOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Howard Draft and his ad agency Draft FCB are back in retail ad business; comeback is result of unexpected decision by Kmart to change creative agencies after four years; Kmart is teaming up with agency that won--then lost--creative account of its major competitor Wal-Mart Stores; Kmart spends about $200 million each year on advertising in major media, compared with about $580 million year spent by Wal-Mart; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HOWARD DRAFT and his agency, Draft FCB, are back in the retail advertising business -- and this time, they hope, it will be for longer than a couple of months.</p>
        <p>The comeback is the result of an unexpected decision by Kmart, announced yesterday, to change creative agencies after four years. By hiring Draft FCB in Chicago, effective in 90 days, Kmart is teaming up with the agency that won -- then lost -- the creative account of its major competitor, Wal-Mart Stores.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kmart is teaming up with Draft FCB, the agency that won  then lost  the creative account of its major competitor, Wal-Mart Stores.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HOWARD DRAFT and his agency, Draft FCB, are back in the retail advertising business -- and this time, they hope, it will be for longer than a couple of months.</p>
        <p>The comeback is the result of an unexpected decision by Kmart, announced yesterday, to change creative agencies after four years. By hiring Draft FCB in Chicago, effective in 90 days, Kmart is teaming up with the agency that won -- then lost -- the creative account of its major competitor, Wal-Mart Stores.</p>
        <p>Kmart spends about $200 million a year on advertising in major media, compared with about $580 million a year spent by Wal-Mart.</p>
        <p>The roller-coaster ride that Draft FCB took with Wal-Mart was one of the most closely watched in Madison Avenue history.</p>
        <p>Wal-Mart hired Draft FCB last October, then dismissed it two months later, citing what Wal-Mart described as improper conduct by two of its own executives who had been involved in a long search for a new creative agency that concluded with the selection of Draft FCB.</p>
        <p>Wal-Mart fired the executives, Julie Roehm and Sean Womack, charging them with favoring Draft FCB and Mr. Draft, its chairman and chief executive. During the review process, Wal-Mart said, the two executives accepted meals and gifts, among them, a watch and a case of vodka, in violation of Wal-Mart policies.</p>
        <p>Ms. Roehm and Mr. Womack have denied any wrongdoing. An internal investigation by the parent of Draft FCB, the Interpublic Group of Companies, found what an Interpublic executive, Philippe Krakowsky, described as ''no instances of behavior that violates any of Interpublic's policies or our code of conduct.''</p>
        <p>Even so, when Wal-Mart conducted version 2.0 of the creative review, Draft FCB was pointedly excluded from the process. Wal-Mart later chose another Interpublic unit, the Martin Agency in Richmond, Va.</p>
        <p>Wal-Mart was Draft FCB's first big client since Mr. Draft oversaw its creation for Interpublic, through the merger last summer of his namesake agency with Foote Cone &amp; Belding, a venerable agency based in New York. So the loss of the assignment was keenly felt.</p>
        <p>Trade publications had recently speculated that Mr. Draft was embarking on one of his famous charm offensives with executives at Kmart and its parent, Sears Holdings, to try to compensate for the stinging loss of the Wal-Mart creative assignment.</p>
        <p>''Of course we knew that,'' Maureen McGuire, chief marketing officer at Sears Holdings in Hoffman Estates, Ill., said of what had taken place between Wal-Mart and Draft FCB, but ''we decided that was not important.''</p>
        <p>''We made this decision totally on the capabilities Draft FCB can bring to Kmart as we build a better brand,'' Ms. McGuire said.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Draft FCB, Wally Petersen, said that Mr. Draft would not be available for comment and referred a reporter to a statement Mr. Draft had made in a news release.</p>
        <p>''Everyone we have met at Kmart is focused on building their business by establishing even stronger connections with their loyal shoppers and bringing more people into their stores,'' Mr. Draft said in the statement, adding, ''Our two organizations have a shared commitment to accountability and creativity.''</p>
        <p>How is Wal-Mart taking the news that the agency it hired and then fired is being hired by a rival?</p>
        <p>''We don't have any comment or worries about this one,'' a Wal-Mart spokeswoman, Mona Williams, said yesterday in an e-mail message.</p>
        <p>Draft FCB will create Kmart campaigns for television, radio and magazines and also handle tasks like producing ads aimed at regular Kmart shoppers, known as customer relationship marketing.</p>
        <p>''At Kmart, we're all about building long-term relationships with our customers,'' said Bill Stewart, chief marketing officer at Kmart.</p>
        <p>In hiring Draft FCB, Kmart is dismissing Grey Worldwide in New York, part of the Grey Global Group unit of the WPP Group. Kmart hired Grey as its creative agency in August 2003.</p>
        <p>''Kmart came to us at a very difficult time in its history,'' James Heekin, chairman and chief executive at Grey Global, wrote yesterday in a memorandum to employees. ''We reinvented the brand, gave it new relevance and created a humanity that connected with consumers.''</p>
        <p>The timing of Grey's dismissal is unusual, because Grey is finishing its work on a major brand-image campaign for Kmart that is scheduled to begin appearing next month.</p>
        <p>''We think the campaign works well,'' Ms. McGuire said. The change, however, is ''about all the capabilities Draft FCB brings,'' she added.</p>
        <p>No review preceded the decision to shift the creative assignment to Draft FCB from Grey. In contrast, earlier this month Sears Holdings announced a review to find an agency to handle the media planning and buying duties for both Kmart and its sister chain, Sears, Roebuck.</p>
        <p>The media assignment is now divided between two WPP agencies: MindShare, for traditional media, and MEC Interaction, for interactive ads. Both are taking part in the media review.</p>
        <p>Mr. Draft and Draft FCB may not have put the Wal-Mart experience entirely behind them. Ms. Roehm is suing Wal-Mart for severance pay and has listed Mr. Draft as a potential witness on her behalf. Wal-Mart is countersuing.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Draft can smile when he thinks about the timing of the Kmart announcement. He is scheduled to speak tomorrow afternoon, in an appearance planned months ago, at a conference of the American Association of Advertising Agencies. The audience will be composed largely of his peers at the top of agency organization charts.</p>
        <p>Before yesterday, Mr. Draft would have been speaking as the chief executive who won and then lost the Wal-Mart creative account. Tomorrow, he will appear as the chief executive who went out and replaced that assignment four months later with work for a Wal-Mart competitor.</p>
        <p>ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
