<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Horror at Virginia Tech, Then the Hard Questions</title>
    <meta content="l18virginia" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841164"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E6DC1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1213" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Horror at Virginia Tech, Then the Hard Questions</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''32 Shot Dead in Virginia'' (front page, April 17):</p>
        <p>Virginia Polytechnic Institute's students and faculty will forever be changed after the massacre on April 16, 2007. College students around the country are shocked and horrified.</p>
        <p>In 2002, a man shot four people, including two professors, at my school, the University of Arizona. Although the attack in Virginia was more a massacre than a shooting, students experience a similar gut-wrenching feeling as they realize that their college campus is a vulnerable environment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''32 Shot Dead in Virginia'' (front page, April 17):</p>
        <p>Virginia Polytechnic Institute's students and faculty will forever be changed after the massacre on April 16, 2007. College students around the country are shocked and horrified.</p>
        <p>In 2002, a man shot four people, including two professors, at my school, the University of Arizona. Although the attack in Virginia was more a massacre than a shooting, students experience a similar gut-wrenching feeling as they realize that their college campus is a vulnerable environment.</p>
        <p>Campuses are not as safe as in the past. We constantly hear about sexual assaults, rapes and even shootings on our campuses.</p>
        <p>I, for one, am worried about the possible increases in danger that threaten future college students if schools do not maintain a safer environment.</p>
        <p>Carolyn Regan  Tucson, April 17, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>How many mass shootings, how much loss, how much grief will it take before our legislators are finally willing to stand up to the National Rifle Association and pass meaningful gun control legislation?</p>
        <p>The University of Texas shooting more than 40 years ago, Columbine High School in 1999 and now Virginia Tech.</p>
        <p>Isn't that enough tragedy to impel action?</p>
        <p>The majority of Americans support gun control. What do we have to do to make it happen?</p>
        <p>Eileen B. Entin  Lexington, Mass., April 17, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In ''Eight Years After Columbine'' (editorial, April 17), you call for more gun control. With 40 states permitting law-abiding citizens to carry handguns for protection, the evidence teaches that prohibiting carrying such weapons leads to tragedy.</p>
        <p>Virginia Tech is one of the ''gun free'' zones in Virginia where gun possession is prohibited -- a place criminals know that they need not fear an armed response. The prohibition did not stop the gunman, but it did prevent anyone on that campus from stopping his murder spree.</p>
        <p>Daniel Schmutter  West Orange, N.J., April 17, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>When will our legislators be able to summon the political will to control the availability of guns and address violence in the media? How many more people will have to die before our leaders will have the sense and the guts to take on the National Rifle Association and honor the wishes of a majority of Americans who want gun control?</p>
        <p>(Rev.) Stephen L. White  Princeton, N.J., April 17, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is the Episcopal chaplain at Princeton University.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>When will America join the civilized world and realize the absolute stupidity of its gun laws?</p>
        <p>Your leaders are not brave enough to stand up to the gun lobby; therefore, shootings like Monday's will continue to occur.</p>
        <p>Years ago, we in Australia banned unregistered users and guns after a similar occurrence, despite the gun lobby; it has made for less gun crime and a safer existence for our citizens.</p>
        <p>I feel very sorry for the parents of the kids who lost their lives in this incident; they will suffer forever.</p>
        <p>Wayne Ellis  Sydney, Australia, April 17, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Interesting. Your first reaction to the Virginia Tech shooting (editorial, April 17) is to increase gun control. My first reaction was, ''I wish there were more kids in that school who had a concealed carry license and a firearm to protect themselves.''</p>
        <p>Here in Vermont, we have the fewest gun restrictions of any state in the Union and the third lowest rate for violent crime.</p>
        <p>So is your way really better? Is there really convincing data to show that restricting firearms reduces violence? Or is it just the opposite?</p>
        <p>Making firearms accessible to lawful citizens actually decreases violence. If you were living and working in Iraq or Israel right now, and you were concerned about your safety and that of your family, would you want your firearm taken away from you? I don't think so.</p>
        <p>Josh C. Manheimer  President  Handgun Club of America  Norwich, Vt., April 17, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Why is it that my phone company can call me with a text message to let me know that my bill is due, but universities that charge thousands of dollars a year in tuition can only send an e-mail message warning students to stay at home?</p>
        <p>Emergency notifications should be sent to student cellphones in the form of a call or a text message that rings. Every college professor and parent knows that students rarely check e-mail and are glued to their phones every waking minute.</p>
        <p>If such a system had been in place at Virginia Tech, dozens of lives may have been saved.</p>
        <p>Jon Reinhardt  State College, Pa., April 17, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is an instructor at Pennsylvania State University.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Surely every campus should have a loud alert siren that could be set off in the case of a shooting or any other peril.</p>
        <p>The sending of e-mail messages by the school administration seems ridiculous to me. A loud, general alarm is not so expensive; it should be mandatory in schools and universities.</p>
        <p>Christina Allison  Santa Barbara, Calif.  April 17, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>A suggestion for a way to warn people on large campuses:</p>
        <p>The University of Illinois or Indiana University (which three of our children attended) located emergency boxes throughout the campus. As I recall, they were located on poles and had a blue light to be pushed if you had an emergency and needed help.</p>
        <p>I would think that there must be a way to incorporate a loudspeaker around campus in the same fashion. It could be used for emergencies to warn everyone immediately of imminent danger.</p>
        <p>Sherry Brown  San Diego, April 17, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>It was shocking to hear Virginia Tech officials say they did not shut down the campus in response to the first shooting because they believed that it was just a domestic quarrel. It sounds as if they are accustomed to domestic quarrels on the campus's being settled by shootings and they are therefore not worthy of anyone's attention. What kind of an excuse was that?</p>
        <p>Evelyn Wolfson  Wayland, Mass., April 17, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I urge the American people to work through the tragedy at Virginia Tech to begin an honest and open discourse about mental health in our country, especially on our college campuses.</p>
        <p>During my senior year of school, a young woman committed suicide on campus. These shootings and suicides illuminate the fact that we do not adequately address mental health in the United States. We do not battle the stigmas against getting counseling or asking for help.</p>
        <p>We are failing our young people by not getting to the root of why things like this happen. How do these young people get to that point where murder and suicide are the only options they feel they have left?</p>
        <p>Let's not just scratch the surface by calling for stricter gun control. I pray that our nation will dig deep as a community, confront taboo issues and try to prevent future tragedies.</p>
        <p>Bailey Childers  Washington, April 17, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is national training manager for Progressive Majority.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
