<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For School, Several Ties to Shootings</title>
    <meta content="18school" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/us/18school.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070427T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841179"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MASSACRE IN VIRGINIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cho Seung-Hui</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E0DC1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="349" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For School, Several Ties to Shootings</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For School, Several Ties to Shootings</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN URBINA and SUEVON LEE</byline>
      <dateline>CHANTILLY, Va., April 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Heaven gained an amazing angel'' was written in black marker on a boulder next to Westfield High School that became a makeshift shrine of plastic flowers and candles for Reema Samaha, one of the victims of Monday's shooting at Virginia Tech. ''We love you,'' read a note written on a boulder for another of the high school's victims, Erin Peterson.</p>
        <p>As students filed past the boulders here on their way out Tuesday, they looked dazed as they grappled with the loss of two of their former classmates while also coming to terms with the school's connection to a third graduate of Westfield, Cho Seung-Hui, the killer in the worst campus shooting rampage in United States history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two classmates from Westfield High School in Virginia died in the Virginia Tech shootings. Their killer, Cho Seung-Hui, was also a graduate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Heaven gained an amazing angel'' was written in black marker on a boulder next to Westfield High School that became a makeshift shrine of plastic flowers and candles for Reema Samaha, one of the victims of Monday's shooting at Virginia Tech. ''We love you,'' read a note written on a boulder for another of the high school's victims, Erin Peterson.</p>
        <p>As students filed past the boulders here on their way out Tuesday, they looked dazed as they grappled with the loss of two of their former classmates while also coming to terms with the school's connection to a third graduate of Westfield, Cho Seung-Hui, the killer in the worst campus shooting rampage in United States history.</p>
        <p>The attack occurred less than a year after another Westfield graduate, Michael W. Kennedy, 18, shot and killed two officers at a police station about five miles away.</p>
        <p>''It's as though we're getting a reputation for being that school where all this violence happens,'' said Natalia MaLaret, 17, a junior.</p>
        <p>Opened in 2000, Westfield High had a graduating class of about 800 students last year, about 45 of whom attended Virginia Tech. With about 3,200 students, Westfield is one of the largest schools in Fairfax County, which is one of the fastest-growing counties in Virginia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cho was a 2003 graduate of Westfield, while Ms. Peterson and Ms. Samaha both graduated last year, school officials said. Mr. Kennedy, who was killed by the police in the shootings last May, graduated from Westfield in 2005, police officials said.</p>
        <p>''Mostly, people are confused,'' said Steve Webb, who dropped out of Westfield last year to become a professional juggler, as he left campus after visiting friends. ''It seems like a lot of bad things to happen to one place.''</p>
        <p>As students filed out of the school, heads bowed, the police kept the news media at bay. Some students wore ribbons in the high school's colors, black and gold, in honor of the victims.</p>
        <p>Mary Shaw, a spokeswoman for Fairfax County schools, said counseling services were being provided throughout the week.</p>
        <p>MASSACRE IN VIRGINIA</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 27, 2007, Friday  An article on April 18 about Westfield High School in Chantilly, Va., from which the killer in the Virginia Tech massacre and two of his victims graduated, referred incorrectly to the academic background of Steve Webb, who visited friends at the high school a day after the killings. He transferred to an alternative educational program in the district; he did not drop out of school.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 27, 2007, Friday</p>
        <p>An article on April 18 about Westfield High School in Chantilly, Va., from which the killer in the Virginia Tech massacre and two of his victims graduated, referred incorrectly to the academic background of Steve Webb, who visited friends at the high school a day after the killings. He transferred to an alternative educational program in the district; he did not drop out of school.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
