<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What the Octopus Really Wants</title>
    <meta content="18rest" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/dining/reviews/18rest.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841093"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Seafood</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Esca</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DE1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1406" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What the Octopus Really Wants</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">What the Octopus Really Wants</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank Bruni</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GIVEN all the talk about horse whisperers and dog whisperers, it's impossible not to wonder: is Dave Pasternack a fish whisperer?</p>
        <p>Does he enjoy some preternatural rapport with the sea's creatures, an extrasensory insight into which might benefit from a raw appointment with coarse salt and which are fated for frying? Can he tease out their greatest performances?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In an era when too many restaurants try to be everything to everyone, Esca has a specific agenda: show what the sea can yield.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GIVEN all the talk about horse whisperers and dog whisperers, it's impossible not to wonder: is Dave Pasternack a fish whisperer?</p>
        <p>Does he enjoy some preternatural rapport with the sea's creatures, an extrasensory insight into which might benefit from a raw appointment with coarse salt and which are fated for frying? Can he tease out their greatest performances?</p>
        <p>On the evidence of Esca, I'd have to say yes. At few other restaurants, for example, does swordfish take such meaty, moist form. The paces he puts it through must be charmed, though they don't actually sound all that magical.</p>
        <p>He brushes the fish with olive oil. Rolls it in a blanket of fried bread crumbs seasoned with lemon, parsley and garlic. Throws it on a gas grill. And comes up with something nearly as succulent as bluefin tuna.</p>
        <p>For the tuna, he sees another possibility. He sees a Bolognese sauce. That's usually the province of red meat, but Mr. Pasternack understands when surf can do the work of turf. To the tuna he adds Spanish mackerel, pancetta and tomatoes, among other ingredients, then ladles this mix over housemade fettuccine. The tuna gives the dish a cool luxuriousness all its own, while the mackerel provides a blast of the sea.</p>
        <p>And what about the scorpionfish he's been serving of late? Many other chefs would no doubt bypass this species, understandably deeming it too bland. But Mr. Pasternack appreciates how custardy its texture becomes when it's cooked with care. And what if it's given a contrasting, crunchy shell, courtesy of a light batter of milk and flour and a bath in sizzling olive oil?</p>
        <p>He showily presents the results whole and upright, or at least what would qualify as upright for a fish: belly down, head pointed forward, tail stretched in the opposite direction. And he throws a few capers its way, for extra saltiness, and some lemon, for a necessary brightness.</p>
        <p>In a 2005 profile of him in The New Yorker, the 7,500-word fact of which spoke to the respect he has deservedly won, Mr. Pasternack, 43, defined his talent as ''knowing when something needs a little something.''</p>
        <p>But the profile established that he knows a lot more than that: the waters and weathers in which certain fish prosper; the vendors, large and small, with the quality of fish he demands. He's an honest-to-God fisherman, in love with the ocean, and Esca is his ongoing ode to it.</p>
        <p>I lived outside New York and didn't eat at Esca when it opened in 2000 and received two stars in The Times from William Grimes. But I've dropped by over the last three years and especially the last two months. And in my experience it just keeps getting better.</p>
        <p>It's not that Mr. Pasternack, one of its principal owners as well as its chef, latches on to many new tricks as the years go by. He's had no follow-up to Esca's one big innovation: introducing New Yorkers to the delicately seasoned raw fish compositions known as crudo.</p>
        <p>But by all appearances his dedication to Esca has never waned, and apart from a brief dalliance with Bistro du Vent, a French restaurant that failed, his attention has never really been divided. Sure, he's about to publish a book, ''The Young Man &amp; the Sea,'' with recipes and recollections. But by current standards that's more an obligatory rite than a serious bid at branding.</p>
        <p>On almost every occasion when I've called the Esca kitchen to interview him, he's answered the phone. When he hasn't, he's usually been right near it. I'm skeptical of reports that he has a home away from Esca. I'm convinced he sleeps with the fishes.</p>
        <p>He's tinkered with the restaurant's look, keeping the lemony walls and chocolate color of the upholstery but redoing the oak floors and moving the bar. That last change was a mistake. The bar is too small; on a crowded night, there's nowhere comfortable to wait for a table.</p>
        <p>The dining room closest to the bar feels inferior to the larger room just inside the entrance, and the patio, smack against a hulking brick tower of Manhattan Plaza, belies the lovely promise of outdoor dining.</p>
        <p>Friends have complained of inattentive service during off hours, and while I've never experienced that, the range of servers' demeanors can be jarring. Some dart around nervously and struggle to recall ingredients. Others swan about, making grand pronouncements.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Pasternack's kitchen is a steady, well-oiled trawler moving through placid seas. Be it weakfish or wolffish, the catch I've had at Esca has always tasted fresh. Whether black bass, wild striped bass or golden spotted bass, it's almost never been overcooked or undercooked.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pasternack has partners in Esca, including Mario Batali and Joseph Bastianich, and there's a straightforwardness, an air of conviviality and a Mediterranean orientation that link it to other Batali-Bastianich productions.</p>
        <p>But it's Mr. Pasternack's show, more low-key than most of its brethren and more tightly focused. In an era when too many restaurants try to be everything to everyone, Esca has a specific agenda: show what the sea can yield. To scan its long menu is to feel like you spend most of your time nibbling in a shallow tidal flat and ignoring deep waters beyond.</p>
        <p>From those waters comes orange marlin, seared and served with fava beans, as well as pink snapper, grilled and presented in its natural cloak. You can trust Esca to leave the skin on when it should be and to turn it crispy if it can be.</p>
        <p>For the terrific fritto misto, Esca marshals not just two or three players but a diverse team: skate, halibut, cod, steamers, oysters, octopus, shrimp. And not each gets the same shawl. For some it's bread crumbs; for others, flour and cornstarch.</p>
        <p>At many other restaurants, one category of the menu outshines the others. At Esca, it's a toss-up between the crudo preparations, the fish entrees and even the desserts, few but memorable. The wine list alone is potent bait (the translation of the word esca), taking in much of Italy and keeping the prices in check.</p>
        <p>And the pasta dishes, sometimes overlooked, shouldn't be. Esca's maccheroni alla chitarra, fat housemade noodles, are sauced with an emulsion of olive oil and sea urchin roe that takes on a gorgeous salmon color and tastes like a light and briny cream. Lump crab meat rounds out the dish.</p>
        <p>Bucatini provides the right strong support for ''Rita's spicy baby octopus,'' the tenderness of which Mr. Pasternack attributes to a secret he learned from the Neapolitan woman for whom the dish is named. Into a tomato-based stew he adds one used wine cork -- removed at the end -- per pound of octopus.</p>
        <p>He can't say why this method works. But intuition tells him it's best. So does the octopus.</p>
        <p>Esca  *** [Rating: Three Stars]  402 West 43rd Street; (212) 564-7272.</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE  -- Gentle-looking, peaceful-feeling rooms with lemony walls and chocolate-colored chairs and banquettes open to a warm-weather patio with about 40 seats.  SOUND LEVEL -- Somewhat loud when crowded.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Weakfish, hamachi, bay scallop and fluke crudo; spaghetti with crab and sea urchin; bucatini with baby octopus; fettuccine with tuna Bolognese; whole grilled pink snapper; grilled swordfish; grilled or seared mahi-mahi; roasted haddock; fried scorpionfish; espresso cake; caramel affogato.  WINE LIST -- Lengthy and almost entirely Italian, with a trove of interesting choices from a wide variety of regions, scores of bottles under $50 and more than a dozen wines by the quartino.  PRICE RANGE -- Lunch appetizers, $9 to $15. Pasta dishes and fish entrees, $21 to $24. Dinner appetizers, $14 to $22. Pasta dishes and fish entrees, $22 to $36. Desserts, $11.  HOURS -- Lunch from noon to 2:30 p.m. Monday through Saturday. Dinner from 4:30 to 10:30 p.m. Sunday; from 5 to 10:30 p.m. Monday; and from 5 to 11:30 p.m. Tuesday through Saturday.  RESERVATIONS -- Call at least three weeks in advance for prime dinner times.  CREDIT CARDS -- All major cards.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Entrance and all dining areas at street level; no accessible restroom.  WHAT THE STARS MEAN -- Ratings range from zero to four stars and reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.  PAST REVIEWS -- from The Times, with additional capsule reviews by Times critics:  nytimes.com/dining</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
