<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Limits Access to Student Loan Database</title>
    <meta content="18loans" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Front Page; Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/us/18loans.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841195"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Information Policies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Education Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spellings, Margaret (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Edward M (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glater, Jonathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cuomo, Andrew M (Atty Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Education Department</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Spellings, Margaret</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E6DB1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1060" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Limits Access to Student Loan Database</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Limits Access to Student Loan Database</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN D. GLATER; Karen W. Arenson and Sam Dillon contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glater, Jonathan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US Education Department cuts off outside access to government database containing personal financial information of millions of student aid applicants; Sec Margaret Spellings acts on concern that loan marketers are improperly obtaining data; letter to Sen Edward Kennedy strongly defends department practices and oversight and discloses that since 2003 department has revoked 261 user IDs granting access to National Student Loan Data System, including 246 belonging to loan campanies, loan holders, guaranty agencies and loan servicers and 15 belonging to schools; access issue has been longstanding one but department has not acted until now, in face of scandal and investigation by New York Atty Gen Andrew Cuomo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Education Department last night cut off outside access to a government database that contains the personal financial information of millions of student aid applicants.</p>
        <p>The department acted on concerns that loan companies or other marketers were improperly obtaining private information on potential borrowers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Officials were concerned that marketers were improperly obtaining private information on potential borrowers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Education Department last night cut off outside access to a government database that contains the personal financial information of millions of student aid applicants.</p>
        <p>The department acted on concerns that loan companies or other marketers were improperly obtaining private information on potential borrowers.</p>
        <p>The shutdown, announced by Education Secretary Margaret Spellings, is its strongest response to a broadening student loan scandal that has already implicated loan companies and caused several universities to put their financial aid administrators on leave and review their dealings with lenders.</p>
        <p>In a six-page letter to Senator Edward M. Kennedy, chairman of the education committee, Ms. Spellings offered a staunch defense of the department's practices and its oversight of the student loan industry.</p>
        <p>The letter disclosed that since 2003, the department had revoked 261 user IDs that grant access to the database, known as the National Student Loan Data System. The database was used, among other things, to help determine eligibility for financial aid. Of the revoked IDs, 246 belonged to student loan companies, holders of loans, guaranty agencies and loan servicers, and 15 to schools.</p>
        <p>Ms. Spellings said that monitoring the database had shown ''a significant increase in usage by lenders, loan holders, services and guaranty agencies'' and that the uptick ''was a matter of concern to us.''</p>
        <p>''I hold the department and the thousands of civil service professionals who administer these programs to the highest ethical standards,'' Ms. Spellings said to Mr. Kennedy, Democrat of Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>The shutdown of access to the database, described as temporary, came a few weeks after the disclosure that a department official involved in oversight of access to the database had sold at least $100,000 of stock in a student loan company. That employee, Matteo Fontana, was put on paid leave; filings released by the department showed that he had disclosed his shareholdings.</p>
        <p>The question of improper searches of the database has been a longstanding one. Mr. Fontana, the general manager in the Education Department office that oversees federal student loan programs, warned in an April 2005 letter to loan companies, university financial aid administrators and others with access to the database that the access ''is made available only for the general purpose of assisting with determining the eligibility of an applicant for federal student aid and in the collection of federal student loans and grant overpayments.''</p>
        <p>But critics said the department until now had taken few steps to protect access to the database.</p>
        <p>Representative George Miller, Democrat of California and chairman of the House education committee, said last night, ''I am pleased that the secretary has belatedly taken some steps to address these fundamental privacy issues. However, it is long past time for the department to step up to the plate and vigorously investigate both the extent of lenders' misuse of the student loan database and the exploitation for profit of federal programs'' for student aid.</p>
        <p>Some financial aid officers said they believed student loan companies were trolling the database for potential borrowers.</p>
        <p>''My understanding is that there have been lenders accessing the database for very long periods of time, looking at large numbers of students to mine the database for possible borrowers they can market to,'' said Eileen K. O'Leary, director of student aid and finance at Stonehill College in Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>The possibility that the department might restrict access to the database was reported Sunday in The Washington Post. Mr. Kennedy had raised concerns about access to the database in a letter to the department. Last night, he hailed Ms. Spellings's action, saying, ''I look forward to working with her to ensure that students receive their loans without sacrificing their privacy.''</p>
        <p>Kevin Bruns, executive director of America's Student Loan Providers, said he hoped that the shutdown ''is, in fact, temporary.'' He added, ''The department's lax oversight in the past should not be grounds for a permanent shutdown.''</p>
        <p>The department's announcement came after months of investigation of the ties between lenders and universities by Andrew M. Cuomo, New York's attorney general.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, Mr. Cuomo has won $6.5 million from lenders that he had accused of improper practices. He has criticized a range of tactics including ''kickbacks'' to universities for steering student loan volume to companies and paying consulting fees to university aid administrators who provide students with information on where to borrow.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Mr. Cuomo briefed his counterparts from more than 40 states on his investigation, raising the possibility that more states will begin seeking to regulate the industry's practices. ''I look forward to working with other states to clean up the student loan industry,'' Mr. Cuomo said after the call. ''This is a widening national scandal, and we need to address it as such.''</p>
        <p>The Education Department itself has been reacting to the heightened scrutiny in other ways. After two members of federal advisory committees on student aid -- the directors of financial aid at the University of Texas and at Johns Hopkins University -- were found to have financial relationships with a lending company, Ms. Spellings asked them to resign from the committees.</p>
        <p>Other committee members say that department officials have contacted them in recent days to verify information they had provided on financial disclosure forms. The department has also announced that it was looking for ways to ''enhance'' its disclosure program.</p>
        <p>The department has been criticized in the past by its inspector general's office as exercising lax oversight of the kinds of incentives that lenders were offering universities. In her letter to Mr. Kennedy, Ms. Spellings defended the department on that score. ''The department's Office of Federal Student Aid reviews complaints about lender inducements and determines what, if any, action is required,'' she wrote. ''If it suspects violations, it evaluates the facts and takes appropriate action.''</p>
        <p>She added that a review last year had identified ''only a few cases where college and lenders may have violated the rules.''</p>
        <p>But the department stands in danger of being overtaken by the states. Attorneys general in California, Connecticut, Minnesota and Ohio have indicated they are looking into relationships between student loan companies and colleges and universities.</p>
        <p>Attorney General Edmund G. Brown Jr. of California announced yesterday that his office had demanded that two student-loan companies based in the state provide records concerning their financial relationships with public and private universities, and vocational schools in California.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
