<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>China Leans Less on U.S. Trade; Weak Dollar Encourages Emphasis on Exports to Other Nations</title>
    <meta content="18yuan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/business/worldbusiness/18yuan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841234"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Canton Trade Fair</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Protectionism (Trade)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Africa</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Middle East</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Latin America</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Far East, South and Southeast Asia and Pacific Areas</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Protectionism (Trade)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E0DB1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1597" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>China Leans Less on U.S. Trade; Weak Dollar Encourages Emphasis on Exports to Other Nations</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">China Leans Less on U.S. Trade</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <dateline>GUANGZHOU, China, April 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chinese producers say their fastest growth lies in Europe, Africa, Middle East, South America and elsewhere in Asia and less on US; Chinese companies are poised to expand into markets of many of world's rapidly growing economies, and in some cases, they are running directly into American competitors; Chinese business representatives at what is still known as Canton Fair say they are discouraged by weaker growth in American economy, rising protectionist sentiment in Washington and decline of dollar against China's currency, which makes it more expensive for Americans to buy Chinese products; China's exports to US are huge and growing, as is trade imbalance, which is significantly larger than European Union's deficit with China; that is main reason trade is focus of attention for newly empowered Democrats in US Congress, making it likely that trade frictions between two countries will persist and possibly worsen in months ahead; China is still nearly 25 times as dependent on exports to US as percentage of its total economic output as US is on exports to China; government and companies across China increasingly see danger in becoming too dependent on single market; graph; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At booth after booth at China's main trade fair this week, the refrain from Chinese business executives is the same: the American market is not as crucial as it used to be.</p>
        <p>Instead, Chinese producers of everything from socket wrenches to sport utility vehicles say, their fastest growth these days lies in Europe, Africa, the Middle East, South America and elsewhere in Asia -- in other words, practically anywhere other than the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chinese companies are finding their fastest growth in the world’s rapidly growing economies, not the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At booth after booth at China's main trade fair this week, the refrain from Chinese business executives is the same: the American market is not as crucial as it used to be.</p>
        <p>Instead, Chinese producers of everything from socket wrenches to sport utility vehicles say, their fastest growth these days lies in Europe, Africa, the Middle East, South America and elsewhere in Asia -- in other words, practically anywhere other than the United States.</p>
        <p>So it is throughout China. With ample support from the Beijing government -- including a flurry of trade missions to Africa and assistance with trade fairs in Germany, Australia or someplace in between -- Chinese companies are poised to expand into the markets of many of the world's rapidly growing economies. In some cases, they are running directly into American competitors.</p>
        <p>Chinese business representatives at what is still known as the Canton Fair, after this city's old name, say they are discouraged by weaker growth in the American economy, rising protectionist sentiment in Washington and the decline of the dollar against China's currency, which makes it more expensive for Americans to buy Chinese products.</p>
        <p>While the European Union has restricted certain imports, particularly shoes, American trade barriers have drawn more attention.</p>
        <p>''The U.S. government is still trying to protect its own markets, unlike Europe, which is very free,'' argued Huang Yasong, international sales manager for the Hubao Group, a men's shirt maker that is rapidly expanding in Eastern Europe and Brazil.</p>
        <p>Even so, trade barriers limit a small percentage of commerce. A more powerful driver is the strength of domestic demand and currency fluctuations.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the rise in the euro's value propelled China's exports to European Union countries past its exports to the United States for the first time in February.</p>
        <p>Currency rates have certainly influenced the finances of the Hang-zhou Jilin Machinery Company, which makes screwdrivers and other tools. Its American sales have remained basically flat, while those to Africa, Europe, the Middle East and especially Australia are on the rise.</p>
        <p>Zhao Wei, the company's sales manager, assigns much of the blame to the dollar's lower value against the Chinese yuan. Officials in Beijing raised the value of their currency by 2.1 percent against the dollar in July 2005, and have let it drift up 5 percent more since then.</p>
        <p>''It's a big problem,'' Ms. Zhao said.</p>
        <p>To be sure, China's exports to the United States are huge and growing, as is the trade imbalance, which is significantly larger than the European Union's deficit with China. That is the main reason trade is a focus of attention for the newly empowered Democrats in Congress, making it likely that trade frictions between the two countries will persist and possibly worsen in the months ahead.</p>
        <p>China surpassed Canada in the first two months of this year as the largest exporter to the United States. According to statistics released by the World Trade Organization last Thursday, China also overtook the United States in the second half of 2006 to become the world's second-largest exporter of goods over all, after Germany.</p>
        <p>China is still nearly 25 times as dependent on exports to the United States as a percentage of its total economic output as the United States is on exports to China. Given that the Chinese economy is less than a quarter the size of the American economy, it is all the more striking that Chinese exports to the United States are worth more than six times American exports to China.</p>
        <p>The American exports accounted for roughly four-tenths of 1 percent of economic output in the first two months of this year, while Chinese exports to the United States equaled nearly 10 percent of China's entire output.</p>
        <p>The government and companies across China increasingly see a danger in becoming too dependent on a single market. So they are stepping up efforts to sell to other countries, particularly those outside the industrial world. For example, the Great Wall Motor Company, a maker of sport utility vehicles and sedans, has more than quintupled its exports in two years, to 27,505 vehicles last year. Virtually all the increase has come from fast-growing, oil-rich markets like Russia and the Middle East. ''Europe and North America are not our primary markets,'' the company's chairman, Wei Jianjun, said.</p>
        <p>And Franklin L. Lavin, the American under secretary of commerce for international trade, said, ''China has been making more of an effort in recent years to diversify its export markets.'' He noted that the Chinese share of American imports was still climbing, but at a slowing rate.</p>
        <p>China has also moved beyond just making huge numbers of T-shirts and toys for prosperous Western consumers. It now produces a wide range of industrial goods and transportation gear, like weaving machines and heavy-duty trucks. It exports them in growing quantities to developing nations, many of them profiting from soaring world commodity prices and in need of the rough-and-ready durability of Chinese products.</p>
        <p>China ships a growing share of its goods to Southern Europe, with sales especially strong to Spain and Italy, where buyers are often less affluent than in Northern Europe -- although there have been signs of a backlash by workers and their unions.</p>
        <p>The shift in exports away from the United States has been under way for several years. But it has accelerated in the last year and particularly in the first two months of this year as the dollar has weakened against the yuan, as well as other currencies.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the strength in the euro and other currencies has made Chinese goods less expensive in those markets.</p>
        <p>China sent more than 31 percent of its exports to the United States in 2000, but that dropped below 24 percent in November and reached 22.7 percent in February, according to a Goldman Sachs tabulation that included Chinese goods trans-shipped through Hong Kong. Exports to the rest of Asia have leveled off, while those to European Union countries rose slightly. Exports to the rest of the world, notably India, Brazil and Russia, have doubled in the last seven years, to 32 percent this winter.</p>
        <p>''Right now, the prices we can get from Russia are a lot higher,'' said Sean Zhu, vice general manager of the Ningbo Guotai Knitwear Company, which makes knit shirts.</p>
        <p>Wang Tongsan, a senior Chinese economic forecaster and member of a committee of experts overseeing the current five-year plan, said the government did not have a policy of pushing exporters to focus on markets other than the United States. He attributed the rise in sales to developing countries to the strong entrepreneurial talents of many Chinese business people.</p>
        <p>Several exporters here said they had not been told by the Commerce Ministry to reduce their dependence on the American market. But government-run trade associations have become more active in helping companies attend trade fairs in Europe and the developing world, they said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zhu said that abundant information in Chinese about foreign markets could now be found on Internet sites run by Alibaba.com, based in Hangzhou, and by various government agencies.</p>
        <p>Chinese officials are acutely conscious of the risks of rising trade barriers in the United States. The Bush administration opened the door on March 30 to requests by American industries that contend that their Chinese competitors receive subsidies. Last week, the administration filed two complaints with the World Trade Organization arguing that Beijing tolerates widespread abuses of copyrights and trademarks.</p>
        <p>Chinese officials are expected to go on another buying trip to the United States before next month's round of meetings in Washington to discuss economic policies with the United States. By wrapping together a lot of separate purchase agreements in a few heavily promoted announcements, the officials hope to portray the United States as needing the Chinese market.</p>
        <p>Similar heavily promoted purchases preceded and coincided with President Hu Jintao's visit to the United States a year ago. And Japanese executives conducted such buying trips to the United States in the 1980s, when Japan's trade surplus became a political issue in Washington.</p>
        <p>State-controlled media reported on Friday that China would proceed with long-expected plans to reduce tax rebates for exporters, especially in industries like steel that use a lot of energy and fresh water, both in short supply in China.</p>
        <p>To underline China's desire to increase imports, the name of the Canton Fair has been formally changed, starting this week. It is now officially the China Import and Export Fair, though the organizers and many of those attending continue to call it the Canton Fair.</p>
        <p>Certain old habits die hard, though. Foreign companies were invited to show their wares, but were relegated to the remote top floor of just one of the more than 30 halls that the trade fair fills at the city's two convention centers.</p>
        <p>Only 18 American companies attended, most of them little known and with small booths. One of the few publicly traded companies was Columbus McKinnon of Amherst, N.Y., selling American-made electric chain hoists. Zhang Qing, the company's China sales manager, said that even with the weakening dollar, Columbus McKinnon focused on selling top-quality hoists instead of trying to compete just on price with Chinese manufacturers.</p>
        <p>Far below, in a heavily traveled ground-floor corridor, executives like Henry Hu, general manager of the Ningbo Rightool Industrial I/E Company, said he was responding to the dollar's weakness by improving the company's products.</p>
        <p>''Everyone is worried, but we focus on increasing the quality of our products,'' said Mr. Hu, who makes socket wrench sets. ''The government is encouraging us not just to manufacture, but to do more research and development.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
