<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dow Index Flirts With New High</title>
    <meta content="18economy" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/business/18economy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841230"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Industrial Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standard &amp; Poor's 500-Stock Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Price Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing Starts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Labor Department (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Commerce Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Reserve System</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peters, Jeremy W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing Starts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Price Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E0DB1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1073" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dow Index Flirts With New High</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Dow Index Flirts With New High</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEREMY W. PETERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Peters, Jeremy W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Government economic reports suggest that economy remains on even keel, with underlying inflation showing signs of easing and growth not slipping too far; reports help put stock market within striking distance of record close; Dow Jones industrial average briefly climbs above its record close but falls back slightly; index gains 52.58 points, at 12,773.04; Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index rises 3.01 points, to close at 1,471.48, highest level in six and half years; Nasdaq composite index closes down 1.38 points, to 2,516.95; Labor Department reports Consumer Price Index edged only 0.1 percentage point in March; overall inflation rose 2.8 percent compared with year earlier; core inflation rose 2.5 percent in same period; Commerce Department data show builders picked up pace of construction on new homes in March while rate of building permits issued rose; Federal Reserve reports overall production declined 0.2 percent; economists note manufacturing grew 0.7 percent; graphs; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The economy remains on an even keel, reports released yesterday by the government suggested, with underlying inflation showing signs of easing and growth not slipping too far.</p>
        <p>This abundance of relatively benign data, together with several healthy corporate earnings reports, helped put Wall Street within striking distance of a record close on Tuesday. In trading yesterday, the Dow Jones industrial average briefly climbed above its record close but then fell back a bit. The blue-chip average finished the day up 52.58, or 0.4 percent, at 12,773.04, about 13 points short of the record of 12,786.64 on Feb. 20.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The economy remains on an even keel, with inflation showing signs of easing and growth not slipping too far.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The economy remains on an even keel, reports released yesterday by the government suggested, with underlying inflation showing signs of easing and growth not slipping too far.</p>
        <p>This abundance of relatively benign data, together with several healthy corporate earnings reports, helped put Wall Street within striking distance of a record close on Tuesday. In trading yesterday, the Dow Jones industrial average briefly climbed above its record close but then fell back a bit. The blue-chip average finished the day up 52.58, or 0.4 percent, at 12,773.04, about 13 points short of the record of 12,786.64 on Feb. 20.</p>
        <p>The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index, meanwhile, rose 3.01 points, 0.2 percent, to close at 1,471.48, its highest level in six and a half years. Yesterday was the 10th day of gains in the S.&amp; P. 500 in the last 11 trading sessions, a sign that investors have mostly shaken off the sting of February's global stock market plunge.</p>
        <p>The Nasdaq composite was the laggard among the major stock indexes yesterday, closing down 1.38, or 0.1 percent, at 2,516.95.</p>
        <p>While the economic data helped lift stocks, profit reports from Coca-Cola and Johnson &amp; Johnson for the first quarter were probably even more important in stoking the rise.</p>
        <p>Coke's earnings rose 14 percent, beating Wall Street's expectations; Johnson &amp; Johnson's quarterly profit fell on a large one-time charge but easily surpassed analysts' forecasts on strong revenue gains. Johnson &amp; Johnson and Coke are both among the 30 stocks included in the Dow; Johnson &amp; Johnson accounted for 12 points of the Dow's gain, and Coke added 10.6.</p>
        <p>But as markets open today, investors could find their mood soured by a disappointing earnings report from Yahoo, which was released after regular trading closed. Investors will also be watching earnings reports today from JPMorgan Chase and United Technologies. And Motorola and eBay are scheduled to report after the market closes.</p>
        <p>The economic data released yesterday, while mixed, struck investors as generally positive. Higher gas prices helped push up the Consumer Price Index, the Labor Department reported, but the more closely watched core indicator, which does not include the volatile food and energy prices, edged up only 0.1 percentage point.</p>
        <p>Still, the annual rate of core inflation remained above the roughly 2 percent level the Federal Reserve considers acceptable, virtually ensuring that interest rates will remain unchanged for at least the next few months, economists said.</p>
        <p>''Core consumer inflation has been retreating, irregularly, for the past six months,'' Steven A. Wood of Insight Economics wrote in a newsletter. ''Despite worries about the upside risks associated with inflation and sluggish economic activity,'' he wrote, the Fed will probably not raise interest rates for most or even all of this year.</p>
        <p>New data from the Commerce Department showed that builders picked up the pace of construction on new homes last month while the rate of building permits issued rose. A separate report from the Fed found that manufacturing activity in March expanded even though overall industrial production and capacity utilization fell slightly.</p>
        <p>The modest increase in core inflation was just half the 0.2 percent advance in February. Falling apparel prices, along with slower increases in shelter and medical care costs, helped keep the core increase tame.</p>
        <p>But inflation statistics for the full year remain outside the Fed's preferred target. Overall inflation rose 2.8 percent compared with March 2006; core inflation rose 2.5 percent in the same period.</p>
        <p>''Inflation is rising quite rapidly, and that is not an environment in which one gets terribly confident about the trajectory of inflation,'' said Dean Maki, an economist with Barclays Capital. ''Core inflation is moderating,'' he added, but ''it would have to play out over a few months for it to be convincing.''</p>
        <p>The Fed chairman, Ben S. Bernanke, and other members of the Federal Open Market Committee, which sets policy, have said they would like to see yearly core inflation of 1 percent to 2 percent.</p>
        <p>''We're still not getting inflation improvement that's putting the trend numbers back within the Fed's comfort zone,'' said Gregory Miller, chief economist at SunTrust Banks. ''The Fed has said, 'If inflation rates are outside our band, we're going to stay biased against inflation.' And I believe them.''</p>
        <p>Some economists noted signs of potential aberrations in the data that could suggest that the slowing core inflation last month was a one-time event. Apparel prices dropped 1 percent, falling for the first time since October. Hotel prices fell 2.3 percent, a sharp decline considering that they rose steadily last year.</p>
        <p>And with gas prices rising again, the Fed could become concerned that energy increases might be passed through to other prices and stoke core inflation. In March gasoline prices rose more than 10 percent.</p>
        <p>The Fed probably saw little else in the economic reports yesterday that would persuade it to change its posture, economists said. The residential construction report, while not suggesting a substantial rebound in the housing market, did appear to hint at stabilization.</p>
        <p>The rate of building permits authorized last month rose 0.8 percent after falling in January and February. And the rate of construction of new homes increased for the second consecutive month, climbing 0.8 percent.</p>
        <p>''There's a suggestion that perhaps the decline in housing starts from here on out is going to be limited,'' said Jan Hatzius, chief United States economist at Goldman Sachs. But it could turn out that growth slows more than economists now foresee.</p>
        <p>''We have a slowing economy,'' Mr. Hatzius said. ''And housing getting better doesn't mean you're no longer seeing a drag. In some ways, the drag from housing is still ahead of us.'' On Monday, Goldman Sachs lowered its estimate for growth in economic activity for the first quarter to 1.2 percent from 2 percent.</p>
        <p>Economists took some comfort in the industrial production numbers released yesterday by the Federal Reserve. While overall industrial output declined 0.2 percent, much of that was caused by a 7 percent drop in output from utilities because of warmer temperatures.</p>
        <p>On the upside, economists noted, manufacturing grew 0.7 percent, a sign that businesses are selling off their excess inventories both at home and abroad.</p>
        <p>''Following are the results of yesterday's auction of four-week Treasury bills:</p>
        <p>(000 omitted in dollar figures)  Price: 99.623  High Rate: 4.840  Coupon Yield: 4.939  Low Rate: 4.800  Median Rate: 4.820  Total applied for: $37,313,644  Accepted: $12,761,444  Noncompetitive: $444,747  The four-week bills mature May 17, 2007.</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
