<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Coast Guard to Manage Fleet Modernization</title>
    <meta content="18coast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/washington/18coast.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841172"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Defense Contracts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Defense Contracts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Coast Guard</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Lockheed Martin</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Northrop Grumman</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E3DC1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="705" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Coast Guard to Manage Fleet Modernization</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Coast Guard to Manage Fleet Modernization</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC LIPTON</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After months of criticism and setbacks, the Coast Guard announced Tuesday that it was taking over the management of its $24 billion fleet modernization project, curtailing the role of two military contractors that had been hired to run the job.</p>
        <p>The move by Adm. Thad W. Allen, the Coast Guard commandant, is a major embarrassment for the contractors, Lockheed Martin and Northrop Grumman, which had formed a partnership to oversee the delivery of 91 new ships and more than 240 new or rebuilt aircraft.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Coast Guard announced that it was curtailing the role of two military contractors in its $24 billion fleet modernization project.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After months of criticism and setbacks, the Coast Guard announced Tuesday that it was taking over the management of its $24 billion fleet modernization project, curtailing the role of two military contractors that had been hired to run the job.</p>
        <p>The move by Adm. Thad W. Allen, the Coast Guard commandant, is a major embarrassment for the contractors, Lockheed Martin and Northrop Grumman, which had formed a partnership to oversee the delivery of 91 new ships and more than 240 new or rebuilt aircraft.</p>
        <p>All three major classes of ships that Lockheed and Northrop have worked on since winning the contract in 2002 have had serious problems. Admiral Allen said Tuesday that eight renovated 123-foot patrol boats were so unseaworthy they would be permanently retired.</p>
        <p>The setbacks have undermined earlier assertions that private contractors, not the government, are best suited to manage such a complex project.</p>
        <p>Lockheed and Northrop will still play a major role in the program, known as Deepwater, with the Coast Guard serving as what Admiral Allen described as the ''system integrator.'' The Coast Guard will no longer presume that Northrop and Lockheed, and subcontractors they hire, will be in charge of designing and building the new ships and planes under the 25-year program, Admiral Allen said.</p>
        <p>Instead, the Coast Guard will consider hiring the contractors directly and will play a much more substantial role in reviewing the design for each new class of ships and planes, he said. The Coast Guard also plans to hire outside experts to review the planned designs in an effort to identify flaws before the ships and planes are built.</p>
        <p>The Coast Guard will also now be in charge of maintaining the fleet once it is built.</p>
        <p>Admiral Allen said Deepwater had stumbled because the Coast Guard and its contractors put more emphasis on trying to honor a construction schedule than on worrying about the cost and performance of the ships being built.</p>
        <p>''We understand all too well what has been ailing us within Deepwater for the past five years,'' he said Tuesday. ''We've relied too much on contractors to do the work of government as a result of tightening budgets.''</p>
        <p>Margaret Mitchell-Jones, a spokeswoman for Integrated Coast Guard Systems, the partnership formed by Lockheed and Northrop, said she did not believe that the announcement by Admiral Allen represented a significant change in the relationship between the Coast Guard and the companies. The Coast Guard has always been in charge of the program, Ms. Mitchell-Jones said.</p>
        <p>''We look forward to continuing to build ships and aircraft, communication systems and to provide logistics support as determined by the Coast Guard," she said.</p>
        <p>The chairmen of the House and Senate subcommittees that oversee the Coast Guard praised the move by Admiral Allen.</p>
        <p>''Today, the Coast Guard has moved decisively to take back the helm of the Deepwater contract and to right this floundering procurement program,'' said Representative Elijah E. Cummings, Democrat of Maryland.</p>
        <p>Legislation had already been introduced in Congress to require the Coast Guard to take steps similar to those Admiral Allen announced Tuesday. Senator Maria Cantwell, Democrat of Washington, said in a statement that she would continue to push for passage of the bill.</p>
        <p>''The Coast Guard can't pick and choose elements from this bill and ignore others that many government reports have called essential,'' Ms. Cantwell said.</p>
        <p>The announcement came a day before a hearing at which a House panel was scheduled to take testimony from officials involved in the failed patrol boat project.</p>
        <p>Michael DeKort, a former Lockheed system engineer on the 123-foot patrol boat project, will testify that he spent three years trying to get company officials to address serious flaws with electronics equipment that left the boats vulnerable to failure in bad weather.</p>
        <p>Soon after the first rebuilt patrol boats were launched, cracks formed in their decks and hulls, and then a series of mechanical problems appeared.</p>
        <p>The Coast Guard pulled the renovated ships from service late last year but has decided to permanently retire them because repairs would cost another $50 million, on top of the $100 million spent on renovations.</p>
        <p>Admiral Allen said the Coast Guard would seek to recoup some of the loss from the contractors.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
