<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bell Canada In Discussions With Pensions To Go Private</title>
    <meta content="18phone" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/business/worldbusiness/18phone.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841146"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bce Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bell Canada</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ontario Teachers Pension Plan</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Austen, Ian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Canada</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Bell Canada</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E2DD1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="578" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bell Canada In Discussions With Pensions To Go Private</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bell Canada in Discussions With Pensions to Go Private</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN AUSTEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Austen, Ian</byline>
      <dateline>OTTAWA, April 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>BCE, parent of Bell Canada, is talking about going private with three Canadian pension funds and Kohlberg Kravis Roberts; announcement comes after reports that its BCE's largest shareholder, Ontario Teachers' Pension Plan, is forming consortium to make similar bid (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BCE, the parent of Bell Canada, said Tuesday that it was talking about going private with three Canadian pension funds and Kohlberg Kravis Roberts, the private equity group.</p>
        <p>The announcement from BCE, the largest telecommunications company in Canada, comes after reports that its largest shareholder, the Ontario Teachers' Pension Plan, was forming a consortium to make a similar bid.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The parent of Bell Canada said it was talking about going private with three Canadian pension funds and Kohlberg Kravis Roberts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BCE, the parent of Bell Canada, said Tuesday that it was talking about going private with three Canadian pension funds and Kohlberg Kravis Roberts, the private equity group.</p>
        <p>The announcement from BCE, the largest telecommunications company in Canada, comes after reports that its largest shareholder, the Ontario Teachers' Pension Plan, was forming a consortium to make a similar bid.</p>
        <p>BCE has a market value of $27.54 billion. A buyout of the 127-year-old company would be the largest ever attempted in Canada and could be about $45 billion.</p>
        <p>The battle between the pension groups is a further demonstration of their increasingly dominant role in Canadian markets.</p>
        <p>Shares of BCE, which is based in Montreal, rose $2.34 Canadian, or 6 percent, to $38.60 Canadian a share.</p>
        <p>Debt analysts took a negative view, however. DBRS, a debt rating service based in Toronto, put the company under review with negative implications.</p>
        <p>In a statement, BCE said that it would look at other possibilities ''to further enhance shareholder value'' and added that the company might decide against taking any action.</p>
        <p>Because Canadian law limits foreign ownership of telecommunications companies to 46.67 percent of voting equity, Kohlberg Kravis is a minority partner in the bidding group. The consortium, which is led by the Canada Pension Plan Investment Board, instead emphasized its predominantly Canadian makeup.</p>
        <p>Ian Dale, a spokesman for the investment board, which manages the funds held by Canada's national public pension program but operates at arm's length from the government, said that the fund first considered making a bid with just Kohlberg Kravis as a partner last summer.</p>
        <p>Unlike the teachers' fund, which has been openly critical of the performance of BCE, the pension board group wanted a friendly buyout, Mr. Dale said.</p>
        <p>Kohlberg's history with BCE goes back to 2002 when it joined the teachers' fund to purchase the company's telephone directory operation.</p>
        <p>The pension board and Kohlberg Kravis made several approaches to BCE. But the company announced late last year that it would convert to an income trust, a structure that avoids corporate taxes by paying most of its earnings directly to investors. The federal government, however, thwarted that plan by introducing a tax on the funds.</p>
        <p>One stumbling block for the initial pitch, people close to the talks said, was concern that Kohlberg Kravis might be perceived as having too prominent a role. Recent foreign takeovers of Canadian companies in industries like steel and mining have made such sales a delicate issue.</p>
        <p>The Canada Pension Plan board might eliminate such concerns by bringing in the Caisse de dépôt et placement du Québec, which manages public and government worker pension funds in that province, and the Public Sector Pension Investment Board, which holds funds for federal government employees, members of Canada's armed forces and the Royal Canadian Mounted Police.</p>
        <p>The latest negotiations may not mark the end of bidding for BCE, which dominates the telephone industry in eastern Canada.</p>
        <p>In a statement, the teachers' fund said that it was still considering ''leading an alternative Canadian consortium.''</p>
        <p>Several other large Canadian funds, including one that invests for municipal workers in Ontario, could still join with the teachers' fund and its partner, Providence Equity Partners. an investment firm based in Providence, R.I., that has holdings in many communications companies.</p>
        <p>In addition, some analysts and BCE shareholders have proposed that the company merge with Telus, the main telephone operator in British Columbia and Alberta, a deal that might encounter regulatory hurdles.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
