<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Adding to the Novice's Wine List</title>
    <meta content="18lett-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841223"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E1DB1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="373" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Adding to the Novice's Wine List</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re Eric Asimov's column ''To Study Wine, Buy and Drink'' (April 11):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re Eric Asimov's column ''To Study Wine, Buy and Drink'' (April 11):</p>
        <p>I have to applaud the long overdue dose of common sense advice to consumers. Most wine drinkers who are starting out rely on scores or puffs or stars. Scoring systems have the effect of homogenizing wine and making snobs out of those who would use wine as a social weapon rather than a social pleasure.</p>
        <p>To Mr. Asimov's sage advice I would add the admonition not to get stuck on a wine you love, but to keep exploring beyond it. You can always go back to your favorite chardonnay or Chianti, but there's more out there than you can imagine. Be curious!</p>
        <p>As for buying that first wine book, any one of the excellent wine encyclopedias available (Tom Stevenson, Hugh Johnson, Karen MacNeil, Oz Clarke, et al.) would be far more useful than a ''Dummies'' type book. A wine encyclopedia will include richly detailed maps and wine law information beyond that of a basic, comprehensive primer.</p>
        <p>Overkill, perhaps, for someone starting to learn about wine, but when your trusty wine merchant or sommelier gives you an off-the-beaten-path gem, you can immediately reinforce your tasting with information not found in general wine books.</p>
        <p>There's also Google, of course.</p>
        <p>Steven Hewins  New York</p>
        <p>The writer is the general manager of Five Points restaurant.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>With all due respect to Mr. Asimov, his suggestion is too cumbersome, expensive and limiting.</p>
        <p>Yes, reading, taking wine classes and tasting wine are all well and good, but in the varied world of wine producers -- from Australia to Turkey, from $10 Chileans to $2,000 Bordeaux/Burgundies and varietals from cabernet sauvignon to trebbiano -- a sure and expeditious way to train your palate, to experience the joy of wine and the geniality of fellow wine lovers and to obtain an education in wine is to join a wine society.</p>
        <p>In 1972 I was instrumental in forming the Essex County (N.J.) Wine Society. It has moderated tastings every six weeks, each with a different wine theme, and semiannual dinners. Its 70 members are extremely knowledgeable about wine and have accumulated excellent wines for their cellars.</p>
        <p>Herbert New  Verona, N.J.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
