<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Referee Who Ejected Duncan Is Suspended</title>
    <meta content="18referee" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/sports/basketball/18referee.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841237"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Dallas Mavericks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/San Antonio Spurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Officiating (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Basketball Assn</org>
        <org class="online_producer">San Antonio Spurs</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Dallas Mavericks</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Stern, David</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Ginobili, Manu</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Nelson, Don</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00EFDB1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="789" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Referee Who Ejected Duncan Is Suspended</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Referee Who Ejected Duncan Is Himself Suspended</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just days before the start of the playoffs, the N.B.A. indefinitely suspended one of its top referees, Joey Crawford, for inappropriate behavior during Sunday's San Antonio-Dallas game.</p>
        <p>Tim Duncan, who had been whistled earlier for a technical foul, was ejected by Crawford late in the third quarter for laughing from the bench after his teammate Fabricio Oberto was called for a foul. Duncan left the court and muttered an obscenity at Crawford, and yesterday the N.B.A. fined Duncan $25,000 for doing that.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the N.B.A.’s top referees was indefinitely suspendedfor inappropriate behavior toward Tim Duncan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just days before the start of the playoffs, the N.B.A. indefinitely suspended one of its top referees, Joey Crawford, for inappropriate behavior during Sunday's San Antonio-Dallas game.</p>
        <p>Tim Duncan, who had been whistled earlier for a technical foul, was ejected by Crawford late in the third quarter for laughing from the bench after his teammate Fabricio Oberto was called for a foul. Duncan left the court and muttered an obscenity at Crawford, and yesterday the N.B.A. fined Duncan $25,000 for doing that.</p>
        <p>''Joey Crawford's handling of this situation failed to meet the standards of professionalism and game management we expect of N.B.A. referees,'' Commissioner David Stern said yesterday in a statement. ''Especially in light of similar prior acts by this official, a significant suspension is warranted. Although Joey is consistently rated as one of our top referees, he must be held accountable for his actions on the floor, and we will have further discussions with him following the season to be sure he understands his responsibilities.''</p>
        <p>After the Spurs' 91-86 loss, Duncan told reporters that he believed Crawford had a vendetta against him.</p>
        <p>''Before he gave me the two technical fouls, he made a call and I was shaking my head, and he walks down and stares at me,'' Duncan told The San Antonio News-Express. ''He says, 'Do you want to fight? Do you want to fight?' I didn't say anything to him there, either.''</p>
        <p>Crawford was interviewed by a pool reporter after the game and said that Duncan had been ''complaining the whole time.''</p>
        <p>''And then he went over to the bench and he was over there doing the same stuff behind our back,'' Crawford added. ''I hit him with one and he kept going over there, laughing, and I look over there and he's still complaining. So I threw him out.''</p>
        <p>In an interview yesterday on the ESPN program ''Pardon the Interruption,'' Stern dismissed the notion of a vendetta and said Crawford did not show remorse when they spoke Monday. Stern also indicated that Crawford might not want to come back next season.</p>
        <p>''He doesn't think he did anything wrong,'' Stern said. ''Probably, he doesn't wish to work in the N.B.A. anymore. It's our plan to talk about the future.''</p>
        <p>Crawford, in his 31st season as an N.B.A. referee, has been a fixture, having officiated more playoff games (266) and more N.B.A. finals games (38) than any other active referee.</p>
        <p>Stern was upset that Crawford had not heeded his admonition from an incident in 2003. Crawford was called into league offices to discuss how he gave four technical fouls to the Dallas Mavericks in Game 2 of the Western Conference finals with the Spurs. He had ejected Don Nelson, who was the Mavericks' coach at the time, for standing by the scorer's table in apparent frustration, and later ejected Del Harris, the Mavericks' assistant coach.</p>
        <p>Stern considered Crawford's behavior grandstanding and warned him that he would not tolerate another such incident. Crawford returned to referee two N.B.A. finals games that year between the Spurs and the Nets.</p>
        <p>''He's been specifically asked by me to change his conduct and he wasn't able to do it,'' Stern said on ESPN. The suspension, Stern said, was a result of ''our earlier interaction where Joey knows our views on, shall I say, his loss of control; you just can't keep doing that.''</p>
        <p>Messages left at the National Basketball Referees Association to reach Crawford were not returned yesterday. Lamell McMorris, a spokesman for the association, declined to comment. Duncan and Spurs officials declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Billy Hunter, the executive director of the National Basketball Players Association, has been critical of the league for giving referees powers to discipline players' behavior.</p>
        <p>''In my view, Joey Crawford clearly went over the line in this instance and some level of discipline was warranted,'' Hunter said yesterday in a statement. ''At the same time, I think part of the problem lies with the new rules regarding technical fouls and the lack of consistency with which those rules have been applied.''</p>
        <p>Crawford was not the first referee the N.B.A. suspended this season.</p>
        <p>Rodney Mott, in his ninth season, was suspended for three games without pay in January for directing an obscene gesture toward a fan and using inappropriate language in a game in Portland.</p>
        <p>Crawford, with his bald pate and expressive face, is one of the more conspicuous referees in the game. He is known for his emotional style and comes from a lineage of high-profile officials. His brother, Jerry, is an umpire for Major League Baseball. His father, Shag, was also a major league umpire.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Stern did not consider Crawford's pedigree, but rather how his behavior affected the image of the league.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
