<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Redesigning the Met's Home for Greek and Roman Art</title>
    <meta content="18wing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/arts/design/18wing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841114"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roman Civilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roman Civilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Metropolitan Museum of Art</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Roche, Kevin</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Levy, Leon</person>
        <person class="online_producer">de Montebello, Philippe</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E3DE1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1167" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Redesigning the Met's Home for Greek and Roman Art</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Redesigning the Met’s Home for Greek and Roman Art</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN POGREBIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pogrebin, Robin</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The week that the Metropolitan Museum of Art's southernmost wing reopened as a restaurant in 1954, with outré birdcage chandeliers and a central pool dotted by whimsical muses, the architect Kevin Roche found himself eating there. ''I had a nice lunch,'' Mr. Roche, now 85, said. ''That's about as far as I thought about it.''</p>
        <p>Over the last several years, however, that wing has been an abiding preoccupation for Mr. Roche, whose task has been to transform the space again into the Met's new Greek and Roman galleries, which officially open on Friday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Over the last several years, architect Kevin Roche has been busy transforming the Met’s southernmost wing, which will officially open on Friday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The week that the Metropolitan Museum of Art's southernmost wing reopened as a restaurant in 1954, with outré birdcage chandeliers and a central pool dotted by whimsical muses, the architect Kevin Roche found himself eating there. ''I had a nice lunch,'' Mr. Roche, now 85, said. ''That's about as far as I thought about it.''</p>
        <p>Over the last several years, however, that wing has been an abiding preoccupation for Mr. Roche, whose task has been to transform the space again into the Met's new Greek and Roman galleries, which officially open on Friday.</p>
        <p>The reconstruction of the galleries and adjacent areas -- a 15-year, $220 million project -- will enable the Met to exhibit some 5,300 works, or 95 percent of this collection, about half of which had been in storage in recent decades. By restoring the south wing to its original purpose, the reconstruction also pays homage to the vision of its first architects, McKim, Mead &amp; White, who created it with Greek and Roman art in mind.</p>
        <p>The main challenge for Mr. Roche was reinvigorating the existing architecture while respectfully injecting a fresh perspective. As something like the Met's resident architect for the last 40 years or so -- his firm was hired to map out a new master plan for the museum in 1967 -- he came to the project with ample experience.</p>
        <p>''He knows the building inside out,'' said Philippe de Montebello, the Met's director. ''Where are all the conduits, where is the air-conditioning, how deep are the walls.''</p>
        <p>The hardest challenge, Mr. Roche said, was negotiating various concerns, from the displacement of visitors during construction to making sure that the art was carefully transported and installed. ''The architecture is relatively simple,'' he said. ''The human aspect is always more complicated.''</p>
        <p>The heart of the new galleries is a barrel-vaulted central hall with skylights, now called the Leon Levy and Shelby White Court, for the New York collectors who helped finance the new space. While it was originally opened in 1926 as a single-story, peristyle court with Doric columns, the new courtyard has a two-story peristyle with Ionic columns, doubling the height of the gallery.</p>
        <p>In restoring the court, Mr. Roche said, he had to work out ''exactly what moment in Roman architecture'' to honor. ''We decided to go from B.C. to A.D., when the Roman republic was drifting into becoming an empire,'' Mr. Roche said. ''It was also the time of Augustus and a great time for culture -- Horace and Virgil and Ovid.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Roche studied major Roman buildings, like the Theater of Marcellus, the Coliseum and the Basilica; Etruscan architecture from that period; and the work of the 16th-century architect Vignola, designer of the Villa Giulia.</p>
        <p>The new tessera floor is modeled after that of the Pantheon, with green-and-red marble in alternating squares and circles. The floor pieces were cut and shaped in Italy, then hand-laid on sand bedding without grouting.</p>
        <p>''It allows the stone to settle into place,'' said Jeffrey L. Daly, the Met's senior design adviser to the director for capital and special projects.</p>
        <p>Whether to retain the existing black-and-white mosaic tile floor bordering the gallery, part of McKim, Mead &amp; White's original space, was a focus of debate. The Met finally decided to fix the cracks and keep it.</p>
        <p>The original skylights now have clear glass to allow natural light. ''On a sunny day, you need sunglasses,'' Mr. Daly said.</p>
        <p>Building a fountain was another point of contention. McKim, Mead &amp; White's 1920s court featured a modest rectangular pool surrounded by greenery and classical sculpture. But this time many of those involved were concerned that a water feature in the center of the soaring space would rivet the eye and upstage the art.</p>
        <p>The museum installed a mock-up fashioned from foam board that no one particularly liked. But then Met officials saw the actual black marble fountain -- nine feet in diameter -- that the stone carver had made and loved it. ''It was stunning, sitting outside of a stone quarry yard under a tree,'' said Mr. Daly, who traveled to the work site.</p>
        <p>The floor was a major undertaking; the Met dug down two stories to install heavy-duty steel framework, strong enough to withstand 300 pounds per square foot. (Most museum floors are built to handle 100 to 150 pounds per square foot, Mr. Daly said). The heaviest piece in the new court is a third-century B.C. Greek statue of Dionysus, which weighs around 4,200 pounds, including its base.</p>
        <p>Planning began in 1912 for the construction of the original galleries. In 1916 building was interrupted by World War I and did not resume until 1923, with the galleries finally opening in 1926. Edward Robinson, then the museum's director, wrote that the court was intended ''to show Greek and Roman works of art in something like the setting and atmosphere in which they were seen in antiquity.''</p>
        <p>Another goal, he wrote, was to give the casual visitor a break from the usual museum routine, allowing him or her ''to rest and meditate undisturbed by any sound save the tranquil splashing of water.''</p>
        <p>But when Francis Henry Taylor took over as director in 1940, he resolved to turn the grand Roman court into a public restaurant and install offices on a mezzanine above.</p>
        <p>''Greek and Roman lost half of its exhibition spaces and was not to recover from this amputation for over half a century,'' Carlos Picón, the Met curator in charge of the department of Greek and Roman art, writes in a new catalog. The court became the dining room; the former Etruscan gallery, a kitchen.</p>
        <p>The restaurant would evolve further in the following decades. The central pool with the bronze Fountain of the Muses, by the Swedish sculptor Carl Milles, was eventually drained and became a sunken dining area; the fountain was shipped to South Carolina.</p>
        <p>In remaking the galleries Mr. Roche decided to blow out the southernmost back wall, exposing the mezzanine where the Met's prized bronze Etruscan chariot now sits.</p>
        <p>''It had to be done because you wanted to see all the way to the end,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The new galleries were always intended as the pièce de résistance signaling the completion of the Met's latest master plan, created under Thomas P. F. Hoving, Mr. Montebello's predecessor. Mr. Montebello, who has served as director since 1978, hired Mr. Picón in 1990 to oversee the reinstallation of the Greek and Roman galleries.</p>
        <p>The mezzanine now displays some 3,500 objects identified by perusal of electronic touchpad screens. The adjoining spaces present south Italian art; Hellenistic art, architecture and coins; and the art of Augustan Rome, Roman imperial art and the art of the later Roman empire. The galleries are organized chronologically -- from the Hellenistic period (third to first century B.C.) to the Later Roman Empire (third century A.D.) -- but there is no clearly articulated path for visitors.</p>
        <p>''I don't believe in itineraries; I believe in wanderings,'' Mr. Montebello said. ''The head of Constantine tells you you're in the last stages.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
