<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.M. Says It Will Make More Vehicles and Buy More Parts in India</title>
    <meta content="18auto" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/automobiles/18auto.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841139"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Timmons, Heather</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wagoner, Rick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">India</location>
        <org class="online_producer">General Motors Corp</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E3DD1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="647" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.M. Says It Will Make More Vehicles and Buy More Parts in India</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">G.M. Says It Will Make More Vehicles and Buy More Parts in India</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HEATHER TIMMONS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Timmons, Heather</byline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI, April 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>General Motors has big plans in India; chief executive Rick Wagoner, in visit to New Delhi, hails country's thrifty manufacturing culture and growing car market and says company will significantly increase purchasing and production in India; company introduces new model into Indian market, compact hatchback priced at about $7.400; car sales in India are growing about 15 percent each year, rate projected to continue for next five years, with low-cost cars making up bulk of sales; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>General Motors has big plans in India.</p>
        <p>In a visit to New Delhi on Tuesday, G.M.'s chief executive, Rick Wagoner, hailed the country's thrifty manufacturing culture and growing car market and said the company would significantly increase purchasing and production here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>G.M.’s chief executive hailed India’s growing car market and said the company would increase purchasing and production in the country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>General Motors has big plans in India.</p>
        <p>In a visit to New Delhi on Tuesday, G.M.'s chief executive, Rick Wagoner, hailed the country's thrifty manufacturing culture and growing car market and said the company would significantly increase purchasing and production here.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Wagoner said that G.M. planned to create a ''local base'' in India, a move that he said would not affect United States jobs.</p>
        <p>The company also introduced a new model into the Indian market on Tuesday, a compact hatchback priced at about $7,400. Car sales in India are growing about 15 percent a year, a rate projected to continue for the next five years, with low-cost cars making up the bulk of the sales.</p>
        <p>G.M. and other big automakers, hoping to offset slumping North American operations, are increasingly looking to India. In the past, the country has generally taken a back seat to China, but a growing middle class and new manufacturing prowess have made India popular for joint ventures and investments. G.M. expects India to be the second-fastest-growing car market in the world, after China, over the next 10 years.</p>
        <p>''It's time to redouble our efforts on our manufacturing and market presence here,'' Mr. Wagoner told government ministers and auto industry executives in a conference on the Indian auto industry.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wagoner said G.M. planned to take advantage of India's high-quality, low-cost supply base ''to source more parts out of India.''</p>
        <p>In a statement issued after his presentation, Mr. Wagoner said the sourcing increase could be ''as much as fivefold over the next two years.''</p>
        <p>Analysts said that might translate into G.M.'s buying as much as $1 billion worth of car parts in India annually, which would be the most spent by a foreign automaker in India.</p>
        <p>In a brief interview after the conference, Mr. Wagoner said that the increased sourcing of car parts from India would not affect United States jobs because the components in question are not made in America. He would not specify which parts would come from India in the future.</p>
        <p>Given the growth of G.M.'s manufacturing in Asia, a company base in India would provide new opportunities for Indian suppliers, he said,</p>
        <p>Indian manufacturing costs are already ''extremely competitive and among the lowest in the world,'' Mr. Wagoner said during the conference. That is ''not just due to lower wage rates,'' he said. ''It is also a function of the Indian mentality that abhors waste -- because people cannot afford to throw things away.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wagoner said G.M. would more than double its production capacity in India, to 225,000 vehicles a year, by making more vehicles at its Halol factory in the state of Gujarat and building a new plant in Talegaon, Maharashtra, both in western India.</p>
        <p>India has been trying to become Asia's low-cost car manufacturing center, offering tax breaks and other incentives. Renault and Nissan announced plans in January to work with an Indian company to build a new car plant.</p>
        <p>Local analysts and manufacturing executives say India has a quality advantage over China. ''The Chinese are known to manufacture very cheap cars, but the problem is that safety and emission norms are something they don't meet,'' said Kapil Singh, an auto analyst with Brics Securities, a brokerage house in Mumbai. Indian standards are as good as any in the world, he said.</p>
        <p>G.M.'s North American operations lost $4.6 billion in 2006, including about $3.8 billion that it spent on buyouts and other one-time items. Profit margins are also weakening in China, G.M.'s second-largest market, as competition lowers car prices.</p>
        <p>The new car G.M. will sell in India, the Chevrolet Spark, will be its smallest car in India. The other two G.M. models there cost significantly more, and sales are sluggish. ''G.M. has a long way to go in India,'' said Mr. Singh. ''They haven't been in the mainstream car business yet.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
