<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shoot Straight? Not This Gang</title>
    <meta content="18knicks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/sports/basketball/18knicks.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841175"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Basketball Assn</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Temple University</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E3DC1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1076" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shoot Straight? Not This Gang</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Shoot Straight? Not These Knicks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beck, Howard</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mardy Collins came into the N.B.A. with a character profile that any coach would adore, and a jump shot that was frightful.</p>
        <p>''Seeing his shot early in the year, honestly he had a 50 percent chance of it being an air ball -- every shot,'' the Knicks veteran Malik Rose said of Collins, his rookie teammate. ''I'm serious. One shot a day, easy, was going to be an air ball.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mardy Collins’s recent emergence as a shooter has been a rare bright spot for the Knicks. Yet Renaldo Balkman and David Lee still lack an outside shot that opponents respect.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mardy Collins came into the N.B.A. with a character profile that any coach would adore, and a jump shot that was frightful.</p>
        <p>''Seeing his shot early in the year, honestly he had a 50 percent chance of it being an air ball -- every shot,'' the Knicks veteran Malik Rose said of Collins, his rookie teammate. ''I'm serious. One shot a day, easy, was going to be an air ball.''</p>
        <p>The Knicks did not view Collins, a guard from Temple, as a scoring ace when they made him the 29th pick last June -- nor did they need him to be one. They had a surplus of shoot-happy guards on the roster.</p>
        <p>On draft night, Coach Isiah Thomas praised Collins's ball-handling skills and his basketball acumen, his defense and his size (at 6 feet 6 inches, he is big for a point guard).</p>
        <p>A jump shot, if Collins had one, was immaterial in an off-season that Thomas spent casting for willing defenders. Renaldo Balkman, the Knicks' other first-round pick, and Jared Jeffries, signed as a free agent, also fit the profile.</p>
        <p>But the Knicks' class of 2006-7 is the gang that couldn't shoot straight. In the preseason, Jeffries shot air balls from the foul line. Balkman shot air balls from everywhere else. Teammates were advised to duck and cover.</p>
        <p>Lately, they have been more inclined to watch with glee when the ball leaves Collins's fingertips.</p>
        <p>''If it doesn't go in, it's on the rim,'' Rose said. ''It looks good.''</p>
        <p>The discovery of a jump shot for Collins has coincided with a broader revelation -- Collins as a key piece in the Knicks' future. When injuries wiped out the rotation several weeks ago, Collins was pressed into a major role. His steadiness at the point was not surprising, nor were his quick hands on defense.</p>
        <p>But the scoring touch, the open jumpers made from 15, 18 and 20 feet out, seemed to surprise everyone, including opponents. Collins's emergence has been a rare bright spot in the dreary final days of another losing season that ends tonight at Charlotte.</p>
        <p>''Mardy continues to amaze me,'' Thomas said Monday night. ''After every game, you look at the stat sheet and you're like, 'Wow.' As the game is going on, you don't realize he's having that good a game until at the end, you look at it and the guy's getting close to a triple-double every night. It's pretty impressive.''</p>
        <p>Collins has started the past eight games, filling a void left by injuries to Jamal Crawford, Stephon Marbury and, for a stretch, Steve Francis. During that span, Collins has averaged 15.6 points, 6.4 rebounds and 6.5 assists and flirted with a triple-double three times. On Monday, Collins had a career-high 23 points and was three assists short of a triple-double. On Sunday at Toronto, he missed another by two rebounds. On April 7, at Milwaukee, he fell two assists short.</p>
        <p>The jump shot comes and goes, but Collins no longer risks embarrassment when he takes it. The progress is especially obvious in his 3-point shooting -- he hit 6 of 13 over the past three games. Until this season, Collins rarely even shot from that distance.</p>
        <p>It seems counterintuitive that a basketball player could make it this far without a jumper, although it is not that unusual. It is, however, a problem for the Knicks, because three of their best defenders (Collins, Balkman and Jeffries) and their best rebounder (David Lee) have the same hole in their game -- the lack of an outside shot that opponents will respect.</p>
        <p>All were acquired in part to shore up the Knicks' shaky defense, with Lee, Balkman and Collins all arriving in the last two seasons as relatively unheralded draft picks who turned into pleasant surprises and could become part of a core of an improving team. But all three of them, and Jeffries, can be liabilities at the offensive end, which in turn allows teams to triple-team Eddy Curry in the post and clog the paint when Marbury or Crawford tries to drive.</p>
        <p>''It kind of drives you to work a little harder, because guys are sinking off you,'' Collins said.</p>
        <p>It was not always this way. Collins was a solid midrange shooter at Philadelphia's Simon Gratz High School, scoring off screens and curls -- ''like Rip,'' Collins said, referring to the Detroit Pistons' Richard Hamilton, another player from Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>Things changed when he got to Temple, and Coach Don Chaney converted him into a point guard. For four years, Collins got his points on layups, runners and post-ups against shorter guards, but rarely with a spot-up jumper. He lost his touch.</p>
        <p>The story is similar for the Knicks' other shot-challenged young players. The lanky, 6-11 Jeffries was always the tallest player on the court in high school and college and played exclusively around the basket. So did Lee.</p>
        <p>Rose, who was primarily a rebounder and interior player in college, said players can develop a jumper once they arrive in the N.B.A.</p>
        <p>''I didn't have a jump shot until my third year in the league,'' said Rose, an 11-year veteran. ''Mardy's hustle and his defense and his attitude kept him around, and he knows how to play. Now he's playing more, he's made a few shots, that confidence is kicking in.''</p>
        <p>Collins works daily with the assistant coach George Glymph to refine his form. But he will earn court time because of everything else he does. Collins is smart, steady and selfless as a playmaker. A rangy defender, he is averaging 2.12 steals during his eight games as a starter.</p>
        <p>''Shooting's not everything,'' Collins said.</p>
        <p>Collins has a demeanor to match his fundamentally sound play. His expression never changes, whether he has just dunked or been dunked upon. He is, in many ways, the polar opposite of the Knicks' other young guard, Nate Robinson, a constant yapper whose supreme physical talents are undermined by reckless play.</p>
        <p>The Knicks are almost certain to part ways with the unhappy Francis this summer, either through a trade or contract buyout. Marbury is showing the wear and tear of 11 years as a pro. Crawford is an able playmaker, but seems best suited at shooting guard. Collins could become the Knicks' primary backup at the point -- particularly if he keeps making that jumper.</p>
        <p>''He definitely will make you rethink some things,'' Thomas said. ''I definitely think about things in a different way out front than I did a month ago.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
