<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>California Cuisine Experiments With Mind and Body; Adoring Yourself And Your Appetizer</title>
    <meta content="18grat" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/dining/18grat.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841087"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/San Francisco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Organic Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organic Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">San Francisco (Calif)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDF1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="927" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>California Cuisine Experiments With Mind and Body; Adoring Yourself And Your Appetizer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Adoring Yourself and Your Appetizer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTINE MUHLKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Muhlke, Christine</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I AM Luscious. Say it. Now try it on a stranger.</p>
        <p>Unable to bring myself to say those three little words to the waitress, I jabbed at the menu. A few minutes later, she presented me with a smoothie made with hazelnut milk, figs, dates, vanilla and raw cacao, making eye contact as she said: ''You are luscious!''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At Cafe Gratitude, a raw-food restaurant in San Francisco, every order is a self-affirmation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I AM Luscious. Say it. Now try it on a stranger.</p>
        <p>Unable to bring myself to say those three little words to the waitress, I jabbed at the menu. A few minutes later, she presented me with a smoothie made with hazelnut milk, figs, dates, vanilla and raw cacao, making eye contact as she said: ''You are luscious!''</p>
        <p>And so it goes at Cafe Gratitude, a raw-food restaurant in San Francisco, where every order is a self-affirmation -- I Am Open, I Am Beautiful, I Am Powerful -- mirrored back to you by your server.</p>
        <p>If it sounds like ''The Secret: The Restaurant,'' you might not be far off: the positivity-preaching millionaire owners (''although there is no solid evidence that his wealth is a result of his practice,'' their Web site says) have opened four Bay Area locations in three years, and plan to expand.</p>
        <p>''All of our food is local, sustainable, organic, vegan and raw,'' begin the well-programmed servers, ''except for our rice and quinoa, which are steamed. Quinoa is an ancient.'' But that's the tip of the menu.</p>
        <p>How to wrap one's head around its affirmational glory? The menu's cover reads: ''We invite you to step inside and enjoy being someone who chooses: loving your life, adoring yourself, accepting the world, being generous and grateful everyday, and experiencing being provided for.''</p>
        <p>Wow. So. The appetizers: I Am Bountiful live crustini, ''toasts'' made from seeds and nuts with such toppings as avocado and not-so-local Himalayan salt. I Am Happy live almond-sesame hummus. (''Live'' food has not been cooked above 118 degrees, the temperature that kills enzymes, and incorporates sprouting seeds and nuts.) I Am Insightful spinach-wrapped samosas with cauliflower and macadamia ''potatoes.''</p>
        <p>And on through the long menu: I Am Giving, I Am Festive, I Am Prosperous, I Am Fabulous, Yo Soy Mucho (Mexican bowl).</p>
        <p>The cold-brewed coffee is from a co-op of Muslims, Christians and Jews who ''work together as one to bring us this expression of peace in a cup.''</p>
        <p>After being luscious, I Was Sensational. The flatbread crust of this ''live'' pizza -- served on a plate printed with ''What are you grateful for?'' -- was made from pressed buckwheat and sunflower-seed sourdough. Alone, it had the flavor and consistency of a chew toy. Topped with zippy pesto of basil and hemp seeds; cashew ''ricotta''; ripe cherry tomatoes doused in excellent olive oil; and a crumbling of Brazil-nut ''Parmesan,'' it was wholly satisfying.</p>
        <p>Unlike the fussy (if flavorful) food at the New York raw-food restaurant Pure Food and Wine, this was straightforward and unpretentious, embodying the California-born edict of local, seasonal ingredients, simply prepared. With produce this good, what could be simpler than not cooking it at all?</p>
        <p>Simple pricing, it seems, is also key: Roxanne and Michael Klein were the first to nudge raw food away from the health-store margins with the upscale restaurant Roxanne's in Marin Country in 2001.</p>
        <p>Though popular with purists and dabblers, its nouvelle-live cuisine proved too expensive: the adjoining take-out shop cannibalized the restaurant. Both closed in 2004.</p>
        <p>At Cafe Gratitude, entrees top out at $12.</p>
        <p>The cafe's owners, Matthew Engelhart and his wife, Terces, created the Abounding River game, which helps players discover ''a Spiritual foundation that opens up to a whole new way of looking at money and resources.'' (Mr. Engelhart and his former wife, Jeanne, founded the natural clothing company Flax, whose labels had such affirmations as ''I am perfect spirit radiant life.'' When the then-divorced couple sold it in 2002, gross sales were $28 million.)</p>
        <p>Matthew and Terces Engelhart followed their 2003 board game with a book and workshop series. The next year, they opened the first Cafe Gratitude on San Francisco's Harrison Street as a ''raw food gaming parlor,'' Mr. Engelhart said by phone.</p>
        <p>While people might be reluctant to take a weekend workshop, the couple reasoned, everyone wants to eat: ''So we thought, let's suck 'em in with food and have them play the game!'' (A mural in each restaurant explains the game, the playing cards for which are in the center of every table.)</p>
        <p>The Engelharts had become interested in raw food after reading a book on the subject while visiting their organic farm in Maui. They ate only live food for 30 days; afterward, they felt so good that they made the culinary switch. (Proponents of raw food believe that heating and processing kill enzymes necessary for good health.)</p>
        <p>Ms. Engelhart, a former dental hygienist, flight attendant, Mary Kay Cosmetics executive and business owner who had an eating disorder for 20 years, is in charge of the menu. Her cookbook, ''I Am Grateful,'' written with Orchid, the man responsible for the sweets at the cafe, came out this month.</p>
        <p>She has not formally studied raw food ''cooking''; her husband called her ''a natural food alchemist: she has that sixth sense about what goes together.'' He's not kidding.</p>
        <p>As for the dish naming, Mr. Engelhart said: ''We're always affirming aspects of ourselves: I am shy, I am funny, I am unorganized, I am chubby. We live in language -- we're always languaging something about ourselves. We wanted people to practice saying something that's empowering. It's part of the process to reprogram ourselves, to be who we want to be.''</p>
        <p>Asked what he's grateful for, he said, ''Today, I'm grateful for my stiff body: I did yoga for the first time in a long time.''</p>
        <p>But the real punch line is how good the food is. I can't wait to go back and be, if not luscious, at least sensational. I Am Shocked.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
