<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Silky, Sweet and Tart, a Triple Threat</title>
    <meta content="18appe" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841119"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE GOOD APPETITE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Citrus Fruits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fruit</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E1DE1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1032" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Silky, Sweet and Tart, a Triple Threat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Melissa Clark</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clark, Melissa</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR cooks of a lemon-loving persuasion, a puckery citrus curd is the culinary analogue of a chocolate fanatic's fudgy ganache. A cousin of lemon custard but without the milk or cream, lemon curd is a go-to topping, filling, sauce and eat-off-the-spoon treat. It's a mainstay of the pastry cook's repertory, yet subject to countless variations.</p>
        <p>And so it was one afternoon that in front of me on the counter sat three bowls of curd in glossy pastels: yolk-yellow lemon; pale, coral-tinged blood orange; and a grass-green-speckled lime, showered with zest. My aim was to dollop them into miniature butter-crusted tart shells and arrange them on a platter in a gorgeous springtime mosaic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR cooks of a lemon-loving persuasion, a puckery citrus curd is the culinary analogue of a chocolate fanatic's fudgy ganache. A cousin of lemon custard but without the milk or cream, lemon curd is a go-to topping, filling, sauce and eat-off-the-spoon treat. It's a mainstay of the pastry cook's repertory, yet subject to countless variations.</p>
        <p>And so it was one afternoon that in front of me on the counter sat three bowls of curd in glossy pastels: yolk-yellow lemon; pale, coral-tinged blood orange; and a grass-green-speckled lime, showered with zest. My aim was to dollop them into miniature butter-crusted tart shells and arrange them on a platter in a gorgeous springtime mosaic.</p>
        <p>It was all looking perfectly grand. And then I tasted them. Only the lemon was just right, a restrained balance between acid and sugar. The lime was sour pickle-astringent. The blood orange was cloying and insipid. And my guests were on their way.</p>
        <p>Figuring that things couldn't get any worse and that there was always ice cream in the freezer as a backup, I blithely overturned one bowl of curd into the next and stirred all three together.</p>
        <p>It was a classic eureka moment. The lime and blood orange atoned for each other's sins, and the lemon rounded out the rough edges and brought everything together. It was deeply tart but not enough to make one squint, fresh and buoyant on the palate, and just sweet enough. To my mind, my three-citrus curd tasted better than any of those flavors alone, and it also came out an appealing salmon color.</p>
        <p>The next time I made citrus curd, I mixed together all the juices and zests ahead of time rather than making three separate curds, and that worked well, too. I made a batch, ate most of it directly from the bowl, and then made it again. And again. I was becoming quite curd-addicted, and adept.</p>
        <p>I discovered that the trick to making a perfectly smooth lemon curd, despite the name, is to keep the eggs from curdling. Curdling is desirable in cheesemaking but in a lemon curd (made from sugar, lemon and eggs) it gives you nasty, hard bits if the eggs cook too fast and hot. Patience is the answer. Stir thoroughly (getting into the edges of the pot) and consistently, but not too vigorously, using a wooden spoon. Energetic stirring or whisking creates air bubbles, which can interfere with a silky smooth result. It can also slow down the process.</p>
        <p>And while low heat and a pot with a heavy bottom are essential, using a double boiler is probably overkill, as long as you are vigilant about the stirring.</p>
        <p>One thing I've learned is that even if the curd develops a few tiny lumps, all is not lost. Just quickly strain it through a fine mesh sieve. If, however, the content of your pot starts to look more like scrambled eggs than pudding, dump it and start over.</p>
        <p>As my curd-making skills improved, so did my mania for experimentation. I found recipes for rhubarb and cranberry curds (in Mitchell Davis's authoritative ''Kitchen Sense,'' Clarkson Potter, 2006) and even red currant, kaffir lime, passion fruit and raspberry curds. All were excellent, but I -- as a person who thinks that when life gives you lemons you've hit the jackpot -- found that the citrus was still my favorite.</p>
        <p>Still, there is one elusive curd flavor I'd seen in jars in British specialty shops that I was dying to master: ginger curd. I wasn't able to track down a recipe, but I did find citrus curds flavored with ginger. As good as that sounded, it wasn't what I was looking for. I wanted to create a curd with a sparkly, clean ginger taste unto itself that did not battle citrus for attention.</p>
        <p>My first few attempts were failures. My strategy was to make a potent ginger ''tea'' by infusing grated root into water, and use that in place of citrus juice. But it never quite worked.</p>
        <p>I then tried grating the ginger root directly into the finished egg curd, but the ginger bits skidded abrasively on my tongue. Finally, a friend suggested I stir ginger juice into the curd at the end, which would give it a potent kick without the grit.</p>
        <p>It worked, and lent the curd an intense, spicy ginger flavor that would make even the most diehard lemon fan happily pucker up.</p>
        <p>Three-Citrus Curd  Time: 40 minutes plus at least 4 hours' chilling</p>
        <p>2 blood oranges  1 lemon  1 lime  3 egg yolks  2 whole eggs  1/2 cup sugar  Pinch of salt  4 tablespoons butter, at room temperature, cut into cubes.</p>
        <p>1. Grate zest from one orange, the lemon and the lime. Set aside. Squeeze juice from all citrus into a sieve set over a bowl. Press on solids to extract all juice.  2. In a bowl, whisk together the yolks and whole eggs with sugar and salt. Whisk in strained juice.  3. Transfer mixture to a heavy saucepan and set over very low heat. Add butter. Using a wooden spoon, stir curd constantly, making sure to reach edges around side of pan. Cook, stirring constantly, until mixture has thickened enough to mound when dropped from spoon, 10 to 15 minutes. If mixture starts to curdle, immediately take pot off heat and stir vigorously. If mixture does not thicken, raise heat very slightly and stir vigilantly.  4. Strain curd through a fine sieve into a bowl. Stir in zest. Cover top of curd directly with plastic wrap so a skin will not form. Chill until quite cold and thick, at least 4 hours.  Yield: 1 1/4 cups.</p>
        <p>Ginger Curd Variation: Grate a 4-inch piece of ginger root as finely as possible and, using your fingers, press pulp down into a sieve set over a bowl to obtain juice. You should have 3 tablespoons; yield will vary depending upon how fresh ginger is.</p>
        <p>Cook eggs, sugar, salt and butter into a curd as directed in the recipe above. After straining, stir in as much of the ginger juice as you like. Cover and chill as above. This yields a scant cup.</p>
        <p>THE GOOD APPETITE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
