<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rangers Transform Thrashers Into Clay Pigeons</title>
    <meta content="18rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/sports/hockey/18rangers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841238"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Atlanta Thrashers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Atlanta Thrashers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Nylander, Michael</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Lundqvist, Henrik</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jagr, Jaromir</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02EFDB1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="919" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rangers Transform Thrashers Into Clay Pigeons</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rangers Transform Thrashers Into Clay Pigeons</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinser, Lynn</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Rangers skated onto the ice at Madison Square Garden last night, they were hailed as returning heroes with a 2-0 playoff series lead over Atlanta. The roar from the sellout crowd nearly drowned out the national anthem.</p>
        <p>For a team that had not won a Garden playoff game in almost 10 years, the Rangers felt so at home, scoring 32 seconds into the game -- the first of three goals by Michael Nylander -- and they never let up. Three periods later, the final score was 7-0 and the Thrashers were on the verge of elimination.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a commanding victory behind Michael Nylander’s hat trick, the Rangers can sweep the Thrashers in their first-round series with another win Wednesday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Rangers skated onto the ice at Madison Square Garden last night, they were hailed as returning heroes with a 2-0 playoff series lead over Atlanta. The roar from the sellout crowd nearly drowned out the national anthem.</p>
        <p>For a team that had not won a Garden playoff game in almost 10 years, the Rangers felt so at home, scoring 32 seconds into the game -- the first of three goals by Michael Nylander -- and they never let up. Three periods later, the final score was 7-0 and the Thrashers were on the verge of elimination.</p>
        <p>''We looked at each other on the bench before the game even started,'' Sean Avery said. ''During the anthem they were just rocking. And then Mikey scores that goal and they get going even louder.''</p>
        <p>For a team that scratched its way into the playoffs on the strength of 2-1 games and shootouts, a team that climbed from 11th place to sixth in two desperate months, the Rangers' transformation into a juggernaut -- even for a night -- was stunning. The Rangers, who last won a playoff game at home on May 8, 1997 (3-0 over the Devils), can complete a sweep tonight at the Garden, which would be their first playoff series victory since 1997.</p>
        <p>The Thrashers, the Eastern Conference's No. 3 seed and boasting a handful of the best offensive players in the league, spent the game being turned into a stage props.</p>
        <p>''It's not explainable,'' said Atlanta's Bobby Holik. ''It was about a lack of passion. It had nothing to do with skill or talent. It was about heart and desire.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers had won both games in Atlanta with the kind of grit that had earned them a playoff berth. They tuned out a raucous Atlanta crowd and created just enough breaks for themselves.</p>
        <p>The game was an onslaught, starting with the first shift. Rangers Coach Tom Renney started his top line of Nylander, Jaromir Jagr and Marcel Hossa, hoping they would immediately put their stamp on the game. He could not have predicted how immediately.</p>
        <p>The Rangers collected the puck behind their net and Jagr skated it up ice, stick-handling around Éric Bélanger in the neutral zone as if Bélanger were a traffic cone. He passed across to Nylander, whom not a single Thrasher was guarding, for an open shot that Nylander fired over the goalie Kari Lehtonen.</p>
        <p>A mere 32 seconds into the match, the national anthem roar had barely stopped reverberating when a new one started.</p>
        <p>''Right there we could feel that suddenly the entire bench froze; we were not there,'' Atlanta Coach Bob Hartley said. ''We had plenty of time, but it gave them lots of energy, lots of life and on our side it seemed like it just killed us.''</p>
        <p>The Thrashers had a lot to second-guess in this game, including Hartley's handling of his goalies. He benched Lehtonen after Game 1 and then went back to him, despite an excellent performance from Johan Hedberg in a 2-1 loss in Game 2.</p>
        <p>Lehtonen watched the first shot sail by him and it did not get any better. Hartley left him in because Hedberg will start Game 4.</p>
        <p>Jagr said it did not matter who was in goal.</p>
        <p>''That's a great shot by Mikey Nylander, top shelf,'' Jagr said. ''I don't care who's in the net. It's a goal. It's not easy to start like that.''</p>
        <p>Nylander would score the second goal, on a rebound of a shot by Hossa, after Jagr created a turnover behind the Atlanta net. Marek Malik would score to make it 3-0 in the first. The rookie Ryan Callahan added his first two career playoff goals in the second and Brendan Shanahan added his 54th career playoff goal on a power play in the third. Nylander prompted a shower of hats onto the ice with a power play goal late in the third.</p>
        <p>Henrik Lundqvist's collecting his first career playoff shutout (21 saves) was almost an afterthought because Atlanta had mustered so little in the way of a challenge.</p>
        <p>But the Rangers were careful not to talk about this series in the past tense. They denied that the margin of victory in this game would carry over to the next one. The Thrashers were looking at the back-to-back games as a way to redeem themselves quickly. But the Rangers understand the need to keep Atlanta backpedaling.</p>
        <p>''I think the mentality of this team right now is, we can't let up at all,'' Avery said. ''We have to come in tomorrow night and hammer them even harder than we did tonight. It's just the way we have to go about things.''</p>
        <p>The Thrashers continued to be rattled by Avery. Thrashers' star Ilya Kovalchuk charged into a fight with Avery in the third. Atlanta unraveled to the tune of 79 penalty minutes.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Kovalchuk and Marian Hossa -- who combined for 85 goals in the regular season -- have a grand total of one through three playoff games.</p>
        <p>Asked if Atlanta was finished, Avery just smiled and said, ''We'll see in 24 hours.''</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>Rangers defenseman Fedor Tyutin collected another assist in Game 3, and has five in the series.  Jaromir Jagr assisted on each of the Rangers' first three goals and had four assists over all.  Rangers Coach Tom Renney stuck with the same lineup he used in the first two games, keeping the checking-line forward Ryan Hollweg in the press box in favor of Colton Orr.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
