<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Skakel Seeks New Trial in '75 Moxley Killing</title>
    <meta content="18skakel" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/nyregion/18skakel.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841148"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Greenwich (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Skakel, Michael C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Robert F Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hausbrouck, Adolph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moxley, Martha (1960-75)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowan, Alison Leigh</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Skakel, Michael</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Moxley, Martha</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE2DD1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="708" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Skakel Seeks New Trial in '75 Moxley Killing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Skakel Seeks New Trial in ’75 Moxley Killing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON LEIGH COWAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowan, Alison Leigh</byline>
      <dateline>STAMFORD, Conn., April 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lawyers for Michael C Skakel, who is serving sentence for 1975 killing of Martha Moxley, his 15-year-old neighbor in Greenwich, Conn, seek new trial, arguing that they have new evidence pointing to possible involvement of some youngsters visiting from New York City at time; cite tapes recorded by Robert F Kennedy Jr, Skakel's first cousin, of phone conversations in which one of the out-of-towners, Adolph Hausbrouck, told friend on night of homicide that he wanted to 'go caveman' on local girl; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Five years after he was convicted of killing his 15-year-old neighbor, Martha Moxley, as a teenager in Greenwich in 1975, a teary Michael C. Skakel returned to court on Tuesday seeking a new trial. His lawyers argued that they had found new evidence pointing to the possible involvement of some youngsters who were visiting from New York City.</p>
        <p>The lawyers, citing tapes recorded by Robert F. Kennedy Jr., Mr. Skakel's first cousin, said one of the out-of-towners, Adolph Hausbrouck, who now lives in Bridgeport, told a friend the night of the homicide that he wanted to ''go caveman'' on a local girl and gloated later that he had. Mr. Hausbrouck has denied that he was involved.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Five years after he was convicted of killing his neighbor, Martha Moxley, as a teenager in Greenwich, Conn., in 1975, Michael C. Skakel is seeking a new trial.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Five years after he was convicted of killing his 15-year-old neighbor, Martha Moxley, as a teenager in Greenwich in 1975, a teary Michael C. Skakel returned to court on Tuesday seeking a new trial. His lawyers argued that they had found new evidence pointing to the possible involvement of some youngsters who were visiting from New York City.</p>
        <p>The lawyers, citing tapes recorded by Robert F. Kennedy Jr., Mr. Skakel's first cousin, said one of the out-of-towners, Adolph Hausbrouck, who now lives in Bridgeport, told a friend the night of the homicide that he wanted to ''go caveman'' on a local girl and gloated later that he had. Mr. Hausbrouck has denied that he was involved.</p>
        <p>Mr. Skakel, 46, who is serving a sentence of 20 years to life, lost an earlier appeal when the Connecticut Supreme Court rejected his contentions that the statute of limitations had expired at the time of his arrest in 2000 and that he should not have been tried as an adult, since he was 15 when Ms. Moxley died.</p>
        <p>Now, the burden of proof is on Mr. Skakel's lawyers to prove that the evidence they want to present was unavailable at the time of trial. The trial prosecutors said they planned to argue that some information about the out-of-town visitors was shared before the trial with Mickey Sherman, Mr. Skakel's trial lawyer, who is likely to be called as a witness during the hearing.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Skakel's latest bid for freedom does not work, his current lawyers, Hope C. Seeley and Hubert J. Santos, are expected to argue that he lacked effective counsel at his trial.</p>
        <p>Most of Tuesday's testimony, opening a civil hearing expected to last two weeks in Stamford Superior Court, focused on Mr. Kennedy, who is an active environmentalist. Mr. Kennedy testified that he and his cousin grew close when they both ''became sober'' in the early 1980s, then later had a falling out. ''Although my relationship with him was a troubled one, I knew an innocent man was in prison,'' Mr. Kennedy said.</p>
        <p>Frustrated that he was unable to persuade reporters or prosecutors to pursue leads that might have helped his cousin, Mr. Kennedy said, he ultimately investigated on his own, resulting in a 19-page article for The Atlantic magazine in early 2003.</p>
        <p>That article led a former classmate of Mr. Skakel's to notify Mr. Kennedy that he ought to contact another former classmate who had information, Gitano Bryant, who was often known as Tony. Mr. Kennedy recorded several subsequent phone conversations, some of which were played for the court Tuesday.</p>
        <p>In one conversation, Mr. Bryant confides that he had some self-doubt for not coming forward earlier. ''Do I go to the family and say, 'You know what, I am sorry for the loss of your daughter, but you know, they got the wrong guy?' '' he asks Mr. Kennedy. He also complains that investigators never questioned Mr. Hausbrouck.</p>
        <p>Mr. Santos, Mr. Skakel's lawyer, argued, ''What Tony Bryant told Mr. Kennedy shattered what was then a closed case.''</p>
        <p>In his cross-examination, Jonathan Benedict, who was the lead prosecutor at the 2002 trial, sought to portray Mr. Bryant as an unreliable witness, citing a run-in he has had with the law and tax problems that cost him his business.</p>
        <p>Mr. Benedict also pressed Mr. Kennedy to name people who could corroborate that the out-of-towners were in the exclusive Belle Haven neighborhood of Greenwich on the night of the homicide.</p>
        <p>''Anyone else?'' he repeatedly asked, each time Mr. Kennedy, himself a former prosecutor, sought to reply.</p>
        <p>In another tape played in court, Mr. Hausbrouck tells Mr. Kennedy that he was not in Greenwich that night.</p>
        <p>The scene in many ways was a vivid reminder of the trial. Ms. Moxley's mother, Dorthy, sat attentively in the first row behind the people who had prosecuted the case.</p>
        <p>Before the hearing began, Mr. Skakel tapped his heart in a kind of thank-you gesture to Kris Steele, one of the investigators who helped develop some of the new evidence.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Santos, who arrived without the typical cart full of document boxes, when asked how he could win without much to show, said confidently, ''Anyone can do it with bags.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
