<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two New Markets, With Food to Stay</title>
    <meta content="18unde" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/dining/reviews/18unde.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841094"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="$25 AND UNDER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/$25 and Under</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Fairway Market</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Whole Foods Market Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E6DE1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="738" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two New Markets, With Food to Stay</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Two New Markets, With Food to Stay</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Meehan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Meehan, Peter</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the last year, two mega-grocery stores have opened in communities that were previously making do without one: Fairway Market in Red Hook, Brooklyn, and Whole Foods Market at the nexus of a few under-grocered downtown neighborhoods: the East Village, the Lower East Side and NoLIta.</p>
        <p>Both offer dining options to entice shoppers and the stove-phobic. I set off to find out whether these places are just for puzzling over what to do with the shiso cress and pancetta in your cart, or if they are destinations in themselves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A closer look at the dining offerings in new two mega-grocery stores, Fairway Market in Red Hook, Brooklyn, and Whole Foods Market in downtown Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the last year, two mega-grocery stores have opened in communities that were previously making do without one: Fairway Market in Red Hook, Brooklyn, and Whole Foods Market at the nexus of a few under-grocered downtown neighborhoods: the East Village, the Lower East Side and NoLIta.</p>
        <p>Both offer dining options to entice shoppers and the stove-phobic. I set off to find out whether these places are just for puzzling over what to do with the shiso cress and pancetta in your cart, or if they are destinations in themselves.</p>
        <p>The cafe at Fairway in Red Hook has one of the finest outdoor eating spaces in the city, a concrete pier with commanding views of the Statue of Liberty and the choppy waters of New York Harbor.</p>
        <p>As you wind your way through the labyrinthine space of Fairway's newest outpost on the way to its cafe, you'll pass the lobster tanks where, on a recent Sunday, I spied two specimens the size of small pumas.</p>
        <p>I don't know if monster lobsters are its secret, but Fairway's cafe does serve what must be the cheapest lobster roll in the city. It's not an exemplar of its kind -- there are unorthodox additions like red bell pepper and red onion -- but the (side-sliced) hot dog roll it is tucked into is dutifully crisped on the griddle. With Terra chips, coleslaw and maybe a little sun, you could do worse for $7.99.</p>
        <p>But given the high-quality cafe Fairway has at its Upper West Side store (where brunches are packed and burgers are commendable), I had higher hopes for Red Hook. The cafe's offerings are mostly standard sandwich shop fare -- hot heroes, egg sandwiches in the morning, Reubens -- competent but without flair. Pizzas were pointless, underloved, wan. With its rock-bottom prices and casual counter service, this Fairway cafe is there to feed shoppers and locals, not to lure in diners from afar.</p>
        <p>That's clearly not the case at Whole Foods' new greenwashed 70,000-square-foot theme park on the Bowery. Overhead signs read like word association lists: the word ''Wonka'' floats above the chocolate counter. If I hadn't spotted the photographer Terry Richardson at the gelato counter near the ''Made in NY'' sign, I'd have been stumped by the inclusion of ''Local Heroes'' on it.</p>
        <p>And though prepared foods have long been part of Whole Foods' draw, it has upped the ante downtown, with two stand-alone restaurants, seemingly countless salad and coffee bars, and a French fry operation called Pommes Frites.</p>
        <p>Its Rustica Minardi Osteria offers a menu that might be termed safe. It serves grilled salmon, pasta primavera and other similarly sleepy options to diners who must not know that they're a conventionally grown tomato's throw away from dozens of well-regarded Italian spots.</p>
        <p>Sushiya, on the other hand, may be downtown's first conveyor-belt sushi restaurant. The last time I had the pleasure of eating off a conveyer belt I was a boy at a carousel-themed all-you-can-eat place in Pennsylvania. At Sushiya, plates are color-coded by price. After your meal, one of the cheery staffers tallies the stack of plates you've accumulated.</p>
        <p>I wasn't looking for much: subsistence sushi, that packaged stuff that's a healthier lunch option at delis or down-market sushi places, doesn't need to slay to sate. But Whole Foods' sushi was roughly the same quality I'd expect to find at that buffet in Amish country -- gummy rice, flavorless fish, almost all cooked.</p>
        <p>Blueberries and pineapple played vital roles in many of the unappealing plates that cruised by. The grilled asparagus atop one nugget of rice managed to be both mushy and woody. Even dumplings, which you must specially request from a ''team member,'' managed to disappoint.</p>
        <p>For all the money Whole Foods has sunk into the place, the French fry counter and the salad bars still may be its best options. That said, sometimes nothing beats a home-cooked meal.</p>
        <p>FAIRWAY MARKET CAFE  480-500 Van Brunt Street (Reed Street), Red Hook, Brooklyn; (718) 694-6868.</p>
        <p>BEST DISHES -- Lobster roll.  PRICE RANGE -- $4.49 to $7.99.  CREDIT CARD -- All major cards.  HOURS -- 8 a.m. to 8 p.m. daily.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Accessible.</p>
        <p>WHOLE FOODS MARKET  95 East Houston Street (Bowery), Lower East Side; (212) 420-1320.</p>
        <p>BEST DISHES -- French fries.  PRICE RANGE -- $2.99 to $5.99.  CREDIT CARD -- All major cards.  HOURS -- 11 a.m. to 10 p.m. daily.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Accessible.</p>
        <p>$25 AND UNDER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
