<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>RAMPAGE GUNMAN WAS STUDENT; WARNING LAG TIED TO BAD LEAD</title>
    <meta content="18virginia" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/us/18virginia.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841241"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MASSACRE IN VIRGINIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Virginia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Blacksburg (Va)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cho, Seung-Hui</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hilscher, Emily Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clark, Ryan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thornhill, Karl D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flaherty, W Steven (Col)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steger, Charles</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flinchum, Wendell</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roy, Lucinda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, Laura</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broder, John M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dewan, Shaila</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cho Seung-Hui</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00EEDB1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1594" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>RAMPAGE GUNMAN WAS STUDENT; WARNING LAG TIED TO BAD LEAD</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Two-Hour Delay Is Linked to Bad Lead</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHAILA DEWAN and JOHN M. BRODER; Reporting was contributed by Sarah Abruzzese, Terry Aguayo, Edmund L. Andrews, Karen W. Arenson, Neela Banerjee, Cate Doty, Kareem Fahim, Alan Finder, Dan Frosch, Brenda Goodman, Libby Sander, John Schwartz, Alicia Shepard, Archie Tse, Matthew L. Wald and Katie Zezima.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broder, John M; Dewan, Shaila</byline>
      <dateline>BLACKSBURG, Va., April 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cho Seung-Hui, 23-year-old student, is identified as killer of 32 people in shooting rampage at Virginia Tech in Blacksburg; investigators say South Korean immigrant left rambling, bitter list of complaints about moral laxity and double-dealing among privileged students; fateful two-hour delay in warning campus of gunman apparently stems from fruitless lead in first shooting episode, in which Emily Jane Hilscher and Ryan Clark were killed in dormitory; police spent time looking for and questioning Hilscher's friend Karl D Thornhill, who roommate said had guns at home; he is still considered important witness; state police chief Col W Steven Flaherty says there was no reason to think there was anyone else involved before second outburst at Norris Hall; officials continue to defend actions of college president Charles Steger and campus police chief Wendell Flinchum; Cho used two handguns, purchased legally in recent weeks, to shoot dozens of rounds; one gun was also used at dormitory; preparations at Norris Hall, which contains engineering and other classrooms, included chaining doors; bodies were found in four classrooms and stairwell; English professor Lucinda Roy says Cho's writings, laced with anger, profanity and violence, so concerned faculty that in 2005 she sent examples to campus police, counselors and others, all of whom said there was little they could do; Roy offered to go with Cho to counseling but he refused; says students also reported Cho taking inappropriate pictures of women under desks; victims include at least four teachers, with 14 wounded victims still hospitalized; thousands of students and faculty gather for convocation attended by Pres and Mrs Bush; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The police identified Cho Seung-Hui, a 23-year-old student, as the killer of 32 people in the shooting rampage at the Virginia Polytechnic Institute, releasing new information on Tuesday about the troubled mind of a young man few people on campus knew.</p>
        <p>Federal investigators said Mr. Cho -- a South Korean immigrant who Americanized his name and preferred to be known as Seung Cho -- left behind a note that they described as a lengthy, rambling and bitter list of complaints focusing on moral laxity and double-dealing he found among what he viewed as wealthier and more privileged students on campus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Virginia Tech officials were pursuing what appears to have been a fruitless lead after the first shooting when the second began.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The police identified Cho Seung-Hui, a 23-year-old student, as the killer of 32 people in the shooting rampage at the Virginia Polytechnic Institute, releasing new information on Tuesday about the troubled mind of a young man few people on campus knew.</p>
        <p>Federal investigators said Mr. Cho -- a South Korean immigrant who Americanized his name and preferred to be known as Seung Cho -- left behind a note that they described as a lengthy, rambling and bitter list of complaints focusing on moral laxity and double-dealing he found among what he viewed as wealthier and more privileged students on campus.</p>
        <p>And new information emerged that may help explain a fateful two-hour delay by university officials in warning the campus of a gunman at large. According to search warrants and statements from the police, campus investigators had been busy pursuing what appears to have been a fruitless lead in the first of two shooting episodes Monday.</p>
        <p>After two people, Emily Jane Hilscher, a freshman, and Ryan Clark, the resident adviser whose room was nearby in the dormitory, were shot dead, the campus police began searching for Karl D. Thornhill, who was described in Internet memorials as Ms. Hilscher's boyfriend.</p>
        <p>According to a search warrant filed by the police, Ms. Hilscher's roommate had told the police that Mr. Thornhill, a student at nearby Radford University, had guns at his town house. The roommate told the police that she had recently been at a shooting range with Mr. Thornhill, the affidavit said, leading the police to believe he may have been the gunman.</p>
        <p>But as they were questioning Mr. Thornhill, reports of widespread shooting at Norris Hall came in, making it clear that they had not contained the threat on campus. Mr. Thornhill was not arrested, although he continues to be an important witness in the case, the police said.</p>
        <p>At the time of the dormitory shootings, Col. W. Steven Flaherty, the superintendent of the Virginia State Police, said, ''There was certainly no evidence or no reason to think that there was anyone else at that particular point in time.''</p>
        <p>State officials continued to defend the actions of the campus authorities. John W. Marshall, the Virginia secretary of public safety, said Charles W. Steger, the president of Virginia Tech, and Chief Wendell Flinchum of the campus police ''made the right decisions based on the best information that they had available at the time.''</p>
        <p>At an afternoon news briefing, Gov. Timothy M. Kaine said Dr. Steger had asked him to appoint a committee to examine the university's response and try to answer some of the remaining questions about the gunman's actions.</p>
        <p>After the shootings, the state police executed another search warrant, this time for Mr. Cho's dormitory room. The warrant said a bomb threat against the engineering school buildings was found near Mr. Cho's body. The warrant mentioned two other bomb threat notes against the campus received over the past three weeks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cho had used two handguns, a 9-millimeter and a .22-caliber, to shoot dozens of rounds, leaving even those who survived with multiple bullet wounds, officials said. The guns were bought legally in March and April. Colonel Flaherty said that although one of those guns had been used in the dormitory shooting, investigators were not ready to conclude that the same gunman was responsible for both episodes. But he said there was no evidence of another gunman or an accomplice.</p>
        <p>Among the central unknowns is what prompted the gunman to move to Norris Hall, which contains engineering and other classrooms, where all but the first two killings took place. The authorities said Mr. Cho's preparations, including chaining the doors, suggested planning and premeditation, rather than a spontaneous event.</p>
        <p>Bodies were found in four classrooms and the stairwell of the building, Colonel Flaherty said.</p>
        <p>''You all have reported that this is the most horrific incident that's occurred on a college campus in our country, and the scene certainly bore that out,'' he said. ''Personal effects were strewn about the entire second floor at Norris Hall. So it made it much more difficult for us to identify students and faculty members that were victims.''</p>
        <p>Officers also found several knives on Mr. Cho's body. They first identified him by a driver's license found in a backpack near the scene of the shootings, although it was not clear at first whether the backpack belonged to the gunman. But the name was checked against a visa application, and when a fingerprint on one of the weapons matched a print on the visa application, the authorities made a positive identification. The print matched another print left in the first shooting location.</p>
        <p>Prescription medications said to be related to treatment of psychological problems were found among Mr. Cho's effects, but officials did not specify what drugs they were.</p>
        <p>In addition, investigators were reviewing recent bomb threats at the university in an effort to determine whether the gunman might have been involved in them, as an effort to test the university's emergency response procedures.</p>
        <p>Lucinda Roy, an English professor, said Mr. Cho's writing, laced with anger, profanity and violence, concerned several faculty members. In 2005, she sent examples to the campus police, the campus counseling service and other officials. All were worried, but little could be done, she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Roy said she would offer to go with Mr. Cho to counseling, just to talk. ''But he wouldn't say yes, and unfortunately I couldn't force him to do it,'' she said. Students were also alarmed that Mr. Cho was taking inappropriate pictures of women under desks, she said.</p>
        <p>In all, 33 people died Monday, including Mr. Cho and at least four faculty members. The victims' names were not officially released, but most appeared to be in their late teens or early 20s. They included Liviu Librescu, a Holocaust survivor, and Reema Samaha, a freshman and a devoted dancer. Ms. Hilscher wanted to be a veterinarian; Mr. Clark was a member of the marching band. ''This is a grief that does not know an international boundary,'' Governor Kaine said.</p>
        <p>By Tuesday afternoon there were still 14 injured victims at four hospitals, out of 28 initially transported from the scene, two of whom died. The 14 included two at a Level 1 trauma center in Roanoke, one in critical condition and the other in serious condition.</p>
        <p>One of the luckier ones was Kevin Sterne, a senior who will graduate in a few weeks. He was hit twice in the right thigh, piercing an artery.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sterne grabbed an electrical cord and fashioned a tourniquet until help arrived. ''I think there's a good chance he would have died,'' said Dr. David B. Stoeckle of Montgomery Regional Hospital in Blacksburg.</p>
        <p>Classes at Virginia Tech were canceled for the rest of the week, and Dr. Steger announced that Norris Hall would remain closed for the rest of the semester.</p>
        <p>Thousands of students and faculty and staff members gathered Tuesday afternoon at Cassell Coliseum, the university's basketball arena, for a solemn convocation. President Bush and Laura Bush attended the gathering and then spent much of the afternoon consoling members of the university family.</p>
        <p>''This is a day of mourning for Virginia Tech, and it is a day of sadness for our entire nation,'' Mr. Bush said in his remarks.</p>
        <p>The president said that Monday began like any other school day, but then took a dark turn.</p>
        <p>''By the end of the morning,'' he said, ''it was the worst day of violence on a college campus in American history -- and for many of you here today, it was the worst day of your lives.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush's consoling words, and those of various campus religious leaders and the poet Nikki Giovanni, could not silence the questions of at least some of the stricken families.</p>
        <p>''I guess we're a little curious as to why it took so long'' to lock down the campus after the first two fatal shootings, said Kim Tate, the mother of a sophomore. Ms. Tate contrasted Monday's response to the rapid closing of the entire campus last summer after an incident involving an escaped convict in the area.</p>
        <p>Asian-American students at Virginia Tech reacted to news about the gunman's identity with shock and a measure of anxiety about a possible backlash against them.</p>
        <p>''My parents are actually worried about retaliation against Asians,'' said Lyu Boaz, a third-year accounting student who was born in South Korea and became an American citizen a year ago. ''After 9/11, a lot of Arabs were attacked for that reason.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Boaz, a resident adviser at Pritchard Hall, said many Korean-American students had left campus immediately. Parents of other Korean-American students were preparing to pick up their children on Tuesday afternoon and take them home.</p>
        <p>Dr. Steger, the university president, has been at the center of this week's trauma, which he described as a horrible nightmare from which he hoped to awake. Friends said that despite his stoic demeanor, the campus deaths had exacted a heavy toll on a man who has spent his entire adulthood at Virginia Tech, as a student, professor, dean and administrator.</p>
        <p>''I think he's grieving beyond belief,'' said Alan Merten, the president of George Mason University in Fairfax, Va., who described himself as a colleague and old friend. ''I think he's suffering beyond belief.''</p>
        <p>MASSACRE IN VIRGINIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
