<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Letter From California: On the Court and on the Bounce</title>
    <meta content="18weds4" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/opinion/18weds4.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841161"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Editorial Observer"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klinkenborg, Verlyn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE7DC1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Letter From California: On the Court and on the Bounce</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Letter From California: On the Court and on the Bounce</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VERLYN KLINKENBORG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klinkenborg, Verlyn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Verlyn Klinkenborg Editorial Observer on learning to play tennis at age 54</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In my left hand I am holding the throat of Maria Sharapova's tennis racket -- a confection of titanium and graphite strung with some durable synthetic fiber. My right hand closes loosely on the grip. This is still a surprise to me: having a racket in my hands, standing on a tennis court, waiting for the ball.</p>
        <p>I have been taking lessons for the past couple of months because tennis is so Californian, because the world will soon be nothing but asphalt, and because I have not spent enough of my life using the hand-eye reflexes that are such a pleasure to use. The physical aspects of the game are hard enough -- the footwork, the strokes. But the hardest part -- here it comes, just crossing the net, a phosphorescent green moon -- is watching the ball.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>I have been taking lessons for the past couple of months because tennis is so Californian, because the world will soon be nothing but asphalt, and because I have not spent enough of my life using the hand-eye reflexes that are such a pleasure to use.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In my left hand I am holding the throat of Maria Sharapova's tennis racket -- a confection of titanium and graphite strung with some durable synthetic fiber. My right hand closes loosely on the grip. This is still a surprise to me: having a racket in my hands, standing on a tennis court, waiting for the ball.</p>
        <p>I have been taking lessons for the past couple of months because tennis is so Californian, because the world will soon be nothing but asphalt, and because I have not spent enough of my life using the hand-eye reflexes that are such a pleasure to use. The physical aspects of the game are hard enough -- the footwork, the strokes. But the hardest part -- here it comes, just crossing the net, a phosphorescent green moon -- is watching the ball.</p>
        <p>In the next court is a young player, a girl who is perhaps 9 years old. Her coach is hitting balls to her. My coach is hitting balls to me. The girl next door has been playing tennis for a couple of years, it looks like, and her potential is a matter of physical gifts and good coaching, and how hard she wants to work. I have begun at 54 and am now 10 weeks into it.</p>
        <p>What could I do at 9 as well as this girl hits a tennis ball? I could read, hours a day. I try to remember this when the world seems to be full of 9-year-olds mastering everything. I wonder whether she has trouble watching the ball.</p>
        <p>Not that the ball is hard to see. It is a cautionary chartreuse. It stands out sharply against the court, the windscreen, the grassy slope, the shade of the pines and eucalyptus, the mountains that rise in the distance. The ball is soundless coming at me, though I can hear the hollow pop of balls being struck in the courts nearby. This time I am going to watch it all the way. But I try to remember to shift my weight and so, having a general sense of where the ball is, I stop watching the ball.</p>
        <p>I replay in my mind the sight of Rafael Nadal practicing on a side court at Indian Wells last month and how the ball sizzled in the air. I watched another pro, Andy Murray, bouncing the ball on the edge of his racket in an idle moment. I try to imagine what it is like to have spent most of one's life in communion with a tennis ball. I hope someday to watch the ball the way these players do. I don't mean see or understand or know the ball. I mean keep my head pointed at it, eyes focused on it, watching the ball.</p>
        <p>The ball has always eluded me. Partly it is a matter of doubting what happens if you keep your face pointed at an incoming object -- a grounder that may take a bad hop and bruise the very eye that is watching it. But partly it is a matter of thinking, falsely, that athletic grace lies somehow in the realm of the peripheral.</p>
        <p>Witnessing -- how the name comes back! -- Graig Nettles in flight at third base or Tiger Woods with a long iron, you can see only the fluid lines of motion described by arms and body and legs. What you can never see is how closely they watch the ball, the distinction they enforce between the ball and the everything else that is not the ball. Until now, I never understood that all the grace there is flows from watching the ball.</p>
        <p>When I do -- so my coach says -- my body stays down and balanced, coiled. When I do, I strike the ball cleanly, and it flies true. It reminds me of the story John McPhee tells about Arthur Ashe, about how he was taught to hit tennis balls with a broom handle as a way to narrow his gaze. This, of course, was somewhere around age 9. Better if I play with Sharapova's midsize racket and just keep trying to watch the ball.</p>
        <p>I have every incentive to keep my eyes on the ball. This entire practice session, I tell myself, I am going to think only about watching the ball, which, I soon realize, is different from watching the ball.</p>
        <p>But I am watching the ball now and here it comes and it is not a metaphor and I am actually watching it, all of my awareness on the ball, and none left over to be aware of watching it, and when I hit the ball it has some zip, and it dives into a corner of the court just in, and it is a fine thing no one is there to hit it back.</p>
        <p>Editorial Observer</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
