<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some Had Made Their Marks, and Many Others Were Just Beginning</title>
    <meta content="18portraits" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/us/18portraits.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070421T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841236"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MASSACRE IN VIRGINIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DB1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1999" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some Had Made Their Marks, and Many Others Were Just Beginning</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Some Had Made Their Marks, and Many Others Were Just Beginning</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Remembering some of the students and faculty members killed in the Virginia Tech shootings, in these biographical sketches.</p>
        <p>Ross A. Alameddine, 20</p>
        <p>Originally from Saugus, Mass., he had just decided to major in English. His friends, who described him as a music fanatic -- especially for the jazz trio Medeski Martin and Wood -- as well as a video game enthusiast, credit his witty jokes with buoying their own spirits. They created a memorial for him on Facebook.com. ''You're such an amazing kid, Ross,'' wrote Zach Allen, who like Mr. Alameddine had attended Austin Preparatory School in Reading, Mass. ''You always made me smile.'' Friends said he was proud of his teal Pontiac Grand Am, which he won in a raffle -- the car he ''got for a dollar.''</p>
        <p>Christopher J. Bishop, 35</p>
        <p>A German instructor who was known as Jamie, he received his bachelor's and master's degrees in German linguistics from the University of Georgia, in Athens, and then attended Christian-Albrechts University in Kiel, Germany, on a Fulbright scholarship. During four years in Germany, he wrote in a journal on his Web site, memory39.com, he ''spent most of his time learning the language, teaching English, drinking large quantities of wheat beer, and wooing a certain fr채ulein.'' The fr채ulein, Stefanie Hofer, became his wife. She teaches in Virginia Tech's German department, too, but was not injured. His father, Michael Bishop, a science fiction writer, and his mother, Jeri, live in Pine Mountain, Ga.</p>
        <p>Brian Bluhm, 25</p>
        <p>With an undergraduate degree in civil engineering from Virginia Tech, he was working toward a master's degree in water resources. Mr. Bluhm was a shy, quiet person who did not like the spotlight, said his friend Hannah Barnhill. ''But he loved his friends,'' she said. ''He would light up whenever he saw someone he knew, and he had a memorable laugh and a huge heart.'' She said he ''adored'' Virginia Tech, adopting Blacksburg as his unofficial hometown. Born in Iowa, he lived in Detroit during his childhood, where he became an avid Detroit Tigers fan. His family later moved to Louisville, Ky., where he graduated from high school. He had recently set his future in stone: Mr. Bluhm accepted a job in Baltimore, found an apartment there, and was ready to begin his new life in July, his best friend, Michael Marshall, 25, said. ''He was a real lovable, genuine, peaceful person,'' Mr. Marshall said.</p>
        <p>Ryan Clark, 22</p>
        <p>A senior from Martinez, Ga., he was known as Stack and was smart, kind and well liked by those he met working as a resident adviser at West Ambler Johnston Hall, where the first shootings occurred. While studying for degrees in English and biology, and planning to work toward a doctorate at Northwestern University, he also joined Virginia Tech's marching band, the Marching Virginians. Cady J. Hendershot, 20, his lab partner in molecular biology, said Mr. Clark was ''instantly friends with almost anyone he meets, he was just magnetic. He was just so much fun. We could pretty much ruin an entire experiment and still laugh it off and somehow manage to do our lab reports.'' He was close to his family, friends say, but especially to his twin brother, Bryan.</p>
        <p>Austin Cloyd, 19</p>
        <p>A freshman and international studies major and university lifeguard, she grew up in Champaign, Ill., where her father, C. Bryan Cloyd, taught accounting at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign. Ms. Cloyd excelled in volleyball and basketball and was active in the First United Methodist Church in Champaign, sometimes going on missions to Appalachia to help rehabilitate homes, said Terry Harter, senior pastor. ''She was outgoing, friendly, a warm kid with a good sense of humor, very caring,'' Mr. Harter said. ''It's just horrible.'' Ms. Cloyd's mother served as an administrative assistant and director of youth ministries at First United, Mr. Harter said, until the family moved to Blacksburg in 2005 when Mr. Cloyd took a position as professor of accounting and information systems at Virginia Tech.</p>
        <p>Jocelyne Couture-Nowak</p>
        <p>A French instructor from the Montreal area, she moved eight years ago to Virginia Tech, where her husband, Jerzy Nowak, teaches horticulture. She had worked passionately to spread the French language, and was described as vibrant, enthusiastic and dynamic by the vice president of administration, Bernie MacDonald, at a school where she taught French, Nova Scotia Agricultural College. Ms. Couture-Nowak is survived by her husband and two daughters.</p>
        <p>Kevin Granata, 45</p>
        <p>A professor of engineering science and mechanics, he was an accomplished biomechanics researcher, studying the effects of lower back pain and how to prevent it. He was also an adjunct faculty member of orthopedic surgery at the University of Virginia. He was married to Linda Granata, had three children and coached lacrosse and was active in Scouting.</p>
        <p>Matthew Gwaltney</p>
        <p>A graduate student from Chester, Va., he was in his second year of a program in civil and environmental engineering and enjoyed working on river mechanics and river restoration but left time to play basketball and softball in the summer. He graduated from Virginia Tech in 2005. His master's research focused on stormwater management, and he was a teaching assistant, along with Brian Bluhm.</p>
        <p>Caitlin M. Hammaren, 19</p>
        <p>Born in Westtown, N.Y., she was a sophomore majoring in international studies and French. She was a recognized student leader and belonged to the Kappa Kappa Gamma sorority.</p>
        <p>Jeremy Herbstritt, 27</p>
        <p>A graduate student from Western Pennsylvania, he had undergraduate degrees in biochemistry and molecular biology from Penn State. He was doing graduate work in civil engineering and hoped to begin a career in environmental work. He was known as the kind of student who went out of his way to make others feel at ease. He was an avid long-distance runner whose parents had gone to Boston on Monday to watch his sister run in the Boston Marathon as part of a charity group, Centre Volunteers in Medicine.</p>
        <p>Emily J. Hilscher, 19</p>
        <p>A freshman majoring in animal and poultry sciences and equine sciences, she was a straight-A student and worked at a veterinary clinic last summer and hoped to become a veterinarian. She grew up in a small, tightly knit rural community of about 7,000 people in Rappahannock County, Va. She was an accomplished horsewoman and a member of the Virginia Tech equestrian club.</p>
        <p>Matthew La Porte, 20</p>
        <p>A sophomore from Dumont, N.J., he had traded life in his working-class neighborhood for the order of military school, and then for college on an ROTC scholarship in Virginia. Dane Rogich, 20, one of Mr. La Porte's oldest friends, said the two had known each other since they were 5 and had both chosen military school in Pennsylvania. There, Mr. La Porte tended toward music, as a cellist and a drum major. ''From here, to military school, to college -- it was amazing,'' Mr. Rogich said. ''And then he was gone.''</p>
        <p>Henry Lee, 20</p>
        <p>A freshman majoring in computer engineering, he was in elementary school and unable to speak English when his family emigrated from China. When he became an American citizen in 1999, he changed his name from Henh Ly. That same year he graduated from William Fleming High School in Roanoke, Va., and was salutatorian of his class with a 4.47 grade point average. He worked part time at Sears in high school and was honored for his scholastic achievements by the local Burger King, which gave hisclass vouchers for free Whoppers.</p>
        <p>Liviu Librescu, 75</p>
        <p>A senior researcher and lecturer in engineering, he was a Holocaust survivor originally from Romania. He and his wife, Marlena, had immigrated to Israel in 1978, before moving to the United States in 1984. According to news reports, Mr. Librescu blocked the doorway to his classroom from the gunman so students could flee, before he himself was killed.</p>
        <p>G.V. Loganathan, 52</p>
        <p>A professor of civil and environmental engineering, he was honored for his work in hydraulic engineering and had received many awards from Virginia Tech. He was due to receive in a few weeks the prestigious Wine Award for teaching excellence, given to only three professors each year. Mr. Loganathan was known for helping students and colleagues with complex technical problems and was instrumental in the development of computer tools that predict when pipes will fail because of corrosion. He is survived by his wife and two daughters.</p>
        <p>Lauren A. McCain, 20</p>
        <p>An international studies major from Hampton, Va., she described herself on her MySpace page as deeply religious and a fan of science fiction movies and every kind of music except country. She looked on her brother, Joel, as her hero.</p>
        <p>Juan R. Ortiz, 26</p>
        <p>A graduate student in civil engineering, he was originally from Bayamon, P.R. He married less than a year ago and came to the United States with his new wife to study at Virginia Tech. He was active in the Latin American and Iberic Graduate Student Association.</p>
        <p>Daniel Perez Cueva, 21</p>
        <p>Born in Peru, he was studying international relations and was active in a Peruvian student society on campus.</p>
        <p>Erin Peterson, 18</p>
        <p>A freshman from Centreville, Va., she was studying international relations at Virginia Tech. She graduated from Westfield High School, the same high school as the gunman, where she was a star basketball player.</p>
        <p>Michael S. Pohle Jr.</p>
        <p>A graduate of Hunterdon Central High School in Raritan Township, N.J., he was majoring in biological sciences at Virginia Tech and was a member of the lacrosse team. He tended bar at Nerve Restaurant and Bar in Blacksburg.</p>
        <p>Julia Pryde, 23</p>
        <p>A graduate student in biological systems engineering from Middletown, N.J., she wrote a proposal to have the school cafeteria stop throwing waste in a landfill and start recycling it as compost. She was studying watershed management in mountainous regions to help improve water quality. She was killed in an advanced hydrology class, along with a professor she much admired, G. V. Loganathan.</p>
        <p>Mary K. Read, 19</p>
        <p>A freshman majoring in interdisciplinary studies, she had wanted to become an elementary schoolteacher. She played the clarinet and was a member of her high school marching band in Annandale, Va., winning the band's ''Best Smile'' award in her senior year. She loved baking, and her friends treasured her ''heavenly cookies.''</p>
        <p>Reema Samaha, 18</p>
        <p>A freshman from Centreville, Va., she graduated from the same high school as the gunman. In high school, she was on the dance team and took part in theater productions and talent shows. At Virginia Tech, she was an elegant, talented dancer with Hill and Veil, a Middle Eastern dance group. Last Sunday, she performed with the group as part of the university's International Week Street Fair.</p>
        <p>Leslie G. Sherman, 20</p>
        <p>A sophomore and history major from Springfield, Va., she was a tomboy who loved running, history, foreign languages and making others laugh, said Deepika R. Chadive, 19, a fellow sophomore who played basketball with Ms. Sherman when both were students at West Springfield High School. ''She was very spirited,'' Ms. Chadive said. ''She was always very enthusiastic. Even if we were down 50 points, she would always give us a pat on the back.'' Ms. Sherman, who was passionate about studying history even as a high school student, often took some ribbing from her friends because of her interest in the subject, Ms. Chadive said. ''We used to tell her, 'It's illegal to love history as much as you do,' '' she said. She said Ms. Sherman had talked of becoming a historian.</p>
        <p>Maxine Turner, 22</p>
        <p>A senior chemical engineering major from Vienna, Va., she belonged to Alpha Omega Epsilon, an engineering sorority, and was public relations manager for the Virginia Tech Tae Kwon Do club. She enjoyed volunteering at an animal shelter and hoped someday to breed dogs as a hobby.</p>
        <p>Nicole White</p>
        <p>She was an international studies major from Smithfield, Va.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Remembering some of the students and faculty members killed in the Virginia Tech shootings, in these biographical sketches.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Remembering some of the students and faculty members killed in the Virginia Tech shootings, in these biographical sketches.</p>
        <p>Ross A. Alameddine, 20</p>
        <p>Originally from Saugus, Mass., he had just decided to major in English. His friends, who described him as a music fanatic -- especially for the jazz trio Medeski Martin and Wood -- as well as a video game enthusiast, credit his witty jokes with buoying their own spirits. They created a memorial for him on Facebook.com. ''You're such an amazing kid, Ross,'' wrote Zach Allen, who like Mr. Alameddine had attended Austin Preparatory School in Reading, Mass. ''You always made me smile.'' Friends said he was proud of his teal Pontiac Grand Am, which he won in a raffle -- the car he ''got for a dollar.''</p>
        <p>Christopher J. Bishop, 35</p>
        <p>A German instructor who was known as Jamie, he received his bachelor's and master's degrees in German linguistics from the University of Georgia, in Athens, and then attended Christian-Albrechts University in Kiel, Germany, on a Fulbright scholarship. During four years in Germany, he wrote in a journal on his Web site, memory39.com, he ''spent most of his time learning the language, teaching English, drinking large quantities of wheat beer, and wooing a certain fr채ulein.'' The fr채ulein, Stefanie Hofer, became his wife. She teaches in Virginia Tech's German department, too, but was not injured. His father, Michael Bishop, a science fiction writer, and his mother, Jeri, live in Pine Mountain, Ga.</p>
        <p>Brian Bluhm, 25</p>
        <p>With an undergraduate degree in civil engineering from Virginia Tech, he was working toward a master's degree in water resources. Mr. Bluhm was a shy, quiet person who did not like the spotlight, said his friend Hannah Barnhill. ''But he loved his friends,'' she said. ''He would light up whenever he saw someone he knew, and he had a memorable laugh and a huge heart.'' She said he ''adored'' Virginia Tech, adopting Blacksburg as his unofficial hometown. Born in Iowa, he lived in Detroit during his childhood, where he became an avid Detroit Tigers fan. His family later moved to Louisville, Ky., where he graduated from high school. He had recently set his future in stone: Mr. Bluhm accepted a job in Baltimore, found an apartment there, and was ready to begin his new life in July, his best friend, Michael Marshall, 25, said. ''He was a real lovable, genuine, peaceful person,'' Mr. Marshall said.</p>
        <p>Ryan Clark, 22</p>
        <p>A senior from Martinez, Ga., he was known as Stack and was smart, kind and well liked by those he met working as a resident adviser at West Ambler Johnston Hall, where the first shootings occurred. While studying for degrees in English and biology, and planning to work toward a doctorate at Northwestern University, he also joined Virginia Tech's marching band, the Marching Virginians. Cady J. Hendershot, 20, his lab partner in molecular biology, said Mr. Clark was ''instantly friends with almost anyone he meets, he was just magnetic. He was just so much fun. We could pretty much ruin an entire experiment and still laugh it off and somehow manage to do our lab reports.'' He was close to his family, friends say, but especially to his twin brother, Bryan.</p>
        <p>Austin Cloyd, 19</p>
        <p>A freshman and international studies major and university lifeguard, she grew up in Champaign, Ill., where her father, C. Bryan Cloyd, taught accounting at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign. Ms. Cloyd excelled in volleyball and basketball and was active in the First United Methodist Church in Champaign, sometimes going on missions to Appalachia to help rehabilitate homes, said Terry Harter, senior pastor. ''She was outgoing, friendly, a warm kid with a good sense of humor, very caring,'' Mr. Harter said. ''It's just horrible.'' Ms. Cloyd's mother served as an administrative assistant and director of youth ministries at First United, Mr. Harter said, until the family moved to Blacksburg in 2005 when Mr. Cloyd took a position as professor of accounting and information systems at Virginia Tech.</p>
        <p>Jocelyne Couture-Nowak</p>
        <p>A French instructor from the Montreal area, she moved eight years ago to Virginia Tech, where her husband, Jerzy Nowak, teaches horticulture. She had worked passionately to spread the French language, and was described as vibrant, enthusiastic and dynamic by the vice president of administration, Bernie MacDonald, at a school where she taught French, Nova Scotia Agricultural College. Ms. Couture-Nowak is survived by her husband and two daughters.</p>
        <p>Kevin Granata, 45</p>
        <p>A professor of engineering science and mechanics, he was an accomplished biomechanics researcher, studying the effects of lower back pain and how to prevent it. He was also an adjunct faculty member of orthopedic surgery at the University of Virginia. He was married to Linda Granata, had three children and coached lacrosse and was active in Scouting.</p>
        <p>Matthew Gwaltney</p>
        <p>A graduate student from Chester, Va., he was in his second year of a program in civil and environmental engineering and enjoyed working on river mechanics and river restoration but left time to play basketball and softball in the summer. He graduated from Virginia Tech in 2005. His master's research focused on stormwater management, and he was a teaching assistant, along with Brian Bluhm.</p>
        <p>Caitlin M. Hammaren, 19</p>
        <p>Born in Westtown, N.Y., she was a sophomore majoring in international studies and French. She was a recognized student leader and belonged to the Kappa Kappa Gamma sorority.</p>
        <p>Jeremy Herbstritt, 27</p>
        <p>A graduate student from Western Pennsylvania, he had undergraduate degrees in biochemistry and molecular biology from Penn State. He was doing graduate work in civil engineering and hoped to begin a career in environmental work. He was known as the kind of student who went out of his way to make others feel at ease. He was an avid long-distance runner whose parents had gone to Boston on Monday to watch his sister run in the Boston Marathon as part of a charity group, Centre Volunteers in Medicine.</p>
        <p>Emily J. Hilscher, 19</p>
        <p>A freshman majoring in animal and poultry sciences and equine sciences, she was a straight-A student and worked at a veterinary clinic last summer and hoped to become a veterinarian. She grew up in a small, tightly knit rural community of about 7,000 people in Rappahannock County, Va. She was an accomplished horsewoman and a member of the Virginia Tech equestrian club.</p>
        <p>Matthew La Porte, 20</p>
        <p>A sophomore from Dumont, N.J., he had traded life in his working-class neighborhood for the order of military school, and then for college on an ROTC scholarship in Virginia. Dane Rogich, 20, one of Mr. La Porte's oldest friends, said the two had known each other since they were 5 and had both chosen military school in Pennsylvania. There, Mr. La Porte tended toward music, as a cellist and a drum major. ''From here, to military school, to college -- it was amazing,'' Mr. Rogich said. ''And then he was gone.''</p>
        <p>Henry Lee, 20</p>
        <p>A freshman majoring in computer engineering, he was in elementary school and unable to speak English when his family emigrated from China. When he became an American citizen in 1999, he changed his name from Henh Ly. That same year he graduated from William Fleming High School in Roanoke, Va., and was salutatorian of his class with a 4.47 grade point average. He worked part time at Sears in high school and was honored for his scholastic achievements by the local Burger King, which gave hisclass vouchers for free Whoppers.</p>
        <p>Liviu Librescu, 75</p>
        <p>A senior researcher and lecturer in engineering, he was a Holocaust survivor originally from Romania. He and his wife, Marlena, had immigrated to Israel in 1978, before moving to the United States in 1984. According to news reports, Mr. Librescu blocked the doorway to his classroom from the gunman so students could flee, before he himself was killed.</p>
        <p>G.V. Loganathan, 52</p>
        <p>A professor of civil and environmental engineering, he was honored for his work in hydraulic engineering and had received many awards from Virginia Tech. He was due to receive in a few weeks the prestigious Wine Award for teaching excellence, given to only three professors each year. Mr. Loganathan was known for helping students and colleagues with complex technical problems and was instrumental in the development of computer tools that predict when pipes will fail because of corrosion. He is survived by his wife and two daughters.</p>
        <p>Lauren A. McCain, 20</p>
        <p>An international studies major from Hampton, Va., she described herself on her MySpace page as deeply religious and a fan of science fiction movies and every kind of music except country. She looked on her brother, Joel, as her hero.</p>
        <p>Juan R. Ortiz, 26</p>
        <p>A graduate student in civil engineering, he was originally from Bayamon, P.R. He married less than a year ago and came to the United States with his new wife to study at Virginia Tech. He was active in the Latin American and Iberic Graduate Student Association.</p>
        <p>Daniel Perez Cueva, 21</p>
        <p>Born in Peru, he was studying international relations and was active in a Peruvian student society on campus.</p>
        <p>Erin Peterson, 18</p>
        <p>A freshman from Centreville, Va., she was studying international relations at Virginia Tech. She graduated from Westfield High School, the same high school as the gunman, where she was a star basketball player.</p>
        <p>Michael S. Pohle Jr.</p>
        <p>A graduate of Hunterdon Central High School in Raritan Township, N.J., he was majoring in biological sciences at Virginia Tech and was a member of the lacrosse team. He tended bar at Nerve Restaurant and Bar in Blacksburg.</p>
        <p>Julia Pryde, 23</p>
        <p>A graduate student in biological systems engineering from Middletown, N.J., she wrote a proposal to have the school cafeteria stop throwing waste in a landfill and start recycling it as compost. She was studying watershed management in mountainous regions to help improve water quality. She was killed in an advanced hydrology class, along with a professor she much admired, G. V. Loganathan.</p>
        <p>Mary K. Read, 19</p>
        <p>A freshman majoring in interdisciplinary studies, she had wanted to become an elementary schoolteacher. She played the clarinet and was a member of her high school marching band in Annandale, Va., winning the band's ''Best Smile'' award in her senior year. She loved baking, and her friends treasured her ''heavenly cookies.''</p>
        <p>Reema Samaha, 18</p>
        <p>A freshman from Centreville, Va., she graduated from the same high school as the gunman. In high school, she was on the dance team and took part in theater productions and talent shows. At Virginia Tech, she was an elegant, talented dancer with Hill and Veil, a Middle Eastern dance group. Last Sunday, she performed with the group as part of the university's International Week Street Fair.</p>
        <p>Leslie G. Sherman, 20</p>
        <p>A sophomore and history major from Springfield, Va., she was a tomboy who loved running, history, foreign languages and making others laugh, said Deepika R. Chadive, 19, a fellow sophomore who played basketball with Ms. Sherman when both were students at West Springfield High School. ''She was very spirited,'' Ms. Chadive said. ''She was always very enthusiastic. Even if we were down 50 points, she would always give us a pat on the back.'' Ms. Sherman, who was passionate about studying history even as a high school student, often took some ribbing from her friends because of her interest in the subject, Ms. Chadive said. ''We used to tell her, 'It's illegal to love history as much as you do,' '' she said. She said Ms. Sherman had talked of becoming a historian.</p>
        <p>Maxine Turner, 22</p>
        <p>A senior chemical engineering major from Vienna, Va., she belonged to Alpha Omega Epsilon, an engineering sorority, and was public relations manager for the Virginia Tech Tae Kwon Do club. She enjoyed volunteering at an animal shelter and hoped someday to breed dogs as a hobby.</p>
        <p>Nicole White</p>
        <p>She was an international studies major from Smithfield, Va.  MASSACRE IN VIRGINIA</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 21, 2007, Saturday  A biographical sketch on Wednesday of Michael S. Pohle Jr., one of the victims at Virginia Polytechnic Institute, misspelled the name of the restaurant where he worked. It is Nerv, not Nerve.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 8, 2007, Tuesday  A biographical sketch on April 18 about Henry Lee, a victim of the Virginia Tech massacre, misstated the year he graduated from high school and became an American citizen. It was 2006, not 1999. The sketch, and an article the same day about the victims, also misstated the country from which he emigrated. It was Vietnam, not China.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 21, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>A biographical sketch on Wednesday of Michael S. Pohle Jr., one of the victims at Virginia Polytechnic Institute, misspelled the name of the restaurant where he worked. It is Nerv, not Nerve.</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>Correction: May 8, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A biographical sketch on April 18 about Henry Lee, a victim of the Virginia Tech massacre, misstated the year he graduated from high school and became an American citizen. It was 2006, not 1999. The sketch, and an article the same day about the victims, also misstated the country from which he emigrated. It was Vietnam, not China.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
