<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yet Another Flood, And Residents Ask, Why Stay Here?</title>
    <meta content="18towns" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/nyregion/18towns.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841154"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OUR TOWNS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bound Brook (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Applebome, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Our Towns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03EFDD1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="823" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yet Another Flood, And Residents Ask, Why Stay Here?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Yet Another Flood, and Residents Ask, Why Stay Here?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER APPLEBOME</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Applebome, Peter</byline>
      <dateline>BOUND BROOK, N.J.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter Applebome Our Towns column on Bound Brook, NJ, which is recovering from latest flooding; says town is prone to serious flood every decade or so but residents stay because it is classic middle-class town that is more or less affordable (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kathy Blockus lives in the rambling yellow house on Van Keuren Avenue that her grandparents built nearly a century ago. Rosemary Machicote lives in a house nearby she has rented since she came to this town on the Raritan River in 2005.</p>
        <p>But yesterday, they had equal membership privileges in the Loyal Sisterhood of the Soggy and Bereft, the association of shared misery that has become as much a part of life in Bound Brook as visits to the Brook Arts Center, the old vaudeville house that's been around in various guises since 1927. So under a gray sky and a wet chill they found themselves where people hoped they would never be again -- back under water, just as people were after a notorious flood in 1973, just as they were after Tropical Storm Floyd left this town gasping in 1999, just as they've been for less dramatic floods in between and since.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In flood-prone Bound Brook, N.J., residents talk about the reasons to leave and the reasons to stay.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Kathy Blockus lives in the rambling yellow house on Van Keuren Avenue that her grandparents built nearly a century ago. Rosemary Machicote lives in a house nearby she has rented since she came to this town on the Raritan River in 2005.</p>
        <p>But yesterday, they had equal membership privileges in the Loyal Sisterhood of the Soggy and Bereft, the association of shared misery that has become as much a part of life in Bound Brook as visits to the Brook Arts Center, the old vaudeville house that's been around in various guises since 1927. So under a gray sky and a wet chill they found themselves where people hoped they would never be again -- back under water, just as people were after a notorious flood in 1973, just as they were after Tropical Storm Floyd left this town gasping in 1999, just as they've been for less dramatic floods in between and since.</p>
        <p>Ms. Blockus figured she was in it for the long haul. What else could she do? Ms. Machicote wasn't so sure. ''This isn't like baseball, where you get one, two, three strikes,'' she said. ''One is enough for me.'' But both did their best to navigate the line between resignation and anger that's the lot of a place like this that floods, and floods again, hears promises that it can't happen again, and watches the water pour in one more time.</p>
        <p>So there people were yesterday in this Central Jersey town, wandering aimlessly like seagulls on the beach, watching people cleaning out the homes where the water had receded, taking in the gray van stranded like a grounded schooner in the oily water outside the old Moose hall at Vosseller and Talmage Avenues.</p>
        <p>What united them was a knowledge that this wasn't supposed to happen again, but it did.</p>
        <p>''It's been eight years since Floyd, and since then we've got dikes at one end and dikes on the other, but nothing in the middle,'' said Don McCutcheon, who was cleaning up water damage again at his Foothill Service Station. He said it might be time to level the flood-prone part of town, pay people for their property and make parkland out of it. ''People can't keep going through this.''</p>
        <p>He wouldn't mind a payout that would allow people to move elsewhere, and from afar, it's easy to wonder -- well, if it floods so badly, why live there?</p>
        <p>But in fact, as everyone out and about seemed to say, there are many, many reasons to live in Bound Brook -- its convivial main street full of restaurants and bodegas, its wondrous population mix, one-part the Italians and Polish of old, one-part the Costa Ricans and Hondurans of today. It's a classic middle-class town like ones from long ago, where you can actually get out and walk, know your neighbors, where there's art and culture as well as Little League and soccer. And, most important, partly because of the river looming over your shoulder, you can afford it, more or less, on a salary that wouldn't get you a garage in more prestigious ZIP codes.</p>
        <p>So part of the price of admission, as it is in many places, is a recognition that if you don't have much money, you get a flood every decade or so as part of the bargain? Hard to believe it should be.</p>
        <p>In 1973, after a flood caused devastating damage, federal and local officials began plans to build the Green Brook Flood Control Project. But the project became a study in bureaucratic foot-dragging over the next two decades. There were federal budget cuts, changes to the plan demanded by Congress, environmental debates and political feuds about who pays and who benefits.</p>
        <p>It took the two deaths in Bound Brook during Floyd, and an estimated $630 million worth of damage throughout the state, to push the plan forward. In October 2000, the Army Corps of Engineers broke ground on the $330 million project that would be built over 65 square miles, but no one knows how long it will take to complete it. Officials say it will take another $30 million to $40 million just for Bound Brook. But there's a war to fight. Bigger disasters to deal with. Highways and sewers and flood projects just as pressing as the needs of this little town. Infrastructure is the most boring word in the English language, unless it's your infrastructure that keeps your living room dry.</p>
        <p>Ms. Machicote, who has no renter's insurance, basically lost everything. Ms. Blockus, a homeowner, is still paying off small business loans from Floyd but had flood insurance that will cushion the blow from this one.</p>
        <p>As for the town?</p>
        <p>''After the 1999 storm, the downtown merchants were washed out,'' she said. ''New merchants came in, and now they're washed out, too. You stand and watch the water come in and the water go out. Maybe next time I'll buy a boat.''</p>
        <p>OUR TOWNS E-mail: peappl@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: peappl@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
