<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Looking Back in Anger at the Gilded Age's Excesses</title>
    <meta content="18grim" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/arts/18grim.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841121"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Atlantic Monthly</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Beatty, Jack</person>
        <person class="online_producer">George, Henry</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Carnegie, Andrew</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Beecher, Henry Ward</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Age of Betrayal: Triumph of Money in America, The (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E1DE1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="980" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Looking Back in Anger at the Gilded Age's Excesses</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Looking Back in Anger at the Gilded Age’s Excesses</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GRIMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Grimes, William</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Age of Betrayal  The Triumph of Money in America, 1865-1900  By Jack Beatty  Illustrated. 483 pages. Alfred A. Knopf. $30.</p>
        <p>In the decades after the Civil War, the United States took a sharp right turn and has been wandering in the wilderness ever since, hopelessly lost. Conceived in liberty and dedicated to equal justice for all, it squandered the moral capital painfully accumulated during the war, selling its soul to big corporations and capitalist fat cats. This, in brief, is Jack Beatty's thesis in ''Age of Betrayal,'' his indignant history of the Gilded Age, a long nightmare of repression, racism and greed from which the country, in his view, has never awakened.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jack Beatty’s “Age of Betrayal,” is an indignant history of the decades after the Civil War, a long nightmare of repression and racism from which the country, in his view, has never awakened.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Age of Betrayal  The Triumph of Money in America, 1865-1900  By Jack Beatty  Illustrated. 483 pages. Alfred A. Knopf. $30.</p>
        <p>In the decades after the Civil War, the United States took a sharp right turn and has been wandering in the wilderness ever since, hopelessly lost. Conceived in liberty and dedicated to equal justice for all, it squandered the moral capital painfully accumulated during the war, selling its soul to big corporations and capitalist fat cats. This, in brief, is Jack Beatty's thesis in ''Age of Betrayal,'' his indignant history of the Gilded Age, a long nightmare of repression, racism and greed from which the country, in his view, has never awakened.</p>
        <p>Mr. Beatty, a senior editor at The Atlantic Monthly and the author of ''The Rascal King: The Life and Times of James Michael Curley, 1874-1958,'' tells his cautionary tale with great moral fervor. ''The saddest story,'' as he calls it, looks back wistfully to the abandoned dream of ''free soil, free labor, free men and free land'' as it pauses, like an industrial-age passion play, before the signal events that led to government, in the words of the social reformer Henry George, ''by the corporations, of the corporations and for the corporations.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Beatty traces the rise of the railroads, the great land-grab unloosed in the West, the development of a two-party system devoid of principle and fat with corruption, and the steady abandonment of Reconstruction in the South. He revisits the bloody strike against the Pennsylvania Railroad in 1877, the industrial war at Andrew Carnegie's Homestead steel plant in 1890 and the fabulous Bradley Martin ball at the Waldorf-Astoria in 1897.</p>
        <p>Mr. Beatty serves up these familiar dishes extra-spicy. The past for him is present, and if he seethes, it is because he sees all around him the natural heirs to the satanic figures he describes. In asides and footnotes, unexpected names like those of Karl Rove and Antonin Scalia take a quick turn on the stage, smelling of sulfur. The evil work of the Gilded Age continues because the system it put in place remains substantially the same, enabled by a political culture that has, Mr. Beatty argues, ''insulated industrialism from democracy through a politics of distraction, based on the manipulation of real hatreds and sham issues.''</p>
        <p>The villains in this story greatly outnumber the heroes. There is keen competition for top honors in infamy among an all-star team that includes Andrew Carnegie, John D. Rockefeller, Jay Gould and Tom Scott, czar of the Pennsylvania Railroad. All crush the working class with glee and slake their unquenchable thirst with the people's blood, but the Lucifer in Mr. Beatty's hell is Stephen J. Field, one of America's longest-serving Supreme Court justices, who insinuated into the law of the land, almost by sleight of hand, a corporatist prejudice that survives to the present day.</p>
        <p>Thanks to Justice Field, Mr. Beatty argues, corporations found themselves in the delightful position of being regarded as persons entitled to the protection of the 14th Amendment, the very same amendment originally intended to safeguard the rights of freed slaves. Mr. Beatty savors the contradiction.</p>
        <p>''Age of Betrayal'' is both too personal and not personal enough. Mr. Beatty takes a peculiar tone for a historian. The events he describes occurred more than a century ago, yet Mr. Beatty regards them with fresh indignation, an emotion better left to the reader. He displaces his anger at current American politics on an era well beyond living memory. This is anachronistic. There is no point in savagely attacking the character of Carnegie, but apparently it gives Mr. Beatty satisfaction. The continual score-settling makes ''Age of Betrayal'' seem less like history than therapy.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Beatty too seldom tells this story in his own words. He has done a prodigious, scrupulous job of research, but in the end it does him in, with the sources commandeering the narrative. Scarcely a sentence passes without a quotation or a citation. It is reassuring to know that an author has done his homework, but dispiriting when he proves it relentlessly. When Mr. Beatty throws off the obsessive citing, as he does in his spirited accounts of the industrial battles of the period, the pace quickens noticeably.</p>
        <p>He does, however, have a strange penchant for obscure words like ''salvific,'' ''predaceous,'' ''peccant'' and ''mithridatic,'' and opaque formulations like ''all sentience knew his reputation.''</p>
        <p>It would be wrong to say that Mr. Beatty is of the Devil's party without knowing it, but Mr. Gould, Mr. Carnegie and the rest of his evil company do inhale most of the available oxygen. In their rapacity, shamelessness and cunning, they assume an almost Shakespearean grandeur. ''Ashamed to tell you profits these days,'' Carnegie writes to a friend. ''Prodigious!''</p>
        <p>Never before or since have the rich been so rich, the working class so poor, the politicians so supine. The richest 1 percent owned 26 percent of the wealth, and the richest 10 percent owned 72 percent. When workers complained of low wages, they earned the admonishments of leaders like Henry Ward Beecher, who scoffed when he heard that laborers could not afford butter for their bread on a dollar a day.</p>
        <p>''Man cannot live by bread alone,'' he thundered in a sermon, ''but the man who cannot live on bread and water is not fit to live.''</p>
        <p>Again and again, surveying the post-Civil War landscape, Mr. Beatty throws up his hands in despair. ''The people supported the government, and the government supported the corporations and the rentiers with the people's money,'' he writes. ''And the people did not seem to object, at least not enough of them.''</p>
        <p>Maybe that's because of wheeler-dealers like Jay Gould, who once boasted, ''I can hire one half of the working class to kill the other half.'' They just don't make them like that anymore.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
