<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lightning Outworking the Devils</title>
    <meta content="18devils" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/sports/hockey/18devils.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841208"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Tampa Bay Lightning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Tampa Bay Lightning</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Brodeur, Martin</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Lecavalier, Vincent</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5DB1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="906" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lightning Outworking the Devils</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lightning Outworking the Devils</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crouse, Karen</byline>
      <dateline>TAMPA, Fla., April 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Leaning against his locker Tuesday in a pose of studied nonchalance, Devils goaltender Martin Brodeur said it made him happy not to have given up a goal in the second period of the Devils' 3-2 loss to the Tampa Bay Lightning on Monday night.</p>
        <p>It seemed to be a strange admission coming from the lips of Brodeur, who earlier this month broke the 33-year-old record for victories in a regular season set by the Hall of Famer Bernie Parent. It was like hearing the racecar driver Jeff Gordon say he was glad he negotiated that left turn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Lightning, led by its superlative center, Vincent Lecavalier, has put three pucks past Devils goaltender Martin Brodeur in each game of this series, taking a 2-1 lead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Leaning against his locker Tuesday in a pose of studied nonchalance, Devils goaltender Martin Brodeur said it made him happy not to have given up a goal in the second period of the Devils' 3-2 loss to the Tampa Bay Lightning on Monday night.</p>
        <p>It seemed to be a strange admission coming from the lips of Brodeur, who earlier this month broke the 33-year-old record for victories in a regular season set by the Hall of Famer Bernie Parent. It was like hearing the racecar driver Jeff Gordon say he was glad he negotiated that left turn.</p>
        <p>''Just small goals,'' Brodeur said, laughing. ''Baby steps here.''</p>
        <p>On the eve of Game 4 of the Devils' Eastern Conference quarterfinal series, Brodeur was his usual lighthearted self, his mood belying the unusual turn the series has taken.</p>
        <p>The Lightning, led by its superlative center, Vincent Lecavalier, has put three pucks past Brodeur in each game of this series, taking a 2-1 lead. Brodeur has been the goalie of record in all but three of the Devils' playoff games since 1994. He has allowed as many as three goals in three consecutive playoff games only four times in his 13 seasons, in 1994, 1999, 2000 and last season.</p>
        <p>The past two games have turned on a play or two in the third period, which is how the defensive-minded Devils generally prefer it. But this time, they are the ones who have been outworked and outscored in the final 20 minutes. The Lightning's two victories have come by 3-2 scores.</p>
        <p>''It's never fun losing,'' said Brodeur, whose save percentage in this series is unusually low, at .871. ''If you're not winning you feel like you need to do something. But at the end of the day, when you have the experience you've got to feel the confidence in yourself that you're comfortable playing the game. I think the worst thing you can do is start over-thinking. I mean, it's still a game.''</p>
        <p>Brodeur is not so walled off from the world that he does not recognize there are worst plights than being two losses from elimination. A friend back home in New Jersey, Mike Citarella, owns a bar in West Orange that was flooded during this week's record-setting rainstorm. A one-game deficit is easier to bail oneself out of than knee-high rainwater.</p>
        <p>''You've got to go out and try to perform,'' Brodeur said, ''and I'll try to make that difference.''</p>
        <p>In his last regular-season start, Brodeur recorded his 48th victory. In Game 1 against the Lightning, he registered his 90th playoff victory, putting him third on the career list. He is two behind Grant Fuhr; Patrick Roy holds the record with 151.</p>
        <p>Lecavalier, who usually plays alongside Martin St. Louis, another scary scoring threat, has four of the Lightning's nine goals and 15 of its 70 shots. He is hard to knock off the puck and even harder to read when he has the room to pass or shoot.</p>
        <p>''I think he's getting different looks that I'm not really used to,'' Brodeur said. ''I think he comes in and he's looking at you, picking corners. That makes it a little harder for me to be aggressive. I don't know what he's doing.''</p>
        <p>Rangers forward Brendan Shanahan once paid Brodeur a similar compliment, telling him he was a nightmare to face on breakaways because there was no set pattern to how he would play the puck.</p>
        <p>''Vinny's one of the best,'' Brodeur said, ''so I've got to stay back and be patient.''</p>
        <p>It would help Brodeur if his defensemen gave Lecavalier less room to operate, which is easier said than done. And at the other end, the Devils' skaters have to create more traffic in front of the net.</p>
        <p>Lightning goaltender Johan Holmqvist, in his first N.H.L. postseason, is making some nice stops but he is also leaving plenty of rebounds for the Devils.</p>
        <p>''I think we've got to do a better job of exposing him,'' said Zach Parise, a second-line forward and a first-rate scorer. ''He's played well, he's made the saves he needs to make but I think we can do a better job of challenging him.''</p>
        <p>Parise is doing his part, with four goals in the series. He has two goals more than the top line of Scott Gomez, Patrik Elias and Brian Gionta.</p>
        <p>''No one's pushing the panic button,'' Gomez said, adding: ''If Brian's in front of the net, we've got to get the puck somehow towards his area. Whatever it takes, you have to bear down and put it in.''</p>
        <p>When Brodeur is at his best -- which is to say most of the time -- he makes the saves that help people overlook his teammates' shortcomings. When he lets in a fluky goal or three, all the Devils are exposed.</p>
        <p>''The bar is set so high for Marty,'' Parise said, ''and he's had so much success that if a goal does go in, then people start pointing fingers at him, which I don't think is fair. He's been great all season and he's a big part of the reason why we're here.''</p>
        <p>The Devils are in a bind. But when they look over and see Brodeur laughing, they all loosen up.</p>
        <p>''The series isn't over and what makes Marty so good, what makes him great, is he's always responded,'' Gomez said. ''He's one of the special ones. It's not bugging him in his mind.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
