<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Moktada al-Sadr's Gambit</title>
    <meta content="18weds1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/opinion/18weds1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841158"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Editorial"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maliki, Nuri Kamal Al- (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sadr, Moktada Al-</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Sadr, Moktada Al-</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Maliki, Nuri Kamal al-</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gates, Robert M</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E7DC1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="466" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Moktada al-Sadr's Gambit</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Moktada al-Sadr’s Gambit</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial reports that Iraqi government sinks loewr with brazen power play by Moktada al-Sadr, virulently anti-American cleric who has directed his party's six ministers to resign from Prime Min Nuri al-Maliki's cabinet to bully government into setting timetable for US departure; adds that squeeze play leaves Bush administration with even weaker hand than before</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just when it looked as if the Iraqi government had sunk as low as it could go, it sank still further, following a brazen power play by Moktada al-Sadr.</p>
        <p>Until now Mr. Sadr, a virulently anti-American cleric with an unquenchable appetite for attention and power, had been Prime Minister Nuri Kamal al-Maliki's strongest political ally. But on Monday, at his direction, his party's six ministers quit the Maliki cabinet. The government still depends on the parliamentary votes of Mr. Sadr's party, the largest faction in the ruling Shiite bloc.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just when it looked as if the Iraqi government had sunk as low as it could go, it sank still further, following a brazen power play by Moktada al-Sadr.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just when it looked as if the Iraqi government had sunk as low as it could go, it sank still further, following a brazen power play by Moktada al-Sadr.</p>
        <p>Until now Mr. Sadr, a virulently anti-American cleric with an unquenchable appetite for attention and power, had been Prime Minister Nuri Kamal al-Maliki's strongest political ally. But on Monday, at his direction, his party's six ministers quit the Maliki cabinet. The government still depends on the parliamentary votes of Mr. Sadr's party, the largest faction in the ruling Shiite bloc.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maliki, a colorless and ineffective politician, has been prime minister for the past year. But from the beginning, his authority has depended on the backing of Mr. Sadr, a charismatic demagogue with an intimidating private army, a potent political party and an impressive capacity for sending his followers into the street.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maliki had probably figured that he was better off having Mr. Sadr's party inside his cabinet, demanding patronage for its followers and official protection for its rampaging private militia, than outside, publicly challenging government policies, including Mr. Maliki's support for a continued American military presence in Iraq.</p>
        <p>Now Mr. Maliki may be about to experience the worst of both options. Mr. Sadr had his cabinet ministers resign in an attempt to bully the government into setting a timetable for the departure of American troops from Iraq. Mr. Maliki cannot just say no, because if Mr. Sadr's party turns against him, he could lose his parliamentary majority. Nor can he just say yes because the physical survival of his administration probably still depends on those American troops. Meanwhile, Mr. Sadr has aligned himself with a highly popular cause that is likely to expand his following even further.</p>
        <p>This squeeze play leaves the Bush administration holding what looks like an even weaker political hand in Baghdad than it held before. Defense Secretary Robert Gates, now traveling through the region pleading with Arab leaders to ignore their misgivings about the Maliki government's performance, is gamely trying to sell the idea that the departure of the Sadr ministers, and their likely replacement by politically neutral technocrats, could actually help stabilize the Iraqi government.</p>
        <p>But technocratic caretaking will scarcely be enough, especially with Mr. Sadr inciting division from the sidelines. The American military drive in Baghdad has yet to show significant results. But even if it did, any security gains would be quickly erased without a series of decisive moves by the Iraqi government. These include sharing political power and economic resources with the Sunni minority, shutting down sectarian militias, and creating security forces committed to protect all Iraqis.</p>
        <p>That will require political will and authority, not mere administrative competence. Mr. Maliki displayed neither before Mr. Sadr's latest power play. He seems even less likely to display them now.</p>
        <p>Editorial</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
