<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Role About Winter for Julie Christie, a Star in Eternal Spring</title>
    <meta content="18chri" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/movies/18chri.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841111"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Alzheimer's</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alzheimer's Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Christie, Julie</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Polley, Sarah</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Munro, Alice</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Away From Her (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E3DE1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1229" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Role About Winter for Julie Christie, a Star in Eternal Spring</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Role About Winter for Julie Christie, a Star in Eternal Spring</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN RIDING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Riding, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For moviegoers who fell for Julie Christie in the 1960s (and they were legion), she will always be the tousle-haired blonde with the dazzling smile who lit up the screen in ''Darling,'' ''Doctor Zhivago'' and ''Far From the Madding Crowd.''</p>
        <p>Today they need not feel disappointed. In her new movie, ''Away From Her,'' which opens on May 4, she is still a tousle-haired blonde with a dazzling smile. But yes, like her fans, she too has changed. At 66, she is no longer attracted by fame. She is not even much interested in the Julie Christie of legend.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Julie Christie, who has grown disillusioned with the movies, makes a rare starring appearance in “Away From Her.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For moviegoers who fell for Julie Christie in the 1960s (and they were legion), she will always be the tousle-haired blonde with the dazzling smile who lit up the screen in ''Darling,'' ''Doctor Zhivago'' and ''Far From the Madding Crowd.''</p>
        <p>Today they need not feel disappointed. In her new movie, ''Away From Her,'' which opens on May 4, she is still a tousle-haired blonde with a dazzling smile. But yes, like her fans, she too has changed. At 66, she is no longer attracted by fame. She is not even much interested in the Julie Christie of legend.</p>
        <p>''I have no connection with that person at all,'' she said over lunch in a pub near her home in the East End. ''That person has gone.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, since that person went -- by her own calculation, sometime in the late 1970s -- Ms. Christie has become a reluctant actress, choosing political causes over show business, turning down more movie roles than she has accepted, preferring the calm of her country life in mid-Wales to the jostling egos and stress of film sets.</p>
        <p>''I don't like that world very much,'' she said. ''I feel I should apologize because it sounds so prissy and so ungrateful. Of course I have got so much out of it and I'm glad my life has gone the way it has. But I can't help it: it leaves a slightly bad taste in my mouth.''</p>
        <p>So it is not surprising that she took some persuading to play the lead in ''Away From Her,'' the first feature film directed by the young Canadian actress Sarah Polley. Ms. Christie's last major role was in ''Afterglow'' a decade ago. Since then, she said, she has made only cameo appearances ''to pay for my roof to be fixed.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Polley, 28, who had Ms. Christie in mind when she adapted Alice Munro's short story ''The Bear Came Over the Mountain'' for the screen, was nonetheless determined to have her in her movie. ''I knew I'd get a few noes before I got a yes,'' Ms. Polley said. ''And I was just hoping the yes would eventually come.''</p>
        <p>It did, although not because Ms. Christie had a sudden change of heart about the movie industry. Rather, it was because she met Ms. Polley in 2000 when they were both filming Hal Hartley's ''No Such Thing'' -- Ms. Polley in the lead, Ms. Christie in a small role.</p>
        <p>''I fell totally in love with her,'' Ms. Christie recalled. ''Of course, when she sent me this screenplay, I said no. But she kept on and on. She said she felt like a stalker. In the end, I thought, if I don't do it, I'll miss the opportunity of being with her on her first feature film.''</p>
        <p>And now she has no regrets.</p>
        <p>On one level ''Away From Her'' is a movie about Alzheimer's. Ms. Christie's Fiona is a beautiful woman in her early 60s who is gradually consumed by the disease, as her longtime husband, Grant, played by Gordon Pinsent, reluctantly accepts that she must be hospitalized. Through the early stages of her decline, Fiona is also aware of her affliction, noting poignantly at one point, ''I think I may be beginning to disappear.''</p>
        <p>As Ms. Polley conceived the movie, however, it is no less a portrait, in her words, of ''what a marriage looks like after that much life is piled on top of it,'' something that interests her, she said, because she is herself ''at the very beginning of a marriage.'' As Fiona's mind fades, memories she had long buried suddenly surface to confront Grant uncomfortably with his own past.</p>
        <p>At the hospital, Fiona develops an affection for another patient, Aubrey (Michael Murphy), further testing the love of both Grant and Aubrey's wife, Marian (Olympia Dukakis), for their ailing spouses.</p>
        <p>Ms. Christie noted that, while her parents were not afflicted by Alzheimer's, she had witnessed its effects on the parents of friends and some of her own friends, including one 90-year-old who ''just drifted away.''</p>
        <p>She recalled gently, ''I ceased to be important to her; I ceased to be anything to her.''</p>
        <p>So, Ms. Christie was asked, does she fear Alzheimer's?</p>
        <p>''No, it doesn't worry me too much,'' she said. ''I am more worried about what's happening to people in the rest of the world, to be honest, more than anything that could possibly happen to me.''</p>
        <p>But, she added with a laugh, she was not always like that.</p>
        <p>''I have been rereading letters I wrote in the 1960s to a girlfriend and I sound so ghastly,'' she said. ''All I'm talking about is boys and parties and music. I pointed that out to my girlfriend. 'Yes,' she said, 'I used to think of you then as being deeply shallow.' 'Deeply shallow' I was, then something happened.''</p>
        <p>As she looked back over her life, it was the discovery of ''people in the rest of the world,'' she said -- specifically, her discovery of politics in the 1970s, later reinforced by her longtime partner, the journalist Duncan Campbell -- that led her to rethink her career. And it was then that she began to see herself in the movie industry ''surrounded by all the things you hate most in life, which are consumerism and advertising and celebrity and false representation.''</p>
        <p>Even then, though, she still had to adjust to growing up or, rather, growing older.</p>
        <p>''All women are aware of that moment when suddenly the boys don't look at you,'' she noted. ''It's a fairly common thing, when suddenly you no longer attract that instant male attention because of the way you look. I never really knew how to enjoy beauty, but it took the form of a subconscious arrogance, expecting things, all muddled up with celebrity.''</p>
        <p>''Then you begin to deal with it,'' she went on. ''In the 1970s I was amazed to be talked about as a '60s sex symbol. I wasn't that person, as if I were a doll from the past. I had to learn to come to terms with that. It's funny, it's silly, the ridiculousness of having asked so much of celebrity. Then it becomes really interesting and very much part of the excitement of the life you're living now, knowing you're approaching the end of it.''</p>
        <p>Well, perhaps, but judging by her energy, humor and appearance, the end is not quite nigh.</p>
        <p>Ms. Polley would certainly agree. ''I have never met anyone so completely engaged with whomever they are talking to and so essentially curious about the world around her,'' she said. ''A huge motivating factor in wanting to make this film was to have Julie as Fiona. I just could not stop picturing her in the part.''</p>
        <p>For Ms. Christie, on the other hand, ''Away From Her'' may be her last major role, unless she is once again wooed back to the screen. But either way, she seems at peace with herself, away from the shadow of the Julie Christie of yore.</p>
        <p>''If I don't make films, no one is going to write about me,'' she said. ''And most people have forgotten who I am anyway. My life is not interrupted because I am more or less anonymous.''</p>
        <p>And yet, if the mere mention of Ms. Christie's name still brings sighs from her fans, it is also because that dream girl of the 1960s lives on.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
