<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Citigroup Listens and Listens to Holders</title>
    <meta content="18citi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/business/18citi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841135"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">Citigroup Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Prince, Charles O III</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dash, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Citigroup Incorporated</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Prince, Charles O III</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E4DD1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="630" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Citigroup Listens and Listens to Holders</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Citigroup Listens and Listens to Holders</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC DASH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dash, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Citigroup chairman Charles O Prince III listens and answers numerous questions from shareholders at company's annual meeting at Carnegie Hall; companies are being urged to listen more closely to shareholders (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Companies are increasingly being urged to listen more closely to shareholders. There could be such a thing as too much.</p>
        <p>In sharp contrast to the Home Depot annual meeting last May that investors decried as unresponsive, Citigroup's session yesterday dragged on. And on. And on.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Companies are increasingly being urged to listen more closely to shareholders. There could be such a thing as too much.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Companies are increasingly being urged to listen more closely to shareholders. There could be such a thing as too much.</p>
        <p>In sharp contrast to the Home Depot annual meeting last May that investors decried as unresponsive, Citigroup's session yesterday dragged on. And on. And on.</p>
        <p>The meeting at Carnegie Hall was a veritable concert of shareholder concerns. With more than two dozen questions from nearly as many investors, it stretched for almost three hours -- about the time it takes an orchestra to perform Mahler's ''Symphony of a Thousand.'' Twice.</p>
        <p>One by one, shareholders stepped in front of the microphones to lob questions at Citigroup's chairman, Charles O. Prince III, who stood alone at a podium on stage right.</p>
        <p>Some investors pitched him ideas on strategy, like spinning off parts of the company. (''A flat, unqualified no,'' he said.)</p>
        <p>Others offered unsolicited management advice. They called for him to step down so the stock would go up, as James Cramer recommended on CNBC. (Mr. Prince said he did not watch much television.)</p>
        <p>Still others offered thoughts on less-than-topical topics, ranging from Don Imus to the Duke lacrosse case to Citigroup's need to fight tooth decay. Evelyn Y. Davis, the outspoken shareholder advocate, rose to speak at least half a dozen times.</p>
        <p>Mr. Prince patiently responded to question after question. Hesitant to cut anyone off, he let the meeting run.</p>
        <p>''It's obviously not the most efficient way to have interactions with your shareholders, but it's important to be open,'' Mr. Prince said in a brief interview. ''Even if you wade through a lot of the questions that don't seem pertinent, you can find things that are pretty interesting.''</p>
        <p>''I'd rather people have strong views than people hold things in,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Some investors thought less could be more.</p>
        <p>''It's a goat rodeo with individual shareholders run amok,'' said Richard Ferlauto, the director of investment policy for a big labor pension fund, after waiting more than two hours before stepping to the microphone with a ''say on pay'' proposal, which called for an advisory vote on Mr. Prince's compensation. (It received a 43 percent vote.) ''Rarely are shareholders served when a meeting goes out of control.''</p>
        <p>Citigroup's meeting, Mr. Ferlauto said, was the mirror opposite of Home Depot's meeting last year, when investors had a 60-second time limit and its board did not attend. This time, Citigroup directors -- prominently seated in the first row -- were checking their watches.</p>
        <p>Soon after 9 a.m., the meeting began with the more than 1,000 seats on the ground floor of Carnegie Hall's auditorium at near standing-room only. By 10 a.m., about 80 percent of the room was full. By 11, about half the seats were empty. And just before noon, when Mr. Prince adjourned the meeting after thanking shareholders for their endurance, only a few hundred people -- including the board -- were left.</p>
        <p>Citigroup's shareholder meetings have always been long and anomalous affairs. In 2006, the annual meeting morphed into a three and a half hour celebration of Sanford I. Weill, Citigroup's departing chairman. One woman stood up and read a poem.</p>
        <p>This year, Citigroup inverted the agenda. Before voting on the 11 investor proposals, Mr. Prince took questions.</p>
        <p>Some shareholders used the forum to complain about bank customer service or policies, prompting Mr. Prince to give out his e-mail address (princec@citigroup.com) and his office phone number (212-793-8854) and a customer service line (800-950-5114). One young investor lobbied him for an internship, noting that he would be a cheap hire at a time when the bank is eliminating 17,000 jobs.</p>
        <p>Ms. Davis, for her part, rattled off a laundry list of complaints. ''I think that the presentation was a little long,'' she said, but at least she was able to bring up ''my important stuff.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
