<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HOME AWAY: With Second Homes, the Outdoors Is In</title>
    <meta content="18GH-home" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841254"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DA1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="890" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HOME AWAY: With Second Homes, the Outdoors Is In</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMY GUNDERSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Kim Melrose looked out at the backyard of his vacation home in Rancho Mirage, Calif., he envisioned more than a swimming pool, a grill and a couple of lounge chairs on the patio. He saw the yard as the hub for entertaining -- and living.</p>
        <p>So he added an outdoor kitchen with a double sink, a dishwasher, a built-in grill, a full-size refrigerator, a bar with seven stools, and a sheltered outdoor living room complete with a wood-burning fireplace, a television and plush seating covered with a waterproof and fade-resistant version of a chenille-like fabric. The project took a year and a half.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Kim Melrose looked out at the backyard of his vacation home in Rancho Mirage, Calif., he envisioned more than a swimming pool, a grill and a couple of lounge chairs on the patio. He saw the yard as the hub for entertaining -- and living.</p>
        <p>So he added an outdoor kitchen with a double sink, a dishwasher, a built-in grill, a full-size refrigerator, a bar with seven stools, and a sheltered outdoor living room complete with a wood-burning fireplace, a television and plush seating covered with a waterproof and fade-resistant version of a chenille-like fabric. The project took a year and a half.</p>
        <p>Even the concrete flooring resembled something fit for any room of the house. ''I had the concrete cut and stained so that it looks like travertine,'' said Mr. Melrose, 52, a real estate agent and owner of a home-staging company. He estimates that the backyard work cost upward of $130,000 -- an investment that has proved attractive to both friends and renters who occupy the house in winter.</p>
        <p>''It's not unusual for me to have 50 people over for a barbecue,'' he said.</p>
        <p>These days, outdoors is in. Walk into most any home-improvement store or pick up a home-retailer catalog, and the options abound. There are outdoor beds and sofas designed to withstand the elements; intricate outside lamps; floors that seem polished enough for a formal dining room; and outdoor dressing rooms that accompany outdoor showers, long a beach-house staple.</p>
        <p>More designers are inaugurating outdoor lines, and big-box stores have many items for creating backyard oases. Manufacturers of outdoor kitchens are including accessories -- outdoor gas ovens and weatherproof plasma televisions -- that until now rarely if ever had a place out in the open.</p>
        <p>The focus on the backyard is not new, but this year the amenities have reached mainstream retailers, and product lines are growing more diverse, home specialists say, just as vacation homeowners contemplate the warmer months, as well as ways to expand the living areas of their houses.</p>
        <p>''The bonus room used to be the room over the garage,'' said Susan McCoy, the president of the Garden Media Group, a public relations agency in Chadds Ford, Pa., that specializes in the gardening and outdoor living fields. ''Now the bonus room is the deck or patio.''</p>
        <p>If you're shopping for outdoor accessories, there seem to be more choices than ever -- from new products at Target and Home Depot to lines by high-end designers.</p>
        <p>''Designers who have been celebrated for their interiors are now moving outside,'' said Jackie Hirschhaut, the vice president of the American Home Furnishings Alliance. This year, the New York-based designer Vladimir Kagan (vladimirkagan.com) created his first outdoor collection for the furniture maker Barlow Tyrie (teak.com).</p>
        <p>It includes a deep-seated sectional sofa, outdoor tables and even a daybed, all constructed from a synthetic woven material that is rain- and sun-resistant. The daybed, which comes with a curved ottoman, sells for $3,999; sectional sofa pieces start at $1,249; armchairs are $1,239 each.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hirschhaut says the diversity of products has a lot to do with new materials like synthetic wicker, which can stand up better to the elements, as well as an increase in the number of mills turning out fabrics resistant to sun damage and mildew. Those fabrics, in turn, are getting more detailed, with a greater range of colors available and with more intricate designs.</p>
        <p>If a backyard project goes beyond basic decorating, homeowners can turn to a pool contractor who specializes in creating outdoor living areas, or hire a landscape architect. The American Society of Landscape Architects (asla.org), an industry membership group that noted the popularity of outdoor fireplaces and fire pits in its trend forecast for this year, has a feature on its Web site that allows homeowners to find an architect who specializes in residential work.</p>
        <p>Scott Cohen, president of the Green Scene (greenscenelandscape.com), an outdoor design and construction firm in Canoga Park, Calif., says decorative items are only part of the equation when he creates a backyard retreat. Mr. Cohen's firm installs swimming pools, full landscaping and outdoor kitchens.</p>
        <p>''This is not your dad on a Weber,'' said Mr. Cohen, who has incorporated into his designs a swim-up outdoor kitchen for those who enjoy lunching in the water. It sits adjacent to a swimming pool or spa and has a bar.</p>
        <p>He said he preferred cast concrete or cast glass countertops to granite in his kitchen designs, especially in climates that have the biggest temperature swings. ''We had some problems with granite in freezing temperatures,'' he said; his backyard projects cost $200,000 to $700,000.</p>
        <p>In addition to custom designs, there are manufacturers like Cal Spas (www.calspas.com), which is based in Pomona, Calif., and sells, through a network of dealers, complete backyard setups that are growing more elaborate.</p>
        <p>The company is adding both a microwave oven and a built-in stainless steel gas oven later this year as options to its outdoor kitchen systems, which range from $1,950 to $70,000.</p>
        <p>It recently started selling what it calls the Ultimate Outdoor Theater: a $70,000 backyard collection that includes a 63-inch high-definition television, an Ipod docking station, surround-sound speakers and two subwoofers, along with a five-burner grill, an ice machine, a beer tap, two fire pits and weatherproof reclining chairs -- all of which may put any indoor living room to shame.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
