<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Offense Intended With This Year's Choice of Entertainer, but Still an Outcry</title>
    <meta content="18memo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/washington/18memo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841177"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WHITE HOUSE MEMO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Colbert, Stephen</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E1DC1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1204" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Offense Intended With This Year's Choice of Entertainer, but Still an Outcry</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">No Offense Intended With This Year’s Choice of Entertainer, but Still an Outcry</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM RUTENBERG</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After more than 40 years in show business, Rich Little is still a working comedian, doing his well-practiced impersonations from Las Vegas to Granite Falls, Minn. He is even available for corporate retreats and weddings.</p>
        <p>But this weekend, Mr. Little will return to the national stage, where he once held a regular place, when he appears at the Hilton Washington as headliner at the White House Correspondents' Association dinner. It is the capital's premier social event for the president, Congressional leaders and the reporters who cover them -- some of whom were too young to know Mr. Little's work, others who were surprised to learn he was still alive (actually, he is only 68).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rich Little, who will headline at the White House Correspondents’ Association dinner this weekend, has said he will avoid delivering the type of stinging performance Stephen Colbert delivered last year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After more than 40 years in show business, Rich Little is still a working comedian, doing his well-practiced impersonations from Las Vegas to Granite Falls, Minn. He is even available for corporate retreats and weddings.</p>
        <p>But this weekend, Mr. Little will return to the national stage, where he once held a regular place, when he appears at the Hilton Washington as headliner at the White House Correspondents' Association dinner. It is the capital's premier social event for the president, Congressional leaders and the reporters who cover them -- some of whom were too young to know Mr. Little's work, others who were surprised to learn he was still alive (actually, he is only 68).</p>
        <p>In hiring an impersonator practiced in an old-school approach to comedy, meant to entertain but not offend, the White House Correspondents' Association has, however, provoked left-leaning political activists, who see his assignment as a retreat from last year's dinner. Then, the television satirist Stephen Colbert delivered a stinging roast of President Bush and, to a lesser extent, the White House press corps.</p>
        <p>Mr. Little has said he would deliver no such performance this year. And his selection has become something of a symbol in the liberal blogosphere for what its members consider the proclivity of Washington reporters to give Mr. Bush and his administration a pass.</p>
        <p>''It represents that the White House press corps is more interested in playing friendly and cozying up to the Bush administration than it is in providing the sort of oversight that a free press should provide in a democracy,'' said Markos Moulitsas Zúniga, founder of the Daily Kos. ''They shouldn't be yukking it up together as if they're pals and friends, and that's why we've had so much terrible coverage.''</p>
        <p>Conservatives, of course, hoot at the idea that reporters are too cozy with the White House, saying that by and large the news media is implacably hostile to the administration and ideologically left-leaning. And association officials say they are in no way seeking to protect their relationships, to the extent they have any, with Mr. Bush and his aides -- and that whatever relationships they do have are neither cozy nor friendly.</p>
        <p>Mr. Little's appearance has further fueled a long-running debate over whether these types of dinners are relics best dispensed with, especially at a time when partisan divisions are intense, the nation is at war and reporters are pursuing scandals on multiple fronts.</p>
        <p>But for Mr. Little, who began his career in the early days of television, the reaction to his coming appearance has come as a lesson in the Bush-era clash between the old-line news media and the new-line liberal activists angry about what they view as journalistic malpractice during a time of war, and empowered by the Internet to make their views heard.</p>
        <p>He has been on the receiving end of some tough jokes since his appointment was announced this year. ''Bob Hope Sadly Too Dead to Headline WCHA Dinner,'' read the headline on Wonkette.com. Under the heading ''A 'Little' cowardice for the White House Correspondents Association dinner,'' The Carpetbagger Report wrote, ''As a rule, when you have to say, 'My dad loved him' to sell a performer, you've probably picked the wrong guy.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Little's comments to The Las Vegas Review-Journal that he had no plans to mention Iraq and that association officials ''don't want anyone knocking the president,'' stoked the blog firestorm that much more, and he and the association have since denied that he had agreed to any restrictions on what he could say.</p>
        <p>In an interview from Nevada this week, Mr. Little, a Canadian, said that he preferred a nonpartisan and unoffensive approach to comedy. He readily acknowledges he harks back to a time before the Internet, before cable, and before the era of off-color, no-holds-barred comedy that rose as his profile faded.</p>
        <p>His promotional biography says, ''He's particularly fond of doing Alan Ladd and other stars no longer typically remembered.'' And Mr. Little said his specialty remains impersonations of Presidents Richard Nixon, Jimmy Carter and Ronald Reagan, as well as Johnny Carson -- though he plans to mimic Mr. Bush and Senator John McCain of Arizona on Saturday night.</p>
        <p>Mr. Little said he was an especially well-chosen guest for the dinner after the dust-up over the offensive comments about the Rutgers women's basketball team by the radio host Don Imus (to whom he twice mistakenly referred as ''Amus.'')</p>
        <p>''There's a fine line between freedom of speech and being disrespectful and racist,'' Mr. Little said. He said when he imitates Mr. Bush at Saturday's dinner, ''It won't be anything on him personally. I don't do that anyway, and I think it would be in bad taste.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Little said he did not fault Mr. Colbert for his performance last year, though he said he disagreed with his approach: ''I don't care what your beliefs are politically, when you've got a man sitting there, you've got to use some judgment.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Colbert played the part of the mock, conservative commentator of his Comedy Central show, ''The Colbert Report.'' In one typical joke, he argued against describing a White House staff shake-up as ''rearranging the deck chairs on the Titanic.'' Rather, the administration was ''soaring,'' he said, and, ''If anything, they are rearranging the deck chairs on the Hindenburg.''</p>
        <p>White House officials did not publicly criticize the routine, though some privately said they thought it was more critical than comical.</p>
        <p>Steve Scully of C-Span and president of the correspondents' group, said he hired Mr. Little after seeing him last fall on ''Late Show with David Letterman.'' But Mr. Scully indicated that he was not looking for somebody who would offend this year. ''He doesn't have to come to our dinner,'' Mr. Scully said of Mr. Bush, adding that the event raised money for college scholarships. ''Clearly, you want to make the dinner enjoyable; you don't want to embarrass anyone.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Colbert was not the first to offend in this type of setting. Mr. Imus angered the Clinton White House in 1996 when he made fun of Mr. Clinton as a philanderer at a Radio and Television Correspondents' Association Dinner. Larry McQuillan, a former White House Correspondents' Association president, said he had chosen Ray Romano, whose routine is nonpolitical, as a safe bet in 1998 as impeachment loomed.</p>
        <p>But that was pre-blogosphere, which is populated by people who ''feel that the press was run over, and kind of told itself some story to avoid confrontation and lapsed into a phony kind of balance,'' said Jay Rosen, a journalism professor at New York University.</p>
        <p>It is enough to make some reporters bristle. ''Some of them seem to want us to hate the people we cover,'' said Ken Herman, a White House correspondent for Cox Newspapers and an association board member. ''They don't seem to understand that you can have a professional relationship with them where you don't hate them, and you can sometimes talk to them, and maybe have dinner with them.''</p>
        <p>But this is all beyond the scope of Mr. Little, who just wants to score some laughs. ''If I don't go over at the White House dinner,'' he said, ''maybe next year they should go with Julie Andrews.''</p>
        <p>WHITE HOUSE MEMO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
