<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Before Draft, Eyes Are Upon the Texans, Again</title>
    <meta content="18texans" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/sports/football/18texans.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841199"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Houston Texans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Houston Texans</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Williams, Mario</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Carr, David</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, Reggie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6DB1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="894" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Before Draft, Eyes Are Upon the Texans, Again</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Before the N.F.L. Draft, All Eyes Are on the Texans</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From his furniture store hard by Interstate 45 in Houston, Jim McIngvale has a window seat on a state's obsession with football and with man's ability to forgive.</p>
        <p>McIngvale -- Mattress Mack, as he is known from his commercials for Gallery Furniture -- watched as Vince Young became a local high school legend, cheered as Young won a national championship for the Texas Longhorns and despaired when it became clear before last year's National Football League draft that the Houston Texans were not quite as smitten with Young as he was.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Texans were second-guessed and publicly criticized for their 2006 draft choice. Now with a new front office in place, there will be less pressure when the Texans pick 10th.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From his furniture store hard by Interstate 45 in Houston, Jim McIngvale has a window seat on a state's obsession with football and with man's ability to forgive.</p>
        <p>McIngvale -- Mattress Mack, as he is known from his commercials for Gallery Furniture -- watched as Vince Young became a local high school legend, cheered as Young won a national championship for the Texas Longhorns and despaired when it became clear before last year's National Football League draft that the Houston Texans were not quite as smitten with Young as he was.</p>
        <p>It was hard to ignore McIngvale's angst after he took out a two-page ad in The Houston Chronicle, imploring the Texans to select Young. Considering McIngvale's status as a prominent sponsor of the Texans, the message was heard by everyone from Bob McNair, the owner, to Charley Casserly, then the general manager.</p>
        <p>The Texans ultimately decided to pass on Young, and on running back Reggie Bush. Instead, they took defensive end Mario Williams with the first overall pick, which stunned much of the N.F.L. and set off fan fury. And when Young returned to Houston with the Tennessee Titans in December to rip off a 39-yard, game-winning touchdown run in overtime, the Texans' fans -- many wearing Young's college jersey -- cheered him.</p>
        <p>Local pundits viewed that Sunday as the nadir for the franchise. But hope springs eternal, especially in the off-season.</p>
        <p>Casserly left the team before last season and now works for CBS Sports. The Texans hired Rick Smith from Denver as the general manager to reunite him with the team's new coach, Gary Kubiak. Together, they have had a busy off-season: signing running back Ahman Green, giving up on quarterback David Carr and trading for the promising Atlanta backup Matt Schaub.</p>
        <p>For now, the pressure is off the Texans, who will pick 10th when the draft begins April 28. Houston will not pick again until the third round because the team traded its second-round pick for Schaub.</p>
        <p>The invective that was hurled at the Reliant Stadium draft-day party last year has been replaced by quiet optimism.</p>
        <p>''That's water under the bridge,'' McIngvale said in a telephone interview. ''Everybody makes mistakes, and you've got to move on. I wouldn't be surprised if they're 9-7 this year. I think they've got the thing headed in the right direction.''</p>
        <p>That is surely welcome news for McNair, who conceded that he was surprised by how heated and widespread the reaction was to the selection of Williams. McNair answers mail from fans as long as it is signed, so he is attuned to public perception. He said he spent much of last year explaining that the Texans had to get a pass rusher if they were ever going to win a division dominated by Peyton Manning.</p>
        <p>''You have to be disciplined to do what you think is best long term and not be swayed by public cries, who might have different goals,'' McNair said in a telephone interview yesterday. ''I knew what the easy decision would be. I knew it would give us a honeymoon for three years if we would have picked Reggie Bush. But long term, we didn't feel that was in the best interests of the team.''</p>
        <p>Last year was a rare situation, with a glamour-filled draft featuring two Heisman Trophy winners and three national championship players -- Young, Bush and quarterback Matt Leinart. Without that kind of sizzle atop this year's draft class, the early scrutiny has not been as intense as the Oakland Raiders, who hold the first pick, consider their decision.</p>
        <p>Even the draft pundits who were certain the Texans should have taken someone else were not sure whom they should have taken instead. Mike Mayock of the NFL Network said it should have been Bush. Gil Brandt, the former Dallas Cowboys' personnel guru who now works for NFL.com, said Williams over Bush was the right choice because he values pass rushers over running backs. But he said would have gone with Young.</p>
        <p>''We're not sure they messed up last year,'' Brandt said. ''You have different folks doing evaluations, and some like vanilla ice cream and some like strawberry.''</p>
        <p>Lost in the quick-take analysis was that the Texans had a good draft. Williams, despite a foot injury, finished with four and a half sacks. The second-round pick, linebacker DeMeco Ryans, was the N.F.L.'s defensive rookie of the year. Wali Lundy, a rookie running back, started for much of the season.</p>
        <p>In an interview last week, Casserly said he had never been involved in such a closely watched pick and that he would make the same choice again. He said he knew the Texans would be blasted for passing on Bush and Young.</p>
        <p>''Jack Kent Cooke had a line when he would get criticized,'' Casserly said. '' 'It's like being in the rain. Once you've been wet, what's another drop?' ''</p>
        <p>The second-guessing will probably not end until Bush, Young and Williams have retired, and the final analysis can be completed. But McNair said only three people canceled their season tickets last season, and Schaub's arrival drew raves in the local papers.</p>
        <p>As for McIngvale, he still wistfully tells stories of Young returning to Houston and stopping to play ball with children in a park. And he offered a bit of good news for the Texans: ''No newspaper ads from me this year.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
