<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rookie Shows Some Potential; Yankees Show Some Power</title>
    <meta content="18yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/sports/baseball/18yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841240"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Devil Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cleveland Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Cleveland Indians</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Rodriguez, Alex</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EEDB1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="972" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rookie Shows Some Potential; Yankees Show Some Power</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rookie Shows Some Potential; Yankees Show Some Power</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chase Wright's major league debut came on a chilly evening, but his teammates gave him a Yankee Stadium housewarming gift: eight runs in the first two innings last night against the Cleveland Indians. That carried Wright and the Yankees to a 10-3 victory and some intriguing possibilities.</p>
        <p>Might Wright remain to make a second start against the Red Sox in Fenway Park on Sunday night? ''I hope so,'' he said with a smile.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chase Wright’s teammates scored eight runs in the first two innings, as the Yankees beat the Cleveland Indians Tuesday, 10-3.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Chase Wright's major league debut came on a chilly evening, but his teammates gave him a Yankee Stadium housewarming gift: eight runs in the first two innings last night against the Cleveland Indians. That carried Wright and the Yankees to a 10-3 victory and some intriguing possibilities.</p>
        <p>Might Wright remain to make a second start against the Red Sox in Fenway Park on Sunday night? ''I hope so,'' he said with a smile.</p>
        <p>With four starters -- Chien-Ming Wang, Mike Mussina, Carl Pavano and Jeff Karstens -- out with injuries, there certainly are openings in the rotation, at least temporarily.</p>
        <p>''Well, we'll see,'' Manager Joe Torre said of Wright's chances of facing Boston. ''I certainly like what we saw.''</p>
        <p>At the very least, even if Wright returns to Class AA Trenton, the Yankees now know they have in the farm system a 24-year-old left-hander with an impressive changeup and the poise to recover from walking his first two batters in his first inning and bounce back from a one-run deficit.</p>
        <p>Of course, it helped to have Alex Rodriguez, Jorge Posada and Doug Mientkiewicz hitting home runs, as they did off Jake Westbrook (0-2), as they did in a six-run second inning that increased a 2-1 New York lead to 8-1.</p>
        <p>''That kind of settled me down,'' Wright said.</p>
        <p>Posada also settled Wright by telling him to take deep breaths, relax and trust his pitches. Posada said of Wright's changeup: ''He does a lot of things well with it. Great arm speed on it. He sells it well.''</p>
        <p>After the game, Rodriguez said Wright was very relaxed ''for a young guy.''</p>
        <p>The home runs by Rodriguez and Posada -- Posada's was the 200th of his career -- each came with a man on base. Rodriguez has 8 home runs and 21 runs batted in this season. He drove in his first run of the night with a first-inning single to tie the score before a sacrifice fly by Posada gave the Yankees a 2-1 lead.</p>
        <p>But Rodriguez took second billing to Wright, who worked five innings, the minimum for a starter to get a victory. He gave up three earned runs and five hits, one of them a home run to Travis Hafner. Wright struck out three, walked three and threw 61 strikes in 104 pitches.</p>
        <p>Wright's father, David, was in the stands taking pictures, part of an entourage of nine family members and friends.</p>
        <p>Wright said he arrived a day early and went out to the tarp-covered mound to get acquainted. ''You kind of look around, like 'This is amazing,' '' Wright said.</p>
        <p>Wright wore the glove of his longtime friend, Yankee pitcher Sean Henn, who described Wright's mood as excited before the game. ''He had today's paper in his locker,'' Henn said. ''He's a small-town guy.'' The friends are from Texas, Wright from Wichita Falls and Henn from Fort Worth.</p>
        <p>Henn said he gave Wright some pregame advice that proved prescient. ''You don't have to throw a shutout,'' Henn said. ''The lineup we have is going to give us five, six or seven runs.'' The Indians also hurt themselves with three errors. One was a throw by second baseman Josh Barfield that landed several rows behind the first-base dugout.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the wind was to blame. It was gusting from left to right. Along with the lopsided score, it encouraged the early departure of the crowd, which looked smaller than the announced 38,438.</p>
        <p>Some aspects of the Yankees' unsettled rotation are encouraging. Torre did not guarantee that Jeff Karstens would pitch on Saturday afternoon against the Red Sox but hinted strongly in that direction.</p>
        <p>When asked about Karstens, the 24-year-old right-hander who started the season on the disabled list with elbow stiffness, Torre said, ''Karstens is definitely a possibility.''</p>
        <p>Karstens threw four shutout innings Monday for Class A Tampa, allowing three hits and one walk while striking out five. Last season, Karstens went 2-1 for the Yankees in six starts with an earned run average of 3.80.</p>
        <p>''We really haven't totally made up our mind yet,'' Torre said about using Karstens. He said there would probably be ''some kind of announcement'' today. Mussina has a strained left hamstring, Pavano a sore forearm and Wang a strained right hamstring. Tonight's Yankee starter is the left-hander Kei Igawa. Tomorrow afternoon, the right-hander Darrell Rasner will pitch.</p>
        <p>Andy Pettitte will start in Fenway Park on Friday night. Wang might pitch for the Yankees on Tuesday when they visit the Devil Rays.</p>
        <p>''We're starting to get healthy,'' Torre said. Should Wang complete tomorrow's assignment without further injury, he could pitch for the Yankees on Tuesday when they visit the Tampa Bay Devil Rays.</p>
        <p>Mussina can return from the disabled list when the Yankees begin a series at home against the Red Sox on April 27.</p>
        <p>Pavano can return on April 25 against Toronto. He said yesterday that he did not have a magnetic resonance imaging exam on the arm but that it was treated by team trainers. ''Just try to get the muscles to relax and get the inflammation out of there and move forward,'' Pavano said.</p>
        <p>When asked whether his condition has moved forward, Pavano replied ''Yeah, definitely,'' but could not predict a date of return. ''We haven't really talked about that yet,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Pavano, who missed last season with a variety of injuries, is 1-0 in two starts this season.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Left fielder Hideki Matsui, who is on the disabled list with a left hamstring strain, should play Friday night for Class A Tampa, Manager Joe Torre said. Matsui could rejoin the Yankees next week when they play the Devil Rays.  Before the game, the Yankees dedicated a memorial in Monument Park to Jackie Robinson, the former Brooklyn Dodgers star. The Yankees also painted Robinson's No. 42 along the baselines.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
