<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Tour of Muslim-Americans' America</title>
    <meta content="18heff" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/arts/television/18heff.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841104"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Muslim-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Public Broadcasting Service</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E4DE1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="703" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Tour of Muslim-Americans' America</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Tour of Muslim-Americans’ America</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIRGINIA HEFFERNAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Heffernan, Virginia</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''The Muslim Americans,'' the seventh entry in ''America at a Crossroads,'' PBS's omnibus series about the post-9/11 world, ought to have been spellbinding. Just five and a half years ago, the one American Muslim who could reliably be recruited to stand for Islam in the United States was Muhammad Ali, an athlete and a convert who had lost most of his eloquence on the subject. That was pathetic. Plenty of attention has been paid to Irish-Americans, Jewish Americans, Italian-Americans and African-Americans. ''The Muslim Americans'' could have been really powerful.</p>
        <p>The program might have told about the form of Islam that crossed the Atlantic, first with slaves at the start of the republic and then with immigrants in the 19th century. It might have traced the fate of the Arabic language and Koranic learning in the United States in slavery days. And it might have explored the reasons immigrant adherents chose to settle where they did: surprising places like Dearborn, Mich., and Cedar Rapids, Iowa.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The seventh entry in PBS’s series about the post-9/11 world makes a rather dull documentary out of the complex warp of Islamic life in the U.S.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''The Muslim Americans,'' the seventh entry in ''America at a Crossroads,'' PBS's omnibus series about the post-9/11 world, ought to have been spellbinding. Just five and a half years ago, the one American Muslim who could reliably be recruited to stand for Islam in the United States was Muhammad Ali, an athlete and a convert who had lost most of his eloquence on the subject. That was pathetic. Plenty of attention has been paid to Irish-Americans, Jewish Americans, Italian-Americans and African-Americans. ''The Muslim Americans'' could have been really powerful.</p>
        <p>The program might have told about the form of Islam that crossed the Atlantic, first with slaves at the start of the republic and then with immigrants in the 19th century. It might have traced the fate of the Arabic language and Koranic learning in the United States in slavery days. And it might have explored the reasons immigrant adherents chose to settle where they did: surprising places like Dearborn, Mich., and Cedar Rapids, Iowa.</p>
        <p>''Muslims in America'' might have illuminated the ways Islam survived among slaves, to the extent that it did, and how sharia -- Islamic law -- informed business practices and everyday life in Muslim communities. It might have taken viewers inside madrassas and mosques. It might have considered what America's vaunted ''religious freedom'' meant and means to Muslims, who now outnumber Episcopalians in the United States.</p>
        <p>It might have discussed the split between Shia and Sunni here, and explored the Nation of Islam. Muslims on the program might have been asked their impressions of American Christianity and Judaism, and not just secular culture, which PBS, as usual, glancingly presents as virtually co-extensive with sex and drugs.</p>
        <p>(A rousing exception is the monologue by Ayman Amer, a Muslim in Cedar Rapids, on the subject of inalienable rights. As he says: ''Nobody can take these rights from you! This is not a gift from the government. This is not a gift from the president. No! It says 'endowed by the Creator'!'')</p>
        <p>But had ''The Muslim Americans'' put on display the complex warp and woof of Islamic life in the United States, it would not have been the public-service announcement that PBS, along with ''The NewsHour with Jim Lehrer,'' was determined to produce. What the network offers here instead of a documentary is little more than a handful of case studies in hate crimes and racism and a few ''see, we're all cool'' profiles, as well as another hagiography of Hamza Yusuf, an Islamic scholar based in California who briefly advised President Bush.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yusuf, who is an imam, converted to Islam from Greek Orthodox Christianity. Now, using what the broadcast describes -- while panning over the paraphernalia, infomercial-style -- as ''dozens of books, tapes, CDs, podcasts and YouTube videos,'' he preaches a version of American Islam that is peaceful, tolerant and exceptionally congenial to the American media.</p>
        <p>Women of preternatural beauty are shown in hijab alongside minivans. The Muslim men are described, at one point, as mostly doctors and lawyers. Even one who was falsely singled out by the F.B.I. -- he had the same name as someone on their watch list -- doesn't seem that bothered by the experience. Everyone appears to love our big, warm, happy melting pot. They simply want to worship discreetly and get back to business. Perfect Americans.</p>
        <p>That's fine, as far as it goes. But it makes a rather dull and not especially enlightening documentary. Does not one Muslim here think the nudity on American beaches is appalling? Or that Muslim girls shouldn't date Christian boys? Or that jihad contains an element of violence? Or that the war in Iraq is unjustified? Or that 9/11 was (in the words of some Brooklyn graffiti) ''an inside job''? Come on. Are Muslims really that much more measured and evenhanded than everyone else?</p>
        <p>Finally, ''Muslims in America'' is misleading: it is not a requirement of citizenship in the United States that one be good-natured, assimilated, patriotic, discreet or even a doctor or a lawyer. That is only a requirement for inclusion in a PBS documentary.</p>
        <p>America at a Crossroads  The Muslim Americans  On most PBS stations tonight (check local listings).</p>
        <p>Susan Mills for MacNeil/Lehrer Productions, executive producer; Ricki Green, producer.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
