<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>They Spar Over Politics, But Are Far From Foes</title>
    <meta content="18diaz" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841187"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diaz, Ruben Sr (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diaz, Ruben Jr (Assemblyman)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hicks, Jonathan P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEEDC1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1082" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>They Spar Over Politics, But Are Far From Foes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN P. HICKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hicks, Jonathan P</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Bureau of Investigation is reportedly conducting corruption investigation of State Sen Ruben Diaz and his son, Assemblyman Ruben Diaz Jr, who are among best-known Democratic legislators in Bronx; father and son say they have not been contacted by any investigators but say they will cooperate in any way possible; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The father is a decidedly conservative Pentecostal minister who opposes abortion and same-sex marriage and often endorses Republicans. The son is an unabashed liberal who favors abortion rights and frequently aligns himself with the Rev. Al Sharpton. When they appear together on radio programs, they spar like combatants on CNN's ''Crossfire.''</p>
        <p>Even in New York, where political families are anything but uncommon, State Senator Rubén Díaz Sr. and his son, Assemblyman Rubén Díaz Jr., stand out. They are among the best-known legislators in the Bronx, where they have built a formidable political organization that has won them election after election.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The father is a decidedly conservative Pentecostal minister who opposes abortion and same-sex marriage and often endorses Republicans. The son is an unabashed liberal who favors abortion rights and frequently aligns himself with the Rev. Al Sharpton. When they appear together on radio programs, they spar like combatants on CNN's ''Crossfire.''</p>
        <p>Even in New York, where political families are anything but uncommon, State Senator Rubén Díaz Sr. and his son, Assemblyman Rubén Díaz Jr., stand out. They are among the best-known legislators in the Bronx, where they have built a formidable political organization that has won them election after election.</p>
        <p>But lately, father and son have been the subject of other attention. Last month, the Federal Bureau of Investigation was looking into allegations of corruption against the two. The inquiry was confirmed by an official familiar with the investigation who spoke on the condition of anonymity.</p>
        <p>F.B.I. agents visited the Board of Elections in the Bronx and obtained copies of the Díazes' candidate petitions and their personal voter registration and voter history records, a Board of Elections spokeswoman said.</p>
        <p>The focus of the investigation is unclear, since F.B.I. officials would not speak about nor offer any confirmation regarding the investigation. In an interview last week, both father and son said they have not been contacted by any investigators and have no idea what the agents are seeking. But both said they would cooperate in any way possible.</p>
        <p>In the Bronx, there have been a number of political families in recent years: the Riveras, the Arroyos, the Fosters and the Espadas. But in none are the differences in political philosophy as stark.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people think that when you elect people who are from the same family, you're getting some kind of carbon copies of political philosophy,'' said Assemblyman Carl E. Heastie, a Bronx Democrat who is close to the Díazes. ''But with this father and son, you're getting nothing like that at all. And that's refreshing, and it makes people pay attention to them.''</p>
        <p>For example, in 1997, the elder Mr. Díaz supported the re-election of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, a Republican, while his son endorsed a Democrat, Ruth W. Messinger. In 2000, the son endorsed Hillary Rodham Clinton for the United States Senate, while the father supported Rick A. Lazio, the Republican candidate.</p>
        <p>''My father sometimes jokes with me and calls me a radical,'' Assemblyman Díaz, 33, said.</p>
        <p>The father, 63, replied, ''My son thinks I'm too old-fashioned.''</p>
        <p>Unlike most parent-and-child elected officials, the Díazes are unusual in that Assemblyman Díaz, who was elected in 1996, took office before his father. Senator Díaz was elected to the City Council five years later, and then to the State Senate in 2002.</p>
        <p>Both men say they engage in fierce debate regularly, particularly in their private conversations. Indeed, during another interview over breakfast in the Bronx, the two often interrupted each other with scolding voices.</p>
        <p>''The Democratic Party is the party of abortion,'' Senator Díaz said. ''They say they are pro-choice. But the only choice there is is when a man and woman decide to go to bed and she gets pregnant.''</p>
        <p>To which Assemblyman Díaz interjected fiercely: ''How can you even say something like that? You're being ridiculous.''</p>
        <p>Despite their differences, father and son are close, speaking with each other by telephone three to five times a day, by their own account. (Even their birthdays are close: Senator Díaz turns 64 on Sunday, and Assemblyman Díaz turns 34 on April 26.) Senator Díaz is widely viewed as a shoot-from-the-hip politician who often irritates fellow Senate Democrats for what they call his lack of diplomacy.</p>
        <p>''There have been occasions when I had to reach out to Rubén Jr. to help with political problems we were having in the Democratic conference with Rubén Sr.,'' said State Senator Eric T. Schneiderman, recalling his days as the floor leader for the Senate Democrats.</p>
        <p>''They are tremendously close, and Rubén Sr. listens to his son,'' Mr. Schneiderman said.</p>
        <p>Senator Díaz has been involved in controversy before. When Gov. Eliot Spitzer was attorney general, he found that Mr. Díaz had improperly spent almost $5,000 in government grants intended for a Bronx nonprofit group on furniture for his district office and loudspeakers for his campaign. The elder Mr. Díaz said all of the money had been repaid, and he described the case as a misunderstanding.</p>
        <p>Three years ago, an ally of one of the Díazes' longtime political rivals, former State Senator Pedro Espada Jr., accused Senator Díaz of not living in the Bronx district that he represents and sued him in federal court. Senator Díaz said the suit had no merit. The case was later dismissed by a judge who said it belonged in state court.</p>
        <p>His son, meanwhile, is widely considered to have a bright political future -- despite the F.B.I. investigation. He is considering running for Bronx borough president in 2009, when the incumbent, Adolfo Carrión Jr., is barred by term limits from seeking re-election. (That is a race that could well place him in direct rivalry with another young Bronx official: City Councilman Joel Rivera, who is the son of Jose Rivera, an assemblyman and the Bronx Democratic leader.)</p>
        <p>Assemblyman Díaz is known for highly regarded constituent services through his Bronx office, which is almost always filled with residents seeking help for everything from getting answers from government agencies and utility companies to job-placement assistance.</p>
        <p>In fact, more than most state legislators, Assemblyman Díaz is widely recognized and greeted when he walks the streets of his district, which includes the Soundview and Hunts Point sections of the Bronx.</p>
        <p>He became particularly well known for his outspoken and visible role in condemning the 1999 shooting of Amadou Diallo, who was killed in a barrage of 41 bullets fired by four New York City police officers.</p>
        <p>With regard to the F.B.I. investigation, many Bronx officials say that if no charges are filed against the Díazes, or if they are not convicted of any wrongdoing, it will have little impact on Assemblyman Díaz's political career.</p>
        <p>Senator Díaz, meanwhile, said in an interview that he had no plans to run for any position other than his Senate seat.</p>
        <p>''The fact of the matter is that it might not hurt them at all,'' Mr. Sharpton said. ''Sometimes, in communities of color, attacks from law enforcement backfire. When you're under attack, it gives your supporters a chance to rally around you, especially when the attacks seem unfair or unwarranted.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
