<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Officials Seek Solace In Business Of the State</title>
    <meta content="18chatter" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/nyregion/18chatter.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841218"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kolluri, Kris (Comr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smothers, Ronald</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2DB1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="824" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Officials Seek Solace In Business Of the State</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Officials Seek Solace in Business of the State</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smothers, Ronald</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, April 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey polticians and officials quietly go about business of running state under pall of Gov Jon S Corzine's near-fatal car accident on April 12; Kris Kolluri, state transportation commissioner, says they cannot help him but they can do what he expects them to do (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It seemed a natural and human inclination to Darrell Bethea, the owner of Sweet Heaven, the snack shop and newsstand in the basement of the State House, to consider getting a get-well card for Gov. Jon S. Corzine.</p>
        <p>''The man is human and he's hurt,'' said Mr. Bethea, who has operated the snack shop for eight years. ''I was thinking of doing it for us, the little people in the building, to sign, you know, the rest of the crew of this ship.'' But Mr. Bethea was quietly discouraged from making the gesture by those who suggested to him that the governor's people would take care of such things.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>TRENTON, April 17  It seemed a natural and human inclination to Darrell Bethea, the owner of Sweet Heaven, the snack shop and newsstand in the basement of the State House, to consider getting a get-well card for Gov. Jon S. Corzine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It seemed a natural and human inclination to Darrell Bethea, the owner of Sweet Heaven, the snack shop and newsstand in the basement of the State House, to consider getting a get-well card for Gov. Jon S. Corzine.</p>
        <p>''The man is human and he's hurt,'' said Mr. Bethea, who has operated the snack shop for eight years. ''I was thinking of doing it for us, the little people in the building, to sign, you know, the rest of the crew of this ship.'' But Mr. Bethea was quietly discouraged from making the gesture by those who suggested to him that the governor's people would take care of such things.</p>
        <p>It was not that such natural fellow feeling has no place in the Capitol, a layered world where those at the center of power are fairly insulated. There nevertheless has been a pall -- all but wordless to outsiders -- enveloping the building since Friday morning, after word spread that the governor was in critical condition with multiple fractures from a punishing traffic accident near Atlantic City.</p>
        <p>Kris Kolluri, the state transportation commissioner, who was in the midst of dealing with a storm that had pummeled New Jersey over the weekend, put it this way: ''It is cathartic to be calm and levelheaded in thinking through problems because we know we can't help him much where he is. But we can do what he expects us to do.''</p>
        <p>After the state police said on Tuesday that the governor's vehicle was going 91 miles per hour when the accident occurred, the news was fodder for some shrill reactions from callers to at least one afternoon radio talk show. But to some around the Capitol, speed seemed irrelevant to the way people felt.</p>
        <p>''We are not anywhere close to the time when we can be thinking about anything but the governor's health,'' said Thomas G. Dallessio, executive director of Leadership New Jersey, a nonprofit organization that trains civic leaders.</p>
        <p>For some others here, lurking in the back of their minds was a sense of the snakebit nature of state politics in recent years, from the indictments of legislators to the broken bones of governors and even the resignation of James E. McGreevey midway through his term after admitting to an extramarital affair with a male aide.</p>
        <p>Yet Governor Corzine's perilous accident, which has left him in critical condition in a Camden hospital, has added a human face and a real sense of mortality.</p>
        <p>''You had a sense of things getting back to normal with Corzine in there,'' said Jeff Tittel, the head of the New Jersey chapter of the Sierra Club, who can regularly be found working the State House hallways. ''Now there is a kind of wondering about what will happen next.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Tittel, along with many others, greeted the news of the governor's injuries -- at first it was thought he suffered only a broken leg -- with a lighthearted shrug and a joke that perhaps it was a requirement for the governor of New Jersey. After all, he said, Christie Whitman broke her leg in a skiing accident, and Mr. McGreevey broke his leg on the beach in Cape May.</p>
        <p>''But as we got more information,'' Mr. Tittel said, ''it dawned on everybody how serious this was for him, and the shock has been a sort of delayed reaction.''</p>
        <p>Assemblyman Bill Baroni, a Republican from Mercer County, who recalled his own broken femur 17 years ago, said, ''We have to take the coarseness and angst out of the discussion of issues because we are all in this together.''</p>
        <p>That seemed to be the prevailing feeling among the powerful and the not-so-powerful. Yet there was still room for some other raw feelings more common in the political arena.</p>
        <p>For instance, Mr. Corzine's staff was pleased to hear the acting governor, Richard J. Codey, declare at a news conference on Friday that he had no intention of moving into the governor's office and would perform his duties in his Senate office. But legislators close to the administration said that there was some ''outrage'' and a sense of betrayal on Monday when Mr. Codey took part in a television interview about the weekend storm from the governor's office.</p>
        <p>Where protocol and prerogatives are both the symbol and substance of power, this was no small matter.</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Codey said that he had arranged to be interviewed in his Senate office, but the reporter arrived just as he was finishing a briefing with Mr. Corzine's staff. So he called the reporter to the governor's office because that was where he happened to be at the time.</p>
        <p>He said he had heard second-hand that some of the staff members were upset, and brought it up at a meeting with them Tuesday morning to clear the air.</p>
        <p>''It is tough for them because Jon is their guy,'' Mr. Codey said, ''and I understand that, and I am not Jon.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
