<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rebuilt Cubs Start the Season By Putting Up a For-Sale Sign</title>
    <meta content="03cubs" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837708"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4DD1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="833" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rebuilt Cubs Start the Season By Putting Up a For-Sale Sign</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN SCHWARZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schwarz, Alan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Chicago Cubs' 2007 marketing slogan exclaims, ''Play Like There's No Tomorrow!'' That will be literally true this season for the Tribune Company, which announced yesterday that it would sell the Cubs, its storied subsidiary, later this year as part of the company's overall sale to the Chicago billionaire Sam Zell.</p>
        <p>The company did not reveal any prospective ownership groups, only that it planned to complete the transaction after the 2007 season. The end of the season usually comes before the October playoffs for the Cubs, who have not won a World Series since 1908 or participated in one since 1945.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Chicago Cubs' 2007 marketing slogan exclaims, ''Play Like There's No Tomorrow!'' That will be literally true this season for the Tribune Company, which announced yesterday that it would sell the Cubs, its storied subsidiary, later this year as part of the company's overall sale to the Chicago billionaire Sam Zell.</p>
        <p>The company did not reveal any prospective ownership groups, only that it planned to complete the transaction after the 2007 season. The end of the season usually comes before the October playoffs for the Cubs, who have not won a World Series since 1908 or participated in one since 1945.</p>
        <p>''The Cubs are a great franchise -- great history, great tradition,'' Major League Baseball's commissioner, Bud Selig, told reporters in Chicago, where he was attending the White Sox' opener against Cleveland. ''I'm not going to speculate on price.''</p>
        <p>All club sales are subject to the approval of Major League Baseball's other 29 owners, which typically lengthens the process to 6 to 12 months.</p>
        <p>On Forbes magazine's 2006 assessment of franchise values, the Cubs ranked fifth among baseball's 30 clubs at $448 million, with revenue of $179 million and a $7.9 million operating profit. (The team had been valued at $247 million in 2001, representing 12 percent annual growth.)</p>
        <p>With baseball's booming overall business, in part because of labor peace and successful international and Internet ventures, the Cubs are expected to fetch $600 million or more. In 2002, the Boston Red Sox were sold for a league-record $660 million to a group led by John Henry.</p>
        <p>Soon after Tribune's announcement Monday, several names emerged as possible candidates to buy the team, including Mark Cuban, who owns the Dallas Mavericks, and Jerry Colangelo, the chairman of the Phoenix Suns. Colangelo, the former owner of the Arizona Diamondbacks, told The Associated Press in November that he would be interested in buying the Cubs if they became available.</p>
        <p>The announcement of the pending sale comes at what is already a turning point in the franchise's history, which dates to the founding of the National League in 1876.</p>
        <p>The Cubs finished with the National League's worst record (66-96) last season, then fired their manager, Dusty Baker. The team then embarked on an off-season spending spree, committing almost $300 million in contracts to the slugger Alfonso Soriano ($136 million over eight years), third baseman Aramis Ramírez ($75 million over five years) and the left-hander Ted Lilly ($40 million over four years), among others, in its biggest push ever to buy its way back into contention.</p>
        <p>The Cubs have enjoyed only fleeting success in their 26 seasons under Tribune ownership, posting a .478 winning percentage and reaching the playoffs only four times. There has been considerable local dissatisfaction over how the team payroll did not appear to measure up to the size of its home market or its corporate owner's wherewithal -- until this winter.</p>
        <p>''The Tribune is going to run the team this year, and I've been assured that we're going to run it the way that we planned on all off-season and all spring training,'' Jim Hendry, the team's general manager, said in a telephone interview Monday, minutes before his team took the field for its opening day game at Cincinnati. The Cubs lost to the Reds, 5-1.</p>
        <p>Tribune has overseen a renaissance at the team's landmark ballpark, Wrigley Field. Lights were finally installed in the nearly century-old stadium in 1988, opening the possibility for night games, and both luxury and bleacher seats were added. With a historic ballpark that in some ways has become more of a draw than the team that plays in it, the Cubs attracted more than 3 million fans in 2004. Annual attendance has not dropped below that total since.</p>
        <p>''While they didn't get to the World Series, which is how most people measure a team, they did a tremendous job and the fans should be thankful for their stewardship of Wrigley Field,'' Andy MacPhail, the team's president and chief executive from 1994 until his resignation last October, said of Tribune's ownership in a telephone interview. ''They did a marvelous job in that area.''</p>
        <p>Tribune purchased the Cubs in June 1981 for $20.5 million from William Wrigley, whose family -- known also for its chewing gum -- owned the team for three generations, since 1916.</p>
        <p>Tribune's simultaneous ownership of the Cubs and the cable superstation WGN, a synergy similar to that of Ted Turner's Atlanta Braves and WTBS, was a source of immediate tension in baseball because the team's games could be broadcast into other teams' home markets. It also preceded an era in which media companies sought major league teams to leverage the content across various platforms, particularly television.</p>
        <p>With Tribune's impending sale of the Cubs, that era appears to be waning. The Disney Company sold the Angels in 2003, and a year later Rupert Murdoch's News Corporation unloaded the Dodgers. The Braves are in the process of being sold to Liberty Media by AOL Time-Warner, which acquired the team from Turner.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
