<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Verdict Backing Oil-Royalty Whistle-Blower Is Overturned</title>
    <meta content="03royalty" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/business/03royalty.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837742"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Whistle-Blowers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Royalties</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Interior Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kerr-Mcgee Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrews, Edmund L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maxwell, Bobby L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Figa, Phillip S (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Interior Department</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Kerr-McGee Corp</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E7DC1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="663" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Verdict Backing Oil-Royalty Whistle-Blower Is Overturned</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Verdict Backing Oil-Royalty Whistle-Blower Is Overturned</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Andrews, Edmund L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Judge Phillip S Figa overturns jury's verdict in favor of whistle-blower Bobby L Maxwell at Interior Department who charged that Kerr-McGee Corp cheated government out of millions for oil and gas it pumped in publicly owned coastal waters; rules that Maxwell is not eligible to sue Kerr-McGee as private citizen because he gathered most of his evidence while on job; Figa does not question jury's verdict nor does he dispute that Maxwell filed his lawsuit as private citizen after senior Interior Department officials ordered him to abandon his findings; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A federal judge in Denver has overturned a jury's verdict in favor of a whistle-blower at the Interior Department who charged that the Kerr-McGee Corporation cheated the government out of millions of dollars for oil and gas it pumped in publicly owned coastal waters.</p>
        <p>In a ruling that could have big implications for whistle-blowers, as well as for the oil and gas industry, the judge ruled that the former Interior Department auditor was not eligible to sue Kerr-McGee as a private citizen because he had gathered most of his evidence while on the job.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A federal judge overturned a verdict in favor of a whistle-blower at the Interior Department who charged that the Kerr-McGee Corporation cheated the government out of millions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A federal judge in Denver has overturned a jury's verdict in favor of a whistle-blower at the Interior Department who charged that the Kerr-McGee Corporation cheated the government out of millions of dollars for oil and gas it pumped in publicly owned coastal waters.</p>
        <p>In a ruling that could have big implications for whistle-blowers, as well as for the oil and gas industry, the judge ruled that the former Interior Department auditor was not eligible to sue Kerr-McGee as a private citizen because he had gathered most of his evidence while on the job.</p>
        <p>The judge did not question the jury's verdict that the auditor, Bobby L. Maxwell, had uncovered cheating by Kerr-McGee. Nor did the judge dispute that Mr. Maxwell had filed his lawsuit as a private citizen after senior Interior Department officials in Washington ordered him to abandon his findings.</p>
        <p>Rather, the judge said Mr. Maxwell failed a crucial technical requirement for seeking to recover money under the False Claims Act, a law that encourages private whistle-blowers to help recover money from companies that cheat the government.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maxwell is expected to appeal, and many industry experts expect both sides to fight the case to the Supreme Court. The issue has been closely watched by the big oil companies. Many of them warned an appellate court last year that Mr. Maxwell would ''open the floodgates'' to litigation if he were allowed to proceed.</p>
        <p>Indeed, three other federal auditors in Oklahoma City have filed similar fraud lawsuits against more than a dozen oil companies; those auditors also say that they were ordered by superiors to stop making their accusations.</p>
        <p>After a one-week trial in January, a federal jury in Denver agreed with Mr. Maxwell that Kerr-McGee had cheated the government out of about $7.5 million in royalties on oil that it had been pumping on federal leases in the Gulf of Mexico.</p>
        <p>Under the False Claims Act, Kerr-McGee could have been forced to repay more than $30 million, and Mr. Maxwell would have been entitled to as much as 30 percent.</p>
        <p>But the judge who presided over the trial, Phillip S. Figa, dismissed the verdict on Friday, saying that he had re-evaluated the question about Mr. Maxwell's eligibility to invoke the law.</p>
        <p>Judge Figa ruled that the False Claims Act requires that a person first ''voluntarily disclose'' any evidence of fraud to the government before filing a lawsuit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maxwell presented his evidence of fraud in 2002, and the judge noted that his supervisor in Denver agreed in principle that Kerr-McGee had probably violated the law. But senior lawyers for the Interior Department in Washington said they did not want to proceed, and ordered Mr. Maxwell to retreat.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maxwell, who filed his own lawsuit as a private citizen in 2004, was fired one week after the suit became public.</p>
        <p>In a series of rulings before the trial began, Judge Figa repeatedly rejected Kerr-McGee's arguments that Mr. Maxwell was disqualified from suing because of his work as a federal investigator.</p>
        <p>But in his decision last week, the judge said he had changed his mind because of arguments that Kerr-McGee raised during and after the trial.</p>
        <p>''The court concludes that a re-evaluation of its prior holding,'' Judge Figa wrote, ''is appropriate.''</p>
        <p>Specifically, he ruled that Mr. Maxwell could not meet the requirement to ''voluntarily disclose'' his evidence before filing suit because he had been obligated by the rules of his work to provide the evidence.</p>
        <p>''Once involuntarily disclosed, the same information cannot subsequently be voluntarily disclosed within the meaning of the False Claims Act,'' Judge Figa ruled.</p>
        <p>The judge emphasized that his ruling had no bearing on the question of Kerr-McGee's reported fraud, and he noted evidence that Mr. Maxwell's supervisor in Denver, John Russo, had agreed that Kerr-McGee probably was guilty of fraud.</p>
        <p>Interior officials, who have repeatedly accused Mr. Maxwell and other auditors of violating procedures by going outside the department, refused to comment on the decision.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
