<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Tribune Buyer, a Storm to the West</title>
    <meta content="03paper" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/business/media/03paper.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837767"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="A NEWSPAPER SHAKE-UP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tribune Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Times</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zell, Samuel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holson, Laura M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Waxman, Sharon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Geffen, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burkle, Ronald W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broad, Eli</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Los Angeles Times</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Tribune Company</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Zell, Samuel</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07EEDC1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1462" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Tribune Buyer, a Storm to the West</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Tribune Buyer, a Storm to the West</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURA M. HOLSON and SHARON WAXMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Waxman, Sharon; Holson, Laura M</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, April 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Los Angeles Times was nothing but trouble for Tribune Co, and it may prove even more of challenge for new owner Samuel Zell; there has been culture clash between Chicago-based owners at Tribune and Los Angeles Times; schism seems to have helped fuel things like public criticism that paper is out of touch and recent battles in newsroom that have led to high-profile resignations; tension has been particularly pronounced throughout deal-making process, which pitted Chicago resident Zell against pair of Los Angeles businessmen Ronald W Burkle and Eli Broad; also in running has been Hollywood mogul David Geffen, who reaffirms his interest in either acquiring Los Angeles Times outright or buying stake in it and running it; backdrop of wounded civic pride is only one factor that provoked cries of dismay from newsroom and community at news Zell prevailed; there is also fact that Zell has no interest in taking corporate reins at critical time of declining circulation; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Los Angeles Times was nothing but trouble for the Tribune Company, and it may prove even more of a challenge for its new owner, Samuel Zell.</p>
        <p>Ever since the Tribune Company bought the Times Mirror Company in 2000 -- and, with it The Los Angeles Times -- there has been a culture clash between the Chicago-based owners at Tribune and its marquee California newspaper. The schism seems to have helped fuel things like the public criticism that the paper is out of touch and the recent battles in the newsroom that have led to high-profile resignations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Los Angeles Times, a problem for Tribune, may be even more of a challenge for its new owner, Samuel Zell.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Los Angeles Times was nothing but trouble for the Tribune Company, and it may prove even more of a challenge for its new owner, Samuel Zell.</p>
        <p>Ever since the Tribune Company bought the Times Mirror Company in 2000 -- and, with it The Los Angeles Times -- there has been a culture clash between the Chicago-based owners at Tribune and its marquee California newspaper. The schism seems to have helped fuel things like the public criticism that the paper is out of touch and the recent battles in the newsroom that have led to high-profile resignations.</p>
        <p>The tension has been particularly pronounced throughout the deal-making process, which pitted Mr. Zell, a Chicago resident, against a pair of Los Angeles businessmen, Ronald W. Burkle and Eli Broad. Also in the running was a Hollywood mogul, David Geffen, who yesterday reaffirmed his interest in either acquiring The Los Angeles Times outright or buying a stake in it and running it.</p>
        <p>But the backdrop of wounded civic pride was only one factor that provoked cries of dismay from the newsroom and the community yesterday at the news that Mr. Zell had prevailed. There was also the fact that Mr. Zell has stated that he has no interest in newspapers, and that he is taking the corporate reins at a critical time of declining circulation.</p>
        <p>''It's scary,'' said Nick Goldberg, editor of the paper's Op-ed page. ''The problem is, as of right now we know nothing about the guy. He hasn't expressed any real philosophy about the company, to my knowledge, or any indication of what he plans to do. We're just sitting here waiting to hear.''</p>
        <p>At the newspaper's headquarters on Spring Street, the newsroom ground to a halt Monday morning as several hundred members of the staff attended a videoconference by the Tribune Company chairman, Dennis J. FitzSimons, who has been the focus of much of the tension between Los Angeles and Chicago.</p>
        <p>Mr. FitzSimons explained details of the deal with Mr. Zell, which involves a complex component of employee ownership, and fielded questions. But he did not have an answer to a question about Mr. Zell's vision for the company, and Mr. Zell did not speak at the event.</p>
        <p>At the meeting, David Hiller, the publisher of The Los Angeles Times, depicted the change in ownership as a positive step, suggesting that the company, which will become privately owned, would be under less pressure to produce short-term profits.</p>
        <p>''You can plan for the next five years, rather than the next five months,'' Mr. Hiller said at the meeting, according to people who were there. But he also said that the newspaper was going ahead with planned staff reductions, which are expected to cut $7.5 million in costs but have served as a flashpoint for controversy in the newsroom.</p>
        <p>Like most major newspapers, The Los Angeles Times has been losing circulation. The last figures by the Audit Bureau of Circulation, in late October, showed that The Times had lost 8 percent of its daily circulation -- down to 776,000 subscribers -- and 6 percent on Sunday, down to 1.17 million subscribers. The decreases were higher than the national average of 2.8 percent.</p>
        <p>The paper's editor, James O'Shea, said in an interview Monday that he believed the drop had flattened by the end of 2006. He added that the paper's online readership was growing rapidly, though he could not cite specific figures.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Shea put a positive gloss on the news, saying that he believed Mr. Zell would allow the paper to continue to function as before, and that he did not put much stock in the speculation that Mr. Zell might immediately turn around and sell The Times to Mr. Geffen or another suitor.</p>
        <p>''I can't sit here and tell you that Sam Zell has called to say 'Don't worry about a thing,' but I don't see that it would make much sense to sell the L.A. Times,'' Mr. O'Shea said. ''From what I understand, the way Mr. Zell thinks about the future of newspapers and the Internet, this would be a key element of his ownership.''</p>
        <p>Media analysts said that the way Mr. Zell's deal is structured, it would make little sense financially to sell The Times soon, because the tax bill would eat up about 40 percent of the sale price. They said a proposal by Mr. Geffen, the entertainment executive, to pay $2 billion for the paper would probably be insufficient for that reason.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Geffen said he still held out hope -- and his offer. ''So far, there is no response,'' he said. ''The Los Angeles Times needs someone willing to invest, and more cuts at the newspaper will damage it.''</p>
        <p>The leadership of the Tribune Company has had hostile relations with The Los Angeles Times for some time, while the paper has endured one crisis after another. Both the publisher Jeffrey M. Johnson and the editor Dean Baquet were forced out late last year after they refused to submit to yet another round of staff reductions meant to increase the bottom line. Mr. Baquet has since rejoined The New York Times, where he is the Washington bureau chief and an assistant managing editor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hiller was sent from Chicago to try to bring the newsroom in line, but he has largely been perceived as a tool of the corporate leadership, rather than a bridge to the newsroom.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Shea, who arrived as Mr. Baquet's replacement from Chicago, has fared better, recently winning the support of the staff in the latest crisis to rock the newsroom, over the publishing of a guest opinion section last month. That dispute, over whether a publicist had unfairly influenced the decision to invite the Hollywood producer Brian Grazer to be a guest editor, ended in a public relations black eye for the paper, with the indignant resignation of the editorial page editor, Andrés Martinez, who accused Mr. Hiller of undermining him.</p>
        <p>Outside the newsroom, some community leaders said they were disheartened that Mr. Zell was the winner because he seemed uninterested in the paper's future. ''We've been through several editors and publishers,'' said Jack Kyser, the chief economist at the Los Angeles County Economic Development Corporation. ''Does he do further cuts at the newspaper? Will there be a new editor and publisher? If I had my druthers, I'd rather have Broad and Burkle.''</p>
        <p>Still others expressed concern for the newspaper's future and whether Mr. Zell had the wherewithal to bring a sense of calm and stability to a newsroom in turmoil once an acquisition is completed.</p>
        <p>''There is fear of another shoe about to drop,'' said Marty Kaplan, who holds the Norman Lear chair in entertainment, media and society at University of Southern California's Annenberg School of Journalism. ''The fear is that they will be squeezed hard, especially when Zell looks at the company's debt. There is all kinds of talk that he might let The Times go. Why have a distant and unruly outpost in his empire?''</p>
        <p>Richard Riordan, the former Los Angeles mayor who is a good friend of Mr. Broad, said he would have preferred to see Mr. Broad and Mr. Burkle prevail because they care about the community and the newspaper, in particular.</p>
        <p>''What do you do when you have to point out to someone that there is no uptown in Los Angeles and the Valley isn't a place you go camping?'' said Mr. Riordan. ''We want someone that will love L.A. Knowing Sam Zell, he might sell off the pieces.''</p>
        <p>Readers who submitted comments to The Times's Web site also expressed some sentiments that bordered on xenophobia. A sample: ''Sam, zell the L.A. Times and get out of town.''</p>
        <p>Steve Lopez, a columnist for The Times, expressed his disappointment in an article publishedMonday that the ''local boys'' -- the billionaires Mr. Burkle and Mr. Broad -- had been beaten.</p>
        <p>He wrote that Mr. Zell had ''at least one thing in common'' with Mr. Broad and Mr. Geffen: ''They all have beach houses in Malibu.'' Mr. Lopez added that he had called a local coastal authority ''to see if Zell, like Geffen, has a history of denying beach access to the hoi polloi. If he does -- I'm awaiting a callback -- you'll read it here first.''</p>
        <p>Rather than rolling up their sleeves for a fight, some staff members at The Times said that whatever the outcome, they were relieved to be out of the limbo where the Tribune Company has dangled for the last six months as it considered strategic options.</p>
        <p>On Monday, ''people were swinging wildly between hope and fear -- nobody knows what to do or think or feel,'' said Marjorie Miller, the paper's foreign editor. ''But people think this does give us a little breathing room.''</p>
        <p>A NEWSPAPER SHAKE-UP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
