<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>3 Dancers Making a Show of Their Age</title>
    <meta content="03jasp" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/arts/dance/03jasp.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837669"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Jasperse, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E6DE1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="922" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>3 Dancers Making a Show of Their Age</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">3 Dancers Making a Show of Their Age</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GIA KOURLAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kourlas, Gia</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the relatively short history of modern dance, an awkward chain of events has unfolded that goes something like this: a choreographer gets older, his dancers get younger and suddenly, plopped into the middle of a work, is a solo in which the aging choreographer tries to get his groove back.</p>
        <p>John Jasperse, 43, wants no part of it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Jasperse created “Becky, Jodi and John,” a portrait choreographed by Mr. Jasperse for himself and two of his friends, to share his experience on getting older.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the relatively short history of modern dance, an awkward chain of events has unfolded that goes something like this: a choreographer gets older, his dancers get younger and suddenly, plopped into the middle of a work, is a solo in which the aging choreographer tries to get his groove back.</p>
        <p>John Jasperse, 43, wants no part of it.</p>
        <p>''I really wanted to find a context to continue to be able to perform in my own work,'' he said last month. ''I felt committed to creating a project where there was a relevance to the age that I was.''</p>
        <p>That new undertaking is ''Becky, Jodi and John,'' a portrait of three dancers choreographed by Mr. Jasperse for himself, Becky Hilton and Jodi Melnick, who are also, oddly enough, both 43.</p>
        <p>Although friends since moving to New York in the mid-1980s, they each took a different artistic path. ''Becky, Jodi and John,'' their first major project together, will be performed this week at Dance Theater Workshop, with live music by Hahn Rowe.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hilton, a former member of the Stephen Petronio Company whose exceptional virtuosity inspired countless dancers in the '90s, now lives in her native Australia, where she choreographs. Ms. Melnick, having performed with a long list of choreographers from Vicky Shick to Twyla Tharp, has singularly straddled the worlds of uptown and downtown dance. And Mr. Jasperse is one of the most successful choreographers in New York.</p>
        <p>The new work's title places the audience on a first-name basis with the dancers; Mr. Jasperse draws on their individual qualities. He became intrigued by the possibility of working with Ms. Melnick, a petite, doll-like redhead whose precision and delicacy are disarming, after watching her perform a solo in 2005.</p>
        <p>In the project's early days, he also hoped to enlist Chrysa Parkinson, another 43-year-old dancer now based in Brussels. (She appears in the work via video.) But when her schedule proved too complicated, ''I had to think of someone else,'' Mr. Jasperse said, ''and I knew it had to be somebody from our history.''</p>
        <p>He thought of Ms. Hilton, who countered with, '' 'Well, darling, I've retired from the stage, you know.' And my response was, 'I probably should have as well.' ''</p>
        <p>For Ms. Hilton, the construct of ''Becky, Jodi and John'' (billed in alphabetical order) presented the only kind of context she would be interested in taking part in as a performer.</p>
        <p>''The piece is kind of about the experience of getting older and the choices we've made, and how things have changed and stayed the same,'' she said. ''The themes of the work are what we live. It's not like I'm going out there and doing a couple of stag leaps in a unitard, which was my former life.''</p>
        <p>There are, it turns out, a few stag leaps -- jumps in which one knee is bent and the other leg extended -- in the work, as well as fragmented storytelling sections in which the performers reveal private aspects of their lives. Ms. Hilton reads an e-mail message detailing Ms. Melnick's list of don'ts: ''I don't jump. I can't stress this enough.''</p>
        <p>There is also a minute list, both sad and funny, of her physical ailments, which include pain in her left hip, foot and neck; the possible onset of arthritis in her right toe; and a surprising admission from the seemingly self-possessed Ms. Melnick: ''I am always nervous in rehearsals. Becky makes me especially nervous.''</p>
        <p>Later, Ms. Melnick, adopting a German accent, relates a conversation between Mr. Jasperse and a European presenter in which the choreographer is reprimanded for being so formal: ''She was really saying that I can't be so old.''</p>
        <p>There are also powerful moments of, as Ms. Hilton summed up, ''proper dancing.'' Through finely timed partnering and impeccable placement, Mr. Jasperse's choreography showcases something missing in many dance artists of today: a deeply ingrained sense of articulation.</p>
        <p>''That is something that really marks our generation and sets us apart,'' Mr. Jasperse said. ''You can really tell that we come from a particular community of people at a particular time, and that brings up issues of relevance and irrelevance.''</p>
        <p>The dancers share a bickering affection that comes not from rivalry but from deep camaraderie, which subtly makes itself apparent in the dance. In rehearsals, Mr. Jasperse is known as Snippy and Ms. Melnick as Sassy. The boisterous Ms. Hilton presides over both with her wisecracking, maternal earthiness.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Jasperse is technically in charge, the women aren't afraid to challenge him; at times, they also bring him down to earth. When Mr. Jasperse, for instance, brought up a quotation from Proust to make a point about aging, Ms. Hilton stuck her finger down her throat, while Ms. Melnick interrupted, in an erudite voice, ''I'll be quoting Judy Blume.''</p>
        <p>But as much as ''Becky, Jodi and John'' is about individual dynamics, it can also be seen on a more universal level.</p>
        <p>''The awareness of us being connected, but that our lives have led us to these different places, is a big part of what we're bringing into the work as well,'' Mr. Jasperse said. ''So there is something a little bit sentimental about it, but hopefully in not too sappy of a way. I do feel like what the work seems to be trying to talk about is that phenomenon of where life takes you.''</p>
        <p>''Becky, Jodi and John'' will be performed tomorrow through Saturday at Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea; (212) 924-0077 or dtw.org.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
