<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Cites Indian Government Agencies in Weapons Conspiracy</title>
    <meta content="03india" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/world/asia/03india.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837690"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arms Sales Abroad</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cirrus Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mazzetti, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Neil A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Sales Abroad</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">India</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Justice Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EEDE1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="520" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Cites Indian Government Agencies in Weapons Conspiracy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Cites Indian Government Agencies in Weapons Conspiracy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK MAZZETTI and NEIL A. LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewis, Neil A; Mazzetti, Mark</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Justice Dept charges that Indian government agencies participated in conspiracy to sidestep United States export regulations and obtain sensitive missile and weapons technology for its military programs; indictment charges that Cirrus Inc, private electronics firm operating in Singapore, South Carolina and Bangalore, worked as agent of Indian govenrment to obtain secret weapons technology; charges, coming months after Congress approved Pres Bush's plan to ship American nuclear reactors and fuel to India, could be embarrassing for administration, which seeks closer ties with India; indictment suggests that India broke pledge to Bush administration two years ago not to flout US export laws (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Justice Department, in an indictment disclosed Monday, charged that agencies of the Indian government participated in a conspiracy to sidestep United States export regulations and obtain secret weapons technology from American companies over several years.</p>
        <p>The indictment charges that a private electronics firm, Cirrus Inc., operating in Singapore, South Carolina and Bangalore, India, was working as an agent of the Indian government to obtain sensitive missile and weapons technology for its military programs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An indictment suggests that India broke a pledge not to flout export laws and seek sensitive weapons technology from the U.S.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Justice Department, in an indictment disclosed Monday, charged that agencies of the Indian government participated in a conspiracy to sidestep United States export regulations and obtain secret weapons technology from American companies over several years.</p>
        <p>The indictment charges that a private electronics firm, Cirrus Inc., operating in Singapore, South Carolina and Bangalore, India, was working as an agent of the Indian government to obtain sensitive missile and weapons technology for its military programs.</p>
        <p>It lists four company officials, including the founder, Parthasarathy Sudarshan, and a number of unidentified co-conspirators who were not charged, including one mentioned only as an Indian government official who worked in Washington. The indictment indicates that the defendants were buying equipment for three Indian government agencies.</p>
        <p>The charges, coming just months after Congress approved President Bush's plan to ship American nuclear reactors and fuel to India, could prove to be a diplomatic embarrassment for the administration, which has made cementing closer ties with India a top foreign policy priority.</p>
        <p>The indictment suggests that India broke a pledge to the Bush administration more than two years ago not to flout American export laws and secretly seek weapons technology from the United States.</p>
        <p>Although Congress has signed off on the nuclear deal, India must still reach a separate agreement on nuclear inspections with several international organizations before the deal is complete.</p>
        <p>In a letter to the State Department in September 2004, Shyam Saran, then the Indian foreign secretary, wrote, ''The Government of India shall not obtain or use U.S. origin licensable items in contravention of U.S. export control laws and regulations.''</p>
        <p>The weapons sales detailed in the indictment occurred between 2003 and 2006 and were shipped to government agencies that were part of the Indian Ministry of Defense and Department of Space.</p>
        <p>The defendants were charged with violating the United States Export Administration Act, which prohibits the export of dual-use technologies, those with both military and nonmilitary uses, without approval from the Commerce Department attesting that the technology will be used only for nonmilitary purposes.</p>
        <p>The indictment charges that Cirrus officials sometimes forged certificates to show the vendors in the United States that the sales had Commerce Department approval.</p>
        <p>Officials at the Indian Embassy in Washington declined to comment except to say that government officials in New Delhi have pledged to look into the allegations.</p>
        <p>Some critics of the nuclear deal reacted angrily to the indictment, and criticized the administration for pressing Congress to approve the agreement at the same time that the Justice Department was investigating an alleged conspiracy involving Indian government officials.</p>
        <p>''This is not only an indictment of individuals for breaking export control law, it is also a blistering indictment of the Bush administration's judgment,'' said Representative Edward J. Markey, the Massachusetts Democrat who was one of the leading Congressional opponents of the nuclear deal.</p>
        <p>Tom Casey, a State Department spokesman, said, ''This is a law enforcement matter that began before our efforts to conclude a civilian nuclear cooperation agreement.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''The arrests of these individuals are not connected to our efforts to conclude an agreement.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
