<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Racing to Make Surf City Beach Safe by May 25, Opening Day</title>
    <meta content="03beach" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/nyregion/03beach.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837795"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dredges and Dredging</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Surf City (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Army Corps of Engineers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Capuzzo, Jill P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Machinery and Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Army Corps of Engineers</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2DB1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="908" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Racing to Make Surf City Beach Safe by May 25, Opening Day</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Racing to Make Surf City Beach Safe by May 25, Opening Day</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JILL P. CAPUZZO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Capuzzo, Jill P</byline>
      <dateline>SURF CITY, N.J., April 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Army Corps of Engineers is racing to make sure 1.4-mile stretch of beach in Surf City, NJ, is safe by opening weekend; dredging to renourish beach pulled up several unexploded military fuses and adaptors, believed to be from World War II-vintage ordnance, forcing closing of beach on March 5; Corps will begin intensive sweep of beach to determine how many other potentially explosive devices are lying in replenished sand and have them removed by proper organizations; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Much of the sand along this popular 18-mile barrier island had washed away, leaving sections of beach with barely enough room to spread a towel.</p>
        <p>After battles with surfers fearful of shifting wave patterns and homeowners concerned that their expensive ocean views would be blocked by sand dunes, the United States Army Corps of Engineers got started, leaving behind a renourished 200-foot-wide beach in the middle of Long Beach Island.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A trove of live World War II munitions discovered during a replenishment project threatens to keep the beach closed beyond the beginning of the season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Much of the sand along this popular 18-mile barrier island had washed away, leaving sections of beach with barely enough room to spread a towel.</p>
        <p>After battles with surfers fearful of shifting wave patterns and homeowners concerned that their expensive ocean views would be blocked by sand dunes, the United States Army Corps of Engineers got started, leaving behind a renourished 200-foot-wide beach in the middle of Long Beach Island.</p>
        <p>That is not all it left, however. About a month ago it was discovered that mixed in with the 500,000 cubic yards of sand dredged from the ocean floor were several unexploded military fuses, and now the Corps of Engineers is racing to make sure that Surf City's 1.4-mile stretch of beach -- the lifeblood of this borough -- will be safe for bathers when the season begins in two months.</p>
        <p>''We have to verify if they're dangerous, and then call the proper organizations out to clear them out, '' said Keith Watson, project manager from the Philadelphia office of the Corps of Engineers. ''Depending on what we find, it could go from a little time to more than we want to know.''</p>
        <p>The entire beach here has been closed since March 5, when a resident with a metal detector found a rusty fuse as he strolled at the edge of the surf. Since then, about 30 fuses and adaptors -- believed to be from World War II-vintage ordnance -- have been found, some as recently as last week.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday morning, the Corps will begin an intensive sweep of the beach to determine how many other potentially explosive devices are lying in the newly replenished sand that was scraped from the ocean floor three miles offshore. The investigative phase is expected to take two weeks, while the time needed to remove what is found will depend on what the sweep uncovers.</p>
        <p>''After the characterization comes the digging, and that's the part that becomes more time-consuming,'' Mr. Watson said.</p>
        <p>Last Friday the Corps tested its sweeping system -- a flatbed trailer equipped with four powerful ground-penetrating metal detectors called magnetometers that will crawl along the entire stretch of beach, marking and recording the sites where metal objects -- from old ordnance to wristwatches -- are detected.</p>
        <p>That was about the time that the state's two United States senators, Robert Menendez and Frank R. Lautenberg, sent a letter to the Corps urging that the beach be cleaned up by Memorial Day.</p>
        <p>''We believe the Corps can and must take whatever steps necessary to ensure that the beach at Surf City is clear and safe before the start of the summer season on May 25, 2007,'' the letter read. ''Any economic disruption during this critical time of year could have disastrous consequences.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, the prospect of deflecting vacationers to places up and down the island from Barnegat Light to Beach Haven has many residents and business owners worried.</p>
        <p>''If people want to come down to the beach, and they can't get onto the beach, there's no doubt it could hurt business,'' said the general manager of the Surf City Hotel, Tom Gentry, whose 26-room hotel, with its 150-seat restaurant, is a leading destination.</p>
        <p>Ann Tambini, who came here last Friday to open her beach house, was surprised to find the entrance to the beach at the end of her street peppered with ''danger'' signs and closed off with plastic orange fencing. When she asked at the borough hall what was going on, she was told the beaches would be closed for at least the next two weeks.</p>
        <p>''It's really disappointing,'' said Ms. Tambini, who lives on Staten Island. ''Easter is next weekend and we're having people down who wanted to come and see the new expanded beach.''</p>
        <p>Ruth Bauer is annoyed because she cannot take her daily walks along the beach.</p>
        <p>''I don't think they're going to detonate after sitting in saltwater at the bottom of the ocean for 50 years,'' said Ms. Bauer, who has owned a house here since 1965.</p>
        <p>But Tim Rider, a spokesman for the 754th Ordnance Company at Fort Monmouth, where the objects were taken, said some of the recovered munitions contained unexploded powder. If detonated, Mr. Rider said, the devices could still maim or even kill.</p>
        <p>''Everything has to be treated like it is an explosive,'' Mr. Watson of the Corps said.</p>
        <p>The unwelcome discovery came at the end of the first phase of a controversial $71 million beach replenishment project planned for most of the towns on Long Beach Island.</p>
        <p>The discovery of the munitions is hardly the project's first stumbling block. Surfers up and down the island have voiced concern that the replenishment would alter wave patterns, and homeowners of multimillion-dollar beachfront houses in communities to the north and south are distraught because the project will leave a 22-foot-high sand dune blocking their view.</p>
        <p>So far, Surf City is the only town on the island where all necessary easements have been granted to allow the project to move forward.</p>
        <p>Mr. Watson acknowledged that this latest development could add fuel to the arguments of those opposed to the replenishment, although he said that in the next phases screens would be placed over the intake valves on the sand pumps.</p>
        <p>''That's the nature of this island,'' he said. ''You're going to have some people against it, and some people for it. But it's a positive project and it's vital to get it done for all the communities.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
