<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Shtetl by the Sea, Only a Few Fading Signs Remain</title>
    <meta content="03vanish" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/us/03vanish.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070406T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837760"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MIAMI BEACH JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Miami</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Synagogues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Synagogues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Miami (Fla)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807EFDC1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1077" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Shtetl by the Sea, Only a Few Fading Signs Remain</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Shtetl by the Sea, Only a Few Fading Signs Remain</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY GOODNOUGH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodnough, Abby</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI BEACH, April 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The synagogue at 1415 Euclid Avenue had only a few members left when Daniel Davidson, a New Yorker seeking a standout South Beach retreat, bought it in 2003.</p>
        <p>''I thought the space magical,'' he said of the spare, white 16,000-square-foot building -- now back on the market for $9,950,000 -- ''irrespective of religion.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The community that earned Miami Beach nicknames like Little Jerusalem and Shtetl by the Sea is now largely gone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The synagogue at 1415 Euclid Avenue had only a few members left when Daniel Davidson, a New Yorker seeking a standout South Beach retreat, bought it in 2003.</p>
        <p>''I thought the space magical,'' he said of the spare, white 16,000-square-foot building -- now back on the market for $9,950,000 -- ''irrespective of religion.''</p>
        <p>And so the Orthodox synagogue, Kneseth Israel, became Temple House, where Mr. Davidson has not only lived but also allowed Budweiser to film a commercial, Senator Bill Nelson of Florida and Al Gore to hold a Democratic fund-raising event and Jennifer Lopez to stage a listening party for her latest album, belting out love songs near where the Torah ark used to be.</p>
        <p>Like so many buildings that served a thriving Jewish population here for decades -- synagogues, delicatessens, kosher markets and hotels, even Yiddish theaters -- Temple House's history is all but imperceptible now. The community that earned Miami Beach nicknames like Little Jerusalem and Shtetl by the Sea is largely gone, and many of today's residents know nothing of it.</p>
        <p>Miami Beach had roughly 60,000 people in Jewish households, 62 percent of the total population, in 1982, but only 16,500, or 19 percent of the population, in 2004, said Ira Sheskin, a demographer at the University of Miami who conducts surveys once a decade. The decline -- due mostly to elderly Jews dying or getting priced out after the city's Art Deco revival, but also to the migration of others to Broward and Palm Beach Counties as greater Miami became more Hispanic -- has forced old-timers to scour for hints of their past.</p>
        <p>A few remain, like the Hebrew-inscribed doors of a deserted Orthodox shul being converted to condominiums and the old entryway to Wolfie's, a beloved coffee shop demolished for a condo building that will keep the faded front as a relic.</p>
        <p>But Miami Beach's last kosher resort hotel, the Saxony, closed in 2005 to make way for condominiums. Its oldest synagogue, Beth Jacob, also closed that year after membership dropped to 22, from 1,200 in the 1950s. Its domed building is now the Jewish Museum of Florida, housing memorabilia like mah-jongg boards and anti-Semitic real estate ads promising ''always a view, never a Jew.'' (Residents with ''Hebrew or Syrian blood'' generally could not rent or buy north of Fifth Street until the 1950s.)</p>
        <p>On Lincoln Road, the pedestrian thoroughfare at the heart of South Beach, Temple King Solomon has given way to Touch, a restaurant and lounge with occasional belly dancers and flame throwers. On Washington Avenue, the Cinema Theater, home to one of the longest-running Yiddish vaudeville shows in the world, is now Mansion, a club favored by Paris Hilton types.</p>
        <p>Farther north, in Sunny Isles Beach, Wolfie Cohen's Rascal House -- Miami's version of Katz's Deli in New York, famous for ''mile-high'' corned beef sandwiches -- will soon be demolished and replaced with yet another condo tower.</p>
        <p>This is not to say all Yiddishkeit is lost here: Talmudic University, which opened in Miami Beach in 1974, remains on Alton Road, along with a Lubavitch center that runs a day school and a rabbinical college. A few miles north of blingy South Beach, beachfront resorts like the Fontainebleau and the Eden Roc still fill up at Passover, and an Orthodox Jewish community is flourishing around 41st Street.</p>
        <p>But in South Beach alone, the number of people in Jewish households dropped by 53 percent between 1994 and 2004, to 4,171 from 8,775. Charlotte Cooper, who came to Miami Beach from New York to perform Yiddish theater in the 1960s and stayed until she was priced out in 1999, said she could hardly stand to return these days.</p>
        <p>''It's an entirely different story now,'' said Mrs. Cooper, a Holocaust survivor who moved to a condominium in Pembroke Pines but still performs here now and then. ''People from Hollywood, movie stars, come to stay in those hotels now. It has nothing to do with the Jewish people anymore.''</p>
        <p>At Temple Emanu-El in South Beach, Rabbi Kliel Rose is striving to attract young Jews while keeping older, second- and third-generation members. The cavernous stone synagogue drew 1,200 families in the 1980s; it claims about 260 now.</p>
        <p>Rabbi Rose's tactics include regular outings to South Beach bars and clubs, lectures on Kabbalah and a recent Havdalah ceremony, marking the end of Sabbath at sundown Saturday, with cocktails at Temple House. Rabbi Rose has added drums, guitar and an element of mysticism to Shabbat services. Still, to ensure the requisite 10 people for morning minyans, or prayer sessions, Temple Emanu-El teams up with the Cuban Hebrew Congregation, one of the neighborhood's only other surviving synagogues.</p>
        <p>''We are truly experimenting,'' said Rabbi Rose, 36, who wears an earring and was recruited from Congregation B'Nai Jeshurun, a booming conservative synagogue on the Upper West Side of Manhattan. ''We are trying to think outside the box.''</p>
        <p>When his congregants started shifting in their seats toward the end of Shabbat services one recent Friday night, Rabbi Rose asked them not to leave just yet, admonishing, ''Lincoln Road can wait.''</p>
        <p>David Weintraub, who directed ''Where Neon Goes to Die,'' a film about the Jewish retirees who flocked to Miami Beach from the 1920s through the 1980s, said his research was frustrated by an astonishing lack of documentation.</p>
        <p>''This legacy went on for over 60 years, and yet there is almost no memory that it even happened,'' Mr. Weintraub said. ''At the Miami Beach archives, I went through their file drawers for two weeks. There were drawers and drawers of cheesecake on the beach but not one photograph of Yiddish culture.''</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Weintraub is thinking of organizing ''ghost tours'' of Jewish Miami Beach. But he does not want a tourist clientele. ''We would target the folks who already live in Miami in the hopes that if people get a better sense of who and what came before,'' he said, ''they might be more pro-active when city planners destroy another piece of Miami's past.''</p>
        <p>Marcia Zerivitz, founding executive director of the Jewish Museum of Florida, said that while the decline of the Jewish population is an old story here, the rest of the country is surprisingly unaware. Filmmakers and writers still call her to say they want to document Jewish culture in Miami Beach, Ms. Zerivitz said.</p>
        <p>''I get calls like that all the time, especially from California and up east,'' she said. ''I say: 'Sorry, you're many, many years too late. There's nothing left.' ''</p>
        <p>MIAMI BEACH JOURNAL</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 6, 2007, Friday  An article on Tuesday about the disappearance of Jewish landmarks in Miami Beach included an outdated reference to Congregation B'Nai Jeshurun in Manhattan, from which Rabbi Kliel Rose, who is trying to attract new members to Temple Emanu-El in South Beach, was recruited. It is unaffiliated and no longer a Conservative synagogue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 6, 2007, Friday</p>
        <p>An article on Tuesday about the disappearance of Jewish landmarks in Miami Beach included an outdated reference to Congregation B'Nai Jeshurun in Manhattan, from which Rabbi Kliel Rose, who is trying to attract new members to Temple Emanu-El in South Beach, was recruited. It is unaffiliated and no longer a Conservative synagogue.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
