<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Embattled Ukrainian Leader Disbands Parliament</title>
    <meta content="03ukraine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/world/europe/03ukraine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070404T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837684"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ukraine</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kramer, Andrew E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yanukovich, Viktor F (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yushchenko, Viktor A (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ukraine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Ukraine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Ukraine</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Yushchenko, Viktor</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Yanukovich, Viktor F</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401EFDE1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="565" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Embattled Ukrainian Leader Disbands Parliament</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ukrainian Leader Disbands Parliament</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW E. KRAMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kramer, Andrew E</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, April 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Viktor A Yushchenko of Ukraine orders dissolution of Parliament, base of support for his rival Prime Min Viktor F Yanukovich, and orders new elections for May 27; Yanukovich's supporters in Parliament call emergency session and pass resolution declaring Yushchenko's decree to disband Parliament unconstitutional; vote against allocating money for new elections; rivalry between pro-Western Yushchenko and Yanukovich, who supports Russia, is pushing country into its worst political crisis since Orange Revolution in 2004; small groups supporting both camps gather on streets in another worrisome sign of deepening rift; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A fragile power-sharing deal in Ukraine collapsed Monday when President Viktor A. Yushchenko ordered the dissolution of Parliament, the base of support for his rival, Prime Minister Viktor F. Yanukovich, whom the president accused of usurping power. Mr. Yushchenko ordered new elections for May 27, less than eight weeks away.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yanukovich's supporters in Parliament responded by calling an emergency session and passing a resolution declaring Mr. Yushchenko's decree to disband Parliament unconstitutional. The deputies also voted against allocating money for the new elections.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Viktor A. Yushchenko accused his rival of usurping power and ordered new elections for May 27.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A fragile power-sharing deal in Ukraine collapsed Monday when President Viktor A. Yushchenko ordered the dissolution of Parliament, the base of support for his rival, Prime Minister Viktor F. Yanukovich, whom the president accused of usurping power. Mr. Yushchenko ordered new elections for May 27, less than eight weeks away.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yanukovich's supporters in Parliament responded by calling an emergency session and passing a resolution declaring Mr. Yushchenko's decree to disband Parliament unconstitutional. The deputies also voted against allocating money for the new elections.</p>
        <p>The maneuvers pushed Ukraine into its worst political crisis since the Orange Revolution in 2004, when Mr. Yushchenko defeated Mr. Yanukovich after street protests led to the reversal of a fraudulent election. The rivalry between Mr. Yushchenko, a pro-Western leader, and Mr. Yanukovich, who is supported by Russia, has been simmering in Ukrainian politics since then, reflecting a divide in Ukrainian society between a Russian-speaking eastern area and the Ukrainian-speaking west.</p>
        <p>In another worrisome sign of the deepening rift, small groups supporting both camps gathered on the streets on Monday evening.</p>
        <p>Yulia V. Tymoshenko, a fierce partisan in Ukrainian politics and former prime minister in Mr. Yushchenko's government, joined protesters on Independence Square in Kiev late Monday. In an echo of the 2004 events, meanwhile, Mr. Yanukovich's supporters erected tents in a park near the Parliament building.</p>
        <p>Inside, deputies from the Socialist, Communist and Party of Regions factions appealed to the prosecutor general's office, demanding that they be allowed to remain in session.</p>
        <p>Earlier, in a meeting with party leaders, Mr. Yushchenko accused the Party of Regions led by Mr. Yanukovich of consolidating power. The coalition led by Mr. Yanukovich had been recruiting Mr. Yushchenko's allies and boasting that it would achieve a veto-proof two-thirds majority of 300 votes, further undermining Mr. Yushchenko's authority.</p>
        <p>Just last month, some of Mr. Yushchenko's supporters in Parliament defected to Mr. Yanukovich's coalition, most prominently Anatoly K. Kinakh, the president's former national security adviser.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yushchenko, in his address, said his dissolving of Parliament was motivated by ''an acute necessity to preserve the nation, its sovereignty and territorial integrity.''</p>
        <p>All but written off after Mr. Yushchenko defeated him, Mr. Yanukovich staged an improbable comeback in parliamentary elections in March 2006, and formed enough of a coalition to become prime minister in August, leading to the power-sharing deal that ended Monday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yushchenko's press service said the decree dissolving the Rada, as the Parliament is known, would take effect on Tuesday morning, when it was to be published in a government newspaper.</p>
        <p>''Early elections to the Rada will take place in full compliance with the Constitution of Ukraine and democratic, national and international standards,'' he said in his speech. Mr. Yushchenko, whose face was disfigured from dioxin poisoning before the 2004 election in a mystery that has never been solved, has generally preferred compromise in his two years in power, to the point that critics and supporters alike have labeled him indecisive.</p>
        <p>He has declared his role to be ensuring democracy in Ukraine, even if that means his political opponents win at the polls, as happened in the March 2006 elections that led to the impasse on Monday. Polls, meanwhile, suggest new elections may not resolve the divisions; they give Mr. Yanukovich's party a slight lead over Ms. Tymoshenko's bloc, followed by the Our Ukraine Party of Mr. Yanukovich in third place.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 4, 2007, Wednesday  An article yesterday about the deepening crisis in Ukraine misidentified the political leader affiliated with the Our Ukraine Party. He is President Viktor A. Yushchenko, not Prime Minister Viktor F. Yanukovich.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 4, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about the deepening crisis in Ukraine misidentified the political leader affiliated with the Our Ukraine Party. He is President Viktor A. Yushchenko, not Prime Minister Viktor F. Yanukovich.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
