<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Randolph Takes an Early Measure of a Rookie's Nerve</title>
    <meta content="03mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/sports/baseball/03mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837793"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Smith, Joe</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Randolph, Willie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E2DB1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="870" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Randolph Takes an Early Measure of a Rookie's Nerve</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mets’ Randolph Takes Early Measure of Rookie’s Nerve</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAT BORZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Borzi, Pat</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS, April 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first day of anyone's major league career is usually filled with special moments. By the time he put on his uniform Sunday, the Mets rookie reliever Joe Smith said he already had a great one.</p>
        <p>''I rode a golf cart to the ballpark,'' Smith said. ''That was the most fun.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 5-1 lead gave Manager Willie Randolph the chance to test rookie reliever Joe Smith, the Mets’ biggest pitching surprise of spring training.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first day of anyone's major league career is usually filled with special moments. By the time he put on his uniform Sunday, the Mets rookie reliever Joe Smith said he already had a great one.</p>
        <p>''I rode a golf cart to the ballpark,'' Smith said. ''That was the most fun.''</p>
        <p>The Mets' team hotel is across the street from Busch Stadium. Why the 23-year-old Smith needed motorized transportation to go less than a block is almost as interesting a question as why Manager Willie Randolph chose to use him against the Cardinals in Sunday night's season opener.</p>
        <p>Less than a year after Smith threw his last collegiate pitch for Wright State, and not quite 10 months after he began his professional career, Smith jogged in from the bullpen in the eighth inning of a game the Mets led by four runs.</p>
        <p>This was the one curious moment in a satisfying 6-1 victory for the Mets, who turned four double plays and used several other defensive highlights to beat the team that defeated them in Game 7 of the National League Championship Series.</p>
        <p>The left-hander Pedro Feliciano had walked Aaron Miles leading off the eighth. That brought up the top of the Cardinals' order in David Eckstein, the first of five consecutive right-handed batters, one of whom was Albert Pujols. The situation begged for Aaron Heilman, the Mets' proven right-handed setup man, and no one would have questioned Randolph had he chosen him in that spot.</p>
        <p>But Randolph does not always manage by the book. A 5-1 lead gave him the chance to test the Mets' biggest pitching surprise of spring training. Smith compiled a 1.26 earned run average with 17 strikeouts in 141/3 innings to force his way on the team. But was he really that good? Bringing in Smith before a capacity crowd of 45,429 was a quick way to find out.</p>
        <p>''I liked the matchup, plain and simple,'' Randolph said.</p>
        <p>Smith, of course, had never faced any of the coming Cardinals batters in a game that counted. But in the minors for Class A Brooklyn and Class AA Binghamton last season, the sidearming Smith had been overpowering against right-handed batters, holding them to a .104 average (7 for 67).</p>
        <p>When the bullpen coach, Guy Conti, said, ''Smitty, you're in,'' it was hard not to be overwhelmed.</p>
        <p>''That was the most nerve-racking, that run to get in there,'' Smith said. ''It took me forever.''</p>
        <p>And when he reached the mound, Smith said, ''all I wanted to do was smile, but we had a game.'' Smith also understood that he was taking the ball from a manager who would not have appreciated an unfocused rookie pitcher goofing around. ''Once Willie left, guys started kidding with me, telling jokes,'' Smith said.</p>
        <p>Smith quickly got ahead of Eckstein, 0-2, but could not finish him off. Eckstein singled, and Cardinals Manager Tony La Russa chose to stick with the strikeout-prone Preston Wilson rather than pinch-hit with the left-handed batting Chris Duncan, who last year batted .318 with 20 home runs against right-handers. Wilson struck out on a slider, bringing up Pujols with runners on first and second.</p>
        <p>Randolph briefly considered bringing in Heilman, but decided to stick with Smith, even though a home run would have cut the Mets' lead to a run. ''He showed his poise all spring,'' Randolph said of Smith.</p>
        <p>Days earlier, Smith said, he had imagined a situation in which he faced Pujols and got him out. Falling behind in the count, 3-0, then walking Pujols on five pitches, was not part of that thought.</p>
        <p>''I didn't visualize it this way, I'll tell you that much,'' Smith said. ''He grounded out once, struck out twice. Didn't have a walk in there.</p>
        <p>''I was just trying to get ahead, to throw strike one. I thought it was a good pitch. When you've got the greatest hitter in the game up there, you've got to go after him. At least I didn't let him hurt us.''</p>
        <p>With Scott Rolen due up and representing the tying run, Randolph finally called for Heilman.</p>
        <p>Heilman induced a sharp ground ball, and second baseman Jose Valentín started a slick double play with a diving stop up the middle, ending the inning. That left Smith officially credited with a third of a scoreless inning in his debut.</p>
        <p>The Mets will need another right-handed setup reliever to keep from overworking Heilman, who had an operation on his right elbow after last season. Unless the Mets develop several starters who can pitch deep into games, they will have to rely even more on their bullpen than they did last season.</p>
        <p>Randolph can lean on the left-handers Feliciano and the veteran Scott Schoeneweis. But with Duaner Sánchez out with a fractured bone in his right shoulder and Guillermo Mota serving a 50-game suspension for violating baseball's drug policy, the Mets' best right-handed option could be Smith, if he can harness his slider and low-90s fastball.</p>
        <p>Sunday, he had one other thing going for him.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to pitch today really bad,'' Smith said after the game. ''Who wouldn't? Opening day, St. Louis, packed house, only game on TV. Who wouldn't want to be out there?''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
