<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Police Say Synagogue Fire Was Probably Not Arson</title>
    <meta content="03fire" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/nyregion/03fire.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837715"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Synagogues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Monsey (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Neturei Karta (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Connor, Anahad</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ahmadinejad, Mahmoud (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Synagogues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Synagogues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E2DD1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="748" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Police Say Synagogue Fire Was Probably Not Arson</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After Threats, Anti-Zionist Group’s Synagogue Burns, but Arson Is Doubted</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANAHAD O'CONNOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'Connor, Anahad</byline>
      <dateline>MONSEY, N.Y., April 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Investigators with Ramapo Police Dept rule that blaze that destroyed synagogue of Neturei Karta congregation in Monsey, NY, was not arson; tension between anti-Zionist congregation and other town residents have been rising since some members of congregation traveled to Tehran and shook hands with Pres Mahmoud Ahmadinejad at conference on the Holocaust; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The bitterness felt toward the Neturei Karta congregation had been evident since December, when members of the congregation, an anti-Zionist Jewish group, traveled to Tehran and shook hands with President Mahmoud Ahmadinejad at a conference on the Holocaust.</p>
        <p>In the months that followed, the ultra-Orthodox group with the unorthodox beliefs received threatening phone calls at its synagogue. A protest was held outside its doors. Rocks were thrown at its windows.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Authorities are investigating a suspicious fire that destroyed the synagogue of an anti-Zionist Jewish group that had been heavily criticized for attending a conference in Iran last year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The bitterness felt toward the Neturei Karta congregation had been evident since December, when members of the congregation, an anti-Zionist Jewish group, traveled to Tehran and shook hands with President Mahmoud Ahmadinejad at a conference on the Holocaust.</p>
        <p>In the months that followed, the ultra-Orthodox group with the unorthodox beliefs received threatening phone calls at its synagogue. A protest was held outside its doors. Rocks were thrown at its windows.</p>
        <p>Then on Sunday night, on the eve of Passover, that tension seemed to erupt into flames. About 8:15 p.m., the synagogue became engulfed in a blaze that nearly burned it to the ground. The fire raised the possibility that the heated debate over Zionism had escalated to violence, setting off angry exchanges on the streets of this heavily Hasidic community in Rockland County, about an hour's drive north of Manhattan.</p>
        <p>But on Monday afternoon, hours after calling the blaze suspicious, investigators with the Ramapo Police Department reversed themselves and said that although the fire, which began in a washroom on the ground floor, remained under investigation, they had determined that arson was almost certainly not a factor.</p>
        <p>Detective Lt. Brad Weidel of the Ramapo police said that dogs had gone through the rubble but failed to detect any traces of an accelerant, leading investigators to believe that a gas or electrical problem might have touched off the blaze.</p>
        <p>''We understand that there is some controversy surrounding this group,'' Detective Weidel said at a news conference on Monday. ''But our best investigators are telling us that they believe this was not an arson. At this time, the fire is not suspicious.''</p>
        <p>That statement brought some small measure of relief to Rabbi Yisroel Dovid Weiss of the Neturei Karta congregation. Earlier in the day, he had suggested that the fire had been started by people linked to the Jewish Defense Organization, a militant group that organized the protest outside the synagogue in January and encourages other Jews to harass its members.</p>
        <p>But the preliminary conclusion did not bring calm. Several times throughout the day, as Rabbi Weiss and other members of the group stood beside the rubble denouncing Zionism and calling for peace, they were met with angry chants of ''Go back to Iran'' and ''You hate Jews'' from Orthodox Jews and other residents who lined the street.</p>
        <p>Over the years, Neturei Karta, which has thousands of members worldwide, has been the subject of scorn and ridicule. Founded in the 1930s to counter the Zionist movement in what was then Palestine, the group -- whose name translates to ''guardians of the city'' in Aramaic -- calls for the ''speedy, peaceful dismantlement'' of the state of Israel because God has forbidden the formation of a Jewish state until the Messiah arrives.</p>
        <p>In December the group set off international outrage when Rabbi Weiss and other members of the group met with Mr. Ahmadinejad at a conference in Tehran despite the Iranian president's pronouncement that the Holocaust was a myth. (Neturei Karta does not question the Holocaust.)</p>
        <p>Since their return, they have been denied service at kosher stores in Monsey, vilified in Jewish discussion boards on the Web and threatened by anonymous callers.</p>
        <p>In addition to threats, it was the timing of the fire -- on the eve of Passover -- that aroused suspicion.</p>
        <p>Rabbi Weiss said the fire began after several members of the congregation left the synagogue, called Bais Yehuda. When they returned minutes later, he said, they smelled smoke and saw flames shooting from a window toward the back.</p>
        <p>When they tried to open a door, the rabbi added, they discovered it had been blocked by a bookshelf that appeared to have papers stacked on top of it.</p>
        <p>Within minutes, the fire had raced through all three floors of the building.</p>
        <p>''The whole thing was an inferno in a couple of minutes,'' said Moish Feldstein, who lives across the street from the synagogue on Saddle River Road. ''After about a half an hour, it looked like the sun was lit. You could see the flames from a half a mile away.''</p>
        <p>At the news conference on Monday, investigators said that the fire began in the ground-floor washroom, and that as it spread, bookcases and other furniture fell and blocked the doorway.</p>
        <p>Rabbi Weiss said the group would assess the damage and try to rebuild.</p>
        <p>''We're going to find another place to hold our services for now, and we're not by any means going to stop speaking out against Zionism,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
