<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To Help Rikers, City Wants More Prisoners in Brooklyn</title>
    <meta content="03jail" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/nyregion/03jail.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070414T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837787"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brooklyn House of Detention</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rikers Island Prison Complex (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Correction Department (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Trymaine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Rikers Island Prison Complex</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E3DB1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="835" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To Help Rikers, City Wants More Prisoners in Brooklyn</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">To Help Rikers, City Wants More Prisoners in Brooklyn</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRYMAINE LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Trymaine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City Dept of Correction plans to re-open and expand Brooklyn House of Detention, which has been closed since 2003, to help city eliminate beds for 4,000 prisoners at Rikers Island and ease pressure on aging jail complex; expansion will be built on empty land next to House of Detention and will include jail space and retail development (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The city's Department of Correction wants to double the number of prisoners it plans to house at a reopened Brooklyn House of Detention as part of its effort to ease pressure on the aging jail complex on Rikers Island, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The plan to expand the Brooklyn jail, which has been closed since 2003, will take five years and should help the city eliminate beds for 4,000 prisoners at Rikers Island, Correction Department officials said. Most of those inmates would be transferred to the Brooklyn House of Detention, at Boerum Place and Atlantic Avenue, and to a planned jail in the Oak Point section of the Bronx, the officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The city’s Department of Correction wants to double the number of prisoners it plans to house at a reopened Brooklyn House of Detention as part of its effort to ease pressure on the aging jail complex on Rikers Island, officials said yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The city's Department of Correction wants to double the number of prisoners it plans to house at a reopened Brooklyn House of Detention as part of its effort to ease pressure on the aging jail complex on Rikers Island, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The plan to expand the Brooklyn jail, which has been closed since 2003, will take five years and should help the city eliminate beds for 4,000 prisoners at Rikers Island, Correction Department officials said. Most of those inmates would be transferred to the Brooklyn House of Detention, at Boerum Place and Atlantic Avenue, and to a planned jail in the Oak Point section of the Bronx, the officials said.</p>
        <p>The Brooklyn jail, in its current state, has room for 749 inmates. The expansion would allow it to house 1,479.</p>
        <p>The expansion would be built on empty land next to the House of Detention, which is in the heart of a booming residential and commercial area, and it would include jail space and a retail development, officials said. The existing building would not be altered.</p>
        <p>Stephen Morello, a spokesman for the Correction Department, said the city would soon seek proposals from developers about how they might design the combined retail-jail space.</p>
        <p>Some neighborhood groups are opposed to the plan to reopen and expand the jail.</p>
        <p>''Before it was mothballed, the House of Detention was not a good neighbor,'' said Robert Perris, district manager of Community Board No. 2 in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>''The bottom line for people in that corner of Boerum Hill is the impacts of both the Department of Correction and the visitors to the facility have caused in the past and might cause in the future,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Sandy Balboza, president of the Atlantic Avenue Betterment Association, said the reopened jail could hurt the rebounding neighborhood's momentum. ''People have invested recently, they developed around the jail site,'' he said. ''They've invested, and the jail hurts their investment, especially the expansion of the jail.''</p>
        <p>A majority of the inmates expected to be sent to the Brooklyn jail would be from the borough, which is in keeping with a corrections trend in which inmates are kept closer to home, Mr. Morello said. Over all, he said, 33 percent of the city's inmates come out of Brooklyn courts.</p>
        <p>''Rikers Island is not a great place to have jails, for a number of reasons,'' Mr. Morello said, citing its proximity to La Guardia Airport and the limited access from the mainland to the East River complex.</p>
        <p>''It's an impossible trip for family members, attorneys and aid groups who offer various services to the inmates,'' Mr. Morello said. The Correction Department shuffles some 1,500 inmates a day from Rikers Island to court appearances throughout the city in an ''inefficient manner that is not good for the justice system,'' Mr. Morello said.</p>
        <p>He added that 80 percent of the inmates on Rikers Island have not been convicted of any crime and that 50 percent of the prisoners are released within 10 days. The average stay in the jail is 45 days, Mr. Morello said, adding that it does not make sense to have inmates spending so much time traveling from Rikers Island to courts in each borough.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perris said the plan to increase the inmate population at the House of Detention is not just about keeping prisoners closer to home.</p>
        <p>''That is a very humane goal, but there are people in the community who question whether it's just rhetorical leverage,'' Mr. Perris said. He said the community board's Transportation and Public Safety Committee and its Land Use Committee both voiced opposition to the expansion at the board's February meeting.</p>
        <p>''Court officers abused placard parking thought the area, and some visitors to the jail would urinate in people's yards, hide weapons and contraband in flower pots,'' Mr. Perris said. ''So there is concern that if the jail reopens and doubles in size, these problems will reappear and be worse than they were before.''</p>
        <p>Some residents and community groups also spoke out against the plan at a public hearing held by the full board.</p>
        <p>Still, many of those who oppose the expansion say they will work with developers to include community goals, particularly in the plans for a retail development.</p>
        <p>Mr. Balboza expressed skepticism about that part of the plan. ''The retail, how do we know retail can work there?'' Mr. Balboza asked, citing the no-parking and no-standing areas along that stretch of Atlantic Avenue and the lack of a viable loading dock.</p>
        <p>''We have developers who have come to the neighborhoods around the jail and developed it, not because the jail was there but because people came in and saved these neighborhoods,'' Mr. Balboza said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Morello said the next step in the Brooklyn jail expansion plan is the Unified Land Use review process. He said the Correction Department also must still buy the 22-acre parcel in the Oak Point section of the Bronx to build a jail where the city plans to house 2,040 inmates.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 14, 2007, Saturday  An article on April 3 about a plan by the New York City Department of Correction to reopen and expand the Brooklyn House of Detention in Boerum Hill referred incorrectly to a community leader who opposes the reopening. Sandy Balboza, president of the Atlantic Avenue Betterment Association, is a woman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 14, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article on April 3 about a plan by the New York City Department of Correction to reopen and expand the Brooklyn House of Detention in Boerum Hill referred incorrectly to a community leader who opposes the reopening. Sandy Balboza, president of the Atlantic Avenue Betterment Association, is a woman.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
