<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Critic's Choice: New DVD's</title>
    <meta content="03dvd" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/movies/homevideo/03dvd.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837661"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Critics Choice"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/DVD and Video</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Criterion Collection</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bergman, Ingmar</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E7DE1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1137" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Critic's Choice: New DVD's</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New DVDs: Early Bergman</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dave Kehr</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kehr, Dave</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Early Bergman</p>
        <p>The powers that be at the Criterion Collection have chosen five early works by the Swedish filmmaker Ingmar Bergman to initiate a new label, Eclipse, meant to offer relatively low-cost collections of relatively low-profile films. The Bergman set, for example, lists at $69.95 (as opposed to $99.95 for Criterion's recent Paul Robeson box set), the savings made possible by eliminating supplementary materials and commentary tracks. It's a solid idea, and a good way for Criterion, long the Tiffany of home video, to get out of its golden ghetto. No longer will the company largely be restricted to publishing deluxe editions of established classics. It's time for Criterion to cut loose and take some chances.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The powers that be at the Criterion Collection have chosen five early works by the Swedish filmmaker Ingmar Bergman to initiate a new label.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Early Bergman</p>
        <p>The powers that be at the Criterion Collection have chosen five early works by the Swedish filmmaker Ingmar Bergman to initiate a new label, Eclipse, meant to offer relatively low-cost collections of relatively low-profile films. The Bergman set, for example, lists at $69.95 (as opposed to $99.95 for Criterion's recent Paul Robeson box set), the savings made possible by eliminating supplementary materials and commentary tracks. It's a solid idea, and a good way for Criterion, long the Tiffany of home video, to get out of its golden ghetto. No longer will the company largely be restricted to publishing deluxe editions of established classics. It's time for Criterion to cut loose and take some chances.</p>
        <p>Which is exactly what it hasn't done with this cautious initial offering. Mr. Bergman remains identified with the great art-house boom of the 1960s and '70s, when his films were seen all over the world, were almost invariably hailed as masterpieces and consistently topped critics' polls and all-time-best lists. But film aesthetics have since drifted away from the literary-theatrical underpinnings of his work, and his reputation has declined as those of more cinematically engaged, visually and aurally expressive filmmakers have risen. This release already seems out of date, a slightly musty holdover from days of repertory programming long gone by.</p>
        <p>For admirers of Mr. Bergman's work, though, it is an excellent opportunity to watch as he develops from a promising newcomer to a deeply, if sometimes excessively, personal filmmaker, from the textbook Freudian conflicts of his first produced screenplay, ''Torment'' (1944, directed by Alf Sjoberg), to the full-blown domestic psychodrama of ''To Joy,'' a 1950 feature written and directed by Mr. Bergman that looks forward to ''Scenes From a Marriage'' (1973).</p>
        <p>''Crisis'' (1946), Mr. Bergman's first complete film as a director, is a small-town melodrama that wouldn't have seemed out of place on the Fox release schedule of 1934. Marianne Lofgren plays the sinister Miss Jenny, the owner of a beauty parlor in decadent Stockholm who arrives in a rural village to reclaim her 18-year-old daughter, Nelly (Inga Landgre), whom she left in the care of a beloved local piano teacher. Nelly is tempted by the wild ways of the big city (represented by one of her mother's acquaintances, a lounge lizard with a pencil mustache played by the early Bergman regular Stig Olin), a life that seems much more glamorous than a rural one shared with the earnest young veterinarian (Allan Bohlin) who loves her. ''Let the play begin,'' announces an off-screen narrator at the beginning as a window shade rises to reveal Mr. Bergman's favorite stage, the claustrophobic interior of a middle-class home.</p>
        <p>''Port of Call'' (1948) already seems more Bergmanesque, if only for the early sequence of Berit (Nine-Christine Jonsson), an attractive young woman with a firmly downturned mouth, marching to the end of a pier and flinging herself off. An expressionistic flashback, in this otherwise determinedly neo-realist film, reveals the source of Berit's unhappiness: a miserable childhood, in which she regularly watched her father beat her mother. An important Bergman theme raises its head when one of Berit's old reform-school comrades tries to shake her down for abortion money; in the scene showing the botched procedure, the huge, intense close-ups that were to become a Bergman trademark make an appearance, and we are in that Bergman world, in which gynecology is fate's darkest agent.</p>
        <p>An unwanted pregnancy and a traumatic abortion also figure in ''Thirst,'' an ambitious 1949 film that blends short stories by the actress Birgit Tengroth. A self-destructive ballerina, Rut (Eva Henning), squabbles with her patient new husband, Bertil (Birger Malmsten), as they travel in a cramped train compartment from Basel to Stockholm; meanwhile Mr. Bergman cuts away to the agonies of Bertil's cast-off fiancée, Viola (played by Ms. Tengroth), as she wanders disconsolately through the empty streets of Stockholm on Midsummer's Day and very nearly suffers that late-'40s fate worse than death, seduction by a lesbian. Their marriage may be a hell, Rut and Bertil admit, ''but at least we have each other.''</p>
        <p>The pieces of the puzzle finally seem to come together in ''To Joy,'' the first of Mr. Bergman's films to have an unmistakably confessional cast. Rather than project his restlessness, anger and self-doubt onto female characters, as he had largely done in his earlier work, he produces a monstrous version of himself. Stig (Mr. Olin again) is a moderately talented musician in a provincial orchestra. (The town is Halsingborg, where Mr. Bergman was once the director of the local theater.) He dreams of becoming an internationally recognized soloist; he is also an insufferable drunk, womanizer and bully who has had the good luck to marry the most saintly woman in Sweden, Marta (Maj-Britt Nilsson), a fellow musician who stands by him during his worst tantrums.</p>
        <p>But again biology raises its ugly head, and Stig is destroyed to learn that Marta is pregnant. ''Maybe you thought I'd be happy?'' he asks her, dreading the prospect of a rival infant in the family. The subject of ''To Joy'' is no longer that of an oppressive society crushing unconventional individuals, but how those individuals erect their own blocks and barriers, a paradigm shift that would henceforth define much of Mr. Bergman's work (and Woody Allen's as well).</p>
        <p>As advertised, there are no supplements with the films, though each disc comes with informative, unsigned notes. The transfer quality, however, is every bit as fine as a full-fledged Criterion release; there has been no skimping where it really counts. Upcoming Eclipse collections include a selection of Louis Malle's documentaries (including the long version of ''Phantom India''), a selection of late films by Yasujiro Ozu and -- the project that seems to me to strike closest to the heart of the Eclipse mission statement -- a pairing of two films by the important French director Raymond Bernard, ''Les Misérables'' (1934) and ''Wooden Crosses'' (1932), which remain almost unknown in the United States. (Criterion Collection, $69.95, not rated)</p>
        <p>Also Out Today</p>
        <p>THE GOOD SHEPHERD -- The secret history of the C.I.A., starring Matt Damon and directed by Robert De Niro. Available in widescreen and pan-and-scan editions. (Universal, $29.98, R)</p>
        <p>CHARLOTTE'S WEB -- Gary Winick's adaptation of the children's classic stars Dakota Fanning as the farm girl desperate to save her pet pig (the voice of Dominic Scott Kay). Julia Roberts voices Charlotte, the publicity-savvy spider. Available in widescreen and pan-and-scan editions. (Paramount, $29.99, G)</p>
        <p>VOLVER -- A loving Spanish mother (Carmen Maura) steps out of the shadows to straighten out the life of her afflicted daughter (Penélope Cruz). From the director Pedro Almodóvar. (Sony, $28.95, R)</p>
        <p>DEATH OF A PRESIDENT -- Gabriel Range's controversial British mockumentary imagines the assassination of George W. Bush at a Chicago rally. (Lionsgate, $27.98, R)</p>
        <p>Critics Choice</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
