<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Opulent Home, a Rich Past</title>
    <meta content="03mansion" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/nyregion/03mansion.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070407T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837756"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mansions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koppel, Lily</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mansions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mansions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E0DC1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="756" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Opulent Home, a Rich Past</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Opulent Home, a Rich Past</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LILY KOPPEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Koppel, Lily</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Schinasi mansion at 107th Street and Riverside Drive is for sale for $20 million, down from $31 million that was asked when it was put on market in 2006; was built in 1909 for Turkish immigrant who made his fortune by selling Turkish cigarettes; its three floors include marble hall inlaid with Turkish glass, drawing room, smoking room and reception hall; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The white marble mansion on Riverside Drive and 107th Street, its entrance guarded by two lions, has always attracted onlookers who have approached the home as if it were a sphinx. Since last year, when it was put on the market for $31 million, a mosaic of New Yorkers, including great-granddaughters of both the original owner and the architect, have shed new light on its rich history.</p>
        <p>The house was built in 1909 for Morris Schinasi, who immigrated from Turkey with his brother, Solomon, in 1893. The brothers, who had grown up barefoot and penniless, made their fortune by selling Turkish cigarettes. Their Natural, Prettiest and Royal brands were widely popular, and by 1904, the Schinasis owned a factory at 120th Street and Broadway where 300 women packed cigarettes made of their secret blend of strong Oriental tobacco into colorful boxes decorated with Egyptian motifs in bright green, yellow and red.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Riverside Drive mansion that Turkish tobacco built is on the market for $20 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The white marble mansion on Riverside Drive and 107th Street, its entrance guarded by two lions, has always attracted onlookers who have approached the home as if it were a sphinx. Since last year, when it was put on the market for $31 million, a mosaic of New Yorkers, including great-granddaughters of both the original owner and the architect, have shed new light on its rich history.</p>
        <p>The house was built in 1909 for Morris Schinasi, who immigrated from Turkey with his brother, Solomon, in 1893. The brothers, who had grown up barefoot and penniless, made their fortune by selling Turkish cigarettes. Their Natural, Prettiest and Royal brands were widely popular, and by 1904, the Schinasis owned a factory at 120th Street and Broadway where 300 women packed cigarettes made of their secret blend of strong Oriental tobacco into colorful boxes decorated with Egyptian motifs in bright green, yellow and red.</p>
        <p>In 1907, Solomon Schinasi bought the Isaac L. Rice mansion, with its reflecting pool and colonnaded garden, on Riverside Drive at 89th Street, where it stands today as an Orthodox Jewish school, Yeshiva Ketana. Morris, not to be outdone, hired William B. Tuthill, the architect who designed Carnegie Hall, to sketch an equally impressive residence for himself.</p>
        <p>The result was a French Renaissance marble mansion with a sea-green tiled roof. Its three floors included an Egyptian marble hall inlaid with Turkish glass, a Louis XVI drawing room, a library, a smoking room and a reception hall. The pineapple, a traditional symbol of hospitality, is found throughout the house, set into the moldings in gold and bronze. Among the house's unusual features is an underground passage to the Hudson River, now sealed.</p>
        <p>Last year, Diane Abrams, a real estate broker for Brown Harris Stevens, contacted the current owner, Hans Smit, a law professor at Columbia University, after receiving an inquiry from a buyer. Ms. Abrams, a lawyer and former student of Dr. Smit's, persuaded him to put the house on the market.</p>
        <p>Dr. Smit lowered the asking price to $20 million, partly to attract buyers who might not ordinarily consider a home so far uptown. ''The right person needs to find it,'' Ms. Abrams said, adding that two different parties have recently expressed interest. She has also shown the home to a foundation seeking a headquarters and a British men's club.</p>
        <p>The mansion's original owner has a story as interesting as his home. Although Morris Schinasi never learned to read or write, according to a daughter's memoir, he was fluent in eight languages. He tended to keep a close watch over his much younger bride, Laurette, whom he married when she was 16, and their three daughters, Victoria, Altina and Juliette. (A portrait of Juliette hangs in the Metropolitan Museum of Art.)</p>
        <p>''He ran it like a pasha,'' said Victoria Sanders, 46, one of his great-granddaughters, a literary agent who lives in downtown Manhattan. Ms. Sanders, who was raised in the mansion by her grandmother Altina, paid her last bittersweet visit to the house, which had changed dramatically since her childhood, in the 1980s.</p>
        <p>In 1930, shortly after Morris Schinasi's death, the house was sold to the Semple School, a finishing academy for young women. By the 1960s, the mansion had been bought by Columbia University as part of a larger land purchase. At different times, its tenants were an Episcopal private school, a publication called the Digest of Soviet Press and a day care center.</p>
        <p>Then in 1979, Dr. Smit noticed the house while biking and bought it from Columbia for $325,000. He has been working on its restoration for nearly three decades.</p>
        <p>He has never lived in the house but rents it out for movie shoots, including the Woody Allen film ''Bullets Over Broadway,'' and holds pizza parties for his students there. His son, Robert, also a lawyer, has lived in the home since the early 1980's after he graduated from college, sharing it with his two daughters in a much more relaxed style than the original owner. Back then, walls were covered in silk damask and the extravagant rooms swirled with Oriental rugs. Today, several Buddha statues sit quietly on bare hardwood floors.</p>
        <p>One Sunday afternoon last fall, Anne Hersey Patterson, 28, a great-granddaughter of the architect and an interior decorator who lives in a studio, decided to take a walk to the mansion with a few friends. They wandered around the outside and glanced into the windows, her friends cooing, ''Wouldn't it be great if you could live here?''</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 7, 2007, Saturday  An article on Tuesday about the history of a mansion for sale on Riverside Drive in Manhattan referred incorrectly to Victoria Sanders, a great-granddaughter of the original owner, Morris Schinasi. She was not in fact raised in the mansion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 7, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article on Tuesday about the history of a mansion for sale on Riverside Drive in Manhattan referred incorrectly to Victoria Sanders, a great-granddaughter of the original owner, Morris Schinasi. She was not in fact raised in the mansion.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
