<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Owner Who Is Hedging His Bets</title>
    <meta content="03carr" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/business/media/03carr.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837761"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="A NEWSPAPER SHAKE-UP: THE MEDIA EQUATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tribune Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zell, Samuel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chandler Family</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carr, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Tribune Company</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Zell, Samuel</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06EFDC1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="860" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Owner Who Is Hedging His Bets</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A New Owner Who Is Hedging His Bets</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CARR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carr, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Carr column on Samuel Zell's decision to acquire Tribune Co for $8.2 billion with investment of his own money of only $315 million; says deal's magic lies in employee stock ownership plan that offers tax benefits that allow Zell to further leverage offer; holds arrangement gets rid of Chandler family, previous owners of Times Mirror who put merged company in play last year; says taking Tribune private will take pressure off quarterly earnings, but other challenges remain, including eventually finding exit for investors in industry that seems little short of future right now (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a self-published little red booklet entitled ''Quotations from the Chairman,'' Samuel Zell, the real estate magnate who often sounds like a thoughtful version of Yosemite Sam, offered this guidance: ''Be a risk taker; however, define risk by your own terms.''</p>
        <p>In his deal to buy the Tribune Company, Mr. Zell has heeded his own advice. The board accepted his offer of $34 a share that was short on equity -- Mr. Zell will contribute less than 4 percent of the total value from his own pocket -- and long on financial engineering.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Taking Tribune private will ease quarterly earnings pressures, but operational challenges will remain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a self-published little red booklet entitled ''Quotations from the Chairman,'' Samuel Zell, the real estate magnate who often sounds like a thoughtful version of Yosemite Sam, offered this guidance: ''Be a risk taker; however, define risk by your own terms.''</p>
        <p>In his deal to buy the Tribune Company, Mr. Zell has heeded his own advice. The board accepted his offer of $34 a share that was short on equity -- Mr. Zell will contribute less than 4 percent of the total value from his own pocket -- and long on financial engineering.</p>
        <p>The deal's magic lies in an employee stock ownership plan, or ESOP, that offered tax benefits that allowed Mr. Zell to further leverage the offer. The novel arrangement gets rid of the Chandler family, the previous owners of Times Mirror who cocked the gun and put the merged company in play last year. But it does not change a much bigger problem, namely that advertising revenue that support the newspaper and television businesses is trending one way right now: down.</p>
        <p>Taking Tribune private will take pressure off quarterly earnings, but other challenges will remain, including eventually finding an exit for investors in an industry that seems a little short on a future right now.</p>
        <p>The price, if you ignore the gimmickry, is a good one. There has been a re-evaluation in newspaper values, most notably at the end of last year when McClatchy sold The Minneapolis Star Tribune for $530 million, less than half the $1.2 billion it paid for the property eight years before.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zell is a real estate guy, someone who has played that cyclical business by buying distressed properties and shining them up while waiting for the market to come back (and it always seems to come back).</p>
        <p>But newspapers, especially large ones built on classified advertising, are a victim of secular, not cyclical, change as ads and audience have fled to the Web. The Tribune Company cannot be blamed for seismic changes in the industry, but it undoubtedly imperiled its future in buying Times Mirror for $8 billion in 2000 (a deal that should stand beside the AOL and Time Warner marriage in the pantheon of Bad Media Mergers). Needless to say, all those anticipated synergies never materialized.</p>
        <p>There's very little in Mr. Zell's past that reveals what kind of newspaper owner he might be. He has never owned one, but if he is looking to cut costs, he could be in for a shock. Say what you will about Tribune executives, they vigorously trimmed back, so there isn't a lot of fat left.</p>
        <p>Nor has he offered many assurances about the public role of newspapers, unlike his rivals from Los Angeles, Eli Broad and Ronald W. Burkle, whose bid stemmed at least in part from a civic impulse, even if it happened to be for the wrong city.</p>
        <p>In the long run, newspaper companies could find new traction in a Web era, using strong local brands and trusted content to rebuild as a digital business. But the profit horizon on that is years away, long enough to try the patience of private equity money and the employees themselves. It will be a long, bumpy ride, and could serve as an inflection point for the Tribune Company's nonunion employees to organize to insure that their interests are represented.</p>
        <p>Because of the ESOP, the Tribune employees are at the center of this deal. Like all Americans, they have been taught to diversify their investment portfolio, not to load up on their own company. ''The employees are being asked to double down their risk at a very uncertain time in the industry,'' said Ken Doctor, a media analyst at Outsell. ''Even the buyers of this paper said that while they were willing to invest, they wanted someone else to take the majority of the risk.''</p>
        <p>Le Monde in Paris has had a mixed record with employee ownership, and an employee-owned approach ended in a sale at The Milwaukee Journal-Sentinel and The Journal Star in Peoria.</p>
        <p>''If they end up with some measure of control, I think that a lot of employees might be wanting to think salvation is at hand, but I wouldn't uncork just yet,'' said Mark Feldstein, associate professor of media at George Washington University. ''Workers tend to be parochial in their interests and not long on vision, which is what drives good journalism.''</p>
        <p>That brings us to one of the many paradoxes of this effort to untangle the purchase of Times Mirror. The Tribune management that engineered that deal will undoubtedly be handed significant incentives to stay put, including Dennis J. FitzSimons, the Tribune president and chief executive, who will remain on the board. Those executives will no doubt be given parachutes that will help them land safely if the novel deal begins to break apart.</p>
        <p>But Tribune employees, who never asked to be part of this bold new experiment, will now have their futures riding on a company being run by a manager who has no experience in the newspaper business. They're not only jumping from the frying pan into the fire -- they're being asked to supply the gas.</p>
        <p>A NEWSPAPER SHAKE-UP: THE MEDIA EQUATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
