<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Brooklyn Academy And Old Vic Teaming Up</title>
    <meta content="03bam" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/theater/03bam.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837667"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/William Shakespeare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Anton Chekhov</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Sam Mendes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Brooklyn Academy of Music</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Old Vic Theater</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Mendes, Sam</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E6DE1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="627" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Brooklyn Academy And Old Vic Teaming Up</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Brooklyn Academy and Old Vic Teaming Up</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAMPBELL ROBERTSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robertson, Campbell</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Brooklyn Academy of Music, in its first foray into producing plays in two decades, has announced a three-year joint venture with the director Sam Mendes and the Old Vic theater company in London to produce two plays a year, which will run in repertory for limited engagements on both sides of the Atlantic.</p>
        <p>For the Bridge Project, as the venture is called, a company of British and American actors will perform a double bill of classics at the Brooklyn Academy, the Old Vic and at least one other international theater each year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The academy has announced a three-year joint venture with the director Sam Mendes and the Old Vic theater company in London to produce two plays a year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Brooklyn Academy of Music, in its first foray into producing plays in two decades, has announced a three-year joint venture with the director Sam Mendes and the Old Vic theater company in London to produce two plays a year, which will run in repertory for limited engagements on both sides of the Atlantic.</p>
        <p>For the Bridge Project, as the venture is called, a company of British and American actors will perform a double bill of classics at the Brooklyn Academy, the Old Vic and at least one other international theater each year.</p>
        <p>The last play that the academy produced was ''The Cherry Orchard,'' directed by Peter Brook, in 1988. In the last two decades it has generally been a stop -- not a source -- for theater on the international touring circuit.</p>
        <p>In 2008, the first year of the project, Mr. Mendes is to direct ''Hamlet'' and ''The Tempest,'' both featuring Stephen Dillane, who starred in the revival of Tom Stoppard's ''Real Thing'' on Broadway in 2000. Other parts are still being cast.</p>
        <p>The plays will run in Brooklyn from January to March and at the Old Vic in May and June. In between they will have a monthlong residency at the Piccolo Teatro in Milan. In 2009 Mr. Mendes will direct ''The Winter's Tale'' and ''The Cherry Orchard,'' with Simon Russell Beale playing Leontes and Lopakhin.</p>
        <p>The third year's plays have not been announced, nor have the other international theaters.</p>
        <p>The idea for the project began around 2002 when Mr. Mendes, who was ending his tenure as artistic director of the Donmar Warehouse in London, directed ''Twelfth Night'' and ''Uncle Vanya'' in repertory, with Mr. Russell Beale starring. The productions played the Donmar (and helped make Mr. Mendes the first person to win three Olivier Awards in a one year), and then went to Brooklyn for a successful run in 2003.</p>
        <p>Joseph V. Melillo, the executive producer of Brooklyn Academy, approached Mr. Mendes about starting a company that would present a couple plays a year; at the same time Mr. Mendes had been talking to Kevin Spacey, whom he had directed in the film ''American Beauty'' and who had recently become artistic director of the Old Vic, about directing a production there.</p>
        <p>''It didn't take much to put two and two together,'' Mr. Mendes said yesterday in a conference call with Mr. Spacey and Mr. Melillo.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spacey, who said they would have to raise $2 million to get the company up and running, said the similarities between the Old Vic's theater and the Brooklyn Academy's Harvey Theater made them natural producing partners. ''From a design aspect it makes complete sense,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Over the last decade the academy has become a dependable place to see the most talked-about shows -- often reworked classics -- by British theater companies, including the Propeller ensemble (which just finished a run at the Harvey with a double bill of ''Twelfth Night and ''The Taming of the Shrew,'' produced by the Old Vic and the Watermill Theater), Cheek by Jowl and the Royal Shakespeare Company, which has appeared seven times.</p>
        <p>Mr. Melillo, who has been criticized in the past for risk-averse programming, acknowledged that he had relied heavily on British productions but insisted that it was because the work was of such high quality.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mendes was more forthrightly pragmatic. ''The truth is, there is and has to be in any English-speaking city a limited audience for foreign-language shows,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The real foreigners in theater at the academy have been American performers, Mr. Mendes said. Promising that the casting would be split down the middle between British and American actors, Mr. Mendes said the partnership would be ''a huge step forward for BAM to be able to achieve this.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
