<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Employee Owners Don't Necessarily Have a Say in Management</title>
    <meta content="03esop" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/business/03esop.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070410T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837753"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tribune Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Uchitelle, Louis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Personal Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Personal Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Tribune Company</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E1DC1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="827" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Employee Owners Don't Necessarily Have a Say in Management</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Employee Owners Don’t Necessarily Have a Say in Management</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOUIS UCHITELLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Uchitelle, Louis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Owners of comp</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>More than 10 million workers have stakes in their companies through employee stock ownership plans, and many have benefited.</p>
        <p>But the owners of the companies that set up such plans are usually the biggest winners -- and that appears to be the case in Samuel Zell's acquisition of the Tribune Company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Employee stock ownership plans of the sort being used by the Tribune Company have not always worked out as hoped.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>More than 10 million workers have stakes in their companies through employee stock ownership plans, and many have benefited.</p>
        <p>But the owners of the companies that set up such plans are usually the biggest winners -- and that appears to be the case in Samuel Zell's acquisition of the Tribune Company.</p>
        <p>ESOPs, which were authorized by a 1974 pension law, grant generous tax breaks to the owners for setting them up. Then, if the companies are successful, employees build retirement wealth as their shares increase in value. As the debt is paid down, the stock in the ESOP is parceled out in the employees' names and, after a vesting period, workers are eligible to cash in their stakes upon leaving or retiring.</p>
        <p>They have in effect accumulated retirement wealth without, in most cases, investing any money -- unless the stock plummets, wiping out their paper wealth.</p>
        <p>But employee ownership does not necessarily mean a voice in management, or even a say. A trustee represents the ESOP, and is often appointed by the owners when the program is formed. The trustee does not have to consult the employees -- unless they bargained for such an arrangement when the ESOP was set up -- except for certain momentous decisions, like selling the company or a division of the company.</p>
        <p>Then the employees instruct the trustee how to vote their shares. And if the ESOP owns a majority of the stock, as Mr. Zell apparently intends, then that vote can be decisive.</p>
        <p>The number of ESOPs across the country reached 9,225 at last count, in 2005, the National Center for Employee Ownership reports. Only about 5 percent involve large, often publicly traded corporations. Most are set up when a family-owned corporation or a privately held small business wants to sell all or part of the operation to employees, who helped build it.</p>
        <p>When big corporations set up ESOPs, the tax breaks -- rather than sharing ownership with employees -- are usually the driving factor. As the debt is repaid, not only is the interest deductible from taxable income but so is the principal. Sometimes the tax breaks are large enough to write off all of a company's taxable income.</p>
        <p>That might turn out to be the case in the Tribune deal.</p>
        <p>''There is going to be so much debt relative to profit that if you can't reduce the cost of repayment through an ESOP, the deal is difficult to bring off,'' said Corey Rosen, executive director of the National Center for Employee Ownership, offering an explanation of why an ESOP figured in the final bidding for Tribune. The center is a nonprofit research and membership group based in Oakland, Calif.</p>
        <p>There is a second tax advantage. If the ESOP holds at least 30 percent of the stock, then the owner can roll the money he earns from selling stock to the ESOP into a ''qualified replacement property'' -- namely stocks and bonds -- without having to ever pay a tax on capital gains. The only requirement is that the ESOP must hold the stock for at least three years.</p>
        <p>''That is a major advantage,'' said John Logue, director of the Ohio Employee Ownership Center at Kent State University.</p>
        <p>Under the proposed arrangement, Tribune will have another tax advantage. The deal calls for the company to be converted into an S corporation. A portion of the profit can then be assigned to the shares held by the ESOP, and that portion would be tax-exempt, as are all pension funds.</p>
        <p>''If the ESOP is the majority shareholder, as Mr. Zell seems to intend, then most of the profit will be tax-free,'' Mr. Logue said. So why aren't ESOPs used in many more acquisitions and buyouts?</p>
        <p>''If you are a merger and acquisition artist,'' Mr. Logue said, ''you are collecting hefty management fees and you make money by shutting down or selling low-profit divisions. You really can't do that with an ESOP present.''</p>
        <p>In perhaps the most famous ESOP, formed at United Airlines in 1994, unions were involved in the negotiations. The ESOP owned a majority of the stock, which was publicly traded, and the employees had three seats on the board, although not much say in management.</p>
        <p>The unions, in exchange, made concessions in pay, a tactic that seemed to benefit employees. The stock rose and thousands of workers counted their wealth in six figures. But it was paper wealth: the stock price collapsed as United filed for bankruptcy protection after the terrorist attacks of Sept. 11. Tribune's employees could similarly end up diverting some of their pay -- perhaps their 401(k) contributions -- into buying the ESOP's stock.</p>
        <p>Whatever their drawbacks, companies with ESOPs seem to outperform non-ESOP companies in the same industry, in part by fostering a sense of ownership and control, Mr. Rosen said, citing surveys done in 1987 and again last year.</p>
        <p>''Over all,'' he said, ''ESOP companies grow 2 to 3 percent faster than you would have expected them to grow absent the ESOP.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 10, 2007, Tuesday  A front-page article last Tuesday about Samuel Zell's acquisition of the Tribune Company for $8.2 billion misstated one aspect of an ''S'' Corporation, which Tribune will eventually become under the takeover proposal. Foreigners who are residents of the United States can invest in an ''S'' Corporation; investors are not restricted to United States citizens.</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day last Tuesday about Samuel Zell using an Employee Stock Ownership Plan, or ESOP, in a transaction for the Tribune Company omitted a condition for an owner to avoid capital gains taxes on the proceeds of a sale of company shares to such a plan. In addition to the ESOP holding the stock for at least three years, the company has to be private for at least one year before the sale.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 10, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A front-page article last Tuesday about Samuel Zell's acquisition of the Tribune Company for $8.2 billion misstated one aspect of an ''S'' Corporation, which Tribune will eventually become under the takeover proposal. Foreigners who are residents of the United States can invest in an ''S'' Corporation; investors are not restricted to United States citizens.</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day last Tuesday about Samuel Zell using an Employee Stock Ownership Plan, or ESOP, in a transaction for the Tribune Company omitted a condition for an owner to avoid capital gains taxes on the proceeds of a sale of company shares to such a plan. In addition to the ESOP holding the stock for at least three years, the company has to be private for at least one year before the sale.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
