<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Home Lender Is Seeking Bankruptcy</title>
    <meta content="03lend" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/business/03lend.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837765"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreclosures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Century Financial</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Greenwich Capital Financial Products</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CIT Group/Business Credit Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Creswell, Julie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bajaj, Vikas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Subprime Lending</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Foreclosures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreclosures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Century Financial Corporation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905EEDC1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1120" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Home Lender Is Seeking Bankruptcy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Home Lender Is Seeking Bankruptcy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIE CRESWELL and VIKAS BAJAJ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Creswell, Julie; Bajaj, Vikas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Century Financial Corp, one of nation's largest mortgage lenders to individuals with weak, or subprime, credit rating during recent housing boom, files for Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection; as lenders and their banks contend with financial and corporate fallout, policy makers in Washington are struggling to come to grips with how to help more than one million subprime borrowers who are either in foreclosure or are more than three months behind on their house payments as of end of year; New Century says it will dismiss 3,200 employees, or slightly more than half of its staff; also outlines plan to liquidate itself over next 45 days in auctions for its three principal assets: platform it used to make home loans, operation that serviced mortgages and interest it held in pools of loans sold to investors; Greenwich Capital Financial Products, one of two companies providing New Century with as much as $150 million in financing during bankruptcy proceeding, agrees to acquire certain loans and residual interests for $50 million; other company providing financing to New Century is CIT Group/Business Credit Inc (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From an 11-story steel-and-glass tower that housed its headquarters in Irvine, Calif., the New Century Financial Corporation ruled as one of the nation's largest mortgage lenders to individuals with weak, or subprime, credit during the recent housing boom.</p>
        <p>That reign officially ended yesterday, when New Century became the biggest, and most prominent, corporate failure in the subprime mortgage business.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New Century Financial became the biggest, and most prominent, corporate failure in the subprime mortgage business.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From an 11-story steel-and-glass tower that housed its headquarters in Irvine, Calif., the New Century Financial Corporation ruled as one of the nation's largest mortgage lenders to individuals with weak, or subprime, credit during the recent housing boom.</p>
        <p>That reign officially ended yesterday, when New Century became the biggest, and most prominent, corporate failure in the subprime mortgage business.</p>
        <p>Plagued by a spike in loan defaults and a loss of confidence among its financial patrons on Wall Street, New Century filed for Chapter 11 protection in Federal Bankruptcy Court in Wilmington, Del.</p>
        <p>While the bankruptcy filing was expected -- indeed it had been widely viewed as inevitable by analysts -- the reverberations nonetheless will be felt for some time. As lenders and their banks contend with the financial and corporate fallout, policy makers in Washington are struggling to come to grips with how to help the more than one million subprime borrowers who are either in foreclosure or are more than three months behind on their house payments as of the end of last year.</p>
        <p>The shakeout is winnowing out a clutch of fast-growing young companies that dominated the subprime business with the help of credit lines from Wall Street and access to borrowers through mortgage brokers. They are being replaced by larger companies like HSBC, Citigroup and Countrywide Financial for whom subprime is just one segment of a much larger portfolio.</p>
        <p>''It's definitely the end of an era,'' said Guy Cecala, publisher of Inside Mortgage Finance, an industry newsletter.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, New Century, which survived a similar credit squeeze nearly a decade ago that took out much of its competition, said it would dismiss 3,200 employees, or slightly more than half of its staff.</p>
        <p>It also outlined a plan to liquidate itself over the next 45 days in auctions for its three principal assets: the platform it used to make home loans, the operation that serviced mortgages and the interest it held in pools of loans sold to investors.</p>
        <p>''As deep into subprime as New Century was, there was just no way out,'' said Matthew Howlett, an analyst with Fox-Pitt Kelton.</p>
        <p>One of the two companies providing New Century with as much as $150 million in financing during the bankruptcy proceeding, Greenwich Capital Financial Products, has agreed to acquire certain loans and residual interests for $50 million. That offer could be bid up in an auction. The other company providing financing to New Century is the CIT Group/Business Credit Inc.</p>
        <p>A sale of New Century's servicing assets and platform to Carrington Capital Management for $139 million is planned; those operations collect loan payments, handle customer service, contact delinquent borrowers and oversee foreclosures. That sale is also subject to an auction.</p>
        <p>Carrington's involvement is expected to be closely scrutinized by New Century's creditors, because the two companies have a long and close relationship. In 2004, New Century helped finance the creation of Carrington, which bought subprime mortgages from New Century and Fremont General and packaged them into bonds that were sold to investors.</p>
        <p>New Century once owned a majority stake in Carrington, which is based in Greenwich, Conn., though its interest had dwindled to 7 percent as of the end of 2005.</p>
        <p>Officials at Carrington did not return a phone call yesterday.</p>
        <p>That leaves New Century's mortgage origination business, which originated $60 billion in mortgages last year. The company was second only to HSBC Finance, the American mortgage division of the large London-based bank, in issuing subprime mortgages in 2006.</p>
        <p>Still, New Century's mortgage origination operation may attract few bidders, according to analysts because the business has not been accepting loans for the last three weeks and it is one of many similar businesses up for sale now.</p>
        <p>Last month, Citadel Investment, a hedge fund, agreed to buy the mortgage origination business of ResMae for $22 million in a bankruptcy auction. H&amp;R Block, the accounting and tax preparation firm, recently missed a self-imposed end-of-March deadline to sell its subprime mortgage business, Option One.</p>
        <p>And yesterday, Barclays Capital, the London-based bank, said that it had closed its purchase of EquiFirst, a subprime mortgage lender, for $76 million, which is a third of the $225 million it agreed to pay in January.</p>
        <p>''Frankly, I'm not sure the origination platform is worth anything right now,'' said Christopher C. Brendler, an analyst with Stifel Nicolaus, ''because of the name, and the fact that so much of the sales force, which dealt with the independent brokers, have already started to leave.''</p>
        <p>Also, state regulators in California, New York and several other states have restricted New Century from making new loans because it was unable to close on thousands of mortgages when it ran into its liquidity squeeze.</p>
        <p>In an indication that the company could get some relief from regulators, New Century said yesterday that it had disposed of all 27,000 loans it had in its pipeline when it stopped taking applications on March 12.</p>
        <p>Given the precarious nature of the subprime mortgage business, it is unclear how much creditors will recover in the bankruptcy proceeding. The company's filing yesterday did not provide details on how much money it owes other than to say it was more than $100 million.</p>
        <p>Earlier, New Century said it owed $17.4 billion on credit lines from investment banks; most of those debts were secured by loans that New Century made with those funds. Many of those banks, which declared New Century in default in early March, began seizing the loans or auctioning them off in the last two weeks.</p>
        <p>The results of those auctions, which have not been disclosed, would provide an important benchmark of what New Century's assets and loan portfolios are worth, said Zach Gast, an analyst at the Center for Financial Research and Analysis. ''The bids for the loans put up for auction will provide a pretty good estimate of how much debtholders will be hurt,'' Mr. Gast said.</p>
        <p>New Century is being advised by Lazard, the investment bank, and AlixPartners, a consulting firm. Its bankruptcy case is being handled by the law firm of O'Melveny &amp; Myers.</p>
        <p>''This was a very hard step for me personally and clearly not the outcome I would have preferred,'' Brad A. Morrice, New Century's president and chief executive and one of its three co-founders, said in a statement. ''However, given the sudden and significant challenges facing our industry and New Century specifically, bankruptcy is the best means available to allow the company's assets and operations to be sold through an orderly process.''</p>
        <p>The bankruptcy proceeding, however, may not be the last word for some executives and board members at New Century. The company and its officials are the subject of two federal investigations and numerous class-action lawsuits.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
