<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Disciplinary Hearings Put N.F.L. Union in Awkward Position</title>
    <meta content="03nfl" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/sports/football/03nfl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837757"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Cincinnati Bengals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Tennessee Titans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Football League</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Upshaw, Gene</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jones, Pacman</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE0DC1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="458" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Disciplinary Hearings Put N.F.L. Union in Awkward Position</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Disciplinary Hearings Leave N.F.L. Union in Awkward Spot</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With disciplinary hearings scheduled today for Tennessee Titans cornerback Pacman Jones and Cincinnati Bengals receiver Chris Henry, the N.F.L. players union could find itself caught between some angry players and a much larger group that applauds the crackdown.</p>
        <p>The hearings could lead to lengthy suspensions for Jones and Henry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The players union could find itself caught between angry members who receive severe discipline and a much larger group who applaud the crackdown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With disciplinary hearings scheduled today for Tennessee Titans cornerback Pacman Jones and Cincinnati Bengals receiver Chris Henry, the N.F.L. players union could find itself caught between some angry players and a much larger group that applauds the crackdown.</p>
        <p>The hearings could lead to lengthy suspensions for Jones and Henry.</p>
        <p>The union chief, Gene Upshaw, is in New York, and the player advisory council will meet with Commissioner Roger Goodell today to discuss the personal conduct policy that is expected to give Goodell broad powers to issue stronger punishments for players who repeatedly run afoul of the law.</p>
        <p>The policy, discussed at length at last week's N.F.L. annual meeting, is expected to be completed by the commissioner's office before the draft's first day on April 28.</p>
        <p>Upshaw and the council will also discuss the specifics of the cases that Goodell is grappling with now: those involving Jones, Henry and Chicago Bears defensive lineman Tank Johnson, who is serving a four-month prison sentence for a parole violation. Johnson also has a weapons charge pending.</p>
        <p>The union will not participate in the hearings for Jones and Henry. Jones, who has been questioned by the police in connection with 10 separate incidents but has no convictions, is expected to receive a lengthy suspension, perhaps as long as a full season, the maximum ban that is expected to be available under the new policy. Henry is one of nine Bengals arrested in the past year.</p>
        <p>After the hearings, Upshaw and his council will meet again with Goodell to discuss his findings and offer their opinions on a penalty. Goodell is likely to announce the discipline within 10 days.</p>
        <p>Last week, Jones's lawyer, Manny Arora, told The Associated Press that he was prepared to fight league discipline. That will leave the union in an unusual position.</p>
        <p>''We have a duty of fair representation for our players,'' Upshaw said. ''But we also understand we have to do something. What we have to do is look at each case and decide, and we don't want to do anything to prejudice a legal case.</p>
        <p>''The players understand this is something we have to solve. Fines are not working, so we have to find other ways to change behavior.''</p>
        <p>Troy Vincent, one of the union's most active members, has spoken several times to Jones, Upshaw said, and is concerned about his mental state. Upshaw said that Jones had little privacy, with gawkers parked in his driveway. Upshaw has no doubt that Jones will receive a suspension of some length, but says that the union and league will look at each case separately.</p>
        <p>''The problem with all this is whatever has happened, the players have brought it on themselves,'' Upshaw said. ''Every day it's been something.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
