<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Looking Fit, Murcer Makes a Return to the Booth</title>
    <meta content="03sandomir" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/sports/baseball/03sandomir.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837794"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Murcer, Bobby</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E2DB1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="887" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Looking Fit, Murcer Makes a Return to the Booth</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Looking Fit, Murcer Makes a Return to the Yankees Booth</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bobby Murcer saw the cream-colored Rolls-Royce that would take him to Yankee Stadium yesterday and uttered a mild protest about vehicular excess to his usual driver.</p>
        <p>''Oh, Anthony,'' he said, wishing that a less ostentatious Lincoln Town Car were leading him to his one of his most memorable entrances at Yankee Stadium since he was called up as a shortstop in September 1965.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A little more than three months removed from a diagnosis of incurable brain cancer and surgery to remove a tumor, Bobby Murcer looks remarkably fit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bobby Murcer saw the cream-colored Rolls-Royce that would take him to Yankee Stadium yesterday and uttered a mild protest about vehicular excess to his usual driver.</p>
        <p>''Oh, Anthony,'' he said, wishing that a less ostentatious Lincoln Town Car were leading him to his one of his most memorable entrances at Yankee Stadium since he was called up as a shortstop in September 1965.</p>
        <p>Murcer, 60, is a little more than three months removed from a diagnosis of incurable brain cancer and surgery to remove a malignant tumor. But except for having lost his hair, he looks remarkably fit. He has lost some muscle tone, but his weight is good thanks to the chocolate cake and the bagels with cream cheese that his wife, Kay, urges on him to keep his calorie intake up.</p>
        <p>''God sent me an angel,'' he said of Kay, whom he met when he was a slugging 10-year-old Little Leaguer in Oklahoma City and she was 8.</p>
        <p>Murcer has been lifting weights and riding a stationary bicycle. He tires a bit and has a pink but fading scar on his head. He enjoys showing off that he does not look emaciated or sick. But, in a not very ominous way, Murcer said: ''There's no cure for the cancer I have. They just want to treat it as a chronic disease.''</p>
        <p>He has completed his chemotherapy and radiation treatments and is in a clinical trial at M. D. Anderson Cancer Center in Houston. He takes a monthly vaccine that is supposed to kill off new cancer cells if they develop and multiply. He may need to take the vaccine for the rest of his life.</p>
        <p>''We want to keep the cancer in check,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As the Rolls-Royce neared the Stadium, Murcer discussed the peace offered by his and Kay's strengthened faith. ''In a Christian's life,'' he said, ''you get so busy that you forget about God, but this is his creation, and he's in charge. This has been a godsend. We know who's in charge.''</p>
        <p>He said that he fully appreciated the often grim survival rate for patients with the type of tumor he had -- glioblastoma multiforme -- but chooses to believe he will live much longer.</p>
        <p>''They go through these percentages, but I don't think of me in there,'' he said. ''It's someone else. Not me. People think we're in denial. We're not.''</p>
        <p>Murcer is, for now, fortunate. John Vukovich, a former Phillies player and coach whom Murcer played against when he was a Cub and Giant, died of brain cancer on March 8. ''Of course I think about him,'' Murcer said. ''Of course. But I don't know if he had the same cancer.''</p>
        <p>Murcer decided late last week to come to New York on opening day to visit the YES Network booth. Now, he said, he can arrange a regular schedule of games and studio work for YES around his monthly vaccines.</p>
        <p>''I have a new three-year deal with YES,'' said Murcer, who is in his 24th season as a team broadcaster, ''and I'm going to be here when they open the new stadium in 2009.''</p>
        <p>At the Stadium, some fans looked twice at Murcer, with his full head of silver hair now down to some stubble, as he walked toward them.</p>
        <p>Downstairs in the press dining room, he was embraced in a bear hug by Ken Singleton, his YES colleague.</p>
        <p>''I missed you a whole lot,'' he said directly into Murcer's ear.</p>
        <p>''Hello, sweetheart, I love you!'' Murcer said to Suzyn Waldman, who calls Yankee games on WCBS Radio. ''Thanks for everything you did.''</p>
        <p>Waldman, a breast cancer survivor, sent him care packages with boxes of lemon drops to stimulate taste buds deadened by his treatments.</p>
        <p>''Welcome back and God bless you,'' the public-address announcer Bob Sheppard said as he wrapped Murcer in a surprisingly long and tight grip, and confided that his daughter was being treated at M. D. Anderson.</p>
        <p>Murcer watched the first two innings in the Babe Ruth Suite, where he was embraced some more, before he walked with his wife to the YES booth to join Singleton, Michael Kay and Joe Girardi for the third inning.</p>
        <p>Their boss, John Filippelli, has been concerned for weeks about the effect that traveling to games from Oklahoma City, and calling them, might have on Murcer's health. Filippelli, YES's president of production, has reason for concern: one of his two sons, Pierce, 17, has been in remission from Burkitt's lymphoma for two years. ''Bobby looks good and feels good,'' Filippelli said, ''but if I sense fatigue, we'll play things accordingly.''</p>
        <p>Murcer stood between Singleton and Girardi for one inning, and then a second, his voice strong as he offered bits of analysis. ''I can't tell you I know everything about baseball,'' he said, ''but I'll just make it up like I always do.''</p>
        <p>He acknowledged fans who rose and cheered for him, and Yankees players who climbed to the front steps of the dugout to wave to him, when prompted by a scoreboard message. ''Bob-by Mur-cer!'' fans chanted.</p>
        <p>''You think this is great for everybody,'' he said in response to a remark by Kay, who said he idolized Murcer as a ''shining light'' on a bad Yankee team when he was a youngster. ''But this is great for me.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
