<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Better New York Budget</title>
    <meta content="03tues2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/opinion/03tues2.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837730"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Editorial"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spitzer, Eliot (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Spitzer, Eliot L</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907EEDD1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="500" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Better New York Budget</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Better New York Budget</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial says Gov Eliot Spitzer of New York has gotten off to good start with his first state budget; says he made some compromises, but won important and fundamental changes in way state operates</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After Gov. Eliot Spitzer, a self-declared ''steamroller,'' negotiated his first state budget last weekend, legislators were gleeful. A few even boasted publicly that for all of Mr. Spitzer's brash talk, he had been easily flattened by the old hands in Albany.</p>
        <p>Such celebrations should be short-lived. Mr. Spitzer made some compromises, but in exchange he won important and fundamental changes in the way the state operates. New Yorkers who yearn for a government that works more for its citizens than for the stale, political subculture in Albany should soon be able to recognize that Mr. Spitzer has gotten off to a good start.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New Yorkers who yearn for a government that works more for its citizens than for the political subculture in Albany should soon be able to recognize that Gov. Eliot Spitzer has gotten off to a good start.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After Gov. Eliot Spitzer, a self-declared ''steamroller,'' negotiated his first state budget last weekend, legislators were gleeful. A few even boasted publicly that for all of Mr. Spitzer's brash talk, he had been easily flattened by the old hands in Albany.</p>
        <p>Such celebrations should be short-lived. Mr. Spitzer made some compromises, but in exchange he won important and fundamental changes in the way the state operates. New Yorkers who yearn for a government that works more for its citizens than for the stale, political subculture in Albany should soon be able to recognize that Mr. Spitzer has gotten off to a good start.</p>
        <p>The most regrettable loss for reform was the secretive way this $121 billion budget was negotiated. Mr. Spitzer came to Albany promising to destroy its backroom culture, yet when Sunday's deadline loomed, he succumbed to horse-trading state assets behind closed doors. He should plan on creating New York's next budget in the sunlight with more of the key negotiating sessions open to the public.</p>
        <p>Still, there were important signs of progress. This year's budget finally establishes a new formula for school financing that tries to disburse state dollars based on need rather than political clout. Clout still mattered: Long Island senators managed to extract millions of dollars in extra financing for their affluent suburban school districts. But by fixing the underlying formula -- and making clear which legislators were intent on grabbing an unfair share -- Mr. Spitzer laid the groundwork for more equitable spending in coming years. He has also made it easy to pick out legislators -- four Republican senators from New York City come immediately to mind -- who are so docile that they are willing to side with their leaders, even when it means less money for needy schools in their own districts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer also scored important victories on health care; mainly, the budget expands health insurance in ways that could make New York a leader in the nation. At the same time, this is the first budget in years that significantly reins in Medicaid costs. Mr. Spitzer accomplished this by being willing to endure a surge of union-sponsored attack ads. He insisted on requiring health care interests to battle for state financing along with everybody else. His approach is a welcome change from Gov. George Pataki's policy of literally giving the health care workers' union a seat at secret budget negotiations.</p>
        <p>There is still more in the budget to be pleased about. There are tax cuts targeted to the middle class. Business tax loopholes will be closed, with some of the savings used to start lowering overall business taxes. There is a new whistleblower statute to help curb Medicaid fraud, and money for embryonic stem cell research -- two items Republicans have resisted for years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer did not get everything he wanted, and this 2,000-page budget may yet hold unpleasant surprises. But over all, the governor's first budget offers some assurance to New Yorkers that he is aiming this huge battleship in the right direction.</p>
        <p>Editorial</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
