<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>EMI to Drop Digital Locks In Web Sales</title>
    <meta content="03music" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/technology/03music.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837766"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Copyrights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Audio)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Apple Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Emi Group Plc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crampton, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nicoli, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jobs, Steven P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leeds, Jeff</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Copyrights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Copyrights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">EMI Group Plc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Apple Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04EEDC1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1139" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>EMI to Drop Digital Locks In Web Sales</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">EMI to Drop Digital Locks in Web Sales</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF LEEDS; Thomas Crampton contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crampton, Thomas; Leeds, Jeff</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>British music giant EMI Group breaks ranks with music industry's biggest corporations by announcing deal to sell songs online through Apple's music service without copy protection; shift means that consumers who buy music by EMI acts may have easier time navigating current jumble of incompatible software in digital music world; consumers who buy unprotected music from iTunes store will be able to play music on variety of devices, not just iPods, and be able to burn unlimited play lists of songs; unprotected music will come at higher price, $1.29 per song, though Apple says songs will have better sound quality; standard-quality versions of same songs, with copy protection, will still be available for 99 cents; Apple will sell albums from EMI artists for regular price, which is generally $9.99; many analysts view deal, announced by EMI chief Eric L Nicoli and Apple chief Steven P Jobs, as first step in broader shift toward all music being sold without antipiracy software; some hope it could also jump-start digital sales for music industry; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EMI Group, the British music giant, broke ranks with the music industry's biggest corporations yesterday by announcing a deal to sell songs online through Apple's music service without copy protection.</p>
        <p>The move by EMI, which ranks last among the four music companies in sales of new music in the United States, represents a significant change of course at a time when the music industry is straining to bolster digital sales as the business of selling the two-decade-old compact disc format continues to erode.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a significant shift, EMI will sell songs online through Apple’s music service without copy protection.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EMI Group, the British music giant, broke ranks with the music industry's biggest corporations yesterday by announcing a deal to sell songs online through Apple's music service without copy protection.</p>
        <p>The move by EMI, which ranks last among the four music companies in sales of new music in the United States, represents a significant change of course at a time when the music industry is straining to bolster digital sales as the business of selling the two-decade-old compact disc format continues to erode.</p>
        <p>Like the industry's other major companies, EMI, home to groups like the Rolling Stones and Korn, had long insisted on the sale of its music online with electronic locks to reduce piracy.</p>
        <p>The shift means that consumers who buy music by EMI acts may have an easier time navigating the current jumble of incompatible software in the digital music world. Consumers who buy the unprotected music from the iTunes store will be able to play the music on a variety of devices -- not just iPods -- and be able to burn unlimited play lists of songs.</p>
        <p>The unprotected music will come at a higher price, $1.29 a song, though Apple said the songs would have better sound quality. Standard-quality versions of the same songs, with copy protection, will still be available for 99 cents. But to entice more consumers to buy full albums, Apple will sell albums from EMI artists -- without the antipiracy software and in the higher quality -- for the regular price, which is generally $9.99.</p>
        <p>Many analysts viewed the deal, announced in London by EMI's chief, Eric L. Nicoli, and Apple's chief, Steven P. Jobs, as a first step in a broader shift toward all music being sold without antipiracy software. Some expressed hope it could also jumpstart digital sales for the music industry. Since the start of the year, the slide in plastic CD sales has accelerated, down more than 20 percent, according to Nielsen SoundScan data.</p>
        <p>''Things will never be the same,'' said Phil Leigh, a senior analyst at Inside Digital Media, a Florida-based research company.</p>
        <p>But others suggest that the partnership is a more isolated instance of two companies joining up amid overlapping agendas. EMI has been working to right itself after a management shake-up and a series of setbacks, including two profit warnings this year. Apple, for its part, has been trying to resolve complaints from European consumer advocates, who say its system should be made to work with rivals' hardware and software.</p>
        <p>Apple may yet have more headaches looming, however. European Commission officials confirmed yesterday that the company -- and the major record companies -- are facing an antitrust inquiry over the pricing of songs on the iTunes service.</p>
        <p>Jonathan Todd, spokesman for Neelie Kroes, the European Union's competition commissioner, said in Brussels that Apple and several of the major music companies, including EMI, Warner and Universal, were being investigated over concerns that the sale of music through iTunes flouts the union's antitrust regulations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Todd said the commission last week sent a formal ''statement of objections'' to Apple and the record companies contending that iTunes was breaching competition rules by preventing consumers in one country from downloading songs more cheaply from the Apple Internet store in another country. He said this violated antitrust rules because prices differed across the 27-member bloc, limiting consumer choice.</p>
        <p>The use of copy protection software has meant in practice that songs purchased from iTunes can be played only on the company's iPod. Apple has declined to share its proprietary protection software with competing companies, effectively locking them out of the iPod. As a result, some music labels have considered dropping their demand for protection software altogether to allow rival music services to sell music that could play on Apple's device.</p>
        <p>While some of EMI's rivals have been testing sales of music in unprotected form, the company's move did not appear to prompt any immediate retreat from antipiracy software. A spokesman for Warner Music Group declined to comment but referred back to comments made in February by the company's chief executive, Edgar Bronfman Jr., who said, ''There is no reason to conclude that music is the one content category that should not or cannot be protected simply because there is an unprotected legacy product available,'' referring to CDs.</p>
        <p>Representatives for the two bigger music companies -- the Universal Music Group of Vivendi and Sony BMG, a partnership between Sony and Bertelsmann -- declined to comment yesterday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jobs, however, was unequivocal in his prediction that the industry would eventually reduce its use of copy protection. He said that he expected more than half of the songs on iTunes would be available in unprotected versions by year's end.</p>
        <p>Apple executives predicted the new structure would lead to a surge in sales, but if it did not, the company might benefit by soothing tensions with European authorities. Critics ranging from Norway's principal consumer rights group to lawmakers in France have taken Apple to task -- and to court -- for making music purchased from iTunes compatible only with the iPod.</p>
        <p>Some of the Europeans most critical of Mr. Jobs and iTunes praised the move yesterday. ''Today marks the beginning of a new era -- an era where the entertainment industry works with the customer and not against them,'' Torgeir Waterhouse, a senior adviser in Norway's Consumer Council, said in a statement.</p>
        <p>The music companies had resisted freeing up their digital tracks from restrictions because they were afraid consumers would make copious copies that would deprive the companies and their recording artists of revenue.</p>
        <p>But peer-to-peer Internet services that freely trade music files have flourished anyway, with 5 billion downloads last year, compared with 509 million songs downloaded from official digital music services, according to NPD Group.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nicoli said early market tests showed EMI that consumers overwhelmingly preferred to purchase tracks without copy protection, even at a higher cost. Unrestricted tracks outsold the others at a rate of 10 to one, Mr. Nicoli said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jobs emphasized how much the music labels had benefited from sales over iTunes. The service, he said, ''has brought more than $1 billion in revenues to the record companies at no addition cost to them.''</p>
        <p>To some in the music industry, though, EMI's move only punctuated the fact that the industry has failed to build a more robust digital business after years of watching its sales base crumble.</p>
        <p>''This appears to be the final acknowledgment on the record companies' part that the guiding principles of their digital distribution strategies have been fundamentally flawed,'' said Ken Hertz, a longtime music industry lawyer who represents artists including Beyoncé and the Black Eyed Peas.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hertz said injecting higher prices into iTunes would drive more consumers to download music from unlicensed free services. ''The consumer's conscience, which is all we had left, that's gone, too.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
