<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yankees Remember Lidle, Then, Steadily, How to Win</title>
    <meta content="03yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/sports/baseball/03yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837828"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Devil Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Tampa Bay Devil Rays</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Rodriguez, Alex</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Giambi, Jason</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Lidle, Cory</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Damon, Johnny</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kazmir, Scott</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Pavano, Carl</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E7DA1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1041" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yankees Remember Lidle, Then, Steadily, How to Win</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Yanks First Remember Lidle in First Victory</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER; Michael S. Schmidt contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A construction crane peeks over the left-field grandstand at Yankee Stadium now, a reminder of new beginnings. There will be only one more opening day at the old ballpark, with a new one rising in two years.</p>
        <p>There is still time to make memories at 161st Street and River Avenue, and the Yankees added a few yesterday. It was not a crisply played opener, but the result satisfied the crowd of 55,035. The Yankees whipped the Tampa Bay Devil Rays, 9-5, losing a lead and then storming back for the last six runs of the game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was not a crisply played opener, but the Yankees' come-from-behind victory over Tampa Bay satisfied the home crowd.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A construction crane peeks over the left-field grandstand at Yankee Stadium now, a reminder of new beginnings. There will be only one more opening day at the old ballpark, with a new one rising in two years.</p>
        <p>There is still time to make memories at 161st Street and River Avenue, and the Yankees added a few yesterday. It was not a crisply played opener, but the result satisfied the crowd of 55,035. The Yankees whipped the Tampa Bay Devil Rays, 9-5, losing a lead and then storming back for the last six runs of the game.</p>
        <p>''We didn't start real good,'' said Alex Rodriguez, who made an error and struck out in the first inning, ''but we finished strong.''</p>
        <p>Rodriguez capped the game with a two-run homer to center field in the eighth inning, earning a curtain call from the fans. Jason Giambi drove in three runs, including the tie breaker with a seventh-inning single, on a day that was especially poignant.</p>
        <p>Giambi played a somber role before the game, standing beside Cory Lidle's widow, Melanie, and 6-year-old son, Christopher, during a tribute on the field. Giambi was a high school teammate of Lidle's, the former Yankees pitcher who died Oct. 11 when his small plane crashed into a Manhattan high rise. Melanie and Christopher threw ceremonial first pitches as Lidle's parents and twin brother looked on.</p>
        <p>''That was probably one of the toughest things I've ever had to do in my life, trying to be strong for Melanie,'' Giambi said. ''I've known her for a long time, and I've seen his son grow up. It was a tough day.''</p>
        <p>Giambi has known Melanie Lidle since high school, and he said that she thanked him for being there. The Yankees, she said, treated her like family.</p>
        <p>''I am hanging in there,'' she said. ''My friends get me through everything, and my family are a big support. It is hard to come back here, but I knew if I didn't I would have regretted it, and I am really glad I did.''</p>
        <p>When Giambi drove in two runs with a single in his first at-bat, he clapped his hands after reaching first base. He is not given to emotional displays on the field, but he said he was thinking of Lidle.</p>
        <p>''You try to turn it into a positive and play well,'' Giambi said. ''Especially the way Cory lived life -- from his flying to poker to all the passions in life, he was one of those go-getters. I got the big hit, that first one, out of the way.''</p>
        <p>As much as opening day can symbolize renewal and hope for fans, there is also that element for players: getting things out of the way. Of all the Yankees, Carl Pavano most needed a fresh start. After 643 days, he finally returned to the mound.</p>
        <p>Various injuries had kept Pavano from pitching since June 27, 2005. According to the Elias Sports Bureau, no pitcher had started an opener after such a long absence since 1956, when Vinegar Bend Mizell came back after two years in the military to start for the St. Louis Cardinals.</p>
        <p>Pavano has no such colorful nickname, although The Daily News dubbed him Butthead on its back page during spring training. There were no bruised buttocks yesterday and no other repeat injuries. There was simply a so-so pitching line, and that is all the Yankees really asked.</p>
        <p>Pavano pitched four and one-third innings, allowing five runs (four earned) on six hits and two walks, with two strikeouts. He let a 3-1 lead slip away, but it was not all his fault. The infielders made three errors behind him, and the Devil Rays ran often on left fielder Hideki Matsui.</p>
        <p>''We need to make plays behind him when we've got a lead,'' said Jorge Posada, who homered in the fourth. ''But his ball was moving; he was getting ahead of the hitters and working down in the zone. It seemed like he was eager to get the ball.''</p>
        <p>Before the game, Pavano said, he was bouncing around the clubhouse anxiously, switching from this chair to that before the 1:10 start. ''I couldn't sit still,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Through four innings, he allowed one unearned run, after an error by Derek Jeter in the second. But Elijah Dukes led off the fifth with a long home run to center in his first official major league at-bat.</p>
        <p>Consecutive singles brought in another run, and first baseman Josh Phelps threw wildly to center field after cutting off a throw from right, advancing Carl Crawford to second. With the score tied, 3-3, Rocco Baldelli singled to put Tampa Bay ahead and chase Pavano.</p>
        <p>A single against Brian Bruney made the score 5-3, but Bruney escaped the inning and four relievers followed with a scoreless inning apiece. Mariano Rivera finished by striking out the side in the ninth.</p>
        <p>The Tampa Bay bullpen struggled, as the Yankees could have predicted. The Yankees' goal was to see as little as possible of Scott Kazmir, the Devil Rays' starter. There were five left-handed hitters in the Yankees' lineup and Kazmir is a left-handed All-Star.</p>
        <p>The best hope for the Yankees was to make Kazmir labor and then pounce on the bullpen, which has no left-handers. The Yankees saw 35 pitches in the first inning, and by the time Kazmir left with two on and no outs in the sixth, he had thrown 107.</p>
        <p>After a pinch-hit sacrifice bunt by Doug Mientkiewicz and a hit batsman, Jeter tied the score with a two-run single up the middle against Shawn Camp. Rodriguez then hit a hard single past shortstop Ben Zobrist in the seventh, followed by a stolen base and Giambi's go-ahead hit against Brian Stokes.</p>
        <p>By the time Rodriguez homered in the eighth, the soupy skies had given way to sunshine. The setting was old, but the memories were fresh, and the Yankees had won their home opener again. They have done so for 10 years in a row, the longest stretch in team history.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Johnny Damon left the game after five innings with cramps in both legs but said he expected to play in the next game, tomorrow afternoon.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
