<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Professor Who Keeps the Circus Dressed to Thrill</title>
    <meta content="03circus" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/nyregion/03circus.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837724"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Circuses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Costumes, Theatrical</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ringling Brothers and Barnum &amp; Bailey Circus</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rutgers, the State University of New Jersey</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murin, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mallozzi, Vincent</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Circuses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jeans (Apparel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Circuses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Ringling Bros and Barnum &amp; Bailey Circus</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EFDD1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="863" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Professor Who Keeps the Circus Dressed to Thrill</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With Professor’s Designs, Circus Is Dressed to Thrill</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VINCENT MALLOZZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mallozzi, Vincent</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of David Murin, professor of costume design at Rutgers, who is preparing for opening night of Ringling Brothers and Barnum &amp; Bailey circus in New York City; he designed nearly 400 costumes for this season's show; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Beneath the high wires being hung from the ceiling at Madison Square Garden, David Murin was on a winding, frenetic walk to women's wardrobe.</p>
        <p>He sidestepped stacks of Hula-Hoops and giant gyroscopes and raced past a couple of Clydesdales that were having a bath. Mr. Murin hugged Taba, the tiger trainer, and saluted a small army of acrobats who were loosening their double-jointed limbs in the dimly lighted, elephant-scented bowels of the arena.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For David Murin, a professor of costume design at Rutgers University, nothing beats the excitement of having been selected costume designer for the circus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Beneath the high wires being hung from the ceiling at Madison Square Garden, David Murin was on a winding, frenetic walk to women's wardrobe.</p>
        <p>He sidestepped stacks of Hula-Hoops and giant gyroscopes and raced past a couple of Clydesdales that were having a bath. Mr. Murin hugged Taba, the tiger trainer, and saluted a small army of acrobats who were loosening their double-jointed limbs in the dimly lighted, elephant-scented bowels of the arena.</p>
        <p>Mr. Murin, along with every man, woman and mammal in the building, was getting ready on Friday for the first of 30 performances of the Ringling Brothers and Barnum &amp; Bailey circus at the Garden. The run ends on April 15.</p>
        <p>''I'm very excited,'' Mr. Murin said, without breaking his stride or his smile. ''This isn't just opening night in any other city; this is opening night in New York.''</p>
        <p>He finally reached his destination, a room filled with colorful costumes, wigs, shoes and ironing boards. He immediately began taking inventory, making sure that every bead, button, crystal and diamond stud was as securely fastened as the padlocks on Taba's tiger cages. A thimble and thread waited in the wings -- just in case.</p>
        <p>''This is where the chorus ladies and the Chinese acrobats dress,'' Mr. Murin said. ''The lead acts have their own dressing room.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Murin, a 54-year-old professor of costume design at Rutgers University, has created the look and feel of costumes worn by actors in more than 200 theatrical settings, including Broadway, Off Broadway, opera, ballet and television.</p>
        <p>Even though he had sewn for stage productions like ''Steel Magnolias'' and ''Mixed Emotions'' and for the soap opera ''Ryan's Hope'' (for which he received an Emmy Award in 1981), Mr. Murin said he was just about doing somersaults after he received a call from Nicole Feld, a producer of the circus, in March 2006. Ms. Feld informed Mr. Murin that he had been selected as the costume designer for the Greatest Show on Earth.</p>
        <p>''I was thrilled when I got the job, but I was scared to death because it was so daunting,'' said Mr. Murin, who has lived in Greenwich Village since the early 1970s. ''Sure, I had done Broadway musicals and television, but this was gigantic, a show seen by millions and millions of people. It doesn't get any bigger than the circus.''</p>
        <p>The moment he put down the phone, Mr. Murin, sketch pad in hand, marched into his SoHo studio and began poring through books and old photographs and other reference materials to get his creative juices flowing.</p>
        <p>By January, when Ringling Brothers opened its season in Tampa, Fla., Mr. Murin had designed nearly 400 costumes -- at a cost of roughly a million dollars -- to be worn by a cast that includes about 100 performers. Some of Mr. Murin's best and brightest creations are worn by Bello Nock, the daredevil clown who is the star of the three-ring extravaganza; Ty McFarlan, the ringmaster; Taba de Campos; Nikolas Wallenda, Bello's sidekick atop the Wheel of Steel; and Erendira Wallenda, the fantasy goddess whom Bello pines for throughout much of the two-hour show.</p>
        <p>''David is an amazing designer with terrific energy and impeccable taste,'' said Ms. Feld, who co-produces the show with her father, Kenneth. ''What really amazed me about him was his imagination, and I was also impressed to learn that he teaches costume design at Rutgers. What that tells me is that David is hip and relevant with today's youth, and that he has a real passion for what he does.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Feld pointed out that Mr. Murin's costumes are expected to last for roughly 1,000 performances in 90 American cities during a two-year span.</p>
        <p>''Not only do these performers have to wear these costumes every day, but they are risking their lives in them,'' she said. ''Therefore, the costumes have to be delicate, and yet be made with industrial quality.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Murin said he has wanted to run away and join the circus since he was a 5-year-old growing up in Lower Burrell, a suburb of Pittsburgh.</p>
        <p>''When the circus came to my town, I was as equally interested in the sets and clothing that were a part of the show as I was with the actual performances,'' he said. ''All those lights and colors and sounds, it really gave me an appreciation for theater.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Murin said he began working ''on little sets'' at St. Margaret Mary, an elementary school in Lower Burrell, and joined the theater club at Burrell High School.</p>
        <p>''I tried acting in high school, but my hands would shake onstage,'' he recalled. ''I realized that design was the next best thing. My work was still onstage, but I didn't have to physically be out there.''</p>
        <p>He took his act to New York University, to study all aspects of theatrical design, including sets, lighting and costumes, but by the end of his sophomore year he had found his true calling.</p>
        <p>''I really like working with the human form, so I began to focus on clothes,'' he said. ''But I never dreamed I'd get to work for the circus, which really was my first true love in theater.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
