<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sanctuary for Sex Slaves</title>
    <meta content="03kristof" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/opinion/03kristof.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837705"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Columnist"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prostitution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pakistan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kristof, Nicholas D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mukhtaran Bibi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Parveen, Shakira</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Nicholas D Kristof</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prostitution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prostitution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Pakistan</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE5DD1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="744" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sanctuary for Sex Slaves</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sanctuary for Sex Slaves</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS D. KRISTOF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kristof, Nicholas D</byline>
      <dateline>Meerwala, Pakistan</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nicholas D Kristof Op-Ed column describes plight of Pakistani woman Shakira Parveen, forced by her husband to become prostitute and refused help from police who are on the take; says nexus of sex trafficking and police corruption is common in developing countries; says poor women and girls who are victimized equally by pimps and by police do have one savior--Mukhtar Mai, also known as Mukhtaran Bibi, who was also victimized but now runs schools and aid organization for Pakistani women, including Shakira Parveen (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If the thought has ever flitted through your mind that your spouse isn't 100 percent perfect, then just contemplate what Shakira Parveen is going through. And give your own husband or wife a hug.</p>
        <p>When Ghulam Fareed proposed marriage to Ms. Parveen, he fingered prayer beads and seemed gentle and pious. Ms. Parveen didn't know him well, but she and her family were impressed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Neo-slavery is the plight of millions of girls and young women (and smaller numbers of boys) around the world, particularly in Asia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If the thought has ever flitted through your mind that your spouse isn't 100 percent perfect, then just contemplate what Shakira Parveen is going through. And give your own husband or wife a hug.</p>
        <p>When Ghulam Fareed proposed marriage to Ms. Parveen, he fingered prayer beads and seemed gentle and pious. Ms. Parveen didn't know him well, but she and her family were impressed.</p>
        <p>''The first month of marriage was O.K.,'' Ms. Parveen recalled. ''And then he said, you have to do whatever I tell you. If I tell you to sleep with other men, you have to do that.''</p>
        <p>It turned out that Mr. Fareed was running a brothel and selling drugs, and he intended Ms. Parveen to be his newest prostitute. ''I said, 'No, I don't want to sleep with other men,' '' she said, but he beat her unconscious with sticks, broke her bones and at one point set fire to her clothes. Finally, she broke and assented.</p>
        <p>Her ''husband'' locked her up in one room, she said, and the only people she saw were customers. ''For two years, I never left the house,'' she said.</p>
        <p>This kind of neo-slavery is the plight of millions of girls and young women (and smaller numbers of boys) around the world, particularly in Asia. A major difference from 19th-century slavery is that these victims are dead of AIDS by their 20s.</p>
        <p>Finally, Ms. Parveen was able to escape and return to her family, but Mr. Fareed was furious and began to torment her family, saying he would let up only if she returned to the brothel as his prostitute. Then Mr. Fareed's gang pressured Ms. Parveen by kidnapping her younger brother, Uzman, who was in the fifth grade. Uzman says that his hands and feet were shackled, and he was raped daily by many different men, apparently pimped to paying customers.</p>
        <p>The gang members explained that they would release the boy if Ms. Parveen returned to the brothel, and she contemplated suicide.</p>
        <p>After six weeks, Uzman escaped while his captors became drunk and left him unshackled. But when Ms. Parveen and her parents went to the police, the officers just laughed at them. Mr. Fareed and other gang members worked hand in glove with the police, the family says.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the police even arrested Ms. Parveen's father, who is one-legged because of a train accident (that is one reason for the family's poverty). Apparently on the gang's orders, the police held him for two weeks, in which time he says he was beaten mercilessly. The police are also searching for Ms. Parveen's brothers, who have gone into hiding.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fareed also threatened to kidnap and prostitute Ms. Parveen's younger sister, Naima, a 10th-grader who was ranked first in her class of 40 girls. Panic-stricken, the parents pulled Naima out of school and sent her to relatives far away. So her dreams of becoming a doctor have been dashed. (For readers who want to help, I've posted some suggestions on my blog: www.nytimes.com/ontheground.)</p>
        <p>This nexus of sex trafficking and police corruption is common in developing countries. The problem is typically not so much that laws are inadequate; it is that brothel owners buy the police and the courts.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Parveen's tale arises not only from corruption, but also from poverty.</p>
        <p>''If I had money, this wouldn't be happening,'' said Ms. Parveen's mother, Akbari Begum. ''It's all about money. In the police station, nobody listens to me. The police listen to those who sell narcotics.''</p>
        <p>''God should never grant daughters to poor people,'' she added. ''God should not give sisters to poor brothers. Because we're poor, we can't fight for them. It's very hard for poor people, because they take our daughters and dishonor them. There's nothing we can do.''</p>
        <p>Yet in a land where poor women and girls are victimized equally by pimps and by the police, they do have one savior -- Mukhtar Mai. She is the woman I've visited and written about often (she also uses the name Mukhtaran Bibi).</p>
        <p>After being sentenced to be gang-raped by a tribal council for a supposed offense of her brother, Mukhtar refused to commit suicide and instead prosecuted her attackers. And then she used compensation money (and donations from Times readers) to run schools and an aid organization for Pakistani women.</p>
        <p>It was in Mukhtar's extraordinary sanctuary that I met Ms. Parveen. In my Sunday column, I'll tell more about Mukhtar today.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Columnist</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
