<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Foundations' Giving Is Said To Have Set Record in '06</title>
    <meta content="03foundation" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/us/03foundation.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837720"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Grants (Corporate and Foundation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grants (Corporate and Foundation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Foundation Center</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E1DD1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="731" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Foundations' Giving Is Said To Have Set Record in '06</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Foundations’ Giving Is Said to Have Set Record in ’06</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE STROM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strom, Stephanie</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Giving by foundations climbed past $40 billion last year, according to estimates by the Foundation Center, breaking a record of $36.4 billion set in 2005.</p>
        <p>The center, a research and educational group, attributed the increase to a strong stock market but also to the establishment of a new breed of foundations whose contributions are greater than those of many older counterparts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Giving by foundations climbed past $40 billion last year, according to estimates by the Foundation Center, breaking a record of $36.4 billion set in 2005.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Giving by foundations climbed past $40 billion last year, according to estimates by the Foundation Center, breaking a record of $36.4 billion set in 2005.</p>
        <p>The center, a research and educational group, attributed the increase to a strong stock market but also to the establishment of a new breed of foundations whose contributions are greater than those of many older counterparts.</p>
        <p>''The new foundations being created today are much bigger,'' said Sara L. Engelhardt, the center's president, ''and much more money is moving through them at a faster pace than through older foundations.''</p>
        <p>In addition, some of the increase is almost certainly attributable to the donation of drugs by foundations associated with pharmaceutical companies. While the center has no estimate for 2006, such donations in 2005 were valued at $3.2 billion, an increase of 90 percent over the year before.</p>
        <p>The number of foundations in the country, the center said, had grown to 71,000 by the end of 2005, the latest year for which data are available in that category. That was an increase of more than 77 percent over a decade. More than 3,000 foundations were added to the ranks in 2005 alone, the third-largest single-year increase on record.</p>
        <p>Many of the new foundations, Ms. Engelhardt said, are controlled by living donors who are pushing larger amounts of money through them each year, spending more than the 5 percent of total assets that is required by law and that older foundations are more likely to give.</p>
        <p>That makes it harder for the center to come up with early estimates of foundation giving. The center estimated last year, for instance, that giving in 2005 was $33.6 billion, but in fact it was $36.4 billion, a 10.6 percent increase over the year before on an inflation-adjusted basis.</p>
        <p>Ms. Engelhardt said that while a number of things had played into the unexpectedly higher number for 2005 -- among them exceptional giving to address the Asian tsunami and Hurricane Katrina, and more robust giving by endowed foundations -- the practices of the newer foundations had certainly been a factor. Gifts are going out almost as fast as the money is flowing in, she said, ''and that's a big change from the past.''</p>
        <p>Consider the JEHT Foundation, established in 2000 by Jeanne Levy-Church, a movie producer and real estate heiress. In 2005 she contributed $27.2 million to the foundation, which spent $24.4 million on grants. The previous year she gave the foundation $23.4 million, and it made grants totaling $19.6 million. Since JEHT's founding, it has given away more than $62 million in support of programs aimed at criminal justice improvement, electoral reform and palliative care, among other things.</p>
        <p>''I've found it liberating,'' Robert Crane, the foundation's president and chief executive, said of its practice of spending most of what comes in each year. ''It allows us to be more driven by needs we see than by structures, which is how I think of the 5 percent model.''</p>
        <p>Richard L. Sprott, executive director of the Ellison Medical Foundation, said the practice of spending down assets each year saved money, because the foundation did not have to pay money managers or worry about market swings.</p>
        <p>''When the dot-com bubble burst, there were a number of traditional foundations that couldn't meet their commitments and had to worry about protecting their dollars,'' Dr. Sprott said. ''We didn't lose a penny. Larry may have had a bad day or two, but we didn't.''</p>
        <p>He was referring to Lawrence J. Ellison, founder of the Oracle Corporation and the Ellison foundation. In 2005, Mr. Ellison contributed $36 million in cash and stock to the foundation, which spent $26.3 million on grants to and symposiums for scientists doing research on the biology of aging, the foundation's chief focus. A year earlier, he gave it $38.3 million in stock, and it made grants totaling $33.1 million.</p>
        <p>Since the foundation was established a decade ago, it has given away $218 million.</p>
        <p>''Some years there is nothing in the bank on Dec. 31; other years there may be a little left over,'' Dr. Sprott said. ''There really is never any extra money around.''</p>
        <p>He said he thought the foundation reflected ''the kind of thinking that comes out of a philanthropist who made the money rather than inheriting it and wants to see the direct results of putting their money into an endeavor like this.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
