<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Top Chicago Police Official Resigns Amid Furor</title>
    <meta content="03chicago" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/us/03chicago.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837719"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois/Chicago</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Chicago (Ill)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E1DD1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="532" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Top Chicago Police Official Resigns Amid Furor</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Top Chicago Police Official Resigns Amid Furor</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN SAULNY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Saulny, Susan</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, April 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Police Superintendent Philip J. Cline resigned Monday amid a public outcry over the lack of swift disciplinary action against several police officers accused of involvement in two videotaped beatings of residents here in the last several months.</p>
        <p>Mayor Richard M. Daley accepted the resignation, alternately thanking Mr. Cline for bringing crime under control and chiding him for not responding appropriately to the recent events that, he said, ''tarnish the entire department.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Philip J. Cline announced that he would retire early as his department tries to deal with two highly publicized videotaped beatings involving off-duty police officers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Police Superintendent Philip J. Cline resigned Monday amid a public outcry over the lack of swift disciplinary action against several police officers accused of involvement in two videotaped beatings of residents here in the last several months.</p>
        <p>Mayor Richard M. Daley accepted the resignation, alternately thanking Mr. Cline for bringing crime under control and chiding him for not responding appropriately to the recent events that, he said, ''tarnish the entire department.''</p>
        <p>''In submitting his resignation, he took responsibility for the incidents of police misconduct that have occurred recently,'' Mr. Daley said at a news conference.</p>
        <p>He continued later, ''Like everyone else, I am outraged by the videos, which clearly show officer misconduct.''</p>
        <p>Widely viewed on the Web site YouTube among other places, one video showed a burly man, whom the authorities believe to be an off-duty police officer, beating a small woman who was tending bar in northwest Chicago.</p>
        <p>Although the attack happened in mid-February, it became public only last month as the video began circulating. Officer Anthony Abbate, who is accused of beating the bartender, faces charges of aggravated battery.</p>
        <p>In an attack that became public last week, the authorities say a downtown bar's surveillance camera showed six off-duty police officers beating four businessmen in December. On-duty officers were called to the scene, but one of the officers involved in the fight had them leave without taking action, the department has acknowledged.</p>
        <p>The police have not released that video, but the officers who were accused of involvement were removed from their assignments last week. Cook County prosecutors are investigating the brawl.</p>
        <p>In both cases, many Chicagoans have said that the department seemed to rally around the accused police officers instead of immediately calling for an investigation or taking disciplinary action.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cline, a veteran officer, took over the Police Department, the country's second largest, in November 2003. He made a brief statement on Monday but did not address the controversy. He called his departure a retirement and said, ''leaving during times of challenge makes my decision even more difficult.''</p>
        <p>But in an interview a few days ago broadcast on National Public Radio, Mr. Cline said, ''The past two weeks have been disheartening and embarrassing for me personally and professionally.''</p>
        <p>He has been credited with incorporating new technologies into crime fighting, and with overseeing a drop in homicides and violent crimes.</p>
        <p>One of the department's signature strategies has been the use of video cameras in public places to document and deter crime.</p>
        <p>''If there's videotape, it's going to get out,'' said Mr. Daley, reinforcing his idea that surveillance, while often controversial, is good.</p>
        <p>The Chicago Police Department has a history of problems with officer misconduct, and many here are calling for systemic reform, not simply a change in chiefs.</p>
        <p>Craig Futterman, a clinical law professor at the University of Chicago, said that a study of abuse complaints over the last five years showed the odds were 2 in 1,000 that an officer charged with abuse would be disciplined. He said the study made clear that a small percentage of officers were responsible for the majority of complaints.</p>
        <p>Mr. Daley said a national search would be conducted for a successor.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
