<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What Will 'Amazing Girls' Do Next?</title>
    <meta content="l03girls" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403EEDD1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="695" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What Will 'Amazing Girls' Do Next?</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''For Girls, It's Be Yourself, and Be Perfect, Too'' (front page, April 1) gets it right in many ways, from the overload of Advanced Placement courses to the whirlwind of extracurricular activities and the importance of being ''effortlessly hot.''</p>
        <p>Many of us who gained admission to the so-called elite schools unburdened by the culture of college test-prep services were far less accomplished than these girls, whose achievements are in so many cases truly awesome.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''For Girls, It's Be Yourself, and Be Perfect, Too'' (front page, April 1) gets it right in many ways, from the overload of Advanced Placement courses to the whirlwind of extracurricular activities and the importance of being ''effortlessly hot.''</p>
        <p>Many of us who gained admission to the so-called elite schools unburdened by the culture of college test-prep services were far less accomplished than these girls, whose achievements are in so many cases truly awesome.</p>
        <p>I keep looking for the silver lining in the arbitrariness of the current college-admissions process, and maybe this is it: that having successfully navigated what may turn out to be the most difficult years of their lives, these amazing girls will become amazing women, better able to cope and achieve in today's complicated world, no matter where they go to college.</p>
        <p>Cynthia Rollings  Chappaqua, N.Y., April 1, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>What have we wrought when bright, hard-working, active, charitable girls are told over and over again that they just aren't good enough? Isn't confidence an important attribute for success?</p>
        <p>If these young women cannot be confident about their futures, who can be?</p>
        <p>Peter G. Coffey  Madison, Conn., April 1, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The amazing girls you describe are also amazingly advantaged.</p>
        <p>Many exceptional students at the Queens high school I attend, Townsend Harris, lack the benefits of legacies, bottomless funds for SAT tutoring and school systems that can afford a seemingly infinite number of Advanced Placement classes.</p>
        <p>They maintain jobs (not just to buy designer jeans), do community service, sports, theater -- and get into top colleges. They are amazing.</p>
        <p>Melanie Sovern  Bayside, Queens, April 1, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Forget the sturm und drang. For me, college just happened.</p>
        <p>I am 77 years old. I was a bright kid from a Depression-poor family, inspired by six years at Girls Latin School in Boston.</p>
        <p>I graduated at 151/2 and commuted to Radcliffe College (at a community college tuition). I left Radcliffe with no real job prospects or money for graduate school.</p>
        <p>My husband, a World War II combat veteran, attended Harvard on the G.I. Bill. At some sacrifice, we sent our three children to Ivy League schools without debt or scholarship help. They excelled and achieved and prospered. Four of our grandchildren are in the rat race described in your article. To what end?</p>
        <p>The real success story is that we all become caring, contributing adults, doing our best to be of service in this troubled world. It's all that counts.</p>
        <p>Phyllis Leonard  Rockville, Md., April 1, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>When will the madness end? Yet another generation consumed with the destination rather than the journey.</p>
        <p>Esther Mobley, the subject of your article, says, ''In a lot of ways, it's all about that one week,'' when the Newton North (Mass.) school newspaper lists where the seniors are going to college.</p>
        <p>Unless we teach our children to enjoy each day, this race to the next peak will continue, and real satisfaction with the here and now will not be realized.</p>
        <p>Chris Ludwig  Maynard, Mass., April 1, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The SAT's are only the beginning. Now the Newton North girls can look forward to the next round of résumé must-haves: the career-focused coursework, the leadership roles and the 80-hour workweeks at the investment-bank summer internship.</p>
        <p>College grads want money and status right out of school, so applying for jobs has become as cut-throat as applying for college.</p>
        <p>So maybe it's good that 17-year-olds can balance their billion responsibilities. It prepares them for the rat race that will be their early 20s.</p>
        <p>Or maybe it's ridiculous to put so much pressure on such young people. Career development does not outrank everything else, and this obsession with perfection can only decrease our ability to be unique.</p>
        <p>Erin Halasz  Chicago, April 1, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I have just one question: Are these ''amazing girls'' more successful in life than the rest of us on the bell-shaped curve?</p>
        <p>Now there's the article I really want to read.</p>
        <p>Sheridan S. Forbes  San Francisco, April 1, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
