<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Payne, Leading Augusta Becomes Another Solemn Mission</title>
    <meta content="03golf" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/sports/golf/03golf.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837693"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Augusta National Golf Club</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Payne, Billy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E7DD1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1043" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Payne, Leading Augusta Becomes Another Solemn Mission</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Payne, Leading Augusta National Is Another Solemn Mission</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hack, Damon</byline>
      <dateline>AUGUSTA, Ga., April 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Billy Payne spends Sunday mornings in a third-row pew at St. Luke's Presbyterian Church in Dunwoody, Ga., sitting close enough to the pulpit that his minister, Christopher A. Price, can view him at his most confident and most vulnerable.</p>
        <p>In 1996, Price saw Payne through the drama of the Summer Olympics in Atlanta. These Sundays, Price glances up from Scripture and sees Payne, the new chairman of the Augusta National Golf Club in charge of his first Masters tournament, which begins Thursday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Billy Payne, the new chairman of the Augusta National Golf Club, faces intense challenges as he prepares for his first Masters tournament.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Billy Payne spends Sunday mornings in a third-row pew at St. Luke's Presbyterian Church in Dunwoody, Ga., sitting close enough to the pulpit that his minister, Christopher A. Price, can view him at his most confident and most vulnerable.</p>
        <p>In 1996, Price saw Payne through the drama of the Summer Olympics in Atlanta. These Sundays, Price glances up from Scripture and sees Payne, the new chairman of the Augusta National Golf Club in charge of his first Masters tournament, which begins Thursday.</p>
        <p>''I saw him at a function the other day and I said, 'How's it going?' '' Price said last week in a telephone interview. ''He said, 'I haven't messed up yet.' I know it's on his mind. He takes all of this very, very seriously. He is not a casual person.''</p>
        <p>Payne, who served as the president and the chief executive of the Atlanta committee for the 1996 Olympics, has again been thrust into the spotlight. He will endeavor to maintain the Augusta customs of his predecessors, but his tenure will have its challenges that reflect his personal vision. There will be questions about how much the course will evolve in the face of technology. There will be questions about the all-male membership, which his predecessor, Hootie Johnson, vigorously defended and which Payne has said is a matter to be determined, in private, by the membership.</p>
        <p>There are pronounced differences in being the Olympic administrator and the Augusta chairman. For the Olympics, Payne was a pitchman who played to corporate interests, alternating between business suits and a white jogging outfit. At Augusta, which has no other logo but its own anywhere on its property, Payne is one in a long line of men wearing green jackets, a keeper of traditions and secrets.</p>
        <p>When Payne was named last May as the replacement for Johnson, he said that any urge to rejoice was tempered by solemn feelings. He walked upstairs to Johnson's second-floor office and did not move a painting or piece of furniture. The only difference in the décor, he said, is the Payne family pictures where Johnson's once stood.</p>
        <p>''In a celebratory moment, I was already thinking down the road,'' Payne said in a recent telephone interview. ''I was thinking, I better not mess this up, I better do the best I can to maintain the quality of this tournament that has been maintained by my predecessors. It weighed heavily on me. The responsibility came pretty quickly, and it remains.''</p>
        <p>There is intensity and humor to Payne, a standout defensive end at the University of Georgia, a lawyer and an investment banker who dreamed of an Atlanta Olympics after church services in February 1987.</p>
        <p>Against long odds, Payne and a group of friends delivered the Games, only for the event to be marred by a bombing, a chaotic downtown bazaar that snarled traffic and, later, a Congressional investigation into Atlanta's bid after the scandal uncovered in Salt Lake City's bid to gain the 2002 Winter Games.</p>
        <p>''That we sold Olympic sponsorships and did that in excess, I say guilty as charged; we had no other choice,'' A. D. Frazier, the chief operating officer for the 1996 Atlanta Olympics, said in a telephone interview last week. ''I could have used $75 million and gotten good buses, but I wasn't going to go broke. Billy hated the fact that we didn't have every possible dollar to spend on those things that would have been wonderful to have, but we just didn't have the dough, and we did the best we could with the dough we had.''</p>
        <p>Payne said, ''I remember as we were begging for sponsorship and support, my dear friend Andy Young would say, 'Don't beg, just tell them how great it's going to be.' '' Payne was referring to Andrew Young, the former mayor of Atlanta who worked with him on the bid. ''Through a lot of hard work and luck, we were able to raise a lot of money,'' Payne said.</p>
        <p>He added: ''Our goal was to introduce the American South for the first time ever. It was known only for Civil War and civil rights. Now it is known as one of the most vibrant cities with some of the nicest people you will ever meet.''</p>
        <p>Price said that the investigation into the Atlanta Olympics was one of the rare moments he saw Payne hurt and concerned.</p>
        <p>''The Salt Lake City scandal brought a lot of secondary publicity to Atlanta,'' Price said. ''I got the impression that he was much more concerned about that because it dealt with him personally, his reputation, and it was out of his hands. I don't think Billy, being an honest person, did anything underhanded. He has a tremendous amount of self-confidence and also a human side, a very high level of sensitivity to what people think and how people think of him.''</p>
        <p>It is not yet clear how that sensitivity will manifest itself behind Augusta's green gates. Payne is the first chairman not to have met Clifford Roberts and Bobby Jones, the club's founders, who created a beloved tournament and an exclusive brotherhood.</p>
        <p>Payne, 59, is nearly 17 years younger than Johnson, who once rejected a call to admit a woman member by stating, ''There may well come a day when women will be invited to join our membership, but that timetable will be ours, and not at the point of a bayonet.''</p>
        <p>How might Payne handle the membership question?</p>
        <p>''My guess is pressure from whatever source will not determine what his decision will be,'' Frazier said. ''He will make his decision on what he thinks is best for the Masters and the traditions that are there. He will never be unkind or rude, but he is not going to be browbeaten into some sort of position.''</p>
        <p>Price, who continues to share church services with Payne, said he was not sure how the new chairman might address the membership issue.</p>
        <p>''I'm looking forward to seeing that myself,'' Price said. ''There is an awful lot, the sex and racial issues, women and minorities; it's a very tough thing he's getting into.</p>
        <p>''I think everything Billy does will be a reflection of his integrity, of his faith, and how he understands it.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
