<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>High School Foes Form a Family at Rutgers</title>
    <meta content="03araton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/sports/ncaabasketball/03araton.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837824"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Stringer, C Vivian</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEEDB1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="897" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>High School Foes Form a Family at Rutgers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">High School Foes Form a Family at Rutgers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
      <dateline>CLEVELAND</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Matee Ajavon had her eye on the University of Maryland and Louisiana State until Essence Carson helped talk her into remaining a Jersey girl.</p>
        <p>Kia Vaughn fancied the idea of leaving the Bronx behind for that more rural Big East outpost in Storrs, Conn., but Ajavon and Carson kept sending her text-messages saying, ''Come to Rutgers, girl!''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>All five starters for the Scarlet Knights come from the New York metropolitan area and talked themselves into joining forces for Rutgers Coach C. Vivian Stringer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Matee Ajavon had her eye on the University of Maryland and Louisiana State until Essence Carson helped talk her into remaining a Jersey girl.</p>
        <p>Kia Vaughn fancied the idea of leaving the Bronx behind for that more rural Big East outpost in Storrs, Conn., but Ajavon and Carson kept sending her text-messages saying, ''Come to Rutgers, girl!''</p>
        <p>Epiphanny Prince always wanted Vaughn behind her on defense, but Vaughn never did make it to Murry Bergtraum High School in Manhattan, so Prince took the New Jersey Turnpike south to New Brunswick, Exit 9, where Vaughn was beginning her sophomore year.</p>
        <p>After passing on a scholarship offer from Georgetown, Heather Zurich was an incoming freshman when she heard that Carson's grandmother had died in the summer of 2005. She asked her mother to join her for the half-hour ride from Montvale in the northernmost part of Bergen County, N.J., to the city of Paterson for the funeral.</p>
        <p>''We had played against each other once in high school, but we really didn't have that personal relationship,'' Carson, one year ahead of Zurich, said. ''I looked up and there she was with her mom. It surprised me, and I thought that was great and a perfect example of the family atmosphere Coach has created, through thick and thin.''</p>
        <p>Coach is C. Vivian Stringer and we should not pretend that Rutgers is a classic underdog, ''Hoosiers'' Northeast, playing Tennessee tonight for a chance to win the university's first N.C.A.A. women's basketball title. For the most part, her players were scholastic stars with a score of options, just like Tennessee's players. But the Scarlet Knights' core -- all five starters, in fact -- that will play a Lady Vols team that represents nine states are New York metropolitan area products who talked themselves into the short ride to Stringer's boot camp.</p>
        <p>Just this past December, locked inside the gym with a coach who was furious over their defensive passivity, they could not have been blamed for wishing that they had gone far, very far, to a warm climate near a beach.</p>
        <p>''I believe that during the school break there's no limited hours,'' said Vaughn, the 6-foot-4 sophomore center and defensive anchor, referring to N.C.A.A. guidelines that restrict practice length. ''They shouldn't tell her that.</p>
        <p>''We'd be up at 5 a.m., exhausted, scrimmaging four hours -- who can scrimmage four hours? We'd sit there and say, 'She can't do this to us.' We'd say, 'We're going to send letters out and tell everybody.' We'd say to the manager, 'Tell her she's got a telephone call and she's got to leave.' ''</p>
        <p>Instead, they all got with the program, basked in the tough love, turned what looked like an unremarkable season into a run that will conclude with tonight's showdown with Tennessee and Candace Parker, considered by many to be the best player in the country.</p>
        <p>At the very least, Parker is, as Coach Pat Summitt called her, ''the go-to player I think you need to have in order to win a national championship.'' Watching Ajavon score the ball these past few weeks, it would be an overstatement to say that Rutgers has no primary shooter. But in the Scarlet Knights' minds, they are classic blue-collar climbers and Tennessee is Summitt, the six-time champion, one last opponent to outwork and surmount.</p>
        <p>''That's who we are,'' Carson said. ''That's what we're about.''</p>
        <p>The outgoing but measured Carson agreed with a reporter's opinion of her as the Scarlet Knights' spokeswoman -- ''a role I welcome,'' she said -- and why not? The formation of this seniorless team pretty much began with her.</p>
        <p>''Don't you want to be able to look up in the stands and see your mom?'' Carson, from Paterson's Rosa Parks School of Fine and Performing Arts (for academics and music) and Paterson Eastside (for basketball) asked Ajavon, from Newark's Malcolm X. Shabazz.</p>
        <p>They were high school seniors at the time, still fierce competitors but also fast friends.</p>
        <p>Ajavon's team, a perennial state powerhouse, typically won the games against Carson's team, but Carson persevered and succeeded in the battle for Ajavon's heart and mind. She stressed the chance to build something close to home. She preached the benefits of playing for Stringer, a female African-American role model.</p>
        <p>Three years later, given all the well-documented personal hardship Stringer has endured in her adult life, could there have been anyone more credentialed to help Ajavon deal with an injury that required the insertion of a titanium rod to stabilize her left shin? Who better than Stringer to counsel Carson after the loss of her grandmother, Betty Cooper, the rock in her life?</p>
        <p>It was Cooper who got Carson started in music, chafed at her early ballplaying because she was so gifted, and ultimately came around when she saw for herself that her granddaughter was as joyful on the court as she was on piano, saxophone and bass guitar.</p>
        <p>Her game was never melodious, all that free flowing, as much as it was tough, steady, passionate, all the qualities of the prototypical C. Vivian Stringer player.</p>
        <p>Almost all college teams preach family values, but how many at this level of competition can take pride from being from the same general neighborhood?</p>
        <p>That is the essence of the Rutgers story, or at least the one they are sticking with and the identity on which they are pinning their championship dream tonight.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
