<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chicagoan Puts Up $315 Million To Win $8.2 Billion Tribune Co.</title>
    <meta content="03tribune" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/business/media/03tribune.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070410T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837806"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="A NEWSPAPER SHAKE-UP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tribune Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siklos, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zell, Samuel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broad, Eli</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burkle, Ronald W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chandler Family</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Tribune Company</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Los Angeles Times</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Zell, Samuel</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E0DB1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1973" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chicagoan Puts Up $315 Million To Win $8.2 Billion Tribune Co.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Chicagoan Puts Up $315 Million to Win $8.2 Billion Tribune Co.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE and RICHARD SIKLOS; Stephen Labaton contributed reporting..</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q; Siklos, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tribune Co announces it will join forces with Samuel Zell to take company private and pay shareholders $34 a share; Zell wins auction over rival team of billionaires Eli Broad and Ronald W Burkle through combination of savvy dealing and creative financial engineering; will make investment of only $315 million in deal that is valued at $8.2 billion; proposed financing transaction through employee stock ownership plan, with himself as chairman and largest shareholder; this will leave him with major interest for his relatively small investment; deal will end legacy of Chandler family, effectively buying out family who became biggest shareholders in Tribune when it bought Times-Mirror Co in 2000; family's complaints about company's sagging stock price set auction in motion; Zell, who has never owned newspaper before, insists that his interest in Tribune is not editorial but economic; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>How did a Chicago real estate tycoon win one of the country's premier media companies -- a chain of big-city papers, two dozen television stations and the Chicago Cubs -- in a deal valued at $8.2 billion with an investment of only $315 million of his own money?</p>
        <p>The Tribune Company, which owns The Los Angeles Times, The Chicago Tribune, The Baltimore Sun and other papers, announced yesterday that it had joined forces with Samuel Zell to take the company private and pay shareholders $34 a share.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tribune has joined forces with Samuel Zell to take the company private and pay shareholders $34 a share.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>How did a Chicago real estate tycoon win one of the country's premier media companies -- a chain of big-city papers, two dozen television stations and the Chicago Cubs -- in a deal valued at $8.2 billion with an investment of only $315 million of his own money?</p>
        <p>The Tribune Company, which owns The Los Angeles Times, The Chicago Tribune, The Baltimore Sun and other papers, announced yesterday that it had joined forces with Samuel Zell to take the company private and pay shareholders $34 a share.</p>
        <p>Despite being a late entrant, Mr. Zell managed to win the auction for Tribune over a rival team of Los Angeles billionaires, Eli Broad and Ronald W. Burkle, through a combination of savvy dealing and creative financial engineering. It was Mr. Zell who first proposed financing the transaction through an employee stock ownership plan, an arrangement that is typically used by much smaller companies.</p>
        <p>Most of the company's stock will be owned by the employees through the plan, but Mr. Zell, who becomes the Tribune chairman, will be the largest individual shareholder, leaving him with a major interest for his relatively small investment.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Zell is a hometown player, not an inconsequential advantage when negotiating with a company characterized by a strong antipathy between the head office in Chicago and its biggest single asset, The Los Angeles Times. The deal ends the legacy of the Chandler family, once of America's great newspaper dynasties. It effectively buys out the family who became the biggest shareholders in Tribune when it bought the Times-Mirror Company in 2000 and whose loud complaints last June about the company's sagging stock price set the auction in motion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zell, who has never owned a newspaper before, insists that his interest in Tribune is not editorial but economic.</p>
        <p>As part of yesterday's announcement, the company said it would sell the Chicago Cubs at the end of the season. But otherwise Mr. Zell has said that he does not want to break up the company by selling off its individual properties or spinning off the television stations.</p>
        <p>In a statement yesterday, he called himself ''a long-term investor,'' and added, ''I look forward to partnering with the management and employees as we build on the great heritage of Tribune Company.''</p>
        <p>Still David Geffen, the Los Angeles media mogul who made an early bid for The Los Angeles Times, made it clear that he would still like to acquire the newspaper. ''I remain interested and open to talking,'' Mr. Geffen said. Others have expressed interest in Tribune papers, including Newsday, The Hartford Courant and The Baltimore Sun.</p>
        <p>Even Mr. Broad and Mr. Burkle may not be completely out of the picture. They were originally interested in buying The Los Angeles Times, and they still could make a higher bid for the company. Tribune set a relatively low breakup fee of $25 million so that if it wanted to take a higher bid -- and avoid a possible lawsuit -- it could dismiss its deal with Mr. Zell and pay him only $25 million.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's announcement closes a contentious 10-month chapter for the Tribune Company, which occupies the landmark Tribune Tower in downtown Chicago.</p>
        <p>It also ends a labored auction in which little interest in the company materialized. Wall Street appeared to approve of the move, sending Tribune stock up 70 cents, to close at $32.81.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zell, 65, the son of refugees who fled Poland on the eve of Hitler's invasion, is a self-made billionaire who has thrived on buying distressed businesses, turning them around and selling them at a profit. Newspapers, which face declining revenues and dropping circulations, might fit that description. Like other newspaper owners, Tribune has been hammered on Wall Street in the last few years as advertisers and readers left newspapers for the Web.</p>
        <p>So far, Mr. Zell has not presented a plan for how he might turn Tribune around. Nonetheless, he was not only the favored bidder, but Tribune executives actively encouraged him over the weekend to match a higher bid from Mr. Burkle and Mr. Broad, who were offering $34 a share to Mr. Zell's $33. Only after raising his bid three times did Mr. Zell match the Burkle-Broad bid, and each time, Tribune executives pushed him to do so.</p>
        <p>They wanted Mr. Zell for many reasons.</p>
        <p>Dennis J. FitzSimons, the company's current president, chief executive and chairman -- who will cede the title of chairman to Mr. Zell when the transaction is complete at the end of the year -- said in an interview that Mr. Zell offered the certainty of closing a deal. The company had been working with him for several weeks when a revised Burkle-Broad offer came in. His offer delayed the company's self-imposed deadline of the end of March by only one day.</p>
        <p>''The biggest thing we wanted to do was end this process, have a good outcome for shareholders and get focused on the future as opposed to the process,'' Mr. FitzSimons said, weary of the long public deconstruction of Tribune's management.</p>
        <p>Others said that Mr. Zell's legendary success in turning around distressed companies helped get him in the door.</p>
        <p>As James O'Shea, the editor of The Los Angeles Times, put it in a note to his staff yesterday: ''Sam Zell is a creative thinker and an inventive entrepreneur. A fresh shot of new thinking is not going to hurt us.'' Mr. O'Shea added: ''Mr. Zell also says he believes in the future of the news business. That is certainly good to hear.''</p>
        <p>Mr. FitzSimons said that geography did not play a role in the selection of Mr. Zell, and that he had met the real estate mogul only in the last two months when Mr. Zell presented himself as a potential buyer.</p>
        <p>But others close to the talks said that Mr. Zell's Chicago roots gave him an advantage, particularly since the Burkle-Broad team was from Los Angeles. Tribune has been in an open feud with The Los Angeles Times, where the publisher and editor were forced out last year for taking public stands against cost cuts and where the newsroom, which could still see more job cuts, feels under siege. As a matter of pride, Tribune did not want to be seen as bowing to California, these people said.</p>
        <p>Another related factor in Mr. Zell's favor, they said, was that he was explicit about wanting to buy out the Chandler family, who had long been a thorn in Tribune's side. Representatives of the Chandlers who sit on Tribune's board abstained over the weekend from voting to accept Mr. Zell's plan, but they have agreed to support the transaction when it comes up for a shareholder vote later this year.</p>
        <p>Tribune executives may also have liked Mr. Zell's plan because it keeps most of them in place. Mr. FitzSimons said he expected to stay as president and chief executive after the transaction is completed and that many of the current board members would serve on a reconstituted board. And he said Mr. Zell was not likely to be constantly looking over his shoulder.</p>
        <p>''Sam is chairman of, what, five other companies, and his reputation is that he doesn't micromanage,'' Mr. FitzSimons said.</p>
        <p>Given that Tribune's core business is built on delivering news to readers in a clear and concise fashion, the deal the company announced yesterday was startlingly complex. Mr. Zell will invest an initial $250 million in Tribune shares and securities at a price of $34 a share. The stock ownership plan will also purchase $250 million worth of new Tribune shares, but at a discounted price of $28 a share. Then, in two stages, the company will spend $8.4 billion to buy back the shares, including Mr. Zell's. He will then invest $315 million in new securities, including $90 million for a warrant to buy 40 percent of Tribune's shares.</p>
        <p>Tribune will then become an S corporation, which will exempt it from paying federal income tax. By not paying tax, the Tribune will greatly increase its cash flow, helping it pay down the mountain of debt it is taking on to finance going private. More important for Mr. Zell, only individuals who are United States citizens are eligible to invest in S corporations. That partly explains why only he, Mr. Broad and Mr. Burkle were in the auction at the end.</p>
        <p>The stock ownership plan in particular fostered confusion among some employees. And the overall plan, with its assumption of $8.4 billion in debt in top of nearly $5 billion in existing debt, prompted bond rating services to downgrade Tribune's standing. It also left some wondering how the plan would address the major issues facing the newspaper industry.</p>
        <p>''There are a whole bunch of questions, and it's not like Joseph Pulitzer just bought the company,'' said Michael Hill, a reporter at The Baltimore Sun and chairman of the Sun unit of the Washington-Baltimore Newspaper Guild.</p>
        <p>Employees' chief concern, he said, was whether their retirement plans would be affected by the stock ownership plan, although Tribune insists they will not be.</p>
        <p>''If this means investing our retirement in the current Tribune management, I don't think people will be very excited about that because there's very little confidence in Tribune management,'' Mr. Hill said.</p>
        <p>Stan Simpson, a columnist at The Hartford Courant, said he was ambivalent about the news of Mr. Zell's involvement. ''The big issue is, does he have a vision for the new company and a plan for the digital age?'' Mr. Simpson said.</p>
        <p>Others said they worried that Mr. Zell would take an ax to the staffs at Tribune papers.</p>
        <p>Mr. FitzSimons told employees yesterday in an electronic town hall meeting that was broadcast companywide that he expected some staff reductions in the next few months, which he hoped to accomplish mostly through attrition. In the interview, he said that he would not fill current vacancies in an attempt to stave off having to make further cuts. But, he cautioned, newspapers everywhere are facing the same challenges.</p>
        <p>''We get the headlines, but it's happening all across the industry,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Tribune agreement still has some regulatory hurdles: any new owner needs waivers from the Federal Communications Commission to own newspapers and broadcast outlets in the same market, but the agency is involved in a major debate about whether to loosen those rules.</p>
        <p>''The basis on which they have always sought their exemptions is that the Tribune Company has a special tradition of quality in journalism,'' said Andrew Jay Schwartzman, president of the Media Access Project, an advocacy group that has been critical of efforts to deregulate the industry. ''Zell can't make those claims. He has no tradition of promoting journalism and he's a cost cutter.''</p>
        <p>But Blair Levin, managing director of Stifel Nicolaus &amp; Company, said the challengers to the deal could face an uphill battle. He said that although the two Democrats on the commission may maintain that it was finally time to enforce the restrictions on cross-ownership, the three Republicans who are more critical of those restrictions would probably be more inclined to approve the Tribune deal.</p>
        <p>Tribune was advised by Merrill Lynch and Citigroup; the company's special committee was advised by Morgan Stanley. Mr. Zell was advised by JPMorgan Chase.</p>
        <p>Despite the potential hurdles, some analysts said they were relieved to see the process move forward and hoped that going private would give the company a much-needed break from the spotlight.</p>
        <p>''It gives them a little time to look at the long-term view, reorganize the company and pursue its strategy without analysts commenting all the time,'' said Edward Atorino, a media analyst with Benchmark Company. ''The $34 a share is not a bad price, given the state of the world of newspaper companies. So Sam Zell could be a stabilizing force.''</p>
        <p>A NEWSPAPER SHAKE-UP</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 10, 2007, Tuesday  A front-page article last Tuesday about Samuel Zell's acquisition of the Tribune Company for $8.2 billion misstated one aspect of an ''S'' Corporation, which Tribune will eventually become under the takeover proposal. Foreigners who are residents of the United States can invest in an ''S'' Corporation; investors are not restricted to United States citizens.</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day last Tuesday about Samuel Zell using an Employee Stock Ownership Plan, or ESOP, in a transaction for the Tribune Company omitted a condition for an owner to avoid capital gains taxes on the proceeds of a sale of company shares to such a plan. In addition to the ESOP holding the stock for at least three years, the company has to be private for at least one year before the sale.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 10, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A front-page article last Tuesday about Samuel Zell's acquisition of the Tribune Company for $8.2 billion misstated one aspect of an ''S'' Corporation, which Tribune will eventually become under the takeover proposal. Foreigners who are residents of the United States can invest in an ''S'' Corporation; investors are not restricted to United States citizens.</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day last Tuesday about Samuel Zell using an Employee Stock Ownership Plan, or ESOP, in a transaction for the Tribune Company omitted a condition for an owner to avoid capital gains taxes on the proceeds of a sale of company shares to such a plan. In addition to the ESOP holding the stock for at least three years, the company has to be private for at least one year before the sale.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
