<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>British Captives Admit Illegal Entry, Iran Says</title>
    <meta content="03iran" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/world/middleeast/03iran.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837686"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iran</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803EFDE1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="917" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>British Captives Admit Illegal Entry, Iran Says</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">British Captives Admit Illegal Entry, Iran Says</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, April 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Iran said Monday that all 15 captured British sailors and marines had confessed to intruding illegally into Iranian waters on March 23, when they were seized at gunpoint.</p>
        <p>But Ali Larijani, Iran's chief negotiator, struck what seemed to be a new, authoritative tone, saying in a British television interview that ''there is no need for a trial'' -- a course Tehran had threatened. ''This issue should be solved bilaterally,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Iran said that all 15 captured British sailors and marines had confessed to intruding illegally into Iranian waters on March 23.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Iran said Monday that all 15 captured British sailors and marines had confessed to intruding illegally into Iranian waters on March 23, when they were seized at gunpoint.</p>
        <p>But Ali Larijani, Iran's chief negotiator, struck what seemed to be a new, authoritative tone, saying in a British television interview that ''there is no need for a trial'' -- a course Tehran had threatened. ''This issue should be solved bilaterally,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Larijani, the secretary general of Iran's National Security Council, set conditions for solving the dispute, however. He said the exact whereabouts of the Britons when they were captured should be ''clarified'' and renewed Iran's insistence that they were in its waters when they were seized.</p>
        <p>''We are not living in the Stone Age,'' he said. ''The G.P.S. has clearly pinpointed their presence,'' he said, referring to the global positioning system.</p>
        <p>''Definitely our priority is to solve the problem through proper diplomatic channels,'' he said, speaking through a simultaneous interpreter in a live interview from Tehran with Channel 4 News in Britain. ''We are not interested in having this issue get further complicated.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''We definitely believe that this issue can be resolved. And there is no need for any trial.''</p>
        <p>In addition, Iran pledged not to broadcast additional video images of the British captives, while Iranian state television cited, apparently with approval, what it called a shift in Britain's attitude in the dispute.</p>
        <p>The British Foreign Office responded with a conciliatory gesture of its own. A British official, speaking anonymously because of the delicacy of the diplomatic exchanges between London and Tehran, said Britain might be open to discussions about preventing maritime disputes.</p>
        <p>However, the official said, such talks could not be a condition for the release of the captives.</p>
        <p>''Our priority is to get them out,'' the official said. ''Anything else -- talking about avoiding this in the future -- might be helpful at some point. But it could not be part and parcel of seeking to release these people.''</p>
        <p>The dispute is in its 11th day, and the latest diplomatic signals have emerged, coincidentally, as Britain and Argentina separately observe the 25th anniversary of Argentina's invasion of the Falkland Islands.</p>
        <p>The occasion has inspired comparisons between British caution in the current dispute and the seeming gung-ho decisiveness of Margaret Thatcher, who, as prime minister, turned the humiliation of the Falklands occupation into a military triumph woven into her legacy as the Iron Lady.</p>
        <p>The British government is now being challenged by some critics, though not by the official parliamentary opposition, to act more forcefully. Mr. Blair, who is preparing to leave office in a few months, is eager to prevent his legacy from being stained by the humiliation of British sailors and marines being paraded on Iranian television and making what have been depicted as admissions of guilt.</p>
        <p>For many here, the issue is whether British authority has been weakened by acting as a junior partner to the United States, drawing fire as the weaker ally least likely to respond to Iranian hostility.</p>
        <p>''Would they have done it to the Americans?'' said Oliver Miles, a former British ambassador and Middle East specialist, referring in a telephone interview to the action, ascribed to Iranian Revolutionary Guards, of taking British captives. ''I think I doubt it.''</p>
        <p>Britain is still pressing for the unconditional release of the seven marines and eight sailors -- four of whom have given what appear to be carefully choreographed statements acknowledging that they had strayed into Iranian waters, statements possibly made under duress. All of them appear to be physically unharmed.</p>
        <p>The British Foreign Office has called the broadcasts ''unacceptable.'' Britain insists that the naval personnel in two patrol boasts were operating legally in Iraqi waters with the authority of the government of Iraq and the United Nations.</p>
        <p>On Monday, Iranian television broadcast what appeared to be a montage of other British captives who did not speak. Instead, according to Reuters, a commentary accompanying the images stated, ''It seems that Britain has shifted a little bit from its stance in the last one or two days over the undeniable facts and from some of its clamor.''</p>
        <p>''If this path continues, one can hope that the issue would be resolved in a bilateral process and far away from fuss and clamor and with achieving Iran's logical demands,'' the commentary said.</p>
        <p>While the remarks seemed to soften the tone, Iran has frequently sent contradictory signals in the dispute, varying between diplomatic correspondence and public condemnation from people as senior as President Mahmoud Ahmadinejad. The Iranians have also complained about British moves to internationalize the incident, by seeking support for London's case from the United Nations Security Council and the European Union.</p>
        <p>U.S. Asks Iran About Missing Man</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON, April 2 (Reuters) -- The United States is asking Iran to provide information about an American citizen believed to have vanished several weeks ago in Iran while on private business, the State Department said Monday.</p>
        <p>The State Department spokesman, Sean McCormack, said that the family and employer of the man had reported him missing, and that the department was sending an official inquiry to Iran on Monday via Swiss diplomats, who act as a go-between with Iran because the two countries do not have diplomatic relations.</p>
        <p>The man is believed to have disappeared from Kish Island south of Iran. He was not identified. State Department officials said he retired from the Federal Bureau of Investigation some years ago and no longer worked for the government.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
