<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oden Does Plenty to Impress the N.B.A. Scouts but Is Denied a Championship</title>
    <meta content="03jenkins" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/sports/ncaabasketball/03jenkins.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837829"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Ohio State University</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Basketball Assn</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Oden, Greg</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E7DA1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="747" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oden Does Plenty to Impress the N.B.A. Scouts but Is Denied a Championship</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Improved Draft Status but No Championship for Oden</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEE JENKINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jenkins, Lee</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, April 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ohio State center Greg Oden showed the N.B.A. scouts Monday night that he could play smart, play hard and play angry.</p>
        <p>He stayed out of foul trouble. He blocked shots with both hands. He dunked the ball with such authority that it sometimes looked as if he were using the rim as a pull-up bar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ohio State center Greg Oden, likely to be the No. 1 pick in the coming N.B.A. draft, showed that he could play smart, play hard and play angry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ohio State center Greg Oden showed the N.B.A. scouts Monday night that he could play smart, play hard and play angry.</p>
        <p>He stayed out of foul trouble. He blocked shots with both hands. He dunked the ball with such authority that it sometimes looked as if he were using the rim as a pull-up bar.</p>
        <p>As a result, he is probably the No. 1 pick in the coming N.B.A. draft. But he is not a national champion.</p>
        <p>Oden delivered his best performance on his most disappointing night. Ohio State lost the national championship game to Florida, 84-75, and perhaps just as discouraging for the Buckeyes, Oden may not stick around to build on what he accomplished.</p>
        <p>After Final Four losses, top underclassmen often vow to return and redeem themselves. Usually, they reconsider their stance. Sometimes, they do not.</p>
        <p>But after this game, when Oden was asked about his plans for next year, he said only: ''No questions about next year.''</p>
        <p>For one night, Oden was everything the Buckeyes expected when they signed him as the top recruit in the country. He scored 25 points, snatched 12 rebounds and swatted 4 shots. He put all three Florida big men in foul trouble.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't matter,'' Oden said. ''Winning games is all that matters.''</p>
        <p>Florida tried to defend Oden with just one man, and for once, the Gators got burned. Despite shoves and elbows, Oden dominated every one-on-one matchup. He just could not win one-on-five.</p>
        <p>In order to escape the referees, Oden camped underneath the basket and stayed as far as possible from the perimeter. The Gators did not want to go near him. So they simply stepped back and shot over him.</p>
        <p>Lee Humphrey made four 3-pointers. Corey Brewer made three, as did Taurean Green. Even post players like Al Horford and Chris Richard made jumpers. The Gators increased the degree of difficulty on their shots, but did not sacrifice anything.</p>
        <p>''Every time we came back they had an answer,'' Oden said. ''What they're doing right now is what we wanted to do.''</p>
        <p>The defining moment in the game came with less than eight minutes remaining, when Richard flew to the hoop for a dunk, and Oden stuffed the ball back in his face. But the loose ball wound up going to Humphrey, who made yet another 3-pointer.</p>
        <p>''They got all the hustle plays we needed to get,'' Oden said.</p>
        <p>In basketball, the team that dominates inside usually wins. But in the N.C.A.A. tournament, the team with the best guards usually wins. And for the second year in a row, the Gators' guards led them to the national title.</p>
        <p>While Florida went 10 of 18 from 3-point range, a portrait of efficiency, Ohio State went 4 of 23, a sign of desperation. For a seven-minute stretch in the second half, Oden did not even take a shot. The Buckeyes were too busy attempting 3-pointers.</p>
        <p>Asked if Oden could have done more, Ohio State Coach Thad Matta said, ''No.''</p>
        <p>If Oden does turn pro, his one-year college career was both tantalizing and a little disappointing. When he was not injured or in foul trouble, he changed the complexion of every game. But he was injured and in foul trouble for much of the season.</p>
        <p>Often criticized for his passive demeanor, Oden played as if he were possessed against Florida. During pregame introductions, Matta got right in Oden's face, obviously trying to stir his emotions. The pep talk worked.</p>
        <p>In the first minute of the game, Oden chased down a loose ball. Then he split a double team for a dunk. Then he made a two-handed block on Brewer. Whenever the Buckeyes were in danger of a blowout, Oden went to the rim for an easy basket.</p>
        <p>Now that Matta has seen Oden's full potential, he has even more reason to re-recruit him to Ohio State. But it could be more difficult than luring him the first time.</p>
        <p>''I know he hasn't thought about it,'' Matta said. ''We'll sit down when we get back, take a look at everything and see what he wants to do. But honestly, I couldn't even give you a percentage right now.''</p>
        <p>Matta can only hope that Oden returns to the Buckeyes, just as Brewer and Horford and Joakim Noah returned to Florida last year. Matta will have to sell Oden on the prospect of winning the national championship next season.</p>
        <p>But he may also have to promise him some more help.</p>
        <p>N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
