<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Last Diva Standing: Young Voices Vie on a Grand Stage</title>
    <meta content="03oper" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837670"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E6DE1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="476" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Last Diva Standing: Young Voices Vie on a Grand Stage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE MIDGETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Midgette, Anne</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A snapshot of a segment of opera's next generation, with elements of randomness in the composition: that's the most the Metropolitan Opera National Council Auditions Grand Finals concert can actually hope to offer. The 11 finalists who sang onstage at the Metropolitan Opera on Sunday afternoon had been culled from some 1,500 singers in four rounds of national competition. The six winners took home $15,000 each; the five others, runner-up prizes of $5,000. All got the same boost of singing with the Met orchestra, on the Met stage, for an enthusiastic audience; for most of them, this will lead to new professional opportunities, though there are no instant tickets to a big career.</p>
        <p>Were they the best young singers in America? Probably not. Some were excellent. Some were all right. No competition is definitive: rather than achievement, the judges can only evaluate a given singer's performance on a given day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A snapshot of a segment of opera's next generation, with elements of randomness in the composition: that's the most the Metropolitan Opera National Council Auditions Grand Finals concert can actually hope to offer. The 11 finalists who sang onstage at the Metropolitan Opera on Sunday afternoon had been culled from some 1,500 singers in four rounds of national competition. The six winners took home $15,000 each; the five others, runner-up prizes of $5,000. All got the same boost of singing with the Met orchestra, on the Met stage, for an enthusiastic audience; for most of them, this will lead to new professional opportunities, though there are no instant tickets to a big career.</p>
        <p>Were they the best young singers in America? Probably not. Some were excellent. Some were all right. No competition is definitive: rather than achievement, the judges can only evaluate a given singer's performance on a given day.</p>
        <p>The most common flaws of the afternoon were overemoting and undersinging; more energy from the pit, rather than the gentle but leisurely approach of the conductor Marco Armiliato, might have helped. Even for Angela Meade, an impressive soprano, more spark would have benefited ''Ach, ich liebte'' from Mozart's ''Entführung aus dem Serail'' -- a small-scale choice for a strong voice that proceeded to let loose with ease and authority in ''Casta Diva'' (from Bellini's ''Norma'').</p>
        <p>She was certainly a deserving winner, as was Michael Fabiano -- at 22 the youngest of the singers -- whose full, warm tenor had a presence well beyond his years in ''Torna ai felici dì'' from ''Le Villi'' by Puccini and Lensky's aria from Tchaikovsky's ''Eugene Onegin,'' and who, to judge from the applause, was the audience favorite. Amber L. Wagner won on the strength of a solid if uninflected dramatic soprano.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, those were the most impressive performances. Disella Larusdottir, a soprano who had been reliably breathtaking at every earlier stage of the competition, had lost some of the ''float'' to her tone -- she may have been indisposed -- and failed to advance. But Alek Shrader, a light tenor who had sounded undersupported in the semifinals, showed off to advantage with Donizetti's bravura ''Ah! mes amis'' (from ''The Daughter of the Regiment''); the high C's may not have been beautiful, but they were clearly easy for him, and he won handily.</p>
        <p>Jamie Barton, a mezzo-soprano, was another winner who would have been helped by more crackle from Mr. Armiliato in a pretty but underpowered ''Priva son d'ogni conforto,'' from Handel's ''Giulio Cesare,'' but she showed range, if slightly overdone histrionics, by following it with the witch's aria from ''Hänsel und Gretel.'' The sixth winner was Ryan Smith, a tight, light tenor.</p>
        <p>There are plenty of other singers who failed to advance who could have acquitted themselves as well. The watchword, as in any competitive event, remains, ''Wait until next year.''</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
