<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From the Sidelines, a View Of the Middle as the Loser</title>
    <meta content="03kaku" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Health; Washington; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/books/03kaku.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837668"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bradley, Bill</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">New American Story, The (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E6DE1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1176" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From the Sidelines, a View Of the Middle as the Loser</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From the Sidelines, a View of the Middle as the Loser</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kakutani, Michiko</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New American Story  By Bill Bradley  364 pages. Random House. $25.95.</p>
        <p>Bill Bradley, the former United States senator from New Jersey and former presidential candidate, got out of politics in 2000 after losing the Democratic nomination to Al Gore, and so wrote this book, he says, from ''outside the political pressure cooker,'' with ''no ax to grind and no political ambition to accomplish.'' And once the reader gets past the logy, platitude-filled opening pages of ''The New American Story,'' it becomes clear that Mr. Bradley is not going to pull his punches.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In this tart assessment of national politics today, Bill Bradley argues for the “general interest” over the special interests.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New American Story  By Bill Bradley  364 pages. Random House. $25.95.</p>
        <p>Bill Bradley, the former United States senator from New Jersey and former presidential candidate, got out of politics in 2000 after losing the Democratic nomination to Al Gore, and so wrote this book, he says, from ''outside the political pressure cooker,'' with ''no ax to grind and no political ambition to accomplish.'' And once the reader gets past the logy, platitude-filled opening pages of ''The New American Story,'' it becomes clear that Mr. Bradley is not going to pull his punches.</p>
        <p>He not only excoriates President Bush for his handling of the Iraq war -- which the former senator bluntly calls an ''oil war'' -- and for leading the country ''down a dangerous path toward empire,'' but he's also scathing about his fellow Democrats, who he says are afraid to think big and ''have coasted on the intellectual work of the New Deal'' for decades.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley assails the Bush administration for its deficit spending (fueled, he says, by irresponsible tax cuts), its woeful record on the environment and its mistrust of experts on everything from Iraq to economics. He writes, ''The case can be made that George Bush has destroyed the Republican Party by his profligacy, his arrogance, his stubborn machismo, and his absolute conviction that whatever he does is right.''</p>
        <p>He describes Bill Clinton's tenure in the White House as a ''lost opportunity'' and says that that administration's health care initiative failed because ''Hillary Clinton's political skills were not well honed'' and ''mistakes of conception, consultation, pace, and strategy'' were made.</p>
        <p>In an earlier book, Mr. Bradley noted that in his own case, ''ambition had fueled a desire to please'' and that for much of his career he had ''no authentic political voice,'' campaigning ''not to change the world or shake up my audiences but to please the roomful of people to whom I was speaking.'' It was only in the wake of his near-defeat in the 1990 Senate race in New Jersey, he wrote, that he began ''to speak from my gut as well as my head.''</p>
        <p>This time around, Mr. Bradley eschews what he once called ''the comfort of ambiguity or silence'' to set forth views that are bound to be controversial on issues like education, health care and tax policy, and he also provides a tart assessment of national politics today.</p>
        <p>The reader may well take issue with some of his observations. His suggestion, for instance, that the Democratic Party is ''relatively faction-free'' seems ludicrous, given the many intraparty splits between moderates and liberals, between, say, the Democratic Leadership Council and Web followers of Daily Kos.</p>
        <p>But most of his suggestions are grounded in an appealing mix of idealism and common sense, and the result is a thoughtful, incisive book animated by an eagerness to grapple with an array of middle-class concerns that bridge red- and blue-state America.</p>
        <p>Contesting the popular notion that the country is deeply polarized, Mr. Bradley cites a 2000 study showing that 52 percent of red-state voters want gun control, 70 percent of blue-state voters favor the death penalty and 62 percent of red-state voters say there should be no job discrimination against gays. He goes on to argue that the growing power of special interest groups -- enhanced by the gerrymandering of Congressional districts, the media's fascination with noisy partisanship and candidates' susceptibility to lobbyists -- is corroding the political process.</p>
        <p>''Because their agendas dominate,'' he writes, ''what rarely gets addressed comprehensively is what most people want: affordable health care, excellent schools, adequate pensions, a clean environment, and an economy that generates more and more well-paying jobs. Instead, an inordinate amount of attention goes to issues such as abortion, gay rights, gun control, medical marijuana, the display of the Ten Commandments, the wording of the Pledge of Allegiance, or the subsidy desires of a particular corporation or industry -- issues that don't motivate the majority but are all important to the activists.''</p>
        <p>After drubbing the Republicans for requiring ''lockstep adherence to narrow party positions'' and pandering to corporate interests, Mr. Bradley writes that Democrats must learn to ''assert the general interest'' over the agendas of their party's ''special friends'' -- namely, teachers' unions (which he says tend to ''defend the status quo in school organization, student performance and teacher accountability''); trial lawyers (whose litigiousness, he says, has led to higher costs in health care, the ''flight of doctors from their profession, and little improvement in health care delivery''); and the autoworkers' union (which he says has ''opposed higher mileage standards'' and ''opposed requiring companies to shore up private pension systems'').</p>
        <p>As Senator Chuck Schumer did in his recent book, ''Positively American: Winning Back the Middle Class Majority One Family at a Time,'' Mr. Bradley addresses the larger identity crisis afflicting the Democratic Party and the many tactical and strategic disadvantages it faces in taking on a Republican Party that has built up a daunting infrastructure buttressed by research organizations and a well-oiled voter-turnout machine.</p>
        <p>He articulates a wide array of specific policy suggestions, from raising the age threshold for receiving Social Security to implementing a gasoline tax of $1 a gallon to providing up to $12,000 in college tuition money for high school students in the top third of their graduating classes.</p>
        <p>He also contends that Democrats must address eight ''perennial curses,'' which include allowing Republicans to dictate the terms of the national debate, failing to enunciate a coherent political philosophy, and looking for the emergence of a charismatic leader like John F. Kennedy, instead of doing the hard work of building a support structure based on ''money, ideas, political language and media outreach'' as the Republicans have done.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Bradley's view, the Iraq war isn't the only thing threatening to derail the Republican machine; it's also that the presidency of George W. Bush has undermined the uneasy Republican coalition of disparate groups like fundamentalists, libertarians, neo-conservatives and supply-siders.</p>
        <p>''The Medicare drug entitlement has denied them the platform of 'limited government','' the former senator writes. ''A first term without one presidential veto even as federal spending increased 33 percent has denied them the platform of 'fiscal responsibility.' The Iraq War has destroyed the idea that they are advocates of a sober, limited foreign policy.''</p>
        <p>And ''the opening up of government coffers to industry special interests by granting them obscenely generous special favors has embarrassed those Republicans who believe that the market, not Congress, is the most efficient allocator of resources.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley ends this perspicacious book by calling for a new kind of politics that would transcend red-state/blue-state partisanship, and that would emphasize consensus over what ''purists'' on both the left and right put at the top of their agendas.</p>
        <p>''I believe,'' he concludes, ''that in a world in which activists and political consultants focus on peripheral issues -- even in a world in which few elections are legitimately contested and money seems a necessary evil -- the political party that emphasizes what 70 percent of the people care about will be in power for a generation.''</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
