<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>One Troupe's Exploration Of Big Ideas</title>
    <meta content="03lerm" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/arts/dance/03lerm.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837653"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Performing Arts Center</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Lerman, Liz</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00EEDF1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="521" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>One Troupe's Exploration Of Big Ideas</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">One Troupe’s Exploration of Big Ideas</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunning, Jennifer</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, April 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Liz Lerman has been choreographing pieces about social issues for nearly three decades. Her company, Liz Lerman Dance Exchange, includes members as old as 72 as well as disabled performers. In recent years the themes have grown very large, incorporating fewer and fewer of the small, vivid details that give such themes a life onstage.</p>
        <p>Only the final moments of her 2006 ''Ferocious Beauty: Genome,'' for instance, had that kind of defining detail. It came at the end of the discursive multimedia piece about genetics: a woman in a wheelchair coursed onto the stage, and the point was made, in glancing movement and words, that imperfection has its own, invaluable beauty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ms. Lerman’s new pieces on prayer practices and genocide , as performed at the New Jersey Performing Arts Center on Sunday, lacked the piercing revelations of her earlier works.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Liz Lerman has been choreographing pieces about social issues for nearly three decades. Her company, Liz Lerman Dance Exchange, includes members as old as 72 as well as disabled performers. In recent years the themes have grown very large, incorporating fewer and fewer of the small, vivid details that give such themes a life onstage.</p>
        <p>Only the final moments of her 2006 ''Ferocious Beauty: Genome,'' for instance, had that kind of defining detail. It came at the end of the discursive multimedia piece about genetics: a woman in a wheelchair coursed onto the stage, and the point was made, in glancing movement and words, that imperfection has its own, invaluable beauty.</p>
        <p>There were no such piercing revelations in Ms. Lerman's new ''613 Radical Acts of Prayer: Opening Acts,'' performed Sunday afternoon at the New Jersey Performing Arts Center in Newark on a program with ''Small Dances About Big Ideas.''</p>
        <p>''Radical Acts'' was inspired by the company's residency in Japan last year and subsequent visits there as part of the Newark theater's Global Exchange program. The idea of the new work, whose cast includes 13 guest performers from Japan, was to explore ancient and modern ideas about prayer practices as a way, as Ms. Lerman has put it, to illuminate what unifies and divides people.</p>
        <p>Several Japanese performers talked of pungent memories of approaching war. There were allusions to senninbari (''thousand-person-stitches''), belts made for Japanese soldiers that incorporate single embroidery stitches collected from 1,000 people. The wonderfully rustling paper back-curtain recalled omikuji, fortunes written on paper strips at Shinto shrines and Buddhist temples. Poetic one-sentence prayers for protection were projected on the stage's back wall.</p>
        <p>Suggestive images studded the flow of dance segments: a woman trying to soothe a despairing man who sits at a small table with her; the way the wheels of one performer's upended wheelchair spin fitfully without human intervention; the reverent touch of a stone or a hand to a cheek. But the whole was far less than the sum of its parts in what was essentially a series of processionals and clustered dances whose connection to prayer practices is more illustrative than defining.</p>
        <p>''Small Dances'' addressed genocide and the Nuremberg Trials. Stories were drawn from the audience as well as from written historical material as members of the Lerman company went out into the lighted house to solicit recollections of audience members' first awareness of the word genocide; these memories were recounted onstage. The audience members' unconscious gestures were then woven into a sweet group dance, performed by the company and the audience and led by Peter DiMuro, a company member who did a good imitation of a pompous group therapy leader.</p>
        <p>Here, again, there were a few telling images in the stream of processions and bursts of dancing, among them a shift of power between a rapist, who confusingly seemed to be the presiding Nuremburg judge, and his victim. Lewis Folden's set design of all-purpose tables was ingenious. But the feisty, unassumingly humanistic spirit of earlier pieces by Ms. Lerman was sadly missing. How about a small dance or two about small ideas?</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
