<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stuck in an Airplane And in an Overloaded System</title>
    <meta content="03road" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/business/03road.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837712"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON THE ROAD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/On the Road</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Business Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Traffic Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Traffic Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE4DD1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="777" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stuck in an Airplane And in an Overloaded System</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Stuck in an Airplane and in an Overloaded System</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE SHARKEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE last two flights I have been on were delayed on takeoff for a total of three hours. Not so bad, considering that thousands of passengers were stranded on planes for up to nine hours in airports near Dallas on Dec. 29 as severe thunderstorms crossed the region. And on Feb. 14, thousands more were stranded by an ice storm for up to 10 1/2 hours on JetBlue planes, mostly at Kennedy International Airport.</p>
        <p>Then on the first weekend in March, US Airways combined its numbingly complicated reservations system with America West's numbingly complicated system, which had been operating independently since the airlines merged in 2005.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>More people and more airplanes are being squeezed into an infrastructure that wasn’t built to accommodate such a load.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE last two flights I have been on were delayed on takeoff for a total of three hours. Not so bad, considering that thousands of passengers were stranded on planes for up to nine hours in airports near Dallas on Dec. 29 as severe thunderstorms crossed the region. And on Feb. 14, thousands more were stranded by an ice storm for up to 10 1/2 hours on JetBlue planes, mostly at Kennedy International Airport.</p>
        <p>Then on the first weekend in March, US Airways combined its numbingly complicated reservations system with America West's numbingly complicated system, which had been operating independently since the airlines merged in 2005.</p>
        <p>US Airways labeled the initiative as if it were a military campaign: Operation Res Migration. But open hostilities soon ensued between the independent computer systems, which refused to follow orders. As a result, 100,000 passengers were stranded, some sleeping overnight in airports that began to resemble Civil War army camps. More than 2,000 flights were canceled.</p>
        <p>''Where to begin with Res Migration?'' the airline said cheerily in an e-mail message to members of its frequent-flier program. Over all, said the airline, which had decided not to warn passengers in advance of the computer merger, ''while it didn't go as well as we would have liked in some regards, it went better than expected in others.''</p>
        <p>US Air conceded, ''We hit a few bumps along the way.''</p>
        <p>We can expect to see a lot more bumps in air travel. As demand domestically and internationally reaches record levels, most flights are taking off full or nearly so.</p>
        <p>And more people, and more airplanes, are being squeezed into an infrastructure -- including airports and the Federal Aviation Administration's air traffic control system -- that wasn't built to accommodate such a load.</p>
        <p>In its recently released forecast for 2007-20, the F.A.A. predicts that the domestic commercial airliner fleet will grow to 11,203 in 2020 from 7,626 this year. That does not include growth in the number of business jets, currently more than 6,000, or the anticipated surge in the so-called very light business and personal jets, which the F.A.A. has said will add 5,000 more aircraft to the skies in 10 years.</p>
        <p>While the airlines get the blame, ''These delays are inextricably linked with the government's outdated and inefficient air traffic control system,'' said James C. May, the president of the Air Transport Association.</p>
        <p>It's clear that more business travelers are choosing to drive rather than fly. Will Allen III, a Raleigh, N.C., management consultant who is on the road five days a week, monitored delays piling up at O'Hare International Airport one day in March, and decided instead to drive from Raleigh to Chicago, renting a Toyota Avalon for the 1,700-mile round trip.</p>
        <p>Mr. Allen is a kind of business traveler Everyman, and I take his temperature on occasion. I've never heard him sound so unhappy about air travel.</p>
        <p>''The next time I feel I'm being held hostage by the airlines, I'm calling Hertz,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Speaking of being held hostage, Frank Yurasko and his wife, Rosalee, of Redington Beach, Fla., were among passengers on a Royal Air Maroc flight from Kennedy to Casablanca on March 16 who, by my calculation, hold the 2006-7 record for time held on board a parked airliner.</p>
        <p>''Sixteen and a half hours in the plane, which I think is a record-setting event,'' said Mr. Yurasko, a retired trial lawyer. The weather that night was snowy, and planes were stacked up for de-icing procedures that ultimately broke down after passengers boarded around 7 p.m.</p>
        <p>As the night wore on and the plane sat on a ramp, away from the gate, ''people were sleeping on the floor of the airplane,'' he said. Dinner was served, but after that for the rest of the 16 1/2 hours, ''there were no further offers of water or anything else, let alone food,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''They kept saying, 'We're waiting for clearance; we're waiting for clearance.' They had on board a continental breakfast, but didn't serve that, though some of our seatmates saw the flight attendants eating breakfasts in the back,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''The flight attendants had given up on looking after the passengers and stopped making announcements. When the flight was finally canceled, and was moving back to the gate on an active runway, people were milling around; nobody was in their seats.''</p>
        <p>Passengers were given $15 for lunch ''at McDonalds or the Wok &amp; Roll'' at the airport, and then boarded on a flight the next evening. Total travel time, New York to Morocco: 60 hours.</p>
        <p>''Air service in general is deteriorating,'' Mr. Yurasko said in the understatement of the year so far.</p>
        <p>ON THE ROAD E-mail: jsharkey@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: jsharkey@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
