<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Three Who Stayed, And One Ready to Go</title>
    <meta content="03vecsey" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/sports/ncaabasketball/03vecsey.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837831"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Noah, Joakim</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Oden, Greg</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7DA1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="899" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Three Who Stayed, And One Ready to Go</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Two Star Players, Two Glimpses of the College Experience</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Joakim Noah's favorite course last semester was called The Africa Diaspora. The other day, he confessed that he did not earn a good grade -- ''the workload was unbelievable'' -- but he added, ''I felt that I learned a lot.''</p>
        <p>If there is one place where learning shows, it is in sport. The celebrated redux academic year that Noah and Al Horford and Corey Brewer have taken, rather than turn professional, has been sentimentally hailed as a reaffirmation of the good old days, when college players stayed around for four years. And maybe, in some modest way, it was.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For all the mixed messages of big-time college basketball, there are times when even N.B.A.-bound superstars sound like college students.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Joakim Noah's favorite course last semester was called The Africa Diaspora. The other day, he confessed that he did not earn a good grade -- ''the workload was unbelievable'' -- but he added, ''I felt that I learned a lot.''</p>
        <p>If there is one place where learning shows, it is in sport. The celebrated redux academic year that Noah and Al Horford and Corey Brewer have taken, rather than turn professional, has been sentimentally hailed as a reaffirmation of the good old days, when college players stayed around for four years. And maybe, in some modest way, it was.</p>
        <p>That choice by the three academic musketeers also led directly to Florida's second consecutive national championship last night, as the Gators outplayed Ohio State, 84-75.</p>
        <p>After the game, Coach Billy Donovan talked about the concept of ''team,'' which was evident the way Noah, Horford and Brewer, all 6 feet 9 inches or taller, could handle the ball. They were so smooth, so poised, the way John Wooden's U.C.L.A. teams were when players began as sophomores and stayed for three varsity seasons. Now, often enough, it is one and done, as with Carmelo Anthony at Syracuse four years ago.</p>
        <p>The experience and talent of Florida negated the power of Ohio State's 7-foot freshman, Greg Oden, who almost surely played his last collegiate game. Florida kept running bodies at Oden as he scored 25 points and had 12 rebounds. He said that he was sure Chris Richards, the valuable senior substitute, must have been a member of Florida's national championship football team.</p>
        <p>Oden is not pretending to be long for the academic world. He's here because of the current rule that mandates a year of college before players turn professional. He would not give a glimmer of a hint about his plans after last night's game.</p>
        <p>Asked recently what he has enjoyed about college, Oden said, ''being away from home, enjoying freedom.'' But when people brought up the lavish praise for the Florida Three for coming back for their junior seasons, Oden did not sound impressed with the concept of staying in school to learn the business of basketball, if for no other reason.</p>
        <p>''It really doesn't matter,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He brought up Dwight Howard, all 6-11 of him, who went directly from Southwest Atlanta Christian Academy to the Orlando Magic in 2004, under the more liberal policy of the time.</p>
        <p>''He's an N.B.A. all-star in three years,'' Oden said evenly. ''He's making a living. That's what college is for.''</p>
        <p>Oden showed he is something more than the average freshman the way he flung his 7-foot body toward the basket last night. After falling behind quickly, Ohio State kept throwing the ball inside to him.</p>
        <p>After complaining about ''ticky-tacky'' calls in Ohio State's semifinal victory against Georgetown, Oden seemed to have far more physical leeway last night, and he praised the referees for letting him play. After looking tentative earlier in his first, and probably only, national tournament, Oden was a force last night on the way to his second-highest point total of his season.</p>
        <p>Pragmatically, Oden is right about Howard not needing college to play in the N.B.A. He could have mentioned Kobe Bryant, LeBron James, Kevin Garnett, Tracy McGrady, Amare Stoudemire and Jermaine O'Neal, all of them thriving without accumulating college credits. He may not be ready to be any of them, but if he wants to leave college, he helped advertise himself last night.</p>
        <p>There have been a lot of snide jokes about the History of Rock 'n' Roll course, which Oden took last semester. Frankly, half a century of rock 'n' roll, in the hands of a savvy instructor -- bringing in Vietnam and civil rights and social attitudes and sexual mores -- sounds like a stimulating subject to me. But that wasn't the class Oden mentioned yesterday.</p>
        <p>Asked what courses he was taking this semester, Oden mentioned history, mathematics, and then he displayed enthusiasm for a biology course. He hasn't been able to make the lab yet because he has been on the road this month, but he has attended one of those mass lectures we all remember -- 600 students in one hall.</p>
        <p>''Four hundred girls,'' Oden added, a smile crossing his face, finally.</p>
        <p>But, somebody interjected, Oden already has a girlfriend.</p>
        <p>''It's good to just watch,'' Oden replied.</p>
        <p>Well, that's part of college, too.</p>
        <p>Noah is a virtual Holden Caulfield, albeit a Cameroonian-French-Swedish New Yorker with a pony tall flapping nearly 7 feet from the ground. He rails against injustice and hypocrisy, grows misty-eyed when he mentions how his Swedish mother cried after Saturday night's semifinal victory, and he politely criticizes the Bush administration in the same sentence that he talks about his love for America. He talks about a memorable bull session with a championship Florida football player as they roamed the campus, unable to sleep, from 3 a.m. to 6 a.m. Sounds like college to me.</p>
        <p>Asked if he had any advice for Oden, Noah replied, ''I would say, 'Follow your own heart.' ''</p>
        <p>After last night, Oden's heart may have a clear signal. Enough of the mixed messages of pompous statements about scholar-athletes along with team gear being hawked without a cut going to the talent.</p>
        <p>The three Florida players have said the extra year would have paid off even without this championship. Now they have two -- and it's time to take another look.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
