<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Opening Day, Williams Can Only Watch and Wish</title>
    <meta content="03curry" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837792"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E2DB1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="830" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Opening Day, Williams Can Only Watch and Wish</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hiram Williams spoke yesterday to his brother, Bernie, who played so gracefully with the Yankees for the past 16 seasons. Hiram could hear the disappointment in Bernie's voice and could understand why it was a draining day for a baseball player who no longer has a team.</p>
        <p>It was opening day at Yankee Stadium, a time for the fans to rekindle their love affair with Derek Jeter and the rest. But Bernie Williams, who had been part of that relationship for almost two decades, was absent. The man who does not want to play for anyone except the Yankees watched the game on television.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hiram Williams spoke yesterday to his brother, Bernie, who played so gracefully with the Yankees for the past 16 seasons. Hiram could hear the disappointment in Bernie's voice and could understand why it was a draining day for a baseball player who no longer has a team.</p>
        <p>It was opening day at Yankee Stadium, a time for the fans to rekindle their love affair with Derek Jeter and the rest. But Bernie Williams, who had been part of that relationship for almost two decades, was absent. The man who does not want to play for anyone except the Yankees watched the game on television.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, he's got a lot of emotions going on,'' Hiram Williams said from San Juan, P.R. ''There are mixed emotions. He obviously wants to be there contributing to the Yankees. He misses them.''</p>
        <p>A few hours before the Yankees defeated the Tampa Bay Devil Rays, 9-5, Bernie Williams was thinking about his old teammates and called the clubhouse to wish them luck. He talked to Manager Joe Torre, and then Torre buzzed around the clubhouse searching for Williams's buddies. Torre found Jeter and Jorge Posada and passed them the telephone.</p>
        <p>Posada told Williams that he missed him and would miss him throughout the season. Jeter, who has been communicating with Williams, said they did not even talk about baseball.</p>
        <p>Jeter said Williams sounded fine. ''His voice didn't crack or anything,'' Jeter said.</p>
        <p>Hiram Williams described Bernie, his older brother, as a big brother to Jeter and Posada. Although the friendships may remain, Hiram said it was a much different feeling for his brother these days. Torre sensed that, too.</p>
        <p>''There's no question he's missing it,'' Torre said. ''It's opening day.''</p>
        <p>Bernie Williams declined an invitation to compete for a roster spot in spring training because the Yankees did not offer a guaranteed contract. So, while Williams, who still lives in Armonk, N.Y., works out three or four times a week and hopes his fleeting chances of rejoining the Yankees somehow become more realistic, the team has moved on.</p>
        <p>''He has this dream that something might happen down the road,'' Hiram said in a telephone interview. ''Maybe they will need him in the middle of the season. He still has the dream. He definitely wants to play baseball.''</p>
        <p>When Torre called Bernie Williams in mid-February and nudged him to come to spring training, he was telling Williams that he could not make the Yankees from Armonk. Torre broached the possibility of playing first baseman Doug Mientkiewicz full time, which could have freed up a spot for Williams by eliminating the need for a platoon partner. It seemed unlikely Torre would have pushed for Williams to journey to Tampa, Fla., and then waive him.</p>
        <p>After Hiram Williams was reminded of Torre's comments and the situations that could have led to Bernie Williams's being with the Yankees yesterday, he said he understood why it seemed sensible for Bernie to accept the invitation. Still, Hiram explained why Bernie, who has 2,336 hits, 4 World Series rings and a batting title, refused.</p>
        <p>''He's not a journeyman,'' Hiram said. ''He's seen the same thing offered to minor leaguers. He's been with the Yankees for 16 years. Last year, he didn't do badly. He probably felt that he had earned the right to have a guaranteed spot.''</p>
        <p>Williams, 38, batted .281 with 12 homers and 61 runs batted in last year and provided a safety net when Hideki Matsui and Gary Sheffield had wrist injuries. Surely, Williams figured, the Yankees would want him back. But General Manager Brian Cashman considered 2006 to be Williams's swan song and does not see him as an option for 2007.</p>
        <p>Even if outfielders Johnny Damon, Bobby Abreu or Matsui incur a serious injury, club officials have indicated that their first choice would be to summon Kevin Thompson or Kevin Reese from Class AAA Scranton/Wilkes-Barre.</p>
        <p>When Roger Clemens ponders a midseason return, he can set his timetable because he is a dominant starter. When Williams, who would be a reserve outfielder with the Yankees, considers the same, he does have not the same liberties.</p>
        <p>Before the season was an inning old, the fans in the right-field bleachers remembered Williams by chanting, ''We want Bernie,'' several times. Mariano Rivera did not hear the chant but loved hearing about it.</p>
        <p>''The job Bernie did for this organization, this city, was tremendous,'' Rivera said. ''Those fans out there, they know.''</p>
        <p>Hiram Williams, 37, is a paralegal in San Juan and is a cellist who appeared on his brother's first album. If Bernie, a guitarist, does another album, Hiram will probably perform on it as well. But for now, Hiram said, Bernie remains focused on baseball over music. Even if it is a long shot, Bernie still envisions himself as a Yankee.</p>
        <p>''That would be a nice way for him to end the season,'' Hiram said. ''Maybe they could do that and it could be a kind of farewell.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
