<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>German Suitor Makes Deal With Rivals and Ends Its Bid for Endesa, a Spanish Utility</title>
    <meta content="03energy" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/business/worldbusiness/03energy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837741"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Spain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">E.on Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Endesa Sa</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Enel Spa</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Acciona</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burnett, Victoria</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sims, G Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernotat, Wulf H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Endesa SA</org>
        <org class="online_producer">E.ON AG</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E7DC1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="705" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>German Suitor Makes Deal With Rivals and Ends Its Bid for Endesa, a Spanish Utility</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">German Suitor Makes Deal With Rivals and Ends Its Bid for Endesa, a Spanish Utility</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VICTORIA BURNETT; G. Thomas Sims contributed reporting from Frankfurt.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burnett, Victoria; Sims, G Thomas</byline>
      <dateline>MADRID, April 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>German energy giant E.On withdraws its offer of 42.4 billion euros ($56.6 billion) for Spanish utility Endesa in exchange for promise from rival bidders to sell it part of Endesa's assets; E.On, acknowledging that it would not have been able to secure majority in Endesa, signs deal to gain assets valued at about 10 billion euros if its bidding rivals gain control; others, which are making joint bid, are Acciona and Enel; E.On's chief executive Wulf H Bernotat comments; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The German energy giant E.On on Monday withdrew its offer of 42.4 billion euros ($56.6 billion) for the Spanish utility Endesa in exchange for a promise from rival bidders to sell it part of Endesa's assets, ending one of Europe's most arcane takeover battles.</p>
        <p>Acknowledging that it would not have been able to secure a majority stake in Endesa, E.On said it had signed a deal to gain assets valued at about 10 billion euros if its bidding rivals gained control.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>E.On withdrew its offer in exchange for a promise from rival bidders to sell it part of Endesa’s assets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The German energy giant E.On on Monday withdrew its offer of 42.4 billion euros ($56.6 billion) for the Spanish utility Endesa in exchange for a promise from rival bidders to sell it part of Endesa's assets, ending one of Europe's most arcane takeover battles.</p>
        <p>Acknowledging that it would not have been able to secure a majority stake in Endesa, E.On said it had signed a deal to gain assets valued at about 10 billion euros if its bidding rivals gained control.</p>
        <p>The others, which are making a joint bid, are Acciona, the Spanish construction and energy conglomerate, and Enel, the Italian energy company.</p>
        <p>The deal came on the eve of a deadline for investors to tender shares to E.On, whose chances of mustering more than 50 percent of Endesa's stock collapsed 10 days ago when Acciona and Enel announced a plan to initiate a bid of 43.4 billion euros. The two companies had already gained control of 46 percent of Endesa's stock.</p>
        <p>''Acciona and Enel's involvement in Endesa has made our original goal of acquiring a majority stake in Endesa impossible,'' E.On's chief executive, Wulf H. Bernotat, said in a statement. ''Obtaining a minority interest in Endesa would have led to a stalemate between the shareholders and triggered unpredictable lawsuits.''</p>
        <p>By contrast, it said, Monday's agreement ''will rapidly establish clarity for everyone involved.''</p>
        <p>The E.On decision ends an 18-month fight for Endesa that has pitted the Spanish government against European regulators and has strained relations between Madrid and Berlin.</p>
        <p>It is also a defeat for Mr. Bernotat, who campaigned against the Spanish government's attempts to block the bid -- and raised it three times seeking to win shareholder support.</p>
        <p>''Given the mess that this bid was in -- and it was an extraordinary mess -- this is a happy ending,'' said Juan Carlos Martinez Lázaro, professor of economics at the Instituto de Empresa in Madrid. ''There had to be a negotiation of some sort. They were on a road to nowhere.''</p>
        <p>But it is far from the happy ending predicted six months ago by Prime Minister José Luis Rodríguez Zapatero of Spain, whose government fought to keep Endesa out of E.On's hands, only to now see a proposal for the company to be carved up and shared out.</p>
        <p>Spain had tried to keep E.On from buying Endesa to protect an earlier bid by Gas Natural of Spain, which could have produced a huge national energy company.</p>
        <p>But under the agreement, which was signed over the weekend, Enel and Acciona will formally begin their bid, which values Endesa at 43.4 billion euros. That bid was barred last week by Spain's stock market regulator for six months, except in the event that E.On dropped its bid.</p>
        <p>Under the deal, E.On will buy assets from Endesa in Spain as well as Enel's Spanish power utility, Viesgo, becoming the No. 4 player in the Spanish market. E.On will also buy Endesa Italia, to become the fourth-largest energy producer in Italy, and Endesa France/SNET.</p>
        <p>Ahead of E.On's announcement Monday, Enel and Acciona emphasized the ''Spanishness'' of their bid, which involves awarding Acciona primary control over the new Endesa, while requiring that Enel put up most of the money.</p>
        <p>Hours before E.On dropped its bid Monday, Manuel Conthe, Spain's top stock market regulator, said he would quit.</p>
        <p>His resignation came after fierce debates within the stock market regulatory agency about how to handle Acciona and Enel's offer for Endesa, which was deemed illegal by many legal experts and bankers.</p>
        <p>Ten days ago, Mr. Conthe pushed for sanctions against the two companies, saying that he thought their last-minute bid for Endesa broke the rules of the stock market. He was voted down by his fellow commission members.</p>
        <p>The stock market commission agreed on March 23 to the six-month ban on the bid by Enel and Acciona.</p>
        <p>Mr. Conthe said Monday only that he was resigning in accordance with a corporate governance code that indicates a director should take action if his board makes ''material or reiterated decisions'' about which he has serious reservations.</p>
        <p>He said he would present his resignation and his motives for stepping down to the economics committee of Spain's chamber of deputies.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
