<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Mideast Trip, U.N. Chief Sought to Expand New Role</title>
    <meta content="03nations" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/world/middleeast/03nations.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837691"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Middle East</location>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ban Ki-moon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7DD1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="874" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Mideast Trip, U.N. Chief Sought to Expand New Role</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On Mideast Trip, U.N. Chief Sought to Expand New Role</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN HOGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoge, Warren</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, April 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Secretary General Ban Ki-moon addressed United Nations peacekeepers standing at attention in their powder-blue berets and military decorations in southern Lebanon on Saturday, he confessed that he had risen only to the lowly rank of corporal in the South Korean Army.</p>
        <p>''But, as you know, my title is secretary general,'' he added. ''So now you can call me General Ban.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ban Ki-moon’s power resides in enhancing proposals with international legitimacy and respectability.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Secretary General Ban Ki-moon addressed United Nations peacekeepers standing at attention in their powder-blue berets and military decorations in southern Lebanon on Saturday, he confessed that he had risen only to the lowly rank of corporal in the South Korean Army.</p>
        <p>''But, as you know, my title is secretary general,'' he added. ''So now you can call me General Ban.''</p>
        <p>Over the past 10 days, the courtly and circumspect Mr. Ban made a start at putting a stamp of personal authority on the job in a furiously paced Middle East trip through some of the most fractious and confounding areas of his new responsibility.</p>
        <p>In every place he visited -- Egypt, Israel, the West Bank, Jordan, Lebanon and Saudi Arabia, where the leaders of the 22 nation-Arab League held a conference -- the United Nations is a player, and people freely throw around resolution numbers with no need to explain them.</p>
        <p>At the same time, while Mr. Ban is greeted in palaces and airport ceremonies with the red carpets, brass bands and full-dress military displays that welcome heads of state, he can make no ringing announcements of individual initiatives.</p>
        <p>Instead, his power resides in enhancing such proposals with international legitimacy and respectability.</p>
        <p>On becoming secretary general in January, Mr. Ban felt obliged to caution people not to mistake his Asian modesty for indecisiveness.</p>
        <p>On this trip, he pointedly sought out leaders from countries that make a habit of snubbing the United Nations.</p>
        <p>In Riyadh, Saudi Arabia, he spent three and a half hours in two meetings, one of which went into the early morning hours, with Omar Hassan al-Bashir, the president of Sudan, who is defying all efforts to get United Nations peacekeepers into Darfur.</p>
        <p>He acted to place the weight of the United Nations behind international efforts to free captured British sailors and marines by setting a breakfast meeting with Manouchehr Mottaki, the foreign minister of Iran, which persists in ignoring repeated Security Council demands to suspend its nuclear program.</p>
        <p>In Lebanon, he sought out Nabih Berri, the pro-Hezbollah speaker of Parliament, who is stalling efforts to convene a United Nations tribunal into the 2005 assassination of former Prime Minister Rafik Hariri.</p>
        <p>However, in an illustration of how he must weigh his actions, he spent a day with Mahmoud Abbas, the Palestinian president, and some of his cabinet members in Ramallah, but did not meet the prime minister, Ismail Haniya, of Hamas, which Washington and Jerusalem consider a terrorist organization.</p>
        <p>Along the way, there were frequent reminders of his newcomer status. In Jerusalem, Ehud Olmert, the Israeli prime minister, addressed him as Secretary Moon, and in Beirut, the Lebanese capital, Prime Minister Fouad Siniora referred to him as Mr. Annan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Olmert also publicly questioned his authority to invite leaders to a coming meeting of the quartet of countries and groups pursuing Middle East peace, of which the United Nations is one.</p>
        <p>In the Palestinian territories, where the United Nations spends about $500 million in assistance and its officials openly side with residents against their Israeli occupiers, Salam Fayyad, the Palestinian minister of finance, pleaded other priorities in not showing up at a lunch for Mr. Ban.</p>
        <p>In Amman, Mr. Ban's plane left him at Queen Alia International Airport while his welcoming party awaited him 20 miles away at Amman Airport. Reports broadcast by Al Arabiya showed him staring uncomprehendingly at a glass exit door and then sitting alone in the royal reception room until his convoy of limousines arrived from across town.</p>
        <p>When he persuaded Mr. Bashir to consider a plan to let the United Nations arrange logistical and financial support for an expanded African Union peacekeeping mission in Darfur, Mr. Ban and his aides portrayed it as a breakthrough.</p>
        <p>But human rights groups, aid organizations and others familiar with Mr. Bashir's record of duplicity saw it as yet another success by the Sudanese leader in forestalling the action that they consider imperative -- the deployment of United Nations peacekeepers alongside the Africans.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ban's aides said that he displayed a combative style in meetings, and that he seemed to exult in standing up to Mr. Bashir. ''The debate was sometimes very heated,'' he said of their meeting. Aides said that after midnight he evicted them so he could deal with Mr. Bashir one on one.</p>
        <p>The United Nations reputation for ineffectiveness results, at least in part, from the collision of high expectations and institutional limitations. No situation better illustrates that crippling reality than the continuing killing in Darfur.</p>
        <p>The United Nations led the way in calling attention to the crisis, then proved unable to overcome Sudan's refusal to accept peacekeepers and is now faulted for inaction in the face of genocide.</p>
        <p>At times, Mr. Ban demonstrated a sense of humor about himself and his ambitions in the compromising world of international diplomacy. After persuading Saud al-Faisal, the Saudi foreign minister, to approve a visa for Orly Azoulay, a Washington-based Israeli journalist traveling with his party, Mr. Ban came to reporters in the back of his plane on Tuesday and made the scooping arm motion of a sports figure celebrating a good shot.</p>
        <p>''Everything else is still just a proposal,'' he said. ''This is the first thing I have actually done.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
