<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Another Marathon Season Begins With a Quick First Step</title>
    <meta content="03rhoden" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/sports/baseball/03rhoden.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837773"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/William C Rhoden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Devil Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Jeter, Derek</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E6DB1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Another Marathon Season Begins With a Quick First Step</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Another Marathon Season Begins With a Quick First Step</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rhoden, William C</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There was a happy beginning in the Bronx yesterday.</p>
        <p>The Yankees pounded out a 9-5 victory against the Tampa Bay Devil Rays and opened their 105th season of major league baseball on a high note.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Derek Jeter reminded reporters after the Yankees pounded out an opening day victory, there are 161 more games to play.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There was a happy beginning in the Bronx yesterday.</p>
        <p>The Yankees pounded out a 9-5 victory against the Tampa Bay Devil Rays and opened their 105th season of major league baseball on a high note.</p>
        <p>But as Derek Jeter reminded reporters afterward, the players will play, and the news media will analyze, 161 more games. ''It's one game,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The message, of course, is to relax, take the long view, don't put too much into these opening moments or these April games.</p>
        <p>That's a lost cause, and Jeter knows it. There's a monster running loose at Yankee Stadium that lives for championships, has made championships the imprimatur of the organization, the source of its glory.</p>
        <p>George Steinbrenner III created the beast, and a core of veteran players -- led by Jeter -- feeds it. Jeter, the Yankees' captain, is fond of pointing out at the beginning and end of each season that the Yankees are about winning championships. Anything short of that is failure.</p>
        <p>Hence, from April to September no moment will be too great or too small to dissect. In an era of Not Enough, there is a renewed demand in the Bronx for more. More from Jeter, more from Alex Rodriguez, infinitely more from Carl Pavano.</p>
        <p>In many ways Jeter, Pavano and Rodriguez represent the qualities that have consistently been missing in the Yankees' six-year quest to win another world championship and recent failures to get out of the first round: leadership, durability and performance.</p>
        <p>Yankees General Manager Brian Cashman was philosophical about opening day and the pressures on his organization.</p>
        <p>''Early on, I was geeked every opening day,'' he said. ''I was overly excited. I learned the hard way not to put too much significance in the first win or the first loss.</p>
        <p>''This is a marathon, not a sprint. The playoffs are a sprint, not a marathon.''</p>
        <p>What happens in April often has little bearing on October, when the Yankees usually are in the postseason and a team like Tampa Bay has long since folded its tent. Welcome to another Yankees marathon.</p>
        <p>The other day, Manager Joe Torre made a plea to Yankees fans to more or less have mercy on Pavano, who hadn't pitched for the Yankees since June 2005.</p>
        <p>Pavano survived yesterday. He lasted four and a third innings; allowed five runs, six hits and two walks; and overcame two fielding errors. He also provided Tampa Bay's Elijah Dukes with a Yankee Stadium memory: Dukes's line-drive home run against Pavano was his first major league hit.</p>
        <p>Last month A-Rod made a similar plea for mercy during a radio interview, effectively saying that fan reaction to his theatrics would determine whether he would remain in New York or leave after the season. Let's get one thing straight: anyone who manages or plays for a team with a $200 million payroll forfeits any claim to mercy.</p>
        <p>If yesterday's fan reaction was any indication, Rodriguez should not immediately pack, but should leave a suitcase on the bed, just in case.</p>
        <p>He committed a first-inning error. He was booed.</p>
        <p>In his first at-bat, with fans roaring their support, Rodriguez struck out. More boos.</p>
        <p>He rallied in the seventh inning when he singled, stole second and scored on Jason Giambi's hit. Cheers.</p>
        <p>In the eighth, Rodriguez hit a two-run homer, his 465th career home run. Wild cheers, followed by a curtain call.</p>
        <p>After the game, in what will surely be a pattern for the season, Jeter was asked about Rodriguez's performance. ''Yeah, he played well,'' Jeter said, clearing his throat. ''I thought for the most part everyone, except for being a little soft on defense, everyone played well.''</p>
        <p>The most significant moment of the afternoon took place before the game when Steinbrenner made his way into the stadium, appearing more feeble and struggling more than ever. This was not the robust Steinbrenner who would often stop to address reporters and make a proclamation or a threatening comment about a manager's job security.</p>
        <p>The Boss's apparent fragility and last week's news of his daughter's filing for divorce from his presumed successor, Steve Swindal, reminded Yankees fans of potential storm clouds ahead.</p>
        <p>Steinbrenner will be 77 in July. There are escalating questions about his health and looming questions about the future of the organization. Who will inherit the team? Will the family sell? If they sell, to whom?</p>
        <p>While the championship run between 1996 and 2000 was impressive, the distance between championships continues to widen.</p>
        <p>Yankee Stadium remains impressive as a national treasure. But the Yankees as a team are no longer intimidating and haven't been since 2003, when the world watched the upstart, low-budget Florida Marlins celebrate a World Series victory at Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>The Yankees have not won a World Series since 2000. There have been six different champions since then. Yesterday was a good day. But as Cashman and Jeter pointed out, it was only one day and one game.</p>
        <p>At a time of insatiable appetites for success, this will be yet another season when the fans demand more. Much more.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: wcr@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: wcr@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
