<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GATORS' DEFENSE RESTS</title>
    <meta content="03men" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/sports/ncaabasketball/03men.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837830"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Florida</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Ohio State University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Noah, Joakim</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Oden, Greg</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E7DA1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1000" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GATORS' DEFENSE RESTS</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Gators Repeat as National Champions</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETE THAMEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Thamel, Pete</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, April 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Florida Gators left one final, indelible memory as one of the great teams in modern college basketball. Their emphatic 84-75 victory over Ohio State in the national title game Monday night gave them back-to-back championships -- the first repeat titlist since Duke in 1991 and 1992 -- and a claim as arguably the best team since John Wooden's dynasty days at U.C.L.A.</p>
        <p>For decades, perhaps, Joakim Noah, Al Horford, Corey Brewer, Taurean Green and Lee Humphrey will be compared to the great college basketball starting lineups.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Florida Gators left one final mark for their legacy as one of the great teams in college basketball.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Florida Gators left one final, indelible memory as one of the great teams in modern college basketball. Their emphatic 84-75 victory over Ohio State in the national title game Monday night gave them back-to-back championships -- the first repeat titlist since Duke in 1991 and 1992 -- and a claim as arguably the best team since John Wooden's dynasty days at U.C.L.A.</p>
        <p>For decades, perhaps, Joakim Noah, Al Horford, Corey Brewer, Taurean Green and Lee Humphrey will be compared to the great college basketball starting lineups.</p>
        <p>They were Florida's primary starters for the past two seasons and will be best remembered as chemistry majors on the floor, with their unselfishness as strong a defining trait as their talent.</p>
        <p>''I think I was fortunate enough to coach a group of guys that has to go down in history as one of the greatest teams of all time,'' Florida Coach Billy Donovan said.</p>
        <p>With Bill Belichick, Donovan's close friend, watching from the stands, these Gators again personified the team concept that Belichick's Patriots brought to the National Football League. Florida is the first team to win the N.C.A.A. football and men's basketball championships in the same academic year. The Gators defeated Ohio State to win the football title in January.</p>
        <p>Florida (35-5) won the university's second national title in basketball with many strong performances. Each Gators starter except Noah scored in double figures, led by Horford's 18. The senior reserve forward Chris Richard played a valuable role off the bench by scoring 8 points, grabbing 8 rebounds and guarding Ohio State center Greg Oden. Corey Brewer had 13 points and 8 rebounds and was named the Final Four's most outstanding player.</p>
        <p>''I would put them in a category as probably one of the best teams to win,'' Ohio State Coach Thad Matta said. ''You're going to see those guys playing a lot of basketball for many years ahead.''</p>
        <p>Florida controlled the entire game but never quite put Ohio State away. The Buckeyes cut the Florida lead to 6 late in the second half, but a 3-pointer by Green with 4 minutes 50 seconds remaining gave Florida a 69-60 lead and enough cushion to hang on. The shot crystallized the theme of the second half: Every time Ohio State scrapped back into shouting distance, Green or Humphrey seemed to hit a key shot.</p>
        <p>''Their key players stepped up in big situations,'' Ohio State point guard Mike Conley Jr. said. ''That's why they're national champions again.''</p>
        <p>As unlikely as it was for Noah, Brewer and Horford to return for their junior seasons for this title run, it would be even more improbable for them to return as seniors.</p>
        <p>The parallel to the Florida juniors' returning this season was the return of elite freshmen like Oden to college basketball because of new N.B.A. rules. Oden led the Buckeyes to a 35-4 record but short of their first national title since 1960.</p>
        <p>The end of Oden's career is considered somewhat of an inevitability in college basketball circles; he is almost guaranteed to be the No. 1 pick in the N.B.A. draft.</p>
        <p>Oden left with a bang, scoring 25 points and grabbing 12 rebounds. The lasting image of his final collegiate game will be his hammering dunks on overmatched defenders and doing his trademark pull-up on the rim.</p>
        <p>''We got any and everything out of Greg tonight,'' Conley said.</p>
        <p>But Oden's singular dominance was overshadowed by the superior all-around talent of Florida's starting five.</p>
        <p>Florida won the loose-ball battles and played better as a team. No play better epitomized these Gators than a key sequence early in the second half. After a missed a shot, Horford dived for a loose ball. He tipped the ball to Green, and four passes later Humphrey was all alone for a 3-point shot at the top of the key. All that hustle, teamwork and unselfishness ended with Humphrey making the shot and the Gators taking a 49-38 lead.</p>
        <p>Humphrey had his second consecutive stellar national title game, scoring 14 points and shooting 4 for 7 from 3-point range. As a team, Florida made 10 of 18 3-pointers.</p>
        <p>After trailing by as many as 13 points in the first half and by 11 at halftime, Ohio State never cut the lead below 6 points in the second half.</p>
        <p>Ohio State fell behind in the first half after Conley picked up two early fouls. His second foul came on a 3-point attempt by Green with 12:16 remaining in the half and the score tied at 11-11. Florida took the lead with Green's three free throws and proceeded to take control of the game with an 8-2 run.</p>
        <p>One of the biggest story lines heading into the game was Oden's ability to stay on the floor, which he did last night surprisingly well. Oden had been mired in foul trouble throughout this N.C.A.A. tournament.</p>
        <p>Oden played less than three minutes of the first half of Ohio State's semifinal game against Georgetown, and the Ohio State assistant Dan Peters openly questioned if officials in college knew how to officiate true centers because there had been so few in recent years.</p>
        <p>But the referees Karl Hess, Ed Corbett and Tony Greene let the big men muscle around down low, and Oden did not pick up a foul until nearly 11 minutes had passed. He left the game with 8:41 remaining in the first half because he needed a rest, not because of foul trouble.</p>
        <p>The other key first-half run came after a 3-pointer by Ivan Harris cut the Florida lead to 2 points with 5:33 remaining in the half. But 3-pointers from Humphrey, Brewer and Green built the lead back to 11 within the next two minutes.</p>
        <p>That burst showcased the offensive explosiveness that was among the hallmarks of this Gators team, one of the many reasons that this night sealed their place in history.</p>
        <p>''Hopefully, we'll be viewed as one of the best college basketball teams to ever play the game,'' Brewer said.</p>
        <p>N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
