<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Itineraries; Lost and Very Rarely Found</title>
    <meta content="03lost" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/03/business/03lost.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837710"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Business Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Industry News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Lost and Found Property</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lost and Found Property</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E4DD1F30F930A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1130" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Itineraries; Lost and Very Rarely Found</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lost and Very Rarely Found</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAIRE ATKINSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The minute Scott Karambis passed through security on his way out of Logan Airport in Boston he realized his new video iPod was still onboard the Midwest Airlines plane.</p>
        <p>''It was one of those endless days,'' said Mr. Karambis, an advertising executive from Beverly Farms, Mass. ''The plane was delayed and I was half asleep and I just didn't keep my things together.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Small electronic gadgets are the items most easily left behind, but travelers leave all sorts of things on planes and in hotel rooms.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The minute Scott Karambis passed through security on his way out of Logan Airport in Boston he realized his new video iPod was still onboard the Midwest Airlines plane.</p>
        <p>''It was one of those endless days,'' said Mr. Karambis, an advertising executive from Beverly Farms, Mass. ''The plane was delayed and I was half asleep and I just didn't keep my things together.''</p>
        <p>For anyone who travels for a living, the loss of personal belongings can be a frustrating and painful experience. And it is becoming more common, as gadgets become smaller and the list of essential business travel tools becomes longer.</p>
        <p>In addition to hanging on to boarding passes and other travel documents, business travelers are carrying a cornucopia of electronic items, including BlackBerrys, cellphones, iPods and earphones, digital cameras, U.S.B. sticks and laptops. Travelers can be hauling several thousand dollars' worth of electronic gear on any one trip (sentimental value not included).</p>
        <p>''That's a trend that we've seen coming for a while,'' said Robert Egner, a vice president at Pointsec, a Chicago-based data security firm. ''The smaller they get, the more frequently they flip away. Our data shows that trend.''</p>
        <p>Every year, 3 to 6 percent of portable electronic gadgets with corporate network access end up missing, according to Pointsec. And during the six-month period from April through September last year, Pointsec found, 8,701 mobile devices were left in taxicabs in the Washington-Baltimore area, and 3,106 were left in cabs in the San Francisco-Oakland area.</p>
        <p>It is not hard to figure out why people forget things on business trips. Sleep deprivation, hunger and lack of concentration can all affect memory. Travel-related losses fall under the category of absent-mindedness, said Daniel L. Schacter, a Harvard University psychology professor and author of ''The Seven Sins of Memory: How the Mind Forgets and Remembers.''</p>
        <p>''When we're traveling we are very focused on the goal of the trip and what we do when we get there,'' he said, adding that when people are distracted they do not encode the information required to carry on multiple activities or they miss regular cues for remembering their possessions. He recalled how Yo-Yo Ma left an 18th-century cello worth $2.5 million in the trunk of a New York taxicab in 1999 (the cello was recovered a few hours later, safe and sound).</p>
        <p>Like the rest of us, Mr. Schacter has lost items on business trips. ''There have been a few times I've left clothes,'' he admitted. ''Generally, I don't follow up.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schacter is not alone. Many business travelers simply write off the loss and move on. The evidence piles up in lost-and-found closets at hotels, airports and train stations, where everything from phone chargers to wigs, dentures, cosmetics and clothes are left.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for Continental Airlines, Mary Clark, said the most common items left on board were iPods, eyeglasses and cellphones, followed by portable DVD players.</p>
        <p>Those who try to retrieve their possessions are usually in for a lot of heartache. Kate Macaluso, a director of creative services at an Italian fashion house, said she left a beloved Gucci trench coat on a first-class seat on a British Airways flight, and remembered it minutes after passing through security. ''I followed up with a phone call to the gate agent less than one hour after deplaning,'' she said. ''I never heard back. I also sent an e-mail to customer service which went unanswered.''</p>
        <p>A British Airways spokeswoman, Michele Kropf, said that passengers were reminded to take their belongings and that passengers who lost items should call the customer contact center, which in turn calls the baggage services at the airport where the item was lost.</p>
        <p>If you remember you left an item on a plane while you are on your way out of the airport in the United States, do not expect to be able to turn around and retrieve it. A Transportation Security Administration spokeswoman said that once travelers passed beyond secure checkpoint areas into public areas they were not allowed to return. The T.S.A. does allow passengers who have not passed out of security to return to the aircraft with airline personnel to retrieve items.</p>
        <p>Returning lost property appears to be far down the list of priorities at most airlines, judging by the lack of information at airline Web sites. Some airlines, like American, offer phone numbers for airports and local ticket desks; others, like US Airways, have an online form to complete.</p>
        <p>According to the Continental Airlines Web site, items left on board can be reported using a toll-free number run by its baggage resolution center staff (that number is 1-800-335-BAGS, or 1-800-335-2247). A baggage services representative at any airport can also be notified of the loss. If the item is found, Continental will ship it via FedEx at the owner's cost, according to a spokeswoman.</p>
        <p>At Amtrak, claims for lost items must be submitted within 30 days at the station of arrival or by calling the national phone number (1-800-USA-Rail or 1-800-872-7245) and asking for a customer relations agent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Karambis never recovered his iPod. He was unable to return to his airplane once he exited through the checkpoints, and was frustrated by the customer service provided by both the airport and airline. He said that the lost-and-found process exposed many faults in the airline customer-service chain. ''The phone tree is just another steel vault,'' he said, describing his attempts to contact various lost-and-found departments.</p>
        <p>Since the incident, Mr. Karambis said, he never rushes to get off an aircraft. He takes a good look around before leaving his seat.</p>
        <p>Patrick Hatton, general manager of the James Chicago hotel, also has a strategy for keeping losses to a minimum while he is traveling. Before he checks out of a hotel, he looks in every drawer and under the bed and advises travelers to never be overconfident that they have everything.</p>
        <p>Professor Schacter added: ''Try to develop a systematic approach for cues that can remind you of what you might otherwise forget. Each time you move from one location to another, review the status of your belongings. Maybe even keep a checklist that you review regularly.''</p>
        <p>Some businesses go the extra mile. Mr. Hatton recalls one guest of the James insisting that an urgent DHL package had arrived from her office, but no one at the hotel could find it. Fearful it could have landed in the trash, the hotel contacted its garbage contractor, Waste Management, and had hotel employees conduct the kind of hotelwide search usually reserved for homicide detectives. The waste company agreed to isolate the trash at a warehouse before it reached the landfill. When the package still did not turn up, the guest was informed and later admitted: the package was still sitting in her office.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
