<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For a Versatile Director, a Season of Trilogies</title>
    <meta content="20obri" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/arts/20obri.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841519"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Tom Stoppard</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays/Coast of Utopia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Metropolitan Opera</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3DB1F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1038" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For a Versatile Director, a Season of Trilogies</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For a Versatile Director, a Season of Trilogies</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE MIDGETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Midgette, Anne</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Everybody likes Jack O'Brien. At the mention of his name, people audibly soften. ''He has a wonderful aura about him that makes him incredibly attractive,'' said the mezzo-soprano Stephanie Blythe. ''You just want to spend time with him.''</p>
        <p>It seems downright reactionary for a major stage director to be so popular.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jack O’Brien has a number of Broadway hits to his credit. But these days he is best known around town for directing two trilogies at Lincoln Center, back to back.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Everybody likes Jack O'Brien. At the mention of his name, people audibly soften. ''He has a wonderful aura about him that makes him incredibly attractive,'' said the mezzo-soprano Stephanie Blythe. ''You just want to spend time with him.''</p>
        <p>It seems downright reactionary for a major stage director to be so popular.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Brien has a number of Broadway hits to his credit -- ''The Full Monty,'' ''Dirty Rotten Scoundrels,'' ''Hairspray'' -- and has won two Tony Awards (for ''Hairspray'' and ''Henry IV''). But these days he is best known around town for directing two trilogies at Lincoln Center, back to back. First there was Tom Stoppard's ''Coast of Utopia'' at the Vivian Beaumont Theater; tonight he will make his debut at the Metropolitan Opera with Puccini's ''Trittico.'' Pretty heady stuff.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Brien, in fact, is worried about what people think of him in the wake of so much work. Friends, he said, hearing he was taking on the double whammy of two trilogies, said, ''Only you, Jack.'' What did that mean, he wondered, about how his friends perceived him?</p>
        <p>''A sort of dray horse?'' he said.</p>
        <p>But there is no doubt in his mind about how he'll follow this tough act.</p>
        <p>''I feel I must quickly, swiftly return to the world of commerce,'' he said. ''It's been a whole year of fees and no royalties. Thank goodness 'Hairspray' is still running.''</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Brien, an ageless 67, came from a ''Trittico'' rehearsal into an office at the Met with a clear, gracious smile and eyes that seem perpetually to shine through his glasses. On the video screens in the Met's public spaces, stage hands could be seen taking apart pieces of the sets (by Douglas W. Schmidt, a longtime collaborator) that have turned out to be the biggest, in terms of the number of stage wagons required, that the Met currently has in its repertory -- bigger, even, than those for Franco Zeffirelli's ''Turandot,'' frequently cited for its excess.</p>
        <p>Size wasn't the point of the exercise. Doing justice to the pieces was.</p>
        <p>''It was written for this house,'' Mr. O'Brien said of the trilogy, which had its world premiere at the Met in 1918. ''It was Puccini's New York piece. James Levine felt it had never been given its due.'' (Mr. Levine is conducting.) The operas had only one other Met production: Fabrizio Melano's in 1975, which remained in intermittent rotation until 1989.</p>
        <p>''I didn't want to do a thematic thing,'' Mr. O'Brien said of his approach to the triptych. ''I felt we should take each piece on its own.''</p>
        <p>Puccini's trilogy, staged in a single performance, is made up of three unrelated stories. ''Il Tabarro'' is about an ill-fated love triangle among working people on a French barge; ''Suor Angelica'' portrays a woman whose family has shut her up in a convent; and ''Gianni Schicchi,'' set in Florence, is a comedy about the greedy relatives of a dying miser.</p>
        <p>'' 'The Coast of Utopia' is very different,'' he added. ''The story is evolving in a historical perspective. The pieces of 'Trittico' are bound by Puccini's own imagination and the sound of his music.''</p>
        <p>Another difference: ''The incessant, extremely complex voice of Stoppard needed to be banged off surfaces,'' he said. ''I had to refresh you, not tire you. 'Il Trittico' has different problems, especially prejudices. This is not the first time you've seen these operas. Whereas with 'Coast of Utopia,' no one knew what the hell it was.''</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Brien's story is not simply that of a theater director approaching opera. He's been working in opera from the beginning. His ''Porgy and Bess'' for the Houston Grand Opera, which came to Broadway in 1976, won a Tony the next year and continued to tour for a decade -- highly unusual for an opera production. He has also directed ''Tosca'' in Santa Fe, N.M., ''The Magic Flute'' in San Francisco, ''Street Scene'' in New York and many others.</p>
        <p>''My debut was 'Dido and Aeneas' with Jon Vickers and Tatiana Troyanos,'' he said, naming two towering singers of recent operatic history. ''I didn't know. I thought they all sounded like that.''</p>
        <p>But after his intense experience with ''Porgy,'' working with a single production for 10 years, ''it seemed a comedown,'' he said, to go into the more time-constrained process of regular opera directing. And he didn't want opera to become his whole career. So in 1982 he became artistic director of the Old Globe Theater in San Diego, where he has maintained a remarkable flexibility, doing everything from Shakespeare to Stoppard to ''Scoundrels.''</p>
        <p>''My job is storytelling,'' he said. ''My medium is people. Sometimes they dance; sometimes they sing.''</p>
        <p>His approach to ''Hairspray'' is not a priori different from his approach to ''Suor Angelica.'' It begins with getting to know the piece, inside and out, and, as he puts it: ''Waking a beating heart in anything I try to do. To make it live is important to me.''</p>
        <p>It has the stamp of something he says often, and yet it doesn't sound trite.</p>
        <p>His ability to animate seems to be working in ''Trittico,'' at least among the cast members, whom Ms. Blythe -- singing alongside Salvatore Licitra, Maria Guleghina, Barbara Frittoli, Juan Pons -- describes as ''very turned on by the process.''</p>
        <p>''It's fascinating to watch him work,'' she continued. ''He's such a terrific actor. He doesn't tell you, 'Go here and do this.' What he does is actually demonstrate the inner working of the character by creating an inner dialogue. He helps you see your character from the inside out.''</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Brien's next project, with Terrence McNally and the ''Hairspray'' team, is a stage musical version of ''Catch Me If You Can,'' based on the Steven Spielberg movie of the same title. But he hasn't ruled out more opera.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, he had work to do.</p>
        <p>'' 'Suor Angelica' has to have a miracle,'' Mr. O'Brien said. ''I have to make a real world for Angelica, or the miracle won't happen.''</p>
        <p>''Il Trittico'' opens tonight and runs through May 12 at the Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center; (212) 362-6000, metopera.org. There will be a live broadcast in movie theaters around the world on April 28. (The Web site has the locations.)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
