<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Killings of Afghan Civilians Recall Haditha</title>
    <meta content="20abuse" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/world/asia/20abuse.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841563"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE REACH OF WAR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jalalabad (Afghanistan)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Haditha (Iraq)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Von Zielbauer, Paul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Afghanistan</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Marine Corps</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E0D91F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Killings of Afghan Civilians Recall Haditha</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Killings of Afghan Civilians Recall Haditha</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL von ZIELBAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Von Zielbauer, Paul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Military investigation finds marines killed at least 10 civilians and wounded dozens near Jalalabad, Afghanistan, on March 4, with no evidence they were being fired upon; episode bears striking similarities to 2005 killings of 24 civilians in Haditha, Iraq, by marines; actions taken by marines suggest training that required them to respond to danger with thoughtful precision were forgotten; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After it became clear last year that several marines had killed 24 civilians in Haditha, Iraq, following an attack on their convoy of Humvees, the Marine Corps, which had initially played down the massacre, began an offensive of a different kind.</p>
        <p>Last May, Gen. Michael W. Hagee, the commandant of the Marine Corps at the time, went to Iraq to express deep concern to his marines and to reinforce what he called the ''core values'' that required them to respond to danger with thoughtful precision.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The killing of 10 civilians in Afghanistan suggested that the Marine Corps had not learned the lessons of a earlier attack on civilians in Haditha, Iraq.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After it became clear last year that several marines had killed 24 civilians in Haditha, Iraq, following an attack on their convoy of Humvees, the Marine Corps, which had initially played down the massacre, began an offensive of a different kind.</p>
        <p>Last May, Gen. Michael W. Hagee, the commandant of the Marine Corps at the time, went to Iraq to express deep concern to his marines and to reinforce what he called the ''core values'' that required them to respond to danger with thoughtful precision.</p>
        <p>But almost a year later, marines killed at least 10 civilians in Afghanistan in an episode that bore some striking similarities to the Haditha killings and suggested that the lesson had not taken, even in a platoon of combat veterans wearing the badge of the elite new Marine Corps Special Operations forces.</p>
        <p>Marine Corps officials said the unit, whose members undergo at least four months of specialized military training, did not receive specific values training addressing the lessons of Haditha. The actions of the 30 marines on patrol in Afghanistan appeared to contradict many of the edicts General Hagee had implored the marines to remember.</p>
        <p>''We use lethal force only when justified, proportional and, most importantly, lawful,'' General Hagee declared in a series of talks he gave at Marine bases around the world. ''We must regulate force and violence,'' he added. ''We protect the noncombatants we find on the battlefield.''</p>
        <p>A preliminary military investigation found that the marines killed at least 10 civilians and wounded dozens along a stretch of road near Jalalabad on March 4, and no evidence that they were being fired upon.</p>
        <p>The killings illustrate the difficulty American forces have encountered in fighting an enemy who often wears no uniform, uses civilians for cover and understands the limits of the American military's strict rules of engagement.</p>
        <p>But they also show how hard it can be for officers to control the actions of heavily armed troops in the heat of battle.</p>
        <p>As the marines did in Haditha, those on patrol in Afghanistan began shooting at civilians in reaction to an attack, in this case a suicide bomber who drove into their convoy as it traveled to Jalalabad from Torkham and detonated his explosives, said Lt. Col. Lou Leto, a spokesman for Army Maj. Gen. Frank Kearney, the commander of all American Special Operations forces in the region.</p>
        <p>''When the marines recovered from the blast, they thought they were taking fire, so they returned fire,'' Colonel Leto said Wednesday, paraphrasing findings of the inquiry, in which the marines and civilian witnesses had been interviewed.</p>
        <p>As the convoy sped away, several marines shot at people near the side of the road, in cars on the shoulders or working in fields nearby, Colonel Leto said. As they did in Haditha, the marines near Jalalabad overreacted to the initial attack, the investigation suggests, firing at unarmed civilians who happened to be nearby.</p>
        <p>''The evidence that we found was that they just weren't fighters,'' Colonel Leto said. ''They saw people in the fields. They thought these people were carrying weapons, but they could have been tools.''</p>
        <p>Colonel Leto said by telephone from the United Arab Emirates that the marines had fired on several cars. ''Some cars they thought were taking aggressive actions, another was not following directions,'' he said. ''You can imagine, you are hit with a pretty good blast, the air gets sucked out of you, you have to make judgment calls real quick.''</p>
        <p>The military report found that the marines had killed 10 people, including an elderly man and a young woman, and wounded 33 others. But a report by the Afghanistan Independent Human Rights Commission said the marines had killed 12 people and wounded 35.</p>
        <p>As in Haditha, many of the civilians killed in Afghanistan were women and children, a detailed report by the human rights group said.</p>
        <p>General Kearney ordered the entire company, the first Special Forces unit sent into battle since the Marines Special Operations command was formed 14 months ago, to leave Afghanistan at the beginning of April, Colonel Leto said. He also referred the matter to the Naval Criminal Investigative Service.</p>
        <p>The platoon involved in the ambush and subsequent killings was responsible for gathering intelligence in the field and capturing or killing enemy fighters, said Maj. Cliff Gilmore, a spokesman for the Marine Corps Forces Special Operations Command. The marines were drawn from a Marine Force Reconnaissance unit and have an average of seven years of military experience and more than 15 months of combat experience in Iraq or Afghanistan. Colonel Leto said, ''They were still new on the scene.'' He declined to say how many marines had fired or possibly killed civilians but, without elaborating, he said marines being questioned have been ''separated'' from the unit.</p>
        <p>All marines get instructions on the laws of armed conflict, the Geneva Conventions and the rules of engagement, which require positive identification of hostile intent before shooting. But General Kearney's month-long investigation seems to indicate that those rules were violated by an elite unit, military officers said.</p>
        <p>''You do ask, 'How did this happen?' '' said an officer familiar with the inquiry, speaking on condition of anonymity. ''And it's a fair question.''</p>
        <p>THE REACH OF WAR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
