<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Principal Gets Up to 14 Years In Case of Sex With Student</title>
    <meta content="20teacher" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/nyregion/20teacher.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841659"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Private and Sectarian Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Principals (School)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sinha, Lina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berkman, Carol (Justice)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hartocollis, Anemona</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Principals (School)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Private and Sectarian Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E0D61F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="640" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Principal Gets Up to 14 Years In Case of Sex With Student</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Principal Gets Up to 14 Years in Case of Sex With Student</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANEMONA HARTOCOLLIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hartocollis, Anemona</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Justice Carol Berkman sentences Linha Sinha, former private school principal in Manhattan, to up to 14 years in prison for having sexual relationship with student; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Lilies that fester smell far worse than weeds,'' a judge in Manhattan said yesterday, quoting Shakespeare, before sentencing a former private school principal to up to 14 years in prison for having a sexual relationship with a student.</p>
        <p>Justice Carol Berkman of State Supreme Court in Manhattan said she was reminded of the line, from Sonnet 94, as she listened to a prosecutor and a defense lawyer argue over whether the principal, Lina Sinha -- whom the judge described as ''well raised'' and beautiful -- should be granted leniency because of her privileged background and unblemished life before the offense.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A judge in Manhattan sentenced a private school principal to up to 14 years in prison for having a sexual relationship with a student.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Lilies that fester smell far worse than weeds,'' a judge in Manhattan said yesterday, quoting Shakespeare, before sentencing a former private school principal to up to 14 years in prison for having a sexual relationship with a student.</p>
        <p>Justice Carol Berkman of State Supreme Court in Manhattan said she was reminded of the line, from Sonnet 94, as she listened to a prosecutor and a defense lawyer argue over whether the principal, Lina Sinha -- whom the judge described as ''well raised'' and beautiful -- should be granted leniency because of her privileged background and unblemished life before the offense.</p>
        <p>The prosecutor, Florence Chapin, argued that Ms. Sinha, 40, was an arrogant, Ivy League-educated woman who had used her sophistication, education and position as a teacher to manipulate the lives of two boys, violating their innocence and abusing their trust and that of society.</p>
        <p>Ms. Chapin said Ms. Sinha had had ''every privilege, every advantage,'' and had led ''a life untouched by hardship.'' Ms. Sinha had a degree from Columbia. Her family owns three Montessori schools in Manhattan, Brooklyn and Queens.</p>
        <p>More typically, Ms. Chapin told the judge, criminal defendants have ''lives scarred by poverty,'' by drug addiction, bad education and broken families. ''Why is Lina Sinha any more worthy than those people?'' she said. Prosecutors said she seduced a student in a classroom of the Montessori School of New York, on East 55th Street, with oral sex when he was 13 and had sex with him at 15. He is now a 24-year-old police officer.</p>
        <p>Ms. Sinha was also convicted of bribing a second boy to prevent him from cooperating with prosecutors, but the jury deadlocked on whether she had sex with him.</p>
        <p>Gerald Shargel, Ms. Sinha's lawyer, countered that it seemed as if the prosecutor wanted to punish Ms. Sinha more rather than equally because of her exemplary life.</p>
        <p>''I am stunned -- and I am not easily stunned, judge -- by the fact that the prosecutor should suggest this is the case for maximum imprisonment,'' Mr. Shargel said.</p>
        <p>''It sounds to me that she is asking for some kind of additional punishment because Lina Sinha comes from a privileged background,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He said Ms. Sinha, who did not speak during the sentencing, should receive a sentence comparable to those of other sex offenders in similar cases. Mr. Shargel -- seemingly taking into account the victim's testimony that he had enjoyed the sex -- said that Ms. Sinha's crime was not as egregious as that of someone who had forcibly had sex with an under-age victim, who had a previous criminal record or who had sex with a prepubescent child.</p>
        <p>In sentencing Ms. Sinha to 4 years and 8 months to 14 years, Justice Berkman refused to compare this case with others, saying she was not going to wade into ''the thicket of proportionality.'' But she said that Ms. Sinha's privileges did make her ''all the more culpable'' because she had the means to make other choices or get help.</p>
        <p>Justice Berkman said some of Ms. Sinha's actions -- a series of hysterical calls to police falsely accusing the student of raping another woman after the first student broke up with her when he entered the Police Academy -- appeared to be the product of a disturbed mind. But she said she found the calls ''chilling'' and Ms. Sinha's ability to lie in them ''astonishing.''</p>
        <p>She said Ms. Sinha ''took a great deal'' from the victim: ''his innocence, the natural experience of adolescence, his first girlfriend, first prom, whatever, it's speculative, I don't know.''</p>
        <p>Yet while the damage might be speculative, Justice Berkman said, ''our culture, our society,'' presumed that sex between adults and children was damaging.</p>
        <p>''Miss Sinha is intelligent,'' Justice Berkman said. ''She's well educated. She's well raised. She's hard-working. She's beautiful. And she's a predator who lived a lie.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
