<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Asia to the Caribbean to New York, Appetite Intact</title>
    <meta content="20immigrants" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/nyregion/20immigrants.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841625"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Caribbean-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asian-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Richmond Hill (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Trinidad and Tobago</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Guyana</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernstein, Nina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Guyana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Trinidad and Tobago</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Trinidad and Tobago/Trinidad</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Trinidad and Tobago/Tobago</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asian-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00EFD71F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1028" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Asia to the Caribbean to New York, Appetite Intact</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From Asia to the Caribbean to New York, Appetite Intact</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NINA BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Nina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Caribbean Asians are emerging as vibrant force in Queens, most obviously in thriving market in Richmond Hill, which now draws Indo-Caribbean shoppers from whole region as well as New Yorkers of all backgrounds; estimates of Indo-Caribbean immigrants to New York vary from 50,000 to 300,000; most are from Guyana and Trinidad; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Yearning for a taste of home in 1950s New York, a man from Trinidad hunted for aloo pie, the spicy potato pastry that is a favorite of Trinidadians of South Asian ancestry. But he could not find it in his Brooklyn neighborhood, where, unlike him, most Caribbean immigrants were of African descent.</p>
        <p>Then he discovered the potato knish, a city street food with a Jewish immigrant pedigree. Sliced open and slathered with hot pepper sauce, knishes became his comfort food -- much as aloo pie had once comforted his forebears, immigrants to the Caribbean who had longed for the samosas of their homes in India.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A story about an encounter with knishes illustrates the layered immigrant experience of Caribbean Asians, an ethnic group that is emerging as a vibrant force in southern Queens.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Yearning for a taste of home in 1950s New York, a man from Trinidad hunted for aloo pie, the spicy potato pastry that is a favorite of Trinidadians of South Asian ancestry. But he could not find it in his Brooklyn neighborhood, where, unlike him, most Caribbean immigrants were of African descent.</p>
        <p>Then he discovered the potato knish, a city street food with a Jewish immigrant pedigree. Sliced open and slathered with hot pepper sauce, knishes became his comfort food -- much as aloo pie had once comforted his forebears, immigrants to the Caribbean who had longed for the samosas of their homes in India.</p>
        <p>As told by Ramin Ganeshram, a writer, chef and teacher of Caribbean cooking, the story about her father's encounter with knishes illustrates the layered immigrant experience of Caribbean Asians, an ethnic group that is emerging as a vibrant force in southern Queens.</p>
        <p>They are the descendants of hundreds of thousands of indentured workers taken to the sugar cane fields of the Caribbean from India, and to a lesser extent from China, to replace freed African slaves between 1838 and 1917.</p>
        <p>''Caribbeans of Indian descent or Chinese descent have an interesting dilemma,'' said Ms. Ganeshram, one of several scheduled speakers at a one-day conference on Caribbean Asians to be held today at Midtown offices of the City University of New York. ''They physically look Asian, but they're so displaced from the motherland, by as much as 200 years, that they have no relationship. So they find themselves turning back to their food roots.''</p>
        <p>With a unique fusion of cultures and cuisines, Caribbean Asians are making their own contribution to city life, most obviously in the thriving market under the A train on Liberty Avenue, in Richmond Hill, Queens, which now draws Indo-Caribbean shoppers from the whole region, as well as New Yorkers of all backgrounds.</p>
        <p>Estimates of the number of Indo-Caribbean immigrants in New York vary from 50,000 to 300,000. Most are from Guyana and Trinidad, but they also come from Suriname, and from Caribbean islands like Jamaica and Guadeloupe. They may be Hindus, Muslims or Christians, noted Mahin Gosine, a sociologist who has written many books on the Indian diaspora in the West Indies, but collectively they have often been called the Jews of the Caribbean.</p>
        <p>After five years of indentured labor in the islands, workers were offered a ticket home or a plot of land. Most took the land. While Caribbean blacks moved to towns, where they soon dominated the civil service, teaching and the army, said Professor Gosine, who teaches in the State University of New York system, Indians became the islands' rural workers and landowners.</p>
        <p>Often stereotyped as country bumpkins, they were looked down upon by more urban West Indian blacks. But their children became engineers, lawyers and business entrepreneurs in large numbers, typically after higher education in Britain or the United States.</p>
        <p>The Chinese, less numerous except in Cuba, opened mercantile ventures and were more likely to marry outside their ethnic group. But more than 20,000 West Indians in the Caribbean still count themselves as being of Chinese ancestry, and another 20,000 West Indian Chinese are scattered around the globe, said Walton Look Lai, a historian coming from Trinidad to speak at the conference, which is part of the city's Immigrant History Week. Caribbean cuisine reflects their contribution, too, starting with the introduction of rice early in the 19th century.</p>
        <p>These groups coexisted well for decades, but racial tensions escalated in the 1960s and early '70s, with a steep drop in the price of sugar and the rise of the American black power movement. In a competition for scarcer local resources, politics in Trinidad and Guyana began polarizing voters along racial lines, or alarming property owners with socialism, Professor Gosine said.</p>
        <p>The grandchildren of the indentured laborers began to leave, not for their ancestral lands, but first to the old colonial powers -- Britain, the Netherlands and France -- and then to the United States, where an overhaul of immigration laws in 1965 ended quotas based on national origin. Now, Caribbean Asians find their entrepreneurial drive and crossover cuisine embraced by a widening ethnic spectrum in New York. But many say they also feel distant from Asians who immigrated directly from their ancestral homelands.</p>
        <p>''There is quite a divide,'' Professor Gosine said. ''We speak English, we drink and we party and we have a good time. They see us as Western, people associated with Carnival and the beach and rum and Coke.'' On the other hand, he added, ''we see them as kind of squares.''</p>
        <p>For a younger generation navigating the ethnic and racial stew of Queens in search of their own identity, food still offers comfort and a way to explore and claim a cultural heritage of their own, especially after their favorite foods have been rejected by more recent arrivals from India as ''inauthentic.''</p>
        <p>''They are desperate to learn the food ways of what has become their motherland, which may be Trinidad or Jamaica or Guyana,'' said Ms. Ganeshram, the author of the cookbook ''Sweet Hands: Island Cooking from Trinidad and Tobago.''</p>
        <p>''It becomes a point of pride with them.''</p>
        <p>In her cooking classes, they learn how Indians driven by famine signed on as indentured laborers and were forced on the sea voyages to abandon religious food taboos in one fell swoop. One ship captain in 1877 wrote of dosing the sickly with ''plenty of port wine, extract of beef, chicken broth and condensed milk.''</p>
        <p>On plantations where rations were typically meat and rum, the migrants struggled to adapt local vegetables like taro, yucca and manioc to the masalas and curries of old. Instead of beef burgers, they created doubles, a fried chickpea paste on flatbread that is now accepted by all Trinidadians as a local tradition.</p>
        <p>These days, Ms. Ganeshram comes to Liberty Avenue from Stony Brook, on Long Island, to buy spices and Scotch bonnet peppers in bulk, or to treat herself to a coconut tart at her favorite Guyanese bakery.</p>
        <p>Knishes have virtually disappeared from the streets of New York. But under the A train, she finds, the new knish is an aloo pie.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
