<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chaotic Duo Indignantly Fills Post-Imus Void</title>
    <meta content="20lives" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/nyregion/20lives.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841652"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wfan (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rutgers, the State University of New Jersey</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Francesca, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Russo, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finn, Robin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">WFAN-AM</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Imus, Don</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E2D61F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="928" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chaotic Duo Indignantly Fills Post-Imus Void</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Chaotic Duo Indignantly Fills Post-Imus Void</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN FINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finn, Robin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of and interview with Chris Russo and Mike Francesca, radio personalities who are temporarily filling slot on WFAN in New York City that was left void by firing of Don Imus for his remarks about Rutgers University's women's basketball team; they disagree with Imus's penalty and feel initial two-week suspension was sufficient; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>UNLIKE the sunset-hued office suite at Kaufman Astoria Studios that fit the disgraced talk show host Don Imus like a custom-made Sante Fe serape, the eyesore office assigned to Mike and the Mad Dog, the oddball afternoon sports duo temporarily and unhappily filling in weekday mornings for their fired mentor, is a hodgepodge of bobble-headed sports dolls, discarded books, stray Snapple bottles and a Maltese Falcon statuette with a broken beak.</p>
        <p>In a word, chaos. Even family photos -- incomprehensibly, Mike and the Mad Dog, besides being sports-centric to the brink of obsession, are happily married guys with seven offspring between them -- are askew.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mike and the Mad Dog, the oddball afternoon sports duo, are filling in for the fired Don Imus as WFAN tries to stabilize the franchise.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>UNLIKE the sunset-hued office suite at Kaufman Astoria Studios that fit the disgraced talk show host Don Imus like a custom-made Sante Fe serape, the eyesore office assigned to Mike and the Mad Dog, the oddball afternoon sports duo temporarily and unhappily filling in weekday mornings for their fired mentor, is a hodgepodge of bobble-headed sports dolls, discarded books, stray Snapple bottles and a Maltese Falcon statuette with a broken beak.</p>
        <p>In a word, chaos. Even family photos -- incomprehensibly, Mike and the Mad Dog, besides being sports-centric to the brink of obsession, are happily married guys with seven offspring between them -- are askew.</p>
        <p>But they've got more important things to worry about in an office they basically use as a garbage can: WFAN, their beloved brand and performance stage, is in a state of breakage, and so, to a lesser degree, are they.</p>
        <p>Their colleague and exemplar, Mr. Imus, was fired by CBS Radio April 12 for his inexcusably racist and sexist on-air description of the Rutgers University's women's basketball team as ''nappy-headed hos'' on April 4. With Mr. Imus's high-profile morning slot on WFAN abruptly empty, they were asked to replace him and bloviate about sports on a double shift basis in the station's emergency attempt at damage control.</p>
        <p>Eight hours of yakking a day instead of the normal five. Not impossible, but grueling, and we're not just talking about the listeners. Mike Francesa, 52, and Chris Russo, 47, a k a the Mad Dog, playing verbal one-on-one inside a glass box with just a pair of hefty microphones fencing off each one's personal face space. ''Radio is so personal,'' Mr. Francesa said. ''You can't be sensitive and do what we do. He likes to yell a lot. I'm the more calculating one. But in this business, you've got to have a hard bark.''</p>
        <p>Just not as hard as Mr. Imus's.</p>
        <p>''Everyone here, including Imus, thought that what he said was reprehensible,'' Mr. Francesa, sipping from the ever present diet soda enlisted to get him to 210 pounds, said between shifts. ''Usually Imus targets those who can fight back, people in a position of authority.'' People like Mr. Francesa and Mr. Russo, whom Mr. Imus rudely dubbed 'Fatso and Froot Loops.' And got away with it because? ''Because he's Imus,'' Mr. Francesa said. ''But the young ladies on that team were seen as vulnerable, were vulnerable. Victims. And these young ladies were the only ones with a right to forgive him, and they did forgive him; everyone else had an agenda.'' He includes management in that latter grouping: ''This was a decision made by the corporate suits; they caved.''</p>
        <p>SO the fellow Long Islanders Mr. Francesa, who grew up poor and fatherless in Long Beach, and Mr. Russo, who grew up comfortable in Syosset, were asked to help stabilize their franchise. As good team players, they agreed to sub for Mr. Imus for two weeks to mollify WFAN, which is owned by CBS; its advertisers; and Mr. Imus's bereft audience. And theirs. But they remain indignant at having to do so.</p>
        <p>They disagree with Mr. Imus's penalty -- they thought his initial two-week suspension was sufficient -- and insist that his remorse is genuine.</p>
        <p>''Although Imus can be mean, he is not a racist,'' Mr. Russo said, slipping into a chair vacated by Mr. Francesa. When they aren't in the studio, they vacillate toward different rooms. Different states, even. Mr. Francesa lives in Manhassset with his wife, Roe, and their three children; Mr. Russo, his wife, Jeanne, whom he met on an airplane with the novel ''Jurassic Park'' as icebreaker, and their four children reside in New Canaan, Conn. On this afternoon, Mr. Francesa scolds Mr. Russo on-air for blabbering about A-Rod instead of going to his 5-year-old's birthday bash.</p>
        <p>Mr. Russo blithely confesses to dropping and breaking the Maltese Falcon, a gift from a fan, in a not-so-rare moment of, ah, overexcitement. Mr. Russo, a sports-crazed space cadet with a Gilligan-esque physique, may not froth at the mouth but still qualifies for his sobriquet earned decades ago at WMCA radio: He possesses the howl, and vocal stamina, of a hound on a scent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Francesa, a graduate of St. John's University, is the more bombastic member of a duo thrown together -- to their mutual horror -- in 1989 at the suggestion of Mr. Imus. Neither wanted to balance his chops against those of a co-host, but both wanted to host the afternoon drive show.</p>
        <p>''It was an arranged marriage and almost a quickie divorce,'' said Mr. Francesa. Who taught them about timing and chemistry? Mr. Imus. Sigh.</p>
        <p>Reached by phone on his drive to New Canaan, where he missed his son's party and was already grousing about getting back to Astoria by dawn for the wake-up show, Mr. Russo pondered, hoarsely but loudly, the notion of a Mike and the Mad Dog breakup in the service of providing -- long-term -- a morning and afternoon show for WFAN's coveted commuter-guy demographic.</p>
        <p>He admitted that 15 years ago such a proposition would have been celebrated. Not now.</p>
        <p>''I think that, in the long-term, the station sees us as a tandem and would not want to break the brand up,'' he said. ''And to tell you the truth, after almost 20 years together, Mike and I are like a married couple: It would be too hard to leave him. I never thought I would hear myself say this, but it would feel very strange to be on the air without him.''</p>
        <p>Even stranger than being on the air minus Imus.</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
