<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Virginia Tech: The Killer, the Guns, the Anguish</title>
    <meta content="l20virginia" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841618"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E0D71F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="970" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Virginia Tech: The Killer, the Guns, the Anguish</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''Officials Knew Troubled State of Killer in '05'' (front page, April 19) reports that Cho Seung-Hui was allowed to continue as a student at Virginia Tech despite the fact that he had been determined to be mentally ill by a doctor and according to a judge's order presented an imminent danger to himself or others.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''Officials Knew Troubled State of Killer in '05'' (front page, April 19) reports that Cho Seung-Hui was allowed to continue as a student at Virginia Tech despite the fact that he had been determined to be mentally ill by a doctor and according to a judge's order presented an imminent danger to himself or others.</p>
        <p>So why was Mr. Cho allowed to buy a gun, given his obvious mental health problems?</p>
        <p>If this country is not yet ready to outlaw guns outright, then at the very least stringent safeguards and background checks urgently need to be put in place that deny easy access to guns to people with severe mental imbalances.</p>
        <p>Mathias Frisch  College Park, Md., April 19, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''The Silence of Politicians'' (editorial, April 19):</p>
        <p>While I commend your editorial urging politicians to confront what you call ''the runaway gun problem,'' I see the only workable solution to putting a stop to more and more Columbine and Virginia Tech-type disasters is not for politicians to admit there is a problem but to repeal and rewrite the Second Amendment to the Constitution.</p>
        <p>While it's true that even the whisper of gun control causes politicians to run for cover, I believe that a groundswell can be built by those of us -- and we are in the majority -- who are appalled by what the rest of the civilized world sees as our Wild West heritage.</p>
        <p>Yes, it's time, at long last, to stop arguing over what the founding fathers meant by ''the right of the people to keep and bear arms shall not be infringed.''</p>
        <p>Instead, it's time to write a sane national gun law that is right and proper for our nation in the 21st century.</p>
        <p>Allen M. Cobrin  Massapequa, N.Y., April 19, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>We are a nation in denial. Your editorial states that the Virginia Tech deaths ''represent a mere tenth of 1 percent of the 30,000 gunshot deaths each year.''</p>
        <p>The rate of gun deaths in 5- to 14-year-olds is 17 times higher in the United States than in 25 other developed countries combined.</p>
        <p>In many school districts, teenagers tell me that they can get a gun as easily as a six-pack.</p>
        <p>How many more young people will have to die before we demand that our gun laws be changed? Have we completely lost our moral compass?</p>
        <p>Naomi Drew  Lambertville, N.J., April 19, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is the author of ''Peaceful Parents, Peaceful Kids.''</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The people of Scotland will empathize with those who are grieving in Virginia.</p>
        <p>On March 13, 1996, at a school in Dunblane, Scotland, 16 5- and 6-year-olds and their teacher were shot dead in three minutes by a man who legally owned a small arsenal of guns.</p>
        <p>But out of this horrific carnage there emerged an opportunity for radical positive change. I had read that in the wake of this tragedy a campaign was being coordinated to ban handguns, so I contacted the organizers to see if I could help.</p>
        <p>A couple of days later, I met two fathers who had lost their children in the massacre, and as a result ended up providing money for the campaign, which proved to be enormously successful.</p>
        <p>It resulted in new legislation that banned the private ownership of handguns in Britain.</p>
        <p>Surely the horror at Virginia Tech provides the opportunity for a similarly radical change in direction in the United States.</p>
        <p>(Sir) Peter Lampl  London, April 18, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is chairman of the Sutton Trust.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Package Forced NBC to Make Tough Decision'' (news article, April 19):Why would any news organization broadcast the Virginia Tech killer's made-for-infamy videos? Is there not a way to report the news without making those seeking infamy infamous?</p>
        <p>Thomas Eickhoff  Minneapolis, April 19, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Korean-Americans Brace for Problems in Wake of Killings'' (news article, April 19): If the killer had been white, we would not have seen the same kind of attention to his whiteness, nor would there be apologies from the white community.</p>
        <p>In addition, the article mentioned how many Koreans have immigrated to America. The United States is a country entirely composed of immigrants in search of the American Dream; why is the Korean community being singled out because of the actions of one person?</p>
        <p>Rebekah Park  Los Angeles, April 19, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The massacre at Blacksburg has caused pain, disbelief and sadness across the country. What must it be like to live in a community where massacres happen every day, day after day, killing men, women and children who, just like the students and the faculty at Virginia Tech, are just trying to live decent, kind lives?</p>
        <p>Blacksburg and Baghdad are, for now, sister cities in mourning.</p>
        <p>Wick R. Chambers  Hamden, Conn., April 19, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''The Portrait of a Gunman, and of a Society'' (letters, April 19):</p>
        <p>There were several good suggestions for ways to decrease the isolation, anger and humiliation felt by many in our society. I would like to add one.</p>
        <p>There are classes required for graduating from high school; why not make psychology one of them? The introductory classes teach so much about human behavior that could help people to understand themselves and others, and to behave better toward one another.</p>
        <p>By 16, most kids will have more information about how to operate a car than about their own psyche.</p>
        <p>Lessons about how we make each other feel good or bad and how important these feelings are should begin in kindergarten; they are crucial to someday truly having a kinder and gentler nation.</p>
        <p>Zay Hartigan  Patagonia, Ariz., April 19, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
