<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Google Profit Soars 69% For Quarter</title>
    <meta content="20google" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/business/20google.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841662"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Google Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE0D61F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="911" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Google Profit Soars 69% For Quarter</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Profits Up 69% at Google, Exceeding Expectations</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIGUEL HELFT</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, April 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For much of this year, the buzz around Google has been all about the flurry of new initiatives at the No. 1 Internet search company, from its YouTube video sharing site, to its new software for office workers, to its forays into television, radio and newspaper advertising.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, Google executives sought to change the focus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The company’s core search and advertising business continued to outpace that of Microsoft and Yahoo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For much of this year, the buzz around Google has been all about the flurry of new initiatives at the No. 1 Internet search company, from its YouTube video sharing site, to its new software for office workers, to its forays into television, radio and newspaper advertising.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, Google executives sought to change the focus.</p>
        <p>The company said that nearly three of every four Googlers, as the company's workers call themselves, remained focused on the business that turned Google into a money-minting Internet powerhouse: search and online advertising.</p>
        <p>And it is that business, executives said, that delivered a surge in Google's profits during the first three months of the year, as the company continued to outpace rivals like Microsoft and Yahoo.</p>
        <p>''We are ecstatic about our financial results this past quarter,'' Eric E. Schmidt, Google's chief executive, said during a conference call.</p>
        <p>Google said first-quarter profit rose 69 percent, to $1 billion, or $3.18 a share, from $592.3 million, or $1.95 a share, in the period a year ago. The results topped analysts' expectations, sending Google's shares up more than 3 percent in after-hours trading.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schmidt predicted that search and advertising would continue to be the main source of profits for the foreseeable future.</p>
        <p>''The core business is search and ads,'' Mr. Schmidt said. ''We are still at the beginning of that business. It is a huge business, and we have a lot of room to grow.''</p>
        <p>For example, Mr. Schmidt said that just as in previous quarters, the company devoted significant resources to continuing to perfect the art of linking search results with ads that are tailored to users' interests. Since, Google is paid when users click on an ad, those efforts translate into higher profitability.</p>
        <p>''We are showing fewer ads and those ads are worth more because they are better targeted,'' Mr. Schmidt said.</p>
        <p>Overall quarterly revenue was $3.66 billion, up from $2.25 billion a year ago. Excluding commissions paid to marketing partners, revenue was $2.53 billion, compared with $1.53 billion a year earlier.</p>
        <p>Excluding certain expenses, like stock-based compensation, profits were $3.68 a share, though analysts noted that without a benefit resulting from a change in tax rates, the figure would have been $3.50. On that basis, analysts polled by Thomson Financial had expected Google to earn $3.30 a share and report revenue of $2.5 billion, without the marketing commissions.</p>
        <p>''Google has been able to deliver amazing profitability given its enormous investments in human resources and capital equipment,'' said Jordan Rohan, an analyst with RBC Capital Markets.</p>
        <p>Google said its overseas business was particularly strong. Revenue from outside the United States was $1.7 billion, or 47 percent of the total.</p>
        <p>Google's strong growth stands in sharp contrast to that of Yahoo, which announced this week that sales increased 7 percent from the year-ago quarter, while profits dropped 11 percent.</p>
        <p>A growing number of Internet users are going to Google for their search needs. Nielsen/NetRatings reported Thursday that the number of searches conducted on Google in February reached 3.6 billion, up 40 percent from a year earlier. By comparison, searches on Yahoo grew 12 percent, to 1.3 billion, and on Microsoft, 9 percent, to 618 million.</p>
        <p>Google continued to add workers at a brisk pace, ending the quarter with 12,238 employees worldwide, nearly 1,600 more than at the end of the previous quarter.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, Google's shares dipped as investors worried that its expenses for everything from engineers and sales staff to computers and data centers would grow. But expenses, excluding stock-based compensation, actually declined to 31 percent of revenue, from 33 percent, said Gene Munster, an analyst with Piper Jaffray &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>''That's particularly impressive given that they hired 1,600 employees,'' Mr. Munster said.</p>
        <p>Google's shares slipped $4.36 in regular trading, to close at $471.65, up a bit more than 2 percent for the year. After the earnings announcement, the stock rose to more than $486 in extended trading.</p>
        <p>The earnings report comes after a period of ambitious expansions into new businesses by Google. Just last week, the company said it would acquire the online ad services company DoubleClick for $3.1 billion. Google also recently announced deals with Clear Channel to sell radio ads and with EchoStar Communications to sell television commercial time.</p>
        <p>If such initiatives are not contributing to Google's bottom line yet, they are earning it a long list of increasingly assertive rivals.</p>
        <p>During the quarter, Viacom filed a $1 billion suit against Google over copyrighted material that users post on YouTube. And this week, Microsoft and AT&amp;T asked antitrust officials to scrutinize Google's proposed acquisition of DoubleClick, which they say would reduce competition in the online advertising market.</p>
        <p>On Friday, the Electronic Privacy Information Center, an advocacy organization, is planning to file a related complaint with the Federal Trade Commission, asking it to open an investigation into the privacy implications of the DoubleClick acquisition.</p>
        <p>''No one knows today what a combined Google and DoubleClick will be able to do in the future,'' said Marc Rotenberg, executive director of the center. ''But we think this is the right time for the commission to look at that issue and require genuine privacy safeguards if the acquisition is to go forward.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schmidt said in an interview that as part of the integration with DoubleClick, Google already planned to strengthen privacy protections.</p>
        <p>''Our incentive is to get this right because our whole business is dependent on the trust of users,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
