<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wanted: A Third Party To Complete Love Triangle</title>
    <meta content="20vale" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/movies/20vale.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841545"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Veber, Francis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elmaleh, Gad</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Taglioni, Alice</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Auteuil, Daniel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thomas, Kristin Scott</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Valet, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Veber, Francis</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Valet, The (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E7DA1F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="779" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wanted: A Third Party To Complete Love Triangle</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Wanted: A Third Party to Complete Love Triangle</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews film The Valet, written and directed by Francis Veber; Gad Elmaleh, Alice Taglioni, Daniel Auteuil and Kristin Scott Thomas star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you love to hate the superrich, ''The Valet,'' a delectable comedy in which the great French actor Daniel Auteuil portrays a piggy billionaire industrialist facing his comeuppance, is a sinfully delicious bonbon. His character, the beady-eyed Pierre Levasseur, is a human rodent with an explosive temper and an ego the size of Versailles; his nostrils twitch like rat whiskers when he flashes a sickly smile. A liar, a bully and a cheapskate, he has broken every promise he made to the picketing workers who threaten to close down his factories.</p>
        <p>But a possible strike is a minor nuisance compared with the domestic crisis that looms after a tabloid splashes a picture of Pierre on the street with Elena (Alice Taglioni), the spectacular supermodel who has been his mistress for two years and counting. The lovers are caught on camera by a stalking paparazzo when, in a rare lapse of discretion, Pierre chases her onto the street after a fight. She has just delivered the usual ultimatum: Divorce your wife or it's over.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you love to hate the superrich, “The Valet” is a sinfully delicious bonbon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If you love to hate the superrich, ''The Valet,'' a delectable comedy in which the great French actor Daniel Auteuil portrays a piggy billionaire industrialist facing his comeuppance, is a sinfully delicious bonbon. His character, the beady-eyed Pierre Levasseur, is a human rodent with an explosive temper and an ego the size of Versailles; his nostrils twitch like rat whiskers when he flashes a sickly smile. A liar, a bully and a cheapskate, he has broken every promise he made to the picketing workers who threaten to close down his factories.</p>
        <p>But a possible strike is a minor nuisance compared with the domestic crisis that looms after a tabloid splashes a picture of Pierre on the street with Elena (Alice Taglioni), the spectacular supermodel who has been his mistress for two years and counting. The lovers are caught on camera by a stalking paparazzo when, in a rare lapse of discretion, Pierre chases her onto the street after a fight. She has just delivered the usual ultimatum: Divorce your wife or it's over.</p>
        <p>That wife, Christine (Kristin Scott Thomas), is no worn-out doormat. Beautiful, haughty and imperturbably cool, she owns 60 percent of Pierre's business. A divorce would cost him dearly. Frantic to keep both wife and mistress in their places, Pierre appeals to his sleazy lawyer, Mr. Foix (Richard Berry), to do something.</p>
        <p>The only solution, Mr. Foix decides, is that the world must be convinced that the blurry third figure in the photograph is Elena's actual lover. The passer-by must be tracked down and paid to collaborate in a public charade of living happily with Elena. For her part in the game, Elena is to receive a ''deposit'' of 20 million euros, which she will return once Pierre gets a divorce. The diabolical Mr. Foix of course has contrived a loophole to make sure Elena never gets a cent.</p>
        <p>The mysterious third party, François Pignon (Gad Elmaleh, who resembles a younger, homelier Nicolas Cage), turns out to be a humble parking valet at a swank Paris hotel who shares a dumpy apartment with his co-worker Richard (Dany Boon). François is despondent because his close childhood friend Émilie (Virginie Ledoyen) has just rejected his marriage proposal. Pressured by Mr. Foix, he agrees to play along in return for 34,450 euros, the exact sum Émilie has borrowed to open a book shop, which François intends to give her once the game is over.</p>
        <p>Francis Veber, who wrote and directed ''The Valet,'' is a master of the modern French farce. And this film has the same tight structure and carefully plotted surprises and reversals as his earlier comedies ''The Dinner Game'' and ''The Closet.'' These movies are wonderfully frothy contrivances, built with traditional machinery from models that have been around for centuries.</p>
        <p>As the story plays out, age-old tricks are played with up-to-date toys. A purloined letter is now a tiny concealed tape recorder. Instead of people hiding behind doors and in closets, we get snooping paparazzi staking out spots from which to photograph the blissful couple after Elena is installed in François's apartment.</p>
        <p>Subplots and subsidiary characters multiply. Pierre and Christine hire rival detectives to report back to them, and naturally they cross paths. One of the wittiest subplots involves the exiled roommate, Richard, who can't believe that someone like Elena would look twice at François.</p>
        <p>Because its structure and the targets of its satire -- vanity, greed and lust -- hark back to Molière, ''The Valet'' offers a reassuring vision of a fixed social order, bourgeois to the core, in which virtue is rewarded and hubris exposed. For all its cynicism about sex, money and power, it doesn't rock any boats.</p>
        <p>The rich are greedy, corrupt, insecure and scheming, and the valets of this world, personified by the sweet-natured François, have their feet on the ground and their values intact. In between are high-flying birds like Elena, a free spirit, fending for herself. She may have few illusions, but she still has enough integrity to recognize and respect the decency of her partner in deception.</p>
        <p>''The Valet'' is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has mild sexual situations and some strong language.</p>
        <p>The Valet  Opens today in New York and Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Written (in French, with English subtitles) and directed by Francis Veber; director of photography, Robert Fraisse; edited by Georges Klotz; music by Alexandre Desplat; production designer, Dominique Andre; produced by Patrice Ledoux; released by Sony Pictures Classics. Running time: 85 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Gad Elmaleh (François Pignon), Alice Taglioni (Elena), Daniel Auteuil (Pierre Levasseur), Kristin Scott Thomas (Christine), Richard Berry (Mr. Foix), Virginie Ledoyen (Émilie) and Dany Boon (Richard).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
