<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Tilt in Wall Street's Pursuit of Private Equity</title>
    <meta content="20insider" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/business/20insider.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841554"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="STREET SCENE: INSIDER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Investment Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Investment Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E2DA1F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Tilt in Wall Street's Pursuit of Private Equity</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Tilt in Wall Street’s Pursuit of Private Equity</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNY ANDERSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EARLY one recent morning, I was in my fuzzy slippers talking by phone about private equity with a hyper-kinetic senior Wall Street executive who had time to talk only very early in the morning. He said something that woke me up: ''Of course we are conflicted.''</p>
        <p>This bank, I hasten to add, was not Goldman Sachs, which is why the statement was so surprising. (Goldman's intensive and wide-ranging private equity efforts include British airports and major energy companies).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As investment banks increasingly compete with their clients over private equity deals, conflicts arise.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EARLY one recent morning, I was in my fuzzy slippers talking by phone about private equity with a hyper-kinetic senior Wall Street executive who had time to talk only very early in the morning. He said something that woke me up: ''Of course we are conflicted.''</p>
        <p>This bank, I hasten to add, was not Goldman Sachs, which is why the statement was so surprising. (Goldman's intensive and wide-ranging private equity efforts include British airports and major energy companies).</p>
        <p>For years, most of the other Wall Street banks stuck closely to a script that went something like this: ''We do invest our own capital in deals, but we only co-invest and only when our clients want us to, and never at the risk of alienating the client.''</p>
        <p>A major change has now quietly swept Wall Street. A some point, about the time when the Blackstone Group's $15.6 billion fund became a $20.6 billion fund and Goldman neared a $20 billion fund, the script was rewritten. What was once an agonizing business decision -- should we compete against our clients? -- has become an accepted business practice.</p>
        <p>The reason is simple. Wall Street banks cannot resist the lure of the private equity cash machine, so that the challenge, as the executive went on to say, is not to avoid conflicts but to manage them. Roughly translated that means: We refuse to leave money on the table or in someone's pocket, even if that someone is a client.</p>
        <p>The balancing act has been a delicate one. Generally the banks have partnered with important, fee-generating clients, sometimes by not seeking too much control, but being there to rake in the fees. Every iteration of partnership has been tried: Merrill Lynch used its balance sheet to partner with Bain Capital and Kohlberg Kravis Roberts to buy HCA, and JPMorgan and Bank of America teamed up with J. C. Flowers to bid for Sallie Mae.</p>
        <p>Of course, banks have always been investors, but the huge scale of deals now means that the balancing act will get a lot messier.</p>
        <p>Goldman's fund will be one of the biggest, which means that it needs to get in on the biggest deals around. It can try to do this by holding hands with its clients, but with more money on the table, that effort becomes harder.</p>
        <p>For one, the bank has an obligation to the investors in its fund to get the best deal, and that can often be different from the obligation they have to shareholders, which is to make sure that Goldman Sachs maintains its franchise of offering chief executives the best possible advice -- that is, advice free of motives from a bank on the prowl for deals.</p>
        <p>(Goldman Sachs declined to comment for this column.)</p>
        <p>There was a time when banks were advisers. Then they advised and financed. Now they advise, finance, invest. Logic would suggest that if the banks truly had their clients' interests at heart, the banks would stick to advising and financing, hardly low-fee businesses.</p>
        <p>Wall Street, however, is sending a clear message that it will try to coin every opportunity available, some with clients, some alone. One banker recalled a former chairman of Morgan Stanley, as saying, ''The day we get nervous is the day we don't have conflicts'' -- because it would mean Morgan Stanley was not in enough discussions.</p>
        <p>A few banks are sticking to their knitting, including Lehman Brothers and Credit Suisse. Credit Suisse stopped trying to go it alone on important deals after it infuriated clients by buying Warner Chilcott, a drug maker its clients wanted. In 2006, the bank's private equity group raised a $2.1 billion fund, significantly smaller than the $5.6 billion it raised in 2001. Lehman just closed a $1.6 billion ''co-invest'' fund whose name suggests that if it deviates from co-investments, it will have some serious explaining to do. (Lehman also has a merchant banking fund).</p>
        <p>But the so-called MGM triumvirate -- Morgan, Goldman and Merrill -- are going full steam ahead into private equity.</p>
        <p>Some executives say this new business model better aligns bank interests with the clients. Previously banks pitched deals to chief executives and they made a fee and walked away. There was no pay for performance.</p>
        <p>Now, bankers have a more compelling pitch to the chief executives, these people say: We will put our own skin in the game and rise or fall with you.</p>
        <p>The banks are also betting that private equity firms would rather partner with them than their archrivals because the banks have to be slightly more cautious about alienating their clients. Archrivals do not.</p>
        <p>Which brings us back to conflicts and the new Wall Street mantra that it is in ''the business of managing conflicts.'' A more honest approach would be that Wall Street is increasingly competing with its clients with all its might and capital -- essentially trying to sound nice while playing rough. And so far, it has worked out swimmingly.</p>
        <p>The test of these partnerships will be, of course, when the wheels fall off a deal and the conversation shifts from how to divvy up the profits to who is in control of the Titanic.</p>
        <p>Then the mantra will not be about managing conflicts, but about pointing fingers.</p>
        <p>STREET SCENE: INSIDER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
