<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Wishing Corzine Well, Sympathy Is Mixed With Resentment</title>
    <meta content="20voices" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/nyregion/20voices.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841623"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Speed Limits and Speeding</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Seat Belts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hu, Winnie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Speed Limits and Speeding</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seat Belts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seat Belts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EFD71F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1399" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Wishing Corzine Well, Sympathy Is Mixed With Resentment</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Wishing Corzine Well, Sympathy Is Mixed With Resentment</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WINNIE HU; Jill P. Capuzzo, in Point Pleasant, N.J., David K. Randall, in Maplewood, and Nate Schweber, in Camden, contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hu, Winnie</byline>
      <dateline>HOBOKEN, N.J., April 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey residents have mixed feelings about Gov Jon S Corzine's near-fatal car accident: both sympathy for his injuries and anger and resentment that he was violating speed limit and state's seat-belt law; Corzine remains in critical condition; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The regulars at Frankie &amp; Johnnie's Steakhouse have been asking every night about Gov. Jon S. Corzine, who before last week's traffic accident would hunker down with a slab of sirloin at the gleaming cherry-wood bar, parked elbow to elbow with his friends and neighbors.</p>
        <p>But as Mr. Corzine's uncertain recovery stretches into weeks and possibly months, even some of his supporters in Hoboken, the Hudson River city he calls home, say they do not understand why he was violating both the speed limit and the state law requiring that he wear a seat belt.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many New Jersey residents say they do not understand why Gov. Jon S. Corzine was violating both the speed limit and the state law requiring that he wear a seat belt.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The regulars at Frankie &amp; Johnnie's Steakhouse have been asking every night about Gov. Jon S. Corzine, who before last week's traffic accident would hunker down with a slab of sirloin at the gleaming cherry-wood bar, parked elbow to elbow with his friends and neighbors.</p>
        <p>But as Mr. Corzine's uncertain recovery stretches into weeks and possibly months, even some of his supporters in Hoboken, the Hudson River city he calls home, say they do not understand why he was violating both the speed limit and the state law requiring that he wear a seat belt.</p>
        <p>Underpinning the outpouring of sympathy and well wishes, there was palpable anger and resentment among residents here and across the state over what they see as a serious lapse in judgment. Some said the accident has left New Jersey without its strongest champion in such pressing issues as crushing debt, flooding, school reform and legal challenges over civil unions.</p>
        <p>''It seems irresponsible to me,'' said Morgan McNeish, an office manager who said she had turned the accident into a cautionary lesson about car safety for her 7-year-old son. She said she worried that progress on social and legal issues might stall in the political void left by Mr. Corzine's hospitalization.</p>
        <p>''It's worrisome,'' Ms. McNeish added, ''that the person you elected isn't able to perform the duties of office, and for something as stupid as not wearing a seat belt.''</p>
        <p>In a busy parking lot down the street from where Ms. McNeish was taking a smoke break, Robert Diaz, 36, who lives in Passaic, paused between hopping in and out of cars to say that he had thought Mr. Corzine was doing a good job in Trenton, but could not help but question the governor's decision-making and common sense.</p>
        <p>''It makes it look like, 'We are the law, so we're above the law because we're in a rush,' '' he said of the accident, in which a state trooper driving Mr. Corzine was going 91 miles an hour before the crash on the Garden State Parkway. ''It wouldn't have been a bad thing for him to wear a seat belt, either.''</p>
        <p>Having once broken his collarbone, Mr. Diaz said he knew firsthand how painful and prolonged the recovery would be, and said he felt bad for the governor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine, 60, remained in critical condition at a Camden hospital for a seventh day on Thursday, still semiconscious and dependent on a breathing tube after breaking more than a dozen bones in the crash on April 12.</p>
        <p>The governor was en route to Princeton from Atlantic City for a meeting with the Rutgers women's basketball team and the embattled radio host Don Imus. The emergency lights on his Chevrolet Suburban were flashing as he sped through rush hour on the parkway in Galloway Township, in Atlantic County.</p>
        <p>While state police officials originally said that speed was not a factor in the accident, an independent panel is reviewing the situation to determine whether the trooper who was driving, Robert J. Rasinski, should face disciplinary action or a traffic citation.</p>
        <p>A Quinnipiac poll released on Wednesday, based on interviews last week both before and after the accident, showed virtually no change in the governor's standing since a previous survey in February, with 51 percent of voters approving of how Mr. Corzine is handling his job, and 36 percent disapproving.</p>
        <p>But in dozens of interviews across the state over the past two days, many residents expressed ambivalence about the turn of events.</p>
        <p>There was worry over Mr. Corzine's health, as well as tinges of frustration that for the fifth time in six years, New Jersey is in the hands of an unelected acting governor.</p>
        <p>The concern over the state's future leadership was mixed with annoyance at a perceived sense of entitlement by its leader.</p>
        <p>These sentiments were echoed by voters young and old and largely cut across party lines to include Democrats as well as Republicans and independents.</p>
        <p>Joseph Salmons, who lives on the Jersey Shore, pointed out that his Chevrolet Silverado, a vehicle with features similar to those of the governor's sport utility vehicle, cannot go past 90 m.p.h. without alterations to its computer.</p>
        <p>Jeanne Brzozowski, a letter carrier in Point Pleasant, marveled that the governor had survived without wearing a seat belt at such a high speed, questioning whether a civilian traveling without police escorts would have been as lucky to get help as quickly.</p>
        <p>And many questioned whether Mr. Corzine, given the intensity and length of expected rehabilitation for his extensive injuries, would be able to govern effectively any time soon.</p>
        <p>''You don't really know how he will be until he wakes up,'' said Nancy Pugliese, 58, of Spring Lake, as she left her health club in Manasquan. ''I think he should focus on his health.''</p>
        <p>Late Thursday afternoon, a spokesman for Mr. Corzine, Anthony Coley, released a statement saying that the catheters inserted into the governor's back the day before to deliver a local anesthetic directly to his broken rib cage appeared to be successful.</p>
        <p>''Although the governor continues to rely on the ventilator, his dependence on it is decreasing,'' the statement said. ''The governor does not show any sign of complications or infection at this time.''</p>
        <p>But the uncertainty has frustrated some residents who had felt that after the political turmoil of the past few years, their state was finally on track again -- only to be derailed once more.</p>
        <p>Jane Vega of Middletown, a Republican who did not vote for Mr. Corzine, tried to sum up the situation while waiting for the commuter train home from Pennsylvania Station in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''When is New Jersey going to get it right?'' she asked. ''There's been a lot of upheaval in the past couple of years, and I don't think anything is going to get done now.''</p>
        <p>Still, there were also those who said that things could have been worse, and that the state would quickly bounce back and forget its latest misfortune.</p>
        <p>Behind the counter of the Maplewood Pet Shop, Courtney Schenck pointed out that just as the meeting between Mr. Imus and the Rutgers athletes continued without Mr. Corzine, so, too, would the daily workings of state government.</p>
        <p>''It makes you think that someone in such a high position should set an example,'' Ms. Schenck said. ''I feel sad for him and his family, but maybe this will help him teach a larger lesson about safety.''</p>
        <p>In Point Pleasant, where Trooper Rasinski lives, Matt Perrotta, 48, said he did not blame his neighbor for the crash. ''I'm sure he was under orders to step on it,'' Mr. Perrotta said. ''I don't think it's that uncommon for troopers to rush if they're running late. After all, that's their road, the Garden State Parkway.''</p>
        <p>In Hoboken, Mr. Corzine's neighbors have said prayers for his recovery, even as they puzzled aloud over the circumstances of the crash. The night of the accident, the conversation level at Frankie &amp; Johnnie's dropped off as the owner, Dino Panopoulos, turned up the volume on the television perched over the bar.</p>
        <p>For a half-dozen years, Mr. Corzine has been coming to Frankie &amp; Johnnie's several times a month for his steaks -- rib-eye, sirloin or T-bone, and always medium rare -- served alongside club soda with a splash of cranberry. In recent months, a waitress said, the governor has been on a diet and reluctantly cut back to half a steak under the watchful eyes of his staff members.</p>
        <p>Mr. Panopoulos, who said he did not want to talk about the accident, described Mr. Corzine as a friendly, understated man who never used his position to demand a corner table but instead ate at the bar with everyone else when the restaurant was full. He said that Mr. Corzine liked to hug his friends, including some of the waiters, and shake hands with acquaintances before sitting down for his meal. And he always tipped 20 percent.</p>
        <p>''Nobody's concerned about his job,'' said Deborah Greene, 56, a waitress at the restaurant and bar, where the actress Eva Marie Saint was filmed in the 1954 classic ''On the Waterfront'' sipping a cocktail. ''Usually they'd be more concerned about what his responsibilities are, and what's good for them. They're not. They're more concerned about him.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
