<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TODAY IN BUSINESS</title>
    <meta content="20biztoday" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841581"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4D81F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="814" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TODAY IN BUSINESS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NACCHIO IS GUILTY -- Joseph P. Nacchio, the former chief executive of Qwest Communications International, was convicted on 19 of 42 counts of insider trading. Witnesses had testified that he exaggerated financial forecasts while concealing Qwest's growing troubles. [Page C1.]</p>
        <p>A DRUG'S BENEFITS ARE QUESTIONED  -- The Food and Drug Administration is expected to approve a birth control pill for women that eliminates monthly menstruation -- a prospect that leaves some women uneasy. [A1.]</p>
        <p>GOOGLE PROFIT ROSE 69% -- Google reported that its bread and butter -- search and online advertising -- was the source of a 69 percent increase in first-quarter profit. [C1.]</p>
        <p>SEARCH IN THE PALM OF YOUR HAND -- The three giants of search -- Google, Microsoft and Yahoo -- have all trained their sights on improving Internet search via cellphones, which they see as the next great battleground. Their new services answer urgent questions like: Where is the best local pizzeria? [C1.]</p>
        <p>CHINA KEEPS GROWING -- China's economy continues to accelerate at a blistering pace, growing 11.1 percent in the first quarter of this year from the first quarter of 2006, according to data from the National Bureau of Statistics. The surge in growth is almost certain to force Beijing to step up efforts to cool the economy. [C3.]</p>
        <p>A RUSH TO ORGANIC MILK -- Dairy farmers are hurrying to convert to organic milk production before new, more stringent federal regulations take effect, prompting predictions of a serious oversupply. [C1.]</p>
        <p>SIEMENS'S CHAIRMAN TO STEP DOWN -- The corruption scandals at Siemens claimed one of German's most prominent industrialists, as the company said its chairman, Heinrich von Pierer, would resign next week. [C3.]</p>
        <p>AMGEN ANEMIA DRUG CLEARS TRIAL -- Amgen said that its anemia drug Aranesp did not increase the death rate of lung cancer patients in a clinical trial, an announcement that could dispel at least some of the recent safety concerns over a widely used class of drugs. Amgen's stock rose 4 percent. [C7.]</p>
        <p>STRONG SALES FOR DRUG MAKERS -- Merck, Schering-Plough and Wyeth all rode strong drug sales to quarterly profits that topped Wall Street expectations, adding to the wave of good news for investors in major pharmaceutical companies. [C7.]</p>
        <p>MERRILL REPORTS GAINS -- Merrill Lynch posted a higher-than-expected increase in first-quarter profit, suggesting that efforts to bolster results from trading and private equity are paying off. [C2.]</p>
        <p>PROFIT IS NOT THE FULL PICTURE -- Continental Airlines and Southwest Airlines posted first-quarter profits on higher fares, but the results showed early signs that domestic air fares are under pressure. Both airlines managed to overcome an unusually difficult quarter, which is seasonally their weakest, but their shares fell on fears that the nascent airline recovery might falter. [C2.]</p>
        <p>NOKIA'S EARNINGS DROP 7% -- Nokia, the world's largest mobile phone maker, said that its first-quarter earnings dropped nearly 7 percent as expanding sales of low-end models in emerging markets pushed down its average selling price. [C8.]</p>
        <p>A.M.D. POSTS A LOSS -- Advanced Micro Devices announced that its loss during the first quarter was even bigger than expected, hurt by slower sales and a bruising price war with its larger rival, Intel. [C3.]</p>
        <p>KNOW THY CUSTOMER -- The creativity that was being celebrated at an advertising conference this week was not of the artsy, award-winning variety, but rather the kind that is rooted in insights derived from hard data about customer shopping patterns. Advertising: Stuart Elliott. [C7.]</p>
        <p>NEWSPAPERS PROFITS NARROW  -- The New York Times Company and the Gannett Company announced that their first-quarter profits declined while the Tribune Company reported a loss, as the companies continued to deal with an advertising recession. [C2.]</p>
        <p>A MIXED DAY IN THE MARKETS -- Wall Street averages closed mostly lower, as investors juggled upbeat economic data, divergent earnings reports and a pullback in Chinese stocks. [C10.]</p>
        <p>CELEBRITY CHEF IN A PICKLE -- Paula Deen, the Food Network's ebullient queen of butter-drenched Southern cooking, has found herself in the middle of a dispute between Smithfield Foods and a union that has long tried to organize one of the company's pork processing plants. [A17.]</p>
        <p>ONLINE</p>
        <p>Business Briefing  Articles on these developments are at nytimes.com/business</p>
        <p>The Delphi Corporation said that it expected a big investor to withdraw from a plan to pump up to $3.4 billion into the company to help it emerge from bankruptcy protection, but that other investors were still involved. (AP)</p>
        <p>Federal authorities said that the government had joined in a whistle-blower case filed against Hewlett-Packard, Sun Microsystems and Accenture over suspected improper payments connected to government contracts. (REUTERS)</p>
        <p>The American Express Company said that increased use of its credit cards by more customers helped drive first-quarter profit up 21 percent. (AP)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NACCHIO IS GUILTY -- Joseph P. Nacchio, the former chief executive of Qwest Communications International, was convicted on 19 of 42 counts of insider trading. Witnesses had testified that he exaggerated financial forecasts while concealing Qwest's growing troubles. [Page C1.]</p>
        <p>A DRUG'S BENEFITS ARE QUESTIONED  -- The Food and Drug Administration is expected to approve a birth control pill for women that eliminates monthly menstruation -- a prospect that leaves some women uneasy. [A1.]</p>
        <p>GOOGLE PROFIT ROSE 69% -- Google reported that its bread and butter -- search and online advertising -- was the source of a 69 percent increase in first-quarter profit. [C1.]</p>
        <p>SEARCH IN THE PALM OF YOUR HAND -- The three giants of search -- Google, Microsoft and Yahoo -- have all trained their sights on improving Internet search via cellphones, which they see as the next great battleground. Their new services answer urgent questions like: Where is the best local pizzeria? [C1.]</p>
        <p>CHINA KEEPS GROWING -- China's economy continues to accelerate at a blistering pace, growing 11.1 percent in the first quarter of this year from the first quarter of 2006, according to data from the National Bureau of Statistics. The surge in growth is almost certain to force Beijing to step up efforts to cool the economy. [C3.]</p>
        <p>A RUSH TO ORGANIC MILK -- Dairy farmers are hurrying to convert to organic milk production before new, more stringent federal regulations take effect, prompting predictions of a serious oversupply. [C1.]</p>
        <p>SIEMENS'S CHAIRMAN TO STEP DOWN -- The corruption scandals at Siemens claimed one of German's most prominent industrialists, as the company said its chairman, Heinrich von Pierer, would resign next week. [C3.]</p>
        <p>AMGEN ANEMIA DRUG CLEARS TRIAL -- Amgen said that its anemia drug Aranesp did not increase the death rate of lung cancer patients in a clinical trial, an announcement that could dispel at least some of the recent safety concerns over a widely used class of drugs. Amgen's stock rose 4 percent. [C7.]</p>
        <p>STRONG SALES FOR DRUG MAKERS -- Merck, Schering-Plough and Wyeth all rode strong drug sales to quarterly profits that topped Wall Street expectations, adding to the wave of good news for investors in major pharmaceutical companies. [C7.]</p>
        <p>MERRILL REPORTS GAINS -- Merrill Lynch posted a higher-than-expected increase in first-quarter profit, suggesting that efforts to bolster results from trading and private equity are paying off. [C2.]</p>
        <p>PROFIT IS NOT THE FULL PICTURE -- Continental Airlines and Southwest Airlines posted first-quarter profits on higher fares, but the results showed early signs that domestic air fares are under pressure. Both airlines managed to overcome an unusually difficult quarter, which is seasonally their weakest, but their shares fell on fears that the nascent airline recovery might falter. [C2.]</p>
        <p>NOKIA'S EARNINGS DROP 7% -- Nokia, the world's largest mobile phone maker, said that its first-quarter earnings dropped nearly 7 percent as expanding sales of low-end models in emerging markets pushed down its average selling price. [C8.]</p>
        <p>A.M.D. POSTS A LOSS -- Advanced Micro Devices announced that its loss during the first quarter was even bigger than expected, hurt by slower sales and a bruising price war with its larger rival, Intel. [C3.]</p>
        <p>KNOW THY CUSTOMER -- The creativity that was being celebrated at an advertising conference this week was not of the artsy, award-winning variety, but rather the kind that is rooted in insights derived from hard data about customer shopping patterns. Advertising: Stuart Elliott. [C7.]</p>
        <p>NEWSPAPERS PROFITS NARROW  -- The New York Times Company and the Gannett Company announced that their first-quarter profits declined while the Tribune Company reported a loss, as the companies continued to deal with an advertising recession. [C2.]</p>
        <p>A MIXED DAY IN THE MARKETS -- Wall Street averages closed mostly lower, as investors juggled upbeat economic data, divergent earnings reports and a pullback in Chinese stocks. [C10.]</p>
        <p>CELEBRITY CHEF IN A PICKLE -- Paula Deen, the Food Network's ebullient queen of butter-drenched Southern cooking, has found herself in the middle of a dispute between Smithfield Foods and a union that has long tried to organize one of the company's pork processing plants. [A17.]</p>
        <p>ONLINE</p>
        <p>Business Briefing  Articles on these developments are at nytimes.com/business</p>
        <p>The Delphi Corporation said that it expected a big investor to withdraw from a plan to pump up to $3.4 billion into the company to help it emerge from bankruptcy protection, but that other investors were still involved. (AP)</p>
        <p>Federal authorities said that the government had joined in a whistle-blower case filed against Hewlett-Packard, Sun Microsystems and Accenture over suspected improper payments connected to government contracts. (REUTERS)</p>
        <p>The American Express Company said that increased use of its credit cards by more customers helped drive first-quarter profit up 21 percent. (AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
