<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Antiques</title>
    <meta content="20anti" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/arts/design/20anti.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841521"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Antiques"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jewels and Jewelry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Furniture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E2DB1F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1070" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Antiques</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rare Books, New Worlds</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Wendy Moonan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Moonan, Wendy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rare Books, New Worlds</p>
        <p>You never know what secrets books may hold, which is reason enough to attend the New York Antiquarian Book Fair. This year's event, with 200 international exhibitors, opens today at noon at the Seventh Regiment Armory on Park Avenue at 67th Street and continues through Sunday.</p>
        <p>Here's one example of the surprises in store: The Manhattan gallery Cohen &amp; Taliaferro will exhibit a seemingly ordinary, pigskin-bound set of books, but with wonders inside. Theodore de Bry's ''Grand Voyages'' is a 13-part work in German with maps, plates and descriptions of the New World.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Drawings by a Roanoke settler are one of the many reasons to attend this weekend’s New York Antiquarian Book Fair.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rare Books, New Worlds</p>
        <p>You never know what secrets books may hold, which is reason enough to attend the New York Antiquarian Book Fair. This year's event, with 200 international exhibitors, opens today at noon at the Seventh Regiment Armory on Park Avenue at 67th Street and continues through Sunday.</p>
        <p>Here's one example of the surprises in store: The Manhattan gallery Cohen &amp; Taliaferro will exhibit a seemingly ordinary, pigskin-bound set of books, but with wonders inside. Theodore de Bry's ''Grand Voyages'' is a 13-part work in German with maps, plates and descriptions of the New World.</p>
        <p>Among them are engravings of drawings of American Indians made by the English artist John White during explorations in the 1580s. De Bry engraved plates from the drawings sometime before 1590.</p>
        <p>White drew his illustrations while serving on a mission sent by Sir Walter Raleigh in 1585 to establish a British colony, settling on Roanoke Island. Their efforts, though, did not go well. When Sir Francis Drake stopped there the following year, most of the men, including White, returned to England on Drake's ship.</p>
        <p>(White returned to Roanoke in 1587 as governor of a second colony, which disappeared sometime between White's departure later that year and his return in 1590. He was never able to find any survivors of what is now known as the lost colony of Roanoke Island.)</p>
        <p>As drawn by White, the natives look like marble athletes: tall, well muscled, handsome. In one engraving, men and women are dancing in a circle, waving palm fronds and branches. In another, women with long, wavy hair (hiding their nudity) plant seeds in neat rows.</p>
        <p>A third engraving shows a man wearing a fur-skin loincloth. A tasseled pouch hangs from his waistband and a bird is attached to his head, like an ornament. He is running across a meadow; behind him, tribesmen in canoes shoot arrows at wild shore birds.</p>
        <p>''De Bry's engravings are regarded as the earliest accurate depictions of Indian dress, artifacts and customs,'' said Paul E. Cohen, co-owner of the gallery. ''They would influence the depiction of Native Americans for the next 200 years.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cohen also plans to have antique English globes in his booth, and an exceptional hand-colored 16th-century world map by the Dutch cartographer Cornelis de Jode. It depicts the hemispheres from the poles rather than from the more conventional vantage point, the Equator.</p>
        <p>Bedroom to Go</p>
        <p>Christie's sale of European furniture in New York today has one supersize lot of French craftsmanship at its best. It is an elegant Louis XVI paneled bedroom, complete with an alcove bed, an overmantel mirror frame with gilded scrolling foliage, a carved limestone mantel, pale gray wall panels and oak ''parquet de Versailles'' flooring. The estimate is $150,000 to $300,000.</p>
        <p>Commissioned in the 1770s for the Hôtel Gaulin, a townhouse in Dijon, and attributed to an accomplished French sculptor, Jérôme Marlet, the room has a long, international history.</p>
        <p>In 1922, J. P. Morgan bought it, with a library and a music room from the same house, and donated all three rooms to the Metropolitan Museum of Art, which displayed them as period rooms from 1922 to 1953. Then the Met deaccessioned them and the rooms were separated. The music room was acquired by the Musée des Beaux-Arts in Dijon, with help from Carlton Hobbs, an antiques dealer in New York.</p>
        <p>''To me, the paneled rooms Jérôme Marlet did for the Hôtel Gaulin are as fine in design and execution as anything produced in Paris during the Louis XVI period,'' Mr. Hobbs said.</p>
        <p>Ten years ago, Phyllis Washington of Palm Desert, Calif., bought the bedroom but never installed it. She recently donated it to the French Heritage Society, an American nonprofit organization that finances educational and restoration programs in France and America.</p>
        <p>''Our most recently announced grant is to restore the French Consulate building on Fifth Avenue,'' said Jessica London, the executive director. ''The sale of the bedroom will augment our programs.''</p>
        <p>Pearls With a Past</p>
        <p>On Wednesday Christie's New York will auction the so-called Baroda Pearls, a two-strand necklace of giant natural pearls assembled for Maharaja Khande Rao of Baroda in the 1850s. The pearls, perfectly matched in color and graduated in size, are as large as marbles, with a luminous pink glow.</p>
        <p>''They are 68 of the largest and finest pearls from what has been historically considered the finest pearl necklace in the world,'' said Rahul Kadakia, the head of Christie's jewelry department in New York. ''These are about as good as real pearls get. There are no more pearls this size in the Persian Gulf.''</p>
        <p>The value of the necklace is estimated at $7 million to $9 million. (The lot also includes a pair of natural pearl and diamond ear pendants, a pearl-and-diamond brooch and a platinum ring with a button pearl flanked by diamonds.)</p>
        <p>The Baroda necklace had seven strands of pearls until 1948, when it was broken up. ''Three stands were divided among various members of the family,'' Mr. Kadakia said. ''The necklace represents over 150 years of history of a family that is known for its passion for jewelry.'' (This is very well illustrated in ''Made for Maharajas: Design Diary of Princely India'' by Amin Jaffer, published last year by Vendome Press.)</p>
        <p>The Maharajas of Baroda, whose land was in what is now the state of Gujarat, have had treasuries overflowing with diamonds and pearls since the 18th century. Pearls were sewn into royal outfits and incorporated into architectural elements. (The family's 19th-century Lakshmi Vilas Palace in Baroda is three times the size of Buckingham Palace.)</p>
        <p>The estimate for the pearls may not be too high. On Monday, Sotheby's sold a miniature enameled Fabergé chair with no gems for $2.3 million, against an estimate of $1 million to $1.5 million.</p>
        <p>Last year, Christie's sold $355 million worth of jewelry, a 27 percent rise over 2005. The highest price for a single lot of natural pearls was a double-strand necklace with 88 graduated pearls that Christie's Geneva sold in 2004 for $3.1 million. In 1999, Christie's Geneva sold the ''Barbara Hutton necklace,'' a single strand of 41 graduated natural pearls, for $1.4 million.</p>
        <p>''Those two necklaces can't compare with the Baroda pearls,'' said Mr. Kadakia. And he is confident people will be attracted to the sale: ''There are now 36 billionaires in India, more than in Japan,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Antiques</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
