<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>University Explains the Return of Troubled Student</title>
    <meta content="20virginia" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/us/20virginia.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070425T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841657"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MASSACRE IN VIRGINIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Blacksburg (Va)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cho, Seung-Hui</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Urbina, Ian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fernandez, Manny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cho Seung-Hui</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E0D61F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1116" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>University Explains the Return of Troubled Student</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">University Explains the Return of Troubled Student</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN URBINA and MANNY FERNANDEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fernandez, Manny; Urbina, Ian</byline>
      <dateline>BLACKSBURG, Va., April 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Virginia Tech officials defend decision to allow gunman Cho Seung-Hui to return to campus after he was released from psychiatric facility, even though they were aware of his troubled mental history and potential for violence; say they had no role in monitoring Cho's psychiatric treatment; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Officials at Virginia Tech on Thursday defended their decision to allow the gunman in Monday's rampage to return to campus after he was released from a psychiatric facility, even though they were aware of his troubled mental history and potential for violence.</p>
        <p>Cho Seung-Hui, 23, the student who killed himself and 32 others, received outpatient psychiatric care ordered for him after he was involuntarily hospitalized and reportedly suicidal in late 2005.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Virginia Tech officials defended their decision to allow the gunman in Monday’s rampage to return to campus after he was released from a psychiatric facility.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Officials at Virginia Tech on Thursday defended their decision to allow the gunman in Monday's rampage to return to campus after he was released from a psychiatric facility, even though they were aware of his troubled mental history and potential for violence.</p>
        <p>Cho Seung-Hui, 23, the student who killed himself and 32 others, received outpatient psychiatric care ordered for him after he was involuntarily hospitalized and reportedly suicidal in late 2005.</p>
        <p>Christopher Flynn, director of the campus counseling service, said the university had played no role in monitoring Mr. Cho's psychiatric treatment.</p>
        <p>''The university is not part of the mental health system nor the judiciary system, and we would not be the providers of mandatory counseling in this instance,'' Mr. Flynn said at a news conference. ''This is not a law enforcement issue. He had broken no law that we know of. The mental health professionals were there to assess his safety, not particularly the safety of others.''</p>
        <p>Also on Thursday, a law enforcement official who asked not to be identified said it now appeared that Mr. Cho had fired more than 100 shots during his rampage. The official said investigators believed that most of the 32 dead were shot a minimum of three times.</p>
        <p>Investigators now believe that after Mr. Cho left the scene of the first shooting, where two people were killed in a dormitory just after 7 a.m., he went to the post office to mail a package of writings and videos to NBC News, the official said, and then returned to his dormitory room before going to Norris Hall, where 30 people died.</p>
        <p>He chained shut a door to the building from the inside, using chains he had bought at Home Depot, the official said. The police who first responded to the shootings were able to force their way in by firing at the door with a shotgun, the official said.</p>
        <p>Investigators believe the shotgun blast alerted the gunman to the arrival of the police, and he shot himself.</p>
        <p>In the weeks before the violence, the investigator said, Mr. Cho went to a shooting range in Blacksburg, spending an hour practicing with the weapons.</p>
        <p>Investigators believe, based on interviews with an employee at the range, that Mr. Cho recorded part of his video statement in a van in the range parking lot, the official said.</p>
        <p>Soon after the shootings, university officials and police were criticized as taking too long to alert students to the danger after the first one.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, criticism increased after court documents, classmates and professors indicated that Mr. Cho had a long history of disturbing and menacing behavior. On Thursday, even President Bush joined the chorus of those questioning whether more could have been done to avoid the tragedy, though he did not specifically mention university officials.</p>
        <p>In previous cases like that of Virginia Tech, ''there have been warning signals that if an adult, for example, had taken those signals seriously, perhaps tragedy could have been avoided,'' Mr. Bush said at a town meeting in Tipp City, Ohio.</p>
        <p>''One of the lessons of these tragedies is to make sure that when people see somebody or know somebody that is exhibiting abnormal behavior, to do something about it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Also on Thursday, Gov. Timothy M. Kaine of Virginia said the state, rather than the university, would oversee a review panel that plans to examine how the university handled Mr. Cho's mental health needs and the Monday shootings.</p>
        <p>The panel, which Mr. Kaine said would seek to make recommendations before classes start in the fall, will be led by retired Col. Gerald Massengill, a former state police superintendent, and includes Tom Ridge, the former secretary of homeland security, Mr. Kaine said.</p>
        <p>''This is a case study of a very tragic incident that has occurred unfortunately in Virginia,'' Colonel Massengill said at a news conference. ''We're not trying to second-guess anyone with any decision or any action that was taken.''</p>
        <p>In defending their actions, university officials pointed out that Mr. Cho was legally an adult and that a doctor at the psychiatric center in nearby Radford where Mr. Cho was sent in 2005 determined that he was mentally ill but not an imminent danger to himself or others.</p>
        <p>''I know that we followed all of our policies correctly in the past and we acted on information that we had at the time,'' said Edward Spencer, associate vice president for student affairs.</p>
        <p>He added that Mr. Cho had lived in a suite with five other students, and that ''none of them expressed any concern to us of any violence, danger or whatever. I think that gives you a view of the inner world of mental illness.''</p>
        <p>Police officials said that while the multimedia manifesto Mr. Cho sent to NBC News on Monday provided them with little new information to help their investigation, they were disappointed it was broadcast.</p>
        <p>''We appreciate NBC's cooperation, and they're cooperating with all of the authorities, though we're rather disappointed in the editorial decision to broadcast these disturbing images,'' Col. W. Steven Flaherty, the superintendent of the Virginia State Police, said during a morning news conference.</p>
        <p>NBC defended its decision to release parts of Mr. Cho's video, saying that it ''did not rush the material onto air, but instead consulted with local authorities, who have since publicly acknowledged our appropriate handling of the matter.''</p>
        <p>The police recovered a Dell laptop computer and a cellphone that appeared to belong to Emily J. Hilscher, Mr. Cho's first victim, according to an affidavit for a search warrant filed on Thursday afternoon.</p>
        <p>The police have been investigating whether there were any links between Mr. Cho and Ms. Hilscher.</p>
        <p>Police officials said they were also continuing to explore whether Mr. Cho had any connection with any of his other victims.</p>
        <p>Crime scene technicians recovered a total of 17 spent magazines of ammunition, the majority of which were for Mr. Cho's 9-millimeter handgun, a law enforcement official said.</p>
        <p>''He ended up buying a load of mags from Wal-Mart and Dick's Sporting Goods,'' said the official, who asked not to be identified. ''This was a thought-out process. He thought this through.''</p>
        <p>Classes were scheduled to resume on Monday, but Mark G. McNamee, university provost and vice president for academic affairs, said that the university planned to offer students a number of ways to complete the semester. Students will have the option of removing themselves from the campus for all or part of the semester without penalty to their academic standing, Mr. McNamee said.</p>
        <p>The students killed on Monday will be posthumously awarded the degrees they were pursuing, he added. The degrees will be awarded in regular commencement exercises.</p>
        <p>MASSACRE IN VIRGINIA</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 25, 2007, Wednesday  An article on Friday about the massacre at Virginia Tech included erroneous information from a law enforcement official about the origin of chains the gunman, Seung-Hui Cho, used to secure doors in a classroom building where most of the killings took place. (The error was repeated in a front-page article on Sunday about Mr. Cho's life.) Although officials now say the chains were not bought at Home Depot, they have declined to say where the chains were obtained.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 25, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article on Friday about the massacre at Virginia Tech included erroneous information from a law enforcement official about the origin of chains the gunman, Seung-Hui Cho, used to secure doors in a classroom building where most of the killings took place. (The error was repeated in a front-page article on Sunday about Mr. Cho's life.) Although officials now say the chains were not bought at Home Depot, they have declined to say where the chains were obtained.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
