<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chekhovian Characters Swirl to Rachmaninoff in a Glass-and-Steel Studio</title>
    <meta content="20seag" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/arts/dance/20seag.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841541"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Eifman Ballet Company</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DEEDB1F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="481" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chekhovian Characters Swirl to Rachmaninoff in a Glass-and-Steel Studio</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Chekhovian Characters Swirl to Rachmaninoff in a Glass-and-Steel Studio</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunning, Jennifer</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is not surprising that Boris Eifman chose not to set ''The Seagull'' in the late-19th-century Russia of the Chekhov play from which the ballet is drawn, though it is disappointing, given the beauty of the Eifman Ballet's costumes and the extravagance of its sets. Mr. Eifman likes to turn tradition and the familiar on their heads. And so the new ballet, performed on Wednesday as the centerpiece of the Eifman Ballet of St. Petersburg's 30th-anniversary season at City Center, is set for the most part in a glass-and-steel ballet studio.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eifman's lavish theatrical imagination and gift for staging seem to have deserted him. Chekhov's play is short on action. Its heart lies in the words and images with which the themes of art and genius -- favorites of Mr. Eifman -- are addressed in interactions between the characters. With no strong narrative to transform, the ballet, set to Rachmaninoff and Scriabin, reduces the themes to bursts of hollow agony and bad dance through which the ballet staggers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chekhov’s play, “The Seagull,” lacks a strong narrative, and thus the ballet version reduces the themes to bursts of hollow agony and bad dance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is not surprising that Boris Eifman chose not to set ''The Seagull'' in the late-19th-century Russia of the Chekhov play from which the ballet is drawn, though it is disappointing, given the beauty of the Eifman Ballet's costumes and the extravagance of its sets. Mr. Eifman likes to turn tradition and the familiar on their heads. And so the new ballet, performed on Wednesday as the centerpiece of the Eifman Ballet of St. Petersburg's 30th-anniversary season at City Center, is set for the most part in a glass-and-steel ballet studio.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eifman's lavish theatrical imagination and gift for staging seem to have deserted him. Chekhov's play is short on action. Its heart lies in the words and images with which the themes of art and genius -- favorites of Mr. Eifman -- are addressed in interactions between the characters. With no strong narrative to transform, the ballet, set to Rachmaninoff and Scriabin, reduces the themes to bursts of hollow agony and bad dance through which the ballet staggers.</p>
        <p>Irina Arkadina, the play's aging actress, has become an aging ballerina, danced by Nina Zmievets. Her wayward lover, the famous writer Trigorin, is now a famous choreographer, portrayed by Yuri Smekalov. Her son, the would-be writer Constantine Treplev, is now a struggling young choreographer (danced by Dmitri Fisher in a bowl haircut), a would-be artist who is eager to push dance into the future. And Treplev's sweetheart, Nina Zarechnaya, is now a foxy young ballerina, played by Maria Abashova.</p>
        <p>The choreographic high point comes with a passage of street or hip-hop dancing, apparently Treplev's idea of the height of avant-garde. Its vitality doesn't survive his reworking of it in the ballet studio, represented by a skimpy motif in which the momentum of a slowly swinging, crooked right arm carries his ever-crumpling body leftward from a lean to the right. Once performed and once repeated, the motif might simply suggest that the ballet's Treplev is as naïve as the play's Treplev. But its frequent repetition suggests that Mr. Eifman does not have much more to say.</p>
        <p>Choreography is not his forte, with the passages of pure dancing often looking more like imitations of dance than like means of expression. Trigorin's dances are almost as foolish-looking as Treplev's. So the hip-hop is welcome because, for once, a core vocabulary informs the dancing and gives it a texture missing from the rushes and swirls across the stage, the acrobatic duets and the choruses of trotting robots that tend to inform an Eifman ballet. Even Mr. Smekalov, usually so vividly dramatic, is a cipher in ''The Seagull.''</p>
        <p>Thankfully, Mr. Eifman will return next week to the compelling theatrical form of ''Russian Hamlet'' and ''Anna Karenina,'' the repertory ballets that close his engagement.</p>
        <p>The Eifman Ballet of St. Petersburg performs through Sunday night at City Center, 131 West 55th Street, Manhattan; (212) 581-1212, nycitycenter.org.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
