<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Each At-Bat Is the Focus, and That's the Difference</title>
    <meta content="20arod" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841658"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E0D61F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="904" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Each At-Bat Is the Focus, and That's the Difference</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alex Rodriguez was destroying baseballs on a warm morning in Tampa, Fla., two months ago, scorching line drives or making some balls vanish. With each fluid swing in a routine batting practice session, Rodriguez looked content. He performed as if it were any month except October.</p>
        <p>As one member of the Yankees' organization watched Rodriguez's display, he strayed from what was happening and pondered what could happen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Alex Rodriguez was destroying baseballs on a warm morning in Tampa, Fla., two months ago, scorching line drives or making some balls vanish. With each fluid swing in a routine batting practice session, Rodriguez looked content. He performed as if it were any month except October.</p>
        <p>As one member of the Yankees' organization watched Rodriguez's display, he strayed from what was happening and pondered what could happen.</p>
        <p>''I hope we don't lose him,'' the person said.</p>
        <p>That thought, the possibility that Rodriguez will opt out of his contract and become a free agent after the season, hovers over the Yankees. Rodriguez has said that he wants to finish his career in New York, but Scott Boras, his agent, did not negotiate an escape clause simply to make a 10-year, $252 million deal sweeter. It is there to be used, not ignored.</p>
        <p>When Rodriguez hammered a two-out, three-run homer in the ninth inning to push the Yankees past the Cleveland Indians, 8-6, he gave himself a little more leverage in what is already a one-sided situation. Rodriguez, not the Yankees, controls where he will play next season. Maybe that is why Rodriguez is relaxed. For once, Rodriguez has created tranquillity, not discord, in his world.</p>
        <p>''I just wanted to come back and enjoy myself, regardless of what happens,'' Rodriguez said. ''Just enjoy it as much as I can.''</p>
        <p>Can Rodriguez enjoy himself any more? He socked a game-winning grand slam against the Baltimore Orioles 13 days ago and did the same kind of giddy dance around the bases that he did yesterday. Rodriguez leads the major leagues with 10 homers and 26 runs batted in and is batting .351 in 14 games.</p>
        <p>Rodriguez was 0 for 4 with two strikeouts and a throwing error that led to Cleveland's sixth run before getting a final chance against Joe Borowski. After a wild pitch moved the runners to second and third, Rodriguez might have fretted about Borowski trying to avoid him.</p>
        <p>''In years past, maybe I would have out-thought myself in that situation, with men on second and third,'' Rodriguez said. ''I just wanted to see the ball and put a good swing on it and trust what I saw.''</p>
        <p>Manager Joe Torre called Rodriguez's presence ''scary.'' Johnny Damon referred to Rodriguez as the ''new Alex.'' But Brian Bruney, a reliever who makes $395,545, offered Rodriguez a bottom-line appraisal.</p>
        <p>''I told him if he opted out of his contract, he could sign a billion-dollar contract right now,'' Bruney said.</p>
        <p>Rodriguez has three years and $81 million remaining on his contract. General Manager Brian Cashman has said that the Yankees wuold not try to sign Rodriguez to an extension, which enables any interested suitors, like the Los Angeles Angels or the Chicago Cubs or the Boston Red Sox, to plot now how they could slot Rodriguez into their payroll. Cashman politely declined to discuss Rodriguez's contract status yesterday.</p>
        <p>While Rodriguez has told teammates that he loves New York, he also loves being the highest-paid player in the game. It is doubtful Rodriguez would get a contract that averages $27 million a year, but, if the Cubs gave Alfonso Soriano an eight-year, $136 million deal, Rodriguez, who is a superior player, would surely find a team to offer him more. It could end up being the Yankees.</p>
        <p>For now, Rodriguez is deflecting questions about next season and pledging to keep everything simple. Torre said Rodriguez had not done that often enough.</p>
        <p>''He's dealing with every at-bat, as opposed to trying to make up for at-bats,'' Torre said. ''And that's a big difference for me.''</p>
        <p>Despite Rodriguez's postseason demons, there are surely teams that would pursue him. Arte Moreno, the Angels' owner, has said that Rodriguez could be too pricey, but that could have been a negotiating tactic. Lou Piniella, the Cubs' manager, would relish being reunited with Rodriguez, whom he managed in Seattle.</p>
        <p>The Red Sox had a deal to unload Manny Ramírez to the Texas Rangers for Rodriguez in 2003, but the players union negated it because Rodriguez was deferring too much money and was not receiving benefits to alter his contract. Surprisingly, Rodriguez then landed in New York.</p>
        <p>If the Red Sox wanted Rodriguez so badly once, it is natural to wonder if they would have interest again. Third baseman Mike Lowell is a free agent after the season. The addition of Rodriguez would either give the Red Sox a staggering batting order in the 3-4-5 slots of Ramírez, David Ortiz and Rodriguez, or enable them to deal Ramírez.</p>
        <p>Naturally, Rodriguez will be booed when the Yankees open a three-game series against the Red Sox at Fenway Park tonight. The visit will be another test for the newly relaxed Rodriguez, who went 0 for his first 16 the first time he played there as a Yankee.</p>
        <p>''It felt like 0 for 50,'' Rodriguez said at the time.</p>
        <p>How will it feel this time?</p>
        <p>''He's enjoying himself and not stressed to worry about having those big games,'' designated hitter Jason Giambi said.</p>
        <p>For Rodriguez to play the big games that will truly test him, the Yankees have to make the postseason again. Rodriguez said he had not smiled this much since his daughter, Natasha, who is 2 1/2 years old, was born. Whether Rodriguez is still smiling in October is an unknown. Whether Rodriguez will still be a Yankee after that is a much bigger unknown.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
