<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tales of Yosemite's Fatal Attraction</title>
    <meta content="20yosemite" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/travel/escapes/20yosemite.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841518"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/National Parks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Yosemite National Park</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">National Parks, Monuments and Seashores</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">National Parks, Monuments and Seashores</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Yosemite National Park</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E3DB1F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1349" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tales of Yosemite's Fatal Attraction</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tales of Yosemite’s Fatal Attraction</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRAD STONE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''It is 3,000 feet to the bottom and no undertaker to meet you. Take no chances. There is a difference between bravery and just plain ordinary foolishness.''</p>
        <p>Sign posted in the 1930s at Glacier Point in Yosemite National Park.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The anthropologist Michael P. Ghiglieri, who recently wrote a book on the fatalities throughout Yosemite’s recorded history, led a tour through park.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''It is 3,000 feet to the bottom and no undertaker to meet you. Take no chances. There is a difference between bravery and just plain ordinary foolishness.''</p>
        <p>Sign posted in the 1930s at Glacier Point in Yosemite National Park.</p>
        <p>IT was a sunny, idyllic Sunday earlier this month in America's splendidly vertical Yosemite National Park. On the wooden footbridge straddling a raging Merced River, children frolicked and marveled at the 317-foot Vernal Falls above, while spectators brashly leaned over the bridge railings to snap the perfect photograph under a bright blue sky.</p>
        <p>Everywhere he looked, Michael P. Ghiglieri saw danger.</p>
        <p>An ecologist, author and wilderness guide, Dr. Ghiglieri knows this stretch of the Merced well. As much as the iconic granite face of El Capitan or the imposing shoulder of Half Dome, the Merced figures prominently in his new book: ''Off the Wall: Death in Yosemite,'' co-written with a veteran park ranger, Charles R. Farabee Jr., who goes by the nickname Butch.</p>
        <p>The book is not for the faint of heart. It's an exhaustively researched, sprightly account of nearly 900 fatalities in Yosemite's 156 years of recorded history -- every waterfall slip, rock-climbing mishap, animal attack, drowning and cold-blooded murder.</p>
        <p>Like his 2001 book, ''Over the Edge: Death in Grand Canyon,'' which was self-published and, he says, has sold more than 156,000 copies, the sequel offers more than voyeuristic thrills and chills. Dr. Ghiglieri, who has a doctorate in wildlife ecology from the University of California, Davis, finds useful lessons in human tragedy. He wants to peek inside the heads of victims and understand the string of disastrous decisions that lead to catastrophe.</p>
        <p>''Most people who end up in fatal incidents at Yosemite played some role in their demise'' Dr. Ghiglieri says. ''The primary reason to delve into any history like this is that there are lessons, and the lessons are valuable lest we repeat them.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Ghiglieri, 60, has a scholarly predilection for delivering long lectures and a deep knowledge of national park history. But here on the tourist-jammed footbridge, with a mischievous glint in his eye, he notes that there have been 10 fatalities on this very spot, and then spins one of the dreadful stories.</p>
        <p>In 1978, Chol Han, 16, was hopping among river boulders with other boys from his high school in Japan. ''There were several girls admiring the prowess of these boys,'' Dr. Ghiglieri said, when Mr. Han misjudged a jump and fell into the river.</p>
        <p>Bystanders improvised a rope of buckled-together belts and got one end into in his hands, but Mr. Han, moments from pulling himself to safety, and even while thanking his rescuers, let go and was fatally swept downstream.</p>
        <p>Investigating park rangers later theorized that he was showing off for his friends and thought he could save face by rescuing himself.</p>
        <p>While fatalities are rare among Yosemite's more than three million annual visitors, young males are disproportionately represented in the park's annals of misfortune. During their research, the ''Death in Yosemite'' co-authors found that males represented 82 percent of both drowning and waterfall victims, with an average age of 23.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ghiglieri says that boys seek a rite of passage -- a chance to prove themselves as men -- which society no longer offers. ''In Yosemite, a young person who is trying to prove he is a man is surrounded by these small instantaneous challenges,'' Dr. Ghiglieri says. ''And they are often off the trail and off the beaten path.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, modern culture no longer trains people to recognize and avoid natural dangers. Their misjudgments give Dr. Ghiglieri, and his readers, insight into the species he calls homo domesticus.</p>
        <p>The species surrounded him on that sunny day earlier this month. Tourists thronged the popular trail to Vernal Falls, ascending from the valley with shoulder bags and flip-flops. Though the famous Mist Trail up to the falls was closed for the winter, visitors were going around the gate and scrambling down to the Merced banks, playing on rocks and snapping photographs.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ghiglieri was bemused but worried. ''The most dangerous part of this park is the river,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Though he's written scientific studies like ''The Chimpanzees of Kibale Forest'' (Columbia University Press, 1984) and treatises on psychology like ''The Dark Side of Man: Tracing the Origins of Male Violence'' (Perseus Books, 2000), his work took a sharp turn in 2001.</p>
        <p>When his proposal for ''Over the Edge: Death in Grand Canyon'' was rejected by the publishing arm of the Grand Canyon Association, he wrote and self-published the book with Thomas M. Myers, a canyon physician.</p>
        <p>Part of the gruesome appeal of ''Death in Grand Canyon'' are the tales of hapless victims who backed up over the canyon rim while posing for photographs (seven)--or who slipped while relieving themselves into the chasm (at least five).</p>
        <p>But both books are also filled with serious historical information. In ''Death in Yosemite,'' sections are devoted to the 19th-century persecution of the Sierra Miwok Indians and the construction, over the objections of environmentalists, of the Hetch Hetchy Reservoir on the Tuolumne River to satisfy the water needs of San Francisco.</p>
        <p>But the book's most stirring episodes are its chronicles of bad decision-making, often by experts whose wits abandoned them at key moments. In 1999, Jan Davis, a 58-year-old stunt woman, jumped from the top of El Capitan as the fourth of five demonstrators protesting the park's ban of BASE-jumping -- the sport of leaping from mountains, bridges or buildings with a parachute.</p>
        <p>Because she expected her equipment to be confiscated by park rangers, Ms. Davis borrowed a less valuable rigging with a leg-sheath pilot chute, which was different than her own back-mounted gear. Spectator videos of her fatal 3,000 foot fall showed her swatting at her back in an apparent attempt to clear her chute, but she was unable to activate the less-familiar equipment effectively.</p>
        <p>Strung together, the tales in ''Off the Wall: Death in Yosemite'' offer some simple rules. Do not underestimate the spectacular, unforgiving terrain. Capturing that perfect photograph, if it involves wading anywhere near the edge of a waterfall, is suicide. Hiking alone, particularly off trail or in winter, has proven disastrous again and again.</p>
        <p>There's also one comforting lesson: Yosemite is still relatively safe. Though the number of rescue missions has climbed over the last 30 years along with attendance, fatalities have dropped from around 18 a year in the 1970s to 7 a year in this decade, according to the authors.</p>
        <p>But these improving trends do not get in the way of Dr. Ghiglieri's curiosity about errant human instinct -- the impulses that move distressed hikers to head tragically in the opposite direction of safety, or that cause rock climbers to incorrectly tie their safety ropes and then rappel off the end into open air.</p>
        <p>''There are incredible benefits to our life of modern luxury. But we pay for it by domesticating ourselves,'' he said. ''When we set out in a park like Yosemite, we enter a world for which we are not very well trained.''</p>
        <p>''You don't practice sitting on top of 3000-foot-high cliffs. You don't get that at the office,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Two miles above the Merced footbridge at Clark Point, with the 594-foot Nevada Falls to the east, he recited a few more terrible tales. Sonia Del Carmen Caceres, 27-year-old mother, floated on her back in a gentle eddy above those falls one hot day in 1985, then got carried over the brink, apparently without even noticing she had started to drift.</p>
        <p>And on a cold New Year's Day in 1975, a Boy Scout playing on the ice above Vernal Falls cracked through and was carried by the current underneath the ice cap, his parka visible only as an orange torpedo streaking under the surface. After re-emerging for two seconds right at the lip of the falls, an adult troop leader defied odds, grabbed hold of the boy's jacket and hoisted him to safety.</p>
        <p>It is an unusual story coming from Dr. Ghiglieri: a tale of youthful folly and carelessness that ends -- surprisingly -- with salvation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
