<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SPARE TIMES: April 20 - April 26; THE CHILDREN'S GLADE</title>
    <meta content="20bkids" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841525"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DB1F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="388" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SPARE TIMES: April 20 - April 26; THE CHILDREN'S GLADE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAUREL GRAEBER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Boys and girls are forever wandering into enchanted forests in fairy tales, but they don't expect to stumble onto one just off the bustling streets of Manhattan. But thanks to Frederick Law Olmsted, one of the original designers of Central Park -- and more recently to the Peter Jay Sharp Foundation and the Central Park Conservancy -- they can soon enjoy the next-best thing. It may not be filled with storybook magic, but it will offer the genuine mysteries of nature, as well as year-round arts programs to hold young audiences spellbound.</p>
        <p>The space, the Children's Glade, left, will open on Sunday with a ribbon-cutting at 11 a.m., followed by a celebration of Earth Day. The seating in the glade, at 104th Street on the park's west side, will consist of natural boulders and fallen tree trunks instead of park benches, and the play areas will have garden paths and leafy boughs rather than sandboxes or jungle gyms. ''There are so many trends in playgrounds right now,'' said Douglas Blonsky, president of the Central Park Conservancy, which designed the project with Edwina von Gal, ''and we thought this was an opportunity to do something different.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Boys and girls are forever wandering into enchanted forests in fairy tales, but they don't expect to stumble onto one just off the bustling streets of Manhattan. But thanks to Frederick Law Olmsted, one of the original designers of Central Park -- and more recently to the Peter Jay Sharp Foundation and the Central Park Conservancy -- they can soon enjoy the next-best thing. It may not be filled with storybook magic, but it will offer the genuine mysteries of nature, as well as year-round arts programs to hold young audiences spellbound.</p>
        <p>The space, the Children's Glade, left, will open on Sunday with a ribbon-cutting at 11 a.m., followed by a celebration of Earth Day. The seating in the glade, at 104th Street on the park's west side, will consist of natural boulders and fallen tree trunks instead of park benches, and the play areas will have garden paths and leafy boughs rather than sandboxes or jungle gyms. ''There are so many trends in playgrounds right now,'' said Douglas Blonsky, president of the Central Park Conservancy, which designed the project with Edwina von Gal, ''and we thought this was an opportunity to do something different.''</p>
        <p>Financed entirely by the Sharp Foundation, the glade includes a natural amphitheater near the park's Great Hill, to be dedicated to theater, dance, music, storytelling and other performances. A profusion of native plants, including dogwoods and mountain laurel, will provide themes for environmental workshops. Both types of activities are planned for Sunday, when children can make nature-based crafts, plant asters and join a bingo game requiring them to complete tasks like measuring a tree, navigating a labyrinth and raking mulch. The entertainment, part of the Green Apple Music &amp; Arts Festival, begins at noon with Brady Rymer and the Little Band That Could. Next is the headline attraction -- the Laurie Berkner Band -- and dancing from Baby Loves Disco.</p>
        <p>Not to mention the romance of the glade itself, with gnarly black locust trees and a huge catalpa. ''It died, and we left the trunk,'' Mr. Blonsky said. ''It's eight feet tall and has a hole in it, and it almost feels as if it's talking to you.'' In a language, no doubt, that all children understand. (Noon to 4 p.m.; entrance at 103rd Street and Central Park West. Free. Information: 212-310-6638.)</p>
        <p>LAUREL GRAEBER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
