<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Experts Shy From Instant Diagnoses of Gunman's Mental Illness, but Hints Abound</title>
    <meta content="20psych" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/us/20psych.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841601"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MASSACRE IN VIRGINIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Blacksburg (Va)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwartz, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carey, Benedict</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cho, Seung-Hui</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stone, Michael (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Schizophrenia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Paranoia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Paranoia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Schizophrenia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Cho Seung-Hui</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E4D71F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="877" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Experts Shy From Instant Diagnoses of Gunman's Mental Illness, but Hints Abound</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Experts Shy From Instant Diagnoses of Gunman’s Mental Illness, but Hints Abound</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN SCHWARTZ and BENEDICT CAREY; Reporting was contributed by Sarah Abruzzese, John M. Broder, Shaila Dewan, Cate Doty, Bob Driehaus, Brenda Goodman, Choe Sang-Hun, Suevon Lee, Carolyn Marshall, Lori Moore, Haeyoun Park, William K. Rashbaum, Alicia C. Shepard and Archie Tse.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carey, Benedict; Cho, Seung-Hui; Schwartz, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Forensic psychology experts say video testament that Cho Seung-Hui mailed to NBC during intermission in his killing spree offers compelling peek into troubles that shaped gunman; Dr Michael Stone, expert on personality disorders and killers, says video illustrates person with serious disorders; says people with such disorders might see conspiracies all around, and have very little empathy for others (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The video testament that Cho Seung-Hui mailed to NBC during the intermission in his killing spree offers a compelling peek into the troubles that shaped a gunman, experts in forensic psychology say.</p>
        <p>The clips suggest a person with holes in his soul, who lacked features like the emotional control and empathy for others that keep a lid on the violent impulses anyone might have.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The video that Cho Seung-Hui mailed to NBC offers a compelling peek into the troubles that shaped a gunman, experts in forensic psychology say.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The video testament that Cho Seung-Hui mailed to NBC during the intermission in his killing spree offers a compelling peek into the troubles that shaped a gunman, experts in forensic psychology say.</p>
        <p>The clips suggest a person with holes in his soul, who lacked features like the emotional control and empathy for others that keep a lid on the violent impulses anyone might have.</p>
        <p>But can grainy, YouTube-ish video snippets offer real insight into the nature of Mr. Cho's mental illness?</p>
        <p>A solid diagnosis requires time and access to the patient, whose history can be as important as his actions; and most people with mental illness are far more likely to harm themselves than others. There is a universe of possible labels, and the exercise can be an empty one, said Robert Hare, an expert in violent behavior who has been a consultant to the F.B.I.</p>
        <p>''Diagnoses are ill advised if they are made too quickly,'' said Dr. Hare, who created one of the most authoritative models for detecting psychopathy. ''After-the-fact explanations of this sort can go in about a thousand different directions.''</p>
        <p>Experts who have watched the videos say that while the picture may yet change, they did see sentiments and thought that hint at Mr. Cho's mental landscape. Their opinions coalesce around a handful of conditions with names like ''psychotic depression'' and ''avoidant personality disorder'' and ''schizophrenia-paranoid type.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Michael Stone, an expert on personality disorders and killers, said in an interview that he saw in the videos ''a paranoid person with sadistic traits, possibly psychotic.'' These are people, he said, who might see conspiracies all around, and who have so little empathy that they ''can do the most heinous things almost as if they were whittling wood.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Stone, who is a professor of clinical psychiatry at Columbia University, said this lack of empathy did not define any single mental illness. Mr. Cho appears to be a near opposite of psychopaths, who often have superficial charm to go along with an indifference to the effect of their actions on others.</p>
        <p>In the video manifesto, Dr. Stone said he saw a man characterized fundamentally by a feeling of powerlessness. ''For 23 years he was a powerless, impotent cipher,'' the professor said, and so, ''for two hours of his life, he was a powerful man.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cho's taped rants, and his peers' descriptions of him as a classmate, suggest a blend of severe and specific personality problems, said Dr. Theodore Millon, dean and scientific director of the Institute for Advanced Studies in Personology and Psychopathology in Coral Gables, Fla., who has designed testing questionnaires used in many colleges.</p>
        <p>People with so-called avoidant personality disorder shun social situations because of a paralyzing dread of disapproval or criticism. Those with paranoid personality disorder nourish a deep distrust of others and see insults and malicious meanings in almost every interaction. Both are stubborn patterns of behavior that can begin in adolescence or earlier, and in his influential book, ''Disorders of Personality'' (Wiley, 1996), Dr. Millon identifies a blend of the two as ''insular paranoid'' disorder.</p>
        <p>''Such people feel persecuted, deeply isolated, that the world rejects them, and they will often replace the real world with an inner one in which they act out their fantasies,'' Dr. Millon said, adding that this inner world can be elaborate, a ''pseudo-community'' modeled after the real one in which they live.</p>
        <p>''The acting out usually stops there,'' Dr. Millon said. ''Only in rare circumstances do they confuse reality with this inner world.''</p>
        <p>Severe psychiatric disorders like bipolar disorder and schizophrenia often first emerge during late adolescence or in the early 20s. People diagnosed with schizophrenia, a disorder characterized by delusions and imaginary voices, most often have their first psychotic ''break'' as young adults. Some of Mr. Cho's actions are suggestive of that kind of a break with reality, some experts said.</p>
        <p>''If you think of the problem of psychosis as blowing a fuse in the brain that allows us to distinguish clearly between what is really happening and what is not -- between real things and ideas, fantasy -- you see some evidence of that here,'' said Dr. Frank Ochberg of the Dart Center for Journalism and Trauma and an expert on violence and psychiatry who worked with officials at Columbine High School after the deadly shootings there in 1999.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ochberg said that a first psychosis was often a terrifying experience, and that eventually people with schizophrenia developed ''ways of coping by projecting, denying and at times indulging in this grandiose fantasy about their own purpose and lives.''</p>
        <p>To Dr. Hare, the nagging question is recognizing the traits that will lead to violence. Most warning signs often stand out only in retrospect, he said, and many of Mr. Cho's traits were ''not all that uncommon.''</p>
        <p>The population of killers is very small, and no one knows how prevalent their common traits are in the population at large.</p>
        <p>''We have to try to understand,'' Dr. Hare said. ''The basic research can be done.''</p>
        <p>MASSACRE IN VIRGINIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
