<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Change in Batting Order Doesn't Change the Offense</title>
    <meta content="20mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/sports/baseball/20mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841683"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Florida Marlins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Florida Marlins</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Duca, Paul Lo</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Randolph, Willie</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Beltran, Carlos</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Hernandez, Orlando</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7DF163EF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1032" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Change in Batting Order Doesn't Change the Offense</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lineup Changes, but Not the Way the Mets Hit</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shpigel, Ben</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, April 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After deciding to give the dinged-up Paul Lo Duca a day off, Manager Willie Randolph jotted down three lineups on a legal pad. He thought them over for about 90 seconds, and in the end it proved about 90 seconds too much.</p>
        <p>The Mets are scoring runs with such staggering frequency that if the bench coach Jerry Manuel had scrawled in his own name, Carlos Beltrán and seven clubhouse attendants, they could perhaps put up a 10-spot. As it was, they held a supreme mismatch against Rick Vanden Hurk, a rookie right-hander for Florida who had yet to pitch above Class A before making his major league debut last week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Batting second, Carlos Beltrán had four hits, blasted his team-leading fourth home run and scored twice as the Mets pounded Florida’s rookie right-hander Rick Vanden Hurk for eight runs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After deciding to give the dinged-up Paul Lo Duca a day off, Manager Willie Randolph jotted down three lineups on a legal pad. He thought them over for about 90 seconds, and in the end it proved about 90 seconds too much.</p>
        <p>The Mets are scoring runs with such staggering frequency that if the bench coach Jerry Manuel had scrawled in his own name, Carlos Beltrán and seven clubhouse attendants, they could perhaps put up a 10-spot. As it was, they held a supreme mismatch against Rick Vanden Hurk, a rookie right-hander for Florida who had yet to pitch above Class A before making his major league debut last week.</p>
        <p>The Mets pounded Vanden Hurk for eight runs Thursday night and routed the Marlins, 11-3, at Dolphin Stadium for their third consecutive victory. For the third time this season, every Mets starter, including the pitcher, had at least one hit. And it was those hitting in new positions who did the most damage.</p>
        <p>Batting second in Lo Duca's spot, Beltrán had four hits, blasted his team-leading fourth home run and scored twice. Moved to sixth, Shawn Green had two doubles and two runs batted in. Ramón Castro, Lo Duca's replacement at catcher, hit a two-run homer to cap a six-run fourth inning and had three R.B.I.</p>
        <p>''This lineup was built to score runs,'' Beltrán said.</p>
        <p>The Mets' advantage on the mound was just as huge. Orlando Hernández, who has appeared in 193 more major league games than Vanden Hurk, stymied the free-swinging Marlins over seven innings, striking out 10 and allowing only one hit after the game's second batter.</p>
        <p>In sweeping the two-game series here, allowing only seven hits, the Mets (10-4) vaulted over the Atlanta Braves to move into first place in the National League East, and they now own the best record in the majors. Their weekend series with Atlanta at Shea Stadium could serve as a decent litmus test. The Braves lined up their rotation so that their three best pitchers -- Tim Hudson, Chuck James and John Smoltz -- would start.</p>
        <p>''We all know it's early, but this is the time when you can start separating yourselves from everyone else,'' the Mets' José Valentín said.</p>
        <p>Before being promoted last week, the 21-year-old Vanden Hurk was known as the second most-famous pitcher to be born in the Netherlands, behind Bert Blyleven. He was also noted for making the Hawaiian Winter League All-Star team as a member of the Waikiki Beach Boys. He may be recognized now as the latest pitcher -- nationality irrelevant -- to be hammered by the Mets. In the past three games, the Mets scored 28 runs on 46 hits (19 for extra bases), with everyone getting into the act.</p>
        <p>''You're not going to get these many runs on a road trip all the time, but that's the kind of offense we have,'' said Moises Alou, who went 2 for 4 and scored a run.</p>
        <p>That was why it mattered so little who Randolph batted where. The first lineup had Green hitting second. That was followed by versions with Beltrán and then David Wright, whose fifth-inning single extended his team-record hitting streak to 26 games, in that spot. Of the Mets' eight regular starters, six are batting above .300. Valentín, who homered in the ninth, barely misses the cut at .298. Carlos Delgado is the low man, at .220.</p>
        <p>''I don't know the kid, but if I were him, I'd be a little concerned about facing this lineup,'' Randolph said of Vanden Hurk before the game.</p>
        <p>In the last few seasons, the Mets have struggled facing young pitchers for the first time, being shut down by the likes of Matt Cain, Joe Blanton and Zach Duke, and they could not do much of anything against Vanden Hurk through the first two innings. But trailing by 2-1 in the third, they started timing his slow curve and pouncing on his fastballs when he was behind in the count.</p>
        <p>With two out and runners on first and third, Delgado smoked a double to the right-field fence that drove in José Reyes and Alou. After Wright walked, Green doubled off the left-field scoreboard, extending the Mets' lead to 5-2. Castro then lined a two-run homer that was hit so hard it ricocheted about 20 feet back onto the outfield grass.</p>
        <p>''I hope to keep doing what I'm doing,'' Castro said.</p>
        <p>By that point, Hernández was well into his rhythm. He struck out the side in the bottom of the third, then struck out two batters in each of the next two innings while allowing only one hit, a sixth-inning double to Aaron Boone. It was the first time Hernández had reached double digits in strikeouts since July 22, 2004, when he played for the Yankees.</p>
        <p>Thursday's lineup could be used for more than one game if Lo Duca continues feeling discomfort in his right index finger. He said he hoped that the one-day break would allow him to return Friday night. Even if he cannot, Beltrán, Green and Castro can, and that may be enough.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Nearly a week after the Jackie Robinson Day festivities were rained out, Willie Randolph will wear Robinson's No. 42 jersey on Friday night. The Mets decided to have Randolph be the lone person to wear No. 42 to dramatize his long relationship with the Robinson family, but he raised the idea Thursday that as many players and coaches who want to wear the jersey should be able to do so. But Jeff Wilpon, the Mets' senior executive vice president, repeated Thursday that Randolph, who grew up in Brooklyn, deserved to be the only one wearing No. 42. ''We believe that Willie -- as a person and leader, as a New Yorker and Brooklynite, as a family man -- embodies Jackie's nine ideals wonderfully articulated by his daughter Sharon,'' Wilpon said in a statement. ''Willie has a personal connection to Rachel Robinson and the Robinson family. For those reasons, we felt the singular focus of Willie wearing 42 would best represent the entire Mets organization in most appropriately honoring Jackie's enduring legacy.'' Florida's Miguel Cabrera left before the third inning with a stiff right torso.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
