<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Civil Unions Gain Ground As a Governor Vows Action</title>
    <meta content="20civil" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/us/20civil.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841588"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Hampshire</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">McKerney, Christy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belluck, Pam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lynch, John (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Hampshire</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Lynch, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E7D71F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="651" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Civil Unions Gain Ground As a Governor Vows Action</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Civil Unions Gain Ground as a Governor Vows Action</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAM BELLUCK; Christy McKerney contributed reporting from New Hampshire.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Belluck, Pam; McKerney, Christy</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, April 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Hampshire Gov John Lynch says he will sign bill legalizing civil unions for same-sex couples; measure would make New Hampshire fourth state to allow civil unions (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New Hampshire's governor said Thursday that he would sign a bill legalizing civil unions for same-sex couples.</p>
        <p>For weeks, the governor, John Lynch, declined to express his views on the civil union bill, which was passed by the House of Representatives and is expected to be passed by the Senate next week. Both chambers are controlled by Democrats for the first time in more than a century.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New Hampshire’s governor said Thursday that he would sign a bill legalizing civil unions for same-sex couples.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New Hampshire's governor said Thursday that he would sign a bill legalizing civil unions for same-sex couples.</p>
        <p>For weeks, the governor, John Lynch, declined to express his views on the civil union bill, which was passed by the House of Representatives and is expected to be passed by the Senate next week. Both chambers are controlled by Democrats for the first time in more than a century.</p>
        <p>The measure would make New Hampshire the fourth state to allow civil unions, following the lead of Vermont, Connecticut and New Jersey. California allows domestic partnerships with benefits similar to civil unions. Massachusetts is the only state that allows same-sex marriage.</p>
        <p>''It's a matter of conscience, of fairness and preventing discrimination,'' the governor, a Democrat, told reporters in Allenstown, N.H., according to his spokesman, Colin Manning.</p>
        <p>Mr. Manning said the governor opposed same-sex marriage, adding that ''the civil unions bill does extend the rights that married couples do enjoy -- hospital visitation, crime victims' rights, health insurance -- but at the same time it preserves the distinction of marriage.''</p>
        <p>Both opponents and proponents of the bill said they expected it would lead to efforts to establish same-sex marriage in New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>''This is a steppingstone for us,'' said Mo Baxley, executive director of the New Hampshire Freedom to Marry Coalition.</p>
        <p>Representative James R. Splaine, an openly gay Democrat who sponsored the bill, said: ''Essentially, it is a marriage without the word. People are going to see that couples in relationships will become more stable, that it's good for families, that it's good for society. Then I think in a year or two or three or four, the people of New Hampshire will say, 'Why not marriage with the word?' ''</p>
        <p>Senator Robert J. Letourneau, a Republican and an opponent of civil unions, said the law would ''bring unintended consequences of biblical proportions.''</p>
        <p>''It won't be long before schools will be required to teach alternative lifestyles,'' Mr. Letourneau said. ''You're going to have confrontations within churches. I don't have an issue with what people do with their private lives. This is about marriage, tradition. It's not about discrimination. It's about a minority of the population taking away something from the majority of the population that they don't want taken away from them.''</p>
        <p>Karen Testerman, executive director of Cornerstone Policy Research, a conservative group, citing AIDS and other sexually transmitted diseases, predicted that the law ''could promote the acceptance of a behavior that is jeopardizing the health of our children.''</p>
        <p>''Multiple partners when you're doing something unnatural -- it's just not good,'' Ms. Testerman said.</p>
        <p>Dawn Touzin, 56, of Windham, who works for Planned Parenthood, said she and her partner of eight years would join in civil union. ''In principle, we'd prefer marriage,'' Ms. Touzin said. ''But we've gone through a lot of effort trying to establish the legal protections that we might want for each other, yet no matter what you do you always fall short.''</p>
        <p>The law would recognize as civil unions same-sex marriages from other states or countries. Brian Rater, 37, a gay software engineer, lives in Brookline, just over the border from Massachusetts, where he is unable to marry because of that state's residency requirements. He said he and his partner would ''go to Canada and get a marriage license there and then have the marriage recognized as a civil union in New Hampshire.''</p>
        <p>New Hampshire residents seem to be divided on the issue.</p>
        <p>Michael Goyette, 36, who runs Pete's Gun and Tackle in Hudson, said: ''That's their way of life. I mean, hey. It's a personal thing. I just feel that marriage should be between a man and a woman.''</p>
        <p>Tim Chrysostom, 40, a restaurant worker from Canterbury, said that when Vermont became the first state to recognize civil unions, ''people were predicting terrible things would happen'' but that ''now everyone realizes they haven't.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
