<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On a Stunned Campus, Longing for the Normal But Enveloped by Grief</title>
    <meta content="20mood" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/us/20mood.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841644"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MASSACRE IN VIRGINIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Blacksburg (Va)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Banerjee, Neela</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cho, Seung-Hui</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Emotions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Emotions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cho Seung-Hui</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E3D61F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On a Stunned Campus, Longing for the Normal But Enveloped by Grief</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Shadow of a Tragedy, Longing for Normalcy but Enveloped by Grief</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEELA BANERJEE; Reporting was contributed by Sarah Abruzzese, John M. Broder, Shaila Dewan, Cate Doty, Bob Driehaus, Brenda Goodman, Choe Sang-Hun, Suevon Lee, Carolyn Marshall, Lori Moore, Haeyoun Park, William K. Rashbaum, Alicia C. Shepard and Archie Tse.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cho, Seung-Hui; Banerjee, Neela</byline>
      <dateline>BLACKSBURG, Va., April 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mood described on Virginia Tech campus following massacre by Cho Seung-Hui in which 32 people were killed; many students have gone home and may not be back for semester; most who remain are juniors and seniors who live off campus and long for familiar routine of classes, which resume Apr 23; some students lash out at news media, and many say they still support university administration, despite criticism from media and others about its handling of killings and Cho's mental health problems; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The heart of Virginia Tech was mostly empty.</p>
        <p>On the Drill Field, the vast green in the middle of campus, life flickered in small patches on Thursday, all of it in the shadow of Norris Hall, where Cho Seung-Hui killed 30 of his 32 victims on Monday before taking his own life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many students at Virginia Tech have begun to long for some move toward the familiar routine of classes, which are scheduled to resume on Monday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The heart of Virginia Tech was mostly empty.</p>
        <p>On the Drill Field, the vast green in the middle of campus, life flickered in small patches on Thursday, all of it in the shadow of Norris Hall, where Cho Seung-Hui killed 30 of his 32 victims on Monday before taking his own life.</p>
        <p>In the immediate aftermath of the massacre, there were vigils and crowds. Now many of the students have gone home, and some may not be back this semester. School officials said Thursday that they would let students finish the term with the grades they have now, should they choose.</p>
        <p>Most who remain are juniors and seniors who live off campus and who have begun to long for the familiar routine of classes, which are scheduled to resume on Monday.</p>
        <p>At the base of a stone wall on the field near Norris Hall, people have left flowers. Students came to the wall, read what some had written on boards propped against it, held one another and cried. Someone had set 32 small blocks of granite in a semicircle.</p>
        <p>Two young women walked around the Drill Field offering free hugs and Hershey's Kisses. Other women -- students, mothers -- accepted the hugs quietly.</p>
        <p>By Norris Hall, handmade signs read, ''VT Stay Strong, Media Stay Away.'' Families of the dead made their way inside past the yellow police tape around the building . Some left crying.</p>
        <p>A group of seven Amish men from Lancaster County, Pa., sat just outside the tape to pay their respects.</p>
        <p>''The world reached out to us during the killings in Nickel Mines,'' said a man who identified himself only as Michael, referring to the killing of five girls at an Amish schoolhouse there last October. ''We thought we would come and show our support as an expression of Christ's love.''</p>
        <p>Many students, largely those who live on campus, had gone home for the week.</p>
        <p>''My friend and I feel like we're the only ones in our dorm,'' said Natalie Lauby, 21. ''We walked across campus the other night and could count the lights that were still on.''</p>
        <p>Now open except for the crime scenes, the campus remained largely empty. Meredith Black, 21, said the campus still seemed ''kind of frightening.'' She added, ''There have been those bomb scares.''</p>
        <p>Those who had stayed came to the field and quietly made their way between large, whitewashed plywood boards that had been set up under a tent.</p>
        <p>On the boards, students and well-wishers wrote to those who had been killed and told of their grief. Many quoted the Bible, telling the dead they were in a better place. One message said: ''Gun reform now! Never again!'' On one new board, still largely empty, someone had written in a cramped script, ''Jesus wept and does.''</p>
        <p>The quiet field seemed a respite from the ubiquitous images of Mr. Cho.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday night, the news media began to broadcast and publish videos and photos of the gunman, which he had mailed to NBC News. Newsstands in town are splashed with his photos, and televisions in bars and restaurants are tuned to the seemingly endless loop of his videos.</p>
        <p>Most students had seen the videos, and along with their grief, they had begun to feel anger.</p>
        <p>''Emotions now are very different as things are getting released,'' said Rob Williams, 20, whose friend, Caitlin Hammaren, was killed. ''At the convocation and vigil, it was very sad, and then there was this sense of happiness because we were becoming united as one. But now with the videos, people are angry.''</p>
        <p>Some said they were angry at the media for showing the videos without much warning. Others felt frustrated that the videos revealed so little about why Mr. Cho embarked on his rampage.</p>
        <p>''The only way they might have helped in some way is that they showed how disturbed he was, that he wasn't like everyone else, like some person who just snapped,'' Ms. Black said.</p>
        <p>Students also said they still supported the university administration, despite criticism from the news media and others about its handling of the killings and of Mr. Cho's mental health problems.</p>
        <p>''No one I know is placing any blame on the university for how they have done things,'' Mr. Williams said. ''I don't think we should be blamed for not kicking him out for odd behavior, because if you went by that, there would be people kicked out every day. No one could have predicted what he did.''</p>
        <p>Students also said they were nervous about the resumption of classes next Monday. Would there be endless discussion about the killings? Would there be copycat threats?</p>
        <p>Some would probably not return.</p>
        <p>''I have a friend with a very troubled daughter who heard the gunshots and doesn't want to come back,'' said Diane Morrison of Winchester, Va., whose daughter, Maggie, is a freshman. ''Some really need to be here for closure but for her, it's too much.''</p>
        <p>But others said they hungered for some kind of normalcy after first the terror, and then the silence of this week.</p>
        <p>''If I had gone home, I would be with other kids from different schools, and I wanted to be with people who were experiencing the same thing as me,'' said Nathan Knotts, 21. ''Usually, the campus is really bustling, so it will be nice to see people again.''</p>
        <p>His friend, Laurence O'Neill, 22, said, ''I'm ready to go back to class.''</p>
        <p>Returning, said Barrett Clark, a senior, would mean that the university was starting to heal.</p>
        <p>''Life will go on at some point,'' Mr. Clark said. ''We will get back on our feet.''</p>
        <p>MASSACRE IN VIRGINIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
