<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mom Goes Shopping for a Shiny New Gun</title>
    <meta content="20wife" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/arts/television/20wife.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841531"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Stewart, Susan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E1DB1F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="574" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mom Goes Shopping for a Shiny New Gun</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mom Goes Shopping for a Shiny New Gun</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN STEWART</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stewart, Susan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Wife, Mom, Bounty Hunter,'' which makes its debut on the WE network tonight, is the third reality show about bounty hunters in recent years. (''Human Bonds'' had a 10-episode run on HBO in 2004, and ''Dog the Bounty Hunter'' is going strong on A&amp;E.) If this keeps up, there may be more TV bounty hunters than criminals.</p>
        <p>Maybe these breathless portrayals of strapping, tough-talking law enforcers are the new westerns. More likely, they're the new sitcoms. ''Wife'' doesn't have a laugh track, but it offers a motley crew of characters making fools of themselves without realizing it. Sometimes the situations are farcical; many end with hugging and learning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The WE’s reality show, which features a motherly bounty hunter who apprehends scofflaws by day and takes care of her family by night, is short on action and interesting characters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Wife, Mom, Bounty Hunter,'' which makes its debut on the WE network tonight, is the third reality show about bounty hunters in recent years. (''Human Bonds'' had a 10-episode run on HBO in 2004, and ''Dog the Bounty Hunter'' is going strong on A&amp;E.) If this keeps up, there may be more TV bounty hunters than criminals.</p>
        <p>Maybe these breathless portrayals of strapping, tough-talking law enforcers are the new westerns. More likely, they're the new sitcoms. ''Wife'' doesn't have a laugh track, but it offers a motley crew of characters making fools of themselves without realizing it. Sometimes the situations are farcical; many end with hugging and learning.</p>
        <p>Even when things get gritty, ''Wife'' has the potential for uplift. No matter how bad your day was, it probably didn't involve handcuffs and a pat-down. Some TV we watch to feel good about ourselves.</p>
        <p>Sandra Scott, a former professional wrestler, is a suburban Phoenix bounty hunter who apprehends scofflaws by day and takes care of her family by night. She mothers everybody. A teenage fugitive gets a hamburger and a lecture on the way to jail, and Sandra's husband, Ron, a video game fanatic 11 years her junior, gets a lesson on ordering steak in a restaurant. The children are 15-year-old Sabree, preoccupied with cheerleading and hair care, and 6-year-old Ever-Skye, who splits her time between the Scotts' tract house and her father's home in California.</p>
        <p>If the Scotts were richer, they could be in the cast of ''The Real Housewives of Orange County,'' with whom they share a tank-top wardrobe and flashy, characterless décor. Ms. Scott sees herself as a girl who likes to have fun. Early on, she and her fellow bounty hunter Theresa go shopping, and not for Capri pants.</p>
        <p>''Some girls like shopping for clothes, some like shoes, and we like guns,'' she says, trying out a sporty revolver. In her hands it seems as innocuous as a pair of espadrilles.</p>
        <p>Ms. Scott's days, at least in the first three episodes, are not exactly pulse-pounding. Among the bail violators she brings to justice -- or at least to jail -- are a frightened young girl and an apparent methamphetamine addict who tells jokes while handcuffed in the back of a car.</p>
        <p>There's a moment of tension when Ms. Scott and her team enter a house, guns at the ready, to flush out a fugitive. He turns out to be seriously ill.</p>
        <p>In an era of shocking gun violence, it seems wrong to criticize a television series for not being brutal enough. And the producers removed a scene showing Ms. Scott and her partners at a firing range in deference to this week's events in Blacksburg, Va. Still, ''Wife'' could use a little more action.</p>
        <p>The real energy here is psychological. Everybody has a story or, at least, an excuse. The meth addict, handcuffed and flanked by Ms. Scott's behemoth partners, offers hers: ''My intentions are good, but I have stress disorder.''</p>
        <p>A few minutes later Ms. Scott catches her husband without his wedding ring. His excuse: ''I work with nine-volt batteries.''</p>
        <p>Huh? There are clear fault lines in the Scott household. Unless the criminals get more interesting, expect the family to erupt, and to be fully exploited.</p>
        <p>Wife, Mom, Bounty Hunter  WE, tonight at 9, Eastern and Pacific times; 8, Central time.</p>
        <p>Produced by World of Wonder; Randy Barbato and Fenton Bailey, executive producers; Kevin Leadingham, supervising producer.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
