<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lawyer Says Tip That May Have Aided Skakel Came After Murder Conviction</title>
    <meta content="20skakel" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/nyregion/20skakel.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841653"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Greenwich (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Skakel, Michael C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moxley, Martha (1960-75)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bryant, Gitano</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowan, Alison Leigh</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Skakel, Michael</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Moxley, Martha</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E2D61F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lawyer Says Tip That May Have Aided Skakel Came After Murder Conviction</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lawyer Says Tip That May Have Aided Skakel Came After Murder Conviction</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON LEIGH COWAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowan, Alison Leigh</byline>
      <dateline>STAMFORD, Conn., April 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael C Skakel's former lawyer, Mickey Sherman, tells court he was not given information until after 2002 murder trial that might have spared Skakel from being convicted of 1975 killing of Martha Moxley in Greenwich, Conn; says he learned name of former classmate of Skakel's, Gitano Bryant, who has since furnished evidence pointing to other possible culprits, one month after conviction; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With his former client sitting a few feet away, Michael C. Skakel's former lawyer, Mickey Sherman, told a court on Thursday that he was not given information until after the 2002 murder trial that might have spared Mr. Skakel from being convicted in the 1975 killing of Martha Moxley in Greenwich.</p>
        <p>Taking the stand in a civil proceeding that will determine whether Mr. Skakel, 46, is entitled to a new trial, Mr. Sherman said he learned the name of Gitano Bryant, a former classmate of Mr. Skakel's, in July 2002, one month after Mr. Skakel was convicted. Mr. Bryant has since furnished evidence pointing to other possible culprits. Mr. Sherman said Jonathan Benedict, the lead prosecutor at the murder trial, ''dropped me a note saying, 'Got a tip. It's going to be the first of many we're going to be getting in the future.' ''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>STAMFORD, Conn., April 19  With his former client sitting a few feet away, Michael C. Skakel’s former lawyer, Mickey Sherman, told a court on Thursday that he was not given information until after the 2002 murder trial that might have spared Mr. Skakel from being convicted in the 1975 killing of Martha Moxley in Greenwich.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With his former client sitting a few feet away, Michael C. Skakel's former lawyer, Mickey Sherman, told a court on Thursday that he was not given information until after the 2002 murder trial that might have spared Mr. Skakel from being convicted in the 1975 killing of Martha Moxley in Greenwich.</p>
        <p>Taking the stand in a civil proceeding that will determine whether Mr. Skakel, 46, is entitled to a new trial, Mr. Sherman said he learned the name of Gitano Bryant, a former classmate of Mr. Skakel's, in July 2002, one month after Mr. Skakel was convicted. Mr. Bryant has since furnished evidence pointing to other possible culprits. Mr. Sherman said Jonathan Benedict, the lead prosecutor at the murder trial, ''dropped me a note saying, 'Got a tip. It's going to be the first of many we're going to be getting in the future.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sherman also testified that the local authorities had failed to provide him with several documents that could have been valuable at trial, including two suspect profiles, time-lapse data and a police sketch.</p>
        <p>On cross-examination Mr. Benedict elicited from Mr. Sherman that much of the information in those documents was contained in other materials that Mr. Sherman did receive. Mr. Benedict also noted that the presiding judge had rebuffed Mr. Sherman's efforts to obtain at least two of the documents at trial.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Sherman insisted that he could have made use of it all, especially comments in one suspect profile signed by two former police investigators stating that ''it has been established that'' Mr. Skakel had left the area in a car with three relatives about 9:30 p.m. on Oct. 30, 1975, the night the police say Ms. Moxley was beaten to death with a golf club.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sherman said jurors accepted his findings about the estimated time of death, but discounted Mr. Skakel's alibi, thinking perhaps that his relatives ''were biased.''</p>
        <p>''Had I had this, I could have put on and cross-examined'' the report's writers to show that some law enforcement officials had other conclusions, Mr. Sherman said. Other materials, he said, could have been used to convince the jury that there was reasonable doubt of guilt.</p>
        <p>On cross-examination, Mr. Sherman also said he believed that he shared the tip involving Mr. Bryant's name with Hope C. Seeley and Hubert J. Santos, Mr. Skakel's appellate lawyers, but could not offer proof. Mr. Bryant ultimately told Mr. Skakel's current legal team that two friends of his had talked about getting a local girl ''caveman-style.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sherman acknowledged having been contacted before the trial by the same person who furnished Mr. Bryant's name, a screenwriter who had attended the same prep school as Mr. Skakel and Mr. Bryant, but said he did not think his information was of interest at the time. ''It was about somehow pushing a script called 'Little Martha,' and it wasn't something I was interested in,'' Mr. Sherman said.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Skakel to get a new trial based on newly discovered evidence, the information has to have been unavailable at trial and likely to change the outcome. He is serving a sentence of 20 years to life.</p>
        <p>The proceeding is expected to continue through next week, and both sides are likely to file post-hearing briefs before Judge Edward R. Karazin Jr. of Connecticut Superior Court rules on the case.</p>
        <p>Outside the courtroom, Ms. Seeley and Mr. Santos said that even if they prevailed, their client might not be released right away.</p>
        <p>If their bid for a new trial falls short, they are widely expected to argue -- with the blessing of at least one member of the Skakel family, Robert F. Kennedy Jr. -- that Mr. Skakel was deprived of effective counsel at his trial.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
