<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Sharp Turn for the Supreme Court on Abortion</title>
    <meta content="l20abortion" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841617"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E0D71F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="977" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Sharp Turn for the Supreme Court on Abortion</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''In Reversal of Course, Justices, 5-4, Back Ban on Abortion Method'' (front page, April 19):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''In Reversal of Course, Justices, 5-4, Back Ban on Abortion Method'' (front page, April 19):</p>
        <p>The Supreme Court decision on Wednesday is a stunning assault on women's health and rights. Callously disregarding 30 years of precedent -- as well as the core tenets of Roe v. Wade -- the Supreme Court decided to play doctor, and women's health now lies in the balance.</p>
        <p>Americans should be outraged that the Supreme Court turned women's health concerns over to politicians, as they inserted themselves into our most private medical decisions.</p>
        <p>Joan Malin  President and Chief Executive  Planned Parenthood of New York City  New York, April 19, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Here's what Wednesday's Supreme Court decision means to me and my patients:</p>
        <p>Now, when I want to act in my patient's best interest, I must stop and call a lawyer to find out what I'm permitted to do under the law or face federal prosecution.</p>
        <p>Now, when my patient trusts me to do what's best and safest for her health, I must tell her that my hands are tied by justices who have put ideology above scientific evidence.</p>
        <p>Now, when I sit talking to my patient, a little voice at my ear will tell me that politicians know best.</p>
        <p>Now, when I work in my office and my operating room, I will wonder who's a potential informant.</p>
        <p>This ruling insidiously injects government into the personal decisions a woman makes with her physician. It is an insult to a woman's right to protect her own health and to a physician's ability to advise her.</p>
        <p>Deborah Oyer, M.D.  Boston, April 19, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is a board member of the National Abortion Federation.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The term ''partial-birth abortion'' is called a ''provocative'' alternate label for the presumably more descriptive ''intact dilation and extraction'' (front page, April 19). But if anything obscures the actual nature of the procedure at issue, it is the latter jargon.</p>
        <p>What the federal Partial-Birth Abortion Ban Act prohibits is puncturing the brain of a baby whose head or most of whose body has emerged into the world.</p>
        <p>Most reasonable people, I suspect, would likely concur with the position of Jewish law here and consider that act to constitute not abortion at all, but, in effect, infanticide.</p>
        <p>(Rabbi) Avi Shafran  Director of Public Affairs  Agudath Israel of America  New York, April 19, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The Supreme Court's opinion in Gonzales v. Carhart upholding the Partial-Birth Abortion Ban Act is beyond belief. The court acknowledges that there is medical support for the position that the procedure at issue, intact dilation and extraction, is sometimes necessary to protect the health of the mother. It goes on to hold that the government can put a doctor in jail if he performs that procedure.</p>
        <p>This ruling puts the few doctors willing to perform abortions in an impossible position. In the rare situation where a doctor determines in his best medical judgment that a dilation and extraction is the safest procedure for his patient, how is the doctor to choose between obeying the law and respecting his personal and professional commitment to protect the health of his patient?</p>
        <p>For a doctor who confronts that dilemma, it will surely be cold comfort that the court has left the door open for an ''as applied'' challenge to the law.</p>
        <p>Emily Rubin  Hanover, N.H., April 19, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer, a lawyer, is a student at Dartmouth Medical School.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Denying the Right to Choose'' (editorial, April 19):</p>
        <p>I was most anxious this morning to obtain a copy of The Times in order to read the predictably apoplectic editorial regarding the Supreme Court decision upholding the ban on what was described by the late pro-choice Daniel Patrick Moynihan as ''infanticide.''</p>
        <p>I was not in the least disappointed: ''fundamental dishonesty,'' ''atrocious result,'' ''so-called partial-birth method'' and so on. As I read and reread your wail of dismay, I looked for, and couldn't find, the words baby, human life or even fetus.</p>
        <p>You are upset that the court finally made the observation that pregnancy involves two persons, even if one of them lost legal standing under Roe's tortured discovery of a right that had somehow failed to be noticed for 200 years.</p>
        <p>Lawrence Longua  Rockville Centre, N.Y.  April 19, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>After choosing to outlaw a procedure that is sometimes necessary to save a woman's life, Justice Anthony M. Kennedy, writing for the majority, actually says one reason for the decision is to protect women from their own ignorance about how they will feel after they have the procedure.</p>
        <p>Don't miss what he is saying: A woman is incapable of choosing what is in her best interests, and the law must protect her from herself. This is sexism.</p>
        <p>If you didn't understand why choice is about women's rights, there is no clearer example.</p>
        <p>Jennifer Rolnick  New York, April 19, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I applaud the Supreme Court ruling that upheld the Partial-Birth Abortion Ban Act that Congress passed and President Bush signed into law. A horrific abuse of Roe v. Wade, this procedure crushed the skulls of late-term infants after they were partially born.</p>
        <p>The conscience of our culture could no longer allow such a barbaric practice to remain legal.</p>
        <p>Bonnie O'Neil  Newport Beach, Calif.  April 19, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The bottom line is that Wednesday's Supreme Court decision values the potential life of a fetus over that of a woman. This is a profoundly troubling fact.</p>
        <p>Aviva Briefel  Brunswick, Me., April 19, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>This Supreme Court decision will rank with the Dred Scott decision, so thoroughly mistaken as to be a landmark.</p>
        <p>George E. Ehrlich,  M.D.  Philadelphia, April 19, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
