<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Art in Review; Lee Bontecou</title>
    <meta content="20gall-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841627"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEFD71F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="465" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Art in Review; Lee Bontecou</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Roberta</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vacuum-Formed Sculptures and Related Drawings  Knoedler &amp; Company  19 East 70th Street, Manhattan  Through April 28</p>
        <p>Sometimes I think Lee Bontecou's industrious, disciplined career has unfolded in reverse. Her trajectory should have started with the giddy, broochlike, exploding-eye sculptures seen in the final displays of her 2004 retrospective at the Museum of Modern Art. And the glowering black-and-gray canvas reliefs that established her reputation in the early 1960s could easily be the deepening, crowning achievements of a life's work, like Mozart's Requiem or Beethoven's Ninth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vacuum-Formed Sculptures and Related Drawings  Knoedler &amp; Company  19 East 70th Street, Manhattan  Through April 28</p>
        <p>Sometimes I think Lee Bontecou's industrious, disciplined career has unfolded in reverse. Her trajectory should have started with the giddy, broochlike, exploding-eye sculptures seen in the final displays of her 2004 retrospective at the Museum of Modern Art. And the glowering black-and-gray canvas reliefs that established her reputation in the early 1960s could easily be the deepening, crowning achievements of a life's work, like Mozart's Requiem or Beethoven's Ninth.</p>
        <p>Either way, the middle phase would be the efforts isolated in this exhibition: the menacing fish and vigilant, thick-stalked flowers made of vacuum-formed transparent plastic. Using a new technique that she helped perfect, Ms. Bontecou turned to these works in the late 1960s after regular visits to the country renewed her fascination with nature.</p>
        <p>They were exhibited in 1971 at the Leo Castelli Gallery; the unenthusiastic critical response is often cited as one reason Ms. Bontecou withdrew from the New York art world to live full time in western Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>The plastic fish and flowers signal a retreat from the power and unity of the groundbreaking reliefs and a growing involvement with material, technique and details for their own sake rather than as means to a larger, more complex statement. Sure, they can have a nice theatrical effect: at times the see-through, often-suspended forms create an unsettling aqueous wonderland, inhabited by crustaceous creatures that seem both physically correct and exaggerated.</p>
        <p>I also like the way the armed-and-dangerous sinisterness of the canvas reliefs informs the seemingly beatific aura of the flowers.</p>
        <p>Shared DNA with Ms. Bontecou's other work abounds, as do signs of future developments elsewhere. Frank Gehry's fish lamps and Jeff Koons's and Takashi Murakami's use of flowers come to mind, as do several Pixar characters.</p>
        <p>But it is the bits and pieces that hold the eye: the way, for example, the parts of the fish are layered and screwed together. The wholes are too much like toys or models, or, as with the fastidious drawings included here, an overly familiar form of Surrealism. Craft and detail are even more dominant in the recent, broochlike pieces.</p>
        <p>Perhaps Ms. Bontecou moved so fast at the beginning of her career that she had to retrace her steps. I remember being taken aback at the MoMA show by the conservative animal sculptures that Ms. Bontecou was making in 1957, only two years before she concocted her first reliefs.</p>
        <p>In technique and sentimentality, these sculptures suggested the dubious Leonard Baskin; they made the canvas reliefs look like a sudden leap that might not have been quite earned, or stable. Perhaps that is why it can seem that Ms. Bontecou has been shoring up their foundations ever since.</p>
        <p>ROBERTA SMITH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
