<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Mixed-Up Son of 'The Graduate'</title>
    <meta content="20wome" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/movies/20wome.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841544"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kasdan, Jonathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brody, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ryan, Meg</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stewart, Kristen</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">In the Land of Women (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Kasdan, Jonathan</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">In the Land of Women (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E7DA1F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="668" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Mixed-Up Son of 'The Graduate'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Mixed-Up Son of ‘The Graduate’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews film In the Land of Women, written and directed by Jonathan Kasdan; Adam Brody, Meg Ryan and Kristen Stewart star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The meek, mopey comedy ''In the Land of Women'' is the film equivalent of a sensitive emo band with one foot in alternative rock and the other in the squishy pop mainstream: a softer, fuzzier ''Garden State.'' Like Zach Braff's Andrew Largeman in that movie, Adam Brody's character, Carter Webb, in ''Land of Women'' is a sensitive mixed-up kid, although at 26 he is hardly a kid. An aspiring screenwriter in Los Angeles who has spent years working on a still-unfinished screenplay about his high school days, he makes his living writing soft-core pornography. His life comes apart when his girlfriend Sofia (Elena Anaya), an attractive young movie star, unexpectedly breaks up with him because she ''wants space.'' Carter flees to Michigan to visit his ailing grandmother, Phyllis (Olympia Dukakis).</p>
        <p>Most of the movie's scattered chortles are generated by remarks from this scowling, death-obsessed termagant whose grouchy shtick becomes a running joke that is quickly milked dry. Phyllis is waiting around to die and wants everyone within earshot to know.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The meek, mopey comedy “In the Land of Women” is the film equivalent of a sensitive emo band with one foot in alternative rock and the other in the squishy pop mainstream.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The meek, mopey comedy ''In the Land of Women'' is the film equivalent of a sensitive emo band with one foot in alternative rock and the other in the squishy pop mainstream: a softer, fuzzier ''Garden State.'' Like Zach Braff's Andrew Largeman in that movie, Adam Brody's character, Carter Webb, in ''Land of Women'' is a sensitive mixed-up kid, although at 26 he is hardly a kid. An aspiring screenwriter in Los Angeles who has spent years working on a still-unfinished screenplay about his high school days, he makes his living writing soft-core pornography. His life comes apart when his girlfriend Sofia (Elena Anaya), an attractive young movie star, unexpectedly breaks up with him because she ''wants space.'' Carter flees to Michigan to visit his ailing grandmother, Phyllis (Olympia Dukakis).</p>
        <p>Most of the movie's scattered chortles are generated by remarks from this scowling, death-obsessed termagant whose grouchy shtick becomes a running joke that is quickly milked dry. Phyllis is waiting around to die and wants everyone within earshot to know.</p>
        <p>Carter is a much less interesting character than his creator, Jonathan Kasdan (son of Lawrence Kasdan, the director of ''The Big Chill''), seems to imagine. And as the movie ambles along in fits and starts, Mr. Kasdan, who is making his directorial debut, appears to dote on this reasonably likable but nebulous young man played with an earnest low-key likability by Mr. Brody (''The O.C.'').</p>
        <p>Like ''Garden State,'' ''In the Land of Women'' has strong ties to ''The Graduate,'' the prototype for every modern portrait of a suburban lost boy with yet-to-be-realized career promise. As Carter flaps around morosely trying to find himself, he is considerably less compelling than Mr. Braff's Andrew or Dustin Hoffman's Benjamin.</p>
        <p>As in ''The Graduate,'' Carter finds himself involved with a mother and daughter who live next door. The mother, Sarah Hardwicke (Meg Ryan taking her first cautious baby steps in a maternal, older-woman mode and maintaining her footing), has just been told she has breast cancer. Adding to her woes is her knowledge that her husband, Nelson (Clark Gregg), is having an affair and her estrangement from Lucy (Kristen Stewart), the older of her two daughters.</p>
        <p>Carter and Sarah meet by chance and begin taking long morning walks. During one she confides in Carter about her illness, and he impulsively instigates a steamy kiss. Earlier Sarah had urged Lucy to ask Carter for a date. She does, and Carter becomes her confidant, unofficial life coach in dating etiquette and surrogate older brother. After he squires her to a high school party where trouble breaks out, Lucy kisses him, and he finds himself in a sticky situation. If the movie is good at putting the petty melodramas of high school life in perspective, its treatment of grown-up relationships is so spineless that its predominant mood is one of mild depression.</p>
        <p>Coy to a fault, ''In the Land of Women'' refuses to connect dots that need to be joined. Although Nelson's extramarital affair is stated as fact, the guilty party acts like a devoted, caring husband, and no whys or wherefores are provided. We are given no clues as to whether either kiss leads to more, although the answer is probably not. Which leaves ''In the Land of Women'' in a void of indecision and hesitancy.</p>
        <p>''In the Land of Women'' is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some strong language.</p>
        <p>In the Land of Women  Opens today nationwide.</p>
        <p>Written and directed by Jonathan Kasdan; director of photography, Paul Cameron; edited by Carol Littleton; music by Stephen Trask; production designer, Sandy Cochrane; produced by Steve Golin and David Kanter; released by Warner Brothers Pictures and Castle Rock Entertainment. Running time: 98 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Adam Brody (Carter Webb), Kristen Stewart (Lucy Hardwicke), Meg Ryan (Sarah Hardwicke), Olympia Dukakis (Phyllis), Makenzie Vega (Paige Hardwicke), Elena Anaya (Sofia Buñuel), Clark Gregg (Nelson Hardwicke), JoBeth Williams (Agnes Webb), Dustin Milligan (Eric Watts) and Ginnifer Goodwin (Janey).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
