<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Classical Treasures, Bathed in a New Light</title>
    <meta content="20anci" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/arts/design/20anci.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841510"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roman Civilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roman Civilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Metropolitan Museum of Art</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E5DB1F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1518" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Classical Treasures, Bathed in a New Light</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Classical Treasures, Bathed in a New Light</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL KIMMELMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kimmelman, Michael</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The other day, apropos of the Metropolitan Museum's fine, new light-washed galleries for Greek and Roman art, a friend e-mailed to me a passage by Virgil. In it Aeneas, fleeing the Trojan War, arrives in Carthage and finds a temple for Juno under construction. He pushes open the temple's big bronze doors (''which made the hinges groan,'' Virgil reports) and ''for the first time he dared to hope for life.'' He's astounded by the skill of the craftsmen and by the nobility and precision of a painting of the war. He starts to cry.</p>
        <p>''It was only a picture, but, sighing deeply, he let his thoughts feed on it, and his face was wet with a stream of tears,'' Virgil writes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Western antiquity now unfolds in logical, stately order at the Metropolitan Museum’s Greek and Roman galleries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The other day, apropos of the Metropolitan Museum's fine, new light-washed galleries for Greek and Roman art, a friend e-mailed to me a passage by Virgil. In it Aeneas, fleeing the Trojan War, arrives in Carthage and finds a temple for Juno under construction. He pushes open the temple's big bronze doors (''which made the hinges groan,'' Virgil reports) and ''for the first time he dared to hope for life.'' He's astounded by the skill of the craftsmen and by the nobility and precision of a painting of the war. He starts to cry.</p>
        <p>''It was only a picture, but, sighing deeply, he let his thoughts feed on it, and his face was wet with a stream of tears,'' Virgil writes.</p>
        <p>The power of ancient art has to do with its ability, as my friend put it, ''to embody great acts and communicate their human dimension.'' Rome became the model for Western culture from the Renaissance through the Enlightenment.</p>
        <p>I'm not sure exactly when its pre-eminence began to fade, but in 1949 a young, populist Met director named Francis Henry Taylor decided to turn the Roman court, the literal and symbolic climax of the building's southern wing, into a restaurant, which devolved into a cafeteria. Plenty of New Yorkers grew up learning from this arrangement that eating a nutted cheese sandwich at Chock full o'Nuts before going to the museum was a thriftier option than buying a tuna sandwich once you got there.</p>
        <p>It was a life lesson, just not the kind that Virgil wrote about.</p>
        <p>Fortunately, now, beside the humongous column from the Temple of Artemis at Sardis, which marked the entrance to the cafeteria, where mobs used to crane their necks looking not like Aeneas for hope and inspiration but for the beef stew, you can instead gaze up at huge architectural fragments from the same temple, including one with the sort of egg-and-dart molding that inspired the Met's facade by Richard Morris Hunt.</p>
        <p>Like countless public institutions in America, the Met aped Rome because Rome stood for civic order, empire and reason. Greek and Roman art weren't the only historic arts of consequence, a lesson the museum taught long before it became fashionable to disparage classical culture. But Rome was a standard against which to measure other cultures, including our own.</p>
        <p>Western artists always had, from Michelangelo, who aspired to equal the Belvedere torso, to Picasso, whose ''Woman in White'' at the Met is unimaginable without classical art. Going from the Greek and Roman galleries to the Picasso is something you can only do there. Willem de Kooning and Arshile Gorky used to haunt these galleries during the 1930s and '40s and loved the Pompeiian frescoes, whose influence you can see in their works, not far away.</p>
        <p>Those frescoes, from luxurious ancient villas on the Bay of Naples, have been cleaned and moved from the museum lobby, where tourists used to mistake them for the coat-check concession. They are reinstalled next to the Roman court, where they look magnificent. I hadn't noticed until lately all the phalluses on the rooftops of the fantasy buildings, painted in cinnabar and blue, which decorate the murals from a bedroom buried by Vesuvius. The opulence of these scenes suggests something of what inspired Aeneas.</p>
        <p>The court, with its burbling fountain, is the centerpiece of the new galleries, which officially open today, and it's a terrific gift to New York, a vast, skylighted, airy new public space, chilly with all the newly scrubbed marble and naked light but aptly lofty.</p>
        <p>It would be wrong to say that everything on view is wonderful. There are garden-variety sculptures from Roman baths and archaeological fragments more meaningful to specialists than to the rest of us, along with imperial portrait busts, funerary reliefs and the Badminton sarcophagus, whose reputation belies the fact that it's a bit over the top. The Met's Greek and Roman collection is enormous but not like the collections in Athens, Rome, Naples, London, Paris or Berlin, built around stupendous masterworks.</p>
        <p>You can say, though, that it tells the whole story. With the Greek galleries, finished eight years ago, Western antiquity from the Bronze Age through the reign of Constantine now unfolds in logical, stately order, as was intended from the museum's early days. Thousands of objects have been exhumed from storage (it's about time) and animated by new touch-screen computers (useful up to a point) and by air and sun.</p>
        <p>In total there are 57,000 square feet of exhibition space for classical antiquity, around 30,000 for Rome alone, equivalent to all the galleries at the Whitney Museum combined. You can exit Rome into African art then go directly into modern art, which depended on both Rome and Africa for utterly different ideas about the human body.</p>
        <p>That itinerary, richly detailed and arrived at over the years as the Met evolved, argues strongly for the universal museum -- the encyclopedic collection, modeled after Diderot -- a concept lately assaulted by lawyers, archaeologists and advocates of nationalism.</p>
        <p>I'm with the philosopher Kwame Anthony Appiah on this score. Looted art, proved as stolen, must be repatriated. But only in a narrow legal sense does patrimony necessarily belong to modern states occupying lands where ancient cultures once were. The Taliban demonstrated how dubious that claim may be when they blew up the Bamiyan Buddhas in Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>Respect for other cultures can come not just from returning an object to where it came from but also from ''holding onto it because you value it yourself,'' Mr. Appiah has written. My epistolary friend sent me a second e-mail message. In 1430, he pointed out, the Italian humanist and book hunter Poggio Bracciolini acquired some Greek sculptures by the great Polyclitus and Praxiteles. A head of Bacchus, Bracciolini told a fellow classical devotee, ''ought to feel grand, for if he deserves lodging anywhere it is certainly in my country, where he is particularly worshiped.'' Bracciolini even enlisted Donatello to check out his Greek collection.</p>
        <p>The point is that objects have one meaning to those who made them, others to those who find or buy them centuries later, and yet other meanings for those who come upon them in a museum. Their different careers ensure immortality. Rising nationalism is an alarming trend as far as this goes. Archeologists who now argue that antiquities are better served in the dirt where they came from than dispersed among public museums like the Met imply that they prefer the past remain dead and buried. The last thing Italy needs today is another Roman vase.</p>
        <p>Philippe de Montebello, the Met director, has often described his museum as a ''cultural family tree in which every visitor can find his roots.'' True enough, notwithstanding the implicit imperialism. The legacy of Rome is shared by countless people who go to the museum, and not just by modern-day Italians.</p>
        <p>Fulfilling a plan initiated by his predecessor, Thomas Hoving, Mr. de Montebello has done the Met and the city -- and everybody -- incalculable good by pushing through this project, which in so many ways goes against the grain. It's not about celebrity architecture. It's not politically correct. The timing is awful, since so much attention is focused on looting. But it is about reiterating an ideal for art and for the museum, about extolling the collection, which is the public's heritage, seen by millions, and about doing the hard thing because it is right.</p>
        <p>Did I fail to mention the art? Well, virtue before pleasure, since Rome has been the subject. Here are a couple of works in the new galleries you might overlook, then you can take it from there.The Etruscan collection on the mezzanine, one of the best in the world, with the famous chariot lately restored, is splendid, but tucked away in the back is a tiny miracle of antique carving, a chunk of glowing amber, that is easy to miss. It's in the shape of a man and woman entwined. He reclines beside her, holding her in his arms. She's reclining too, wearing a pointy hat and holding a small vase in one hand, gently touching its mouth with her other hand, as if about to pour something perhaps. Maybe it's a love potion. Shades of Tristan and Isolde.</p>
        <p>And in what's called the Hellenistic Treasury, there's a figurine of a dancer wearing a mask. It's a small bronze sculpture, not nine inches tall, the Isadora Duncan of ancient Alexandria. Draped in layers, she twists like a corkscrew, her body -- the curve of her back, her buttocks and muscled thighs -- outlined by the taut fabric. The thinnest veil hides her face, and her head tilts discreetly behind one shoulder, a slippered foot emerging, suggestively, from beneath her robes.</p>
        <p>She's all virtuosity and grace. You can detect in sculptures by Matisse and Richard Serra the influence of her torqued, complicated eloquence, transformed and transmuted through intermediaries like Borromini and Canova.</p>
        <p>If you want to know why Greek and Roman art matters eternally, she's your answer.</p>
        <p>The new Greek and Roman galleries open today at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
