<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>S.I. Businesswoman's Killing in Panama Is a Tangled Tale</title>
    <meta content="20murder" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/nyregion/20murder.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841622"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Panama</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abrams, Toni Gross</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ridgley, Debra Ann</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newman, Andy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Panama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Staten Island (NYC)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Panama</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07EFD71F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1281" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>S.I. Businesswoman's Killing in Panama Is a Tangled Tale</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">S.I. Businesswoman’s Killing in Panama Is a Tangled Tale</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDY NEWMAN; Daryl Khan, Sean Hamill and R. M. Koster contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Newman, Andy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Body of Toni Grossi Abrams, widow and Staten Island socialite, is found in warehouse on outskirts of Panama City, Panama, where she had moved to begin career in real estate; Debra Ann Ridgley, one of her tenants, is charged with stabbing Abrams to death in her apartment on April 9; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Toni Grossi Abrams was looking for something new.</p>
        <p>The widow of a mortgage executive, Ms. Abrams was something of a force of nature in Staten Island society. Flamboyant and glamorous, generous and eccentric and at times antagonistic, a tireless fund-raiser and a hardheaded businesswoman, she turned up at charity events and preservation meetings. But she wanted to make her own fortune.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prosecutors said the death in Panama of a flamboyant and glamorous Staten Islander appears to have started with a soured relationship between the victim and her tenant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Toni Grossi Abrams was looking for something new.</p>
        <p>The widow of a mortgage executive, Ms. Abrams was something of a force of nature in Staten Island society. Flamboyant and glamorous, generous and eccentric and at times antagonistic, a tireless fund-raiser and a hardheaded businesswoman, she turned up at charity events and preservation meetings. But she wanted to make her own fortune.</p>
        <p>''She wanted to build an estate so that she was independent,'' said her longtime friend Terry Phalen, ''and she wanted to have fun with it.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Abrams found what she was after in Panama, where in recent years many Americans have been drawn by the nightlife, the inexpensive cosmetic surgery, and the low cost of retirement. After buying and remodeling several properties, Ms. Abrams planned to build a retreat where surgery patients could lie low in style while their new faces healed, Ms. Phalen said.</p>
        <p>But last week, Ms. Abrams was murdered. Her remains were discovered beside a warehouse at the edge of a cinder-topped soccer field on the outskirts of Panama City. She had been stabbed to death in her apartment, cut into pieces, stuffed into a suitcase and set afire, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>Only one person has been charged in her death so far: one of her tenants, an American woman who would seem to have much in common with Ms. Abrams.</p>
        <p>The suspect, Debra Ann Ridgley, is, as Ms. Abrams was, a 56-year-old native of the Pittsburgh area. She, too, went to Panama for a fresh start of sorts. After getting a face-lift in Florida, she flew to Panama to recover, joined by her father and teenage granddaughter.</p>
        <p>A few weeks after Ms. Ridgley moved in, prosecutors said, relations between landlord and tenant turned hostile, and finally fatal.</p>
        <p>After a week of contradictory accounts in the international press, Ms. Ridgley's lawyer said last night that his client was innocent. The lawyer, Donatilo Ballesteros, said that Ms. Abrams had attacked Ms. Ridgley with a knife, that a Colombian friend of Ms. Ridgley's had intervened, and that Ms. Ridgley was upstairs in her apartment tending her wounds at the time of the murder.</p>
        <p>''Debra Ann Ridgley had no part in the crime,'' Mr. Ballesteros said.</p>
        <p>Toni Grossi was a go-getter from the word go, driven in part, relatives said, by a need to escape the drama in her home, where her parents divorced and her mother was later murdered by a jilted lover. She was a high school valedictorian, graduated from the University of Pittsburgh and was the first female executive director of a branch of Junior Achievement, a business organization for students.</p>
        <p>After marrying Martin Abrams, a Manhattan mortgage broker, in the mid-1970s, Ms. Abrams worked as a stockbroker and later started her own investment-management company, Financial Profiles.</p>
        <p>The Abramses enjoyed the good life, golfing all over the world and accumulating vacation homes. In the '80s, they bought a house on Staten Island on a bluff above the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge. Ms. Abrams transformed the house into a showpiece.</p>
        <p>Ms. Abrams was a joiner. She served on the board of the Staten Island Museum and the Staten Island Symphony. She helped feed the homeless at St. Paul's Episcopal Church. She formed a group called ROAR to fight a proposed racetrack.</p>
        <p>A magnet for attention in jewels and flounces, she ingratiated herself to some people and grated against others.</p>
        <p>''She could drive you absolutely crazy,'' said a good friend of hers, the Rev. William Blasingame of St. Paul's. ''She would get so worked up about something, you would just want to throttle her. But she had a big heart.''</p>
        <p>After her husband died in 1998, Ms. Abrams got more involved in real estate. She moved to Bay Street Landing, a gated waterfront community near the Staten Island Ferry terminal, and bought and sold several condos there, Ms. Phalen said. She set her sights abroad and focused on Panama, where a cousin of her husband's had gone into business.</p>
        <p>Starting in 2003, Ms. Abrams bought a beach house on Contadora Island and three apartments in a white-and-orange high-rise in Panama City called the Atlantis, near the Veneto Hotel and Casino. She combined two units into a seven-bedroom suite, where she stayed on her frequent visits from Staten Island, and rented out the other.</p>
        <p>In February 2007, Ms. Abrams and Ms. Ridgley were introduced through a real estate promotional group, and Ms. Ridgley arranged to rent the upstairs apartment.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ridgley left her home in Zelienople, Pa., 30 miles north of Pittsburgh, and arrived in Panama in early March with her father and her granddaughter, Courtney Rader, 19.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ridgley and her granddaughter enjoyed Panama City's nightlife, said Stacy L. Rader, Ms. Ridgley's daughter and Courtney's mother. They made friends with a 24-year-old Colombian, Didier Osorio Garcia. Ms. Ridgley gave Mr. Garcia money, while to Courtney Rader, Mr. Garcia was ''really nice and kind,'' Stacy Rader said.</p>
        <p>Soon, Courtney and Ms. Ridgley's father returned to Pennsylvania. And Ms. Abrams, who had been in Panama when her tenants arrived, returned to Staten Island.</p>
        <p>When she went back to Panama unexpectedly in early April, she was upset to find that Ms. Ridgley had been downstairs in her apartment, which is connected by an interior staircase, said Franklin Amaya, the prosecutor on the case. A quarrel ensued, he said.</p>
        <p>''There were very serious differences between the two women,'' Mr. Amaya said.</p>
        <p>Many aspects of the case were first reported by The Staten Island Advance.</p>
        <p>On the night of Monday, April 9, Ms. Abrams was fatally stabbed in her apartment, probably in the chest and abdomen with a kitchen knife, the Panamanian authorities said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ridgley was in Ms. Abrams's apartment that night, as were Mr. Garcia and a friend, Camilo Castro, Mr. Amaya said. Ms. Abrams's body was stuffed into a travel bag in the fetal position, said Dr. Jose Vicente Pachar, director of Panama's Institute of Legal Medicine.</p>
        <p>''Whatever didn't fit in was cut off,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Garcia and Mr. Castro wheeled the travel bag out of the building and were joined by Ms. Ridgley, Mr. Amaya said. They took a taxi to Rio Abajo, a poor neighborhood on the edge of the city.</p>
        <p>In the morning, Mr. Amaya said, children on their way to school found charred human remains in a vacant lot, and a carpenter who came to do work at Ms. Abrams's apartment found it spattered with blood. The remains were Ms. Abrams's, Dr. Pachar said.</p>
        <p>When the police questioned Ms. Ridgley the next day, they noted she had a cut on her hand that required stitches. She was arrested and remains in jail.</p>
        <p>On April 12, Stacy Rader said, the family learned what had happened when Mr. Garcia called the Raders from Ms. Abrams's cellphone. He told Courtney that her grandmother had been charged with Ms. Abrams's death, but that he himself had killed her to save Ms. Ridgley's life, Stacy Rader said.</p>
        <p>''He told her that he killed Toni and my mom was innocent,'' Ms. Rader said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Garcia has called several times since then, Stacy Rader said, crying and sounding scared. ''He's asking for money,'' she said on Tuesday. ''He said he's afraid to turn himself in because he is afraid they'll kill him,'' she said, referring to the authorities.</p>
        <p>Mr. Garcia and Mr. Castro are wanted for questioning in Ms. Abrams's murder. Ms. Abrams's body remains in the Panama City morgue.</p>
        <p>On the answering machine at St. Paul's in Staten Island, Father Blasingame's voice says that Ms. Abrams's funeral will be delayed several weeks, ''due to affairs that must be concluded in Panama.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
