<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Listings: April 20 - April 26</title>
    <meta content="20theater" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070424T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841505"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E7DE1F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="15686" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Listings: April 20 - April 26</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'AMERICAN FIESTA' In previews; opens on Thursday. Steven Tomlinson's new play, directed by Mark Brokaw, is about an avid collector of ceramic dinnerware whose family disapproves of his same-sex marriage (1:30). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 353-0303.</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY ON THE VINE' Previews start on Tuesday. Opens on May 2. Zak Berkman's romantic fable follows a man falling in love with a budding star of right-wing radio (2:10). Clurman Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'CORAM BOY' In previews; opens on May 2. An adaptation of Jamila Gavin's novel about two orphans is the latest National Theater hit to move from London to Broadway (2:30). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'DIXIE'S TUPPERWARE PARTY' In previews; opens on May 10. Dixie Wingate has left her Alabama trailer park to sell Tupperware in New York in this irreverent comedy. Ars Nova, 511 West 54th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444.</p>
        <p>'DEUCE' In previews; opens on May 6. The grandes dames Angela Lansbury and Marian Seldes play retired tennis players in this new Terrence McNally comedy. Michael Blakemore directs. Music Box Theater, 239 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'FROST/NIXON' In previews; opens on Sunday. Frank Langella plays Richard M. Nixon in this acclaimed London transfer about the famous post-Watergate interview. With Michael Sheen. (1:40). Jacobs Theater, 242 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'THE J.A.P. SHOW: JEWISH AMERICAN PRINCESSES of comedy' Expect healthy amounts of whining and kvetching at this comedy showcase featuring four funny women, including Jackie Hoffman (''Hairspray'') (1:30). Actors Temple Theater, 339 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'JANE EYRE' Previews start on Monday. Opens on Tuesday. The Acting Company presents a new adaptation of Charlotte Brontë's classic (2:45). Baruch Performing Arts Center's Nagelberg Theater, 55 Lexington Avenue, at 25th Street, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'LEGALLY BLONDE' In previews; opens on April 29. Laura Bell Bundy plays the smiling, ditsy sorority girl who takes Harvard Law by storm in this musical adaptation. Jerry Mitchell directs (2:20). Palace Theater, 1564 Broadway, at 47th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'LOVEMUSIK' In previews; opens on May 3. The Tony winners Michael Cerveris and Donna Murphy star in a musical about the relationship between Kurt Weill and Lotte Lenya (with songs by Weill). Harold Prince directs (2:30). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'110 IN THE SHADE' In previews; opens on May 9. Audra McDonald stars in the Roundabout's revival of the musical version of N. Richard Nash's ''Rainmaker.'' Studio 54, 254 West 54th Street, (212) 719-1300.</p>
        <p>'RADIO GOLF' Previews start today. Opens on May 8. The last play in August Wilson's cycle is set in 1997 and centers on the vital question of what will be done with the fabled Aunt Esther's house. Tonya Pinkins (''Caroline, or Change'') stars (2:30). Cort Theater, 138 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'REALISM' and 'JUMP!' The first play has opened; the second opens on Thursday. The Exchange, formerly known as the Jean Cocteau Rep, presents in repertory these new works by emerging British writers (1:30 each). Kirk Theater, 420 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'A CHORUS LINE' If you want to know why this show was such a big deal when it opened 31 years ago, you need only experience the thrilling first five minutes of this revival. Otherwise, this archivally exact production, directed by Bob Avian, feels like a vintage car that has been taken out of the garage, polished up and sent on the road once again (2:00). Schoenfeld Theater, 236 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE COAST OF UTOPIA' Lincoln Center Theater's brave, gorgeous, sprawling and ultimately exhilarating production of Tom Stoppard's trilogy about intellectuals errant in 19th-century Russia. A testament to the seductive powers of narrative theater, directed with hot and cool canniness by Jack O'Brien and featuring a starry cast (Brian F. O'Byrne, Jennifer Ehle, Martha Plimpton, Josh Hamilton and Ethan Hawke, among others) in a tasty assortment of roles. Vivian Beaumont Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'COMPANY' Fire, beckoning and dangerous, flickers beneath the frost of John Doyle's elegant, unexpectedly stirring revival of Stephen Sondheim and George Furth's era-defining musical from 1970, starring a compellingly understated Raúl Esparza. Like Mr. Doyle's ''Sweeney Todd,'' this production finds new clarity of feeling in Sondheim by melding the roles of performers and musicians (2:20). Barrymore Theater, 243 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CURTAINS' This musical comedy about a musical-comedy murder -- featuring songs by John Kander and Fred Ebb and a book by Rupert Holmes -- lies on the stage like a promisingly gaudy string of firecrackers, waiting in vain for a match. The good news is that David Hyde Pierce, playing a diffident Boston detective, steps into full-fledged Broadway stardom. Scott Ellis directs a talent-packed cast that includes Debra Monk and Karen Ziemba. (2:30). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920s stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, it has theatergoers responding as if they were withering houseplants finally being watered after long neglect. (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'GREY GARDENS' Christine Ebersole is absolutely glorious as the middle-aged, time-warped debutante called Little Edie Beale in this uneven musical adaptation of the notorious 1975 documentary of the same title. She and the wonderful Mary Louise Wilson (as her bedridden mother), in the performances of their careers, make ''Grey Gardens'' an experience no passionate theatergoer should miss (2:40). Walter Kerr Theater, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HOWARD KATZ' The subject of Patrick Marber's comedy of unhappiness about a rabid talent agent, starring a baleful Alfred Molina and directed by Doug Hughes, is nothing more nor less than your standard-issue midlife crisis. This familiar topic gets the better of all the talented people here trying to make it seem fresh (1:30). Laura Pels Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'INHERIT THE WIND' Doug Hughes's wooden revival of this worthy war horse, based on the Scopes ''monkey'' trial of 1925, never musters much more velocity than that of a drugstore fan. Be grateful that the cast includes Christopher Plummer, in savory form as a Will Rogers of jurisprudence. An oddly subdued Brian Dennehy plays his pompous adversary (2:00). Lyceum Theater, 149 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'JOURNEY'S END' A splendid revival of R. C. Sherriff's 1928 drama of life in the trenches during World War I. Acutely staged (by David Grindley) and acted by a fine ensemble led by Hugh Dancy and Boyd Gaines, this production offers an exemplary presentation of that theatrical rarity, an uncompromising, clear-eyed play about war and the experience of day-to-day combat. An essential ticket (2:40). Belasco Theater, 111 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MARY POPPINS' This handsome, homily-packed, mechanically ingenious and rather tedious musical, adapted from the P. L. Travers stories and the 1964 film, is ultimately less concerned with inexplicable magic than with practical psychology. Ashley Brown, who sings prettily as the family-mending nanny, looks like Joan Crawford trying to be nice and sounds like Dr. Phil. Directed by Richard Eyre and Matthew Bourne (2:30). New Amsterdam Theater, 214 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LES MISÉRABLES' This premature revival, a slightly scaled-down version of the well-groomed behemoth that closed only three years ago, appears to be functioning in a state of mild sedation. Appealingly sung and freshly orchestrated, this fast-moving adaptation of Victor Hugo's novel isn't sloppy or blurry. But its pulse rate stays well below normal (2:55). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'A MOON FOR THE MISBEGOTTEN' Kevin Spacey gives a bizarre, beat-the-clock performance, as lively as a frog on a hot plate, as James Tyrone in this off-kilter revival of Eugene O'Neill's last play. Mercifully, he does not block the view of Eve Best, who maps the contradictory levels of Tyrone's strapping love interest with clarity and intelligence (2:50). Brooks Atkinson Theater, 256 West 47th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PIRATE QUEEN' How to river-dance your way to the bottom of the ocean, courtesy of the songwriters of ''Les Misérables'' (2:30). Hilton Theater, 213 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' Duncan Sheik and Steven Sater's bold adaptation of the Frank Wedekind play is the freshest and most exciting new musical Broadway has seen in some time. Set in 19th-century Germany but with a ravishing rock score, it exposes the splintered emotional lives of adolescents just discovering the joys and sorrows of sex. Performed with brio by a great cast, with supple direction by Michael Mayer and inventive choreography by Bill T. Jones (2:00). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'TALK RADIO' The most lacerating portrait of a human meltdown this side of a Francis Bacon painting. Playing an abrasive radio talk show host with a God complex, the astounding Liev Schreiber seems to fill the air as inescapably as weather in Robert Falls's gut-grabbing revival of Eric Bogosian's 1987 play (1:40). Longacre Theater, 220 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN'  This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a superdeluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE YEAR OF MAGICAL THINKING' Joan Didion's arresting but ultimately frustrating adaptation of her best-selling memoir about being blindsided by grief, starring Vanessa Redgrave. The tension between style and emotional content that made the book such a stunner does not translate to the stage. The substance here is in the silences, when the focus shifts from words to Ms. Redgrave's wry, wounded face (1:40). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'ANNE OF GREEN GABLES' The trick to refashioning beloved children's books for the stage is to keep both the spirit and the story largely intact. In this, Gretchen Cryer and Nancy Ford -- a musical-theater partnership of five decades' standing, who have moved from their hit ''I'm Getting My Act Together'' to the American Girl demographic -- have largely succeeded. This breezy, upbeat musical avoids slickness and gets the job done, and is nicely cast into the bargain (1:30). The Lucille Lortel Theater, 121 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 279-4200. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>* 'APOSTASY' Gino Dilorio's fearless play about a dying white Jewish woman who falls under the spell of a black televangelist is pretty good; the acting that delivers it is terrific, especially Susan Greenhill as the woman, and Susan Louise O'Connor as her daughter (2:00). Urban Stages, 259 West 30th Street, (212) 868-4444. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'THE BIG VOICE: GOD OR MERMAN?' Think of two gifted and smart gay men with years of life together deploying their considerable talents from the two pianos you happen to have in your living room. The result is a hilarious and very touching memoir of two decades of love and the funky glories of show business life (2:00). Actors Temple Theater, 339 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Honor Moore)</p>
        <p>'BILL W. AND DR. BOB' This insightful new play about the founders of Alcoholics Anonymous subtly makes the claim that the recovery movement was born as a series of accidents. Patrick Husted is excellent as Bob Smith, Bill Wilson's partner in combating addictions (2:15). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Ginia Bellafante)</p>
        <p>* 'BLACKBIRD'  David Harrower's stunning new drama looks back at a sexual relationship -- between a 40-year-old man and a 12-year-old girl -- that transforms, cripples and paralyzes. Jeff Daniels and Alison Pill, both extraordinary, peel their characters down to their barest souls. Joe Mantello is the masterly director (1:30). Manhattan Theater Club at City Center Stage I, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DEFENDER OF THE FAITH' This grim tale by Stuart Carolan of low-level I.R.A. agitators trying to identify the informer in their midst features some visceral performances and a set by Charles Corcoran that makes excellent use of the Irish Rep's small stage. If only the cause itself didn't feel so small in these days of global terrorism (1:30). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>* 'DYING CITY' Christopher Shinn's crafty and unsettling play about grief and violence, set in the shadow of the Iraq war. Directed by James Macdonald and fiercely acted by Pablo Schreiber and Rebecca Brooksher, this quiet, transfixing production turns passive aggression into a theatrical dynamic (1:30). Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-7600. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'EXITS AND ENTRANCES'  Athol Fugard casts a tender glance back at an actor whose dedication to theater helped spark his own in this warm if insubstantial stage memoir. Morlan Higgins capably excavates the emotional core of a role that might have seemed generic, playing an aging gay actor reckoning with the end of an up-and-down career. William Dennis Hurley plays the Fugard stand-in (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'IN THE HEIGHTS' Lin-Manuel Miranda's joyous songs paint a vibrant portrait of daily life in Washington Heights in this flawed but enjoyable show. Essentially a valentine to the barrio -- conflict of a violent or desperate kind is banished from the picture -- the musical contains a host of funny performances and brings the zesty sound of Latin pop to the stage. (2:10). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'JACK GOES BOATING' Bob Glaudini's gentle comedy about pothead losers in love is a reminder of how engrossing uneventful lives can be in the hands of the right actors. Peter DuBois directs the easygoing ensemble, brilliantly led by Philip Seymour Hoffman (2:00). Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'A JEW GROWS IN BROOKLYN' You don't have to be Jewish or Brooklynish to empathize with Jake Ehrenreich, but in terms of fully appreciating his essentially one-man show, it probably helps. Especially the Catskills jokes (2:05). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 560-8912. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>'MARIE ANTOINETTE: THE COLOR OF FLESH' Joel Gross's intriguing play features impeccable performances by Amanda Jones, Samantha Ives and Jonathan Kells Phillips as the three corners of a triangle of love and friendship caught up in the French Revolution. It's no ordinary triangle: Ms. Jones plays Marie Antoinette, and Ms. Ives the real portraitist who often painted her (1:30). The 45th Street Theater, 354 West 45th Street, Clinton, (212) 254-9533. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>* 'THE NIBROC TRILOGY' ''Last Train to Nibroc,'' ''See Rock City'' and ''Gulf View Drive'' make no mention of 19th-century Russian intellectuals but they do signal the arrival of a talented American playwright, Arlene Hutton. Set in Kentucky and Florida, between the beginning of World War II and the early 1950s, the plays track the life of a young couple whose individual ambitions conflict; they also clash with the goals of a changing American society. Straightforward and heartfelt, but never treacly, the works stand out in a cold, postmodern universe. Try ''See Rock City'' if you have time for only one (1:25, 1:30 and 1:55). 78th Street Theater Lab, 236 West 78th Street, (212) 352-3101. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'OUR LEADING LADY' Kate Mulgrew stars as Laura Keene, who was starring in ''Our American Cousin'' on the night Lincoln was shot, in Charles Busch's uneven new comedy. An occasionally lively but mostly lumpen tribute to the glamour and grit of the theatrical life of a past era (2:00). Manhattan Theater Club at City Center Stage II, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'SPALDING GRAY: STORIES LEFT TO TELL' A disarming collage of selections from the monologues and journals of Mr. Gray, the ultimate stand-up solipsist, who died in 2004. Directed by Lucy Sexton, and read by five performers, none of whom resemble Mr. Gray, with an affection that shrewdly stops short of hero worship (1:30). Minetta Lane Theater, 18 Minetta Lane, Greenwich Village, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden Theater, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' Singing CliffsNotes for Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS'  The biomusical that walks like a man (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT'  A singing scrapbook for Monty Python fans (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' ''A Chorus Line'' with pimples (1:45). Circle in the Square, 254 West 50th Street, Manhattan, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'THE DARK AT THE TOP OF THE STAIRS' Jack Cummings III directs a respectable if reverential revival of William Inge's last major play. Seeking to access the poetry in Inge's homely tale of troubled lives in the Midwest in the 1920s, he can't quite hide its fundamentally prosaic qualities. Still, this Transport Group production gives audiences a chance to encounter a rarely seen drama from Broadway's heyday (2:35). Connelly Theater, 220 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101; closes tomorrow. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'FUGUE' ''Mary Smith'' is found wandering the streets of Chicago, suffering from amnesia. A young psychiatrist, who has his own demons, is consulted, and the process of treatment and Mary's memories in flashback are the action of ''Fugue,'' Lee Thuna's unrewarding play, directed by the Tony-winning actress Judith Ivey (2:15). Cherry Lane Theater, 38 Commerce Street, between Barrow and Bedford Streets, West Village, (212) 239-6200; closes tomorrow. (Moore)</p>
        <p>* 'KING HEDLEY II' The Signature Theater Company concludes its season dedicated to August Wilson with a gritty, strongly cast revival of this play set in a violence-ravaged Pittsburgh in the 1980s. Russell Hornsby gives a galvanizing performance in the title role, as a man struggling to live down the errors of his past and plant the seeds for a promising new life (2:45). Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 244-7529; closes on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'PRELUDE TO A KISS' Craig Lucas's broken-hearted romantic comedy from 1990 receives a first-rate remounting, courtesy of the Roundabout Theater Company. Alan Tudyk and Annie Parisse play a young couple whose marriage founders shortly after the bride receives a kiss from an elderly stranger (John Mahoney). The kiss awakens all three to an unsettling awareness of love's frailty and, paradoxically, of its durability too (2:00). American Airlines Theater, 227 West 42nd Street, (212) 719-1300; closes on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200; closes on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SERENDIB' David Zellnik's play about a group of scientists observing monkeys in Sri Lanka tackles questions about masculinity and social dominance within a framework that is too cute by half. That said, Mr. Zellnik seems to have more on his mind than many young playwrights (1:55). Ensemble Studio Theater, 549 West 52nd Street, Clinton, (212) 247-4982; closes on Sunday. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'SOME MEN' Terrence McNally's hit-and-miss comedy about gay life is a parade of cleanly drawn types, zippy one-liners and sentimental set pieces, woven into a pageant of the ages à la ''Cavalcade,'' Noël Coward's generations-spanning tribute to the British stiff upper lip. Trip Cullman directs the agile, appealing cast (2:00). Second Stage, 307 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 246-4422; closes on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TROPHY WIFE' Honky-tonk piano music and flickering film credits on a screen behind the stage set the tone for this slender period piece about a young woman who marries a wealthy older man to help her family's financial difficulties. The plot is taken from a short story by Chekhov, but it works fine in the 1920s milieu to which Mary Fulham and Terry Waldo, who wrote and performs the music, have transposed it; Mr. Waldo has also provided a veritable cornucopia of songs, to which Sharon Ann Farrell, as the ingénue, can at least do justice. But the piece, which seems a bouncy entertainment, turns out to want to stress its darker side; its abrupt ending leaves you hanging, wondering if, to make its point, the whole tone might have been a little less frothy (1:15). La MaMa E.T.C., 74 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 475-7710; closes on Sunday. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>* 'WAKE UP MR. SLEEPY! YOUR UNCONSCIOUS MIND IS DEAD!' Richard Foreman's latest film-theater hybrid is a memorial service, of sorts, for the intuitive self, killed by a surface-worshiping world. It is also a dazzling exercise in reality shifting that is as invigorating as it is mournful (1:05). Ontological Theater at St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101; closes on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>'AFTER THE WEDDING' (R, 119 minutes, in Danish) A modern creation with a classic theme involving haves and have-nots, bloodlines and family ties. The canned realism of the Danish director Susanne Bier is strictly Dogme-lite, but the spiky, screen-filling performances of her two male leads, Mads Mikkelsen and Rolf Lassgard, are really something to see. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'AQUA TEEN HUNGER FORCE COLON MOVIE FILM FOR THEATERS' (R, 87 minutes) Not as funny as the title or the Cartoon Network series on which it's based. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>'Blades of Glory' (PG-13, 93 minutes) In this fast, light, frequently funny comedy about a male figure-skating team, Will Ferrell and Jon Heder stake an early claim to being the comedy couple of the year. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>'DISTURBIA' (PG-13, 104 minutes) A pleasant, scary, well-directed variation on the killer-next-door theme, with the engaging Shia LeBeouf as Kale, a young man who turns house arrest into an occasion for voyeurism and crime-fighting. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'DREAMING LHASA' (No rating, 90 minutes, in Tibetan and English) This documentary from Ritu Sarin and Tenzing Sonam is about a Tibetan-American documentary-maker named Karma (Tenzin Chokyi Gyatso), who is making a movie about Tibetans who fled persecution by the Chinese and settled in Dharamsala, the Dalai Lama's exile headquarters in northern India. The movie is filled with heartbreaking moments, . but the central story, about the relationship between Karma and an ex-monk named Dhondup (Jampa Kalsang), can't help feeling contrived. (Matt Zoller Seitz)</p>
        <p>'FIREHOUSE DOG' (PG, 111 minutes) When a pampered Hollywood pooch trades his movie-star lifestyle for a rundown firehouse, it's not long before he is saving a father-son relationship and tracking down a serial arsonist. Yet the movie's wittiest moment -- a canine parody of Dudley Moore's first glimpse of Bo Derek in ''10'' -- will be appreciated only by parents, and in trying to straddle both age groups, ''Firehouse Dog'' proves decidedly less nimble than its furry star. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'THE GLAMOROUS LIFE OF SACHIKO HANAI' (No rating, 90 minutes, in Japanese) A wayward bullet turns a hooker into a brainiac in this Japanese clutter of soft-core political parody, hard-core narrative nonsense, breezy sexism and penny-ante surrealism. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'GRINDHOUSE' (R, 180 minutes) A double feature, complete with fake previews for schlocky exploitation pictures, that pays nostalgic tribute to disreputable traditions of moviemaking and moviegoing. Robert Rodriguez contributes ''Planet Terror,'' a purposely incoherent zombie gross-out flick that flaunts is own badness the way Rose McGowan (as a go-go dancer named Cherry Darling) shows off her weaponized prosthetic leg. For his part, Quentin Tarantino, more of a connoisseur than his collaborator (and a much better filmmaker), turns out a brutal, talky and satisfying car-chase revenge movie in ''Death Proof,'' starring Kurt Russell. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'THE HOAX' (R, 115 minutes) A first-rate performance by Richard Gere drives this true story of Clifford Irving (Mr. Gere), who claimed to be the authorized biographer of Howard Hughes. Shadowed by the paranoia of its period (the early '70s), this movie, crisply directed by Lasse Hallstrom from an excellent script by William Weaver, is less a morality play than the entertaining portrait of a literary gambler. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE HOLY MOUNTAIN' (No rating, 114 minutes, in Spanish) A scandal when first released, Alejandro Jodorowsky's 1973 movie -- a follow-up to his midnight landmark ''El Topo'' -- is a dazzling, rambling, often incoherent satire on consumerism, militarism and the exploitation of third world cultures by the west. The free-associative narrative follows a Christ-like thief through a series of surreal tableaus; the mission ends with a postmodern punch line that suggests that movies are drugs too, and the revolution can't happen until we kick our habits. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>* 'KILLER OF SHEEP' (No rating, 83 minutes) Largely hidden from view for three decades, Charles Burnett's lyrical film about a working-class family living in a broken-down home in a bombed-out stretch of Los Angeles is an American masterpiece, independent to the bone. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'LONELY HEARTS' (No rating, 100 minutes) This beautifully photographed remake of Leonard Kastle's 1970 cult B movie ''The Honeymoon Killers'' succeeds better than many modern crime dramas in balancing the philosophical with the visceral, although its villains' dirty deeds still trump its deeper strain of melancholy. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE LOOKOUT' (R, 99 minutes) This directorial debut by the veteran screenwriter Scott Frank (''Out of Sight'') is a variation of an old, old story, about a nobody (a brain-damaged janitor played by Joseph Gordon-Levitt) who falls in with crooks who make him feel like somebody. Although the movie's no masterpiece -- the final stretch feels forced and unconvincing -- there's a lot to like here. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>'MEET THE ROBINSONS' (G, 93 minutes) Actually, if you see them coming, run in the other direction. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'PATHFINDER' (R, 100 minutes) It's all grunting, all goring in this witless period flick about some Norsemen of the apocalypse come to wreak bloody ruin in the New World. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'PERFECT STRANGER' (R, 109 minutes) There is enough of a grain of truth in this noirish, paranoid thriller set in the New York media world that even after it lurches from the farfetched into the preposterous, the movie leaves a clammy residue of unease. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'PRIVATE FEARS IN PUBLIC PLACES' (No rating, 120 minutes, in French) A film from the venerable French auteur Alain Resnais about love and cinematic spaces, elegant camera moves and six heavenly bodies as seen through a mighty telescope. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'RED ROAD' (No rating, 113 minutes) Andrea Arnold's first feature falls into melodrama and implausibility at the end, but along the way it is a remarkably assured and complex piece of work, anchored by the director's formal control and by Jackie Dick's quietly heartbreaking performance as a Glasgow video-surveillance officer with an unhappy past. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'REIGN OVER ME' (R, 124 minutes) Mike Binder's comic drama of post-9/11 grief is wildly uneven -- by turns insightful and grindingly mawkish. Don Cheadle and Adam Sandler are two college buddies who reunite, somewhat improbably, some years after the attacks that robbed one of them of his family. The actors rise above the material, particularly in the longer, looser scenes that allow their contrasting temperaments -- Mr. Cheadle's tense understatement and Mr. Sandler's shaggy emoting -- to find a workable syncopation. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'ROCK THE BELLS' (No rating, 103 minutes) Casey Suchan and Denis Henry Hennelly's lively documentary follows the independent music promoter Chang Weisberg as he struggles to reunite the original members of the Wu-Tang Clan for a 2004 hip-hop concert. Capturing onstage and off with equal energy, the movie is a fascinating glimpse of a dreamer and a music culture that has always depended on them. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'SLOW BURN' (R, 93 minutes) There's not a line of dialogue that doesn't sound squeezed from a grade-C ''Law &amp; Order'' imitator affecting a bogus inner-city street cred. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE TV SET' (R, 87 minutes) Jake Kasdan's knowing satire of network television sends up the neuroses of writers and the ruthlessness of executives with minimal exaggeration. Nothing in this story of a writer (David Duchovny) pursuing his dream project seems implausible, which is less a limitation on the movie's comedy than it is its source. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'VOICE OF A MURDERER' (No rating, 122 minutes, in Korean) The unpredictable Korean director Park Jin-pyo returns to the docudrama form with this fictionalized account of the unsolved 1991 kidnapping and killing of a 9-year-old boy. Filmed relentlessly from the point of view of the distraught parents (Sol Kyung-gu and Kim Nam-joo), the movie unfolds in endless, repetitive scenes of parental hysteria punctuated by phone calls from the shadowy abductor. By the 44th day and the umpteenth call, it's déjà vu all over again. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'YEAR OF THE DOG' (PG-13, 97 minutes) Mike White's touching comedy about a woman who loses a dog and finds herself is funny ha-ha but firmly in touch with its downer side, which means it's also funny in a kind of existential way. Molly Shannon stars alongside a menagerie of howling scene-stealers. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>BUFFY THE VAMPIRE SLAYER SING-ALONG (Tonight) The IFC Center tries to get a little ''Rocky Horror'' action going by sponsoring a midnight screening of this cult television show's celebrated all-singing, all-dancing episode. Audience participation is strongly encouraged. IFC Center, 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 924-7771, ifccenter.com; $10.75. (Dave Kehr)</p>
        <p>* COMMITMENT AND GRACE: THE FILMS OF CARLOS SAURA (Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Saura is, of course, one of Spain's great film masters. But for those who love dance, he will always be an artist who spoke vivid new truths about Spanish dancing and the relationship between film and dance. This tribute by the Film Society of Lincoln Center covers 50 years of his work, with ''Blood Wedding'' and ''Sevillanas'' on Wednesday at 1:30 p.m., and ''Carmen'' on Thursday at 1 p.m. (Through May 3.) Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5600, filmlinc.com; $11; $7 for students with ID and for 65+ at weekday screenings before 6 p.m.; $40 for a series pass for eight films. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>INDIA NOW (Sunday through Thursday) Nine new features and two short films from India, in a series co-sponsored by the Museum of Modern Art and the Indo-American Arts Council. On the opening night the director Rahul Dholakia will introduce his controversial feature ''Parzania,'' a fictionalized account of the Gujarat riots of 2002. Other highlights include Arindam Mitra's ''Shoonya'' (Monday), an adaptation of T. S. Eliot's ''Murder in the Cathedral'' transposed to the world of Indian cricket, and ''Kaalpurush'' (''Memories in the Mist''), a new work by the Bengali filmmaker Buddhadeb Dasgupta (Wednesday). Museum of Modern Art Roy and Niuta Titus Theaters, (212) 708-9400, moma.org; $10. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>ACID MOTHERS TEMPLE (Thursday) This Japanese band describes its style as ''extreme trip music,'' which basically means big, sloppy, psychedelic noise jams. It doesn't necessarily mean peasant frocks and long wizard's robes, but Acid Mothers Temple usually has plenty of those too. With Mammatus and Alasehoutek. At 8 p.m., Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3132, knittingfactory.com; $13 in advance, $15 at the door. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>ASHFORD AND SIMPSON (Tomorrow) The Steve and Eydie of pop-soul still put on a convincing and musically solid demonstration of being the world's happiest show-business couple. With Melba Moore. At 8 p.m., Apollo Theater, 253 West 125th Street, Harlem, (212) 531-5305 or (212) 307-7171, apollotheater.com; $45 to $65. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>* BASEMENT BHANGRA (Tonight) For 10 years Rekha Malhotra, better known as DJ Rekha, has been leading this dance party at the downtown club S.O.B.'s, introducing legions of New Yorkers to the musky sound of bhangra, which melds Punjabi folk melodies with reggae and house-rocking electronic beats. Her efforts have been instrumental in popularizing the style in America, and she celebrates the milestone with an all-star anniversary show at the Hammerstein Ballroom, which should feel about 100 times bigger than S.O.B.'s but just as hot. Guests include Panjabi MC (whose song with Jay-Z, ''Beware of the Boys,'' is bhangra's biggest hit), Dhol Foundation and Bikram Singh. At 9 p.m., 311 West 34th Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171, mcstudios.com; $35 to $100. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BRAND NEW (Sunday) Not all emo goes the way of smirky punk-pop or sentimental singalongs. This excellent Long Island band plies dense, angry tangles of guitar and opaque lyrics of spiritual crisis, a cross between Pink Floyd and Nirvana. With Kevin Devine and the Manchester Orchestra. At 7 p.m., Fillmore New York at Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>THE BUNKER (Tonight) Honking saxophones and screeching guitars were the best-known musical residents of Tonic, the Lower East side club that closed last week. But Tonic was also an important home for avant-garde electronica. The Bunker, Tonic's long-running late-night techno party, is moving to a new club without missing a single week. Tonight it opens at the Luna Lounge, another former Lower East Side boîte, which is now in Brooklyn. Besides the resident D.J.'s, Spinoza and Derek Plaslaiko, tonight features Bodycode, a noisemaker based in Portugual who is also known as Portable (and as Alan Abrahams). At midnight, 361 Metropolitan Avenue, at Havemeyer Street, Williamsburg, lunalounge.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CLIPSE (Thursday) Comeback stories in rap are rare and sweet. In 2002 this Virginia duo rose to the Top 10 with sly rhymes about the cocaine trade and brutally minimal rhythm tracks by the Neptunes. Since then Clipse struggled in music-industry purgatory but triumphed with ''Hell Hath No Fury'' (Re-Up Gang/Jive), another cold, lean and virtuosic exercise that was one of last year's best hip-hop albums. With Monica and Jovan Dais. At 8 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club &amp; Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $30. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* JARVIS COCKER (Sunday and Monday) Carrying on the wittily misanthropic vignette style he perfected in his 1990s Britpop band, Pulp, Mr. Cocker, now 43, has returned with a solo album, ''Jarvis'' (Rough Trade). Without his former band, he is just as caustic but seems to have turned into a studio tinkerer, sampling the Righteous Brothers and Tommy James. At 8 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; $32 in advance, $35 at the door (sold out on Monday). (Sisario)</p>
        <p>COCOROSIE (Tonight) As CocoRosie, the Casady sisters, Sierra and Bianca, make swirling and surrealistic dramas out of girlish daydreams, hints of trip-hop, chirping crickets and cooed Billie Holiday-ish vocals. With Tez and the Girls of Karen Black. At 8, Warsaw, 261 Driggs Avenue, at Eckford Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 387-0505, warsawconcerts.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CONSTANTINES, TIM FITE (Thursday) Constantines is a feedback-worshiping Canadian band in the neo-MC5 mold: the bigger their guitar chords, the higher their fists fly. Tim Fite is harder to pin down. A lo-fi lone wolf from Brooklyn, he is somewhere between folk and hip-hop, and with his latest album, ''Over the Counter Culture'' -- a harsh rap indictment of consumerism and the American dream of selling out, which he offers free on his Web site (timfite.com) -- he has made himself into a cultural gadfly. At 8:30 p.m., Luna Lounge, 361 Metropolitan Avenue, at Havemeyer Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, lunalounge.com; $12 in advance, $14 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* DEERHUNTER (Thursday) Recalling Spacemen 3, this Atlanta quintet plays loose, sprawling psychedelia that grows from sweet guitar and vocal melodies into patterns that seem both florid and evil. With First Nation and Pterodactyl. At 8:30 p.m., Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700, mercuryloungenyc.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DIMMU BORGIR (Thursday) Dimmu Borgir is a Norwegian black-metal band: black as in dark and dismal, with haunted-house keyboard arpeggios and vocals rendered in an electronically processed monster growl. It's good for a shudder; few kinds of fans are as deeply into their scene as those who attend these shows, and the band doesn't come to the United States often. With Unearth, DevilDriver and Kataklysm. At 7 p.m., Nokia Theater, 1515 Broadway, at 44th Street, (212) 307-7171, nokiatheatrenyc.com; $25 in advance, $29 at the door. (Ben Ratliff)</p>
        <p>* DNTEL (Wednesday) As he did in the Postal Service, his project with Ben Gibbard of Death Cab for Cutie, Jimmy Tamborello -- who has been recording under the name Dntel for a decade or more -- gracefully joins stutters of electronic noise and soft, pensive melodies. His latest, ''Dumb Luck'' (Sub Pop), features collaborations with indie royalty like Bright Eyes, Jenny Lewis and Grizzly Bear, which means that you might be hearing this gurgly, not-quite-innocuous music, like the Postal Service, on late-night bar playlists for years to come. At 10 p.m., Union Pool, 484 Union Avenue, at Meeker Avenue, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 609-0484; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* FOUNTAINS OF WAYNE (Tuesday) Chris Collingwood and Adam Schlesinger of Fountains of Wayne earned their seats in the songwriting pantheon with a fluent power-pop classicism and songs that celebrate beta males and bridge-and-tunnel quotidiana (and, in the case of their 2003 hit, ''Stacy's Mom,'' teenage fantasies of older women.) Their new album, ''Traffic and Weather'' (Virgin), is full of familiar Fountains of Wayne-isms, with Beatlesesque chord progressions and stories of love encumbered by competition for taxis. With Robbers on High Street. At 8 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* FRATELLIS (Thursday) Like Sweet and Slade before it, this Scottish trio is not afraid to be both tough and silly, employing bubblegum shout-alongs in its stompy, completely catchy hard-rock tunes. At 9 p.m., Fillmore New York at Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>KRISTIN HERSH (Wednesday) Through the 1980s and '90s Ms. Hersh led Throwing Muses, the textbook college rock band, whose songs set turbulent and free-associative psychodramas to twisting guitar lines. Motherhood and experience have softened her music somewhat, but she remains a provocative songwriter, and her voice has aged into an expressive, sensual rasp. For this show her band will be augmented by a string section. With Dolorean. At 7:30 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; $15 in advance, $17 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>TAYLOR HICKS (Tonight) ''American Idol'' has sent many singers into the shark tank of Top 40 radio, but this smoky-voiced Alabama crooner, who has more in common with Michael McDonald than with Kelly Clarkson, heads in the direction of buttery soul. At 8, Beacon Theater, 2124 Broadway, at 74th Street, (212) 307-7171, beacontheatrenyc.com; $36 to $62. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>HOT CHIP (Tonight) With wobbly electronic rhythms and a strong command of the drippy, semi-ironic disco ballad, this English group plays wistful but still snarky dance music. Get too lost in the beats and you'll miss gags like the oh-so-art-rock countdown of nonsense words in descending size (''S-E-X-I-N-G, C-A-S-I-O, P-O-K-E''). With Tussle. At 6:30, Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* JOHN LEGEND, CORINNE BAILEY RAE (Sunday and Monday) A five-time Grammy winner, John Legend has the right to be a little cocky. But on his second album, ''Once Again'' (Sony), he plays the gentleman -- for the most part, anyway. Channeling the most tasteful of '70s R&amp;B, he permits himself the slightest racy double-entendre, telling his lady that ''love hurts sometimes when you do it right.'' In a sweet, tissue-thin voice, Corinne Bailey Rae sings of sisterly rituals, loves lost and her ''choux pastry heart.'' Sunday at 7:30 p.m., New Jersey Performing Arts Center, 1 Center Street, Newark, (888) 466-5722, njpac.org; Monday at 8 p.m., Theater at Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741, thegarden.com. Both sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DAVE MATTHEWS AND TIM REYNOLDS (Sunday) The jam-band frog prince plays with an old guitar buddy whose style leans toward world-fusion. Expect long solos and inside jokes. At 7:30 p.m., Radio City Music Hall, (212) 307-7171, radiocity.com; $75. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LOREENA McKENNITT (Tonight) On ''An Ancient Muse'' (Verve), her first album in nine years, this Canadian singer explored her Celtic heritage in depth, from the British Isles to Turkey and along the Silk Road of Central Asia. And what did she find? Pretty much what she already knew: that with the help of some gossamer major-chord swells and reverberant, Enya-like vocals, any sound can be incorporated into the New Age fantasy of Celtic music. At 8, Radio City Music Hall, (212) 307-7171, radiocity.com; $35 to $75. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ERIN McKEOWN (Tonight) A smiley sprite whose knack for wordplay and light touch on the guitar have sometimes evoked Tin Pan Alley, Ms. McKeown took the plunge in her new album, ''Sing You Sinners'' (Nettwerk), recording 12 nuggets by Harold Arlen, Cole Porter, Fats Waller and others (along with one by herself). If her voice is not quite up to the subtleties of wit the songs demand, her joy of discovery is sincere. With John Southworth. At 7:30, Southpaw, 125 Fifth Avenue, near Sterling Place, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0236, spsounds.com; $15. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>NOISETTES (Monday) Conjuring the Yeah Yeah Yeahs and X-Ray Spex, this London band, led by the throaty and uninhibited Shingai Shoniwa, plays grimy, muscular punk-funk punctuated with lighter touches of something like vaudeville. With Looker and Cities on Fire. At 8 p.m., Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700, mercuryloungenyc.com; $12. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>RICKY SKAGGS AND BRUCE HORNSBY (Tuesday) One of the most virtuosic musicians in bluegrass, Ricky Skaggs sends his fingers flying in a blur over mandolin, guitar and fiddle. He performs with Bruce Hornsby, whose years playing with the Grateful Dead have made him a more versatile and playful musician. The two have a new, untitled album that is maybe a little too versatile and playful: it includes a cornball version of Rick James's ''Super Freak.'' At 8 p.m., the Concert Hall at the New York Society for Ethical Culture, 2 West 64th Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171, concertstonight.com; $50 and $60. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Keely Smith (Tonight and tomorrow night, and Tuesday through Thursday) This ''queen of swing,'' as she has been nicknamed, may be the last surviving top-of-the-line entertainer from the Rat Pack era of Las Vegas. She is still in reasonably good voice. (Through April 28.) At 8:45, with additional shows at 10:45 tonight and tomorrow night, Café Carlyle, Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212) 744-1600, thecarlyle.com; $75 and $125 cover tonight and tomorrow night, $65 and $100 Tuesday through Thursday. (Holden)</p>
        <p>PATTI SMITH (Tuesday) With ''Twelve'' (Columbia), a new album in which Ms. Smith covers the Rolling Stones, Jimi Hendrix and Nirvana -- whose ''Smells Like Teen Spirit'' gets an eccentric, bluegrass-tinged interpretation -- she and her band play three separate shows at the Bowery Ballroom on Tuesday night; tickets to each performance include a copy of the CD. At 6, 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* RICHARD SWIFT, DAVID VANDERVELDE (Tomorrow and Sunday) Retro-pop can easily go the way of mere imitation, but these singers have found ways to evoke their heroes without being entirely defined by them. Richard Swift's cynical gloss on piano-driven cabaret-rock adds a taste of vinegar to Harry Nilsson. David Vandervelde, from Chicago, has the thin whine and androgynous swagger of T. Rex down pat, but also wisely pursues his gift for the elegiac folk-rock ballad. Tomorrow at 9:30 p.m., Luna Lounge, 361 Metropolitan Avenue, at Havemeyer Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, lunalounge.com; $10 in advance, $12 at the door. Sunday at 10 p.m., Pianos, 158 Ludlow Street, near Rivington Street, Lower East Side, (212) 505-3733, pianosnyc.com; $12. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>BUFFALO COLLISION (Monday) Free improvisation is the working method for this collective, made up of the saxophonist Tim Berne, the violist Mat Maneri, the pianist Ethan Iverson and the drummer David King. As the name implies, results will be concussive at times, and maybe a bit hairy (in a good way). At 8:30 p.m., Center for Improvisational Music, 295 Douglass Street, between Third and Fourth Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (212) 631-5882, schoolforimprov.org; cover, $12; $8 for students. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>* THE CONGA KINGS (Today) Candido Camero, Carlos (Patato) Valdés and Giovanni Hidalgo are three of the most accomplished congueros alive; they join forces here at the helm of a nine-piece Afro-Cuban ensemble. At 12:30 and 7 p.m., Winter Garden, World Financial Center, West Street, south of Vesey Street, Lower Manhattan, (212) 945-0505, worldfinancialcenter.com; free. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CONGA MADNESS WEEK (Tuesday through Thursday) Congas dominate next week at the Blue Note too, with appearances by Francisco Aguabella and his fellow percussionist Carlos Valdés (Tuesday); Candido Camero, celebrating his 86th birthday (Wednesday); and Poncho Sanchez, with his crisp working band (Thursday). (Through April 29.) At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592 bluenote.net; cover, $30 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ANDREW CYRILLE, BOB STEWART AND ROY CAMPBELL (Tomorrow) Mr. Cyrille is an expressive drummer capable of creating a radiant sense of pulse; he interacts here with Mr. Stewart, on tuba, and Mr. Campbell, on trumpet. At 8:30 p.m., Roulette, 20 Greene Street, at Grand Street, SoHo, (212) 219-8242, roulette.org; $15; $10 for students. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>OLU DARA (Tuesday) Before he was known as the father of the rapper Nas, Mr. Dara was a trumpeter, guitarist and singer who infused New York avant-gardism with Mississippi twang. At 8 p.m., Studio Museum in Harlem, 144 West 125th Street, (212) 864-4500, Ext. 264, studiomuseum.org; $20; $15 in advance and for students; $12 for members. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PAQUITO D'RIVERA'S JAZZ CHAMBER TRIO / EDMAR CASTANEDA TRIO (Thursday) The saxophonist and clarinetist Paquito D'Rivera explores a hybrid of jazz and chamber music in his group with Alon Yavnai on piano and Dana Leong on cello. The harpist Edmar Castaneda shares the bill with his working trio, which has a separate engagement on Monday night at 7:30 and 9:30 at the Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; $15. Thursday at 8 p.m., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212)501-3330, kaufman-center.org; $35 in advance, $40 at the door . (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DIGITAL PRIMITIVES (Wednesday) The multireedist Assif Tsahar, the multi-instrumentalist Cooper-Moore and the percussionist Chad Taylor make up this experimental ensemble, which released an album of the same title last year. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Tea Lounge, 837 Union Street, between Sixth and Seventh Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 789-2762, tealoungeny.com; donation, $5. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MIKE DILLON'S GO-GO JUNGLE (Tonight) Mike Dillon is a vibraphonist whose caffeinated approach to rhythm finds a suitable outlet in a funk-inspired jam band he calls the Go-Go Jungle. Sharing the bill are two similarly inclined bands, Licorice and the Bomb Squad. At 8, Knitting Factory Tap Bar, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3132, knittingfactory.com; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SONNY FORTUNE QUARTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) A powerful and searching saxophonist, Sonny Fortune leads a group with Michael Cochrane on piano, Chip Jackson on bass and Steve Johns on drums. At 8, 10 and midnight, Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212) 255-3626, sweetrhythmny.com; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>AL FOSTER QUARTET (Tuesday through Thursday) The well-traveled drummer Al Foster has a lithe touch, ideal for modern jazz and more than suitable for funk; his band consists of the tenor saxophonist Eli Degibri, the pianist Kevin Hays and the bassist Doug Weiss. (Through April 29.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* FREQUENCY/ ANGELICA SANCHEZ TRIO (Sunday) Frequency is a Chicago-based ensemble consisting of the saxophonist and clarinetist Edward Wilkerson, the flutist Nicole Mitchell, the bassist Harrison Bankhead and the drummer Avreeayl Ra; its self-titled debut, released last year on the Thrill Jockey label, pairs textural experimentation with a slippery sense of swing. That stylistic negotiation is likely to resurface in a later set with Angelica Sanchez on piano, Tony Malaby on saxophone and Tom Rainey on drums. At 7 and 9 p.m., Jimmy's, 43 East Seventh Street, East Village, (212) 982-3006, freestylejazz.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MIKE GAMBLE'S MULTI METEORCHESTRA (Tonight) The guitarist Mike Gamble goes for density and velocity in this confab of nearly a dozen energetic young players. At 9 and 10:30, Tea Lounge, 837 Union Street, between Sixth and Seventh Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718)789-2762, tealoungeny.com; donation, $5. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>THE GANG FONT, FEAT. INTERLOPER (Tomorrow and Sunday) David King, the intensely propulsive drummer for Happy Apple and the Bad Plus, formed this Minneapolis-centered group with the bassist Greg Norton, a former member of the influential post-punk band Hüsker Dü. Adding to the prog-rock churn are Craig Taborn, on keyboards, and Erik Fratzke (of Happy Apple), on guitar. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Silent Barn, 915 Wyckoff Avenue, at Hancock Street, Ridgewood, Queens, toddpnyc.com; cover, $8. Sunday at 7:30 p.m., Knitting Factory Tap Bar, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3132, knittingfactory.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVID GILMORE QUINTET (Tomorrow) David Gilmore favors a clean guitar tone, but his playing tends toward rhythmic convolution; his dynamic band includes Marcus Strickland on tenor saxophone and Jeff (Tain) Watts on drums. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $15; $10 for members. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* HUMAN FEEL (Tomorrow) This reunited confab -- Chris Speed and Andrew D'Angelo on reeds, Jim Black on drums and Kurt Rosenwinkel on guitar -- has a smartly enigmatic new album called ''Galore'' (Skirl), its first in a decade. Its strength lies in an ideal of interconnectedness, and a tonal palette partly informed by underground rock. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Tea Lounge, 837 Union Street, between Sixth and Seventh Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 789-2762, tealoungeny.com; suggested donation, $5. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>IN A SENTIMENTAL MOOD (Tonight) The Jazz Museum in Harlem All-Stars Band, led by the saxophonist, pianist and historian Loren Schoenberg, plays some lesser-known music from the book of Duke Ellington and Billy Strayhorn, in a concert in collaboration with the Duke Ellington Society. At 8, Flushing Town Hall, 137-35 Northern Boulevard, at Linden Place, Queens, (718) 463-7700, flushingtownhall.org; $40; $28 for members. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* OLIVER LAKE (Tomorrow and Sunday) Mr. Lake is a saxophonist with a piercing sound and a fearless style. Tomorrow he leads a quartet with Freddie Hendrix on trumpet, Jared Gold on organ and Bill McClelland on drums; on Sunday he presents his Reunion Trio, with Pheeroan akLaff on drums and Michael Gregory on guitars. Tomorrow at 9 and 10:30 p.m., Sista's Place, 456 Nostrand Avenue, at Jefferson Avenue, Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn, (718) 398-1766, sistasplace.org; cover, $25 in advance, $30 at the door. Sunday at 8:30 p.m., Roulette, 20 Greene Street, at Grand Street, SoHo, (212) 219-8242, roulette.org; $15; $10 for students. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>THE LEGENDS OF BLUE NOTE (Thursday) The celebrated hard boppers from the 1960s Blue Note roster -- like Lee Morgan and Horace Silver -- provide a promising repertory foundation for this concert, featuring new arrangements for the Jazz at Lincoln Center Orchestra. (Through April 28.) At 8 p.m., Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 721-6500, jalc.org; $37.50 to $127.50. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MAHAVISHNU PROJECT (Tomorrow) This single-minded repertory project, led by the percussionist Gregg Bendian, boldly apprehends the fusion of the Mahavishnu Orchestra. As on its new Cuneiform release, the group involves a total of 11 musicians here, performing all the material from the 1975 album ''Visions of the Emerald Beyond.'' At 9 p.m., Makor, 35 West 67th Street, near Columbus Avenue, (212) 601-1000, mahavishnuproject.com; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>RON MILES /JENNY SCHEINMAN (Monday) Mr. Miles is a trumpeter with a dual attraction to sunlight and shadow, as he demonstrated on ''Stone/Blossom,'' a double album issued last year. He performs an early set with his band, and then joins Ms. Scheinman, a thoughtful violinist and frequent collaborator, in a set of her own. At 7 and 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $10 a set. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* CHARLES MINGUS: EPITAPH (Wednesday) Charles Mingus never saw a full performance of ''Epitaph,'' his epic orchestral composition; its premiere at Lincoln Center in 1989, came a decade after his death. That concert's conductor, Gunther Schuller, resuscitates the work here with a 30-piece orchestra; he also includes ''Inquisition,'' a recently discovered movement that has never been performed. Among the accomplished musicians in the ensemble is Christian McBride, filling Mingus's formidable bass chair. At 7:30 p.m., Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212)721-6500, jalc.org; $45. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BEN MONDER (Thursday) In the hands of Mr. Monder, the electric guitar is a coloristic instrument first and foremost. He features his coolly convoluted pieces for a trio with Chris Lightcap on bass and Ted Poor on drums, recording the results for a forthcoming album. At 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JEROME SABBAGH QUARTET (Tuesday) ''Pogo'' (Sunnyside), the new album by the tenor and soprano saxophonist Jerome Sabbagh, highlights his casual yet focused rapport with the guitarist Ben Monder, the bassist Joe Martin and the drummer Ted Poor, who all join him here. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* DINO SALUZZI AND ANJA LECHNER (Tuesday) ''Ojos Negros'' (ECM) is a sparse and often haunting new album by Mr. Saluzzi, an Argentine bandoneón player, and Ms. Lechner, a German cellist; tango feeds into its mood, but so do jazz and some mournful strains of the European classical tradition. At 8 p.m., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212) 501-3330, kaufman-center.org; $35 in advance, $40 tomorrow. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SAMBA JAZZ &amp; MUSIC OF JOBIM (Tuesday through Thursday) A cosmopolitan Brazilian-jazz ensemble consisting of the pianist Helio Alves, the drummer Duduka da Fonseca, the trumpeter Claudio Roditi and the bassist Eddie Gomez. The group salutes Antonio Carlos Jobim, with vocals by his son (Paulo Jobim) and a frequent collaborator (Maucha Adnet). (Through April 29.) At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>THIRD WHEEL (Sunday) The bright young drummer Ted Poor bears primary responsibility for this trio with the trumpeter Ralph Alessi and the guitarist Ben Monder, but its creative energies are emphatically collective. At 8:30 p.m., Center for Improvisational Music, 295 Douglass Street, between Third and Fourth Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (212) 631-5882, schoolforimprov.org; cover, $12; $8 for students. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TYSHAWN SOREY QUARTET (Thursday) Tyshawn Sorey, a drummer with an aggressively physical style, showcases his own compositions in this group with Ben Gerstein on trombone, Cory Smythe on keyboards and Thomas Morgan on bass. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $12; $10 for members. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STILL LIFE WITH COMMENTATOR (Tomorrow) The brazen theatricality of the modern news cycle fuels this collaboration between the pianist and composer Vijay Iyer and the poet Mike Ladd, originally presented at Brooklyn Academy of Music in December. The work is scaled back here but still features Pamela Z and Guillermo Brown on vocals, Okkyung Lee on cello and Liberty Ellman on guitar. At 11:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 539-8778, joespub.com; cover, $15, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* WOMEN IN JAZZ FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday) This first annual festival of the nonprofit International Women in Jazz organization begins tonight with a reception featuring music by the saxophonist Virginia Mayhew; the first performance tomorrow is by the pianist Deanna Witkowski, and the last is by the singer Ann Hampton Callaway. Sunday's offerings include a Jazz Vespers service with the vocalist Kate McGarry. Times vary. St. Peter's Church, Lexington Avenue, at 54th Street, (212) 935-2200, internationalwomeninjazz.com; tickets range from free to $25, depending on the event, or $50 for a festival pass. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* JOHN ZORN (Thursday) A couple months ago Columbia University presented the iconoclastic composer John Zorn with its William Schuman Award, a distinction of lifetime-achievement proportions. Mr. Zorn now presents selections from his fathomless oeuvre at the school's Miller Theater, including chamber works, Masada miniatures and ''Cobra,'' his celebrated game piece. At 7:30 p.m., Miller Theater, Columbia University, Broadway at 116th Street, Morningside Heights, (212) 854-7799, millertheatre.com; $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>* 'IL BARBIERE DI SIVIGLIA' (Thursday) This production conveys the comic confusions of the story through its fluid staging and a wonderfully abstract set: a matrix of movable doors, staircases and potted orange trees, behind which characters spy on one another. The heated sexuality of the characters also comes through strongly, thanks to Mr. Sher's subtle directing of, notably, the captivating mezzo-soprano Joyce DiDonato as a vocally agile and feisty Rosina. But some major changes are coming this week. The emerging American tenor Lawrence Brownlee makes his Met debut as Count Almaviva, and the hardy German baritone Russell Braun sings Figaro. At 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; sold out. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'La Finta Giardiniera' (Wednesday) Singers from the Juilliard Opera Center present a staged production of Mozart's first mature opera buffa, which he wrote at 18. The cast includes Erin Morley as the Marchioness. Jay Lesenger directs, and Gary Thor Wedow conducts the Juilliard Orchestra. At 8 p.m., Peter Jay Sharp Theater, Juilliard School, 155 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, juilliard.edu; $20; $10 for students and 65+. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>'FLAVIO' (Tomorrow) Candy pink and candy green set the tone for Chas Rader-Shieber's antic production of this opera, which consists of arias nestled side by side, bright and sweet as a box of fondants. Making company debuts are Katherine Rohrer, a light mezzo with a nice tone; Gerald Thompson, a promising but sometimes wild countertenor; and the conductor William Lacey, who led a strong, lithe performance on opening night. David Walker was fine as the foppish, foolish king of the title. At 8 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nycopera.com; $25 to $125. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>* 'GIULIO CESARE' (Tomorrow and Tuesday) Though its auditorium is too big for Handel, the Metropolitan Opera makes this work come alive, thanks to exceptional Handel singers. The countertenor David Daniels excels in the daunting title role, and the soprano Ruth Ann Swenson makes a vocally exquisite Cleopatra. Patricia Bardon, a rich-toned Irish mezzo-soprano, brings lyrical elegance to the role of Cornelia. Harry Bicket conducts stylishly. (On Tuesday the countertenor Lawrence Zazzo, who has been singing Tolomeo, takes over the title role; Danielle de Niese sings Cleopatra; and Jill Grove sings Cornelia.) Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., Tuesday at 7:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $220 to $375 tickets remaining for tomorrow; $15 to $175 for Tuesday. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'L'ITALIANA IN LONDRA' (Wednesday) Rossini's Italian girl got to Algiers; Cimarosa's, a generation earlier, made it only as far as London, but both were in pursuit of their beloveds. Cimarosa's opera is this year's little-known offering in the pleasingly offbeat canon of the Manhattan School of Music. Steven Mosteller conducts; Albert Sherman directs. At 8 p.m., Manhattan School of Music, Broadway at 122nd Street, Morningside Heights, (917) 493-4428, msmnyc.edu; $20; $10 for students and 65+. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>'Madama Butterfly' (Tonight and Sunday) Paul Kellogg's administration at New York City Opera ends along with the spring season in these last two performances of this Puccini crowd-pleaser. Shu-Ying Li and Christopher Jackson head the cast in a minimalist production by Mark Lamos. Tonight at 8, Sunday at 1:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nycopera.com; $25 to $93 remaining tonight, sold out on Sunday. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>'MANON LESCAUT' (Tonight through Sunday) Because of its difficulties, this early masterpiece by Puccini probably does not appear in production as often as the music merits. There are two long and demanding lead roles, crowd scenes, intimate scenes and a teeming orchestra score. The adventurous Dicapo Opera Theater is presenting a production by Michael Capasso this weekend, conducted by Pacien Mazzagatti, with rotating leads in the main roles of the impulsive Manon and her lover Des Grieux. It should be interesting to experience the opera in the company's intimate theater. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8 and Sunday at 4 p.m., 184 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212) 288-9438, dicapo.com; $47.50. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* 'IL TRITTICO' (Tonight and Monday night) The Broadway stage director Jack O'Brien has taken on two trilogies at Lincoln Center in the same year. First was Tom Stoppard's ''Coast of Utopia,'' and now he has moved on to Puccini's trilogy of dissimilar one-acters, in which he makes his debut tonight at the Met. The cast includes Salvatore Licitra, Barbara Frittoli and the inimitable Stephanie Blythe. At 8, Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $80 to $175 remaining tonight; sold out on Monday. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>'TURANDOT' (Tomorrow and Wednesday) For spectacle and big music, the Franco Zeffirelli production of Puccini's final opera, at the Met, is hard to beat. For compelling leads, you might have to look elsewhere. Erika Sunnegardh has replaced the shaky Andrea Gruber in the lead, joining Richard Margison (who does at least have the vocal heft for the role). Liping Zhang, an acclaimed Covent Garden Butterfly, has taken over as Liù, and Marco Armiliato, whose conducting seems increasingly wishy-washy this year, leads the orchestra. But spectacle and size are evidently enough to keep tickets selling briskly. Tomorrow at 8:30 p.m., Wednesday at 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; sold out tomorrow; $100 to $175 for Wednesday. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>* ACADEMY OF ANCIENT MUSIC (Thursday) Richard Egarr, the harpsichordist and conductor, was recently appointed Christopher Hogwood's successor as music director of the Academy of Ancient Music. Mr. Egarr will lead the period-instrument orchestra in three of Handel's six Concerti Grossi (Op. 3), which he recently recorded on Harmonia Mundi in warm, polished and dignified performances. The Carnegie program also includes Telemann's ''Water Music'' Suite in C and Handel's ''Water Music'' Suite in G. At 7:30 p.m., Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; sold out. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>ELAINE ALVAREZ (Sunday) The Marilyn Horne Foundation presents its final ''On Wings of Song'' recital of the season. In her enticing program, this Cuban-American soprano explores the feminine mystique through songs inspired by the Swedish folk character Ingelill, a young maiden who drowns herself out of despair over a lost love. She will sing songs by Stenhammar, Sibelius, Liszt, Strauss and Bo Linde. John Churchwell is the accompanist. At 3 p.m., St. Bartholomew's Church, Park Avenue at 50th Street, (212) 378-0248, stbarts.org; $20; $15 for 65+; free for students. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* EMANUEL AX and EDGAR MEYER (Tonight) Mingling Bach and bluegrass is standard operating procedure for Edgar Meyer, the double-bassist for whom crossover is not a marketing ploy but a natural mode of being. Plenty of mingling takes place on this program, performed with the pianist Emanuel Ax. At one end of the spectrum are Bach and Haydn, arranged for the players' respective instruments; at the other are New York premieres of works by Mr. Meyer; Bright Sheng, the acclaimed Chinese composer; and the mandolin player Chris Thile, a former prodigy and an artist rapidly becoming as diverse as Mr. Meyer himself. At 7:30, Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800; $48 and $54. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>BENJAMIN BAGBY (Sunday) Relying on hefty research and a bit of inspired guesswork, Mr. Bagby offers his re-creation of the ancient Bardic tradition in dramatic performances of ''Beowulf.'' At 1 p.m., the Cloisters, Fort Tryon Park, Washington Heights, (212) 650-2290, metmuseum.org; $35. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* BROOKLYN PHILHARMONIC (Tomorrow) Stefan Asbury, a conductor who has done superb work leading new-music programs at Tanglewood, steps onto the Brooklyn Philharmonic podium to lead Julia Wolfe's ''My Beautiful Scream,'' performed with the Kronos Quartet; Vaughan Williams's ''Fantasia on the Theme of Thomas Tallis''; and Holst's ''Planets.'' At 8 p.m., Brooklyn Academy of Music, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, (718) 636-4100, brooklynphilharmonic.org; $20 to $60. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>CHANTICLEER (Thursday) This all-male vocal ensemble will give the premiere of its latest commission, ''And on Earth, Peace: A Chanticleer Mass,'' for which five diverse composers each contributed a movement. The American composer Douglas J. Cuomo wrote the Kyrie; the Turkish-American composer Kamran Ince wrote the Gloria section to a Sufi text; Michael McGlynn, who is Irish, contributed the Agnus Dei; Ivan Moody, a Briton, wrote the Sanctus; and the Israeli-American composer Shulamit Ran wrote the Credo. At 8 p.m., Temple of Dendur, the Metropolitan Museum of Art, (212) 570-3949, metmuseum.org; $70. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* COMPOSER PORTRAIT: KIMMO HAKOLA (Tuesday) The Miller Theater's Composer Portraits is a kind of stealth series, since the concerts spotlight not only a composer, but also a performing ensemble. The composer, in this case, is the energetic Kimmo Hakola, whose music is getting its first large-scale treatment in New York; the ensemble is Present Music, an enterprising new-music group based in Milwaukee, conducted by Kevin Stalheim, which commissioned one of the works on the program. At 8 p.m., Broadway at 116th Street, Morningside Heights, (212) 854-7799, millertheater.com; $25; $15 for students. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>* EARLY MUSIC NEW YORK (Tomorrow) Frederick Renz leads his period-instrument chamber orchestra in an all-Haydn program that includes three symphonies -- No. 26 (''Lamentatione''), No. 30 (''Alleluia'') and No. 83 (''La Poule'') -- as well as a Concerto for Two Flutes and a Divertimento for Winds. At 8 p.m., St. James's Church, Madison Avenue at 71st Street, (212) 280-0330, earlymusicny.org; $40; $20 for students. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* QUINN KELSEY (Tonight) Born and raised in Honolulu, this baritone has been making his name in the vocal music and opera worlds. A recipient of a career grant from the Richard Tucker Foundation, Mr. Kelsey will sing works by Handel, Brahms, Finzi and Mussorgsky with the pianist Tamara Sanikidze. The event is presented by Carnegie Hall and the Marilyn Horne Foundation. At 7:30, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $30 and $34. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>KREMERATA BALTICA (Monday) Gidon Kremer's eclectic chamber band offers some of its specialties, from Beethoven (the Grosse Fuge) and Schumann (a violin version of the Cello Concerto) to Korngold (the Symphonic Serenade) and Piazzolla (''Las Cuatro Estaciones Porteñas''). At 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $23 to $72. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* MIDORI (Tuesday) This adventurous violinist and champion of contemporary music offers the New York premiere of Einojuhani Rautavaara's ''Lost Landscapes.'' She commissioned the work in 2005 and performed its world premiere in Munich last year with the pianist Robert McDonald, who accompanies her here. The program also includes Beethoven's ''Spring'' Sonata, Hindemith's Sonata in E flat and Strauss's Sonata in E flat. At 8 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $30 to $60. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>NEW JUILLIARD ENSEMBLE (Tonight) Joel Sachs leads his expert student ensemble in an international program of premieres, including works by Seppo Pohjola, from Finland; Snorri Sigfus Birgisson, from Iceland; Gerald Barry, from Ireland; Farangis Nurulla-Khoja, from Tajikistan; and Raymond J. Lustig, from the United States. At 8, Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 769-7406, juilliard.edu; free, but tickets are required. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC (Wednesday and Thursday) Lorin Maazel, the music director, conducts two exercises in orchestral luxury: Stravinsky's ''Chant du Rossignol'' and the second of Ravel's ''Daphnis et Chloé'' Suites. He also leads the admirable Anne-Sophie Mutter in Berg's Violin Concerto. At 7:30 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nyphil.org; $33 to $99. (Holland)</p>
        <p>GIL SHAHAM AND FRIENDS (Tomorrow) This omnipresent and very talented violinist joins eight colleagues, including the mezzo-soprano Michelle DeYoung, in a not-your-everyday Brahms program: the Horn Trio, two songs with viola and piano, and the Clarinet Quintet. At 7:30 p.m., Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; sold out. (Holland)</p>
        <p>UBS VERBIER FESTIVAL CHAMBER ORCHESTRA (Tonight) This chamber orchestra, whose members are chosen from the best members and alumni of the UBS Verbier Festival Orchestra, will perform Mozart concertos with the violinist Maxim Vengerov as soloist and conductor. The program includes the Violin Concertos Nos. 2 and 4 (K. 211 and 218), with Mr. Vengerov's own cadenzas, and the Sinfonia Concertante in E flat (K. 364), with the violist Lawrence Power -- repertory this group recently recorded for a new disc on EMI. At 8, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $28 to $96. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>VERMEER QUARTET (Wednesday) The Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center presents the Vermeer in string quartets by Schubert, Britten and Dvorak. This is the last of a season-long series. At 7:30 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5788, chambermusicsociety.org; $30 to $52. (Holland)</p>
        <p>* YOUNG PEOPLE'S CHORUS OF NEW YORK CITY (Tomorrow) Francisco J. Núñez, the music director of this chorus, has long believed that at an early age, musicians should develop, and benefit from, associations with established composers. The group's ''Transient Glory'' program offers premieres of works written for the young choristers by Ned Rorem, Bruce Adolphe, Michael Gordon, Meredith Monk and Tarik O'Regan. At 7:30 p.m., 92nd Street Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue, (212) 415-5500, ypc.org; $25; $10 for parents and students. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>* AILEY II (Tonight through Sunday) Alvin Ailey created a second, or junior, company in 1974, almost casually, as a way of working on new choreography. Ailey II is now a world-class troupe, filled with dancers who are not only good but also capable of performing with a youthful hunger, as well as with a reverence for dance that is a part of the mission of the company director, Sylvia Waters, whom Ailey himself chose to direct that first group. Now Ailey II is coming home, performing in the black-box theater that is part of the Ailey headquarters: newer, grander and more gleaming than Ailey ever envisioned. The repertory will include new dances by Abdel Salaam, Darrell Grand Moultrie and Jessica Lang, along with Ailey's ''Streams'' and a chunk of Ailey highlights. Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 3 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 3 and 7:30 p.m., Ailey Citigroup Theater, 405 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444, alvinailey.org; $40; $10 student rush tickets available. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>BEST OF THE BOROUGHS: NIA LOVE/BLACKSMITH'S DAUGHTER DANCE THEATER (Tonight through Sunday) Ms. Love represents dance in this festival, and if past programs are any guide, she will do that with a maximum of heat and wit. Tonight at 7, tomorrow at 9:30 p.m., Sunday at 7:30 p.m., Performance Space 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101, ps122.org; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>JANE COMFORT (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ms. Comfort can be depended on for thought-provoking dance and theater pieces, often explorations of politics and sexuality. At 8:30, Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, symphonyspace.org; $21. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CONFIGURATION DANCE (Tuesday) From Cape Cod and unaccountably headed south, this company will perform dances by Michael Shannon, Sasha Janes, Yuri Zhukov and Harrison McEldowney, the resident choreographer of the company, which is directed by Joseph Cipolla, formerly of the Birmingham Royal Ballet in England. At 8 p.m., Ailey Citigroup Theater, 405 West 55th Street, Clinton, (877) 238-5596, smarttix.com; $25; $15 for students. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>DANCE AT DIXON PLACE (Tuesday and Thursday) On Tuesday Marcia Monroe's ''Crossing Boundaries'' series will focus on choreography by Steinunn Ketilsdottir, Josefina Diels, Javier Dzul and Lisa Parra. On Thursday Edisa Weeks's Delirious Dance Company will perform ''Liaisons,'' which explores the degrees of closeness among strangers. (Delirious Dance through April 28.) At 8 p.m., Dixon Place, 258 Bowery, between Houston and Prince Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 219-0736, dixonplace.org; $12; $10 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>DANCE AT DNA (Tonight through Sunday, and Thursday) The theater's ''OB.ject.ob.JECT'' series of choreography by women runs through Sunday. Faye Driscoll's ''Wow, Mom, Wow'' follows on Thursday and runs through April 29. Ms. Driscoll describes the piece as ''postmodern dance meets pop musical meets death-metal fantasy.'' Tonight, tomorrow and Thursday nights at 8, Sunday at 3 p.m., Dance New Amsterdam, 280 Broadway, at Chambers Street, TriBeCa, (212) 279-4200, dnadance.org; $20 (''OB.ject'') and $17 (Driscoll). (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* EIFMAN BALLET OF ST. PETERSBURG (Tonight through Thursday) There is no one in world dance quite like Boris Eifman, for better or for worse. Whatever else he is, Mr. Eifman is a theatrical genius whose ballets are almost always flamboyant fun. This week the company will perform his new ''Seagull,'' after the Chekhov play, through Sunday, followed by ''Russian Hamlet'' on Wednesday and Thursday. (Through April 29.) Tonight and Wednesday and Thursday nights at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 2 and 7 p.m., City Center, 131 West 55th Street, Manhattan, (212) 581-1212, nycitycenter.org; $35 to $100. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>GENDER BENDER: MONICA BILL BARNES AND NICHOLASLEICHTERDANCE (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ms. Barnes's modern-dance choreography is known for its theatricality and knowing humor. And Mr. Leichter explores race and sex with provocative pairings of dancers in work that draws from traditional and street-dance styles. At 8:30, Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, symphonyspace.org; $17 to $25. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>KENNEDY DANCERS (Thursday) Based in Jersey City, this modern-dance troupe will celebrate its 30th anniversary with a program of dances by the company director, Diane Dragone, with one work by a different guest group each night. Donna Scro Gentile's Freespace Dance will perform at the opening. (Through April 28.) At 7:30 p.m., Baryshnikov Arts Center, 450 West 37th Street, Manhattan, (201) 659-2190; $20; $18 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Peter Kyle Dance (Tonight through Sunday night) Peter Kyle was a longtime dancer with Alwin Nikolais and Murray Louis, and he now makes intelligent, humorous work that seems to be frequently inspired by literature. This program of new pieces features ''Nearer'' and ''Fallow Bogs,'' both with live music; and ''On the Divide,'' inspired by Willa Cather's ''O Pioneers.'' At 8, Joyce Soho, 155 Mercer Street, (212) 334-7479; $15; $10 for students. (Roslyn Sulcas)</p>
        <p>* LAR LUBOVITCH DANCE COMPANY (Tonight and tomorrow night) Known for the rich flow of his modern-dance choreography, Mr. Lubovitch and his eloquent dancers will present two programs, which include ''Little Rhapsodies,'' with Rasta Thomas, a guest dancer, and Pedja Muzijevic, who will play the piece's Schumann piano score, as well as the music for ''Dvorak Serenade in E.'' Tonight's gala program also includes ''Recordare,'' performed by the Limón Dance Company At 8, Skirball Center for the Performing Arts, 566 LaGuardia Place, at Washington Square South, Greenwich Village, (212) 279-4200, www.skirballcenter.nyu.edu; $250, $500 and $1,000 tonight; $45 tomorrow. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>BARBARA MAHLER (Tonight through Sunday) ''There's No Place Like Home''' features choreography distinguished by tight focus and strong physicality. At 8:30, Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194, danspaceproject.org; $15. (Jack Anderson)</p>
        <p>LA MAMA MOVES! (Thursday) More than 50 companies and soloists, chosen by Nicky Paraiso and Mia Yoo, will perform in this celebration of downtown dance, in programs that will spill out throughout the nooks and crannies of the funky La MaMa complex. The festival opens with ''New Virtuosity,'' a program that includes dances by Robert Battle, Patrick Corbin, Tynek Dusan, Sunhwa Chung and Nick Seligson-Ross. At 7:30 p.m., La MaMa, 74A East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 475-7710, lamama.org; $15; $10 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>GLORIA MCLEAN (Sunday) Ms. McLean, a leading dancer with Erick Hawkins, will present ''Fossil Garden,'' a piece that unfolds amid a sculpture installation by Ken Hiratsuka. The program, which includes a video and sound installation by Jack Waters and Peter Cramer, takes place in Mr. Hiratsuka's basement studio. At 5 p.m., 516 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 529-5660; donation suggested. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* NEW YORK CITY BALLET (Tuesday through Thursday) The company opens its two-month spring season with the first of six performances that will pay tribute to the centenary of Lincoln Kirstein, co-founder of City Ballet with George Balanchine, and the founder and longtime director of the School of American Ballet. Eight of the 10 tribute ballets, all choreographed by Balanchine, will be presented in three programs this week, including ''The Four Temperaments,'' ''Pavane,'' ''Agon,'' ''Symphony in C,'' ''Concerto Barocco,'' ''Duo Concertant,'' ''Square Dance'' and ''Symphony in Three Movements.'' Tuesday and Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 870-5570; (800) 580-8730, nycballet.com; $15 to $95. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* Stephen Petronio Company (Tuesday through Thursday) Stephen Petronio has a reputation for making provocative, sexually charged dances, but his work can often be as much about identity as about sexuality. A new solo, ''For Today I Am a Boy,'' is set to the music of the avant-garde British singer Antony, and seems set to explore such issues. Also on the program are another new piece, ''Without You II''; a revival of Mr. Petronio's 1997 ''ReBourne''; ''The Ship Song,'' (part of a work made in 2003 for the Sydney Dance company); and last year's enjoyable ''Bud Suite.'' Tuesday and Wednesday at 7.30 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800, joyce.org; $40; $30 for Joyce members. (Roslyn Sulcas)</p>
        <p>PMT SHOWCASE (Tomorrow and Sunday) The program will feature dance by David Kieffer, Kai Kleinbard, Yesid Lopez, Ami Mattison, Brenda Neville and Pavan Thimmaiah, the hip-hopster who produced the showcase. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Sunday at 2:30 p.m., Martin Luther King Jr. High School, 122 Amsterdam Avenue, at 65th Street, Manhattan, (212) 924-5694; $16; $10 for students. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>QUEENS THEATER ASIAN CULTURAL FESTIVAL: KUN-YANG LIN/DANCERS (Tonight) Mr. Lin is one of many Asian crossover choreographers, but his distinctive blend of traditional and Western dance has the dark, bold force of a woodcut print. At 8, Queens Theater in the Park, Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, Queens, (718) 760-0064, queenstheatre.org; $28; $26 for 65+; $20 for students. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>WORKS AND PROCESS AT THE GUGGENHEIM: 'SLOW DANCING' (Sunday and Monday) Subtitled ''Motion Portraits of Dancers,'' this program of larger-than-life, slow-motion video portraits by David Michalek will focus on dancers including Desmond Richardson, Wendy Whelan and Herman Cornejo, with a panel discussion including Mr. Michalek and Nigel Redden, director of the Lincoln Center Festival. At 7:30 p.m., Guggenheim Museum, 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3587, worksandprocess.org. On Sunday: $24, $20 for members and 65+., $15 for students. Monday is sold out. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'KINDRED SPIRITS: ASHER B. DURAND AND THE AMERICAN LANDSCAPE,' through July 29. This show of about 60 works by one of the greats of 19th-century American landscape painting has as its centerpiece ''Kindred Spirits'' (1849), a tribute to the landscapist Thomas Cole and his friend the poet-journalist William Cullen Bryant. A founder of the Hudson River School, Durand (1796-1886) favored the realistic approach to landscape advocated by the English critic John Ruskin. Durand explored forest interiors with close attention to the ways of trees, foliage and rocks and ground cover in smaller works, while his larger and more elaborate exhibition pictures, influenced by European masters, are Arcadian visions suffused with light, color and atmospheric perspective. If the show reveals some of Durand's weaknesses -- repetitive themes and borrowings from other artists -- it also reveals his strong sense of artistic mission and his potent role in shaping the aesthetic of 19th-century America. 200 Eastern Parkway, Brooklyn, (718) 638-5000, brooklynmuseum.org. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>FRICK COLLECTION: 'GEORGE STUBBS (1724-1806): A CELEBRATION,' through May 27. One of the finest horse painters ever, Stubbs knew his subjects from head to hoof and skin to bones. He painted other mammals too: dogs, lions, tigers, oxen, monkeys and humans. This intimate show of 17 Stubbs paintings from English collections reveals his admirable range, although the people he portrayed in two large, late canvases, elegiac celebrations of farm workers raking and reaping grain, have the stiffness of figures on a candy box. His horses are his true monuments. 1 East 70th Street, Manhattan, (212) 288-0700, frick.org. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* JAPAN SOCIETY: 'Awakenings: Zen Figure Painting in Medieval Japan,' through June 17. Japan Society has a history of producing exquisite shows of Buddhist art. And this one, with four dozen paintings of Buddhists gods and saints hung in shrinelike alcoves, is transporting. And it covers an unusually broad swath of geography, bringing together 13th- to 16th-century hanging scrolls, not only from Japan but also from China, where Zen Buddhism, called Chan in Chinese, originated. 333 East 47th Street, (212) 832-1155, japansociety.org. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>The Jewish Museum: Dateline: Israel: 'New Photography and Video Art,' through Aug. 5. Roughly every decade, the Jewish Museum offers a survey of contemporary art from and about Israel. This year non-Israeli artists from Europe and the United States -- and a single artist from Palestine -- have been added to the mix. There's some very good work here, though, on the whole, the show grapples with crucial political issues in an indirect way. 1109 Fifth Avenue, at 92nd Street, (212) 423-3200, jewishmuseum.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* the Metropolitan Museum of Art : 'Journeys: Mapping the Earth and Mind in Chinese Art,' through Aug. 26. Every six months or so, the Met rotates all the work in its Chinese painting galleries to preserve the delicate silks and papers, and each time, the curator in charge, Maxwell K. Hearn, produces a new and illuminating thematic exhibition, as is the case with ''Journeys.'' Outward-bound and inward-bound are the directions taken by Chinese landscape painting, and it carries us on some fascinating voyages in a show that mixes classical and contemporary art. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* the met: 'Venice and the Islamic World, 828-1797,' through July 8. At its peak in the Renaissance, Venice, the Most Serene, was a giant, clamorous Costco-on-the-Rialto. All the necessities, and most of the luxuries, of life flowed into and through it, with many items arriving from Islamic Africa and the Near East. With classic Met largesse, this exhibition suggests the spectacle of two different cultures meeting in one fantastic city, in which commerce and love of beauty, those great levelers, unite them in a fruitful bond. (See above.) (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Museum of Contemporary American Diasporan Arts: 'Postmillennial Black Madonna,' through May 13. This group show of young artists takes various approaches to the female figure as myth and symbol in contemporary African-American cultures. 80 Hanson Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0492. A complementary show is at the Skylight Gallery of the Restoration Plaza, 1368 Fulton Street, third floor, Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn, (718) 636-6976, through May 5, mocada.org or postbme.com. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* Museum of Modern Art: JEFF WALL, through May 14. This majestic show makes a great case for Mr. Wall as the most complete, if traditional, of the untraditional artists who emerged from the turmoil of Conceptual Art. His often immense color transparencies mounted on light boxes are enthralling vehicles, intent on giving pleasure while making a point or two about society, art, history, visual perception, the human animal or all of the above. An imposing blend of painting, street photography and movies, they blur reality and artifice, narrative and form, detail and the big statement. You can't stop looking at them. (212) 708-9400, moma.org (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>Whitney Museum of American Art: 'Taryn Simon,' through June 24. Ms. Simon couches the show in the intellectual, power-to-the-people oratory of leftist politics, yet she clearly delights in exposing, in a quasi-tabloid fashion, America's underbelly. Though she has also worked in war-torn areas, Ms. Simon is best known for ''The Innocents,'' a series of portraits of men and women who were wrongly convicted but later cleared by DNA test results. Ms. Simon can work as long as a year to gain permission to photograph high-security zones like the government-regulated quarantine sites, nuclear waste storage facilities, prison death rows and C.I.A. offices on view in the show. There are also pictures with lighter themes: the sandpit where the Grucci family tests fireworks, ski slopes being dynamited for avalanche control and the second Death Star, from ''Return of the Jedi,'' at George Lucas's Skywalker Ranch. Ms. Simon is at her artistic best when her delight in the strangeness of American culture shines. (212) 570-3676, whitney.org. (Bridget Goodbody)</p>
        <p>* Whitney Museum of American Art: 'Lorna Simpson,' through May 6. This tight, refined and impassioned survey covers more than 20 years of Lorna Simpson's career, from her photo-and-text meditations on race and sexism in the 1980s, to her more recent short films, which unite American history and personal history in forceful and lyrical ways. It would be easy to put some of this work on a shelf as ''identity art,'' but with an African-American woman holding one of the highest offices in the United States government, an African-American man running for president, and the nation embroiled in what some people view as an ethnic war, this art is entirely of the moment. (See above.) (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>* Nancy Brooks Brody Some of the abstract ''paintings'' in this beautiful, reticent solo show have been stitched with cotton thread onto paper, creating patterns of linear ridges. Others are made from painstakingly detailed pencil patterns on plaster. The effect is like having Agnes Martin's bars and bands transmitted as sound waves, a soft, vibrant humming. Ms. Brody's sculptures of stacked bars of bath soap, used but not used up, are right in the poetic picture. Virgil de Voldère Gallery, 526 West 26th Street, Room 416, (212) 343-9694, virgilgallery.com, through April 28. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* WALTER DE MARIA Counting and space -- important to both Minimal and Conceptual Art -- come together with unusual clarity, if a bit too much in the way of gleaming metal, in two large installations by the creator of ''The Lightning Field'' earthwork. Both pieces consist of several dozen shiny meter-long stainless-steel rods presented in spaces that couldn't be much more pristine. Experience the spatial levitation and note the number of sides on the rods; in both cases, they increase row by row. Gagosian Gallery, 522 West 21st Street, (212) 741-1717, and 555 West 24th Street, (212) 741-1111, gagosian.com, through May 5. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* JONATHAN MONK: 'SOME KIND OF GAME BETWEEN THIS AND THAT' As usual, this Conceptually inclined Scottish artist concentrates on sly tributes to, or plays on, works by other artists, among them Bruce Nauman, Chris Burden, John Baldessari and René Magritte. The slightest pieces are best, including drawings done on old books and ''The Cheat,'' in which ''this'' and ''that'' consist of an early silent film accompanied by a boom box tuned to a classical music station. Casey Kaplan, 525 West 21st Street, (212) 645-7335, caseykaplangallery.com, through May 5.(Smith)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Other</p>
        <p>'Gifts of the Forest: Native Traditions in Wood and Bark' Drawn from the collections of the Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center in Connecticut, this show celebrates the trees of the rich forests that once covered the Northeast, yielding essential materials to the Pequot and other Eastern Woodland cultures. The objects run from ancient woodworking tools to contemporary objects that carry on tribal traditions, like the simple and beautiful wooden flute made in 1999 by Hawk Henires (Nipmuc) and adorned with an elegantly carved bird motif. Many things here were made in the 19th and 20th centuries: handsome woven baskets, carved bowls and spoons, decorated cradle boards for carrying babies, birch bark canoe models, an elegant birch-bark hamper whose sides bear a stylized tree motif. UBS Art Gallery, 1285 Avenue of the Americas, between 51st and 52nd Streets, (212) 713-2885, ubs.com, through April 27. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* Chelsea Art Museum: 'DANGEROUS BEAUTY' A somewhat timely update of a well-worn idea, this show of contemporary works in a variety of mediums by 18 artists examines the beauty myth in art, advertising and the fashion industry. Eloquent but blunt imagery of anorexic girls, chiseled male beefcake and close-ups of surgically deformed faces predominates, reminding us of the violent extremes to which some people will go in pursuit of society's ideal of beauty and a designer body. The rest of the show -- often pointing an accusatory finger at skinny models, cosmetic labels and the mass media -- feels familiar in its critique, but the basic premise about the ideology of beauty in our culture is beyond argument. 556 West 22nd Street, (212) 255-0719, chelseaartmuseum.org., closes tomorrow. (Benjamin Genocchio)</p>
        <p>* JOAN JONAS An extraordinary double show from a performance-installation-video artist who emerged in the late 1960s and has only gotten better. The centerpiece is a walk-in-collage of sculpture, props and video projections derived from a new performance work, ''The Shape, the Scent, the Feel of Things,'' accompanied by a film of the performance. Based on a memoir by the art historian Aby Warburg, and accompanied by music composed and played by the jazz pianist Jason Moran, it combines a Fluxus playfulness with task-oriented gestures of early '70s dance to achieve a mysterious visual poetry reminiscent of Joseph Cornell, decanted. Yvon Lambert New York, 550 West 21st Street and 564 West 25th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-3611, yvon-lambert.com; closes on Thursday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* National Academy Museum: HIGH TIMES, HARD TIMES: NEW YORK PAINTING, 1967-1975 Organized under the auspices of International Curators Incorporated, this brave if confused exhibition is the first to tackle a neglected subject: New York painting during the period it was supposed to be dead. The show's 42 works by 37 artists reveal that, far from dead, painting was in fact in an uproar that was commensurate with the artistic, social and political turbulence of the times. The alternation between artists who remained loyal in their way to stretched canvas and those who abandoned it, which makes for clear installation, also tidies up history. The main problem is that the exhibition sticks too purposefully to the margins, mixing generations and levels of achievement and continuing the neglect of the main story. Too much of this work is as derivative now as it was then, and functions more as artifact than art. 1083 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 369-4880, nationalacademy.org; closes on Sunday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* 'PAINTINGS, FLAGS &amp; IRON: HAITIAN ART FROM THE LAST FIFTY YEARS' This splendid exhibition offers total immersion in the originality and continued vitality of Haiti's self-taught artists. Works by well-known painters like Hector Hyppolite, Toussaint Auguste and Rigaud Benoit range across religion, history and everyday themes. They include still lifes, landscapes and Pierre Joseph Valcin's enthralling rendering of a maternity ward. The forged and welded sculptures of Georges Liautaud and Gabriel Bien-Aimé are on a par with Bill Traylor's antic silhouette drawings. And there are no words for the extravagantly sequined and beaded flags depicting Voodoo spirits and saints, except fabulous. Edward Thorp Gallery, 210 11th Avenue, at 25th Street, Chelsea, (212) 691-6565, edwardthorpgallery.com; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'AMERICAN FIESTA' In previews; opens on Thursday. Steven Tomlinson's new play, directed by Mark Brokaw, is about an avid collector of ceramic dinnerware whose family disapproves of his same-sex marriage (1:30). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 353-0303.</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY ON THE VINE' Previews start on Tuesday. Opens on May 2. Zak Berkman's romantic fable follows a man falling in love with a budding star of right-wing radio (2:10). Clurman Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'CORAM BOY' In previews; opens on May 2. An adaptation of Jamila Gavin's novel about two orphans is the latest National Theater hit to move from London to Broadway (2:30). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'DIXIE'S TUPPERWARE PARTY' In previews; opens on May 10. Dixie Wingate has left her Alabama trailer park to sell Tupperware in New York in this irreverent comedy. Ars Nova, 511 West 54th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444.</p>
        <p>'DEUCE' In previews; opens on May 6. The grandes dames Angela Lansbury and Marian Seldes play retired tennis players in this new Terrence McNally comedy. Michael Blakemore directs. Music Box Theater, 239 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'FROST/NIXON' In previews; opens on Sunday. Frank Langella plays Richard M. Nixon in this acclaimed London transfer about the famous post-Watergate interview. With Michael Sheen. (1:40). Jacobs Theater, 242 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'THE J.A.P. SHOW: JEWISH AMERICAN PRINCESSES of comedy' Expect healthy amounts of whining and kvetching at this comedy showcase featuring four funny women, including Jackie Hoffman (''Hairspray'') (1:30). Actors Temple Theater, 339 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'JANE EYRE' Previews start on Monday. Opens on Tuesday. The Acting Company presents a new adaptation of Charlotte Brontë's classic (2:45). Baruch Performing Arts Center's Nagelberg Theater, 55 Lexington Avenue, at 25th Street, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'LEGALLY BLONDE' In previews; opens on April 29. Laura Bell Bundy plays the smiling, ditsy sorority girl who takes Harvard Law by storm in this musical adaptation. Jerry Mitchell directs (2:20). Palace Theater, 1564 Broadway, at 47th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'LOVEMUSIK' In previews; opens on May 3. The Tony winners Michael Cerveris and Donna Murphy star in a musical about the relationship between Kurt Weill and Lotte Lenya (with songs by Weill). Harold Prince directs (2:30). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'110 IN THE SHADE' In previews; opens on May 9. Audra McDonald stars in the Roundabout's revival of the musical version of N. Richard Nash's ''Rainmaker.'' Studio 54, 254 West 54th Street, (212) 719-1300.</p>
        <p>'RADIO GOLF' Previews start today. Opens on May 8. The last play in August Wilson's cycle is set in 1997 and centers on the vital question of what will be done with the fabled Aunt Esther's house. Tonya Pinkins (''Caroline, or Change'') stars (2:30). Cort Theater, 138 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'REALISM' and 'JUMP!' The first play has opened; the second opens on Thursday. The Exchange, formerly known as the Jean Cocteau Rep, presents in repertory these new works by emerging British writers (1:30 each). Kirk Theater, 420 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'A CHORUS LINE' If you want to know why this show was such a big deal when it opened 31 years ago, you need only experience the thrilling first five minutes of this revival. Otherwise, this archivally exact production, directed by Bob Avian, feels like a vintage car that has been taken out of the garage, polished up and sent on the road once again (2:00). Schoenfeld Theater, 236 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE COAST OF UTOPIA' Lincoln Center Theater's brave, gorgeous, sprawling and ultimately exhilarating production of Tom Stoppard's trilogy about intellectuals errant in 19th-century Russia. A testament to the seductive powers of narrative theater, directed with hot and cool canniness by Jack O'Brien and featuring a starry cast (Brian F. O'Byrne, Jennifer Ehle, Martha Plimpton, Josh Hamilton and Ethan Hawke, among others) in a tasty assortment of roles. Vivian Beaumont Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'COMPANY' Fire, beckoning and dangerous, flickers beneath the frost of John Doyle's elegant, unexpectedly stirring revival of Stephen Sondheim and George Furth's era-defining musical from 1970, starring a compellingly understated Raúl Esparza. Like Mr. Doyle's ''Sweeney Todd,'' this production finds new clarity of feeling in Sondheim by melding the roles of performers and musicians (2:20). Barrymore Theater, 243 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CURTAINS' This musical comedy about a musical-comedy murder -- featuring songs by John Kander and Fred Ebb and a book by Rupert Holmes -- lies on the stage like a promisingly gaudy string of firecrackers, waiting in vain for a match. The good news is that David Hyde Pierce, playing a diffident Boston detective, steps into full-fledged Broadway stardom. Scott Ellis directs a talent-packed cast that includes Debra Monk and Karen Ziemba. (2:30). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920s stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, it has theatergoers responding as if they were withering houseplants finally being watered after long neglect. (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'GREY GARDENS' Christine Ebersole is absolutely glorious as the middle-aged, time-warped debutante called Little Edie Beale in this uneven musical adaptation of the notorious 1975 documentary of the same title. She and the wonderful Mary Louise Wilson (as her bedridden mother), in the performances of their careers, make ''Grey Gardens'' an experience no passionate theatergoer should miss (2:40). Walter Kerr Theater, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HOWARD KATZ' The subject of Patrick Marber's comedy of unhappiness about a rabid talent agent, starring a baleful Alfred Molina and directed by Doug Hughes, is nothing more nor less than your standard-issue midlife crisis. This familiar topic gets the better of all the talented people here trying to make it seem fresh (1:30). Laura Pels Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'INHERIT THE WIND' Doug Hughes's wooden revival of this worthy war horse, based on the Scopes ''monkey'' trial of 1925, never musters much more velocity than that of a drugstore fan. Be grateful that the cast includes Christopher Plummer, in savory form as a Will Rogers of jurisprudence. An oddly subdued Brian Dennehy plays his pompous adversary (2:00). Lyceum Theater, 149 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'JOURNEY'S END' A splendid revival of R. C. Sherriff's 1928 drama of life in the trenches during World War I. Acutely staged (by David Grindley) and acted by a fine ensemble led by Hugh Dancy and Boyd Gaines, this production offers an exemplary presentation of that theatrical rarity, an uncompromising, clear-eyed play about war and the experience of day-to-day combat. An essential ticket (2:40). Belasco Theater, 111 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MARY POPPINS' This handsome, homily-packed, mechanically ingenious and rather tedious musical, adapted from the P. L. Travers stories and the 1964 film, is ultimately less concerned with inexplicable magic than with practical psychology. Ashley Brown, who sings prettily as the family-mending nanny, looks like Joan Crawford trying to be nice and sounds like Dr. Phil. Directed by Richard Eyre and Matthew Bourne (2:30). New Amsterdam Theater, 214 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LES MISÉRABLES' This premature revival, a slightly scaled-down version of the well-groomed behemoth that closed only three years ago, appears to be functioning in a state of mild sedation. Appealingly sung and freshly orchestrated, this fast-moving adaptation of Victor Hugo's novel isn't sloppy or blurry. But its pulse rate stays well below normal (2:55). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'A MOON FOR THE MISBEGOTTEN' Kevin Spacey gives a bizarre, beat-the-clock performance, as lively as a frog on a hot plate, as James Tyrone in this off-kilter revival of Eugene O'Neill's last play. Mercifully, he does not block the view of Eve Best, who maps the contradictory levels of Tyrone's strapping love interest with clarity and intelligence (2:50). Brooks Atkinson Theater, 256 West 47th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PIRATE QUEEN' How to river-dance your way to the bottom of the ocean, courtesy of the songwriters of ''Les Misérables'' (2:30). Hilton Theater, 213 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' Duncan Sheik and Steven Sater's bold adaptation of the Frank Wedekind play is the freshest and most exciting new musical Broadway has seen in some time. Set in 19th-century Germany but with a ravishing rock score, it exposes the splintered emotional lives of adolescents just discovering the joys and sorrows of sex. Performed with brio by a great cast, with supple direction by Michael Mayer and inventive choreography by Bill T. Jones (2:00). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'TALK RADIO' The most lacerating portrait of a human meltdown this side of a Francis Bacon painting. Playing an abrasive radio talk show host with a God complex, the astounding Liev Schreiber seems to fill the air as inescapably as weather in Robert Falls's gut-grabbing revival of Eric Bogosian's 1987 play (1:40). Longacre Theater, 220 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN'  This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a superdeluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE YEAR OF MAGICAL THINKING' Joan Didion's arresting but ultimately frustrating adaptation of her best-selling memoir about being blindsided by grief, starring Vanessa Redgrave. The tension between style and emotional content that made the book such a stunner does not translate to the stage. The substance here is in the silences, when the focus shifts from words to Ms. Redgrave's wry, wounded face (1:40). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'ANNE OF GREEN GABLES' The trick to refashioning beloved children's books for the stage is to keep both the spirit and the story largely intact. In this, Gretchen Cryer and Nancy Ford -- a musical-theater partnership of five decades' standing, who have moved from their hit ''I'm Getting My Act Together'' to the American Girl demographic -- have largely succeeded. This breezy, upbeat musical avoids slickness and gets the job done, and is nicely cast into the bargain (1:30). The Lucille Lortel Theater, 121 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 279-4200. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>* 'APOSTASY' Gino Dilorio's fearless play about a dying white Jewish woman who falls under the spell of a black televangelist is pretty good; the acting that delivers it is terrific, especially Susan Greenhill as the woman, and Susan Louise O'Connor as her daughter (2:00). Urban Stages, 259 West 30th Street, (212) 868-4444. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'THE BIG VOICE: GOD OR MERMAN?' Think of two gifted and smart gay men with years of life together deploying their considerable talents from the two pianos you happen to have in your living room. The result is a hilarious and very touching memoir of two decades of love and the funky glories of show business life (2:00). Actors Temple Theater, 339 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Honor Moore)</p>
        <p>'BILL W. AND DR. BOB' This insightful new play about the founders of Alcoholics Anonymous subtly makes the claim that the recovery movement was born as a series of accidents. Patrick Husted is excellent as Bob Smith, Bill Wilson's partner in combating addictions (2:15). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Ginia Bellafante)</p>
        <p>* 'BLACKBIRD'  David Harrower's stunning new drama looks back at a sexual relationship -- between a 40-year-old man and a 12-year-old girl -- that transforms, cripples and paralyzes. Jeff Daniels and Alison Pill, both extraordinary, peel their characters down to their barest souls. Joe Mantello is the masterly director (1:30). Manhattan Theater Club at City Center Stage I, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DEFENDER OF THE FAITH' This grim tale by Stuart Carolan of low-level I.R.A. agitators trying to identify the informer in their midst features some visceral performances and a set by Charles Corcoran that makes excellent use of the Irish Rep's small stage. If only the cause itself didn't feel so small in these days of global terrorism (1:30). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>* 'DYING CITY' Christopher Shinn's crafty and unsettling play about grief and violence, set in the shadow of the Iraq war. Directed by James Macdonald and fiercely acted by Pablo Schreiber and Rebecca Brooksher, this quiet, transfixing production turns passive aggression into a theatrical dynamic (1:30). Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-7600. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'EXITS AND ENTRANCES'  Athol Fugard casts a tender glance back at an actor whose dedication to theater helped spark his own in this warm if insubstantial stage memoir. Morlan Higgins capably excavates the emotional core of a role that might have seemed generic, playing an aging gay actor reckoning with the end of an up-and-down career. William Dennis Hurley plays the Fugard stand-in (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'IN THE HEIGHTS' Lin-Manuel Miranda's joyous songs paint a vibrant portrait of daily life in Washington Heights in this flawed but enjoyable show. Essentially a valentine to the barrio -- conflict of a violent or desperate kind is banished from the picture -- the musical contains a host of funny performances and brings the zesty sound of Latin pop to the stage. (2:10). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'JACK GOES BOATING' Bob Glaudini's gentle comedy about pothead losers in love is a reminder of how engrossing uneventful lives can be in the hands of the right actors. Peter DuBois directs the easygoing ensemble, brilliantly led by Philip Seymour Hoffman (2:00). Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'A JEW GROWS IN BROOKLYN' You don't have to be Jewish or Brooklynish to empathize with Jake Ehrenreich, but in terms of fully appreciating his essentially one-man show, it probably helps. Especially the Catskills jokes (2:05). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 560-8912. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>'MARIE ANTOINETTE: THE COLOR OF FLESH' Joel Gross's intriguing play features impeccable performances by Amanda Jones, Samantha Ives and Jonathan Kells Phillips as the three corners of a triangle of love and friendship caught up in the French Revolution. It's no ordinary triangle: Ms. Jones plays Marie Antoinette, and Ms. Ives the real portraitist who often painted her (1:30). The 45th Street Theater, 354 West 45th Street, Clinton, (212) 254-9533. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>* 'THE NIBROC TRILOGY' ''Last Train to Nibroc,'' ''See Rock City'' and ''Gulf View Drive'' make no mention of 19th-century Russian intellectuals but they do signal the arrival of a talented American playwright, Arlene Hutton. Set in Kentucky and Florida, between the beginning of World War II and the early 1950s, the plays track the life of a young couple whose individual ambitions conflict; they also clash with the goals of a changing American society. Straightforward and heartfelt, but never treacly, the works stand out in a cold, postmodern universe. Try ''See Rock City'' if you have time for only one (1:25, 1:30 and 1:55). 78th Street Theater Lab, 236 West 78th Street, (212) 352-3101. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'OUR LEADING LADY' Kate Mulgrew stars as Laura Keene, who was starring in ''Our American Cousin'' on the night Lincoln was shot, in Charles Busch's uneven new comedy. An occasionally lively but mostly lumpen tribute to the glamour and grit of the theatrical life of a past era (2:00). Manhattan Theater Club at City Center Stage II, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'SPALDING GRAY: STORIES LEFT TO TELL' A disarming collage of selections from the monologues and journals of Mr. Gray, the ultimate stand-up solipsist, who died in 2004. Directed by Lucy Sexton, and read by five performers, none of whom resemble Mr. Gray, with an affection that shrewdly stops short of hero worship (1:30). Minetta Lane Theater, 18 Minetta Lane, Greenwich Village, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden Theater, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' Singing CliffsNotes for Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS'  The biomusical that walks like a man (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT'  A singing scrapbook for Monty Python fans (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' ''A Chorus Line'' with pimples (1:45). Circle in the Square, 254 West 50th Street, Manhattan, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'THE DARK AT THE TOP OF THE STAIRS' Jack Cummings III directs a respectable if reverential revival of William Inge's last major play. Seeking to access the poetry in Inge's homely tale of troubled lives in the Midwest in the 1920s, he can't quite hide its fundamentally prosaic qualities. Still, this Transport Group production gives audiences a chance to encounter a rarely seen drama from Broadway's heyday (2:35). Connelly Theater, 220 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101; closes tomorrow. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'FUGUE' ''Mary Smith'' is found wandering the streets of Chicago, suffering from amnesia. A young psychiatrist, who has his own demons, is consulted, and the process of treatment and Mary's memories in flashback are the action of ''Fugue,'' Lee Thuna's unrewarding play, directed by the Tony-winning actress Judith Ivey (2:15). Cherry Lane Theater, 38 Commerce Street, between Barrow and Bedford Streets, West Village, (212) 239-6200; closes tomorrow. (Moore)</p>
        <p>* 'KING HEDLEY II' The Signature Theater Company concludes its season dedicated to August Wilson with a gritty, strongly cast revival of this play set in a violence-ravaged Pittsburgh in the 1980s. Russell Hornsby gives a galvanizing performance in the title role, as a man struggling to live down the errors of his past and plant the seeds for a promising new life (2:45). Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 244-7529; closes on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'PRELUDE TO A KISS' Craig Lucas's broken-hearted romantic comedy from 1990 receives a first-rate remounting, courtesy of the Roundabout Theater Company. Alan Tudyk and Annie Parisse play a young couple whose marriage founders shortly after the bride receives a kiss from an elderly stranger (John Mahoney). The kiss awakens all three to an unsettling awareness of love's frailty and, paradoxically, of its durability too (2:00). American Airlines Theater, 227 West 42nd Street, (212) 719-1300; closes on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200; closes on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SERENDIB' David Zellnik's play about a group of scientists observing monkeys in Sri Lanka tackles questions about masculinity and social dominance within a framework that is too cute by half. That said, Mr. Zellnik seems to have more on his mind than many young playwrights (1:55). Ensemble Studio Theater, 549 West 52nd Street, Clinton, (212) 247-4982; closes on Sunday. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'SOME MEN' Terrence McNally's hit-and-miss comedy about gay life is a parade of cleanly drawn types, zippy one-liners and sentimental set pieces, woven into a pageant of the ages à la ''Cavalcade,'' Noël Coward's generations-spanning tribute to the British stiff upper lip. Trip Cullman directs the agile, appealing cast (2:00). Second Stage, 307 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 246-4422; closes on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TROPHY WIFE' Honky-tonk piano music and flickering film credits on a screen behind the stage set the tone for this slender period piece about a young woman who marries a wealthy older man to help her family's financial difficulties. The plot is taken from a short story by Chekhov, but it works fine in the 1920s milieu to which Mary Fulham and Terry Waldo, who wrote and performs the music, have transposed it; Mr. Waldo has also provided a veritable cornucopia of songs, to which Sharon Ann Farrell, as the ingénue, can at least do justice. But the piece, which seems a bouncy entertainment, turns out to want to stress its darker side; its abrupt ending leaves you hanging, wondering if, to make its point, the whole tone might have been a little less frothy (1:15). La MaMa E.T.C., 74 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 475-7710; closes on Sunday. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>* 'WAKE UP MR. SLEEPY! YOUR UNCONSCIOUS MIND IS DEAD!' Richard Foreman's latest film-theater hybrid is a memorial service, of sorts, for the intuitive self, killed by a surface-worshiping world. It is also a dazzling exercise in reality shifting that is as invigorating as it is mournful (1:05). Ontological Theater at St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101; closes on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>'AFTER THE WEDDING' (R, 119 minutes, in Danish) A modern creation with a classic theme involving haves and have-nots, bloodlines and family ties. The canned realism of the Danish director Susanne Bier is strictly Dogme-lite, but the spiky, screen-filling performances of her two male leads, Mads Mikkelsen and Rolf Lassgard, are really something to see. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'AQUA TEEN HUNGER FORCE COLON MOVIE FILM FOR THEATERS' (R, 87 minutes) Not as funny as the title or the Cartoon Network series on which it's based. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>'Blades of Glory' (PG-13, 93 minutes) In this fast, light, frequently funny comedy about a male figure-skating team, Will Ferrell and Jon Heder stake an early claim to being the comedy couple of the year. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>'DISTURBIA' (PG-13, 104 minutes) A pleasant, scary, well-directed variation on the killer-next-door theme, with the engaging Shia LeBeouf as Kale, a young man who turns house arrest into an occasion for voyeurism and crime-fighting. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'DREAMING LHASA' (No rating, 90 minutes, in Tibetan and English) This documentary from Ritu Sarin and Tenzing Sonam is about a Tibetan-American documentary-maker named Karma (Tenzin Chokyi Gyatso), who is making a movie about Tibetans who fled persecution by the Chinese and settled in Dharamsala, the Dalai Lama's exile headquarters in northern India. The movie is filled with heartbreaking moments, . but the central story, about the relationship between Karma and an ex-monk named Dhondup (Jampa Kalsang), can't help feeling contrived. (Matt Zoller Seitz)</p>
        <p>'FIREHOUSE DOG' (PG, 111 minutes) When a pampered Hollywood pooch trades his movie-star lifestyle for a rundown firehouse, it's not long before he is saving a father-son relationship and tracking down a serial arsonist. Yet the movie's wittiest moment -- a canine parody of Dudley Moore's first glimpse of Bo Derek in ''10'' -- will be appreciated only by parents, and in trying to straddle both age groups, ''Firehouse Dog'' proves decidedly less nimble than its furry star. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'THE GLAMOROUS LIFE OF SACHIKO HANAI' (No rating, 90 minutes, in Japanese) A wayward bullet turns a hooker into a brainiac in this Japanese clutter of soft-core political parody, hard-core narrative nonsense, breezy sexism and penny-ante surrealism. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'GRINDHOUSE' (R, 180 minutes) A double feature, complete with fake previews for schlocky exploitation pictures, that pays nostalgic tribute to disreputable traditions of moviemaking and moviegoing. Robert Rodriguez contributes ''Planet Terror,'' a purposely incoherent zombie gross-out flick that flaunts is own badness the way Rose McGowan (as a go-go dancer named Cherry Darling) shows off her weaponized prosthetic leg. For his part, Quentin Tarantino, more of a connoisseur than his collaborator (and a much better filmmaker), turns out a brutal, talky and satisfying car-chase revenge movie in ''Death Proof,'' starring Kurt Russell. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'THE HOAX' (R, 115 minutes) A first-rate performance by Richard Gere drives this true story of Clifford Irving (Mr. Gere), who claimed to be the authorized biographer of Howard Hughes. Shadowed by the paranoia of its period (the early '70s), this movie, crisply directed by Lasse Hallstrom from an excellent script by William Weaver, is less a morality play than the entertaining portrait of a literary gambler. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE HOLY MOUNTAIN' (No rating, 114 minutes, in Spanish) A scandal when first released, Alejandro Jodorowsky's 1973 movie -- a follow-up to his midnight landmark ''El Topo'' -- is a dazzling, rambling, often incoherent satire on consumerism, militarism and the exploitation of third world cultures by the west. The free-associative narrative follows a Christ-like thief through a series of surreal tableaus; the mission ends with a postmodern punch line that suggests that movies are drugs too, and the revolution can't happen until we kick our habits. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>* 'KILLER OF SHEEP' (No rating, 83 minutes) Largely hidden from view for three decades, Charles Burnett's lyrical film about a working-class family living in a broken-down home in a bombed-out stretch of Los Angeles is an American masterpiece, independent to the bone. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'LONELY HEARTS' (No rating, 100 minutes) This beautifully photographed remake of Leonard Kastle's 1970 cult B movie ''The Honeymoon Killers'' succeeds better than many modern crime dramas in balancing the philosophical with the visceral, although its villains' dirty deeds still trump its deeper strain of melancholy. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE LOOKOUT' (R, 99 minutes) This directorial debut by the veteran screenwriter Scott Frank (''Out of Sight'') is a variation of an old, old story, about a nobody (a brain-damaged janitor played by Joseph Gordon-Levitt) who falls in with crooks who make him feel like somebody. Although the movie's no masterpiece -- the final stretch feels forced and unconvincing -- there's a lot to like here. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>'MEET THE ROBINSONS' (G, 93 minutes) Actually, if you see them coming, run in the other direction. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'PATHFINDER' (R, 100 minutes) It's all grunting, all goring in this witless period flick about some Norsemen of the apocalypse come to wreak bloody ruin in the New World. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'PERFECT STRANGER' (R, 109 minutes) There is enough of a grain of truth in this noirish, paranoid thriller set in the New York media world that even after it lurches from the farfetched into the preposterous, the movie leaves a clammy residue of unease. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'PRIVATE FEARS IN PUBLIC PLACES' (No rating, 120 minutes, in French) A film from the venerable French auteur Alain Resnais about love and cinematic spaces, elegant camera moves and six heavenly bodies as seen through a mighty telescope. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'RED ROAD' (No rating, 113 minutes) Andrea Arnold's first feature falls into melodrama and implausibility at the end, but along the way it is a remarkably assured and complex piece of work, anchored by the director's formal control and by Jackie Dick's quietly heartbreaking performance as a Glasgow video-surveillance officer with an unhappy past. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'REIGN OVER ME' (R, 124 minutes) Mike Binder's comic drama of post-9/11 grief is wildly uneven -- by turns insightful and grindingly mawkish. Don Cheadle and Adam Sandler are two college buddies who reunite, somewhat improbably, some years after the attacks that robbed one of them of his family. The actors rise above the material, particularly in the longer, looser scenes that allow their contrasting temperaments -- Mr. Cheadle's tense understatement and Mr. Sandler's shaggy emoting -- to find a workable syncopation. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'ROCK THE BELLS' (No rating, 103 minutes) Casey Suchan and Denis Henry Hennelly's lively documentary follows the independent music promoter Chang Weisberg as he struggles to reunite the original members of the Wu-Tang Clan for a 2004 hip-hop concert. Capturing onstage and off with equal energy, the movie is a fascinating glimpse of a dreamer and a music culture that has always depended on them. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'SLOW BURN' (R, 93 minutes) There's not a line of dialogue that doesn't sound squeezed from a grade-C ''Law &amp; Order'' imitator affecting a bogus inner-city street cred. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE TV SET' (R, 87 minutes) Jake Kasdan's knowing satire of network television sends up the neuroses of writers and the ruthlessness of executives with minimal exaggeration. Nothing in this story of a writer (David Duchovny) pursuing his dream project seems implausible, which is less a limitation on the movie's comedy than it is its source. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'VOICE OF A MURDERER' (No rating, 122 minutes, in Korean) The unpredictable Korean director Park Jin-pyo returns to the docudrama form with this fictionalized account of the unsolved 1991 kidnapping and killing of a 9-year-old boy. Filmed relentlessly from the point of view of the distraught parents (Sol Kyung-gu and Kim Nam-joo), the movie unfolds in endless, repetitive scenes of parental hysteria punctuated by phone calls from the shadowy abductor. By the 44th day and the umpteenth call, it's déjà vu all over again. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'YEAR OF THE DOG' (PG-13, 97 minutes) Mike White's touching comedy about a woman who loses a dog and finds herself is funny ha-ha but firmly in touch with its downer side, which means it's also funny in a kind of existential way. Molly Shannon stars alongside a menagerie of howling scene-stealers. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>BUFFY THE VAMPIRE SLAYER SING-ALONG (Tonight) The IFC Center tries to get a little ''Rocky Horror'' action going by sponsoring a midnight screening of this cult television show's celebrated all-singing, all-dancing episode. Audience participation is strongly encouraged. IFC Center, 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 924-7771, ifccenter.com; $10.75. (Dave Kehr)</p>
        <p>* COMMITMENT AND GRACE: THE FILMS OF CARLOS SAURA (Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Saura is, of course, one of Spain's great film masters. But for those who love dance, he will always be an artist who spoke vivid new truths about Spanish dancing and the relationship between film and dance. This tribute by the Film Society of Lincoln Center covers 50 years of his work, with ''Blood Wedding'' and ''Sevillanas'' on Wednesday at 1:30 p.m., and ''Carmen'' on Thursday at 1 p.m. (Through May 3.) Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5600, filmlinc.com; $11; $7 for students with ID and for 65+ at weekday screenings before 6 p.m.; $40 for a series pass for eight films. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>INDIA NOW (Sunday through Thursday) Nine new features and two short films from India, in a series co-sponsored by the Museum of Modern Art and the Indo-American Arts Council. On the opening night the director Rahul Dholakia will introduce his controversial feature ''Parzania,'' a fictionalized account of the Gujarat riots of 2002. Other highlights include Arindam Mitra's ''Shoonya'' (Monday), an adaptation of T. S. Eliot's ''Murder in the Cathedral'' transposed to the world of Indian cricket, and ''Kaalpurush'' (''Memories in the Mist''), a new work by the Bengali filmmaker Buddhadeb Dasgupta (Wednesday). Museum of Modern Art Roy and Niuta Titus Theaters, (212) 708-9400, moma.org; $10. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>ACID MOTHERS TEMPLE (Thursday) This Japanese band describes its style as ''extreme trip music,'' which basically means big, sloppy, psychedelic noise jams. It doesn't necessarily mean peasant frocks and long wizard's robes, but Acid Mothers Temple usually has plenty of those too. With Mammatus and Alasehoutek. At 8 p.m., Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3132, knittingfactory.com; $13 in advance, $15 at the door. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>ASHFORD AND SIMPSON (Tomorrow) The Steve and Eydie of pop-soul still put on a convincing and musically solid demonstration of being the world's happiest show-business couple. With Melba Moore. At 8 p.m., Apollo Theater, 253 West 125th Street, Harlem, (212) 531-5305 or (212) 307-7171, apollotheater.com; $45 to $65. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>* BASEMENT BHANGRA (Tonight) For 10 years Rekha Malhotra, better known as DJ Rekha, has been leading this dance party at the downtown club S.O.B.'s, introducing legions of New Yorkers to the musky sound of bhangra, which melds Punjabi folk melodies with reggae and house-rocking electronic beats. Her efforts have been instrumental in popularizing the style in America, and she celebrates the milestone with an all-star anniversary show at the Hammerstein Ballroom, which should feel about 100 times bigger than S.O.B.'s but just as hot. Guests include Panjabi MC (whose song with Jay-Z, ''Beware of the Boys,'' is bhangra's biggest hit), Dhol Foundation and Bikram Singh. At 9 p.m., 311 West 34th Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171, mcstudios.com; $35 to $100. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BRAND NEW (Sunday) Not all emo goes the way of smirky punk-pop or sentimental singalongs. This excellent Long Island band plies dense, angry tangles of guitar and opaque lyrics of spiritual crisis, a cross between Pink Floyd and Nirvana. With Kevin Devine and the Manchester Orchestra. At 7 p.m., Fillmore New York at Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>THE BUNKER (Tonight) Honking saxophones and screeching guitars were the best-known musical residents of Tonic, the Lower East side club that closed last week. But Tonic was also an important home for avant-garde electronica. The Bunker, Tonic's long-running late-night techno party, is moving to a new club without missing a single week. Tonight it opens at the Luna Lounge, another former Lower East Side boîte, which is now in Brooklyn. Besides the resident D.J.'s, Spinoza and Derek Plaslaiko, tonight features Bodycode, a noisemaker based in Portugual who is also known as Portable (and as Alan Abrahams). At midnight, 361 Metropolitan Avenue, at Havemeyer Street, Williamsburg, lunalounge.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CLIPSE (Thursday) Comeback stories in rap are rare and sweet. In 2002 this Virginia duo rose to the Top 10 with sly rhymes about the cocaine trade and brutally minimal rhythm tracks by the Neptunes. Since then Clipse struggled in music-industry purgatory but triumphed with ''Hell Hath No Fury'' (Re-Up Gang/Jive), another cold, lean and virtuosic exercise that was one of last year's best hip-hop albums. With Monica and Jovan Dais. At 8 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club &amp; Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $30. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* JARVIS COCKER (Sunday and Monday) Carrying on the wittily misanthropic vignette style he perfected in his 1990s Britpop band, Pulp, Mr. Cocker, now 43, has returned with a solo album, ''Jarvis'' (Rough Trade). Without his former band, he is just as caustic but seems to have turned into a studio tinkerer, sampling the Righteous Brothers and Tommy James. At 8 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; $32 in advance, $35 at the door (sold out on Monday). (Sisario)</p>
        <p>COCOROSIE (Tonight) As CocoRosie, the Casady sisters, Sierra and Bianca, make swirling and surrealistic dramas out of girlish daydreams, hints of trip-hop, chirping crickets and cooed Billie Holiday-ish vocals. With Tez and the Girls of Karen Black. At 8, Warsaw, 261 Driggs Avenue, at Eckford Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 387-0505, warsawconcerts.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CONSTANTINES, TIM FITE (Thursday) Constantines is a feedback-worshiping Canadian band in the neo-MC5 mold: the bigger their guitar chords, the higher their fists fly. Tim Fite is harder to pin down. A lo-fi lone wolf from Brooklyn, he is somewhere between folk and hip-hop, and with his latest album, ''Over the Counter Culture'' -- a harsh rap indictment of consumerism and the American dream of selling out, which he offers free on his Web site (timfite.com) -- he has made himself into a cultural gadfly. At 8:30 p.m., Luna Lounge, 361 Metropolitan Avenue, at Havemeyer Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, lunalounge.com; $12 in advance, $14 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* DEERHUNTER (Thursday) Recalling Spacemen 3, this Atlanta quintet plays loose, sprawling psychedelia that grows from sweet guitar and vocal melodies into patterns that seem both florid and evil. With First Nation and Pterodactyl. At 8:30 p.m., Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700, mercuryloungenyc.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DIMMU BORGIR (Thursday) Dimmu Borgir is a Norwegian black-metal band: black as in dark and dismal, with haunted-house keyboard arpeggios and vocals rendered in an electronically processed monster growl. It's good for a shudder; few kinds of fans are as deeply into their scene as those who attend these shows, and the band doesn't come to the United States often. With Unearth, DevilDriver and Kataklysm. At 7 p.m., Nokia Theater, 1515 Broadway, at 44th Street, (212) 307-7171, nokiatheatrenyc.com; $25 in advance, $29 at the door. (Ben Ratliff)</p>
        <p>* DNTEL (Wednesday) As he did in the Postal Service, his project with Ben Gibbard of Death Cab for Cutie, Jimmy Tamborello -- who has been recording under the name Dntel for a decade or more -- gracefully joins stutters of electronic noise and soft, pensive melodies. His latest, ''Dumb Luck'' (Sub Pop), features collaborations with indie royalty like Bright Eyes, Jenny Lewis and Grizzly Bear, which means that you might be hearing this gurgly, not-quite-innocuous music, like the Postal Service, on late-night bar playlists for years to come. At 10 p.m., Union Pool, 484 Union Avenue, at Meeker Avenue, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 609-0484; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* FOUNTAINS OF WAYNE (Tuesday) Chris Collingwood and Adam Schlesinger of Fountains of Wayne earned their seats in the songwriting pantheon with a fluent power-pop classicism and songs that celebrate beta males and bridge-and-tunnel quotidiana (and, in the case of their 2003 hit, ''Stacy's Mom,'' teenage fantasies of older women.) Their new album, ''Traffic and Weather'' (Virgin), is full of familiar Fountains of Wayne-isms, with Beatlesesque chord progressions and stories of love encumbered by competition for taxis. With Robbers on High Street. At 8 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* FRATELLIS (Thursday) Like Sweet and Slade before it, this Scottish trio is not afraid to be both tough and silly, employing bubblegum shout-alongs in its stompy, completely catchy hard-rock tunes. At 9 p.m., Fillmore New York at Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>KRISTIN HERSH (Wednesday) Through the 1980s and '90s Ms. Hersh led Throwing Muses, the textbook college rock band, whose songs set turbulent and free-associative psychodramas to twisting guitar lines. Motherhood and experience have softened her music somewhat, but she remains a provocative songwriter, and her voice has aged into an expressive, sensual rasp. For this show her band will be augmented by a string section. With Dolorean. At 7:30 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; $15 in advance, $17 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>TAYLOR HICKS (Tonight) ''American Idol'' has sent many singers into the shark tank of Top 40 radio, but this smoky-voiced Alabama crooner, who has more in common with Michael McDonald than with Kelly Clarkson, heads in the direction of buttery soul. At 8, Beacon Theater, 2124 Broadway, at 74th Street, (212) 307-7171, beacontheatrenyc.com; $36 to $62. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>HOT CHIP (Tonight) With wobbly electronic rhythms and a strong command of the drippy, semi-ironic disco ballad, this English group plays wistful but still snarky dance music. Get too lost in the beats and you'll miss gags like the oh-so-art-rock countdown of nonsense words in descending size (''S-E-X-I-N-G, C-A-S-I-O, P-O-K-E''). With Tussle. At 6:30, Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* JOHN LEGEND, CORINNE BAILEY RAE (Sunday and Monday) A five-time Grammy winner, John Legend has the right to be a little cocky. But on his second album, ''Once Again'' (Sony), he plays the gentleman -- for the most part, anyway. Channeling the most tasteful of '70s R&amp;B, he permits himself the slightest racy double-entendre, telling his lady that ''love hurts sometimes when you do it right.'' In a sweet, tissue-thin voice, Corinne Bailey Rae sings of sisterly rituals, loves lost and her ''choux pastry heart.'' Sunday at 7:30 p.m., New Jersey Performing Arts Center, 1 Center Street, Newark, (888) 466-5722, njpac.org; Monday at 8 p.m., Theater at Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741, thegarden.com. Both sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DAVE MATTHEWS AND TIM REYNOLDS (Sunday) The jam-band frog prince plays with an old guitar buddy whose style leans toward world-fusion. Expect long solos and inside jokes. At 7:30 p.m., Radio City Music Hall, (212) 307-7171, radiocity.com; $75. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LOREENA McKENNITT (Tonight) On ''An Ancient Muse'' (Verve), her first album in nine years, this Canadian singer explored her Celtic heritage in depth, from the British Isles to Turkey and along the Silk Road of Central Asia. And what did she find? Pretty much what she already knew: that with the help of some gossamer major-chord swells and reverberant, Enya-like vocals, any sound can be incorporated into the New Age fantasy of Celtic music. At 8, Radio City Music Hall, (212) 307-7171, radiocity.com; $35 to $75. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ERIN McKEOWN (Tonight) A smiley sprite whose knack for wordplay and light touch on the guitar have sometimes evoked Tin Pan Alley, Ms. McKeown took the plunge in her new album, ''Sing You Sinners'' (Nettwerk), recording 12 nuggets by Harold Arlen, Cole Porter, Fats Waller and others (along with one by herself). If her voice is not quite up to the subtleties of wit the songs demand, her joy of discovery is sincere. With John Southworth. At 7:30, Southpaw, 125 Fifth Avenue, near Sterling Place, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0236, spsounds.com; $15. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>NOISETTES (Monday) Conjuring the Yeah Yeah Yeahs and X-Ray Spex, this London band, led by the throaty and uninhibited Shingai Shoniwa, plays grimy, muscular punk-funk punctuated with lighter touches of something like vaudeville. With Looker and Cities on Fire. At 8 p.m., Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700, mercuryloungenyc.com; $12. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>RICKY SKAGGS AND BRUCE HORNSBY (Tuesday) One of the most virtuosic musicians in bluegrass, Ricky Skaggs sends his fingers flying in a blur over mandolin, guitar and fiddle. He performs with Bruce Hornsby, whose years playing with the Grateful Dead have made him a more versatile and playful musician. The two have a new, untitled album that is maybe a little too versatile and playful: it includes a cornball version of Rick James's ''Super Freak.'' At 8 p.m., the Concert Hall at the New York Society for Ethical Culture, 2 West 64th Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171, concertstonight.com; $50 and $60. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Keely Smith (Tonight and tomorrow night, and Tuesday through Thursday) This ''queen of swing,'' as she has been nicknamed, may be the last surviving top-of-the-line entertainer from the Rat Pack era of Las Vegas. She is still in reasonably good voice. (Through April 28.) At 8:45, with additional shows at 10:45 tonight and tomorrow night, Café Carlyle, Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212) 744-1600, thecarlyle.com; $75 and $125 cover tonight and tomorrow night, $65 and $100 Tuesday through Thursday. (Holden)</p>
        <p>PATTI SMITH (Tuesday) With ''Twelve'' (Columbia), a new album in which Ms. Smith covers the Rolling Stones, Jimi Hendrix and Nirvana -- whose ''Smells Like Teen Spirit'' gets an eccentric, bluegrass-tinged interpretation -- she and her band play three separate shows at the Bowery Ballroom on Tuesday night; tickets to each performance include a copy of the CD. At 6, 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* RICHARD SWIFT, DAVID VANDERVELDE (Tomorrow and Sunday) Retro-pop can easily go the way of mere imitation, but these singers have found ways to evoke their heroes without being entirely defined by them. Richard Swift's cynical gloss on piano-driven cabaret-rock adds a taste of vinegar to Harry Nilsson. David Vandervelde, from Chicago, has the thin whine and androgynous swagger of T. Rex down pat, but also wisely pursues his gift for the elegiac folk-rock ballad. Tomorrow at 9:30 p.m., Luna Lounge, 361 Metropolitan Avenue, at Havemeyer Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, lunalounge.com; $10 in advance, $12 at the door. Sunday at 10 p.m., Pianos, 158 Ludlow Street, near Rivington Street, Lower East Side, (212) 505-3733, pianosnyc.com; $12. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>BUFFALO COLLISION (Monday) Free improvisation is the working method for this collective, made up of the saxophonist Tim Berne, the violist Mat Maneri, the pianist Ethan Iverson and the drummer David King. As the name implies, results will be concussive at times, and maybe a bit hairy (in a good way). At 8:30 p.m., Center for Improvisational Music, 295 Douglass Street, between Third and Fourth Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (212) 631-5882, schoolforimprov.org; cover, $12; $8 for students. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>* THE CONGA KINGS (Today) Candido Camero, Carlos (Patato) Valdés and Giovanni Hidalgo are three of the most accomplished congueros alive; they join forces here at the helm of a nine-piece Afro-Cuban ensemble. At 12:30 and 7 p.m., Winter Garden, World Financial Center, West Street, south of Vesey Street, Lower Manhattan, (212) 945-0505, worldfinancialcenter.com; free. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CONGA MADNESS WEEK (Tuesday through Thursday) Congas dominate next week at the Blue Note too, with appearances by Francisco Aguabella and his fellow percussionist Carlos Valdés (Tuesday); Candido Camero, celebrating his 86th birthday (Wednesday); and Poncho Sanchez, with his crisp working band (Thursday). (Through April 29.) At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592 bluenote.net; cover, $30 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ANDREW CYRILLE, BOB STEWART AND ROY CAMPBELL (Tomorrow) Mr. Cyrille is an expressive drummer capable of creating a radiant sense of pulse; he interacts here with Mr. Stewart, on tuba, and Mr. Campbell, on trumpet. At 8:30 p.m., Roulette, 20 Greene Street, at Grand Street, SoHo, (212) 219-8242, roulette.org; $15; $10 for students. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>OLU DARA (Tuesday) Before he was known as the father of the rapper Nas, Mr. Dara was a trumpeter, guitarist and singer who infused New York avant-gardism with Mississippi twang. At 8 p.m., Studio Museum in Harlem, 144 West 125th Street, (212) 864-4500, Ext. 264, studiomuseum.org; $20; $15 in advance and for students; $12 for members. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PAQUITO D'RIVERA'S JAZZ CHAMBER TRIO / EDMAR CASTANEDA TRIO (Thursday) The saxophonist and clarinetist Paquito D'Rivera explores a hybrid of jazz and chamber music in his group with Alon Yavnai on piano and Dana Leong on cello. The harpist Edmar Castaneda shares the bill with his working trio, which has a separate engagement on Monday night at 7:30 and 9:30 at the Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; $15. Thursday at 8 p.m., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212)501-3330, kaufman-center.org; $35 in advance, $40 at the door . (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DIGITAL PRIMITIVES (Wednesday) The multireedist Assif Tsahar, the multi-instrumentalist Cooper-Moore and the percussionist Chad Taylor make up this experimental ensemble, which released an album of the same title last year. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Tea Lounge, 837 Union Street, between Sixth and Seventh Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 789-2762, tealoungeny.com; donation, $5. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MIKE DILLON'S GO-GO JUNGLE (Tonight) Mike Dillon is a vibraphonist whose caffeinated approach to rhythm finds a suitable outlet in a funk-inspired jam band he calls the Go-Go Jungle. Sharing the bill are two similarly inclined bands, Licorice and the Bomb Squad. At 8, Knitting Factory Tap Bar, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3132, knittingfactory.com; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SONNY FORTUNE QUARTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) A powerful and searching saxophonist, Sonny Fortune leads a group with Michael Cochrane on piano, Chip Jackson on bass and Steve Johns on drums. At 8, 10 and midnight, Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212) 255-3626, sweetrhythmny.com; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>AL FOSTER QUARTET (Tuesday through Thursday) The well-traveled drummer Al Foster has a lithe touch, ideal for modern jazz and more than suitable for funk; his band consists of the tenor saxophonist Eli Degibri, the pianist Kevin Hays and the bassist Doug Weiss. (Through April 29.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* FREQUENCY/ ANGELICA SANCHEZ TRIO (Sunday) Frequency is a Chicago-based ensemble consisting of the saxophonist and clarinetist Edward Wilkerson, the flutist Nicole Mitchell, the bassist Harrison Bankhead and the drummer Avreeayl Ra; its self-titled debut, released last year on the Thrill Jockey label, pairs textural experimentation with a slippery sense of swing. That stylistic negotiation is likely to resurface in a later set with Angelica Sanchez on piano, Tony Malaby on saxophone and Tom Rainey on drums. At 7 and 9 p.m., Jimmy's, 43 East Seventh Street, East Village, (212) 982-3006, freestylejazz.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MIKE GAMBLE'S MULTI METEORCHESTRA (Tonight) The guitarist Mike Gamble goes for density and velocity in this confab of nearly a dozen energetic young players. At 9 and 10:30, Tea Lounge, 837 Union Street, between Sixth and Seventh Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718)789-2762, tealoungeny.com; donation, $5. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>THE GANG FONT, FEAT. INTERLOPER (Tomorrow and Sunday) David King, the intensely propulsive drummer for Happy Apple and the Bad Plus, formed this Minneapolis-centered group with the bassist Greg Norton, a former member of the influential post-punk band Hüsker Dü. Adding to the prog-rock churn are Craig Taborn, on keyboards, and Erik Fratzke (of Happy Apple), on guitar. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Silent Barn, 915 Wyckoff Avenue, at Hancock Street, Ridgewood, Queens, toddpnyc.com; cover, $8. Sunday at 7:30 p.m., Knitting Factory Tap Bar, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3132, knittingfactory.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVID GILMORE QUINTET (Tomorrow) David Gilmore favors a clean guitar tone, but his playing tends toward rhythmic convolution; his dynamic band includes Marcus Strickland on tenor saxophone and Jeff (Tain) Watts on drums. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $15; $10 for members. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* HUMAN FEEL (Tomorrow) This reunited confab -- Chris Speed and Andrew D'Angelo on reeds, Jim Black on drums and Kurt Rosenwinkel on guitar -- has a smartly enigmatic new album called ''Galore'' (Skirl), its first in a decade. Its strength lies in an ideal of interconnectedness, and a tonal palette partly informed by underground rock. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Tea Lounge, 837 Union Street, between Sixth and Seventh Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 789-2762, tealoungeny.com; suggested donation, $5. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>IN A SENTIMENTAL MOOD (Tonight) The Jazz Museum in Harlem All-Stars Band, led by the saxophonist, pianist and historian Loren Schoenberg, plays some lesser-known music from the book of Duke Ellington and Billy Strayhorn, in a concert in collaboration with the Duke Ellington Society. At 8, Flushing Town Hall, 137-35 Northern Boulevard, at Linden Place, Queens, (718) 463-7700, flushingtownhall.org; $40; $28 for members. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* OLIVER LAKE (Tomorrow and Sunday) Mr. Lake is a saxophonist with a piercing sound and a fearless style. Tomorrow he leads a quartet with Freddie Hendrix on trumpet, Jared Gold on organ and Bill McClelland on drums; on Sunday he presents his Reunion Trio, with Pheeroan akLaff on drums and Michael Gregory on guitars. Tomorrow at 9 and 10:30 p.m., Sista's Place, 456 Nostrand Avenue, at Jefferson Avenue, Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn, (718) 398-1766, sistasplace.org; cover, $25 in advance, $30 at the door. Sunday at 8:30 p.m., Roulette, 20 Greene Street, at Grand Street, SoHo, (212) 219-8242, roulette.org; $15; $10 for students. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>THE LEGENDS OF BLUE NOTE (Thursday) The celebrated hard boppers from the 1960s Blue Note roster -- like Lee Morgan and Horace Silver -- provide a promising repertory foundation for this concert, featuring new arrangements for the Jazz at Lincoln Center Orchestra. (Through April 28.) At 8 p.m., Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 721-6500, jalc.org; $37.50 to $127.50. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MAHAVISHNU PROJECT (Tomorrow) This single-minded repertory project, led by the percussionist Gregg Bendian, boldly apprehends the fusion of the Mahavishnu Orchestra. As on its new Cuneiform release, the group involves a total of 11 musicians here, performing all the material from the 1975 album ''Visions of the Emerald Beyond.'' At 9 p.m., Makor, 35 West 67th Street, near Columbus Avenue, (212) 601-1000, mahavishnuproject.com; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>RON MILES /JENNY SCHEINMAN (Monday) Mr. Miles is a trumpeter with a dual attraction to sunlight and shadow, as he demonstrated on ''Stone/Blossom,'' a double album issued last year. He performs an early set with his band, and then joins Ms. Scheinman, a thoughtful violinist and frequent collaborator, in a set of her own. At 7 and 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $10 a set. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* CHARLES MINGUS: EPITAPH (Wednesday) Charles Mingus never saw a full performance of ''Epitaph,'' his epic orchestral composition; its premiere at Lincoln Center in 1989, came a decade after his death. That concert's conductor, Gunther Schuller, resuscitates the work here with a 30-piece orchestra; he also includes ''Inquisition,'' a recently discovered movement that has never been performed. Among the accomplished musicians in the ensemble is Christian McBride, filling Mingus's formidable bass chair. At 7:30 p.m., Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212)721-6500, jalc.org; $45. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BEN MONDER (Thursday) In the hands of Mr. Monder, the electric guitar is a coloristic instrument first and foremost. He features his coolly convoluted pieces for a trio with Chris Lightcap on bass and Ted Poor on drums, recording the results for a forthcoming album. At 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JEROME SABBAGH QUARTET (Tuesday) ''Pogo'' (Sunnyside), the new album by the tenor and soprano saxophonist Jerome Sabbagh, highlights his casual yet focused rapport with the guitarist Ben Monder, the bassist Joe Martin and the drummer Ted Poor, who all join him here. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* DINO SALUZZI AND ANJA LECHNER (Tuesday) ''Ojos Negros'' (ECM) is a sparse and often haunting new album by Mr. Saluzzi, an Argentine bandoneón player, and Ms. Lechner, a German cellist; tango feeds into its mood, but so do jazz and some mournful strains of the European classical tradition. At 8 p.m., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212) 501-3330, kaufman-center.org; $35 in advance, $40 tomorrow. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SAMBA JAZZ &amp; MUSIC OF JOBIM (Tuesday through Thursday) A cosmopolitan Brazilian-jazz ensemble consisting of the pianist Helio Alves, the drummer Duduka da Fonseca, the trumpeter Claudio Roditi and the bassist Eddie Gomez. The group salutes Antonio Carlos Jobim, with vocals by his son (Paulo Jobim) and a frequent collaborator (Maucha Adnet). (Through April 29.) At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>THIRD WHEEL (Sunday) The bright young drummer Ted Poor bears primary responsibility for this trio with the trumpeter Ralph Alessi and the guitarist Ben Monder, but its creative energies are emphatically collective. At 8:30 p.m., Center for Improvisational Music, 295 Douglass Street, between Third and Fourth Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (212) 631-5882, schoolforimprov.org; cover, $12; $8 for students. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TYSHAWN SOREY QUARTET (Thursday) Tyshawn Sorey, a drummer with an aggressively physical style, showcases his own compositions in this group with Ben Gerstein on trombone, Cory Smythe on keyboards and Thomas Morgan on bass. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $12; $10 for members. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STILL LIFE WITH COMMENTATOR (Tomorrow) The brazen theatricality of the modern news cycle fuels this collaboration between the pianist and composer Vijay Iyer and the poet Mike Ladd, originally presented at Brooklyn Academy of Music in December. The work is scaled back here but still features Pamela Z and Guillermo Brown on vocals, Okkyung Lee on cello and Liberty Ellman on guitar. At 11:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 539-8778, joespub.com; cover, $15, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* WOMEN IN JAZZ FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday) This first annual festival of the nonprofit International Women in Jazz organization begins tonight with a reception featuring music by the saxophonist Virginia Mayhew; the first performance tomorrow is by the pianist Deanna Witkowski, and the last is by the singer Ann Hampton Callaway. Sunday's offerings include a Jazz Vespers service with the vocalist Kate McGarry. Times vary. St. Peter's Church, Lexington Avenue, at 54th Street, (212) 935-2200, internationalwomeninjazz.com; tickets range from free to $25, depending on the event, or $50 for a festival pass. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* JOHN ZORN (Thursday) A couple months ago Columbia University presented the iconoclastic composer John Zorn with its William Schuman Award, a distinction of lifetime-achievement proportions. Mr. Zorn now presents selections from his fathomless oeuvre at the school's Miller Theater, including chamber works, Masada miniatures and ''Cobra,'' his celebrated game piece. At 7:30 p.m., Miller Theater, Columbia University, Broadway at 116th Street, Morningside Heights, (212) 854-7799, millertheatre.com; $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>* 'IL BARBIERE DI SIVIGLIA' (Thursday) This production conveys the comic confusions of the story through its fluid staging and a wonderfully abstract set: a matrix of movable doors, staircases and potted orange trees, behind which characters spy on one another. The heated sexuality of the characters also comes through strongly, thanks to Mr. Sher's subtle directing of, notably, the captivating mezzo-soprano Joyce DiDonato as a vocally agile and feisty Rosina. But some major changes are coming this week. The emerging American tenor Lawrence Brownlee makes his Met debut as Count Almaviva, and the hardy German baritone Russell Braun sings Figaro. At 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; sold out. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'La Finta Giardiniera' (Wednesday) Singers from the Juilliard Opera Center present a staged production of Mozart's first mature opera buffa, which he wrote at 18. The cast includes Erin Morley as the Marchioness. Jay Lesenger directs, and Gary Thor Wedow conducts the Juilliard Orchestra. At 8 p.m., Peter Jay Sharp Theater, Juilliard School, 155 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, juilliard.edu; $20; $10 for students and 65+. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>'FLAVIO' (Tomorrow) Candy pink and candy green set the tone for Chas Rader-Shieber's antic production of this opera, which consists of arias nestled side by side, bright and sweet as a box of fondants. Making company debuts are Katherine Rohrer, a light mezzo with a nice tone; Gerald Thompson, a promising but sometimes wild countertenor; and the conductor William Lacey, who led a strong, lithe performance on opening night. David Walker was fine as the foppish, foolish king of the title. At 8 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nycopera.com; $25 to $125. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>* 'GIULIO CESARE' (Tomorrow and Tuesday) Though its auditorium is too big for Handel, the Metropolitan Opera makes this work come alive, thanks to exceptional Handel singers. The countertenor David Daniels excels in the daunting title role, and the soprano Ruth Ann Swenson makes a vocally exquisite Cleopatra. Patricia Bardon, a rich-toned Irish mezzo-soprano, brings lyrical elegance to the role of Cornelia. Harry Bicket conducts stylishly. (On Tuesday the countertenor Lawrence Zazzo, who has been singing Tolomeo, takes over the title role; Danielle de Niese sings Cleopatra; and Jill Grove sings Cornelia.) Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., Tuesday at 7:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $220 to $375 tickets remaining for tomorrow; $15 to $175 for Tuesday. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'L'ITALIANA IN LONDRA' (Wednesday) Rossini's Italian girl got to Algiers; Cimarosa's, a generation earlier, made it only as far as London, but both were in pursuit of their beloveds. Cimarosa's opera is this year's little-known offering in the pleasingly offbeat canon of the Manhattan School of Music. Steven Mosteller conducts; Albert Sherman directs. At 8 p.m., Manhattan School of Music, Broadway at 122nd Street, Morningside Heights, (917) 493-4428, msmnyc.edu; $20; $10 for students and 65+. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>'Madama Butterfly' (Tonight and Sunday) Paul Kellogg's administration at New York City Opera ends along with the spring season in these last two performances of this Puccini crowd-pleaser. Shu-Ying Li and Christopher Jackson head the cast in a minimalist production by Mark Lamos. Tonight at 8, Sunday at 1:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nycopera.com; $25 to $93 remaining tonight, sold out on Sunday. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>'MANON LESCAUT' (Tonight through Sunday) Because of its difficulties, this early masterpiece by Puccini probably does not appear in production as often as the music merits. There are two long and demanding lead roles, crowd scenes, intimate scenes and a teeming orchestra score. The adventurous Dicapo Opera Theater is presenting a production by Michael Capasso this weekend, conducted by Pacien Mazzagatti, with rotating leads in the main roles of the impulsive Manon and her lover Des Grieux. It should be interesting to experience the opera in the company's intimate theater. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8 and Sunday at 4 p.m., 184 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212) 288-9438, dicapo.com; $47.50. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* 'IL TRITTICO' (Tonight and Monday night) The Broadway stage director Jack O'Brien has taken on two trilogies at Lincoln Center in the same year. First was Tom Stoppard's ''Coast of Utopia,'' and now he has moved on to Puccini's trilogy of dissimilar one-acters, in which he makes his debut tonight at the Met. The cast includes Salvatore Licitra, Barbara Frittoli and the inimitable Stephanie Blythe. At 8, Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $80 to $175 remaining tonight; sold out on Monday. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>'TURANDOT' (Tomorrow and Wednesday) For spectacle and big music, the Franco Zeffirelli production of Puccini's final opera, at the Met, is hard to beat. For compelling leads, you might have to look elsewhere. Erika Sunnegardh has replaced the shaky Andrea Gruber in the lead, joining Richard Margison (who does at least have the vocal heft for the role). Liping Zhang, an acclaimed Covent Garden Butterfly, has taken over as Liù, and Marco Armiliato, whose conducting seems increasingly wishy-washy this year, leads the orchestra. But spectacle and size are evidently enough to keep tickets selling briskly. Tomorrow at 8:30 p.m., Wednesday at 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; sold out tomorrow; $100 to $175 for Wednesday. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>* ACADEMY OF ANCIENT MUSIC (Thursday) Richard Egarr, the harpsichordist and conductor, was recently appointed Christopher Hogwood's successor as music director of the Academy of Ancient Music. Mr. Egarr will lead the period-instrument orchestra in three of Handel's six Concerti Grossi (Op. 3), which he recently recorded on Harmonia Mundi in warm, polished and dignified performances. The Carnegie program also includes Telemann's ''Water Music'' Suite in C and Handel's ''Water Music'' Suite in G. At 7:30 p.m., Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; sold out. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>ELAINE ALVAREZ (Sunday) The Marilyn Horne Foundation presents its final ''On Wings of Song'' recital of the season. In her enticing program, this Cuban-American soprano explores the feminine mystique through songs inspired by the Swedish folk character Ingelill, a young maiden who drowns herself out of despair over a lost love. She will sing songs by Stenhammar, Sibelius, Liszt, Strauss and Bo Linde. John Churchwell is the accompanist. At 3 p.m., St. Bartholomew's Church, Park Avenue at 50th Street, (212) 378-0248, stbarts.org; $20; $15 for 65+; free for students. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* EMANUEL AX and EDGAR MEYER (Tonight) Mingling Bach and bluegrass is standard operating procedure for Edgar Meyer, the double-bassist for whom crossover is not a marketing ploy but a natural mode of being. Plenty of mingling takes place on this program, performed with the pianist Emanuel Ax. At one end of the spectrum are Bach and Haydn, arranged for the players' respective instruments; at the other are New York premieres of works by Mr. Meyer; Bright Sheng, the acclaimed Chinese composer; and the mandolin player Chris Thile, a former prodigy and an artist rapidly becoming as diverse as Mr. Meyer himself. At 7:30, Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800; $48 and $54. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>BENJAMIN BAGBY (Sunday) Relying on hefty research and a bit of inspired guesswork, Mr. Bagby offers his re-creation of the ancient Bardic tradition in dramatic performances of ''Beowulf.'' At 1 p.m., the Cloisters, Fort Tryon Park, Washington Heights, (212) 650-2290, metmuseum.org; $35. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* BROOKLYN PHILHARMONIC (Tomorrow) Stefan Asbury, a conductor who has done superb work leading new-music programs at Tanglewood, steps onto the Brooklyn Philharmonic podium to lead Julia Wolfe's ''My Beautiful Scream,'' performed with the Kronos Quartet; Vaughan Williams's ''Fantasia on the Theme of Thomas Tallis''; and Holst's ''Planets.'' At 8 p.m., Brooklyn Academy of Music, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, (718) 636-4100, brooklynphilharmonic.org; $20 to $60. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>CHANTICLEER (Thursday) This all-male vocal ensemble will give the premiere of its latest commission, ''And on Earth, Peace: A Chanticleer Mass,'' for which five diverse composers each contributed a movement. The American composer Douglas J. Cuomo wrote the Kyrie; the Turkish-American composer Kamran Ince wrote the Gloria section to a Sufi text; Michael McGlynn, who is Irish, contributed the Agnus Dei; Ivan Moody, a Briton, wrote the Sanctus; and the Israeli-American composer Shulamit Ran wrote the Credo. At 8 p.m., Temple of Dendur, the Metropolitan Museum of Art, (212) 570-3949, metmuseum.org; $70. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* COMPOSER PORTRAIT: KIMMO HAKOLA (Tuesday) The Miller Theater's Composer Portraits is a kind of stealth series, since the concerts spotlight not only a composer, but also a performing ensemble. The composer, in this case, is the energetic Kimmo Hakola, whose music is getting its first large-scale treatment in New York; the ensemble is Present Music, an enterprising new-music group based in Milwaukee, conducted by Kevin Stalheim, which commissioned one of the works on the program. At 8 p.m., Broadway at 116th Street, Morningside Heights, (212) 854-7799, millertheater.com; $25; $15 for students. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>* EARLY MUSIC NEW YORK (Tomorrow) Frederick Renz leads his period-instrument chamber orchestra in an all-Haydn program that includes three symphonies -- No. 26 (''Lamentatione''), No. 30 (''Alleluia'') and No. 83 (''La Poule'') -- as well as a Concerto for Two Flutes and a Divertimento for Winds. At 8 p.m., St. James's Church, Madison Avenue at 71st Street, (212) 280-0330, earlymusicny.org; $40; $20 for students. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* QUINN KELSEY (Tonight) Born and raised in Honolulu, this baritone has been making his name in the vocal music and opera worlds. A recipient of a career grant from the Richard Tucker Foundation, Mr. Kelsey will sing works by Handel, Brahms, Finzi and Mussorgsky with the pianist Tamara Sanikidze. The event is presented by Carnegie Hall and the Marilyn Horne Foundation. At 7:30, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $30 and $34. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>KREMERATA BALTICA (Monday) Gidon Kremer's eclectic chamber band offers some of its specialties, from Beethoven (the Grosse Fuge) and Schumann (a violin version of the Cello Concerto) to Korngold (the Symphonic Serenade) and Piazzolla (''Las Cuatro Estaciones Porteñas''). At 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $23 to $72. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* MIDORI (Tuesday) This adventurous violinist and champion of contemporary music offers the New York premiere of Einojuhani Rautavaara's ''Lost Landscapes.'' She commissioned the work in 2005 and performed its world premiere in Munich last year with the pianist Robert McDonald, who accompanies her here. The program also includes Beethoven's ''Spring'' Sonata, Hindemith's Sonata in E flat and Strauss's Sonata in E flat. At 8 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $30 to $60. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>NEW JUILLIARD ENSEMBLE (Tonight) Joel Sachs leads his expert student ensemble in an international program of premieres, including works by Seppo Pohjola, from Finland; Snorri Sigfus Birgisson, from Iceland; Gerald Barry, from Ireland; Farangis Nurulla-Khoja, from Tajikistan; and Raymond J. Lustig, from the United States. At 8, Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 769-7406, juilliard.edu; free, but tickets are required. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC (Wednesday and Thursday) Lorin Maazel, the music director, conducts two exercises in orchestral luxury: Stravinsky's ''Chant du Rossignol'' and the second of Ravel's ''Daphnis et Chloé'' Suites. He also leads the admirable Anne-Sophie Mutter in Berg's Violin Concerto. At 7:30 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nyphil.org; $33 to $99. (Holland)</p>
        <p>GIL SHAHAM AND FRIENDS (Tomorrow) This omnipresent and very talented violinist joins eight colleagues, including the mezzo-soprano Michelle DeYoung, in a not-your-everyday Brahms program: the Horn Trio, two songs with viola and piano, and the Clarinet Quintet. At 7:30 p.m., Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; sold out. (Holland)</p>
        <p>UBS VERBIER FESTIVAL CHAMBER ORCHESTRA (Tonight) This chamber orchestra, whose members are chosen from the best members and alumni of the UBS Verbier Festival Orchestra, will perform Mozart concertos with the violinist Maxim Vengerov as soloist and conductor. The program includes the Violin Concertos Nos. 2 and 4 (K. 211 and 218), with Mr. Vengerov's own cadenzas, and the Sinfonia Concertante in E flat (K. 364), with the violist Lawrence Power -- repertory this group recently recorded for a new disc on EMI. At 8, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $28 to $96. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>VERMEER QUARTET (Wednesday) The Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center presents the Vermeer in string quartets by Schubert, Britten and Dvorak. This is the last of a season-long series. At 7:30 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5788, chambermusicsociety.org; $30 to $52. (Holland)</p>
        <p>* YOUNG PEOPLE'S CHORUS OF NEW YORK CITY (Tomorrow) Francisco J. Núñez, the music director of this chorus, has long believed that at an early age, musicians should develop, and benefit from, associations with established composers. The group's ''Transient Glory'' program offers premieres of works written for the young choristers by Ned Rorem, Bruce Adolphe, Michael Gordon, Meredith Monk and Tarik O'Regan. At 7:30 p.m., 92nd Street Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue, (212) 415-5500, ypc.org; $25; $10 for parents and students. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>* AILEY II (Tonight through Sunday) Alvin Ailey created a second, or junior, company in 1974, almost casually, as a way of working on new choreography. Ailey II is now a world-class troupe, filled with dancers who are not only good but also capable of performing with a youthful hunger, as well as with a reverence for dance that is a part of the mission of the company director, Sylvia Waters, whom Ailey himself chose to direct that first group. Now Ailey II is coming home, performing in the black-box theater that is part of the Ailey headquarters: newer, grander and more gleaming than Ailey ever envisioned. The repertory will include new dances by Abdel Salaam, Darrell Grand Moultrie and Jessica Lang, along with Ailey's ''Streams'' and a chunk of Ailey highlights. Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 3 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 3 and 7:30 p.m., Ailey Citigroup Theater, 405 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444, alvinailey.org; $40; $10 student rush tickets available. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>BEST OF THE BOROUGHS: NIA LOVE/BLACKSMITH'S DAUGHTER DANCE THEATER (Tonight through Sunday) Ms. Love represents dance in this festival, and if past programs are any guide, she will do that with a maximum of heat and wit. Tonight at 7, tomorrow at 9:30 p.m., Sunday at 7:30 p.m., Performance Space 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101, ps122.org; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>JANE COMFORT (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ms. Comfort can be depended on for thought-provoking dance and theater pieces, often explorations of politics and sexuality. At 8:30, Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, symphonyspace.org; $21. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CONFIGURATION DANCE (Tuesday) From Cape Cod and unaccountably headed south, this company will perform dances by Michael Shannon, Sasha Janes, Yuri Zhukov and Harrison McEldowney, the resident choreographer of the company, which is directed by Joseph Cipolla, formerly of the Birmingham Royal Ballet in England. At 8 p.m., Ailey Citigroup Theater, 405 West 55th Street, Clinton, (877) 238-5596, smarttix.com; $25; $15 for students. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>DANCE AT DIXON PLACE (Tuesday and Thursday) On Tuesday Marcia Monroe's ''Crossing Boundaries'' series will focus on choreography by Steinunn Ketilsdottir, Josefina Diels, Javier Dzul and Lisa Parra. On Thursday Edisa Weeks's Delirious Dance Company will perform ''Liaisons,'' which explores the degrees of closeness among strangers. (Delirious Dance through April 28.) At 8 p.m., Dixon Place, 258 Bowery, between Houston and Prince Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 219-0736, dixonplace.org; $12; $10 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>DANCE AT DNA (Tonight through Sunday, and Thursday) The theater's ''OB.ject.ob.JECT'' series of choreography by women runs through Sunday. Faye Driscoll's ''Wow, Mom, Wow'' follows on Thursday and runs through April 29. Ms. Driscoll describes the piece as ''postmodern dance meets pop musical meets death-metal fantasy.'' Tonight, tomorrow and Thursday nights at 8, Sunday at 3 p.m., Dance New Amsterdam, 280 Broadway, at Chambers Street, TriBeCa, (212) 279-4200, dnadance.org; $20 (''OB.ject'') and $17 (Driscoll). (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* EIFMAN BALLET OF ST. PETERSBURG (Tonight through Thursday) There is no one in world dance quite like Boris Eifman, for better or for worse. Whatever else he is, Mr. Eifman is a theatrical genius whose ballets are almost always flamboyant fun. This week the company will perform his new ''Seagull,'' after the Chekhov play, through Sunday, followed by ''Russian Hamlet'' on Wednesday and Thursday. (Through April 29.) Tonight and Wednesday and Thursday nights at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 2 and 7 p.m., City Center, 131 West 55th Street, Manhattan, (212) 581-1212, nycitycenter.org; $35 to $100. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>GENDER BENDER: MONICA BILL BARNES AND NICHOLASLEICHTERDANCE (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ms. Barnes's modern-dance choreography is known for its theatricality and knowing humor. And Mr. Leichter explores race and sex with provocative pairings of dancers in work that draws from traditional and street-dance styles. At 8:30, Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, symphonyspace.org; $17 to $25. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>KENNEDY DANCERS (Thursday) Based in Jersey City, this modern-dance troupe will celebrate its 30th anniversary with a program of dances by the company director, Diane Dragone, with one work by a different guest group each night. Donna Scro Gentile's Freespace Dance will perform at the opening. (Through April 28.) At 7:30 p.m., Baryshnikov Arts Center, 450 West 37th Street, Manhattan, (201) 659-2190; $20; $18 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Peter Kyle Dance (Tonight through Sunday night) Peter Kyle was a longtime dancer with Alwin Nikolais and Murray Louis, and he now makes intelligent, humorous work that seems to be frequently inspired by literature. This program of new pieces features ''Nearer'' and ''Fallow Bogs,'' both with live music; and ''On the Divide,'' inspired by Willa Cather's ''O Pioneers.'' At 8, Joyce Soho, 155 Mercer Street, (212) 334-7479; $15; $10 for students. (Roslyn Sulcas)</p>
        <p>* LAR LUBOVITCH DANCE COMPANY (Tonight and tomorrow night) Known for the rich flow of his modern-dance choreography, Mr. Lubovitch and his eloquent dancers will present two programs, which include ''Little Rhapsodies,'' with Rasta Thomas, a guest dancer, and Pedja Muzijevic, who will play the piece's Schumann piano score, as well as the music for ''Dvorak Serenade in E.'' Tonight's gala program also includes ''Recordare,'' performed by the Limón Dance Company At 8, Skirball Center for the Performing Arts, 566 LaGuardia Place, at Washington Square South, Greenwich Village, (212) 279-4200, www.skirballcenter.nyu.edu; $250, $500 and $1,000 tonight; $45 tomorrow. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>BARBARA MAHLER (Tonight through Sunday) ''There's No Place Like Home''' features choreography distinguished by tight focus and strong physicality. At 8:30, Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194, danspaceproject.org; $15. (Jack Anderson)</p>
        <p>LA MAMA MOVES! (Thursday) More than 50 companies and soloists, chosen by Nicky Paraiso and Mia Yoo, will perform in this celebration of downtown dance, in programs that will spill out throughout the nooks and crannies of the funky La MaMa complex. The festival opens with ''New Virtuosity,'' a program that includes dances by Robert Battle, Patrick Corbin, Tynek Dusan, Sunhwa Chung and Nick Seligson-Ross. At 7:30 p.m., La MaMa, 74A East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 475-7710, lamama.org; $15; $10 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>GLORIA MCLEAN (Sunday) Ms. McLean, a leading dancer with Erick Hawkins, will present ''Fossil Garden,'' a piece that unfolds amid a sculpture installation by Ken Hiratsuka. The program, which includes a video and sound installation by Jack Waters and Peter Cramer, takes place in Mr. Hiratsuka's basement studio. At 5 p.m., 516 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 529-5660; donation suggested. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* NEW YORK CITY BALLET (Tuesday through Thursday) The company opens its two-month spring season with the first of six performances that will pay tribute to the centenary of Lincoln Kirstein, co-founder of City Ballet with George Balanchine, and the founder and longtime director of the School of American Ballet. Eight of the 10 tribute ballets, all choreographed by Balanchine, will be presented in three programs this week, including ''The Four Temperaments,'' ''Pavane,'' ''Agon,'' ''Symphony in C,'' ''Concerto Barocco,'' ''Duo Concertant,'' ''Square Dance'' and ''Symphony in Three Movements.'' Tuesday and Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 870-5570; (800) 580-8730, nycballet.com; $15 to $95. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* Stephen Petronio Company (Tuesday through Thursday) Stephen Petronio has a reputation for making provocative, sexually charged dances, but his work can often be as much about identity as about sexuality. A new solo, ''For Today I Am a Boy,'' is set to the music of the avant-garde British singer Antony, and seems set to explore such issues. Also on the program are another new piece, ''Without You II''; a revival of Mr. Petronio's 1997 ''ReBourne''; ''The Ship Song,'' (part of a work made in 2003 for the Sydney Dance company); and last year's enjoyable ''Bud Suite.'' Tuesday and Wednesday at 7.30 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800, joyce.org; $40; $30 for Joyce members. (Roslyn Sulcas)</p>
        <p>PMT SHOWCASE (Tomorrow and Sunday) The program will feature dance by David Kieffer, Kai Kleinbard, Yesid Lopez, Ami Mattison, Brenda Neville and Pavan Thimmaiah, the hip-hopster who produced the showcase. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Sunday at 2:30 p.m., Martin Luther King Jr. High School, 122 Amsterdam Avenue, at 65th Street, Manhattan, (212) 924-5694; $16; $10 for students. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>QUEENS THEATER ASIAN CULTURAL FESTIVAL: KUN-YANG LIN/DANCERS (Tonight) Mr. Lin is one of many Asian crossover choreographers, but his distinctive blend of traditional and Western dance has the dark, bold force of a woodcut print. At 8, Queens Theater in the Park, Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, Queens, (718) 760-0064, queenstheatre.org; $28; $26 for 65+; $20 for students. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>WORKS AND PROCESS AT THE GUGGENHEIM: 'SLOW DANCING' (Sunday and Monday) Subtitled ''Motion Portraits of Dancers,'' this program of larger-than-life, slow-motion video portraits by David Michalek will focus on dancers including Desmond Richardson, Wendy Whelan and Herman Cornejo, with a panel discussion including Mr. Michalek and Nigel Redden, director of the Lincoln Center Festival. At 7:30 p.m., Guggenheim Museum, 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3587, worksandprocess.org. On Sunday: $24, $20 for members and 65+., $15 for students. Monday is sold out. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'KINDRED SPIRITS: ASHER B. DURAND AND THE AMERICAN LANDSCAPE,' through July 29. This show of about 60 works by one of the greats of 19th-century American landscape painting has as its centerpiece ''Kindred Spirits'' (1849), a tribute to the landscapist Thomas Cole and his friend the poet-journalist William Cullen Bryant. A founder of the Hudson River School, Durand (1796-1886) favored the realistic approach to landscape advocated by the English critic John Ruskin. Durand explored forest interiors with close attention to the ways of trees, foliage and rocks and ground cover in smaller works, while his larger and more elaborate exhibition pictures, influenced by European masters, are Arcadian visions suffused with light, color and atmospheric perspective. If the show reveals some of Durand's weaknesses -- repetitive themes and borrowings from other artists -- it also reveals his strong sense of artistic mission and his potent role in shaping the aesthetic of 19th-century America. 200 Eastern Parkway, Brooklyn, (718) 638-5000, brooklynmuseum.org. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>FRICK COLLECTION: 'GEORGE STUBBS (1724-1806): A CELEBRATION,' through May 27. One of the finest horse painters ever, Stubbs knew his subjects from head to hoof and skin to bones. He painted other mammals too: dogs, lions, tigers, oxen, monkeys and humans. This intimate show of 17 Stubbs paintings from English collections reveals his admirable range, although the people he portrayed in two large, late canvases, elegiac celebrations of farm workers raking and reaping grain, have the stiffness of figures on a candy box. His horses are his true monuments. 1 East 70th Street, Manhattan, (212) 288-0700, frick.org. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* JAPAN SOCIETY: 'Awakenings: Zen Figure Painting in Medieval Japan,' through June 17. Japan Society has a history of producing exquisite shows of Buddhist art. And this one, with four dozen paintings of Buddhists gods and saints hung in shrinelike alcoves, is transporting. And it covers an unusually broad swath of geography, bringing together 13th- to 16th-century hanging scrolls, not only from Japan but also from China, where Zen Buddhism, called Chan in Chinese, originated. 333 East 47th Street, (212) 832-1155, japansociety.org. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>The Jewish Museum: Dateline: Israel: 'New Photography and Video Art,' through Aug. 5. Roughly every decade, the Jewish Museum offers a survey of contemporary art from and about Israel. This year non-Israeli artists from Europe and the United States -- and a single artist from Palestine -- have been added to the mix. There's some very good work here, though, on the whole, the show grapples with crucial political issues in an indirect way. 1109 Fifth Avenue, at 92nd Street, (212) 423-3200, jewishmuseum.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* the Metropolitan Museum of Art : 'Journeys: Mapping the Earth and Mind in Chinese Art,' through Aug. 26. Every six months or so, the Met rotates all the work in its Chinese painting galleries to preserve the delicate silks and papers, and each time, the curator in charge, Maxwell K. Hearn, produces a new and illuminating thematic exhibition, as is the case with ''Journeys.'' Outward-bound and inward-bound are the directions taken by Chinese landscape painting, and it carries us on some fascinating voyages in a show that mixes classical and contemporary art. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* the met: 'Venice and the Islamic World, 828-1797,' through July 8. At its peak in the Renaissance, Venice, the Most Serene, was a giant, clamorous Costco-on-the-Rialto. All the necessities, and most of the luxuries, of life flowed into and through it, with many items arriving from Islamic Africa and the Near East. With classic Met largesse, this exhibition suggests the spectacle of two different cultures meeting in one fantastic city, in which commerce and love of beauty, those great levelers, unite them in a fruitful bond. (See above.) (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Museum of Contemporary American Diasporan Arts: 'Postmillennial Black Madonna,' through May 13. This group show of young artists takes various approaches to the female figure as myth and symbol in contemporary African-American cultures. 80 Hanson Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0492. A complementary show is at the Skylight Gallery of the Restoration Plaza, 1368 Fulton Street, third floor, Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn, (718) 636-6976, through May 5, mocada.org or postbme.com. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* Museum of Modern Art: JEFF WALL, through May 14. This majestic show makes a great case for Mr. Wall as the most complete, if traditional, of the untraditional artists who emerged from the turmoil of Conceptual Art. His often immense color transparencies mounted on light boxes are enthralling vehicles, intent on giving pleasure while making a point or two about society, art, history, visual perception, the human animal or all of the above. An imposing blend of painting, street photography and movies, they blur reality and artifice, narrative and form, detail and the big statement. You can't stop looking at them. (212) 708-9400, moma.org (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>Whitney Museum of American Art: 'Taryn Simon,' through June 24. Ms. Simon couches the show in the intellectual, power-to-the-people oratory of leftist politics, yet she clearly delights in exposing, in a quasi-tabloid fashion, America's underbelly. Though she has also worked in war-torn areas, Ms. Simon is best known for ''The Innocents,'' a series of portraits of men and women who were wrongly convicted but later cleared by DNA test results. Ms. Simon can work as long as a year to gain permission to photograph high-security zones like the government-regulated quarantine sites, nuclear waste storage facilities, prison death rows and C.I.A. offices on view in the show. There are also pictures with lighter themes: the sandpit where the Grucci family tests fireworks, ski slopes being dynamited for avalanche control and the second Death Star, from ''Return of the Jedi,'' at George Lucas's Skywalker Ranch. Ms. Simon is at her artistic best when her delight in the strangeness of American culture shines. (212) 570-3676, whitney.org. (Bridget Goodbody)</p>
        <p>* Whitney Museum of American Art: 'Lorna Simpson,' through May 6. This tight, refined and impassioned survey covers more than 20 years of Lorna Simpson's career, from her photo-and-text meditations on race and sexism in the 1980s, to her more recent short films, which unite American history and personal history in forceful and lyrical ways. It would be easy to put some of this work on a shelf as ''identity art,'' but with an African-American woman holding one of the highest offices in the United States government, an African-American man running for president, and the nation embroiled in what some people view as an ethnic war, this art is entirely of the moment. (See above.) (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>* Nancy Brooks Brody Some of the abstract ''paintings'' in this beautiful, reticent solo show have been stitched with cotton thread onto paper, creating patterns of linear ridges. Others are made from painstakingly detailed pencil patterns on plaster. The effect is like having Agnes Martin's bars and bands transmitted as sound waves, a soft, vibrant humming. Ms. Brody's sculptures of stacked bars of bath soap, used but not used up, are right in the poetic picture. Virgil de Voldère Gallery, 526 West 26th Street, Room 416, (212) 343-9694, virgilgallery.com, through April 28. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* WALTER DE MARIA Counting and space -- important to both Minimal and Conceptual Art -- come together with unusual clarity, if a bit too much in the way of gleaming metal, in two large installations by the creator of ''The Lightning Field'' earthwork. Both pieces consist of several dozen shiny meter-long stainless-steel rods presented in spaces that couldn't be much more pristine. Experience the spatial levitation and note the number of sides on the rods; in both cases, they increase row by row. Gagosian Gallery, 522 West 21st Street, (212) 741-1717, and 555 West 24th Street, (212) 741-1111, gagosian.com, through May 5. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* JONATHAN MONK: 'SOME KIND OF GAME BETWEEN THIS AND THAT' As usual, this Conceptually inclined Scottish artist concentrates on sly tributes to, or plays on, works by other artists, among them Bruce Nauman, Chris Burden, John Baldessari and René Magritte. The slightest pieces are best, including drawings done on old books and ''The Cheat,'' in which ''this'' and ''that'' consist of an early silent film accompanied by a boom box tuned to a classical music station. Casey Kaplan, 525 West 21st Street, (212) 645-7335, caseykaplangallery.com, through May 5.(Smith)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Other</p>
        <p>'Gifts of the Forest: Native Traditions in Wood and Bark' Drawn from the collections of the Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center in Connecticut, this show celebrates the trees of the rich forests that once covered the Northeast, yielding essential materials to the Pequot and other Eastern Woodland cultures. The objects run from ancient woodworking tools to contemporary objects that carry on tribal traditions, like the simple and beautiful wooden flute made in 1999 by Hawk Henires (Nipmuc) and adorned with an elegantly carved bird motif. Many things here were made in the 19th and 20th centuries: handsome woven baskets, carved bowls and spoons, decorated cradle boards for carrying babies, birch bark canoe models, an elegant birch-bark hamper whose sides bear a stylized tree motif. UBS Art Gallery, 1285 Avenue of the Americas, between 51st and 52nd Streets, (212) 713-2885, ubs.com, through April 27. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* Chelsea Art Museum: 'DANGEROUS BEAUTY' A somewhat timely update of a well-worn idea, this show of contemporary works in a variety of mediums by 18 artists examines the beauty myth in art, advertising and the fashion industry. Eloquent but blunt imagery of anorexic girls, chiseled male beefcake and close-ups of surgically deformed faces predominates, reminding us of the violent extremes to which some people will go in pursuit of society's ideal of beauty and a designer body. The rest of the show -- often pointing an accusatory finger at skinny models, cosmetic labels and the mass media -- feels familiar in its critique, but the basic premise about the ideology of beauty in our culture is beyond argument. 556 West 22nd Street, (212) 255-0719, chelseaartmuseum.org., closes tomorrow. (Benjamin Genocchio)</p>
        <p>* JOAN JONAS An extraordinary double show from a performance-installation-video artist who emerged in the late 1960s and has only gotten better. The centerpiece is a walk-in-collage of sculpture, props and video projections derived from a new performance work, ''The Shape, the Scent, the Feel of Things,'' accompanied by a film of the performance. Based on a memoir by the art historian Aby Warburg, and accompanied by music composed and played by the jazz pianist Jason Moran, it combines a Fluxus playfulness with task-oriented gestures of early '70s dance to achieve a mysterious visual poetry reminiscent of Joseph Cornell, decanted. Yvon Lambert New York, 550 West 21st Street and 564 West 25th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-3611, yvon-lambert.com; closes on Thursday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* National Academy Museum: HIGH TIMES, HARD TIMES: NEW YORK PAINTING, 1967-1975 Organized under the auspices of International Curators Incorporated, this brave if confused exhibition is the first to tackle a neglected subject: New York painting during the period it was supposed to be dead. The show's 42 works by 37 artists reveal that, far from dead, painting was in fact in an uproar that was commensurate with the artistic, social and political turbulence of the times. The alternation between artists who remained loyal in their way to stretched canvas and those who abandoned it, which makes for clear installation, also tidies up history. The main problem is that the exhibition sticks too purposefully to the margins, mixing generations and levels of achievement and continuing the neglect of the main story. Too much of this work is as derivative now as it was then, and functions more as artifact than art. 1083 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 369-4880, nationalacademy.org; closes on Sunday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* 'PAINTINGS, FLAGS &amp; IRON: HAITIAN ART FROM THE LAST FIFTY YEARS' This splendid exhibition offers total immersion in the originality and continued vitality of Haiti's self-taught artists. Works by well-known painters like Hector Hyppolite, Toussaint Auguste and Rigaud Benoit range across religion, history and everyday themes. They include still lifes, landscapes and Pierre Joseph Valcin's enthralling rendering of a maternity ward. The forged and welded sculptures of Georges Liautaud and Gabriel Bien-Aimé are on a par with Bill Traylor's antic silhouette drawings. And there are no words for the extravagantly sequined and beaded flags depicting Voodoo spirits and saints, except fabulous. Edward Thorp Gallery, 210 11th Avenue, at 25th Street, Chelsea, (212) 691-6565, edwardthorpgallery.com; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 24, 2007, Tuesday  A classical music entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on Friday about ''Il Barbiere di Siviglia,'' at the Metropolitan Opera, misidentified the nationality of the baritone Russell Braun, who sings Figaro. Although he was born in Germany, he is Canadian.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 24, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A classical music entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on Friday about ''Il Barbiere di Siviglia,'' at the Metropolitan Opera, misidentified the nationality of the baritone Russell Braun, who sings Figaro. Although he was born in Germany, he is Canadian.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
