<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Overlooked By Some, Parise Finds His Place</title>
    <meta content="20devils" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/sports/hockey/20devils.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841560"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Tampa Bay Lightning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Devils</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E1D91F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="718" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Overlooked By Some, Parise Finds His Place</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Overlooked by Some, Devils’ Parise Finds His Place</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crouse, Karen</byline>
      <dateline>TAMPA, Fla., April 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From his seat in the living room of his home in Minnesota, J. P. Parise was transported back in time Wednesday night.</p>
        <p>Watching his son Zach skate in a pivotal first-round playoff game against the Tampa Bay Lightning, Parise said, he saw shades of himself 32 years ago, when he was a shooting star in the New York hockey cosmos.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Zach Parise did not conjure the decisive goal in overtime in Game 4  Scott Gomez did that  but he loomed large in the Devils’ 4-3 victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From his seat in the living room of his home in Minnesota, J. P. Parise was transported back in time Wednesday night.</p>
        <p>Watching his son Zach skate in a pivotal first-round playoff game against the Tampa Bay Lightning, Parise said, he saw shades of himself 32 years ago, when he was a shooting star in the New York hockey cosmos.</p>
        <p>The command with which the 22-year-old Parise skated, the confidence he radiated on every shift and the way the puck seemed drawn to his magnetic field reminded his father of his own playoff run with the Islanders in 1975. In 17 postseason games that year, J. P. counted eight goals among his 16 points, none bigger than his overtime score that eliminated the Rangers in the first round and sealed the Islanders' first playoff series victory in their three-year history.</p>
        <p>Zach Parise did not conjure the decisive goal in overtime in Game 4 -- Scott Gomez did that -- but he loomed large in the Devils' 4-3 victory, recording his fifth and sixth goals of this Eastern Conference quarterfinal series to assume the league lead. The best-of-seven series is tied at two games each, with Game 5 on Friday night at Continental Arena in East Rutherford, N.J.</p>
        <p>''I was a lot more limited in my skills than Zach is,'' J. P. Parise said Thursday by telephone. ''But when you get on a roll like that, things fall into place. It's nice to see Zach in that zone right now. He's playing with a lot of confidence, and when that happens, things slow down for you and you have more time to do things. You try different things and they work. The puck kind of follows you.''</p>
        <p>Parise's first goal Wednesday came on a play that was suitable for diagramming. The rookie center Travis Zajac sent a crisp pass to defenseman Paul Martin, who threaded the puck to Parise for the first-period score that put the Devils ahead, 2-1.</p>
        <p>In the 10th minute of the second period, Parise extended the Devils' lead to 3-1 by redirecting Andy Greene's shot from the point past Lightning goaltender Johan Holmqvist.</p>
        <p>After that, the Lightning fired off 8 of the game's next 11 shots and was rewarded for its effort with two goals, by Martin St. Louis and Vincent Lecavalier (his fifth), to tie the score at 3-3.</p>
        <p>Lecavalier was the No. 1 overall pick of the Lightning in 1998. He was drafted five years earlier and 16 places higher than Parise, and if Parise's play in this series has been obscured by Lecavalier's, well, what else is new? Parise is used to operating in someone's shadows -- his father's, in the beginning, and more recently, Sidney Crosby's and Alexander Ovechkin's.</p>
        <p>''He came in in an era where he doesn't get recognized because everybody's talking about Sidney Crosby and Ovechkin,'' Devils goaltender Martin Brodeur said. ''He's just lost in the shuffle.''</p>
        <p>His teammates recognize his value. ''He's our top guy offensively, and there's a reason why he is,'' Brodeur said. ''He works his butt off every shift.''</p>
        <p>When Parise took a liking to hockey as a child, J. P. dug deep into his 14 years of experience as an N.H.L. player to bestow upon him this pearl of wisdom: Work harder than everybody else.</p>
        <p>''I always told him one of the things you can always control is being the hardest worker,'' J. P. said. ''And that if you do a little more than everybody else every day, you may just get ahead.''</p>
        <p>More than any hockey gene, Parise inherited his father's work ethic. The two are bound by their surname, but also by their sweat. ''I just work hard and try to create chances,'' Parise said.</p>
        <p>Last season, his first in the N.H.L., Parise played 81 regular-season games and had one goal in nine postseason games. He was working as hard then as he is now, but his labor, according to his father, was somewhat misdirected.</p>
        <p>''He was trying to be a pleaser,'' J. P. said, ''instead of just being a player that does whatever is needed for the team to be successful.''</p>
        <p>It has been a joy for J. P. to watch his son come into his own. It thrills him to be known after all these years as Zach Parise's dad.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
