<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Power Lunch, Mayor Presents Wish List, in a Handy Wallet Size</title>
    <meta content="20donors" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/nyregion/20donors.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841610"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bloomberg, Michael R (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rivera, Ray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bloomberg, Michael R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E1D71F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="633" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Power Lunch, Mayor Presents Wish List, in a Handy Wallet Size</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At Power Lunch, Mayor Presents Wish List, in a Handy Wallet Size</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAY RIVERA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rivera, Ray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mayor Michael R Bloomberg delivers his annual political wish list for New York at bipartisan power lunch at Four Seasons; wallet-size plastic cards are given to each guest, listing six of city's top federal and state agenda items; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The guest list included dozens of the city's most influential power brokers and political donors. The entertainment was a panel discussion moderated by Charlie Rose and featuring Newt Gingrich, the former House speaker, and Harold E. Ford Jr., chairman of the Democratic Leadership Council.</p>
        <p>But the real reason for this bipartisan power lunch at the Four Seasons yesterday was to hear Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg deliver what is becoming his annual political wish list for the city.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The guest list included dozens of the city’s most influential power brokers and political donors. The entertainment was a panel discussion moderated by Charlie Rose and featuring Newt Gingrich, the former House speaker, and Harold E. Ford Jr., chairman of the Democratic Leadership Council.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The guest list included dozens of the city's most influential power brokers and political donors. The entertainment was a panel discussion moderated by Charlie Rose and featuring Newt Gingrich, the former House speaker, and Harold E. Ford Jr., chairman of the Democratic Leadership Council.</p>
        <p>But the real reason for this bipartisan power lunch at the Four Seasons yesterday was to hear Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg deliver what is becoming his annual political wish list for the city.</p>
        <p>For the second straight year, each guest received a wallet-size plastic card, this latest labeled ''New York City Card '07.''</p>
        <p>On the back was a list of six of the city's top federal and state agenda items: $2 billion in federal money to finance a rail link between Lower Manhattan and Kennedy Airport; domestic security funds based on risk -- not pork barrel -- assessments; the easing of visa and financial regulations important to Wall Street; $150 million to treat ailing 9/11 workers; financial incentives for moderately priced housing; and state legislation that will be needed to fulfill the city's long-term sustainability plan, which is to be announced on Sunday.</p>
        <p>A key component of that plan will be a 30 percent reduction in greenhouse gas emissions in the city by the year 2030.</p>
        <p>As guests picked over white asparagus under faux blossoming cherry trees in the restaurant's Pool Room, the mayor urged them to keep their cards close by.</p>
        <p>''The next time a politician calls you and asks you for support and tells you what he or she wants, I think it's time you pull out this card and tell them what New York City needs,'' the mayor said.</p>
        <p>The mayor said the city should use its power as a perennial leader in political contributions. In the 2008 presidential race, the 10021 ZIP code -- little more than a square mile of the Upper East Side -- leads all ZIP codes in the country with more than $2.3 million in donations, according to the mayor's office.</p>
        <p>To look at the guest list -- replete with bankers, chief executives and powerful lobbyists and fund-raisers -- was to get a glimpse of the city's public and private potentates. Those invited included the Republican fund-raiser Georgette Mosbacher and the former chief executives Leonard A. Lauder (Estée Lauder Companies) and Sanford I. Weill (Citigroup), though it was not clear if all those invited attended.</p>
        <p>''Each of us contribute heavily to civic causes and political campaigns,'' Mr. Bloomberg said. ''If you look around this room, these are the people who really make a difference, and by leveraging our influence, we really can make an enormous difference for New York City.''</p>
        <p>That citycentric view has not always gone over well outside New York. But Mr. Gingrich, the former Republican congressman from Georgia, said yesterday that what is good for the city is good for the country.</p>
        <p>''The survival of New York's financial district as the leading financial district in the world is important in every town in the United States,'' Mr. Gingrich said.</p>
        <p>The mayor credited his 2006 card holders with helping to persuade the state to expand charter schools and Congress to block legislation limiting eminent domain.</p>
        <p>Donald B. Marron, head of Lightyear Capital and a longtime trustee of the Museum of Modern Art, brought along the card he received last year.</p>
        <p>''We used the card, and more importantly, people from Washington who visited here were aware the card existed; that in itself was a force,'' Mr. Marron said.</p>
        <p>Ben Barnes, the Texas political legend turned lobbyist, who was in town on a business trip, was also at the luncheon.</p>
        <p>''It seems so simple,'' he said, praising the mayor's card. ''I've been raising money for candidates for a long time, and that's the time to get these people committed -- when they're asking for money.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
