<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nascent Stars Stretch Out In Three Daunting Concertos</title>
    <meta content="20diam" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/arts/music/20diam.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841535"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Young Concert Artists</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0DB1F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="521" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nascent Stars Stretch Out In Three Daunting Concertos</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nascent Stars Stretch Out in Three Daunting Concertos</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Since 1961 the estimable Young Concert Artists organization has been awarding prizes and nurturing the careers of top-notch emerging talents. For the most part this has involved presenting them in recitals. But for the last dozen years or so, the organization has been ending its concert season in New York with a special program, the Irene Diamond Concert, offering several recent winners of Young Concert Artists auditions performing concertos, to let them really show off what they can do.</p>
        <p>As a demonstration of charisma, there is nothing like a concerto, a David-and-Goliath clash between a soloist and an orchestra, and on Wednesday night at the Rose Theater in the Jazz at Lincoln Center complex, three Young Concert Artists winners, two pianists and a flutist, played concertos with the Orchestra of St. Luke's. The concert was conducted by Scott Yoo, who, as a 17-year-old violinist, was a winner in 1989. The event, a gala benefit, was introduced by the tireless Susan Wadsworth, who founded the organization 46 years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wednesday’s concert proved to be a demonstration of charisma, with performances by Young Concert Artists winners, two pianists and a flutist, and the Orchestra of St. Luke’s.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Since 1961 the estimable Young Concert Artists organization has been awarding prizes and nurturing the careers of top-notch emerging talents. For the most part this has involved presenting them in recitals. But for the last dozen years or so, the organization has been ending its concert season in New York with a special program, the Irene Diamond Concert, offering several recent winners of Young Concert Artists auditions performing concertos, to let them really show off what they can do.</p>
        <p>As a demonstration of charisma, there is nothing like a concerto, a David-and-Goliath clash between a soloist and an orchestra, and on Wednesday night at the Rose Theater in the Jazz at Lincoln Center complex, three Young Concert Artists winners, two pianists and a flutist, played concertos with the Orchestra of St. Luke's. The concert was conducted by Scott Yoo, who, as a 17-year-old violinist, was a winner in 1989. The event, a gala benefit, was introduced by the tireless Susan Wadsworth, who founded the organization 46 years ago.</p>
        <p>The concertos were played without intermission. Coming between a rhapsodic account of Grieg's popular Piano Concerto in A minor, played by Chu-Fang Huang, and a brilliant performance of Prokofiev's daunting Piano Concerto No. 3 in C, played by Gleb Ivanov, the gifted young Hungarian flutist Dora Seres, who played Mozart's beguiling Flute Concerto in G, must have felt sandwiched in. But Ms. Seres is an impressive artist who played with Mozartean style, attractively warm tone, admirable clarity and lyrical grace.</p>
        <p>Playing a repertory staple like the Grieg concerto takes some daring, since it is hard to distinguish yourself in the piece. But throughout the performance by the Chinese-born Ms. Huang, you sensed the excitement of a young pianist who could hardly wait to get her turn at it. She played with richly mellow tone, vivid colorings and Romantic flair. In a piece that is often the occasion for expressive liberties, Ms. Huang gave a refreshingly direct, honest and sensitive account.</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Yoo is a nimble conductor, there were surprising coordination glitches here and there between Ms. Huang and the orchestra. Preparing three concertos with three very different soloists cannot be easy.</p>
        <p>The Prokofiev Third is a touchstone work for emerging virtuosos. The music teases you into thinking it's a Neo-Classical romp, with its bustling 16-note scales and passagework. But it keeps breaking out into pummeling, propulsive, arm-blurring and harmonically astringent intensity, along with episodes of weighty, ruminative somberness.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Ivanov, a tall, husky Russian who towered over Mr. Yoo, took the stage, he certainly looked like a pianist who could conquer the Prokofiev Third. And he did, playing with incisive attack, a supple touch in the scurrying passagework, blistering power for the volatile outbursts of chords and plenty of stamina.</p>
        <p>As he matures, he may develop the courage to take the piece, especially the first movement, a notch or two more slowly. He was so full of breathless drive that he let themes and motifs become garbled in a rush of energy. Still, this is not to quibble. Mr. Ivanov brought this festive program to an exhilarating conclusion.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
