<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Brutal Passage From India to Misery at Sea, and Back</title>
    <meta content="20migrant" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/world/asia/20migrant.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841565"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Migration</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Migration</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">India</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04EFD91F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1042" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Brutal Passage From India to Misery at Sea, and Back</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Brutal Passage From India to Misery at Sea, and Back</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROLINE BROTHERS</byline>
      <dateline>DUBAI, United Arab Emirates</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Twenty-four Indian men, two of them too young to shave, were sitting under the fake palm trees in the transit zone at the Dubai airport, dressed in track suits like a sports team -- but one dejected by loss.</p>
        <p>The 24 were making the last leg of a journey home to the farmlands of Punjab. They had not intended to return so soon. Most had left six or nine months ago on a desperate voyage along the newest route of migration from Asia to Europe, going by plane to the Middle East, then across Africa and by sea to Europe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Twenty-four Indian men told their painful tales en route, just a few stories from the vast global saga of migrants in motion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Twenty-four Indian men, two of them too young to shave, were sitting under the fake palm trees in the transit zone at the Dubai airport, dressed in track suits like a sports team -- but one dejected by loss.</p>
        <p>The 24 were making the last leg of a journey home to the farmlands of Punjab. They had not intended to return so soon. Most had left six or nine months ago on a desperate voyage along the newest route of migration from Asia to Europe, going by plane to the Middle East, then across Africa and by sea to Europe.</p>
        <p>But they had made it only as far as a dismal warehouse in Mauritania. They were among nearly 400 migrants on a decrepit shrimp trawler, the Marine I, that probably set off from the troubled West African nation of Guinea or from Ivory Coast in early December and then meandered for 11 miserable weeks until it was rescued and towed to safety in Mauritania. At first, the migrants withheld their names and nationalities, but as time passed, they began to identify themselves and volunteered to go home.</p>
        <p>The International Organization for Migration has repatriated 161 to India. Among them are the 24 who told their painful tales en route, just a few stories from the vast global saga of people in motion.</p>
        <p>The men described fear and privation on their journeys, but they found scant relief in returning to their villages and farms. Shame, vanished livelihoods and insurmountable debt lay ahead of them.</p>
        <p>''For a short time my family will be happy,'' Naresh, 37, a sugar cane farmer from Punjab, said on the flight that took the group from Tunis to Dubai. ''I feel very sad because of everything we have lost.''</p>
        <p>Ajay, 26, used to sell clothes in a Punjab market. His son was just 15 days old when Ajay left home nine months ago. ''How can I show my face to my son?'' he said.</p>
        <p>All said they had been misled, promised a quick and safe passage to Europe, with no mention of Africa or any journey by sea.</p>
        <p>The 24 were reluctant to give any details about the smugglers. Nervous after facing so many threats, they also asked that their full names not be used.</p>
        <p>The Indians said they had borrowed against everything they owned to raise the money -- an average $7,000 fee -- for the trip, in the hope of few years of work abroad. They were returning with just $500 each from the aid group.</p>
        <p>Smugglers ''gave us a visa to go by airplane, not by ship,'' said Davinda, who said he was 18 but looked younger. ''They said it would take three days and it took six to nine months, and they behaved like Ali Baba.''</p>
        <p>In the airport, the men stuck together in small bands as they wandered past Arab sheiks in flowing white robes and the Pakistan junior field hockey team in green blazers.</p>
        <p>Time and again, they sought assurance that they would be accompanied through the New Delhi airport by Khaled Qadir, a representative of the aid group.</p>
        <p>Mr. Qadir said the men had fallen victim to smugglers. ''They are illiterate and uneducated,'' he said, ''and it is very easy to give these people a rosy picture, telling them they can get to Greece or Spain and make thousands of dollars and make the family happy.''</p>
        <p>When their sea voyage began, the Indians said, they were ferried out in groups of 25 to 35 to the corroded hulk of the Marine I by night, in small boats.</p>
        <p>Naresh, the sugar cane farmer, said he had waited six months in a house with 115 other men before embarking. He said that when they boarded, ''Conakry men'' -- a reference to the capital of Guinea -- tried to inject them with drugs they were told would put them to sleep. He managed to resist, he said, but some of the passengers did not.</p>
        <p>Ajay said he was on one of the last boatloads. He estimated that 330 men were already huddled in the hold. The heat grew stifling. There were no sanitary provisions and with the men below deck forbidden to come up for air or anything else, tensions quickly arose.</p>
        <p>Some of the passengers ''behaved very badly,'' Naresh said, and were aggressive in commandeering the rations. ''They hit us and wouldn't give us food.'' Some had knives, he said. Fed once every 36 hours on nothing but rice, the men shared one bottle of water a day between six.</p>
        <p>Fever broke out. They were plagued by lice and rashes. ''I wanted to die,'' Naresh said.</p>
        <p>After weeks at sea the ship was buzzed by surveillance aircraft. The captain took off, ostensibly to bring back food. The passengers never saw him again.</p>
        <p>A Spanish rescue vessel towed the ship to port in Mauritania. But in the shelter there, it slowly dawned on them that they would never make it to Europe, and the first of the 369 men asked to go home.</p>
        <p>''I cried when the first group left, because I realized that we had no chance of going to Spain,'' said Mandeep, a bright-eyed 27-year-old who studied history and Punjabi. ''Then I understood that I, too, was going back, that everything was finished, that all my money was gone, and I had risked my life.''</p>
        <p>Their families had bought into their dreams of a passage to Europe, most of them said. The men borrowed against their houses, their shops or the farms passed down the generations.</p>
        <p>Deepa, 24, a taxi driver who wound up trapped in a house in Conakry for 18 months, had pawned his taxi and his home.</p>
        <p>Ajay met a man ''through a friend'' who said that he could get Ajay to Italy ''in two or three days.''</p>
        <p>Ajay's relatives pooled their jewelry and his parents mortgaged their home. ''I don't know how to pay the money back,'' Ajay said in English he taught himself from a book. ''If I don't pay it back, they will take the house.''</p>
        <p>Despite all they lost, many of the 24 said they would make another attempt to get to Europe.</p>
        <p>But not Deepa. ''God saved my life,'' he said. ''I'm not going to try again.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
