<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trial of Amgen Drug May Dispel Some Safety Concerns</title>
    <meta content="20amgen" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/business/20amgen.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841571"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Anemia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Anemia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anemia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Amgen Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00EED91F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="820" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trial of Amgen Drug May Dispel Some Safety Concerns</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Trial of Amgen Drug May Dispel Some Safety Concerns</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW POLLACK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In an announcement that could dispel at least some of the recent safety concerns over a widely used class of drugs, Amgen said yesterday that its anemia drug Aranesp did not increase the death rate of lung cancer patients in a closely watched clinical trial.</p>
        <p>In the trial, which involved 600 patients with small-cell lung cancer who were receiving chemotherapy, there was essentially no difference in survival between those who received Aranesp and those who received a placebo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Aranesp did not increase the death rate of lung cancer patients in a closely watched clinical trial.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In an announcement that could dispel at least some of the recent safety concerns over a widely used class of drugs, Amgen said yesterday that its anemia drug Aranesp did not increase the death rate of lung cancer patients in a closely watched clinical trial.</p>
        <p>In the trial, which involved 600 patients with small-cell lung cancer who were receiving chemotherapy, there was essentially no difference in survival between those who received Aranesp and those who received a placebo.</p>
        <p>Amgen's stock surged $2.31, or 4 percent, to close at $62.32.</p>
        <p>The results mean that Amgen has dodged a bullet, analysts said. Had the results shown a safety problem, sales would have plunged. That is not expected to happen now, although some analysts said there were still safety concerns.</p>
        <p>The drug maker Roche, for instance, has ended a clinical trial with lung cancer patients that compared Aranesp with an anemia drug it is developing because of an unexpected number of deaths in at least some of the treatment groups, a Roche spokeswoman confirmed yesterday.</p>
        <p>Roche had announced in February that enrollment of new patients had been suspended. But after further review of the data, treatment of already enrolled patients has now also been terminated. That suggests the safety concerns are serious.</p>
        <p>Aranesp, along with Epogen from Amgen and Procrit from Johnson &amp; Johnson, are used by nearly a million Americans a year, mainly to treat anemia from kidney disease or cancer chemotherapy. Combined sales of the three drugs were nearly $10 billion last year. Aranesp and Epogen together accounted for $6.6 billion of Amgen's $14.3 billion in 2006 revenue.</p>
        <p>Last month, the Food and Drug Administration imposed strict new warnings on all three drugs after evidence emerged suggesting they could make cancer worse, cause heart problems or hasten death.</p>
        <p>But some of the evidence, particularly involving cancer, has come from trials that were not specifically set up to study survival, making it more difficult to draw definitive conclusions about the risk. That is why attention has focused on the lung cancer study, which was devised from the outset to measure patients' survival.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Amgen issued a news release with sketchy details of the trial, known as the ''145'' study, declining to say more until it announces quarterly earnings on Monday. The release noted that the risk of death was actually reduced by 7 percent in the people who received Aranesp, but the effect was far too small to be statistically significant.</p>
        <p>Roger M. Perlmutter, Amgen's executive vice president for research and development, said in a statement that the results contributed to ''reinforcing the neutral impact'' of the anemia drugs on patients' survival.</p>
        <p>But Geoffrey C. Porges, an analyst at Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company, said it was premature to say Amgen was out of the woods.</p>
        <p>''If the study had been bad, it would have been an unmitigated disaster,'' Mr. Porges said. ''But leaping to the conclusion that just because it's O.K. in small-cell lung cancer, that makes it O.K. in head and neck cancer and breast cancer and colon cancer is ridiculous.''</p>
        <p>Dr. John A. Glaspy, an oncologist at the University of California, Los Angeles, said the new results went ''a long way toward assuaging my concerns,'' although he said it would be good to see similar results in one or two other types of cancer.</p>
        <p>Dr. Glaspy, who has received research and consulting fees from Amgen, said the company had chosen small-cell lung cancer for the 145 study because it had reason to believe results would be more favorable than for other types of cancer.</p>
        <p>Further pressure on Amgen could come from Congress. Representative Pete Stark, a California Democrat who heads the House Ways and Means Subcommittee on Health, sent a letter to his House colleagues yesterday urging a change in Medicare to remove incentives for dialysis centers to overuse the anemia drugs.</p>
        <p>A study published in The Journal of the American Medical Association this week showed that profit-making dialysis centers used significantly more of the drugs than nonprofit centers did.</p>
        <p>The 145 study was devised in 2001 and 2002 during headier times when Amgen thought it could expand use of Aranesp. The goal was to show that using more of the drug than absolutely necessary to treat anemia could actually help patients live longer.</p>
        <p>Patients in the study were treated with Aranesp with a goal of raising the levels of hemoglobin -- the oxygen-carrying component of red blood cells -- to 13 to 14 grams per deciliter, even though the recommended level on the drug's label is 12 or less.</p>
        <p>But as evidence mounted that the drugs could be dangerous, Amgen executives began hoping merely that the 145 trial would not show a negative effect.</p>
        <p>That is apparently what happened. And the lack of risk seen at the higher hemoglobin levels is likely to reassure doctors about the safety of the drug when it is used less aggressively.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
