<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pill That Eliminates the Period Gets Decidedly Mixed Reviews</title>
    <meta content="20period" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/health/20period.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841681"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Food and Drug Administration</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E7DF163EF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1659" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pill That Eliminates the Period Gets Decidedly Mixed Reviews</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pill That Eliminates the Period Gets Mixed Reviews</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE SAUL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For many women, a birth control pill that eliminates monthly menstruation might seem a welcome milestone.</p>
        <p>But others view their periods as fundamental symbols of fertility and health, researchers have found. Rather than loathing their periods, women evidently carry on complex love-hate relationships with them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some women are uneasy about the idea of a contraceptive pill that is designed to eliminate monthly menstruation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For many women, a birth control pill that eliminates monthly menstruation might seem a welcome milestone.</p>
        <p>But others view their periods as fundamental symbols of fertility and health, researchers have found. Rather than loathing their periods, women evidently carry on complex love-hate relationships with them.</p>
        <p>This ambivalence is one reason that a decision expected next month by the Food and Drug Administration has engendered controversy. The agency is expected to approve the first contraceptive pill that is designed to eliminate periods as long as a woman takes it. Doctors say they know of no extra risk to the new regimen, but some women are uneasy about the idea.</p>
        <p>''My concern is that the menstrual cycle is an outward sign of something that's going on hormonally in the body,'' said Christine L. Hitchcock, a researcher at the University of British Columbia. Ms. Hitchcock said she worries about ''the idea that you can turn your body on and off like a tap.''</p>
        <p>That viewpoint is apparently one reason some already available birth control pills that can enable women to have only four periods a year have not captured a larger share of the oral contraceptive market.</p>
        <p>''It's not an easy decision for a woman to give up her monthly menses,'' said Ronny Gal, an analyst at Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>But if the new pill, called Lybrel, is approved, Mr. Gal predicts an onslaught of advertising meant to persuade women to do just that. The drug's maker, Wyeth, said yesterday that it was expecting F.D.A. approval in May, but has declined to discuss its marketing plans.</p>
        <p>The company's research shows that nearly two-thirds of women it surveyed expressed an interest in giving up their periods. That dovetails with the findings of similar research conducted by Linda C. Andrist, a professor at MGH Institute of Health Professions in Boston.</p>
        <p>''We don't want to confront our bodily functions anymore,'' Ms. Andrist said. ''We're too busy.'' Doctors say they know of no medical reason women taking birth control pills need to have a period. The monthly bleeding that women on pills experience is not a real period, in fact.</p>
        <p>And studies have found no extra health risks associated with pills that stop menstruation, although some doctors caution that little research has been conducted on long-term effects.</p>
        <p>The topic has, however, inspired an hourlong documentary by Giovanna Chesler, ''Period: The End of Menstruation?,'' currently screening on college campuses and among feminist groups.</p>
        <p>Ms. Chesler, who teaches documentary making at the University of California, San Diego, said she became concerned about efforts to eliminate menstruation when she first heard about the idea several years ago.</p>
        <p>''Women are not sick,'' she said. ''They don't need to control their periods for 30 or 40 years.''</p>
        <p>The subject has also ignited a debate within the Society for Menstrual Cycle Research, a scientific organization that studies both the medical and social science of menses.</p>
        <p>In 2003, the group issued a position statement saying that more research was needed before women could make an informed choice about using pills that suppress their periods. That statement could be revised at the group's meeting scheduled for Vancouver, British Columbia, in June.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hitchcock, a director of the organization, said that although some research has been comforting, she remained concerned that medical science did not fully understand the long-term implications of interrupting women's periods. The same hormones that work on the menstrual cycles act in the brain, bones and the skin, she said.</p>
        <p>''You need to think about whether there are consequences we don't know about for the whole body,'' said Ms. Hitchcock, who is with the Center for Menstrual Cycle and Ovulation Research.</p>
        <p>There has also been a backlash among groups that celebrate the period as a spiritual or natural process, like the California-based Red Web Foundation. ''The focus of our group is to create positive attitudes toward the menstrual cycle; suppressing it wouldn't be positive,'' said Anna C. Yang, a holistic nurse and executive director of the organization.</p>
        <p>Eliminating menstruation is not a completely new concept. Women who take any kind of oral contraceptive do not have real periods.</p>
        <p>Because the hormones in pills stop the monthly release of an egg and the buildup of the uterine lining, there is no need for the lining to shed -- as occurs during true menstruation.</p>
        <p>Still, since the advent of oral contraceptives in 1960, birth control pills typically have been designed to mimic the natural 28-day menstrual cycle to assure women using the pill that their bodies were functioning normally. The pills are usually packaged as regimens of 21 days of hormone pills and 7 inactive pills. The interruption of hormone therapy during the inactive part of the regimen induces bleeding that resembles a mild period but is, in fact, caused by unstable hormone levels.</p>
        <p>In recent years, drug makers have come out with new pill regimens that tinker with the 28-day cycle by increasing the number of hormone pills, creating a shorter span of bleeding.</p>
        <p>The drug maker Barr caused a sensation in 2003 by introducing Seasonale, a contraceptive regimen packed as 84 hormone pills and 7 placebo pills. Users have ''periods'' once every three months.</p>
        <p>Carol Cox, a spokesman for Barr, said that Seasonale sales reached $120 million in the 12 months ended June 2006, before a generic equivalent by Watson entered the market. But even at that peak, Seasonale accounted for what Mr. Gal called a ''small segment'' of the $1.7 billion annual United States market for oral contraceptives.</p>
        <p>But Barr, which say it believes that there is a larger market for the pills, is sponsoring a Web site, www.fewerperiods.com, that explains how the pill works. And the company plans a direct advertising campaign within the next few months for a newer version, Seasonique, which also reduces periods to four a year.</p>
        <p>At a Wyeth presentation to investors and analysts in New York last October, the company's therapeutic director for women's health, Dr. Ginger D. Constantine, presented data predicting that annual sales could reach $250 million for Lybrel, which is designed to be taken daily.</p>
        <p>The company has not said what it expects to charge for Lybrel, but birth control pills generally cost $18 to $50 a month, depending on the brand.</p>
        <p>Dr. Constantine cited company-financed research indicating that women often feel less effective at work and school during their periods. They limit sexual activity and exercise, wear dark clothes and stay home more, resulting in absenteeism, she said.</p>
        <p>Menstrual suppression may be particularly appealing to women who suffer severe pain, heavy bleeding or emotional problems during their periods. A study by Canadian researchers found that women afflicted by heavy menstrual bleeding give up $1,692 a year in lost wages.</p>
        <p>One woman who now uses Seasonale said she had found her periods debilitating before she started taking it.</p>
        <p>''I had some months when I couldn't get out of bed unless I popped 600 milligrams of Motrin,'' said Marcella O'Neal, a department manager for Nordstrom in Atlanta. Ms. O'Neal, 36, said Seasonale had eliminated many of her symptoms -- cramping, hot flashes and depression. ''I love it, actually,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Views about menstruation have long been mixed. Some cultures have banished menstruating women to huts or required special baths after periods. Others believed that menstruating women had special powers.</p>
        <p>In her diary kept while in hiding from the Nazis, Anne Frank mused about menstruation. ''I have the feeling that in spite of all the pain, unpleasantness and nastiness I have a sweet secret,'' she wrote.</p>
        <p>Wyeth's research indicates that ambivalence toward the menstrual period continues today. A look at the data reveals that half of the women said they found comfort in their periods as an indication that they were not pregnant. Nearly a quarter of the women polled said they were attached to their periods as a natural part of womanhood.</p>
        <p>The currently available medical research shows that the side effects of pills that suppress menstruation are the same as the side effects of regular birth control pills. The risks are generally low, but the most significant risk is cardiovascular problems in women who smoke, the reason that pills are packaged with a warning not to smoke.</p>
        <p>But some doctors caution that there is no data on what happens when menstruation is suppressed for a very long time.</p>
        <p>''We don't have any long-term studies for what happens if you stop periods for years and years and years,'' said Dr. Maria Bustillo, a reproductive endocrinologist in Miami. Dr. Bustillo said there was probably no increased risk over traditional birth control regimens, but added that the ''jury is still out'' on whether breast cancer risk might be increased.</p>
        <p>Although studies are conflicting, some have shown that the birth control pill may increase that risk. According to the National Cancer Institute, research indicates that the pill increases the risk of liver cancer in otherwise low-risk women while decreasing the risk of cancers of the ovary and the endometrium -- the lining of the uterus.</p>
        <p>With Barr's Seasonale and Seasonique, the biggest medical problem so far -- one that has also cropped up in tests of Wyeth's Lybrel -- is that users can have unpredictable and irregular bleeding or ''spotting'' that is worse than with regular birth control pills. But for some women who view their periods as the natural order of things, the qualms go beyond purely medical concerns.</p>
        <p>At the alternative Bluestockings Bookstore on the Lower East Side of Manhattan early this month, several dozen women gathered for the New York premiere of ''Period: The End of Menstruation?,'' Ms. Chesler's hourlong documentary. It explores the idea of suppressing the menstrual period but leaves the viewer to make up her own mind.</p>
        <p>One who attended the screening, Aviva Bergman, a 22-year-old student at Goucher College in Maryland, said she would not use products that suppressed her period because it seemed unnatural.</p>
        <p>''I just feel that there's a reason you're getting it every month,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
