<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Southern Californians Look to Brown Hills With a Fear of Fires</title>
    <meta content="20heat" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/us/20heat.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841589"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinhauer, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E7D71F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="782" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Southern Californians Look to Brown Hills With a Fear of Fires</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Southern Californians Look to Brown Hills With a Fear of Fires</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER STEINHAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinhauer, Jennifer</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, April 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Winter rainy season in southern California is driest in well over century, and residents fear coming season of frequent powerful fires; lack of rain has made region's hillsides potential tinderboxes; normal fire season tends to start in late May, but many local fire departments say they will start official season at end of April; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The hills and palm trees have turned sepia, the winds crackle and the skin of many Angelenos, with the texture and appearance of unpeeled onions, needs a slathering of cream.</p>
        <p>The winter rainy season here has been the driest in well over a century. Much of Southern California and broad swaths of the West are also suffering -- and fearing next a season of virulent fires.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Much of Southern California and broad swaths of the West are suffering from a lack of winter rain and fearing a season of virulent fires.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The hills and palm trees have turned sepia, the winds crackle and the skin of many Angelenos, with the texture and appearance of unpeeled onions, needs a slathering of cream.</p>
        <p>The winter rainy season here has been the driest in well over a century. Much of Southern California and broad swaths of the West are also suffering -- and fearing next a season of virulent fires.</p>
        <p>Since last July, it has rained a mere 2.4 inches in downtown Los Angeles, far below the 15-inch average for the same period, the driest it has been since 1877. The already arid Antelope Valley just north of the city has had about 10 percent of its normal rainfall -- less than an inch -- and Burbank is barely better off. The state's overall snow pack is about 40 percent of its normal level, the lowest since 1988.</p>
        <p>Throughout the West, a dry winter has parched places like Phoenix and Reno, Nev., where roughly half the normal amount of rain has fallen. But the situation in Southern California is particularly egregious. Every morning brings another grim march toward the lawn sprinklers and twitchy glances toward the ever-flammable hills.</p>
        <p>''Southern California has been really hard hit,'' said Elissa Lynn, a senior meteorologist at the California Department of Water Resources.</p>
        <p>Thanks to heavy rains last year, particularly in the north, Ms. Lynn said, the state's reservoirs remain in good shape and a serious drought is not in the offing. But the dry weather, compounded by dry vegetation left by an unusually harsh freeze over the winter and a very windy spring have raised the specter of frequent powerful fires throughout Southern California.</p>
        <p>''You have very dry, very dead fuel out there,'' said Jamie Meier, a meteorologist with the Los Angeles office of the National Weather Service. ''It has the potential to be a difficult fire season.''</p>
        <p>Brush fires, less common in the winter months, have been numerous this year. There have been more than a dozen in Ventura County alone. Last week, three homes burned in Beverly Hills, where flames were whipped by unseasonably high winds.</p>
        <p>Ventura County never ended the official fire season that began last spring and now is bracing for a tough summer.</p>
        <p>''Fire season is a year-round event for us now,'' said Bob Roper, fire chief for Ventura County. ''Right now what we're seeing is that the fuel conditions are already at a critical level and Southern California has had a lot of wind conditions. All I can say is conditions are present to have a really bad season.''</p>
        <p>The normal fire season in Southern California tends to begin at the end of May, but many local departments said they will start the official season at the end of this month. Firefighters will respond in greater numbers to calls around the state and monitor weather conditions closely. Near the Hollywood sign, where a brush fire burned nearby this spring, the dried brush and sand have combined to create a landscape more like the high desert's than like the postcard image of palm trees with dabs of green. Now, its hill is a tinderbox looming over the city.</p>
        <p>A lack of green plant life, which retards fire growth, raises further concerns among fire officials.</p>
        <p>''Certainly looking at the numbers and looking at the vegetation, it looks July already out there,'' said John R. Todd, chief of the forestry division of the Los Angeles County Fire Department. ''Another building concern is that we had a huge rain year in 2005 and all that growth is available to become fuel.''</p>
        <p>A lack of precipitation has crinkled plants, shortened ski seasons and withered the land in large sections of Arizona, Nevada, eastern regions in Oregon, and parts of northern Utah and southern Idaho, said Kelly T. Redmond, regional climatologist at the Western Regional Climate Center in Reno.</p>
        <p>Flagstaff, Ariz., for instance, has had almost half its usual 105 inches of snow this season. Only 2.2 inches of rain has fallen in Reno since Oct. 1, about 43 percent of normal levels.</p>
        <p>Two previous wet winters have kept the reservoirs along the Sierra Nevada amply supplied, enough to offset the effects of this dry season, Mr. Redmond said.</p>
        <p>''A lot of the water interests are now looking ahead to next winter,'' Mr. Redmond added. ''If they get a second winter like this, they are going to be in a world of hurt.''</p>
        <p>There are beneficiaries of the dry winter.</p>
        <p>Julia Sandoval, an aesthetician at the Ra Organic Spa in Burbank, has been living it up with creams containing alpha lipoic acid, an antioxidant.</p>
        <p>''I have seen the dry season reflected on everyone's skin who comes in,'' Ms. Sandoval said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
