<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Agencies Hear a Call for More Creativity, but Also More Accountability</title>
    <meta content="20adco" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/business/media/20adco.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841570"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">American Assn of Advertising Agencies</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EED91F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1054" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Agencies Hear a Call for More Creativity, but Also More Accountability</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Agencies Hear a Call for More Creativity, but Also More Accountability</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STUART ELLIOTT</byline>
      <dateline>NAPLES, Fla.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Decades ago, the Benton &amp; Bowles agency insisted ''It's not creative unless it sells.'' Now, several senior industry leaders are reworking that maxim to assert that it won't sell unless it's creative.</p>
        <p>Creativity as the pathway to consumer persuasion -- and profitability -- was a major theme here yesterday at the opening general session of the 2007 management conference of the American Association of Advertising Agencies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Creativity as the pathway to consumer persuasion  and profitability was a major theme at a recent advertising conference.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Decades ago, the Benton &amp; Bowles agency insisted ''It's not creative unless it sells.'' Now, several senior industry leaders are reworking that maxim to assert that it won't sell unless it's creative.</p>
        <p>Creativity as the pathway to consumer persuasion -- and profitability -- was a major theme here yesterday at the opening general session of the 2007 management conference of the American Association of Advertising Agencies.</p>
        <p>The creativity being celebrated by the speakers was not of the artsy, award-winning variety, but rather an accountable kind that is rooted in insights derived from hard data about customer shopping patterns.</p>
        <p>''The single greatest divide in our business is not the gap between client and agency,'' said Howard Draft, chairman and chief executive at Draft FCB, part of the Interpublic Group of Companies. ''The most damaging distance has always been the split between creativity and accountability.''</p>
        <p>''Every agency has to become fully accountable for its work, every day, on a real-time basis,'' Mr. Draft said. ''The way to great creative, and to great results, is not to run away from accountability but to embrace it.''</p>
        <p>''Our objective is to reduce uncertainty so we can take more creative risks,'' he added, repeating the last three words for emphasis.</p>
        <p>For instance, Mr. Draft described how the 9,000 employees of his agency, formed last year by the merger of Draft and Foote Cone &amp; Belding, are being trained to incorporate customer data into the creative process, ''to come up with big ideas that incite consumer behavior.''</p>
        <p>''Creativity is enhanced by the behavioral intelligence,'' he added. ''Our teams are free to push the creative to the edge and beyond, secure in the knowledge that the underlying strategies are sound.''</p>
        <p>''We recently won a retail account where the owner is a hedge fund guy,'' Mr. Draft said with a smile, referring to the surprising news on Tuesday that Draft FCB was awarded the $200 million creative account of Kmart, part of the Sears Holdings Corporation overseen by Edward S. Lampert.</p>
        <p>''Much as hedge funds operate less on fixed fees and more on participation in performance,'' Mr. Draft said, ''we see the day coming when the majority of agency compensation will be linked to the returns our clients reap from our creative imaginations.''</p>
        <p>The employees assigned to the Kmart account will use consumer data to shape their creative approaches, he added, as those working for clients like Citigroup and the UnitedHealth Group already do.</p>
        <p>Chuck Brymer, president and chief executive at DDB Worldwide, part of the Omnicom Group, endorsed Mr. Draft's concept of collecting data not to tell advertisers what consumers have been buying but to predict what they may or may not buy in the future.</p>
        <p>''Data is no substitute for creativity,'' said Mr. Brymer, whose agency is still fondly recalled for right-brained campaigns for clients like Volkswagen (''Think small'').</p>
        <p>''But I do think by using more predictive analytics, we can create the opportunity and the case for creativity and unleash our creative potential even further,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brymer called for the development of advanced research techniques that would offer ''new opportunities for companies to know more about their brands and their customers and to act more decisively'' as well as help agencies understand why shoppers prefer one product over another ''and how to influence customer behavior.''</p>
        <p>Roy Spence, the president of another Omnicom unit, GSD&amp;M, spoke of how his agency, which thinks highly enough of creativity to call its headquarters in Austin, Tex., Idea City, has on retainer consultants like M.I.T. Laboratories to stimulate ideas for clients that include the Air Force, BMW and Southwest Airlines.</p>
        <p>''We're reaching out to get new thinking because we don't have a corner on smarts,'' Mr. Spence said in his down-home style, adding: ''We're humble about that. We're scared about that.''</p>
        <p>The goal is to develop ''that visionary idea,'' Mr. Spence said, that will keep an agency ''in the business of making a difference, not just making ads.''</p>
        <p>''Don't you love it when your creatives come to you and say: 'You know that Nike spot? This spot is kind of like that one,' '' he added, laughing. ''We need to find ideas that will create a sea change and help a client become a leader, not a follower.''</p>
        <p>Several speakers discussed a popular trend known as user-generated content, which hopes to encourage creativity by recruiting consumers to produce commercials, video clips and jingles. Among the brands sponsoring forms of user-generated content are Chevrolet, Converse, Doritos and Dove.</p>
        <p>''I guess we were all jolted and even a little 'one-upped' by a very powerful force for change, those real people out there,'' said Susan Gianinno, chairwoman and chief executive at Publicis USA, part of the Publicis Worldwide division of the Publicis Groupe, calling the trend ''unlike most anything I've seen in my career.''</p>
        <p>''The thing is, people who act like ad agencies are just the tip of the iceberg,'' she added, citing consumers who use blogs to tell marketers ''how to make their products better'' and who are designing the products they buy, like ''M&amp;M's in custom colors, with personal messages.''</p>
        <p>Madison Avenue should not feel too threatened by consumers ''insinuating themselves as creators of content,'' Ms. Gianinno said, even if the amateurs ''have much more freedom than we do to be as creative as they can be.''</p>
        <p>The reason is that in an era when it is easier than ever for people to avoid ads, ''what they do watch, listen to and are receptive to means so much more than it ever did,'' she added.</p>
        <p>Mr. Draft, remarking on the trend, paraphrased a familiar advisory by the advertising leader David Ogilvy: ''The consumer is not a moron. She is your wife.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Draft's version: ''The consumer is not just our wife. She, he, they all are our creative partners.''</p>
        <p>The conference of the advertising agency association, known as the Four A's, is the 89th annual meeting of the organization. The conference began here at a resort hotel on Wednesday and concludes today.</p>
        <p>About 370 people are attending the conference, compared with 390 last year, 379 in 2005 and 331 in 2004. The most recent high was 450, in 2000, and the most recent low was 257, in 2003. Attendance at the meeting each year is considered something of a gauge of the industry's health.</p>
        <p>MEDIA: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
