<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>One Certainty of Draft: Giants Have Holes to Fill</title>
    <meta content="20giants" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/sports/football/20giants.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841557"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Giants</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Reese, Jerry</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E2D91F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="786" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>One Certainty of Draft: Giants Have Holes to Fill</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">One Certainty of Draft: Giants Have Holes to Fill</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN BRANCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Branch, John</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., April 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the January day that Jerry Reese was introduced as the Giants' general manager, he was reluctant to assess the team's specific needs.</p>
        <p>''You guys know the hotspots,'' he told reporters Jan. 16. ''We're going to address hotspots in free agency and the draft.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Giants’ reluctance to toss large sums at what they thought was a relatively mediocre group of available veterans has put more focus on improving the team through the draft.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the January day that Jerry Reese was introduced as the Giants' general manager, he was reluctant to assess the team's specific needs.</p>
        <p>''You guys know the hotspots,'' he told reporters Jan. 16. ''We're going to address hotspots in free agency and the draft.''</p>
        <p>Three months later, with a largely uneventful free-agent period behind him and the N.F.L. draft nine days away, Reese was at the lectern again. Several hotspots, it would seem, still smolder.</p>
        <p>Free agency provided little relief, in part because of the Giants' reluctance to toss large sums at what they thought was a relatively mediocre group of available veterans. That has put more focus on improving the team through the draft, a difficult place to find instant gratification.</p>
        <p>Even Reese admitted that the Giants, holding the 20th pick, could not expect to fill a specific hole in the starting lineup. But it is not keeping him from a thorough search. He scheduled about 25 visits from potential draft picks, double the usual number for the Giants and close to the league limit, 30.</p>
        <p>''You have some exceptional kids that you throw in the fire and they play right away, but most of the time that is not how it goes,'' Reese said. ''You develop players from the draft.''</p>
        <p>He spoke at what was billed as a predraft news conference, but even a rookie general manager knows there is no advantage in revealing a hint of draft-day intentions. It quickly became obvious that Reese, part of the Giants' personnel department since 1994, learned how to handle these annual discussions from his predecessors, George Young and Ernie Accorsi.</p>
        <p>''George Young used to say, 'Stonewall,' '' Reese said after a 28-minute question-and-answer session, in which the questions were pointed and the answers vague. ''Giants business is Giants business.''</p>
        <p>He was asked which positions he wanted to address through the draft.</p>
        <p>''I can't share that,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He was asked which positions have the deepest talent in the draft class.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to talk about that,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Reese's cordial unwillingness to address the immediate future spun the talk to the free-agency period.</p>
        <p>The Giants were 8-8 last season and lost in a wild-card playoff game to Philadelphia. Running back Tiki Barber retired. The Giants waived several starters, including left tackle Luke Petitgout and linebackers LaVar Arrington and Carlos Emmons. They allowed place-kicker Jay Feely to sign with Miami. Those decisions, which added roster hot spots, were based partly on financial considerations.</p>
        <p>With money in hand to find replacements, the Giants pursued several free agents, including running back Dominic Rhodes and tackle Leonard Davis. But Rhodes signed with Oakland and Davis with Dallas. Several other players signed elsewhere for more money than the Giants wanted to spend.</p>
        <p>''We did what we could in free agency,'' Reese said. ''We went after some guys in free agency and some things just didn't work out. The market was out of control to a degree, and we try to be smart with our money, and some situations just didn't work out for us.''</p>
        <p>It is obvious that the Reese-led Giants will not become one of the league's free-spending teams, like Dallas or Washington, which seem to draw attention each spring with splashy free-agent acquisitions that do not always work out.</p>
        <p>The N.F.L.'s salary cap has risen substantially in the past two years, to $109 million from $85.5 million, largely because of last year's changes in the collective bargaining agreement. Several teams, including New England, went on buying sprees this spring.</p>
        <p>''Guys have more money to spend, so they give it away,'' Reese said, his tone suggesting disapproval.</p>
        <p>''The money was out of control. I think there were some guys who some people would consider marginal players got paid astronomical amounts. We didn't feel like we were going to do that. We didn't feel like it was smart for us to do that.''</p>
        <p>Reese did not classify his team's off-season moves as disappointing. The Giants traded for running back Reuben Droughns and signed linebacker Kawika Mitchell, and both should vie for starting spots. They nearly traded for Denver linebacker Al Wilson, but he failed the Giants' physical exam.</p>
        <p>It all adds a bit more intrigue, if not immediacy, to next weekend's draft. The Giants might not expect to find starters in the college talent pool, but they might need to.</p>
        <p>''If that doesn't happen,'' Reese said, ''obviously we have some players on the team that are going to have to play right now, are going to have to start and play.''</p>
        <p>And many of the hotspots that Reese inherited in the chilly days of January will smolder, at least through the heat of this summer's training camp.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
