<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ex-Chief At Qwest Found Guilty</title>
    <meta content="20qwest" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/technology/20qwest.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841650"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Chronology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Qwest Communications International Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Nacchio, Joseph P</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE3D61F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1066" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ex-Chief At Qwest Found Guilty</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ex-Chief at Qwest Found Guilty of Insider Trading</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN FROSCH</byline>
      <dateline>DENVER, April 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Joseph P. Nacchio, the former chief executive who transformed Qwest Communications International into a major telecommunications rival, was convicted Thursday of insider trading.</p>
        <p>A jury in Federal District Court deliberated six days before finding Mr. Nacchio guilty on 19 of 42 counts of insider trading. He was found not guilty of 23 counts of insider trading. The eight men and four women on the jury listened as witnesses testified during the 15-day trial that Mr. Nacchio had exaggerated financial forecasts while concealing Qwest's growing troubles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The jury convicted Joseph P. Nacchio on 19 of 42 insider trading counts related to his sale of Qwest stock in 2001.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Joseph P. Nacchio, the former chief executive who transformed Qwest Communications International into a major telecommunications rival, was convicted Thursday of insider trading.</p>
        <p>A jury in Federal District Court deliberated six days before finding Mr. Nacchio guilty on 19 of 42 counts of insider trading. He was found not guilty of 23 counts of insider trading. The eight men and four women on the jury listened as witnesses testified during the 15-day trial that Mr. Nacchio had exaggerated financial forecasts while concealing Qwest's growing troubles.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nacchio, 57, who was released on $2 million bond, offered a slight smile as he left the courtroom. He declined to comment as he locked arms with his wife and son and walked away. He faces up to 10 years in prison and up to $1 million per count, as well as forfeiture of assets.</p>
        <p>The judge, Edward W. Nottingham, set sentencing for July 27.</p>
        <p>Earlier, before a packed courtroom, Judge Nottingham methodically read each count. ''Not guilty,'' he said on Count 1, then repeated the phrase 22 times. Mr. Nacchio's son Michael began sobbing, piercing an otherwise hushed courtroom. The defendant and his lawyers stared straight ahead; prosecutors sat stoic.</p>
        <p>On Count 24, the words and mood changed. ''Guilty,'' the judge said, saying it again 18 times. The younger Mr. Nacchio turned somber. A defense lawyer glanced back at the Nacchio family and shook his head.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors said that counts 24 through 42 -- the ones Mr. Nacchio was convicted of -- were the most important because they represented $52 million worth of stock sales he made after a trading window opened in 2001.</p>
        <p>After the trial, Mr. Nacchio's lawyer, Herbert J. Stern, said that he would appeal.</p>
        <p>The prosecution team stood outside the courthouse amid a thicket of reporters and cameras.</p>
        <p>''Convicted felon Joe Nacchio has a very nice ring to it,'' the United States attorney for Colorado, Troy A. Eid, said. ''I couldn't be happier that after five and half years, justice has finally been served.''</p>
        <p>An assistant United States attorney, Cliff Stricklin, who led the prosecution, said the jury's verdict proved that ''insider trading is not a victimless crime.''</p>
        <p>A fellow federal prosecutor, Colleen Conry, said the verdict would ring out from Denver to Wall Street.</p>
        <p>At a later hearing now that the trial has ended, the judge will rule on a prosecution request that Mr. Nacchio forfeit his assets.</p>
        <p>A former financial adviser to Mr. Nacchio testified at the trial that the executive's net worth was $536 million at the time of the stock sales in 2001 -- testimony that defense lawyers had tried to have stricken as irrelevant and prejudicial.</p>
        <p>The charges against Mr. Nacchio related to his sale of more than $100 million worth of Qwest stock in 2001. The case emerged from a federal investigation into accounting practices at Qwest, based in Denver, a telephone service provider in 14 states, mostly in the West.</p>
        <p>During the trial, which began in March, federal prosecutors sought to portray Mr. Nacchio as a man motivated by greed who knowingly deceived analysts by concealing the company's mounting money problems, while simultaneously unloading his own stock options.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nacchio's defense team was led by Mr. Stern, a prominent lawyer who, as a young Manhattan prosecutor, helped investigate the murder of Malcolm X and who was praised for cracking down on political corruption as a federal prosecutor in New Jersey in the 1970s.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stern contended that Mr. Nacchio was a passionately optimistic executive who may have misjudged Qwest's financial future but who believed deeply in his upbeat prognostications. Moreover, Mr. Stern asserted that Mr. Nacchio had needed to sell stock because the options were scheduled to expire.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Nacchio, prosecutors said, set aggressive financial targets that were wildly out of step with the warnings he received from fellow executives about Qwest's failure to increase its recurring revenue.</p>
        <p>Several former Qwest executives, including Lee Wolfe, a former director of investor relations, testified about a surge of concern over how the company was going to meet its projections and over Qwest's lopsided reliance on one-time transactions.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, prosecutors said, Mr. Nacchio continually affirmed a bright financial forecast to analysts, even as the chorus of admonitions from other Qwest executives grew. Finally, in 2001, when he realized Qwest was facing a significant shortfall, prosecutors said, Mr. Nacchio began unloading his stock options, while still publicly proclaiming the company's good fortunes. Mr. Nacchio even backdated the sale of the stock to make it appear unrelated to Qwest's downturn, prosecutors contended.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stern argued that Mr. Nacchio had derived his projections from a report compiled by a consulting firm hired to assess the merger of Qwest and US West in 1999. There was no way Mr. Nacchio could have foreseen a recession in the market, Mr. Stern said.</p>
        <p>The defense called three witnesses, one of them Philip F. Anschutz, Qwest's founder. Mr. Anschutz testified that Mr. Nacchio had come to him despondent over the attempted suicide of one of his sons and wanted to resign, an indication of the enormous pressure Mr. Nacchio was under at the time of the stock sales, the defense said.</p>
        <p>Under Judge Nottingham, who was considered a stickler for punctuality, the trial moved more swiftly than expected. As the proceedings drew to a close, there was speculation as to whether Mr. Nacchio would take the stand to testify about secret government contracts that Qwest was supposedly in line to win.</p>
        <p>Before the trial, the defense indicated that Mr. Nacchio alone knew about the potentially lucrative contracts, which would have bolstered Qwest's revenues.</p>
        <p>But the defense never called Mr. Nacchio; putting him on the stand could have proved risky because he would have faced a relentless cross-examination, legal experts said. As a result, the government contracts were barely mentioned.</p>
        <p>The federal charges capped a sharp turn of fortune for Mr. Nacchio, the son of a New York longshoreman turned bartender, once heralded for his hard-charging leadership as an executive for AT&amp;T.</p>
        <p>Hired to lead Qwest in 1997, Mr. Nacchio oversaw the company during a period of revenue growth and acquisitions.</p>
        <p>But by 2001, Qwest's stock value had started to sink, and Qwest's board forced Mr. Nacchio to resign in June 2002. During that period, the federal government was investigating possible accounting fraud at the company. He was indicted by a federal grand jury on Dec. 20, 2005.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
