<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Horse Is a Horse, Except Barbaro</title>
    <meta content="20sandomir" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/sports/othersports/20sandomir.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841642"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TV SPORTS: HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Barbaro (Race Horse)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Broadcasting Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE4D61F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="836" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Horse Is a Horse, Except Barbaro</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Horse Is a Horse, Except Barbaro</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Kentucky Derby will be run in 15 days, and while horses like Curlin, Nobiz Like Shobiz, Circular Quay and Scat Daddy will grow more familiar by post time, news media coverage will be haunted, if not dominated, by Barbaro.</p>
        <p>''Barbaro's memory hovers above horse racing in the near term,'' said David Michaels, who will direct NBC's Derby coverage. ''But he becomes a little more distant history when the winning horse crosses the finish line.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>During the Kentucky Derby on May 5, NBC will have an hour to balance Barbaro coverage with introducing the field that will produce his successor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Kentucky Derby will be run in 15 days, and while horses like Curlin, Nobiz Like Shobiz, Circular Quay and Scat Daddy will grow more familiar by post time, news media coverage will be haunted, if not dominated, by Barbaro.</p>
        <p>''Barbaro's memory hovers above horse racing in the near term,'' said David Michaels, who will direct NBC's Derby coverage. ''But he becomes a little more distant history when the winning horse crosses the finish line.''</p>
        <p>NBC will have an hour on May 5 to balance Barbaro coverage with introducing the field that will produce his successor. NBC could have an added Barbaro thread if Chelokee -- trained, as Barbaro was, by Michael Matz -- is entered. ''We'd tie them both together,'' Michaels said by telephone.</p>
        <p>That a horse euthanized in January could be a major force in Louisville is testament to Barbaro's story: His six-and-a-half-length Derby victory last May, then his misstep early in the Preakness Stakes that shattered his right hind leg and the eight months of care that ultimately could not save his life. His operations and updates on his ailments, including laminitis in another hoof, became part of the regular news cycle; so did reports on what he was eating and when he left his patient stall to eat grass outside the New Bolton Center in Kennett Square, Pa.</p>
        <p>The interest in Barbaro is enough to generate one documentary about him on NBC on April 29 at 5 p.m., six days before the Derby, and a second documentary on HBO on June 6 at 10 p.m., in advance of the Belmont Stakes.</p>
        <p>''I don't care how many articles you've read about Barbaro,'' Ross Greenburg, the president of HBO Sports, said by telephone. ''The story can't be told as effectively as it can in a documentary. There's a mountain of footage and a depth of storytelling that no one's read about, and because it's a documentary, you can grab the emotion and develop the story around it.''</p>
        <p>He said that the questions his producer, Margaret Grossi, will try to answer, are: Why this horse? Why did Barbaro want to fight for his life?</p>
        <p>Emotion is at the heart of the NBC documentary, ''Barbaro: A Nation's Horse,'' in which tears seem ready to fall on the cheeks of most of those interviewed. The film follows a course from last year's Derby to the veterinary surgeon Dean Richardson's announcement of Barbaro's death, with detours to his previous races, his effect on the people around him, Matz's survival in a plane crash years before, and children reading their letters of love and concern to Barbaro. A brass section plays heraldic music for his victories; strings accompany his injury and death.</p>
        <p>It is nearly impossible to tell Barbaro's story without a degree of anthropomorphizing about his courage and intelligence: how he knew to stand still after his injury, temporarily saving his life; how he withstood one operation after another with equanimity; and how he adapted from life as a racehorse to being the world's most famous equine hospital patient.</p>
        <p>''No question you need trained professionals like Richardson and Matz to explain why this horse is different from other horses they've been involved with and who have had serious injuries,'' Greenburg said. ''Some animals are smarter than others and some just have a different quality.''</p>
        <p>Six months ago, when Greenburg decided that HBO would tell Barbaro's story, he believed his network would be the only one doing a documentary. But to be careful, he signed Barbaro's owners, Gretchen and Roy Jackson, to an exclusive deal, including a payment to a laminitis research fund, that would have permitted them to speak to NBC only for segments on its Derby and Preakness coverage. Otherwise, they were bound to HBO.</p>
        <p>But some time after HBO's work began -- and while Barbaro was still living -- Greenburg heard that NBC was planning its own documentary.</p>
        <p>''I'd heard after I came from vacation in March that Ross's people had been asking for footage of the Derby and Preakness, but that the issue was the deal that HBO negotiated with the Jacksons,'' said Dick Ebersol, the chairman of NBC Sports. He told Greenburg last month that unless he released the Jacksons to speak freely, HBO would not get the footage.</p>
        <p>Each side soon after got what it wanted.</p>
        <p>THE N.H.L.'S YOUTUBE PRESENCE -- The N.H.L., without big TV ratings, has reached out this season to fans on a video channel on YouTube on the Internet that offers clips and promotions, but not a single brawl; the closest are compilations of hard hits.</p>
        <p>A December plays-of-the-week collection has been downloaded the most (327,011) of all 1,041 videos. About 10.5 million officially sanctioned N.H.L. videos have been streamed.</p>
        <p>But the most downloaded hockey video on YouTube that I could find -- provided by a fan, not the league -- is of a sprawling, multiple-front, near riot on the ice during an Ottawa-Philadelphia game in March 2004 that resulted in 419 penalty minutes. It has been downloaded 1.85 million times.</p>
        <p>TV SPORTS: HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
