<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chinese Growth Shows Little Restraint, Rising 11.1% in Quarter</title>
    <meta content="20yuan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/business/worldbusiness/20yuan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841575"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E6D81F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="582" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chinese Growth Shows Little Restraint, Rising 11.1% in Quarter</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Chinese Growth Shows Little Restraint, Rising 11.1% in Quarter</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BARBOZA</byline>
      <dateline>SHANGHAI, April 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>China's economy continues to accelerate at a blistering pace, growing 11.1 percent in the first quarter of this year from the first quarter of 2006, according to data from the National Bureau of Statistics released Thursday.</p>
        <p>The surge in growth is almost certain to force Beijing to step up efforts to cool the economy. Pressure is also mounting on officials to allow the value of the currency, the yuan, to appreciate more quickly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The surge in growth is almost certain to force Beijing to step up efforts to cool down the economy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>China's economy continues to accelerate at a blistering pace, growing 11.1 percent in the first quarter of this year from the first quarter of 2006, according to data from the National Bureau of Statistics released Thursday.</p>
        <p>The surge in growth is almost certain to force Beijing to step up efforts to cool the economy. Pressure is also mounting on officials to allow the value of the currency, the yuan, to appreciate more quickly.</p>
        <p>A benchmark Chinese share index -- anticipating higher interest rates and perhaps other measures aimed at restraining domestic stocks -- dropped 4.5 percent Thursday, ending a robust rally that had driven prices to record highs in recent days.</p>
        <p>Despite the losses, the Shanghai Stock Exchange composite index closed at 3,449.02, up more than 200 percent in the last 16 months.</p>
        <p>Roughly a dozen interest rate increases and other moves to tighten money and lending over the last three years have failed to tame growth in China, the world's fastest-growing major economy.</p>
        <p>Fueled by soaring exports and huge investments in infrastructure, factories and energy supplies, China could soon overtake Germany to become the world's third-largest economy, behind those of the United States and Japan.</p>
        <p>While most economists called the quarterly growth figures surprisingly strong, they said the data was distorted somewhat by a huge injection of government money into the economy, which encouraged lending, as well as by exporters' seeking to avoid foreign tariffs that may be imposed later in the year.</p>
        <p>''This is the first-quarter blowout,'' says Jonathan Anderson, chief Asia economist at UBS. ''But we don't expect this to continue. There were a lot of wacky things happening in the first quarter.''</p>
        <p>The burst of growth, one of the largest in a decade, came on the heels of four consecutive years of double-digit economic growth, including an increase last year of 10.7 percent, the fastest annual growth in a decade.</p>
        <p>The statistics bureau said that retail sales rose 15 percent, industrial production was up 18 percent and exports jumped 28 percent.</p>
        <p>The report also noted a 2.7 percent rise in consumer prices, partly because of rising food costs. But core inflation remained low, the government said.</p>
        <p>One challenge is to keep the economy humming ahead of 2008, when Beijing will play host to the Summer Olympics.</p>
        <p>Economists say China's economy remains largely healthy, though they expect another interest rate increase soon in an effort to reduce excessive lending.</p>
        <p>Mr. Anderson at UBS said officials could intervene in the equity markets to end the steep rally there that could prove to be a threat to the economy.</p>
        <p>Shen Minggao, an economist at Citigroup, said in a report issued late Thursday that officials may also step up efforts to allow the currency to appreciate more quickly, hoping to dry up excess liquidity.</p>
        <p>While some economists say that China could take stronger measures to cool things off, they expect tightening to be gradual.</p>
        <p>Chinese officials have long asserted that the pace of currency revaluation must be measured and that they will not be pressed into moving hastily.</p>
        <p>Last week, the United States filed two complaints with the World Trade Organization, maintaining that China was engaged in widespread abuse of copyrights and trademarks.</p>
        <p>With Washington stepping up efforts to win trade concessions, some economists expect China to concede some ground. Hong Liang of Goldman Sachs has forecast that the Chinese currency will appreciate about 9 percent in value in the next year. She also expects further policy tightening to curb lending.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
