<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Long Hot Summer And the More Perfect Union</title>
    <meta content="20book" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/books/20book.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841547"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Constitutions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Constitutions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Franklin, Benjamin</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">The Summer of 1787 (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E6DA1F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1173" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Long Hot Summer And the More Perfect Union</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Long Hot Summer and the More Perfect Union</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kakutani, Michiko</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Summer of 1787  The Men Who Invented the Constitution  By David O. Stewart  Illustrated. 349 pages. Simon &amp; Schuster. $27.</p>
        <p>As delegates to the Constitutional Convention of 1787 put their signatures to the document that would become the charter of the infant nation, Benjamin Franklin pointed to the carving of a sun on the back of George Washington's chair and observed that he had often looked at the carving ''without being able to tell whether it was rising or setting.'' With months of often contentious debate behind them and the Constitution finally assented to by the delegates, however, Franklin pronounced his satisfaction, declaring that he now had ''the happiness to know that it is a rising and not a setting sun.'' After all, the delegates had succeeded, with just a few thousand words, in inventing a new form of government that would prove stable enough and flexible enough to sustain the nation -- and its liberties -- through more than two centuries of social and political change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his book about the framers of the Constitution, Mr. Stewart has done a nimble job of retelling a familiar story.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Summer of 1787  The Men Who Invented the Constitution  By David O. Stewart  Illustrated. 349 pages. Simon &amp; Schuster. $27.</p>
        <p>As delegates to the Constitutional Convention of 1787 put their signatures to the document that would become the charter of the infant nation, Benjamin Franklin pointed to the carving of a sun on the back of George Washington's chair and observed that he had often looked at the carving ''without being able to tell whether it was rising or setting.'' With months of often contentious debate behind them and the Constitution finally assented to by the delegates, however, Franklin pronounced his satisfaction, declaring that he now had ''the happiness to know that it is a rising and not a setting sun.'' After all, the delegates had succeeded, with just a few thousand words, in inventing a new form of government that would prove stable enough and flexible enough to sustain the nation -- and its liberties -- through more than two centuries of social and political change.</p>
        <p>The story of how the Constitution was written, of course, has been told many times before: most notably in Catherine Drinker Bowen's classic work ''Miracle at Philadelphia,'' as well as in books like Richard B. Morris's ''Witnesses at the Creation,'' Clinton Rossiter's ''1787: the Grand Convention,'' and ''Decision in Philadelphia'' by Christopher Collier and James Lincoln Collier.</p>
        <p>The latest book about the framers, ''The Summer of 1787,'' does not shed a lot of new light on that momentous process. David O. Stewart, a lawyer specializing in constitutional law cases, has written a narrative that is far more descriptive than analytic. One of the few opinions he offers is that the delegates' work on defining the office of the president was hasty and rushed and does ''not compare well to their detailed outline for Congress.''</p>
        <p>And given the many constitutional issues being debated today (concerning the war powers of Congress and the president, and the Bush administration's efforts to amp up the prerogatives of the executive branch) the reader often wishes that the author had used his expertise to illuminate the origin and significance of key passages in the Constitution, the way, say, that Yale law professor Akhil Reed Amar did in his 2005 book ''America's Constitution: A Biography.''</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Stewart has done a nimble job of retelling a familiar story, showing how the Constitution evolved during those hot summer months in Philadelphia, while conjuring the atmosphere of the convention and creating vivid portraits of its chief delegates: from James Madison (who, interestingly, is depicted as often coming out ''on the short end of contests at the Convention'') to lesser known but highly influential figures like James Wilson and the aristocratic Gouverneur Morris of Pennsylvania and the forceful John Rutledge of South Carolina.</p>
        <p>The importance of replacing the Articles of Confederation (which had tied the 13 original states together under a loose umbrella that gave individual states as much independence and sovereignty as possible) had become increasingly clear to Madison and Washington, particularly in the wake of Shays's Rebellion, an uprising over taxes that pitted neighbors against neighbors. ''I am mortified beyond expression,'' Washington wrote in October 1786, ''when I view the clouds that have spread over the brightest morn that ever dawned upon any country.'' Without ''some alteration in our political creed,'' he declared, ''the superstructure we have been seven years raising at the expense of so much blood and treasure, must fall. We are fast verging to anarchy and confusion!''</p>
        <p>At that point in the fledgling nation's history, states issued their own paper money, pursued their own foreign policies and battled one another over trade and commerce; nine states even claimed to have their own navies. Meanwhile the national government was unable to impose taxes directly; in Mr. Stewart's words, ''it could only make 'requisitions' for funds from the 13 states,'' requisitions that ''met with very mixed results.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stewart reviews, sometimes blow by blow, the debates that erupted at the convention over legislative representation, which pitted the small states (who stood behind the principle of one state one vote) against the large states (who favored the principle of proportional representation). And he reviews the fateful accommodations reached between Northern and Southern interests that would wind up giving Southern politicians the power to protect the slave system for many decades to come.</p>
        <p>One thing that seems remarkable in retrospect is how dramatically the Constitution evolved, as various proposals, some of them highly bizarre, were left on the cutting-room floor. Though Madison was prescient about the dangers of a North-South split in the nation, he actually proposed at one point defining the two houses of Congress in terms of slavery: one would have represented Southern interests; the other, Northern ones. As for the so-called Virginia Plan, put forward near the beginning of the conference, it proposed that the people elect the ''first branch'' of the legislature (the House of Representatives), which would then choose the ''second branch'' (the future Senate), and together, the two houses would select the president and appoint all judges.</p>
        <p>Many momentous decisions, Mr. Stewart suggests, were the result of happenstance and individual initiative. Rutledge's committee, which wrote the first draft of the Constitution, the author says, went well beyond the 19 resolutions adopted by the convention, ''to borrow provisions from the despised Articles of Confederation, from state constitutions'' and from at least one delegate's almost forgotten plan.</p>
        <p>In addition the committee members ''added provisions that the Convention never discussed,'' he says. ''They changed critical agreements that the delegates had already approved. Spurred by Rutledge, they reconceived the powers of the national government, redefined the powers of the states and made fresh concessions on that most explosive issue, slavery. It is not too much to say that Rutledge and his committee hijacked the Constitution. Then they remade it.''</p>
        <p>Morris, who was charged with preparing the final draft, would write a new preamble to the Constitution, changing the opening from ''We the people of the States of New Hampshire, Massachusetts'' and so on, to ''We the People of the United States.'' The change, which proclaimed a new government based on the consent of the people, Mr. Stewart argues, stemmed from a very practical reason: ''Listing the states would have been presumptuous, even foolish, since ratification by every state was no foregone conclusion'' at that time.</p>
        <p>The Constitution that came out of Philadelphia was an imperfect charter; it incorporated slavery and neglected to include a bill of rights. (The 10 amendments known as the Bill of Rights would be ratified in 1791.) But for all its faults it would prove to be a remarkably durable and ingenious document, balancing the power of the states and the national government, while dividing federal power into three separate branches -- legislative, executive and judicial -- that would act as checks upon one another.</p>
        <p>Written by delegates described alternately as ''demigods'' and ''coxcombs,'' the Constitution was, as Mr. Stewart notes at the end of ''The Summer of 1787,'' the ''child of lofty idealism and rough political bargains.''</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
