<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Anglophilic Yankee Aristocrat And His Finds Across the Pond</title>
    <meta content="20mell" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/arts/design/20mell.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841512"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Yale Center for British Art</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Mellon, Paul</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E4DB1F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1142" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Anglophilic Yankee Aristocrat And His Finds Across the Pond</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Anglophilic Yankee Aristocrat and His Finds Across the Pond</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRACE GLUECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glueck, Grace</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He described himself as a ''galloping Anglophile,'' hooked on horse breeding, racing, hunting and other pastimes of the English gentry. Yet Paul Mellon (1907-99), the Pittsburgh-born philanthropist and son of the banker and industrialist Andrew Mellon, didn't discover the sport of collecting British art until he was well into middle age.</p>
        <p>But then he became one of the great players in the field, snapping up individual works as well as whole collections. A Yale graduate, he founded the Yale Center for British Art in 1966 and financed a building to house it, designed by Louis Kahn, that opened in 1977. The center now holds more than 2,000 paintings and sculptures; 50,000 drawings and prints, including important maps; and 35,000 rare books, the largest gathering of such art outside Britain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A comprehensive show of 250 objects at the Yale center featuring works by George Stubbs, William Blake and Thomas Rowlands celebrates the centennial of its founder’s birth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He described himself as a ''galloping Anglophile,'' hooked on horse breeding, racing, hunting and other pastimes of the English gentry. Yet Paul Mellon (1907-99), the Pittsburgh-born philanthropist and son of the banker and industrialist Andrew Mellon, didn't discover the sport of collecting British art until he was well into middle age.</p>
        <p>But then he became one of the great players in the field, snapping up individual works as well as whole collections. A Yale graduate, he founded the Yale Center for British Art in 1966 and financed a building to house it, designed by Louis Kahn, that opened in 1977. The center now holds more than 2,000 paintings and sculptures; 50,000 drawings and prints, including important maps; and 35,000 rare books, the largest gathering of such art outside Britain.</p>
        <p>This year is not only the 30th anniversary of the center's opening, but also the centennial of its founder's birth, and celebrations are in order. For one, a splendid commemoration has been organized, ''Paul Mellon's Legacy: A Passion for British Art,'' a comprehensive show of 250 objects at the Yale center, from which a selection will travel to the Royal Academy of Arts in London in October. Displayed among all three floors of the Yale center's public exhibition galleries, ''Legacy,'' organized in association with the academy, presents every aspect of Mellon's collecting activities in the field, from an iconic, light-steeped harborscape by J. M. W. Turner, ''Dort, or Dordrecht, the Dort Packet-boat From Rotterdam Becalmed'' (1818), to a manuscript map from 1587 that shows the route of Sir Francis Drake's circumnavigation of the globe a decade earlier.</p>
        <p>George Stubbs, William Blake, John Constable and Thomas Rowlandson, all Mellon favorites, are here in depth, but the galleries are also full of wonderful single surprises. One is ''A Young Daughter of the Picts,'' a smallish watercolor by Jacques Le Moyne de Morgues, dated around 1585, that shows an idealized blonde from an indigenous tribe, whose frizzy hair ripples to her waist. Her nude body is covered with floral and botanical tattoos, adornments not unknown in hip circles today.</p>
        <p>Another little-known dazzler, ''John Gubbins Newton and His Sister, Mary Newton'' (about 1833), is a large canvas by one Robert Burnard. It depicts a young boy in scarlet hunting garb on a pony, as his older sibling stands beside him in a blue dress, proffering a riding crop. A stalwart dog completes the picture. Although highly accomplished, the painting comes across with almost primitive clarity and simplicity, bearing not a trace of the pomposity often exuding from upper-class family portraits.</p>
        <p>And there is the humorous strip by Isaac Robert Cruikshank, a hand-colored aquatint titled ''Going to a Fight'' (1819), that scrolls out from a small spool to show a group of citizens rushing by horse, bicycle and foot toward an uproar that seems to involve a stubborn horse and the occupants of the tipped cart it has been pulling.</p>
        <p>When Mellon began collecting British art around 1960, it was in the doldrums, by and large snubbed by cognoscenti even in England, in favor of French and other European schools. Availability was high, and prices were low. With taste, an appetite for the best and, of course, money, he helped bring it back to the world's attention, giving it the kind of exposure that the art of other European countries had enjoyed.</p>
        <p>Earlier Mellon, with his wife, Bunny, had gone in heavily for French Impressionism and Post-Impressionism. (Many of those holdings are now in the National Gallery of Art in Washington, which was founded by his father.) But his mother was English, and he had spent much time in Britain as a child and later as a student at Cambridge. There, he had acquired ''a fondness for the English landscape and for the ever-changing English light,'' he wrote in his coyly titled but amusingly upfront autobiography, ''Reflections in a Silver Spoon'' (Morrow, 1992).</p>
        <p>''I grew to love English country life and country sports,'' he wrote. ''I became a lifelong devotee of foxhunting and racing.'' And yes, as far back as 1936 he had bought a horse painting by Stubbs, on view here, that remained his favorite British canvas, the appealing ''Pumpkin With a Stable-Lad'' (1774). He went on to acquire more than 30 Stubbs works, many of which are in this show.</p>
        <p>At a 1959 lunch with Basil Taylor, an art historian at the Royal College of Art in London, Mr. Taylor, who shared an interest in Stubbs's paintings, brought Mellon to the recognition ''that British art was needlessly neglected and undervalued, and that somebody ought to do something about it,'' Mellon wrote. ''By the time we were drinking our coffee, it had been more or less agreed that I was going to collect British art and that Basil would be my adviser.''</p>
        <p>Mellon stepped up his collecting pace, buying, one day in the mid-1960s, 22 watercolors and 11 paintings from a single London dealer, Agnew's. In 1972 he secured from the same dealer the pensive Joshua Reynolds portrait ''Mrs. Abington as Miss Prue in William Congreve's 'Love for Love' '' (1771), one of the stars of the current exhibition. With advice from Mr. Taylor and other connoisseurs, his holdings grew exponentially.</p>
        <p>Even after the main part of his collection was handed over to the Yale center, he went on acquiring. ''As anyone who has started to collect anything knows, it is impossible to stop,'' he wrote. (The contemporary British art he liked was not very venturesome, running to Barbara Hepworth, Ben Nicholson and John Skeaping.)</p>
        <p>What makes this show so invigorating is its uncommon variety of choice selections: the beautifully atmospheric cloud paintings of Constable; the landscapes that Gainsborough liked to do, so different in feeling from his society portraits; the small, glowingly mysterious worlds created by Samuel Palmer; Blake at his very best, in works from ''Jerusalem: The Emanation of the Giant Albion'' (1804-20).</p>
        <p>And then there are the remarkable drawings, created between 1795 and 1806, by Stubbs, comparing the anatomies of the human, the fowl and the tiger in an effort to establish certain basic similarities; the late, glorious paintings of Turner with their subjects dissolved in light; Rowlandson's biting caricatures, like ''A Worn-Out Debauchee'' (about 1790-95).</p>
        <p>In a talk at the Virginia Museum of Fine Arts in 1963, Mellon said his collecting activities were ''part of a logical, deliberate attempt to say to ourselves and to the public, this is English art, not just the Duchess of Devonshire or the Age of Innocence; let's take it seriously, let's re-evaluate it, let's look at it, let's enjoy it.'' The show at the Yale center is a fine chance to do all those things.</p>
        <p>''Paul Mellon's Legacy: A Passion for British Art'' continues through July 29 at the Yale Center for British Art, 1080 Chapel Street, New Haven; (203) 432-2800, www.ycba.yale.edu.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
