<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Students Knew Killer's Demons By His Writings</title>
    <meta content="20english" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/us/20english.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070421T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841643"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MASSACRE IN VIRGINIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cho Seung-Hui</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E3D61F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1269" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Students Knew Killer's Demons By His Writings</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Anger of Killer Was on Exhibit in His Writings</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARC SANTORA and CHRISTINE HAUSER; Reporting was contributed by Sarah Abruzzese, John M. Broder, Shaila Dewan, Cate Doty, Bob Driehaus, Brenda Goodman, Choe Sang-Hun, Suevon Lee, Carolyn Marshall, Lori Moore, Haeyoun Park, William K. Rashbaum, Alicia C. Shepard and Archie Tse.</byline>
      <dateline>BLACKSBURG, Va., April 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>More than anyone else on the Virginia Tech campus, it was the professors and students in the English department who knew of the mental turmoil of Cho Seung-Hui.</p>
        <p>Where the Virginia Tech police only heard scattered reports of his harassing behavior, and mental health professionals knew of his suicidal tendencies, it was the English department -- where he was a major -- that read his writings and saw the images of persecution, revenge and anger that they revealed, many months before he erupted into violence on Monday and killed 32 people, as well as himself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Professors and students in the English department at Virginia Tech knew of the mental turmoil of Cho Seung-Hui through his writings and images.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>More than anyone else on the Virginia Tech campus, it was the professors and students in the English department who knew of the mental turmoil of Cho Seung-Hui.</p>
        <p>Where the Virginia Tech police only heard scattered reports of his harassing behavior, and mental health professionals knew of his suicidal tendencies, it was the English department -- where he was a major -- that read his writings and saw the images of persecution, revenge and anger that they revealed, many months before he erupted into violence on Monday and killed 32 people, as well as himself.</p>
        <p>And those English professors and students appear to have worked harder than anyone to intervene in his life. Trying to balance the freedom needed to be creative against the warning signs of psychosis, as many as eight of his teachers in the last 18 months had formed what one called a ''task force'' to discuss how to handle him, gathering twice on the subject and frequently communicating among themselves.</p>
        <p>On at least two separate occasions they reached out to university officials, telling them as recently as this September that Mr. Cho was trouble. They made little headway, however, and no action was taken by school administrators in response to their concerns.</p>
        <p>The students also made their fears known, some even refusing to attend class as long Mr. Cho was there. Others tried to reach out to him.</p>
        <p>Ross Alameddine sat a few feet from Mr. Cho for months in a class examining contemporary horror films and literature. Both students were required to keep what were known as ''fear journals,'' where they chronicled both their reaction to the material covered in class and their own fears.</p>
        <p>Mr. Alameddine, according to classmates, made an effort to speak to Mr. Cho on several occasions, trying to draw him out of his closed world and his refusal to interact with other students.</p>
        <p>On Monday, Mr. Cho shot and killed Mr. Alameddine.</p>
        <p>There is no evidence to suggest that Mr. Cho targeted his classmate, but it is the first time one of the victims has been connected to Mr. Cho before the shootings.</p>
        <p>The class they took together was new, offered for the first time last fall. The students studied movies like ''Friday the 13th'' and read Stephen King, H. P. Lovecraft and Patricia Cornwall novels. ''We had a whole discussion on serial killers,'' said one student, who asked that she not be named because she wanted to avoid a crush of attention from the news media.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cho never spoke during the discussion, she said, but he took notes.</p>
        <p>The student and Mr. Cho were in another class as well, a small class on playwriting, during which she grew fascinated by him.</p>
        <p>''In all honesty, I took a huge interest in him last semester,'' she said. ''I never heard him speak a word, and I was so curious about him. I actually tried to follow him after class one day, but he got on a bike and I couldn't keep up. He had a red bicycle.''</p>
        <p>In interviews with six members of the English faculty who had Mr. Cho in a class or had been in close contact with him, they described how as early as September 2005 and as recently as September 2006, they found themselves struggling to define the line between a legitimate work of self-expression and one of violent or sick imagery that needed to be restrained.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes, in creative writing, people reveal things and you never know if it's creative or if they're describing things, if they're imagining things or just how real it might be,'' said Prof. Carolyn Rude, chairwoman of the English Department. ''But we're all alert to not ignore things like this.''</p>
        <p>Lisa Norris, an English professor, said that, outside of an explicit threat that was rooted in reality, it would be impossible to have some kind of standard by which to judge whether a student's work was so alarming as to warrant intervention.</p>
        <p>''If the student seems abnormal in his behavior or affect and is writing about violence, then there could be something to worry about -- particularly if the resolution of the story includes suicide or murder for major characters or otherwise ends in despair,'' she said. ''It is not necessarily the work alone that raises concern, but the work plus the student's affect and behavior.''</p>
        <p>In Mr. Cho's case, she was alarmed before he had written a word.</p>
        <p>When he signed up for the 10-person workshop she taught this year, Professor Norris was worried that he simply would not communicate, and in September she reached out to one of her superiors, Mary Ann Lewis, the associate dean at the College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences. She said Ms. Lewis was helpful but had no information about prior problems, including his hospitalization at a mental health facility in 2005. Ms. Lewis said she had no comment on the conversation.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Cho's bizarre behavior was evident to students, faculty and police going back to 2005.</p>
        <p>''Nobody took too much notice of him except for that's the kinda weird quiet kid who never talks,'' said Steven Davis, 23, a senior who was in a drama class with him. ''Until we read his work. And then it was like whoa, something is off.''</p>
        <p>One woman, an English major who was in a contemporary British fiction class with Mr. Cho in the fall of 2005 and who asked not to be identified, said he sent her unsolicited electronic messages after seeing her in class and then looking her up on the Facebook Web site.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cho, she said, also stalked another girl in the class, scaring her so badly that she went to the police that December.</p>
        <p>That matches the campus police account of a woman who came to them in December 2005, part of a series of events that culminated with Mr. Cho being held for psychiatric evaluation and later released.</p>
        <p>She said Mr. Cho knew things about her family that would be difficult to know without serious effort. For instance, he knew what sports her siblings played in high school.</p>
        <p>Beyond that, he simply acted strange. On the first day of class the teacher asked everyone to stand up and introduce themselves.</p>
        <p>''When it was his turn, he didn't stand up and he said his name was Question Mark,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Professor Lucinda Roy, who was the head of the English Department in the fall of 2005, chose to deal with Mr. Cho by removing him from a group class and tutoring him. She also passed along his writing, which she described as ''angry,'' to both the Virgnia Tech police and the university counseling service.</p>
        <p>Prof. Edward Falco, who last semester had him in a playwrighting class, did not make the other students read or critique two of Mr. Cho's plays that contained violent images and profane language. But he alerted other faculty members, and learned that they, too, had been concerned.</p>
        <p>After the shooting Monday, Professor Falco's students began sending him messages about how they felt guilty for not doing or saying something earlier. Professor Falco responded in an e-mail message, hoping to help put their minds at ease.</p>
        <p>''There was violence in Cho's writing -- but there is a huge difference between writing about violence and behaving violently,'' he wrote. ''We could not have known what he would do.''</p>
        <p>MASSACRE IN VIRGINIA</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 21, 2007, Saturday  A front-page article yesterday about the angry writings of Seung-Hui Cho, who went on a shooting rampage at Virginia Polytechnic Institute, misspelled the surname of a novelist whose books were among those he studied in a class on contemporary horror films and literature. She is Patricia Cornwell, not Cornwall.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 21, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>A front-page article yesterday about the angry writings of Seung-Hui Cho, who went on a shooting rampage at Virginia Polytechnic Institute, misspelled the surname of a novelist whose books were among those he studied in a class on contemporary horror films and literature. She is Patricia Cornwell, not Cornwall.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
