<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inside Art</title>
    <meta content="20voge" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/arts/design/20voge.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841509"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Inside Art"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Inside Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Gallery of Art</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Johns, Jasper</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Nevelson, Louise</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E3DC1F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1036" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inside Art</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Special Appearance for Rembrandt’s '‘Titus’'</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Carol Vogel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Special Appearance For Rembrandt's 'Titus'</p>
        <p>The National Gallery of Art in Washington has one of the greatest collections of Rembrandts in the United States, but it is borrowing one of his seminal works. ''Portrait of a Boy in Fancy Dress'' (1655), also known as ''Titus,'' is coming to the gallery from the Norton Simon Foundation in Pasadena, Calif., from May 11 to Sept. 4. While the National Gallery regularly contributes artworks to exhibitions around the world, the Norton Simon almost never lends its holdings. This is the first of what the two institutions say will be a continuing loan program.</p>
        <p>In contrast with the Louvre's new three-year program to lend art to the High Museum of Art in Atlanta in exchange for $6.4 million to go toward renovation of the Louvre's decorative-arts galleries, no money other than basic expenses will change hands between the Norton Simon and the National Gallery, the institutions say. How the gallery plans to reciprocate is unclear, but both institutions said they would not exchange more than one work at a time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a rare move, the Norton Simon sends aRembrandt cross-country to the National Gallery of Art, to launch a continuing loan program.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Special Appearance For Rembrandt's 'Titus'</p>
        <p>The National Gallery of Art in Washington has one of the greatest collections of Rembrandts in the United States, but it is borrowing one of his seminal works. ''Portrait of a Boy in Fancy Dress'' (1655), also known as ''Titus,'' is coming to the gallery from the Norton Simon Foundation in Pasadena, Calif., from May 11 to Sept. 4. While the National Gallery regularly contributes artworks to exhibitions around the world, the Norton Simon almost never lends its holdings. This is the first of what the two institutions say will be a continuing loan program.</p>
        <p>In contrast with the Louvre's new three-year program to lend art to the High Museum of Art in Atlanta in exchange for $6.4 million to go toward renovation of the Louvre's decorative-arts galleries, no money other than basic expenses will change hands between the Norton Simon and the National Gallery, the institutions say. How the gallery plans to reciprocate is unclear, but both institutions said they would not exchange more than one work at a time.</p>
        <p>''We stopped lending in the 1980's because we wanted our art to be available to people who came to the museum,'' said Walter W. Timoshuk president of the two Norton Simon foundations and the museum that shows its collections. ''But now the board decided we'd like people on the East Coast to learn about the Norton Simon.''</p>
        <p>The painting, thought to be of the artist's son, was last on view at the National Gallery more than 40 years ago. It made a brief stop there before it found its way to California after Simon, the industrialist and collector who died in 1993, bought the Rembrandt at a Christie's auction in London in 1965. The sale was considered so monumental it made the cover of Time magazine.</p>
        <p>Not only was the price considered staggering -- $2.1 million, which at the time made it the second most expensive painting ever sold. (The most expensive was a 1653 Rembrandt, ''Aristotle Contemplating the Bust of Homer,'' which the Metropolitan Museum bought for $2.3 million.) So was the bidding war that Simon fought to get the painting. When the auctioneer announced that the winning bid had come from Marlborough Fine Arts, he sprang to his feet and announced that he hadn't stopped bidding. It turned out that he had given the auctioneer such confusing instructions that he misunderstood Simon's body language, thinking he had finished when he hadn't. So the bid was reopened, and Simon bought the portrait.</p>
        <p>Arthur K. Wheelock Jr., the National Gallery's curator, said he planned to hang the painting alongside his museum's 1659 Rembrandt self-portrait.</p>
        <p>'Figure 4' on the Block</p>
        <p>Why has Jasper Johns so often painted numerals in his work? ''They seemed to me preformed, conventional, depersonalized, factual, exterior elements,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As mundane as the numbers may seem, Mr. Johns often used them to push the boundaries of conventional painting.</p>
        <p>A prime example is ''Figure 4'' (1959), which Christie's is to auction on May 16. In a nod to the Cubist canvases of Picasso, Braque and Gris, Mr. Johns layered newsprint on the canvas in addition to oil and encaustic -- pigment suspended in melted wax through an ancient technique -- creating a collage in which the newsprint is visible to the viewer.</p>
        <p>Since ''Figure 4'' was painted, it has been owned by Nina Sundell, the daughter of Mr. Johns's longtime dealer, Leo Castelli, who died in 1999, and her husband, Michael. Mr. Castelli took them to Mr. Johns's studio, where they bought the painting soon after it was finished. The Sundells have decided to take advantage of the strong market and sell the painting next month.</p>
        <p>'' 'Four' is one of the most interesting images,'' said Laura Paulson, a contemporary-art expert and a deputy chairman of Christie's in New York. ''It allows the artist to use the figure in a more complex composition because of its natural and vertical configuration.''</p>
        <p>''Figure 4'' was painted at a time when Mr. Johns began using bolder colors after having created monochrome canvases.</p>
        <p>Most of the 21 paintings he produced in 1959 are in museums.</p>
        <p>Christie's estimates that ''Figure 4'' will sell for $14 million, a hefty sum that takes into account its rarity on the market, and several experts predict that the bidding will be particularly competitive among today's superrich new collectors. To wrest the painting from its archrival, Sotheby's, Christie's offered the Sundells a guarantee -- an undisclosed minimum sum regardless of the outcome of the sale -- that experts say is around $12 million.</p>
        <p>All White and All Nevelson</p>
        <p>''Dawn's Wedding Feast,'' an all-white room-size installation that Louise Nevelson made in 1959 for a show at the Museum of Modern Art called ''Sixteen Americans,'' is going on view at the Jewish Museum in a Nevelson retrospective from May 5 through Sept 16. It is the first survey of her work since 1980.</p>
        <p>Her first foray into producing white sculptures, the work includes wedding chapels, attendants in the form of hanging columns, and a columnar bride and groom in center of the work.</p>
        <p>Over the years, pieces of the installation were dispersed and have ended up in private collections and museums. This is the first time it will have been reassembled since a Nevelson show at the Whitney Museum of American Art 27 years ago.</p>
        <p>''It's been a tale of discovery and detective work,'' said Brooke Kamin Rapaport, an independent curator who organized the exhibition and spent years tracking down the many parts. In addition to private collections, loans have come from 12 museums, including the Museum of Modern Art, the Whitney, the Art Institute of Chicago and the Walker Art Center in Minneapolis. From the Jewish Museum, the show travels to the de Young, part of the Fine Arts Museums of San Francisco.</p>
        <p>Guggenheim's New Curator</p>
        <p>Just as Nancy Spector is putting the finishing touches on the Felix Gonzalez-Torres exhibition that will occupy the American pavilion of the Venice Biennale this summer, she has been promoted to chief curator at the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, where she has been a curator since 1989. In addition to organizing exhibitions she will oversee the museum's acquisitions.</p>
        <p>Inside Art</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
