<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gates Assures Israel on Plan to Sell Arms to Saudis</title>
    <meta content="20gates" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/world/middleeast/20gates.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841564"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arms Sales Abroad</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Saudi Arabia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cloud, David S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Medina, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gates, Robert M (Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Sales Abroad</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Israel</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Saudi Arabia</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Gates, Robert M</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE0D91F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="735" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gates Assures Israel on Plan to Sell Arms to Saudis</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Gates Assures Israel on Plan to Sell Arms to Saudis</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID S. CLOUD; Jennifer Medina contributed reporting from Jerusalem.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cloud, David S; Medina, Jennifer</byline>
      <dateline>TEL AVIV, April 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Defense Sec Robert M Gates says he has reassured Israel that planned major US arms sale to Saudi Arabia and other Persian Gulf nations would not threaten Israel's military superiority and is necessary to counter threat from Iran (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates said Thursday that he had reassured Israel that a planned major American arms sale to Saudi Arabia and other Persian Gulf countries would not threaten Israel's military superiority and was necessary to counter a threat from Iran.</p>
        <p>Speaking to reporters here after talks with Prime Minister Ehud Olmert and other top officials on his visit to the Middle East, Mr. Gates said that he had emphasized that Iran posed a greater threat to Israel than did the Arab countries that were to receive the sophisticated weaponry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates said the sale would not threaten Israel’s military superiority and was necessary to counter a threat from Iran.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates said Thursday that he had reassured Israel that a planned major American arms sale to Saudi Arabia and other Persian Gulf countries would not threaten Israel's military superiority and was necessary to counter a threat from Iran.</p>
        <p>Speaking to reporters here after talks with Prime Minister Ehud Olmert and other top officials on his visit to the Middle East, Mr. Gates said that he had emphasized that Iran posed a greater threat to Israel than did the Arab countries that were to receive the sophisticated weaponry.</p>
        <p>The Bush administration sees such a sale as a way to offset concern in the region about Iran's strength.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gates's visit to Israel is the first by an American defense secretary in nearly eight years.</p>
        <p>Though American officials have not described the arms package publicly, Israel is most concerned about planned transfers of satellite-guided munitions to Saudi Arabia, American officials said, speaking on the condition of anonymity because the information is classified and the deal has not been formally announced. The United States has not previously sold the highly accurate bombs to the Saudis, though Israel has received them for years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gates said that he had made it clear that the United States would help Israel maintain its military advantage but that he had urged Israel not to oppose such a sale. Bush administration officials are worried that Israel may turn to its allies in Congress to block the sale, though so far it has registered its opposition quietly, American officials said.</p>
        <p>He said he had told Israeli officials that they ''needed to take into consideration the overall strategic environment'' in the Middle East and that Russia and other countries might sell arms to Persian Gulf countries if the United States did not.</p>
        <p>Israeli officials are also worried about Iran, and pressed Mr. Gates during his two-day visit here on the need to halt its progress on building a nuclear weapon. After meeting with Defense Minister Amir Peretz on Wednesday, Mr. Gates said they agreed that diplomatic pressure to halt the Iranian nuclear program was working.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Peretz took a harder stance, saying Iranian leaders wanted ''to destroy Israel.'' He said Israel could not rule out other options, apparently a reference to a possible military strike on Iran.</p>
        <p>''The diplomatic track is preferable and it must be exhausted, but it is still not able to remove other options from the table,'' Mr. Peretz told reporters at a news conference with Mr. Gates on Wednesday. ''We expect that the U.S. and the world will stand by us regarding the Iran nuclear issue,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Bush administration has not ruled out military action against Iran. But Mr. Gates's comments in Israel were his most direct explanation of his reluctance to consider military action against Iran's nuclear facilities. He said he had not discussed military options with the Israelis. ''Clearly, if you think that the program is further away from being irreversible, or containable, you have more time for the diplomatic process to work,'' he said, adding that it was his impression ''that at this point they are comfortable with letting the diplomatic process work out.''</p>
        <p>Iran contends that its nuclear program is peaceful, but the United States and a number of other countries contend that Iran is planning to develop nuclear arms.</p>
        <p>Also on Thursday, Tzipi Livni, Israel's foreign minister, said the Arab League should ''show flexibility'' and agree to more broad talks about the Saudi peace initiative that the Arab nations revived last month. The plan, introduced in 2002, calls on Israel to withdraw to its 1967 borders.</p>
        <p>Ms. Livni seemed to be expressing some disappointment with the decision on Wednesday by the Arab League to designate Egypt and Jordan to talk with Israel about the Saudi plan. Israel already has diplomatic relations with each country.</p>
        <p>''Those Arab countries with whom we don't have relations could be a party to such a process from the start,'' Ms. Livni said in a statement.</p>
        <p>King Abdullah II of Jordan met Thursday in Amman with Dalia Itzik, Israel's acting president and leader of Parliament, urging Israel to adopt the Saudi plan as the ''foundation for negotiations.''</p>
        <p>''Israel should not squander this historic opportunity,'' Reuters quoted the king as saying, ''which will ensure Israel's recognition by all Arab states and real integration into the region.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
