<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Owners Lose As Bosses Win In Bad Mergers</title>
    <meta content="20norris" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/business/20norris.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841649"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HIGH &amp; LOW FINANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Floyd Norris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3D61F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="728" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Owners Lose As Bosses Win In Bad Mergers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Owners Lose and Bosses Win in Bad Mergers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If it's not your money, you may be quite willing to spend more of it.</p>
        <p>That insight may seem obvious, but academic research demonstrating that it is true set off the great boom in equity compensation for corporate management over the last three decades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Academic research offers insights into how the very equity-based incentives that were supposed to make managers think like owners have instead encouraged them to overpay for acquisitions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If it's not your money, you may be quite willing to spend more of it.</p>
        <p>That insight may seem obvious, but academic research demonstrating that it is true set off the great boom in equity compensation for corporate management over the last three decades.</p>
        <p>As an article in The Journal of Finance this month puts it, a wealth of studies supports the hypothesis that ''managers with greater ownership, or managers with more equity-based incentives, are less likely to take value-destroying actions.'' Yet over time, few management actions have done as good a job of destroying value as have mergers and acquisitions. Some work out fine, but many do not.</p>
        <p>Now academic research offers insights into how the very equity-based incentives -- stock options and restricted stocks -- that were supposed to make managers think like owners have instead encouraged them to overpay for acquisitions. The bosses win, whether or not the owners lose.</p>
        <p>A new study by economists at the University of Pittsburgh and Ohio State University looked at all-cash takeovers done from 1990 to 2005, and found that the premiums paid varied based on who was doing the buying.</p>
        <p>On average, public companies made bids that drove up the target share price by 32 percent. But bids from privately held companies were lower, pushing prices up 22 percent. The figure for private equity funds was 20 percent.</p>
        <p>That difference means the public companies are paying more -- and thus the merged companies are less likely to do well, all other things being equal.</p>
        <p>One of the authors, René M. Stulz, a finance professor at Ohio State, told me that he first thought the explanation would be in the type of companies being bought, but that did not prove to be the case.</p>
        <p>Nor did it turn out that the ownership position of the bosses of the target company made a difference. Those with big stakes were not more likely to negotiate good deals than those with smaller positions.</p>
        <p>Instead, the data showed that the public company differential vanished if managers of the bidder owned at least 20 percent of the equity. Then they acted like private companies, and paid about the same premium.</p>
        <p>If a bidding war develops, or negative information surfaces, private buyers are also more likely to walk away from deals than are public companies, concluded the study done by Leonce L. Bargeron, Frederik P. Schlingemann and Chad J. Zutter of the University of Pittsburgh, along with Mr. Stulz.</p>
        <p>So why are public companies willing to pay more? An answer may come from the Journal of Finance article, written by Jarrad Harford of the University of Washington and Kai Li of the University of British Columbia.</p>
        <p>They found that corporate managers are often richer after a bad merger than they were before.</p>
        <p>''While shareholders might assume that their C.E.O.s' large portfolios of stock and options provide the necessary incentives to discourage them from making bad acquisitions,'' they wrote, ''the value of the flow of new grants after an acquisition can swamp'' any incentive offered by the pre-takeover holdings.</p>
        <p>Among mergers that left shareholders worse off than before, the managers emerged wealthier for the experience in three-quarters of the deals.</p>
        <p>One important lesson is that the managers' expectation of the continuing flow of equity grants can provide incentives that sharply differ from the incentives that exist because of the prior grants. A lower stock price can mean better-priced options.</p>
        <p>Pay consultants advising boards on pay for chief executives typically start by calculating the compensation at comparable companies. A big merger can catapult a company into a bigger size category, making the old executive-compensation package appear to be very low compared with the new set of comparable companies. So the bosses get big raises long before it is clear whether the merger is going to work out well.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stulz says the clear advantages to management of mergers -- even if they do not help the shareholders -- mean that the board should be involved in merger discussions from the beginning.</p>
        <p>''You also want to make sure that you do not compensate management just because the company is bigger,'' he said.</p>
        <p>More likely, some clever consultant will discover this paper and conclude that the answer is clear: Give management 20 percent of the company to assure they will be adequately motivated to keep the interests of shareholders in mind.</p>
        <p>HIGH &amp; LOW FINANCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
