<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Playing a Game of Cat and Mouse Without Breaking a Sweat</title>
    <meta content="20frac" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/movies/20frac.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841533"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dargis, Manohla</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoblit, Gregory</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hopkins, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gosling, Ryan</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Fracture (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Hoblit, Gregory</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Fracture (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E0DB1F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="727" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Playing a Game of Cat and Mouse Without Breaking a Sweat</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Playing a Game of Cat and Mouse Without Breaking a Sweat</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MANOHLA DARGIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dargis, Manohla</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Manohla Dargis reviews film Fracture, directed by Gregory Hoblit; Anthony Hopkins and Ryan Gosling star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The glib entertainment ''Fracture'' offers an assortment of tasty treats, notably the spectacle of that crafty scene stealer Anthony Hopkins mixing it up with that equally cunning screen nibbler Ryan Gosling. They're beautiful slummers, these two, as well oiled and practiced as those great old-studio dissemblers who worked a soundstage to their and Louis B. Mayer's advantage. The only difference is that once upon a time Joan Crawford would have whispered dangerous nothings into Mr. Hopkins's ear, not Mr. Gosling.</p>
        <p>There are a couple of women onboard in ''Fracture,'' though as usual they're mostly around to look good and play (almost) dead. Embeth Davidtz slips nicely into the ill-fated little woman role, the one mentioned in the eye-catching advertisements that feature Mr. Hopkins softly smiling under the words ''I shot my wife.'' As the smiler with the wife, Mr. Hopkins's Ted Crawford does something complicated looking with airplanes, barks monosyllabic instructions at underlings (''No!'') and leaves the world choking on his Porche-churned dust. He also points and shoots, sending a bullet into his spouse's pampered cheek during the film's precision-timed opener, leaving a hole in her head as well as, presumably, his alibi.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“Fracture” offers the spectacle of that crafty scene stealer Anthony Hopkins mixing it up with that equally cunning screen nibbler Ryan Gosling.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The glib entertainment ''Fracture'' offers an assortment of tasty treats, notably the spectacle of that crafty scene stealer Anthony Hopkins mixing it up with that equally cunning screen nibbler Ryan Gosling. They're beautiful slummers, these two, as well oiled and practiced as those great old-studio dissemblers who worked a soundstage to their and Louis B. Mayer's advantage. The only difference is that once upon a time Joan Crawford would have whispered dangerous nothings into Mr. Hopkins's ear, not Mr. Gosling.</p>
        <p>There are a couple of women onboard in ''Fracture,'' though as usual they're mostly around to look good and play (almost) dead. Embeth Davidtz slips nicely into the ill-fated little woman role, the one mentioned in the eye-catching advertisements that feature Mr. Hopkins softly smiling under the words ''I shot my wife.'' As the smiler with the wife, Mr. Hopkins's Ted Crawford does something complicated looking with airplanes, barks monosyllabic instructions at underlings (''No!'') and leaves the world choking on his Porche-churned dust. He also points and shoots, sending a bullet into his spouse's pampered cheek during the film's precision-timed opener, leaving a hole in her head as well as, presumably, his alibi.</p>
        <p>We know that Ted Crawford done it and perhaps why -- some rumpled hotel sheets provide one steamy clue -- the big question, the one that sets the plot a-churning and Mr. Gosling's lawyer-character a-calling, is how the bad man plans to get away with it. All in good time, my pretties, all in good time.</p>
        <p>First, the lawyer, Willy Beachum, must provide some storybook diversion, mainly in the form of a high-paying, potentially soul-killing new job that will take him out of the public service, where he works for the Los Angeles district attorney's office (which knows a little something if sometimes not enough about rich men accused of murdering the women in their lives), and into the well-upholstered evil of the private sector.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hopkins and Mr. Gosling navigate the film's sleekly burnished surfaces and darkly lighted interiors, its procedural twists and courtroom turns without breaking stride or into a sweat. Each actor is playing a pulp type rather than a fully formed individual, but both fill in the blanks with an alchemical mix of professional and personal charisma. (Mr. Gosling also tosses in a Southern accent.)</p>
        <p>Even Mr. Hopkins's most familiar tricks -- a blank face capped by a hint of a shiver-inducing smile -- work to the story's advantage. In a less capable film those gently upturned lips could easily repulse because they would invoke unfavorable comparisons with Hannibal Lecter; here, though, they simply remind you that memorable screen villainy can be as much a matter of impeccable manners as evil designs.</p>
        <p>The screenwriters, Daniel Pyne and Glenn Gers, hit the customary thriller notes with a touch of humor, and the director, Gregory Hoblit (who worked similar terrain in ''Primal Fear''), arranges those notes into a catchy, insistent rhythm. There are a few loose ends, but questions of logic have a way of receding in a film in which the bad man can be seen reflected in a pool of his victim's blood. ''Fracture'' isn't a movie about ideas; it's about slick surfaces and suggestive adjectives like rich and poor, good and evil, weak and strong. It's about the functionally ornamental Rosamund Pike, who delivers her goods in a tight sweater as Beachum's romantic foil, and the invariably reliable David Strathairn, who delivers his with a firm jaw as the younger man's moral conscience.</p>
        <p>Finally, and without shame, it is about Mr. Gosling making some dough and Mr. Hopkins punching the clock, as much for their obvious pleasure as ours.</p>
        <p>''Fracture'' is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). Some graphic violence mixed in with some circumspect sex.</p>
        <p>Fracture  Opens today nationwide.</p>
        <p>Directed by Gregory Hoblit; written by Daniel Pyne and Glenn Gers, based on a story by Mr. Pyne; director of photography, Kramer Morgenthau; edited by David Rosenbloom; music by Mychael Danna and Jeff Danna; production designer, Paul Eads; produced by Charles Weinstock; released by New Line Cinema. Running time: 111 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Anthony Hopkins (Ted Crawford), Ryan Gosling (Willy Beachum), David Strathairn (Joe Lobruto), Rosamund Pike (Nikki Gardner), Embeth Davidtz (Jennifer Crawford), Billy Burke (Detective Rob Nunally), Cliff Curtis (Detective Flores), Fiona Shaw (Judge Robinson) and Bob Gunton (Judge Gardner).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
