<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LIVING HERE | Ferry Required; No Bridge, No Problem</title>
    <meta content="20live" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841634"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Havens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Living Here</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7D61F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="901" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LIVING HERE | Ferry Required; No Bridge, No Problem</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">As told to Bethany Lyttle</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHO -- Dave and Doreen Keyes, both 57, both retired, of Bellevue, Wash.  WHERE -- San Juan Island, Wash.  WHAT -- 3-bedroom house</p>
        <p>Dave: We started coming here as boaters in the mid-1970s. Every stop in Friday Harbor would turn into a fantasy about living here. But it wasn't until 1990 that we purchased a cabin on some acreage and started to come on long weekends. We still own that cabin, but this year we finished building a new house on an adjacent property. Building a house in a place that requires ferry transportation is a challenge. You have to be very organized. Everything must be ordered and scheduled. You can't just run out to the lumberyard if you forget something.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHO -- Dave and Doreen Keyes, both 57, both retired, of Bellevue, Wash.  WHERE -- San Juan Island, Wash.  WHAT -- 3-bedroom house</p>
        <p>Dave: We started coming here as boaters in the mid-1970s. Every stop in Friday Harbor would turn into a fantasy about living here. But it wasn't until 1990 that we purchased a cabin on some acreage and started to come on long weekends. We still own that cabin, but this year we finished building a new house on an adjacent property. Building a house in a place that requires ferry transportation is a challenge. You have to be very organized. Everything must be ordered and scheduled. You can't just run out to the lumberyard if you forget something.</p>
        <p>Doreen: That's true. It's one thing to want to be on the ferry, floating across the water enjoying the scenery and watching tourists as they experience the smell of the water and the sight of orcas for the first time. It's another to count on it for things you can't easily find on the island. Still, I enjoy it. The ferry ride is a transition from one life to another. We grocery shop when we land, so I like to make my list while I'm on the boat.</p>
        <p>Dave: And there's a lovely social element to the ride. In the passenger cabin, you see friends, sit together and chat. The challenge is long waits during tourist season. We have an amphibious float plane, and sometimes when time is really tight in the summers, we fly instead. The rest of the year, factoring in the ferry ride isn't a problem.</p>
        <p>Doreen: As the ferry docks, there's a feeling of excitement that hasn't changed one bit since we first came here over 30 years ago.</p>
        <p>As told to Bethany Lyttle</p>
        <p>Information on properties was supplied by the owners or the listing companies.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Nantucket, Mass.  WHAT -- 3-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $895,000</p>
        <p>This 1,800-square-foot shingled cape-style house was built in 1989 and is a mile from the ferry dock. It has sliding glass doors onto a patio and yard, a gas fireplace in the living room, wood floors throughout and two bathrooms, including one with a jetted tub and a separate shower in the master suite. The basement is partly finished for use as an office or a den. Ferries connect Nantucket with the mainland and seasonally with Martha's Vineyard. Agent: Pamela Joslin, Congdon &amp; Coleman Real Estate, (508) 360-1273; www.congdonandcoleman.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Mackinac Island, Mich.  WHAT -- 3-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $599,000</p>
        <p>This 2,023-square-foot Victorian-style house has partial views of Lake Huron and the Straits of Mackinac, 290 miles north of Detroit. It has a four-season conservatory, mature gardens, two bathrooms, a fireplace and a rear deck. The house is a few minutes from the ferry dock, whether by bicycle, foot or horse-drawn carriage. Agent: Cheryl Schlehuber, Mackinac Properties, (906) 643-9242; www.mackinacproperties.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Fire Island Pines, N.Y.  WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $925,000</p>
        <p>This approximately 2,200-square-foot Fire Island contemporary is on Bay Walk less than a five-minute walk from the ferry to Sayville on Long Island, about 55 miles east of Manhattan. It has been completely renovated and has an open floor plan and air-conditioning. Sliding doors in the living room open to a swimming pool and a hot tub. There is a fifth bathroom in addition to private bathrooms for each bedroom. It is offered furnished. Agent: Ken Lesser, Pines Harbor Realty, (631) 597-7575; www.pinesharbor.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Block Island, R.I.  WHAT -- 3-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $929,000</p>
        <p>A short walk from Cooneymus Beach, this 768-square-foot renovated cottage has a deck with views of Warden's Pond. The house has an open floor plan with exposed beams, hardwood floors and new appliances in a renovated kitchen. There are one and a half bathrooms. A shed has been converted for use as an extra room, but it has no bathroom. The house is a 10-minute drive from ferries to Point Judith and seasonally to Newport. Broker: Jennifer Phillips, Phillips Real Estate, (401) 466-8806; www.phillipsonbi.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Friday Harbor, Wash.  WHAT -- 3-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $450,000</p>
        <p>This house on San Juan Island was built in 1951 and has views of Mount Baker and Friday Harbor. The house is about five minutes from ferries to North Saanich, near Victoria, British Columbia; to Anacortes, which has road connections to the mainland north of Seattle; and to other San Juan Islands. The house has been renovated and has a new kitchen, a fireplace and one and a half bathrooms. The property is a quarter-acre with mature gardens. Agent: Lisa Lawrence, Friday Harbor Realty, (360) 378-2151; www.sanjuans.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Watervale, Prince Edward Island  WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $67,500</p>
        <p>Situated about 25 minutes from the ferry, which connects the province to Pictou, Nova Scotia, this 1,200-square-foot house has been renovated. It has new windows, new wood floors, one bathroom and new kitchen cabinets. The property is two acres with trees in front and flat land, which is still farmed, in the back. Watervale is an hour drive from Cavendish and the Green Gables house, a popular tourist destination. The asking price is 76,500 Canadian dollars. Agent: Gordon Gosley, Royal LePage Peters &amp; Lank Realty, (902) 892-5355; www.lank.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
