<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Usual, Jets Won't Reveal What Their Draft Plans Are</title>
    <meta content="20jets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/sports/football/20jets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841558"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Jets</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE2D91F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="654" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Usual, Jets Won't Reveal What Their Draft Plans Are</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">As Usual, Jets Won’t Reveal What Their Draft Plans Are</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID PICKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Picker, David</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., April 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>During the Jets' predraft news conference Thursday, Terry Bradway, their director of player personnel, boasted about the team's extensive vetting process. The Jets wrote more than 5,000 scouting reports, evaluated more than 1,000 prospects, conducted more than 200 interviews and had 34 players work out at their practice facility.</p>
        <p>So, which players do the Jets hope to get with the 25th pick in the first round of the N.F.L. draft on April 28?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Jets were not specific when discussing their draft needs Thursday, but they will most likely try to improve at defensive lineman and cornerback.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>During the Jets' predraft news conference Thursday, Terry Bradway, their director of player personnel, boasted about the team's extensive vetting process. The Jets wrote more than 5,000 scouting reports, evaluated more than 1,000 prospects, conducted more than 200 interviews and had 34 players work out at their practice facility.</p>
        <p>So, which players do the Jets hope to get with the 25th pick in the first round of the N.F.L. draft on April 28?</p>
        <p>More than 10 reporters asked more than 50 questions over more than 40 minutes hoping to get an answer. But the Jets, who run a tight ship, were true to form, revealing as little as possible.</p>
        <p>''I don't anticipate taking a punter,'' General Manager Mike Tannenbaum said, offering job security to Ben Graham, who is regarded as one of the best punters in the league. ''But beyond that, I think everything is fair game.''</p>
        <p>The Jets have six draft picks, including two in the second round, 59th and 63rd over all. Last August, they traded their fourth-rounder in 2007 to the San Francisco 49ers for running back Kevan Barlow.</p>
        <p>Tannenbaum said the Jets would consider trading up or down, but he added that such decisions were usually made at the last minute. The Jets made four trades during last year's draft. Tannenbaum said no player on the current roster was untouchable.</p>
        <p>The Jets were not specific when discussing their draft needs. Their director of college scouting, Joey Clinkscales, would say only that they had no glaring needs. They will most likely try to improve at defensive lineman and cornerback. By the 25th pick, however, the most highly regarded cornerbacks could be off the board.</p>
        <p>''Are there certain cornerbacks that will be drafted in the first round?'' Clinkscales said. ''Absolutely. Maybe all of them. But it's just hard to say at this point.'' He added that this year's draft was deep at cornerback, safety, defensive back and wide receiver.</p>
        <p>The Jets did not reveal the names of the 34 players they had brought in. But Clinkscales was asked about cornerbacks Chris Houston of Arkansas, Darrelle Revis of Pittsburgh and Aaron Ross of Texas. He gave glowing reports, noting that Houston and Revis could compete for a starting job immediately.</p>
        <p>Tannenbaum mentioned several times that 21 of 22 starters from last season were returning. When asked about the value of the 25th pick, he said he thought a starter could be found in any round. The Pittsburgh Steelers used the 25th overall pick last year to draft Santonio Holmes, a wide receiver from Ohio State who started four games and had 824 receiving yards last season.</p>
        <p>Whomever the Jets draft, his character will be carefully weighed. The N.F.L. recently toughened its player-conduct policy. Bradway said the Jets did not change their strategy because they have always had high standards.</p>
        <p>''We know what kind of guys he wants,'' Bradway said, referring to Coach Eric Mangini, who did not attend the news conference. ''We've got these core values that are important with these players that we select. From that standpoint, it hasn't really affected us. We've been looking for good guys.''</p>
        <p>If the Jets need advice on draft day, they can always contact Larry David, the ''Seinfeld'' and ''Curb Your Enthusiasm'' creator. David, who was born and raised in Brooklyn, recently met with Mangini and Tannenbaum in Los Angeles, where he offered suggestions on the draft.</p>
        <p>When Tannenbaum was asked Thursday about the Jets' needs, he was so elusive he made a reporter laugh. Tannenbaum then jokingly said he had been working on his comedy with David. With the room sufficiently warmed up, Tannenbaum aimed for more laughs.</p>
        <p>''We admire his passion and his insight,'' Tannenbaum said of David. ''Just so you know, Eric's always coaching. We spent some time out there. Eric coached him up on some of his shows. We expect to see some improvement on his end as well.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
