<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HAVENS | Kingston, N.Y.; A Historic River City Is Losing Its Backwater Reputation</title>
    <meta content="20havens" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/realestate/greathomes/20havens.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841633"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Havens | Kingston, N.Y."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Havens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Great Homes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Upstate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEED71F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1506" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HAVENS | Kingston, N.Y.; A Historic River City Is Losing Its Backwater Reputation</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Historic River City Is Losing Its Backwater Reputation</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA A. PHILLIPS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>APHRODITE CLAMAR-COHEN used to spend weekends at a home on seven wooded acres in the Catskills in Bearsville, N.Y. She loved to get away from Manhattan, but she didn't like the isolation of country life. She was used to walking places and seeing people, and she wanted the same lifestyle on the weekends.</p>
        <p>One afternoon, as she drove through the small city of Kingston, she found herself pulling over at Four Corners, the only intersection in the United States, it is said, with 18th-century stone houses on each corner. One was for sale.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A growing number of enterprising buyers are choosing Kingston, N.Y., for a second home, drawn by its pedestrian-friendly neighborhoods, rich history and housing bargains.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>APHRODITE CLAMAR-COHEN used to spend weekends at a home on seven wooded acres in the Catskills in Bearsville, N.Y. She loved to get away from Manhattan, but she didn't like the isolation of country life. She was used to walking places and seeing people, and she wanted the same lifestyle on the weekends.</p>
        <p>One afternoon, as she drove through the small city of Kingston, she found herself pulling over at Four Corners, the only intersection in the United States, it is said, with 18th-century stone houses on each corner. One was for sale.</p>
        <p>Ms. Clamar-Cohen, 64, a psychologist, sold her house in Bearsville and bought the two-story, three-bedroom Colonial with an attached office building for $575,000 in 2003. Part of the attraction was that the house, which is on a half-acre, was near shops, restaurants, galleries and ''fancy groceries'' -- an organic butcher and a bakery.</p>
        <p>''Every time I wanted to do anything in Bearsville, I had to get into the car,'' she said. ''I don't have to do that here.''</p>
        <p>Kingston, on the west bank of the Hudson River, is not a traditional site for second homes. It's more likely to be the city off the New York State Thruway where second-home owners stop for supplies before heading up Route 28 to Woodstock, Mount Tremper or Phoenicia. A small but growing number of enterprising buyers, however, are choosing Kingston, real estate agents said, drawn by its pedestrian-friendly neighborhoods, rich history and housing bargains.</p>
        <p>Kingston was settled by the Dutch in the 1600s. In 1777, the first New York State constitution was written there, and the city became the first capital of New York. The British burned it in retaliation, an event re-enacted in Kingston every few years.</p>
        <p>Kingston has gone through many lives since -- as a center for shipbuilding, brick making and other 19th-century industries and as an I.B.M. stronghold from the 1950s to the '90s. Today, it is trying another comeback as an affordable alternative to Hudson and Beacon, other small river cities that have become popular in the last decade.</p>
        <p>''I always had a negative view of Kingston as a Hudson River backwater,'' said Steven Paul Mark, a Manhattan lawyer who bought a 2,300-square-foot three-bedroom Bauhaus-style home last October for $395,000. ''Then my eyes popped open.''</p>
        <p>The Scene</p>
        <p>Kingston sits at the confluence of the Hudson River and the Rondout Creek, which is bigger than its name suggests. It is divided into three main neighborhoods. The Uptown Stockade District was named for the fortress that protected the original Dutch settlement. It has history museums, restaurants and an oddball variety of businesses, from galleries and antiques stores to Sam's Swap Shop, a pawn shop.</p>
        <p>Visitors are often surprised by the quaint porticos that cover the Uptown business district. ''It's like the French Quarter,'' Mr. Mark said, ''without the drunks.''</p>
        <p>The Rondout-West Strand District has a riverfront mix of restaurants, bars and shops, and museums that celebrate the region's maritime heritage. For decades, it has been a destination for artists seeking low-cost studio space and housing.</p>
        <p>Midtown runs along Broadway between Uptown and the Rondout. The district's main draw is the Ulster Performing Arts Center's Broadway Theater, a renovated 1927 movie palace that draws acts like Jeff Tweedy and the Moscow Festival Ballet.</p>
        <p>Kingston is the kind of place where you can have a grilled cheese for lunch at the counter of Nekos Luncheonette and foie gras at dinner at the Zagat-reviewed Downtown Cafe, without having to change outfits.</p>
        <p>Kingston's night life is erratic, with clubs often having trouble surviving. The few enduring nights spots include the Rive Gauche Club at the popular restaurant Canard Enchainé and El Coqui, a Puerto Rican restaurant that heats up with live music and salsa dancing on Saturday nights.</p>
        <p>Pros</p>
        <p>Kingston is one of the few places in the Hudson Valley where you don't need a car. Many parts of Uptown are in walking distance of basic amenities and the intercity bus terminal. Kingston also has city buses. For cyclists, a rail trail connects Kingston with several nearby towns.</p>
        <p>But a car can be handy, since Kingston is near hiking, skiing and the other outdoor attractions of the Hudson Valley and the Catskills You don't have to go outside the city for recreation, though. There's swimming at Kingston Point Beach on the Hudson, and boaters can dock at several marinas on the Rondout.</p>
        <p>Cons</p>
        <p>The second-home community is growing, but it is small and scattered, so weekenders may be viewed as a curiosity.</p>
        <p>Kevin McEvoy and Barbara Epstein bought a Colonial-era stone house in a working-class area of the Rondout for $120,000 in 2001. It wasn't until they fixed up a rundown red barn on their property that they came to know their neighbors, all full-timers.</p>
        <p>''They at first were definitely like, 'Who are these people?' '' Ms. Epstein said. ''Then after the renovation, every neighbor came here and said what a good job we did.''</p>
        <p>Kingston has its share of urban problems. Midtown is the ''toughest to police,'' especially south of Broadway, with a crack problem lingering from the drug epidemic of the 1980s, Police Chief Gerald Keller said.</p>
        <p>The Real Estate Market</p>
        <p>Kingston is relatively inexpensive. Count on getting a vacation house for about $100,000 less than what you'd pay for a similar house in the country in Ulster County, said Harris Safier, who owns Westwood Metes and Bounds Realty, which has an office in Kingston.</p>
        <p>The average home price in 2006 was $210,972, and the average listing stays on the market for about five months, according to the Ulster County Board of Realtors. Decent three-bedroom houses can be bought for $200,000 to $300,000, area real estate agents said. Even the ''Robber Baron Mansions,'' as local residents call them, and restored Dutch stone Colonials rarely exceed $600,000.</p>
        <p>Kingston tends to attract people interested in ''houses that are significant architecturally or historically,'' said Sandie Hutton, an agent at Flemming Realty in nearby Stone Ridge. Expect a wide selection of Victorian houses with high ceilings and period details. The city also has plenty of houses built in the Arts and Crafts style, some from kits supplied by Sears and Montgomery Ward.</p>
        <p>Real estate agents estimate that only 5 to 10 percent of their sales in 2006 were to second-home buyers, but they expect this market to grow. ''It's without a doubt in an uptick,'' said Larry O'Toole, an agent with Coldwell Banker Village Green Realty in Woodstock.</p>
        <p>There has been little large-scale housing construction in recent years, but developers are interested in the area. The Teicher Organization of East Brunswick, N.J., is moving ahead in the approval process on plans for a multistory condominium-retail complex in Uptown. AVR Realty of Yonkers has proposed a mixed-use development with 1,750 residential units on the Hudson River. Both projects have faced objections from local and state preservationists.</p>
        <p>LAY OF THE LAND</p>
        <p>POPULATION -- 23,067, according to a 2005 estimate by the Census Bureau.  SIZE -- 8.6 square miles.  LOCATION -- 100 miles north of New York City.  WHO'S BUYING -- Creative types from Manhattan who often have an interest in history and architecture. Real estate agents say they have seen in increase in younger buyers looking for housing deals and a place where they don't need a car.  GETTING THERE -- Kingston is usually just under a two-hour drive from Manhattan. Buses to Kingston leave the Port Authority Bus Terminal several times a day.  WHILE YOU'RE LOOKING -- Rooms start at $125 a night at Schwartz's Inn in Uptown (70 North Front Street, 845-389-9918; www.schwartzsinn.com), with private bathrooms and TV/VCR. The Quality Inn &amp; Suites (114 Route 28, 845-339-3900; www.choicehotels.com), right off the Thruway at Exit 19, has a restaurant and a swimming pool. Rooms start at $89.</p>
        <p>THREE FOR SALE  For Those Who Want Their Country Getaways in a City</p>
        <p>Information on properties was provided by the listing agents.</p>
        <p>WHAT -- 5-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $190,000</p>
        <p>This 1869 house is on 0.22 acres in the Rondout District near the riverfront. It is 2,130 square feet and has two bathrooms and tin ceilings. Agent: Deborah Hitz, Coldwell Banker Village Green Realty; (845) 687-4355; www.villagegreenrealty.com.</p>
        <p>WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $375,000</p>
        <p>This house is about 2,180 square feet and was built around 1720. It has period details, including the fireplaces, wide-board floors and a tiger maple banister. The kitchen and the two and a half bathrooms need restoration. It is on about an acre in the Uptown neighborhood. Agent: Sandie Hutton, Flemming Realty; (845) 687-4451; www.flemmingrealty.com.</p>
        <p>WHAT -- 7-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $1,299,000</p>
        <p>This house, with views of the Hudson River, was built in 1891 and is about 5,900 square feet. It has four and a half bathrooms, a grand staircase, French doors, Palladian windows, 11-foot ceilings, seven fireplaces and two wood-burning stoves. It is on 1.6 acres. Agent: Mary Orapello, Win Morrison Realty; (845) 339-1144; www.winmorrisonrealty.com.</p>
        <p>Havens | Kingston, N.Y.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
