<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Innocence or Experience? An American Tale</title>
    <meta content="20step" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/movies/20step.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841543"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brougher, Hilary</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tamblyn, Amber</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swinton, Tilda</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Stephanie Daley (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Brougher, Hilary</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Stephanie Daley (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E7DA1F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="701" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Innocence or Experience? An American Tale</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Innocence or Experience? An American Tale</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews film Stephanie Daley, written and directed by Hilary Brougher; Amber Tamblyn and Tilda Swinton star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Ski Mom Case: that's the callous label the news media affix to the prosecution of the title character of ''Stephanie Daley'' for the murder of her newborn on a class ski trip. Stephanie (Amber Tamblyn), a shy, guarded 16-year-old who is the only child of conservative religious parents, denies responsibility by insisting that she didn't know she was pregnant. Her condition is discovered when she collapses while traipsing through the snow with her friends.</p>
        <p>The film keeps us in suspense about what actually happened, and it isn't until the end that the sad facts are revealed, in a grisly, agonized scene in a toilet stall. As the movie fills in Stephanie's story in flashbacks, the narrative revolves around her gently persistent interrogation by Lydie Crane (Tilda Swinton), the forensic psychologist hired by the prosecution to draw her out. Lydie, who gave birth to a stillborn child and is now in the final weeks of another pregnancy, is Stephanie's ethical foil in a morally ambiguous game of cat and mouse.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Without standing on a soapbox “Stephanie Daley” suggests a tragic gender gap between men who judge and women who feel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Ski Mom Case: that's the callous label the news media affix to the prosecution of the title character of ''Stephanie Daley'' for the murder of her newborn on a class ski trip. Stephanie (Amber Tamblyn), a shy, guarded 16-year-old who is the only child of conservative religious parents, denies responsibility by insisting that she didn't know she was pregnant. Her condition is discovered when she collapses while traipsing through the snow with her friends.</p>
        <p>The film keeps us in suspense about what actually happened, and it isn't until the end that the sad facts are revealed, in a grisly, agonized scene in a toilet stall. As the movie fills in Stephanie's story in flashbacks, the narrative revolves around her gently persistent interrogation by Lydie Crane (Tilda Swinton), the forensic psychologist hired by the prosecution to draw her out. Lydie, who gave birth to a stillborn child and is now in the final weeks of another pregnancy, is Stephanie's ethical foil in a morally ambiguous game of cat and mouse.</p>
        <p>At moments the parallels between the two women's lives seem a little too programmatic for comfort. There is a fine line between a human drama with its own life and an issue-oriented dramatic essay. And if ''Stephanie Daley,'' written and directed by Hilary Brougher, didn't have its ear so perfectly tuned to intergenerational dialogue, and to the severe language of sex education in schools where abstinence is taught as the only acceptable form of birth control, it would come across as just such an essay.</p>
        <p>But almost until the end, when it makes a confusing, melodramatic misstep, the movie feels extraordinarily lifelike. The scenes set in Stephanie's English class, in which ''The Scarlet Letter'' is being taught, reveal exactly how a classic work of literature can be bent to express a particular agenda.</p>
        <p>When the teacher asks the class to describe the point of this Hawthorne novel, Stephanie pipes up, ''It's harder to live a lie than to tell the truth and be punished.'' But the class rebel, Satin (Caitlin Van Zandt), a plain, stout girl and lapsed Christian with a bad reputation, dismisses the book. Satin's bravado collapses when the teacher approaches her desk, glares down at her and declares: ''You know what great literature is about, Satin? It's about man and God. Nothing else really matters.'' Afterward Satin tearfully accuses Stephanie of being a sheep.</p>
        <p>The equally incisive scene of Stephanie's sly seduction by an older boy during a beer party at which she is too shy to socialize offers a creepy picture of sexual exploitation posing as kindness. The movie also shows the devastating effects on Stephanie's parents of the publicity surrounding the case.</p>
        <p>As the movie compares Stephanie's sullen evasiveness and her impulse to protect her privacy to the underlying ambivalence of Lydie, who professes to be thrilled by her pregnancy while suspecting her distant architect husband, Paul (Timothy Hutton), of infidelity, the teenager and the psychologist are sisters under the skin. On matters of childbirth Paul is as hard-nosed in his way as the officials at Stephanie's school. His disgust with Lydie after her failure to memorialize the baby she miscarried has seriously eroded their marriage.</p>
        <p>Keenly intelligent, sensitive and self-protective, Ms. Swinton's Lydie is as fully realized as Ms. Tamblyn's Stephanie. If one weren't grilling the other, you could imagine them as mentor and protégée. Without standing on a soapbox ''Stephanie Daley'' suggests a tragic gender gap between men who judge and women who feel.</p>
        <p>''Stephanie Daley'' is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It includes sexual situations and an agonizing birth scene.</p>
        <p>Stephanie Daley  Opens today in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Written and directed by Hilary Brougher; director of photography, David Rush Morrison; edited by Keith Reamer; music by David Mansfield; production designer, Sharon Lomofsky; produced by Sean Costello, Lynette Howell, Samara Koffler and Jen Roskind; released by Regent Releasing and Liberation Entertainment. At the Angelika Film Center, Mercer and Houston Streets, Greenwich Village. Running time: 91 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Tilda Swinton (Lydie Crane), Amber Tamblyn (Stephanie Daley), Timothy Hutton (Paul), Denis O'Hare (Frank), Jim Gaffigan (Joe), Deirdre O'Connell (Jane) and Caitlin Van Zandt (Satin).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
