<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New York Plans to Sue Drexel U. in Loans Inquiry</title>
    <meta content="20loans" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/education/20loans.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841597"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Drexel University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cuomo, Andrew M (Atty Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dillon, Sam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Drexel University</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E6D71F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="724" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New York Plans to Sue Drexel U. in Loans Inquiry</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New York Plans to Sue Drexel U. in Loans Inquiry</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM DILLON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dillon, Sam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Atty Gen Andrew M Cuomo notifies Drexel University he intends to sue it for deceptive business practices; is first time he has singled out university for lawsuit in his broadening investigation of college loan industry (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Andrew M. Cuomo, New York's attorney general, notified Drexel University yesterday that he intended to sue it for deceptive business practices, the first time that he has singled out a university for a lawsuit in his broadening investigation of the college loan industry.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo accused Drexel of steering students seeking loans to one private lender, Education Finance Partners, in exchange for payments from that lender based on loan volume. He had settled with eight other institutions that agreed to end such practices, and yesterday he announced settlements with four more: Salve Regina University in Rhode Island and, in New York, Pace University, New York Institute of Technology and Molloy College.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Andrew M. Cuomo, New York’s attorney general, notified Drexel University Thursday that he intended to sue it for deceptive business practices.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Andrew M. Cuomo, New York's attorney general, notified Drexel University yesterday that he intended to sue it for deceptive business practices, the first time that he has singled out a university for a lawsuit in his broadening investigation of the college loan industry.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo accused Drexel of steering students seeking loans to one private lender, Education Finance Partners, in exchange for payments from that lender based on loan volume. He had settled with eight other institutions that agreed to end such practices, and yesterday he announced settlements with four more: Salve Regina University in Rhode Island and, in New York, Pace University, New York Institute of Technology and Molloy College.</p>
        <p>Under the settlements, the colleges agreed to a code of conduct governing relations with lenders, and in most cases have agreed to repay money to students.</p>
        <p>Since April 2005, Drexel has received $124,000 from Education Finance Partners, based in San Francisco, and is owed an additional $126,000 in exchange for designating it as Drexel's ''sole preferred private loan provider,'' according to a letter Mr. Cuomo's office sent to Drexel yesterday.</p>
        <p>''I call this opening another front,'' Mr. Cuomo said in an interview. ''Drexel participated in revenue-sharing, which I consider to be the most egregious activity that we've found at any institution, and they did it to one of the greatest extents in the country, meaning they received more money back.</p>
        <p>''Also, they refused to settle,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Last month, Mr. Cuomo said he would sue Education Finance Partners, accusing it of forming revenue-sharing arrangements with more than 60 colleges. But this week he announced a settlement under which the lender agreed to adopt the code of conduct and to contribute $2.5 million to an educational fund.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo said he had jurisdiction to file suit against Drexel, which is in Philadelphia and has about 13,000 full-time undergraduate, graduate and professional students, because the university recruits students from New York and New York families rely on Drexel's representations about preferred lenders.</p>
        <p>Philip Terranova, Drexel's vice president for university relations, said in a statement Thursday evening: ''Drexel will vigorously defend its position in this matter. We believe the allegations are without foundation in law or in fact.''</p>
        <p>''We have carefully reviewed our practices regarding student loans, and we are satisfied that there is no conflict of interest,'' Mr. Terranova said. He said that the university had ''responded immediately with full disclosure'' of its loan practices after receiving a letter from Mr. Cuomo in February, and that it had not heard from Mr. Cuomo since.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo's tactics, Mr. Terranova said, raise ''troubling questions.''</p>
        <p>Under a contract that Drexel signed in 2006, Education Finance agreed to pay Drexel 75 basis points, or three-quarters of 1 percent, of the amount of all loans assumed by students the university referred to the lender, according to the letter from Mr. Cuomo. Since 2005, Education Finance Partners has received more than $16 million in loan volume from Drexel, the letter said.</p>
        <p>Salve Regina, a Roman Catholic university based in Newport, received $7,800 under ''a form of revenue sharing'' with Education Finance Partners, according to Mr. Cuomo's spokesman, Arthur Harris.</p>
        <p>In a statement yesterday, the university acknowledged no wrongdoing but said it had adopted a code of conduct ''as a measure of support for having all institutions operate by the highest ethical standards.''</p>
        <p>Molloy College, a Roman Catholic college in Rockville Centre, received more than $1,600 from Education Finance, but has returned the money to the lender, Mr. Harris said in a statement. A message left at Molloy College was not responded to.</p>
        <p>Pace University, in New York City and Westchester County, hired Sallie Mae employees to answer phones at financial aid call centers, and the employees falsely identified themselves as university employees, according to Mr. Harris's statement.</p>
        <p>Pace University said in a statement that it had recently barred the workers from misidentifying themselves, and that by Aug. 15 it would stop using call services provided by Sallie Mae or any other lender.</p>
        <p>Financial aid officers at the New York Institute of Technology had accepted reimbursements for meals and trips to conferences from lenders on its preferred lender list, but the college agreed to adopt the attorney general's code of conduct.</p>
        <p>Jason Selss, a spokesman, said the code ''reflects our commitment to act in our students' best interests.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
