<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Minnesota Doesn't Plan To Trade Garnett</title>
    <meta content="20nba" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/sports/basketball/20nba.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841637"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="N.B.A. ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Minnesota Timberwolves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Minnesota Timberwolves</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Garnett, Kevin</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E6D61F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="529" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Minnesota Doesn't Plan To Trade Garnett</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Minnesota Doesn’t Plan to Trade Garnett</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAT BORZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Borzi, Pat</byline>
      <dateline>MINNEAPOLIS, April 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Minnesota Timberwolves need to overhaul their roster, but they will probably not trade Kevin Garnett to do it.</p>
        <p>''I say we're planning on keeping Kevin,'' Kevin McHale, the team's vice president for basketball operations, said Thursday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kevin Garnett’s contract runs through the 2008-9 season but contains an opt-out clause that he can exercise next summer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Minnesota Timberwolves need to overhaul their roster, but they will probably not trade Kevin Garnett to do it.</p>
        <p>''I say we're planning on keeping Kevin,'' Kevin McHale, the team's vice president for basketball operations, said Thursday.</p>
        <p>Garnett's contract runs through the 2008-9 season but contains an opt-out clause that he can exercise next summer. Garnett had another strong season, averaging 22.4 points and winning his fourth consecutive league rebounding title (12.8). He sat out the final five games with right leg and back problems. Last week, Garnett left the team, with permission, for a second opinion and treatment in California.</p>
        <p>At times, Garnett expressed frustration with the team's lackluster play. The Timberwolves started 20-16 but finished 32-50, their fewest victories for a full season since 1995-96, when Garnett was a rookie. Coach Dwane Casey was fired Jan. 23, four days after guard Ricky Davis walked to the locker room after being substituted for during a double-overtime loss to Detroit. The Wolves were 12-30 under Randy Wittman.</p>
        <p>When the Wolves failed to acquire Allen Iverson or anyone else at the trade deadline, Garnett said, ''Typical,'' adding, ''Thank God for opt-outs,'' leading to speculation that he might ask to be traded.</p>
        <p>''Kevin's never expressed that, and we'll go on the assumption he wants to be here,'' said McHale, adding that the team's owner, Glen Taylor, asked him to return next season.</p>
        <p>ODEN TO ENTER DRAFT -- The Ohio State freshman Greg Oden will make himself available today for the N.B.A. draft, Al Powell, a family friend, said last night.</p>
        <p>''There will be a release in the morning from Ohio State,'' said Powell, who has been a party to meetings among Oden and two other Ohio State freshmen stars, Mike Conley Jr. and Daequan Cook. ''Greg Oden will be hiring an agent.''</p>
        <p>Powell was less specific about Conley's and Cook's plans, but said neither would be hiring an agent at this time. (AP)</p>
        <p>RILEY PLANS RETURN TO HEAT -- Pat Riley, who took time off from coaching this season to have surgery on his left hip and right knee, seems likely to return to the Miami Heat next season.</p>
        <p>The Miami Herald reported that Riley planned to return as the team's president and coach. His contract runs through the end of 2010.</p>
        <p>''My plans are to come back,'' he said, according to The Herald. ''I've got three years left on my contract, and Micky and I have a great relationship,'' he said of the team's owner, Micky Arison.</p>
        <p>''I have no plans on ever going to another franchise.''</p>
        <p>Last summer, when Riley did not announce until late August that he was returning to coach the Heat, there was speculation that the 2006-7 season would be his last.</p>
        <p>WARRIORS END PLAYOFF DROUGHT -- Baron Davis had 12 points, 10 rebounds and 14 assists as the Golden State Warriors defeated the Portland Trail Blazers, 120-98, Wednesday night to earn a playoff berth for the first time since 1994. Golden State (42-40) claimed the eighth playoff spot in the Western Conference and will be the underdogs against top-seeded Dallas (67-15), which has the league's best record.(AP)</p>
        <p>N.B.A. ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
