<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Isles Try to Put Close Calls and Noncalls Behind Them</title>
    <meta content="20islanders" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/20/sports/hockey/20islanders.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841636"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Buffalo Sabres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Nassau Coliseum</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Buffalo Sabres</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Smyth, Ryan</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Nolan, Ted</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Blake, Jason</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Dipietro, Rick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E6D61F3FF933A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="696" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Isles Try to Put Close Calls and Noncalls Behind Them</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Isles Try to Put Close Calls and Noncalls Behind Them</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONDALE, N.Y., April 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nassau Coliseum was empty at noon Thursday; the angry emotions 14 hours earlier had all but dissipated. The Islanders held what might be their last practice of the season, and the mood was businesslike and somber.</p>
        <p>''There are no quitters in here -- there'd better not be,'' left wing Ryan Smyth said in the dressing room.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Islanders face elimination from the Stanley Cup playoffs, and the end could come Friday, when they face the deeper and more talented Sabres in Game 5.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nassau Coliseum was empty at noon Thursday; the angry emotions 14 hours earlier had all but dissipated. The Islanders held what might be their last practice of the season, and the mood was businesslike and somber.</p>
        <p>''There are no quitters in here -- there'd better not be,'' left wing Ryan Smyth said in the dressing room.</p>
        <p>The Islanders face elimination from the Stanley Cup playoffs, and the end could come Friday, when they face the deeper and more talented Sabres in Game 5 of a best-of-seven series in Buffalo. The Sabres lead three games to one.</p>
        <p>Islanders Coach Ted Nolan told his team to forget about the negative aspects of Wednesday's 4-2 loss, in which a potential game-tying goal by defenseman Brendan Witt with 1 minute 42 seconds left was waved off.</p>
        <p>''That's water under the bridge,'' Nolan said after practice Thursday.</p>
        <p>Forgetting, however, did not sound as if it would be that easy. The Islanders said they needed to concentrate on playing a smart, tenacious game Friday -- traditional playoff boilerplate -- but Witt's no-goal had still been a topic of conversation.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, it's frustrating, but it's something we can't look at now,'' said Smyth, a trade-deadline acquisition who has easily been the Islanders' best player in the series.</p>
        <p>But a moment later, Smyth added, with a hint of a grin: ''Just be positive -- and beat the officials, too.''</p>
        <p>According to Mike Leggo, one of the referees, Witt and right wing Miroslav Satan shoved Buffalo goaltender Ryan Miller into the goal before Witt's goal that would have tied the game at 3-3.</p>
        <p>Islanders General Manager Garth Snow showed reporters a tape after the game that showed Miller was hit after the puck went into the goal, not before. Snow then suggested that the Islanders had been the victims of biased officiating for years.</p>
        <p>Chris Botta, an Islanders spokesman, said Thursday that Snow would not pursue the matter. The league had not contacted the Islanders with an explanation about why Witt's goal did not count, but the Islanders were not seeking one.</p>
        <p>It is not as if the penalties have been lopsided. The Islanders have had 15 power plays, compared with 20 for the Sabres. Perhaps the Islanders' perspective would be different if they had scored on more than two in the series.</p>
        <p>But the Islanders are also upset at the timing of the penalties. In the Game 3 loss Monday, Islanders defensemen Tom Poti and Marc-André Bergeron were penalized on the same play, with Poti receiving two high-sticking penalties. The Sabres scored on the power play.</p>
        <p>In Game 4, Buffalo defenseman Teppo Numminen rammed Islanders right wing Jason Blake into the boards. Numminen was penalized for two minutes, and the Islanders scored, but Nolan thought the penalty should have been more severe.</p>
        <p>''Even when I got up, I thought I'd broken my back,'' Blake said Thursday.</p>
        <p>Blake, who missed most of the second period, practiced Thursday and said he expected he would play Friday. He was sore, but he sounded as if sitting out what could be the team's final game was not an option.</p>
        <p>''What are you going to do?'' he said. ''It's the playoffs.''</p>
        <p>The Islanders said the penalties were tough to take because they believed that Buffalo, which compiled the best regular-season record in the N.H.L., had not outclassed them in any of the last three games. Witt's no-goal felt like an insult to them.</p>
        <p>''We're a bounce or a call away from winning,'' said Sean Hill, the Islanders' veteran defenseman. ''We'll use that to stay positive. That's what we'll do.''</p>
        <p>But Hill also said the Islanders may be able to use the anger generated by the no-goal call, as well as the penalties, as a motivational tool.</p>
        <p>As the Montreal Canadiens and the Toronto Maple Leafs stumbled, the Islanders earned a playoff berth by winning their final four games. They have been in this spot before, in a way. All they have to do this time is win three in a row.</p>
        <p>''I think we know what it takes to win big games, must-win games, but this is the playoffs,'' goaltender Rick DiPietro said. ''This is a different brand of hockey.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
