<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Four Games, Matsui Finds Himself on the D.L.</title>
    <meta content="09pins" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/09/sports/baseball/09pins.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839151"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Matsui, Hideki</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E0D7143FF93AA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="614" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Four Games, Matsui Finds Himself on the D.L.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After Four Games, Matsui Finds Himself on the D.L.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL S. SCHMIDT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schmidt, Michael S</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It took a broken wrist to sideline Hideki Matsui last season and end his streak of 1,768 consecutive games played, which spanned two continents and 13 years. This season it took only four games, a cold day and a ground ball to put him on the disabled list.</p>
        <p>A magnetic resonance imaging exam yesterday showed a strain in Matsui's left hamstring and the Yankees have placed him on the 15-day disabled list. They recalled outfielder Kevin Thompson from Class AAA Scranton to fill Matsui's roster spot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This season it took only four games, a cold day and a ground ball to put Hideki Matsui on the disabled list.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It took a broken wrist to sideline Hideki Matsui last season and end his streak of 1,768 consecutive games played, which spanned two continents and 13 years. This season it took only four games, a cold day and a ground ball to put him on the disabled list.</p>
        <p>A magnetic resonance imaging exam yesterday showed a strain in Matsui's left hamstring and the Yankees have placed him on the 15-day disabled list. They recalled outfielder Kevin Thompson from Class AAA Scranton to fill Matsui's roster spot.</p>
        <p>''It is something we just don't want to play with,'' General Manager Brian Cashman said after the Yankees' 6-4 loss to the Baltimore Orioles yesterday. ''It is something we could have held back for five or six days, but with hamstrings it's just not worth the gamble.</p>
        <p>''We are going to take the safe route and make sure that this is not an issue that carries deep into the season and get it out of the way now.''</p>
        <p>Matsui was forced to leave Saturday's game after he strained the hamstring running to first base on a ground ball in the second inning.</p>
        <p>Torre speculated that the cold weather in New York might have had something to do with the injury.</p>
        <p>''We know how well conditioned he is,'' Torre said. ''The weather is the only thing I can excuse for that one. He didn't take a misstep.''</p>
        <p>It was 39 degrees at the start of Saturday's game, and it has been a teeth-chattering start to the season for the Yankees, who opened their season with five games at home.</p>
        <p>Matsui also said that weather could have been a factor. ''Maybe to a certain extent, the weather might have been a factor, but the fact that that happened was maybe my responsibility for not being prepared for the season and that could have been a factor too,'' he said through an interpreter.</p>
        <p>He added: ''A lack of preparation might have been a factor. I can't pinpoint it. From my perspective, I gave it the best I can to prepare for the season, but the fact that this happened means that somewhere something wasn't right.''</p>
        <p>Matsui will travel with the team to Minnesota, where Thompson, a scrappy 27-year-old rookie, will join the team.</p>
        <p>Torre said Matsui's injury and the cold temperatures yesterday (it was 41 degrees at game time) scared him away from starting Johnny Damon, who strained his left calf muscle in the season opener. Damon was inserted as a defensive replacement in the top of the eighth inning and later had two hits. He said his calf felt fine.</p>
        <p>All three Yankees starters in the outfield (including right fielder Bobby Abreu, who strained his oblique in spring training) have gone down with some sort of injury so far. Bernie Williams, who played for the Yankees for 16 years, opted not to accept the team's invitation to spring training because he wanted a guaranteed contract. If Williams had decided to attend spring training, it is much more likely that he would be on the roster.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Cashman has made it clear that Williams is not an option to join the team and chose to go with the team's farm system to fill Matsui's spot in the outfield.</p>
        <p>''He is a hungry, tough right-handed bat,'' Cashman said of Thompson, who made his major league debut with the Yankees last June and played in 19 games in three stints with the team. ''He had a good spring training and he deserves the chance to go for the nod early. We have an all-left-handed-hitting lineup and based on what he did in the spring, it is the right move.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
