<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Fictional Video on MySpace Puts a TV Show's Promotion Into Hyperspace</title>
    <meta content="09sparkles" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/09/business/media/09sparkles.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839107"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">MySpace.com</org>
        <object.title class="online_producer">How I Met Your Mother (TV Program)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E7D7143FF93AA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1047" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Fictional Video on MySpace Puts a TV Show's Promotion Into Hyperspace</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Fictional Video on MySpace Puts a TV Show’s Promotion Into Hyperspace</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE RHODES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rhodes, Joe</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The MySpace page appeared in early November, one more online molecule in the endless social networking universe. It was a fan page with a hot pink background, a tribute to a one-hit Canadian teenage pop star from the early 1990s.</p>
        <p>''As Robin Sparkle's #1 Fan, it was my duty to create this page,'' read the copy in the About Me section. ''She's just so cute and her music is so great. She must be the greatest pop singer from Canada ever!'' Her featured hit song is called ''Let's Go to the Mall.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Remember Robin Sparkles? She exists only in a made-up MySpace page meant to promote the CBS sitcom “How I Met Your Mother.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The MySpace page appeared in early November, one more online molecule in the endless social networking universe. It was a fan page with a hot pink background, a tribute to a one-hit Canadian teenage pop star from the early 1990s.</p>
        <p>''As Robin Sparkle's #1 Fan, it was my duty to create this page,'' read the copy in the About Me section. ''She's just so cute and her music is so great. She must be the greatest pop singer from Canada ever!'' Her featured hit song is called ''Let's Go to the Mall.''</p>
        <p>It was just gushing enough to be real. But it wasn't. The Robin Sparkles MySpace page was a plant, concocted by the producers of the CBS sitcom ''How I Met Your Mother'' to play off a storyline in the show's Nov. 20 episode.</p>
        <p>During that episode, it was discovered that one of the main characters, an aspiring New York news anchor named Robin Scherbatsky (played by Cobie Smulders), has an embarrassing childhood secret: her teenage performances as Robin Sparkles. At the moment in the show when a character named Barney Stinson (played by Neil Patrick Harris) discovered a video of Sparkles online -- 21 minutes into the episode -- a streaming video went live on the Sparkles MySpace page, with 3 minutes and 20 seconds of clichéd pop music, big bouncy hair and bad synthesizers, not to mention lyrics like ''I'm going to rock your body 'til Canada Day.''</p>
        <p>By the next morning, the number of ''friends'' on the Robin Sparkles fan page had jumped from fewer than 100 to more than 5,000, and the video was one of the most viewed on both MySpace and YouTube. More important, the ratings for ''How I Met Your Mother'' jumped the next week, increasing by more than a million viewers in the age 18-to-34 demographic group. That gave the show, a critical favorite but a middling ratings success, its highest overall ratings of the season.</p>
        <p>The explanation, as far as Craig Thomas and Carter Bays, the show's 31-year-old co-creators and executive producers, were concerned, was the online brush fire.</p>
        <p>''One of our frustrations is that we're a younger-skewing show on an older-skewing network,'' said Mr. Thomas, sitting alongside Mr. Bays in the show's production office on the 20th Century Fox lot in West Los Angeles. ''We're more like an NBC Thursday night comedy, like 'The Office' or 'My Name Is Earl,' but we happen to be on CBS. So how do we let young people know about our show if they're not watching the other shows on the network?''</p>
        <p>He added that it seemed like a natural way to reach new people. ''People watched the video, linked to it, traded it around, sent it to friends, who end up watching the show the next week and are still with us. Without that, a lot of the younger viewers we have might not have found us.''</p>
        <p>Which is why, with May sweeps looming and rumors that ''How I Met Your Mother'' is in jeopardy, the show is again playing the MySpace card. Tonight's episode, ''The Bachelor Party,'' will use the show's storytelling premise: the series is the story told by a father to his children, 23 years in the future, about how he had met their mother -- yet to be identified -- back in the 2000s, chronicling his young-adult friendships and romances along the way.</p>
        <p>Tonight, though, as he spins the tale of his best friend's bachelor party, the narrative re-enactment stops at a hotel-room door, when the father realizes that, even in the year 2030, there is some information that a parent probably shouldn't share with his children.</p>
        <p>But the party scene, too racy for network television, will be available online, at the show's MySpace page and, eventually, at cbs.com. ''We'd like to get to the point,'' Mr. Bays said, ''where people will know that if they hear in the narration, 'but I can't tell you that part of the story,' then they'll know they should go looking for it online.''</p>
        <p>As network ratings drop and producers try to anticipate future revenue streams, Web-based promotions have become more important for television producers. While some shows have limited their Web offerings to posting deleted scenes or creating glorified press releases, show like ''Lost'' on ABC -- with its elaborate Web sites that play off the show's Dharma Initiative plot line, or ''Scrubs'' on NBC with frequent behind-the-scenes video podcasts -- have heavily courted online fans.</p>
        <p>''It allows you to activate the fan base, to turn them into advocates for your show,'' said Steven Melnick, senior vice president of marketing at 20th Century Fox television, which produces ''How I Met Your Mother.'' ''It's a priority for all of our shows, but some producers, like Carter and Craig, because of their age, really embrace it.''</p>
        <p>The writers have also given Mr. Harris's character a blog, which appears regularly on the CBS Web site as ''Barney's blog.'' Mr. Harris had a spell of slightly campy adolescent fame in the early 1990s on ''Doogie Howser, M.D.,'' where he played a prodigy who had become a doctor at a tender age.)</p>
        <p>''The Internet on one hand is competition, but we have to take advantage of any opportunity that can promote our shows, '' said Kelly Kahl, senior executive vice president at CBS. ''For this show in particular, we encourage them to think outside the norm.''</p>
        <p>Not that Mr. Bays or Mr. Thomas needs any prodding. The two started their writing careers on the staff of David Letterman's ''Late Show,'' where they foreshadowed the Robin Sparkles video by creating a fake boy band called Fresh-Step. The hoax was so effective that the band made an appearance on MTV's ''Total Request Live.''</p>
        <p>''The one thing we learned from Dave is that he was always looking for new ways to have fun interacting with the audience,'' Mr. Thomas said.</p>
        <p>''But we also don't want to forget what we're here to do, which is a television show,'' Mr. Bays said. ''Everything we've done online -- whether it's Barney's blog or the Robin Sparkles video -- has come organically from something going on in the show. It's great to have these things out there, but we don't do them just for the sake of doing them. There has to be a reason.''</p>
        <p>MEDIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
