<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bedard Gives Orioles an Outing Yanks Could Use</title>
    <meta content="09yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/09/sports/baseball/09yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839152"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Baltimore Orioles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Baltimore Orioles</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E0D7143FF93AA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="943" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bedard Gives Orioles an Outing Yanks Could Use</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bedard Gives Orioles an Outing Yanks Could Use</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID PICKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Picker, David</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Orioles starter Erik Bedard made it all look so easy. He retired 20 of the last 22 batters he faced yesterday, baffling the Yankees with a diet of breaking balls and fastballs.</p>
        <p>Watching such an impressive outing from an opposing starter may have been infuriating for the Yankees, who once again received a brief and ineffective start from one of their own. The latest disappointment was Darrell Rasner, a right-hander who lasted four and a third innings in a 6-4 loss to the Orioles at Yankee Stadium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The impressive start by the Oriole’s Erik Bedard may have been infuriating for the Yankees, who received a brief and ineffective outing from Darrell Rasner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Orioles starter Erik Bedard made it all look so easy. He retired 20 of the last 22 batters he faced yesterday, baffling the Yankees with a diet of breaking balls and fastballs.</p>
        <p>Watching such an impressive outing from an opposing starter may have been infuriating for the Yankees, who once again received a brief and ineffective start from one of their own. The latest disappointment was Darrell Rasner, a right-hander who lasted four and a third innings in a 6-4 loss to the Orioles at Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>The Yankees (2-3) have now been through their five-man rotation once, and no starter has reached the sixth inning. Carl Pavano went four and a third innings in the opener and was followed by Andy Pettitte's four innings, Mike Mussina's four and Kei Igawa's five.</p>
        <p>Still, Manager Joe Torre found some optimism. ''Considering where our starting pitching is right now, 2-3 isn't all that bad,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The early exits have made the bullpen work harder than Torre would prefer. But the relievers have held up, and yesterday was no exception. Pettitte even pitched an inning in relief, and he looked nothing like his fellow starters.</p>
        <p>Another unsettling trend continued yesterday. A magnetic resonance imaging exam showed that Hideki Matsui had a mild strain in his left hamstring. Matsui, who was regarded as the most durable player in Japan during his 10 seasons with the Yomiuri Giants, sustained the injury while running to first base Saturday.</p>
        <p>Matsui will be placed on the 15-day disabled list, a move that General Manager Brian Cashman called ''the safe route.''</p>
        <p>Rasner would not have even been in the rotation if Chien-Ming Wang were healthy. Rasner showed signs of promise last season, going 3-1 with the Yankees over the final weeks. But he was woeful yesterday, perhaps because of a blister that formed on the index finger of his pitching hand during the second inning.</p>
        <p>Rasner was shaky even though the Yankees took an early 3-0 lead. In the first inning, Bobby Abreu's sacrifice fly scored Melky Cabrera from third base. Alex Rodriguez then swung at the first pitch he saw with two outs and drilled it over the right-field fence for a two-run homer. It was his third home run in his past five at-bats.</p>
        <p>''We scored three runs off him, but it wasn't because he wasn't throwing strikes,'' Torre said of Bedard. ''He has a couple of different breaking balls. He's got a fastball that he can get in on the right-handers. He's the complete package.''</p>
        <p>While Bedard, a left-hander, settled down to pitch six scoreless innings, Rasner allowed Kevin Millar's two-run home run in the second inning. Paul Bako's three-run homer in the fourth, his first homer since 2004, gave the Orioles a 5-3 lead. The blister seemed to affect Rasner's off-speed pitches, but he said it caused no pain.</p>
        <p>''I'm not going to make any excuse,'' Rasner said. ''I was garbage today and I'll be better next time.''</p>
        <p>Rasner allowed five runs on eight hits, struck out two and walked two. He left the game to a smattering of boos mixed with cheers, the 47,679 fans apparently not sure what to make of him.</p>
        <p>It was that kind of day. The game-time temperature was 41 degrees, and the conditions were windy. In the bottom of the sixth inning, snow flurries began to fall and swirl around the stadium. Moments later, the sun peeked through the clouds.</p>
        <p>Torre said he thought the dryness that may have caused Rasner's blister was related to the weather.</p>
        <p>''But he battled through,'' Torre said. ''Unfortunately, two of the hits he gave up were five runs. It's really tough to overcome that.''</p>
        <p>Rasner left the game in the fifth inning with the Orioles leading, 5-3. Sean Henn inherited runners at first and second with one out but pitched out of the jam, thanks to a diving grab by Josh Phelps at first base to end the inning with the bases loaded.</p>
        <p>Very few people could have predicted the Yankees' next reliever. When the sixth inning began, Pettitte took the mound.</p>
        <p>Pettitte, who is scheduled to start tomorrow in Minnesota, planned on working on his mechanics yesterday. So he suggested to Torre that he could help out the bullpen by pitching an inning of relief instead. It was his first relief appearance since last July and his first with the Yankees since September 1998.</p>
        <p>Pettitte, who allowed four runs against the Tampa Bay Devil Rays on Thursday, threw 13 pitches yesterday, walking one batter and allowing no hits. Torre said the plan was for Pettitte to throw no more than 15 pitches.</p>
        <p>''We're short right now and I needed to throw today and I could,'' said Pettitte, who was greeted warmly by the crowd. ''So I told them I could throw an inning. I'm just glad I was able to give us an inning.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees used five relievers, and they combined for only one unearned run.</p>
        <p>The starters are hoping to somehow duplicate that success soon. After the game, Rasner spoke about his goal against the Orioles.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to come in today to take some strain off the bullpen, and I wasn't able to,'' Rasner said. ''So it's very frustrating.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Kevin Thompson, an outfielder, will be called up to replace Hideki Matsui, General Manager Brian Cashman said. Miguel Cairo started in place of Matsui yesterday and Melky Cabrera started instead of Johnny Damon, who strained his right calf in the opener. Damon entered the game as a defensive replacement in the eighth inning yesterday and said he expected to start the series opener tonight in Minnesota.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
