<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Paring Down a Drama to Basic Mortal Combat</title>
    <meta content="09black" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/09/theater/09black.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839111"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations/Manhattan Theater Club</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Manhattan Theater Club</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Harrower, David</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Daniels, Jeff</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mantello, Joe</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE7D7143FF93AA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1111" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Paring Down a Drama to Basic Mortal Combat</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Paring Down a Drama to Basic Mortal Combat</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELENA RYZIK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ryzik, Melena</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two months ago, as the winners of the Laurence Olivier Awards, Britain's version of the Tonys, were being announced in a posh hotel ballroom in London, the playwright David Harrower, one of the nominees, was sitting in his local pub in Glasgow, downing Guinness. His competition in the best new play category was so stiff -- including ''Frost/Nixon'' by Peter Morgan (screenwriter of ''The Queen'') and ''Rock 'n' Roll'' by Tom Stoppard, the favorite -- that he didn't see the point in making the trip.</p>
        <p>''I didn't want to go down there, put on a suit, get drunk, get the suit crumpled and fly back with nothing -- with a headache,'' Mr. Harrower said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>David Harrower, the author of the play “Blackbird,” a taut two-character drama about an illicit affair between a young woman and an older man, would seem the antithesis of a provocateur.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two months ago, as the winners of the Laurence Olivier Awards, Britain's version of the Tonys, were being announced in a posh hotel ballroom in London, the playwright David Harrower, one of the nominees, was sitting in his local pub in Glasgow, downing Guinness. His competition in the best new play category was so stiff -- including ''Frost/Nixon'' by Peter Morgan (screenwriter of ''The Queen'') and ''Rock 'n' Roll'' by Tom Stoppard, the favorite -- that he didn't see the point in making the trip.</p>
        <p>''I didn't want to go down there, put on a suit, get drunk, get the suit crumpled and fly back with nothing -- with a headache,'' Mr. Harrower said.</p>
        <p>Besides, ''it was a Sunday night,'' he said. ''Sunday night is drinking night.''</p>
        <p>And like the best drinking stories, this one has a twist: He won.</p>
        <p>The next morning he flew to New York, where ''Blackbird,'' a taut two-character drama about an illicit affair between a young woman and an older man, is having its American premiere. The production, directed by the Broadway veteran Joe Mantello, stars Alison Pill (''The Lieutenant of Inishmore'') and Jeff Daniels in his first New York stage role in more than a decade; it opens tomorrow at Manhattan Theater Club.</p>
        <p>Yes, Mr. Harrower said, he does kind of wish he'd gone to the ceremony. Winning ''shocked me, absolutely shocked me,'' he said last week, on his second trip across the Atlantic since the Olivier, a bronze bust of its namesake, has taken up residence on his mantel. The theatrical establishment was equally surprised: Not only was Mr. Harrower the dark horse, but ''Blackbird'' is not exactly audience (or award show) friendly.</p>
        <p>Set in a gray office conference room, where Ms. Pill's character confronts Mr. Daniels's long after their relationship ends, it deals unflinchingly with provocative subjects like sexual power plays, pedophilia and the dark pleasure of abusive relationships. Told in real time in spare, brusquely poetic language, it has a car-wreck effect that can leave audiences stunned into silence.</p>
        <p>Sitting in a restaurant in his Midtown hotel, dressed in a muted grey argyle sweater, Mr. Harrower, 40, with his shaven head and blond eyelashes, would seem the antithesis of a provocateur. He is soft-spoken and a little nervous, green enough to worry about seeming naïve and savvy enough to worry more about seeming pretentious. About the only thing that suggests his propensity for shock is the curse words that litter his conversation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harrower denied being part of the ''in yer face'' school, a group of young British playwrights like Sarah Kane and Mark Ravenhill who are known for their confrontational works and with whom he is sometimes lumped. ''I was always gentler,'' he said, ''and more pernicious.'' But this play, at least, was intended to scandalize. ''I want people shaken up,'' Mr. Harrower said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Daniels -- who rejected a dozen other theater projects to appear in ''Blackbird'' -- certainly was. ''It was just everything that I thought theater was supposed to be about, and so often isn't,'' Mr. Daniels said, in a telephone interview. ''As a play it seems to break rules. I didn't have a clue as to how I was going to pull it off, so I knew that every day at 8 o'clock I would be challenged.''</p>
        <p>The audience is too. ''It's supposed to assault them and pull them in at the same time, and that's a direct result of how David has phrased the play,'' Mr. Daniels said.</p>
        <p>The story is based on a newspaper account of a man who traveled abroad to meet a 19-year-old woman he had encountered in a chat room online, only to discover that in real life she was much younger. That the couple pursued the relationship anyway intrigued Mr. Harrower, but it was a difficult play to write. An early draft, written for the Edinburgh International Festival, with its comparatively large budgets, had 15 characters, four locations, the ghost of Marvin Gaye (don't ask) and a performance by a children's choir (ditto).</p>
        <p>''You kind of have to go to these stupid places, sort of, to get back,'' Mr. Harrower said ruefully. ''So I went there. And then a genocide happened.'' Exeunt a dozen characters. Though he'd labored over drafts for more than nine months, he wrote the final version of ''Blackbird'' in just four weeks.</p>
        <p>''It will never be that easy again,'' he said. ''It was something to do with the language as well. There's not much punctuation in it. I found that I couldn't do full stops, because they were too adamant, too finishing. The form kind of mirrors the uncertainty of people circling around each other. I couldn't use normal across-the-page stuff, so if you look at it, it's very sculpted. It looks rather beautiful, even if I say so myself.''</p>
        <p>The result onstage is a staccato, Mamet-like dialogue that unfolds slowly.</p>
        <p>''It was a revelation actually,'' Mr. Harrower said, ''because I don't usually write like that.''</p>
        <p>Born and raised in Edinburgh but now based in Glasgow, he had a stop-and-start-and-stop college education; he never graduated. Instead he worked some menial jobs (''I took dishwashing to a whole new level,'' he said) before sitting down, at 24, to become a writer. For two years he lived off unemployment checks and self-discipline, schooling himself with library books and working for eight hours a day.</p>
        <p>About a decade ago he had a breakthrough with ''Knives in Hens,'' another tersely worded play about a woman hemmed in by language. It won awards in Europe (though none in Britain, he noted), was translated into many languages and ran for three years in Germany. Several other plays followed, but Mr. Harrower winces when he talks about them; his adaptations -- Pirandello, Chekhov and Georg Büchner's ''Woyzeck'' -- were more successful than those original works in his view. Though he's creating television and film projects for the BBC, he prefers writing his own stuff for the stage. ''It's the only place where I can properly feel the voice that I hear in my head,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Of course the Olivier changed the way that echoes.</p>
        <p>''Someone sent me the list of previous winners'' (which includes Mr. Stoppard, Arthur Miller and Martin McDonagh), ''and I just thought -- this is going to sound a bit gauche -- but I just thought, 'I've written a play that stands with these,' '' Mr. Harrower said, still sounding awed and intimidated.</p>
        <p>''There's actually no enjoying of it,'' he said of the acclaim. ''Post-'Blackbird' I've got to rethink what I'm going to write about, what my style is, what my voice is. Now the pressure's on.'' Cue the cursing: ''The next one better be good.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
