<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Odd One Cometh (Can You Say Drama?)</title>
    <meta content="09wolf" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/09/arts/music/09wolf.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839118"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D7143FF93AA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="746" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Odd One Cometh (Can You Say Drama?)</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Odd One Cometh (Can You Say Drama?)</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KELEFA SANNEH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanneh, Kelefa</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Patrick Wolf is only 23, but already he is one of Britain's most appealing young singer-songwriters. He's a disco-obsessed virtuoso who can (it appears) play just about every instrument in the orchestra; a canny and uncanny performer who has long seemed destined for pop stardom or some weird variant of it.</p>
        <p>The British have been enjoying him for years, and now it's America's turn to reckon with Mr. Wolf. (No doubt he would appreciate that honorific, which makes his stage name even stagier.) His breakthrough third album, ''The Magic Position'' (Fontana Universal), is to be released here on May 1, and he came to town for three New York gigs -- Thursday, Friday and Saturday -- intended to get Americans talking.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Patrick Wolf is only 23, but already he is one of Britain’s most appealing young singer-songwriters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Patrick Wolf is only 23, but already he is one of Britain's most appealing young singer-songwriters. He's a disco-obsessed virtuoso who can (it appears) play just about every instrument in the orchestra; a canny and uncanny performer who has long seemed destined for pop stardom or some weird variant of it.</p>
        <p>The British have been enjoying him for years, and now it's America's turn to reckon with Mr. Wolf. (No doubt he would appreciate that honorific, which makes his stage name even stagier.) His breakthrough third album, ''The Magic Position'' (Fontana Universal), is to be released here on May 1, and he came to town for three New York gigs -- Thursday, Friday and Saturday -- intended to get Americans talking.</p>
        <p>Certainly the trip has succeeded, although perhaps not exactly the way Mr. Wolf wanted. On Saturday night he performed at the MisShapes party, at Don Hill's in the South Village, and from all reports it was a chaotic night. By Sunday morning those of us who missed it could read about it online. It had already become part of the Patrick Wolf legend: Among many other things, he would now be known as the guy who had his own drummer ejected for -- how to put it? -- insufficient consciousness. Twice.</p>
        <p>From one of the first online reviews, posted a few hours later at move.livejournal.com: ''Patrick threw a cymbal stand at the drummer's head, and at that point I realized that what I thought was just an act was actually a band blowing up onstage during the middle of a packed performance. Patrick continued to yell at the drummer and told him he was fired (can you say drama?) and had security escort the drummer off the stage.'' Apparently the drummer returned, only to be met by the same escort. No doubt videos will be available on YouTube by the time you read this.</p>
        <p>By comparison Friday's concert at Studio B in Greenpoint, Brooklyn, was downright tranquil; the only flare-ups were musical. Accompanied by a violist (who sometimes switched to violin), a double-bassist, an electronics wrangler and, yes, that soon-to-be-infamous drummer, Mr. Wolf spent half an hour squeezing a big performance onto a small stage. It's hard to gawk and dance at the same time, but some audience members certainly tried.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolf kept moving: jumping behind a keyboard, strumming a ukulele or just prowling the stage; he's skinny and sly, and looks as if he were slithering even when he's standing still. When he sang ''Overture,'' the sumptuous first song from ''The Magic Position,'' he sounded like a singularly untrustworthy dentist, purring, ''Come on, love, open wide/Open up now/Don't you think it's time?''</p>
        <p>''The Magic Position'' is seductive and utterly confounding: bathetic piano ballads take their place alongside saw-toothed electronic experiments, but you're never more than a few minutes removed from a gleaming pop song. Friday's set included a glorious, pizzicato-driven version of ''Get Lost,'' and a grand version of ''Bluebells,'' complete with a dramatic -- that is, planned -- onstage collapse.</p>
        <p>Near the end came the album's title track, which is probably what most excited the executives at Universal Records. It's one of those songs that seem destined to take on lives of their own: a giddy and infernally catchy expression of lovesick optimism. Mr. Wolf sings, ''You put me in the magic position/To live, to learn, to love in the major key,'' and the strings echo the thought by playing a major scale.</p>
        <p>On Friday the band sounded a bit ragtag (though it could have been worse, as Mr. Wolf discovered soon enough), but the singer never did. Who knows if he'll ever have the chance to give a triumphant New York performance at a major concert hall, backed by a full orchestra and band and an elaborate stage show, but suffice it to say a big budget wouldn't be wasted on him.</p>
        <p>But even on a cramped stage with a skeletal band, he's plenty fierce, as one drummer and many fans found out this weekend. Before Friday's performance, the M.C. pronounced herself smitten with him then said it was ''devastating that he is gay and he won't like me.''</p>
        <p>Hmm. That seemed like a strange thing to say about a performer as coy as Mr. Wolf. And sure enough, during his set, he got his revenge. He dedicated an older song, ''The Libertine,'' to her. And he added, ''I think the lady needs to spend a night with me before she makes personal judgments.''</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
