<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Finishing a Long Trip That Began With Chicken Wings and the Prairie Golf Tour</title>
    <meta content="09link" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/09/sports/golf/09link.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839184"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Sabbatini, Rory</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Goosen, Retief</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E0D6143FF93AA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="655" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Finishing a Long Trip That Began With Chicken Wings and the Prairie Golf Tour</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Johnson Goes From Chicken Wings to Masters Champion</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hack, Damon</byline>
      <dateline>AUGUSTA, Ga., April 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Before Zach Johnson became a Masters champion, he was a golfer chasing titles sponsored by Hooters.</p>
        <p>''Chicken wings and everything,'' Johnson said Sunday, wearing his green jacket after winning the Masters by two shots over Tiger Woods, Retief Goosen and Rory Sabbatini. ''I thought those were the best days of my life.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Before Zach Johnson became the unexpected Masters champion at Augusta on Sunday, he was chasing titles sponsored by Hooters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Before Zach Johnson became a Masters champion, he was a golfer chasing titles sponsored by Hooters.</p>
        <p>''Chicken wings and everything,'' Johnson said Sunday, wearing his green jacket after winning the Masters by two shots over Tiger Woods, Retief Goosen and Rory Sabbatini. ''I thought those were the best days of my life.''</p>
        <p>Johnson, who grew up in Cedar Rapids, Iowa, almost never made it off the Hooters Tour.</p>
        <p>Like countless golfers before him, Johnson, 31, needed financial aid from friends and sponsors to supplement his talent. He bounced around in small towns and hamlets, scraping out a living as best he could.</p>
        <p>''I graduated from Drake in 1998 and I didn't have any money,'' he said. ''I had to find financial backing, and a bunch of gentlemen and their wives backed me for the mini tours and off I went.</p>
        <p>''I got better and better every year and, looking back on it, it's amazing where I came from.''</p>
        <p>Johnson, whose first full year on the PGA Tour was 2004, is more well-known than Ben Curtis and Shaun Micheel were when they won majors in 2003, but he also has a well-traveled, underdog biography.</p>
        <p>In 1998, he played on the Prairie Golf Tour, winning once and finishing sixth on the money list.</p>
        <p>The following year, he earned $945 playing two Nationwide events and followed it up by winning $10,280 in 2000.</p>
        <p>He was beginning to find traction in a sport that sends many professional golfers to different endeavors.</p>
        <p>''I really didn't want to go back to school,'' he said. ''I really didn't want to get a job. The one thing that I clinged to was the fact that every year, as a junior in high school, and then in college, I improved. I felt like, if I get the necessary finances, I'm going to give this a shot for two or three years and see where things go. I worked hard.''</p>
        <p>Along the way, he met others in similar straits. Vaughn Taylor, the Augusta native who finished tied for 10th, also played with Johnson on the mini tours.</p>
        <p>They played in the same group Sunday and were Ryder Cup teammates last year.</p>
        <p>''I told him to finish strong,'' Taylor said. ''Somewhere along the way he got it into another gear. Where he's improved is his putting. His attitude is one of the best out there, his aura, his outlook on life.''</p>
        <p>Of Johnson outplaying Woods in the final round, Taylor said: ''Tiger has an amazing record in majors. It's nice to see him give one up. If he's not Superman, Superman's brother, maybe.''</p>
        <p>In overcoming Woods and the field, Johnson played the four par 5s in 11 under par despite not going for any green in two shots.</p>
        <p>He won $1.305 million, his largest check, and has gone from needing financial backing to earning $8.38 million on the PGA Tour.</p>
        <p>''One of the first places I played? Lincoln, Neb.,'' he said. ''The Prairie Tour. I remember the first check. First place was $2,500, $3,000, something like that. My parents still have it in my room at home.''</p>
        <p>HOLE IN ONE FOR 102-YEAR-OLD -- Elsie McLean thought she might have lost her ball on the par-3, 100-yard fourth hole at Bidwell Park in Chico, Calif. Instead, the 102-year-old McLean became the oldest golfer to make a hole in one on a regulation course. Because of the slope of the green, McLean and her partners could not see where her ball landed after she teed off. Then they found it in the cup.</p>
        <p>''I said: 'Oh, my Lord! It can't be true. It can't be true,' '' McLean told television station KNVN. It was McLean's first ace. McLean, who used a driver, broke the age record of 101 set by Harold Stilson in 2001 at Deerfield Country Club in Florida.</p>
        <p>''For an old lady,'' she said, ''I still hit the ball pretty good.'' (AP)</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
