<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Advantage for Americans In Davis Cup Camaraderie</title>
    <meta content="09tennis" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/09/sports/tennis/09tennis.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839208"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina/Winston-Salem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Davis Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Davis Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Winston-Salem (NC)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Roddick, Andy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E5DF153FF93AA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="742" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Advantage for Americans In Davis Cup Camaraderie</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Roddick Is Putting It All on Line for the Davis Cup</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIV BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Viv</byline>
      <dateline>WINSTON-SALEM, N.C., April 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After Andy Roddick strained a hamstring in Miami in late March, the safe move might have been to lay low for a few weeks, rest his leg for the coming clay-court season and skip the Davis Cup match between the United States and Spain this past weekend.</p>
        <p>Roddick did not play it safe, though.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Andy Roddick and the other United States players have set aside self-interest to try to win the Davis Cup for the first time since 1995.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After Andy Roddick strained a hamstring in Miami in late March, the safe move might have been to lay low for a few weeks, rest his leg for the coming clay-court season and skip the Davis Cup match between the United States and Spain this past weekend.</p>
        <p>Roddick did not play it safe, though.</p>
        <p>''Probably be safer,'' he acknowledged after arriving here, ''but at this time Davis Cup is one of my biggest priorities and I want to be here. If I can go out and try to get a win, then I'm going to try to do that.''</p>
        <p>It was not just talk for the cameras. Roddick played through the injury and won his singles match against Fernando Verdasco on Friday to help the United States to a 4-1 victory against Spain and a berth in the semifinals against Sweden in September.</p>
        <p>With the quarterfinal already clinched, Roddick rested Sunday as the doubles regular, Bob Bryan, took his place at Lawrence Joel Veterans Memorial Coliseum and fell to Tommy Robredo, 6-4, 6-4. James Blake won the other match Sunday, beating Feliciano López by 6-3, 7-6 (3).</p>
        <p>But when the quarterfinal was at stake, Roddick's commitment made clear why this United States team believes it can win the Davis Cup for the first time since 1995.</p>
        <p>''I see Andy Roddick as the single biggest Davis Cup warrior today,'' said Arlen Kantarian, chief executive of professional tennis for the United States Tennis Association. ''He's not going to let any nicks and bruises stop him from helping his team win.''</p>
        <p>That mentality has taken over this team. The players have set aside their self-interest and found a way to bond for a single goal. Roddick, Blake and the doubles pair of Bob and Mike Bryan, have become friends over time, along with the singles players Mardy Fish and Sam Querrey, who showed up here just to contribute as backups and hitting partners in practice.</p>
        <p>And having been brought along together by the team captain, Patrick McEnroe, over the past few years, they are now committed to winning the Davis Cup together.</p>
        <p>''This group is a band of brothers, and these are guys that hold each other accountable to each other,'' Kantarian said. ''Really, I give credit to Patrick in terms of building that camaraderie. In what is an historically individual sport, to see a group of guys come together with this kind of team that would take a bullet for each other is just tremendous for us all to see.''</p>
        <p>Not every American team has been so committed to each other or to the Davis Cup in the past. As McEnroe said: ''There's been different times where maybe some of the top players in the U.S., they weren't enemies, but they weren't great friends.</p>
        <p>''These guys don't feel like Davis Cup is a burden.''</p>
        <p>It is an issue for other countries, too. Consider Spain, which arrived in Winston-Salem without its top player, Rafael Nadal. He chose to rest a foot injury while preparing for the clay-court season rather than play on the fast, hard surface here. How much difference might Nadal have made? In 2004, he defeated Roddick in a crucial match as Spain defeated the United States in the Davis Cup finals.</p>
        <p>''You know, it's definitely tougher on your body,'' Blake said after his victory against Robredo on Friday. ''I've never reached the pinnacle of any team accomplishment. I was thinking about it just a few months ago, about the fact that I never won an N.C.A.A. championship as a team. I never won a high school championship as a team. Now to have a chance to do it at the top level would mean the world to me, especially since this team, as I said before, feels like family. We do everything together.''</p>
        <p>Of course, none of that bonding guarantees victory against Sweden in the semifinals. A lot can happen between now and September. But McEnroe said he liked his chances.</p>
        <p>''I mean, we feel good,'' he said.</p>
        <p>RUSSIA ADVANCES -- Marat Safin defeated Paul-Henri Mathieu, 7-6 (3), 6-3, 6-2, in the decisive singles match Sunday to send Russia, the defending champion, past France, 3-2, for a spot in the Davis Cup semifinals.</p>
        <p>Russia will play Germany in the semifinals in September.</p>
        <p>Russia entered play ahead by 2-1 in the best-of-five quarterfinal. Sébastien Grosjean tied it for France by beating Igor Andreev, 7-5, 4-6, 2-6, 6-3, 6-4. (AP)</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
