<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Soldier's Captors Say They Gave List of Demands to Israel</title>
    <meta content="09mideast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/09/world/middleeast/09mideast.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839144"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">West Bank</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Egypt</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hamas</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fatah</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Medina, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shalit, Gilad (Cpl)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barghouti, Marwan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saadat, Ahmed</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Political Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Israel</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Hamas</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E2D7143FF93AA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="902" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Soldier's Captors Say They Gave List of Demands to Israel</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Soldier’s Captors Say They Gave List of Demands to Israel</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER MEDINA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Medina, Jennifer</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, April 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Spokesman for Hamas militants who seized and have held captive Israeli soldier for last 10 months says they sent Israeli officials list of Palestinian prisoners they would demand released in exchange for freeing him; says list, sent through Egyptian mediators, is sign of progress for Israeli soldier, Cpl Gilad Shalit; list of 450 names is said to include Marwan Barghouti, leader of Fatah faction and former leader of Fatah militia in West Bank; he was sentenced in 2002 to five life sentences for his role in deaths of four Israelis and foreigner; given his high profile in intifada, it would be very difficult for Israel to release him; also said to be on list is Ahmed Saadat, leader of Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine, accused of coordinating assassination of Israeli tourism minister in 2001; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hamas militants involved in seizing an Israeli soldier whom they have held captive for 10 months said over the weekend that they had sent Israeli officials, through Egyptian mediators, a list of Palestinian prisoners they would demand released in exchange for freeing him.</p>
        <p>Reports in the Israeli news media quote unidentified Israeli government officials as saying that they had received the list and would review it, but a spokesman for the prime minister's office would not confirm the reports.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hamas militants said they sent Israel a list of prisoners they want released in exchange for Cpl. Gilad Shalit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hamas militants involved in seizing an Israeli soldier whom they have held captive for 10 months said over the weekend that they had sent Israeli officials, through Egyptian mediators, a list of Palestinian prisoners they would demand released in exchange for freeing him.</p>
        <p>Reports in the Israeli news media quote unidentified Israeli government officials as saying that they had received the list and would review it, but a spokesman for the prime minister's office would not confirm the reports.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Hamas, Fawzi Barhoum, said that the list was a sign of progress in the release of the soldier, Cpl. Gilad Shalit, who was captured by Hamas and two other militant groups in a raid into Israel last June.</p>
        <p>''The names have been presented to the Egyptian mediators, who in turn have presented it to the Israeli side,'' Mr. Barhoum said Sunday. ''There is a clear progress in the fact a list of names has been presented.''</p>
        <p>The list of about 450 names, according to the news reports, included Marwan Barghouti, a grass-roots leader of the Fatah faction and former leader of the Tanzim, a Fatah militia, in the West Bank. He was sentenced in 2002 to five life sentences for his role in the deaths of four Israelis and a foreigner. The list also reportedly included Ahmed Saadat, the leader of the Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine, who is accused of coordinating the assassination of an Israeli tourism minister in 2001.</p>
        <p>The Palestinian Authority information minister, Mustafa Barghouti, a distant relation of Marwan Barghouti, said on Saturday that ''practical measures'' to begin a prisoner exchange with Israel had begun.</p>
        <p>''The Palestinians have done all they can regarding this case, and the ball is now in the Israeli court,'' Mustafa Barghouti said. ''Israel will now decide how quick the prisoners and Shalit will return home. If the Israeli government is serious in its intentions, it must seize the opportunity to end this chapter.''</p>
        <p>The Israeli government is always reluctant to release prisoners who have been convicted of killing Israelis. Israel Radio reported on Sunday that Prime Minister Ehud Olmert would convene a meeting with his security cabinet this week to discuss the standards to determine how Palestinian prisoners could be released in a deal to free Corporal Shalit.</p>
        <p>In an interview with Army Radio, Issac Herzog, the social service minister and a member of the security cabinet, said the government would consider being flexible, but cautioned that a deal was not imminent. ''Regarding the negotiations, I think we should use original thinking,'' he said. ''I understand there has been progress compared to what we have seen until now. Nevertheless, I would refrain from celebrating just yet.''</p>
        <p>The news of the list comes just days after news reports that Corporal Shalit had received a pair of eyeglasses sent to him by his father. But Israeli officials said they had no confirmation. On Sunday, Burham Hammad, the Egyptian security envoy in Gaza, denied the news reports, saying they were ''nothing but speculation.''</p>
        <p>Egypt has spent several months trying to hammer out a deal to release Corporal Shalit, but has apparently been blocked by disagreements over the type and number of prisoners to be exchanged, and the order in which they and the Israeli soldier would be released. Talks of the imminent release of Corporal Shalit have surfaced before. In December, Hamas members said that he could be released ''very soon.''</p>
        <p>Given Marwan Barghouti's high profile in the intifada that began in 2000, it would be especially difficult for Israel to release him. Gideon Ezra, a member of the majority coalition in Parliament and former deputy director of the Israeli secret service, had said several months ago that the government should consider releasing Mr. Barghouti in order to empower Mahmoud Abbas, the Palestinian president and Fatah leader, over Hamas, with which Fatah shares the new unity government. But the situation has changed significantly since then, he said in a telephone interview Sunday.</p>
        <p>''There is a Palestinian unity government that has to be dealt with, and I am not sure what the best solution is,'' he said. ''I am sure the leadership in Israel will consider very carefully to know who, when and how prisoners will be released.''</p>
        <p>Israel has released prisoners in exchange for captured soldiers in the past -- most recently in 2004. As of last November, Israel had 9,075 Palestinians in custody, including 345 minors, according to the independent Israeli human rights group B'Tselem.</p>
        <p>Also on Sunday, a Palestinian teenager stabbed two Israeli border policemen in the West Bank city of Hebron, near the Tomb of the Patriarchs, and was then shot by another Israeli officer. An Israeli Army spokesman said that the youth, who is 17, approached the officers with a knife near a checkpoint there. He had moderately serious wounds in his leg, Israeli officials said. An army spokesman said that one of the policemen had moderately severe wounds in his abdomen.</p>
        <p>Tensions in Hebron have risen in the last several weeks as Jewish settlers took over a house there, which they say was legally purchased, but were ordered to evacuate later this month. The tomb, thought to be the burial ground of Abraham, also contains a mosque and is a holy site for Jews and Muslims. A popular site for pilgrims, it is closed to Muslim worshipers during the Passover holiday, which ends Monday night.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
