<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sit Back, Button Up And Enjoy the Show</title>
    <meta content="09vecsey" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/09/sports/baseball/09vecsey.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839187"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Atlanta Braves</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E0D6143FF93AA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="850" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sit Back, Button Up And Enjoy the Show</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sit Back, Button Up and Enjoy the Show</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wear double socks. That is my only warning about venturing out to a ballpark in much of North America in the next few days. Otherwise, the baseball season, now more than a week old, is just fine.</p>
        <p>After the torpor of spring training, I finally had the occasion to witness a regular-season game yesterday, a 3-2 victory by the home team over the Mets, preparatory to the Mets' home opener at Shea Stadium today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Aside from the chilly weather, the baseball season, now more than a week old, is just fine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Wear double socks. That is my only warning about venturing out to a ballpark in much of North America in the next few days. Otherwise, the baseball season, now more than a week old, is just fine.</p>
        <p>After the torpor of spring training, I finally had the occasion to witness a regular-season game yesterday, a 3-2 victory by the home team over the Mets, preparatory to the Mets' home opener at Shea Stadium today.</p>
        <p>As chilly as the weather is currently in the South, it was delightful to sit in the sun and watch Andruw Jones glide after eight fly balls and catch them under a cloudless sky. There were other issues and agendas in the game, but Jones's perfect control of the outfield was a delight.</p>
        <p>Even the players seemed to appreciate the sunny side of life. Kyle Davies, who last Monday was pitching in a simulated game for the Braves' farm team in Rome, Ga., pitched six and two-thirds innings yesterday to keep the varsity in the game and himself in the major leagues. He said it was nice that the Braves have a 5-1 record after the first week of the season.</p>
        <p>Aaron Heilman, who gave up two runs -- and the game -- in relief decided that the Mets had a good trip with their 4-2 record before heading home to meet the Philadelphia Phillies today.</p>
        <p>I would agree with both of them. After a romp through the lush plantings of Augusta National on Thursday, I was also happy to watch this familiar pageant on the green, green grass of Turner Field.</p>
        <p>Three members of my family and I took advantage of a nice offer from Dr. Philip Weiss, a pediatrician in Atlanta, to use his seats in the first row, right over the tarpaulin past first base.</p>
        <p>With the temperature struggling to reach 50, I wouldn't have wanted to be in the shade, but down low, below the breeze, it was pleasant in the sun. Plus, baseball is so much better when the players are close enough to seem like human beings rather than blips in a video game.</p>
        <p>Without being prompted by the television screen or broadcasters, we could, on our own, observe crafty old Orlando Hernández twitching his shoulders and sometimes slapping his glove on his raised left leg before delivering the ball from a variety of angles.</p>
        <p>El Duque gave up one run in six innings and might have won the game if the Mets could have kept the ball away from Andruw Jones.</p>
        <p>Instead, Jones snuffed out rallies before they could begin. His first catch was the best. In the second inning, David Wright lashed a drive toward the gap in right-center, but Jones ran it down, elevating himself and then seeming to lift his left, gloved hand in midair, to make a one-handed catch.</p>
        <p>In the third inning, José Valentín lofted a high fly ball to center, and Jones held his glove over his left eye so he would not be blinded by the sun. In the fourth, he effortlessly glided back to catch Wright's fly ball. In the sixth, Jones raced over toward left field to make the catch near Ryan Langerhans, then flipped the ball into the stands. In the ninth, he barely moved as he snagged a ball from Shawn Green.</p>
        <p>''On a day like today, it's hard,'' Braves Manager Bobby Cox said after the game, referring to the sun and the breeze. ''Sometimes we take him for granted. He also knows how to position our other outfielders. He's been doing it for years. He makes our jobs much easier.''</p>
        <p>Jones appears stocky, at 6-foot-1 and 210 pounds, but he is deceptively graceful. Amazingly, he is still two weeks shy of his 30th birthday. It just seems that he has been around forever, since he gave the Braves a lead in the 1996 World Series with two homers in the first game in Yankee Stadium. It is widely believed the Braves will not be able to keep him when his contract runs out after this season, qualifying him for the highest level of salary.</p>
        <p>For now, he is a Brave, the one chosen to wear No. 42 in honor of Jackie Robinson in the commemoration next Sunday.</p>
        <p>The rest of the day's show was nice, in this national city where corporate transplants have broadened the accents and the rooting interests. Northern voices and Mets orange and blue were evident all over Turner Field. A dozen other people behind left field wore Easter bunny outfits -- or maybe they were just cold.</p>
        <p>Maybe it was the holiday, but the mood in the ballpark was relatively benign, with fewer witless sound effects and decibels than usual. Even the music had a nice touch -- I noticed ''A-Tisket, A-Tasket'' by Ella Fitzgerald and ''Money'' by Yoko Ono, two voices you don't hear very often in the cacophony of ballparks.</p>
        <p>No doubt it was be noisier today in crowded Shea Stadium. But the main thing, after an up-close inspection, is that baseball is back. How did we go five months without it?</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
