<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets Leave Plenty Of Missed Chances On Plate and Mound</title>
    <meta content="09mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/09/sports/baseball/09mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839186"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Atlanta Braves</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E0D6143FF93AA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="924" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets Leave Plenty Of Missed Chances On Plate and Mound</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mets Leave Plenty of Missed Chances on Plate and Mound</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shpigel, Ben</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, April 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As his teammates rushed around the clubhouse packing bags and tying ties, Aaron Heilman remained in uniform in front of a laptop computer, his head resting on his right hand, dissecting the sequence of events that turned an eighth-inning lead into a two-game losing streak.</p>
        <p>''Kind of seeing if what I was seeing out there was the same as what I thought I was seeing,'' Heilman said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Braves tagged Aaron Heilman for two runs in the eighth inning, sending the Mets back to New York for their home opener with two consecutive losses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As his teammates rushed around the clubhouse packing bags and tying ties, Aaron Heilman remained in uniform in front of a laptop computer, his head resting on his right hand, dissecting the sequence of events that turned an eighth-inning lead into a two-game losing streak.</p>
        <p>''Kind of seeing if what I was seeing out there was the same as what I thought I was seeing,'' Heilman said.</p>
        <p>And what Heilman concluded about his pitching equaled the general feeling about the Mets' season-opening trip: It was good, but could have been better.</p>
        <p>The Braves tagged Heilman for two runs in the eighth inning on Sunday afternoon to squeak by with a 3-2 victory at Turner Field and send the Mets back to New York unsatisfied heading into Monday's home opener against the Phillies.</p>
        <p>After beginning their tour of expected National League contenders with four consecutive victories, the Mets dropped their last two games, the product of missed opportunities at the plate and on the mound. They scored their only two runs Sunday on back-to-back homers in the second inning, by Shawn Green and Ramón Castro, and were 0 for 8 with runners in scoring position. José Reyes was left stranded at third base twice, once with no outs. In the seventh and eighth innings, the Mets could not capitalize with two runners on base.</p>
        <p>''We gave away a couple games,'' Manager Willie Randolph said.</p>
        <p>The Braves, meanwhile, were more than happy to accept the housewarming gifts. If the Mets left St. Louis thinking that the Cardinals had to be better than how they played in getting embarrassed in a three-game sweep, then they left here thinking that the Braves are much improved and will pose a threat all season long.</p>
        <p>''Not every day's going to be a party day for us,'' Carlos Beltrán said. ''We're going to have to be up for the challenge. The Braves have a great team.''</p>
        <p>But the Mets also left encouraged by their starting pitching -- their first four starters, at least; the fifth starter, Mike Pelfrey will debut on Friday -- and the resurgence of Green, who went 5 for 12 this series to raise his average to .375. And they went 4-2 in the first week with their cleanup hitter, Carlos Delgado, who struck out in his first three at-bats Sunday, batting .185.</p>
        <p>The loss spoiled another strong start by Orlando Hernández, who, coming off his strong start Tuesday in St. Louis, allowed one run on two hits in six innings, and that came on a first-pitch home run by Kelly Johnson, the first batter he faced. With that out of his system, Hernández retired the next eight hitters and 12 of 13, bewildering them in his customary how-did-he-do-that fashion.</p>
        <p>When he struck out Andruw Jones in the fourth, the speed of his five pitches ranged from 69 miles an hour to 89, and the final pitch was a 75-m.p.h. changeup. In 13 innings this season, Hernández has allowed two runs on seven hits for a 1.38 earned run average.</p>
        <p>''I had more confidence today on the mound,'' Hernández said. ''Everything was working for every hitter.''</p>
        <p>But with the Mets leading by 2-1 with two outs and a runner on base in the seventh, Randolph pulled Hernández for a pinch-hitter. Scott Schoeneweis replaced Hernández and, in 12 pitches, retired two hitters but also allowed a single and issued a walk. With the right-handed-hitting Édgar Rentería due up, Randolph called on Heilman to finish the job. It could have been an opportunity for the right-handed specialist Joe Smith, but he had pitched the previous two games. And besides, there has been no better reliever in the early going at defusing precarious situations than Heilman.</p>
        <p>In his first outing, on opening night, Heilman came in with the bases loaded and one out and induced a double play. Two nights later, he got Albert Pujols to fly out with runners on first and third. On Sunday, Heilman got Rentería to ground out to end the seventh and then was the obvious choice to face the middle of the Braves' order and bridge the innings to closer Billy Wagner.</p>
        <p>It is challenging for a reliever to enter a pressure situation, cool off in the dugout and then come out to start the next inning, and Chipper Jones took advantage by hitting a middle-in fastball to the fence in right-center field for a leadoff double.</p>
        <p>''It was up more than I wanted it to be, but it wasn't a bad pitch,'' Heilman said.</p>
        <p>After Andruw Jones struck out, the hot-hitting Brian McCann sliced an outside fastball down the left-field line to drive in the tying run.</p>
        <p>''That was the mistake,'' Heilman said.</p>
        <p>The next hitter, Jeff Francoeur, poked a double to shallow right, scoring the pinch-runner Brayan Peña with the go-ahead run. They were the first two runs given up by the Mets' bullpen this season, and when discussing them afterward, Heilman could have been speaking for the team.</p>
        <p>''I felt better than the results that I got,'' Heilman said.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The often-injured Braves starter Mike Hampton felt soreness in his reconstructed left elbow while throwing a bullpen session Sunday morning and will be evaluated in New York on Monday by the Mets' medical director, Dr. David Altchek, who performed Tommy John surgery on Hampton in September 2005. Hampton did not pitch a game during spring training after straining his left oblique muscle.  David Wright extended his hitting streak to 18 games over two seasons with his eighth-inning single.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
