<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Latest Real Estate Drama in the Hamptons Is About Newspaper Turf</title>
    <meta content="09hamptons" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/09/business/media/09hamptons.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839134"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Long Island/Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/The Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Hamptons (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">East Hampton Star</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Southampton Press</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E3D7143FF93AA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1318" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Latest Real Estate Drama in the Hamptons Is About Newspaper Turf</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Latest Real Estate Drama in the Hamptons Is About Newspaper Turf</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARIA ASPAN</byline>
      <dateline>EAST HAMPTON, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a recent Saturday morning in the offices of The East Hampton Star, the low moan of a fire siren came through an open window and David E. Rattray, the newspaper's editor, sprang into action. Swiveling in his chair to his police scanner, he learned about a fire at a local retirement community and quickly called a photographer.</p>
        <p>True, no glamorous people were threatened, but it was bread-and-butter news for The Star, a favorite local institution long before the Hamptons became shorthand for East Coast high society. Founded in 1885, it has been run by the Rattray family since 1935.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The introduction of The East Hampton Press as a competitor to The East Hampton Star involves a dynastic rivalry between its two owners.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a recent Saturday morning in the offices of The East Hampton Star, the low moan of a fire siren came through an open window and David E. Rattray, the newspaper's editor, sprang into action. Swiveling in his chair to his police scanner, he learned about a fire at a local retirement community and quickly called a photographer.</p>
        <p>True, no glamorous people were threatened, but it was bread-and-butter news for The Star, a favorite local institution long before the Hamptons became shorthand for East Coast high society. Founded in 1885, it has been run by the Rattray family since 1935.</p>
        <p>This week, perhaps the biggest story in the Hamptons involves the paper itself. On Wednesday, The Southampton Press, the venerable paper one town over that belongs to the Louchheim family, will introduce a direct competitor, The East Hampton Press, which will come out a day earlier than The Star and will be free (The Star costs $1). Until now, the neighboring papers, both weekly broadsheets, had largely stuck to their turfs.</p>
        <p>''It's a newspaper war,'' said Jerry Della Femina, the advertising executive who owns the Della Femina restaurant in East Hampton and a free local tabloid, The Independent. ''It's two great local newspaper families, and they're about to clash.''</p>
        <p>On a journalistic level, this is not quite the tabloid battle between The New York Post and The Daily News, or even its summer-share equivalent. The papers have tiny circulations, although their readerships include many of the boldface names who make their homes (at least occasionally) in the Hamptons.</p>
        <p>However, there is the element of a dynastic rivalry between the two owners, and the fairly large sums of money to be made in real estate advertising in the Hamptons.</p>
        <p>''It's a company town,'' said Mr. Rattray, the son of the current publisher, Helen S. Rattray, and the fifth person in his family to edit The East Hampton Star. ''One way or another, pretty much everything is tied to the real estate industry.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rattray, 43, attended elementary school with Joseph Louchheim, 42, the publisher and owner of the Press Newspaper Group, whose flagship paper is The Southampton Press. Mr. Louchheim bought the paper in 1997 from his father, Donald Louchheim, a former reporter who purchased it in the early 1970s. Joseph Louchheim calls reports of tension ''a little overblown'' and says he has no desire to put The Star out of business.</p>
        <p>''The Star's probably one of the best papers in the state,'' he said. ''For me to go in there and compete against them on that front would be suicidal.''</p>
        <p>Then why come out a day earlier, at no charge?</p>
        <p>''We're a start-up in an area with an extremely dominant player,'' Mr. Louchheim said, adding that the new paper may not be free indefinitely. He has bought advertising for The East Hampton Press, including a television commercial that is posted on YouTube.</p>
        <p>When asked about the new competition, Mr. Rattray at first declined to field questions about it, and hung up twice on this reporter during a scheduled telephone interview. Then he came around.</p>
        <p>''We've seen them come and we've seen them go, and we've been here 121 years,'' Mr. Rattray said, before allowing that he was ''a little annoyed, obviously.''</p>
        <p>The East Hampton Star has already weathered plenty of storms, including takeover attempts, downturns in the newspaper business and a constant deluge of free publications. In addition to the well-established weeklies like Dan's Papers and The Independent, some of the freebies include glossy magazines published by real estate agents to showcase multimillion-dollar estates.</p>
        <p>In addition to general fears about a downturn in the housing market, both papers also face pressure from consolidation among real estate agencies. In August, the Corcoran Group acquired Allan Schneider Associates, one of the largest agencies in the East End of Long Island, reducing the number of firms looking to buy advertising pages.</p>
        <p>Rick Hoffman, regional vice president for the Corcoran Group, said that the broader reach of The Press, with its well-regarded real estate and home design section, may give it an advantage because advertisers want to ''place one ad that will cover the entire region.'' He added, ''There's only so much print-advertising money to go around.''</p>
        <p>Some local restaurateurs said they felt tapped out already. ''I think it's going to be a tough sell,'' said Mark Smith, an owner of the restaurants Nick and Toni's and Rowdy Hall. But he added, ''If it becomes a legitimate alternative to The Star, I'd have to take note of that.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Della Femina estimated that $30 million to $40 million is spent on print advertising annually in the Hamptons, and surmised that his paper, The Star and The Press capture $8 million to $10 million of that.</p>
        <p>''In terms of print advertising, this is a major city; this is not a small town,'' he said. ''For 16 weeks, everyone wants to reach the people who come out here.''</p>
        <p>That is the paradox of the Hamptons media landscape, where the huge summer population does not share the year-round residents' desire for what Mr. Rattray calls ''hyperlocal coverage.'' Most of the tourists who power the seasonal economy do not care about town board meetings or high school sports results. ''It's hard to both be a serious newspaper and appeal to the shore-house crowd,'' Mr. Rattray said.</p>
        <p>The Star and The Press are also facing the same problems that larger publications confront. Mr. Louchheim and Mr. Rattray spoke of the rising cost of newsprint, the impact of the Internet on advertising revenue, and the pressure to offer decent pay in a community where most reporters cannot afford to live on their salaries.</p>
        <p>And The Star is still feeling the effects of a failed expansion attempt into Sag Harbor in the late 1980s. ''We lost a ton of money,'' Mr. Rattray recalled.</p>
        <p>As a result, the Rattray family took on a minority partner -- Arthur L. Carter, the former owner of The New York Observer -- who tried to gain control of the paper. The Rattray family was able to buy back his shares in 2003 with a bank loan, which is still being paid off.</p>
        <p>Mr. Louchheim, who financed the new paper, said that he has wanted to expand into East Hampton for several years. ''I see this newspaper as more of a supplement to The Star than a competitor,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Star says it has an unaudited circulation of 13,000 to 16,000 in the high season, while The Southampton Press (which already publishes eastern and western editions) says it has a combined circulation of about 18,000. Mr. Louchheim said that his initial circulation goal for The East Hampton Press was about 6,000. The Press's figures are audited by the Circulation Verification Council.</p>
        <p>The East Hampton Press will rely on content from The Southampton Press's arts, sports and real estate sections, but it has also added two East Hampton reporters and an editor, Peter Boody, who is a former editor of The Southampton Press and The Shelter Island Reporter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Boody said that he and his colleagues were anything but carpetbaggers. ''We are not some big corporation from Chicago or Newark or Bridgeport,'' he said. ''We're from Southampton.''</p>
        <p>Even so, the new paper will face skeptics. People interviewed at the East Hampton Library and the Ladies' Village Improvement Society, which are both on Main Street near The Star's offices, did not sound excited about it.</p>
        <p>''I'm very loyal to The East Hampton Star,'' said Elizabeth Sarfati, a 28-year resident of East Hampton who was volunteering at the society. ''It really is our home paper.''</p>
        <p>In addition, there are already plenty of alternatives with magazines like Hamptons, Hampton Style and The Hampton Sheet.</p>
        <p>''We never tire of reading about ourselves in the Hamptons,'' Robert Zimmerman, a Democratic fund-raiser who lives in Southampton, said, with some sarcasm. ''We find ourselves to be an endless source of fascination.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
