<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pushed to Brink, Isles Respond With Playoff Bid</title>
    <meta content="09isles" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839207"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E5DF153FF93AA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pushed to Brink, Isles Respond With Playoff Bid</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., April 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jubilant but careful not to lose his balance, Ted Nolan did a high-step on tiptoe along the edge of his bench, then bear-hugged his players. His first season as the Islanders' coach would roll on, tilting on its axles.</p>
        <p>Needing a victory to make the playoffs, the Islanders defeated the Devils, 3-2, on Sunday in a shootout at Continental Arena.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jubilant but careful not to lose his balance, Ted Nolan did a high-step on tiptoe along the edge of his bench, then bear-hugged his players. His first season as the Islanders' coach would roll on, tilting on its axles.</p>
        <p>Needing a victory to make the playoffs, the Islanders defeated the Devils, 3-2, on Sunday in a shootout at Continental Arena.</p>
        <p>The Devils made it a thriller. John Madden scored two goals in the last five minutes of regulation, the second with nine-tenths of a second left.</p>
        <p>Although the Devils were assured of the second seed in the Eastern Conference playoffs, they pushed the Islanders to the shootout. The Islanders scored twice, the Devils once, and then Wade Dubielewicz, the Islanders' fill-in goaltender, made his biggest save of the season.</p>
        <p>Sergei Brylin, the Devils' third shooter, tried to beat Dubielewicz with the same move that Zach Parise had beaten him with earlier. But when Brylin drew the puck to his backhand, Dubielewicz poked the puck away with his stick before Brylin could shoot.</p>
        <p>The puck stopped about 15 feet in front of the goal, and the Islanders mobbed Dubielewicz, who helped the Islanders finish the season with four consecutive victories.</p>
        <p>They will open a best-of-seven first-round series Thursday against the top-seeded Sabres in Buffalo.</p>
        <p>''I've been waiting for an opportunity like this my whole life,'' said Dubielewicz, who spent most of the season with the Islanders' farm team in Bridgeport, Conn., He replaced Rick DiPietro, who is out indefinitely with a concussion. ''I want to make the most of it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Islanders (40-30-12) finished in eighth place in the Eastern Conference with 92 points, 1 more than the Toronto Maple Leafs, who had given the Islanders a chance to make the playoffs Saturday by beating the Montreal Canadiens, 6-5.</p>
        <p>Had the Canadiens won, the Islanders would have been eliminated from the playoff race, even with a victory Sunday.</p>
        <p>''We feel pretty Hollywood-ish,'' Nolan said. ''We're pretty excited. I don't think I was breathing for the five minutes of overtime and the shootout.''</p>
        <p>The Islanders got goals in the first and third periods from Richard Park, a fourth-line center who played less than six minutes Sunday. Park scored his second goal at 7 minutes 51 seconds of the third period on a shot that whipped past Devils goaltender Scott Clemmensen.</p>
        <p>Yes, Scott Clemmensen. Lou Lamoriello, the Devils' general manager and interim coach, had decided to use Clemmensen on Sunday instead of Martin Brodeur, who had beaten the Islanders in six of the previous seven games this season.</p>
        <p>It was Clemmensen's sixth game of the season and only his fourth start. But the Devils, who open a first-round series at home Thursday against the Tampa Bay Lightning, had little incentive Sunday. So Brodeur watched, a baseball cap pulled low over his eyes.</p>
        <p>''He's never let us down when he's been put in completely cold,'' Lamoriello said of Clemmensen. ''I thought he played outstanding.''</p>
        <p>Madden drew the Devils within a goal when he redirected a shot by Jay Pandolfo past Dubielewicz with 4:13 left in regulation. Lamoriello pulled Clemmensen with 1:17 left, and the Devils, unrelenting, swarmed the Islanders' zone.</p>
        <p>''What do you do? That's just the way the Devils are,'' Islanders center Mike Sillinger said. ''They never say die.''</p>
        <p>In the final seconds of regulation, Islanders left wing Ryan Smyth tried to clear the puck, but the Devils' Jamie Langenbrunner intercepted it and flung a backhand shot at the goal as Dubielewicz lay on the ice, having been tripped accidentally by an Islander. Langenbrunner's shot bounced off his midsection, but Madden quickly chipped the puck over Dubielewicz for his 11th goal of the season. The Islanders were stunned, but apparently only for a moment.</p>
        <p>''I never, ever have gone through something like that, and I hope I don't have to again,'' Smyth said.</p>
        <p>The five-minute overtime was a wash, leading to the Islanders' second shootout in five days. Dubielewicz had stopped Michael Nylander, Brendan Shanahan and Jaromir Jagr in a 3-2 victory against the Rangers on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Miroslav Satan whipped a shot over Clemmensen's stick, but Parise scored on a backhander for the Devils. The Islanders' Viktor Kozlov, one of the Devils' trustiest shootout shooters last season, threw a shot between Clemmensen's legs.</p>
        <p>Dubielewicz stopped Brian Gionta's backhand shot, but Clemmensen got enough of his blocker on a shot by Smyth to keep the Devils alive. Brylin was next.</p>
        <p>''With how bad Parise burned me, I had a feeling he'd do the same thing,'' Dubielewicz said.</p>
        <p>Dubielewicz's hunch paid off. The season will go on, though no one is sure if DiPietro will replace Dubielewicz when the playoffs start. DiPietro, who has not played since March 25, rode an exercise bicycle Thursday but has not practiced.</p>
        <p>Nolan said he would worry on Monday about the Sabres, the team he once coached. He and his team had Sunday night to celebrate a playoff berth that did not even seem possible eight days earlier.</p>
        <p>''If we just believe in ourselves and play for each other, you never know what's going to happen,'' Alexei Yashin said.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
