<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a Television Carnival, Buy, Sell or Cringe</title>
    <meta content="09cramer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/09/business/media/09cramer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070412T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839104"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA TALK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Vaccination and Immunization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prostate Gland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vaccination and Immunization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Dendreon Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">CNBC</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cramer, James J</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E7D7143FF93AA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="593" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a Television Carnival, Buy, Sell or Cringe</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In a Television Carnival, Buy, Sell or Cringe</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIA MILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Miller, Lia</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The cult status of James J. Cramer, the host of the CNBC television show ''Mad Money,'' may derive more from the manic atmosphere he creates on the show than the sagacity of his stock tips.</p>
        <p>Even so, some people were upset that one of his recommendations on March 28 -- to sell shares of Dendreon, a biotechnology company in Seattle -- turned out to be dead wrong. The next day, Dendreon's prostate cancer vaccine, Provenge, was endorsed by a Food and Drug Administration panel, putting it a step away from approval. Dendreon's stock price has since more than tripled, closing last week at $18.05.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some people were upset when a stock tip from James J. Cramer, the host of the CNBC show “Mad Money,” turned out to be dead wrong.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The cult status of James J. Cramer, the host of the CNBC television show ''Mad Money,'' may derive more from the manic atmosphere he creates on the show than the sagacity of his stock tips.</p>
        <p>Even so, some people were upset that one of his recommendations on March 28 -- to sell shares of Dendreon, a biotechnology company in Seattle -- turned out to be dead wrong. The next day, Dendreon's prostate cancer vaccine, Provenge, was endorsed by a Food and Drug Administration panel, putting it a step away from approval. Dendreon's stock price has since more than tripled, closing last week at $18.05.</p>
        <p>On the air, Mr. Cramer joked about the bad advice, saying he ''did not expect'' good news from Dendreon and had gotten Provenge mixed up with Provasic. The latter is a fictional drug from a 1993 movie, ''The Fugitive,'' in which Dr. Richard Kimble, played by Harrison Ford, tries to expose a fictitious pharmaceutical company, Devlin-MacGregor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cramer said he was ''surprised and thrilled that Provenge, which I was confusing with Provasic, could be approved -- remember, staff, that's what Dr. Richard didn't like.''</p>
        <p>Some bloggers thought he was being dense. In investment chat rooms, people called Mr. Cramer ''a fool'' or worse, and demanded that CNBC cancel his show.</p>
        <p>Nonsense, Mr. Cramer said in a telephone interview last week. He said he did not really confuse the two drugs and was obviously joking by making a reference to one of his favorite movies, something he often does on the show. '' 'The Fugitive,' '' he said, ''had an early read on why people despise the pharmaceutical companies.'' He added, ''I always make the joke that even though it's a $9 million company, you should be selling Devlin-MacGregor.''</p>
        <p>It is hard to say how many investors may have missed an earnings opportunity as the result of Mr. Cramer's words, but he is standing by his call. ''There are many people who felt it would not be approved,'' he said of Provenge. As for Dendreon, ''I wish I had recommended it earlier.'' The company did not respond to calls for comment.</p>
        <p>One person who believes Mr. Cramer's account is Kevin Michaels, 27, a Canadian who runs a Web site, CramerWatch.org. The site checks Mr. Cramer's recommendations using a character called Leonard the Wonder Monkey, who flips a coin to make predictions for the same stocks. The results are tracked for 30 days to see whose advice fared better; for the moment, the monkey is one pick ahead, though Mr. Cramer could pull ahead tonight.</p>
        <p>Mr. Michaels said the Dendreon situation underscores the problem with ''Mad Money'' -- that Mr. Cramer exerts too much sway over his fans and in some cases, the market.</p>
        <p>''The guy definitely has a lot of knowledge; it's rare he's not familiar with a stock,'' Mr. Michaels said. ''Our goal is to make people realize they should do their own research, make their own decisions and not just be blind believers.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cramer, who has been weathering a bigger controversy lately for comments he made in December on TheStreet.com, which he co-founded 11 years ago and where he remains a major shareholder. He suggested that in his days as a hedge fund manager, he used to try to buoy the prices of stocks he was buying and selling.</p>
        <p>By telephone last week, Mr. Cramer said he did not like to think about his critics. ''I'm here to educate, but mostly to entertain,'' he said, ''I'm facetious, I'm cynical, I try to have a couple of jokes.''</p>
        <p>LIA MILLER</p>
        <p>MEDIA TALK</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 12, 2007, Thursday  A Media Talk report in Business Day on Monday, about the cult status of James J. Cramer, the host of the CNBC television show ''Mad Money, referred imprecisely to the aftermath of his ''sell'' recommendation on Dendreon shares. Because trading was halted the morning after the recommendation, few investors would have been able to sell -- causing them to miss an earnings opportunity -- before trading in Dendreon shares resumed. Mr. Cramer's recommendation did not necessarily cause investors to lose money.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 12, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>A Media Talk report in Business Day on Monday, about the cult status of James J. Cramer, the host of the CNBC television show ''Mad Money, referred imprecisely to the aftermath of his ''sell'' recommendation on Dendreon shares. Because trading was halted the morning after the recommendation, few investors would have been able to sell -- causing them to miss an earnings opportunity -- before trading in Dendreon shares resumed. Mr. Cramer's recommendation did not necessarily cause investors to lose money.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
