<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Turning Heads as Big Race Nears</title>
    <meta content="09racing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/09/sports/othersports/09racing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839185"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E0D6143FF93AA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="862" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Turning Heads as Big Race Nears</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Two Horses Turning Heads as Derby Nears</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Who is the ''Big Horse,'' the 3-year-old who will take the nation's breath away in the Kentucky Derby and, for at least two weeks, conjure thoughts of a Triple Crown? Twenty-seven days from America's most famous horse race, the conversation focuses on two colts: Nobiz Like Shobiz and Street Sense.</p>
        <p>By winning the Grade I Wood Memorial on Saturday at Aqueduct, Nobiz Like Shobiz established himself as a formidable Derby contender. The son of Albert the Great, Nobiz Like Shobiz convincingly dispatched Any Given Saturday, who had given Street Sense all he could handle before losing by a nose last month at the Tampa Bay Derby.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Twenty-seven days from the Kentucky Derby, the focus is on two colts: Nobiz Like Shobiz and Street Sense.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Who is the ''Big Horse,'' the 3-year-old who will take the nation's breath away in the Kentucky Derby and, for at least two weeks, conjure thoughts of a Triple Crown? Twenty-seven days from America's most famous horse race, the conversation focuses on two colts: Nobiz Like Shobiz and Street Sense.</p>
        <p>By winning the Grade I Wood Memorial on Saturday at Aqueduct, Nobiz Like Shobiz established himself as a formidable Derby contender. The son of Albert the Great, Nobiz Like Shobiz convincingly dispatched Any Given Saturday, who had given Street Sense all he could handle before losing by a nose last month at the Tampa Bay Derby.</p>
        <p>Nobiz Like Shobiz ran strong and straight down the stretch, something he failed to do in his previous start -- a third-place finish in the Fountain of Youth Stakes last month in Florida. His trainer, Barclay Tagg, won the Derby with Funny Cide in 2003 and has prepared his latest contender in traditional fashion.</p>
        <p>Nobiz Like Shobiz has won four of his six races, three of them in graded stakes. His two losses were by three-quarters of a length in last year's Grade I Champagne, and by a half-length in the Fountain of Youth.</p>
        <p>In both instances, troubled trips conspired with Nobiz Like Shobiz's immaturity to give him valid excuses for defeat.</p>
        <p>He is bred to relish the Derby's mile-and-quarter distance, and he has already displayed his stamina by winning twice at a mile and an eighth. Even the rival trainer Todd Pletcher is impressed. He not only beat Nobiz Like Shobiz twice with Scat Daddy, but he will also take at least three other and perhaps as many as five horses to Churchill Downs.</p>
        <p>''That horse has done very little wrong his whole life,'' he said. ''After he won the Holy Bull, everyone kind of talked of him being a megastar. And then he gets beat half a length one start later, and he drops off everyone's list. I thought people were a little quick to overcriticize him.''</p>
        <p>In fact, Nobiz Like Shobiz has many fans among horsemen. Shug McGaughey, the trainer of Sightseeing, was ''tickled to death'' with his colt's late run to finish second behind Nobiz Like Shobiz. Still, he said that he was inclined to skip the Derby, and wait until the summer to throw Sightseeing into top company.</p>
        <p>''I've always been a Nobiz Like Shobiz fan,'' he said. ''My hat is off to him. He ran a great race.''</p>
        <p>How talented Street Sense may be is open to debate. He was voted the champion 2-year-old last year on the strength of a record-breaking 10-length victory in the Breeders' Cup Juvenile at Churchill Downs. Still, it was only his second victory in five starts, and many believe Street Sense and his jockey, Calvin Borel, took advantage of the No. 1 post to skim the rail on a surface that had an inside bias all afternoon.</p>
        <p>The son of Street Cry, Street Sense will tackle an extremely tough field next weekend in the Blue Grass Stakes at Keeneland. It will be only his second race as a 3-year-old and his final prep race before the Derby. Sunny's Halo was the last horse to capture the Derby off two preps and that was in 1983. His trainer, Carl Nafzger, won the Derby in 1990 with Unbridled, and he announced his intentions for a light prep schedule at the beginning of the year.</p>
        <p>Last month in the Tampa Bay Derby, Street Sense broke the track record for a mile and a sixteenth, but he was challenged in the stretch by Any Given Saturday.</p>
        <p>That performance was not flattered Saturday, however, when Any Given Saturday turned in a dull effort, finishing three and three-quarter lengths behind Nobiz Like Shobiz in the Wood.</p>
        <p>Still, Any Given Saturday is Derby-bound, though his trainer, Pletcher, said he needed to improve quickly if he was to win the Derby. ''We will have to step it up a notch to get it done,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Nafzger and Borel are not paying attention to any potential rivals. Last week, Street Sense arrived at his home track, Churchill Downs, from Florida and promptly turned in a wickedly fast five-furlong workout in 582/5 seconds.</p>
        <p>''He was awesome,'' Borel said. ''The horse is just getting better and better. Carl's got him on the right road, and you just couldn't ask for any better. He did it happy. He galloped out strong, and I really didn't squeeze no buttons or nothing -- he was just there for me.''</p>
        <p>Nafzger will know Saturday at the Blue Grass if he has Street Sense primed to become the Big Horse on May 5. Tagg, on the other hand, says he has done all he can to prepare Nobiz Like Shobiz.</p>
        <p>It was plenty, too. Tagg added blinkers to help the colt focus. He also stuffed his ears with cotton to eliminate other distractions.</p>
        <p>Now it is simply a matter of keeping Nobiz Like Shobiz healthy, Tagg said, and getting lucky on race day.</p>
        <p>''These horses have to win these races themselves,'' Tagg said. ''I never get overly confident about anything. So many things can happen in a race.''</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
