<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Madison Avenue Deal Maker Continues His Spending Spree</title>
    <meta content="09adcol" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/09/business/media/09adcol.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839119"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">MDC Partners Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E5D7143FF93AA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1508" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Madison Avenue Deal Maker Continues His Spending Spree</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Madison Avenue Deal Maker Continues His Spending Spree</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STUART ELLIOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Miles S. Nadal, the Monty Hall of Madison Avenue, is at it again, doing what he loves to do best: making deals. But when is enough enough?</p>
        <p>Mr. Nadal, the chairman and chief executive of MDC Partners, an advertising conglomerate based in Toronto, hopes to get ahead in the intensely competitive advertising industry with a contrarian strategy of almost continuous change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Miles S. Nadal, head of MDC Partners, is doing what he loves to do best: making deals. But when is enough enough?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Miles S. Nadal, the Monty Hall of Madison Avenue, is at it again, doing what he loves to do best: making deals. But when is enough enough?</p>
        <p>Mr. Nadal, the chairman and chief executive of MDC Partners, an advertising conglomerate based in Toronto, hopes to get ahead in the intensely competitive advertising industry with a contrarian strategy of almost continuous change.</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Hall sweet-talking a contestant on ''Let's Make a Deal,'' Mr. Nadal has persuaded the owners of well-known agencies like Crispin Porter &amp; Bogusky, Cliff Freeman &amp; Partners and Kirshenbaum Bond &amp; Partners to cast their lot with MDC rather than far bigger competitors like the Omnicom Group, the WPP Group or the Interpublic Group of Companies.</p>
        <p>But following that philosophy can be fraught with risk, as was demonstrated last week with the unraveling of an acquisition and merger involving two New York agencies, which Mr. Nadal orchestrated less than two years ago.</p>
        <p>The agency formed by those deals, Margeotes Fertitta Powell, is being closed because it failed to grow as Mr. Nadal had hoped; the closing costs are being determined.</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Nadal, 49, is about to announce another round of deals, with agencies that work on tasks like brand identity and corporate communications. He plans to spend $150 million in the next three years on acquisitions, to beef up MDC in important, fast-growing areas like digital advertising.</p>
        <p>''All service businesses, all businesses in this industry especially, need to be in a constant state of evolution,'' Mr. Nadal said in one of two interviews over the last month.</p>
        <p>''With the changes in consumers, in the media, we're under more pressure to add talent, to add capabilities,'' Mr. Nadal said. ''The long-term success stories in advertising have evolved, and constantly changed, with the environment.''</p>
        <p>The affable, fast-talking Mr. Nadal can be a charmer. But his ability to close deals is probably predicated less on his personality and more on his offbeat strategy: Rather than acquiring an agency outright, he initially takes a stake -- typically from 20 percent to 80 percent -- and lets the agency operate autonomously, under the MDC umbrella.</p>
        <p>By comparison, the giant rivals of MDC almost always acquire total ownership of the agencies they buy. If the former owners stick around, there are operational rules to follow.</p>
        <p>''The really talented, creative people don't like being told what to do,'' said Jonathan Bond, co-chairman of Kirshenbaum Bond in New York, who with Richard Kirshenbaum sold 60 percent of the agency to Mr. Nadal in 2004.</p>
        <p>''I don't know if we'd be good in a corporate structure,'' he added. ''We'd probably get fired in a week, with good reason.''</p>
        <p>In contrast, ''MDC has been a good fit for us,'' Mr. Bond said. ''We just go do it till someone tells us not to -- and no one ever has.''</p>
        <p>One reason for Mr. Nadal's belief in constant change is how it has paid off for him: a net worth estimated at more than $100 million; homes in the Bahamas and Palm Beach; an 80-foot cruiser with its own Web site (yachtdaretodream.com); and a special bonus from MDC in 2003 of $5.3 million.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nadal started his business in 1980 on a far smaller stake -- 500 Canadian dollars, a cash advance on his Visa card -- which helped him open a company called Action Photographics. He has parlayed that modest beginning into MDC, the world's 11th largest ad conglomerate, with revenue last year of $423.7 million.</p>
        <p>From the start, Mr. Nadal has relished making over his holdings continually, shifting focus from photography to check printing to marketing services. Along the way, he bought and sold everything from a catalog retailer to a postage-stamp producer to a seed company.</p>
        <p>Since deciding a decade ago to cut back the churn and concentrate on advertising, Mr. Nadal has amassed a portfolio of about 30 agencies in areas like creative services, online marketing, public relations, package design and sales promotion.</p>
        <p>''Miles keeps his promises,'' said Chuck Porter, the chairman of Crispin Porter in Miami, arguably the hottest agency in America for its irreverent campaigns for brands like Burger King, Coke Zero, Sprite and Volkswagen.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nadal sometimes ''comes across as a salesman,'' said Mr. Porter, who joined his agency partners in selling 49 percent of Crispin Porter to MDC in 2001, ''and a lot of people do not necessarily want to talk to a salesman.''</p>
        <p>''But he genuinely, truly believes in the product,'' said Mr. Porter, who also serves as the chief strategist for MDC. ''It's not like he's selling Chevys this week and Volkswagens the next.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nadal said he believed his approach encouraged the founders of the agencies he buys to stay on, limiting the damage that can occur when they leave after deals are closed. He also appeals to their entrepreneurial side by letting them share in the future financial success of their agencies.</p>
        <p>''We talked to an awful lot of people who wanted to buy 100 percent, but we were never interested in that because we felt our biggest growth was in front of us,'' Mr. Porter recalled. ''Miles understands the value of partnership instead of ownership.''</p>
        <p>Among the newest converts to the Nadal way is David Melançon, chief executive of the Ito Partnership, a New York agency specializing in brand design and development. He is selling 60 percent of Ito to MDC.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nadal ''doesn't always understand every facet of our business, but he's turned on by what we do and gets that people are the product,'' said Mr. Melançon, who has worked for agencies owned by Interpublic, Omnicom and WPP. ''For the first time, I feel I have a say, when I didn't before.''</p>
        <p>Another new convert is Hamilton South, who is selling MDC a majority stake in the New York agency HL Group, which handles communications and marketing tasks for clients like Vera Wang and David Yurman.</p>
        <p>''We didn't know who he was,'' Mr. South said of Mr. Nadal. ''But we did a lot of research and talked to a lot of people, who told us he had a very interesting model.''</p>
        <p>When the HL founders met Mr. Nadal, ''he asked a lot of questions about how we do business rather than giving us all the answers,'' Mr. South said, adding: ''He's curious and passionate. I have a lot of clients I'd be thrilled to introduce him to.''</p>
        <p>That reaction is crucial for the MDC strategy to succeed, because Mr. Nadal relies on his agencies working voluntarily with one another rather than mandating cooperation, as do some of his bigger competitors.</p>
        <p>Critics of Mr. Nadal point to that as his Achilles' heel because, they contend, if he does not fully control the agencies he owns he cannot maximize the benefits of owning them all.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, there are risks in that you don't get the efficiencies,'' said Joshua Sharf, a research analyst at William Smith &amp; Company in Denver who follows MDC. ''And there can be tension between the demands of dealing with individual companies and the performance as an overall corporation.''</p>
        <p>Still, ''by letting the agencies maintain their independence, MDC gives them a better shot of capturing business,'' he added, because ''they all don't end up looking like each other.''</p>
        <p>The failure of Margeotes Fertitta Powell may serve as a cautionary tale for Mr. Nadal and his strategy. Hoping, as he put it, to ''turbocharge'' the venerable Margeotes Fertitta &amp; Partners, which joined the MDC fold in 1998, Mr. Nadal acquired Powell, a small New York shop, and merged it with the older, larger agency in July 2005.</p>
        <p>But the combination of the ''different cultures, different management teams,'' never gelled, Mr. Nadal said. So MDC is moving ahead with a reorganization that will most likely cost up to 20 people their jobs, combining the remnants of Margeotes Fertitta Powell with Kirshenbaum Bond and installing Neil Powell, chief creative officer, at his own agency with the fanciful name of We Are Gigantic.</p>
        <p>''We think we're very successful, but we knew we'd never be perfect,'' Mr. Nadal said. ''No batter bats 1,000.''</p>
        <p>In assessing the hodgepodge of MDC holdings, even Mr. Porter, the chief strategist for MDC, acknowledged that ''a lot of people in the financial community look at this and say: 'I don't understand it. It's a mess.' ''</p>
        <p>''Performance-wise, I would like to be further ahead, but so would everyone else,'' Mr. Porter said, adding: ''The real trick for MDC, that will either make it an enormous success or not, is the ability to identify great talent to partner with. When talented people think, 'We need a partner,' I think MDC is in a lot of their minds. And that's a huge step.''</p>
        <p>For the Canadian-born Mr. Nadal -- who has been compared in his home country to Duddy Kravitz, the ambitious striver created by the author Mordecai Richler -- that means more deal-making. And he would not have it any other way.</p>
        <p>''A substantial part of the portfolio of MDC Partners hasn't even been created yet,'' Mr. Nadal said. ''A lot more to come.''</p>
        <p>ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
