<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a Flash, Curry Proves He Can Lead the Knicks</title>
    <meta content="09knicks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/09/sports/basketball/09knicks.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839188"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Curry, Eddy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EFD6143FF93AA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="854" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a Flash, Curry Proves He Can Lead the Knicks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In a Flash, Curry Proves He Can Lead the Knicks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beck, Howard</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Until Saturday night, the idea of asking Eddy Curry to hit a buzzer-beating, game-saving 3-pointer was ludicrous, if not outright nutty. It may still be considered so, even after Curry made a 3-pointer to force overtime and help the Knicks defeat Milwaukee.</p>
        <p>But then, Curry has spent the entire season quashing beliefs about what he can and cannot do. It was not long ago, after all, that the notion of Curry as a franchise player was also deemed ludicrous and nutty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With six games to go, Eddy Curry is averaging career highs in points and rebounds, showing that he is capable of carrying his team.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Until Saturday night, the idea of asking Eddy Curry to hit a buzzer-beating, game-saving 3-pointer was ludicrous, if not outright nutty. It may still be considered so, even after Curry made a 3-pointer to force overtime and help the Knicks defeat Milwaukee.</p>
        <p>But then, Curry has spent the entire season quashing beliefs about what he can and cannot do. It was not long ago, after all, that the notion of Curry as a franchise player was also deemed ludicrous and nutty.</p>
        <p>He was deemed too soft to carry a team, too indifferent to be dominant and too flaky to reach his All-Star potential. He was deemed a bust by the Chicago Bulls, his hometown team.</p>
        <p>That derisive tag should never follow Curry's name again.</p>
        <p>With six games to go, Curry is averaging career highs in points (19.5) and rebounds (7.1), while shooting .578 from the field. He has shown time and again this season that he is willing and capable of -- even passionate about -- carrying his team.</p>
        <p>His performance Saturday might be remembered for the eye-popping 3-pointer that Curry hit at the regulation buzzer. It should be remembered as the night he took full responsibility for the Knicks' fate.</p>
        <p>With Stephon Marbury out (joining Jamal Crawford, Quentin Richardson and Steve Francis), Curry was the Knicks' last front-line scorer. The Bucks were free to crowd him on every possession in the post. Yet Curry demolished the double teams with power and finesse and scored 43 points, his career high.</p>
        <p>On a grease board in the locker room, Marbury, calling Curry by his nickname, E-City, scrawled a gleeful congratulatory message: ''City, how does it feel to get 40? Welcome to the club.''</p>
        <p>Among recent Knicks, that is a rather exclusive club. Since 1988, only five others have scored at least 40: Crawford, Marbury, Allan Houston, Latrell Sprewell and Patrick Ewing.</p>
        <p>Curry's total was the most by a Knicks center since Ewing scored 41 at Seattle on Jan. 19, 1996. Curry will be the first center to lead the Knicks in scoring for a season since Ewing (17.3) in 1999.</p>
        <p>Curry was brilliant from the field (17 for 20) and perfect from the arc. With the Knicks trailing by 102-99 and nine-tenths of a second left, Coach Isiah Thomas told Curry -- who had made just one 3-pointer in his career -- to take the final shot. Curry, 6 feet 11 inches and 285 pounds, rarely even shoots face-up jumpers in games (although he often did so in high school).</p>
        <p>''I think they thought I was the last person that would shoot a 3,'' Curry said of the stunned Bucks.</p>
        <p>''But next time we play them, they know I'm a 3-point threat. The secret's out.''</p>
        <p>Curry played 50 minutes Saturday, shattering another commonly held belief -- that he would never be durable enough to stay on the court. He is averaging 35.4 minutes a game, also a career high.</p>
        <p>''To put up these type of numbers, on a back-to-back night when we desperately need a win, tells me a lot about him and his conviction and his determination,'' Thomas said.</p>
        <p>And giving the ball to Curry with the game and the Knicks' slim playoff hopes on the line says a lot about the belief Thomas has in Curry. When Thomas became coach this season, he installed Curry as his No. 1 option. Although the injury-prone Knicks (32-44) have stumbled in the final month, losing 10 of their past 13, they now know that Curry can be their foundation for years to come.</p>
        <p>Thomas, who is also the team president, was widely criticized for acquiring Curry, accused of giving up too much to obtain him. The Bulls received the Knicks' first-round draft pick last year (which became Tyrus Thomas) and have the right to swap first-round picks in the draft this year.</p>
        <p>A month ago, before injuries wrecked them, it appeared that the Knicks would make the playoffs, and the pick sent to Chicago would be in the mid-teens. It seemed Thomas would save face.</p>
        <p>Now the Knicks appear lottery-bound, and Thomas will be cringing on draft day. As of yesterday morning, the Knicks were tied for the 10th-worst record in the league.</p>
        <p>Bulls fans are rooting outright for the Knicks to fail. They will get a chance to do so in person when the Knicks play in Chicago tomorrow night.</p>
        <p>It will be another homecoming of mixed emotions for Curry. He is having his finest season. He has proved his critics wrong. But he has yet to deliver a playoff berth, and he will be measured for years to come against the draft picks the Bulls received.</p>
        <p>In Thomas, however, Curry has an ardent supporter, a true believer who will give him the ball and tell him to go win the game.</p>
        <p>''Isiah's the kind of coach that has a lot of faith in all of us,'' Curry said. ''If he's calling you out to do something, that means that he has faith and he believes. And you've got to believe in yourself.''</p>
        <p>Curry was talking about the 3-pointer. He could have been talking about his career.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
