<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>McCAIN REVAMPS HIS FUND-RAISING</title>
    <meta content="04mccain" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/us/politics/04mccain.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837893"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baghdad (Iraq)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John S (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Loeffler, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmidt, Steve (Political Adviser)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Petraeus, David H (Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Foreign Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <person class="online_producer">McCain, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804EFDF163FF937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1026" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>McCAIN REVAMPS HIS FUND-RAISING</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">McCain Revamps His Fund-Raising</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nagourney, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen John McCain is overhauling his lagging campaign finance operations and delaying official announcement of his presidential candidacy amid criticism of his support for Iraq war; will adopt kind of big-donor program pioneered by Pres Bush, which he criticized when he and Bush were opponents in 2000; enlists Tom Loeffler and Steve Schmidt as senior advisers and puts them in charge of fund-raising effort; will give speech on April 11 explaining support for troop buildup in Iraq and urging Americans to back war effort; Democrats charge that McCain is so committed to surge in Iraq that he fails to appreciate what is happening there even as he visits Baghdad; his aides insist McCain's optimism is based on assessment provided by Gen David H Petraeus, commander of US forces in Iraq (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lagging in fund-raising and under fire for his support of the Iraq war, Senator John McCain is overhauling his campaign finance operation and delaying the official announcement of his candidacy, his aides said Tuesday.</p>
        <p>They said he would adopt the kind of big-donor fund-raising program pioneered by President Bush and give a speech explaining his support for the administration's troop buildup in Iraq.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The maneuvers come at a time when the senator is lagging in fund-raising and under fire for his support of the Iraq war.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lagging in fund-raising and under fire for his support of the Iraq war, Senator John McCain is overhauling his campaign finance operation and delaying the official announcement of his candidacy, his aides said Tuesday.</p>
        <p>They said he would adopt the kind of big-donor fund-raising program pioneered by President Bush and give a speech explaining his support for the administration's troop buildup in Iraq.</p>
        <p>The maneuvers come at a time of sharp anxiety in Mr. McCain's camp, especially over his fund-raising, which is trailing all the major Republican and Democratic presidential candidates.</p>
        <p>The concern grew after his visit to Iraq over the weekend, when he asserted that conditions there were improving.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain's aides said that to deal with his fund-raising problems, he would adopt what had been a centerpiece of Mr. Bush's fund-raising technique, and one that has been embraced by most major presidential candidates: creating an honorary campaign designation to reward the campaign's top money raisers. Mr. Bush called his Rangers and Pioneers; Mr. McCain will call his the McCain 100's, for supporters who collect $100,000 for the campaign, and the McCain 200's, who collect $200,000.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain has been identified throughout his career as an advocate of curbing the influence of money in politics, notably as a co-sponsor of a landmark bill limiting political contributions. He criticized Mr. Bush, when the two were opponents in 2000, as leading overly aggressive fund-raising efforts.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain has also enlisted two senior advisers and put them in charge of a fund-raising effort that campaign aides described bluntly as being in disarray and without a single person in charge. They are Tom Loeffler, a former Texas congressman who was named the campaign's national campaign finance chairman, and Steve Schmidt, who ran Gov. Arnold Schwarzenegger's most recent campaign in California.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain's aides said his problems arose because contributors, staff members -- and perhaps Mr. McCain himself -- had been lulled into complacency after a year in which they had systematically portrayed his nomination as inevitable.</p>
        <p>''This is a moment that has truly defined what needs to be done with respect to political fund-raising,'' said Mr. Loeffler, whom Mr. McCain elevated to run the fund-raising effort at the first signs of trouble three weeks ago. ''What it has shown for this team is that this is not a jog. This is a sprint.''</p>
        <p>John Weaver, Mr. McCain's senior adviser, said: ''We have a responsibility to make sure this doesn't happen again and that we fix it. We take that seriously.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain held only three fund-raisers in January and February, they said. Mr. McCain's aides said that they had spent Tuesday in conference calls with contributors across the country and that they were loading Mr. McCain's schedule through the spring with fund-raisers to try to recover.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. McCain will, upon his return from Iraq, deliver what his aides said would be a major speech at the Virginia Military Institute that will argue that the troop escalation was showing signs of success and urging Americans to back the war effort. The speech will take place on April 11, the day on which Mr. McCain had been scheduled to formally enter the race.</p>
        <p>The candidate's coming speech on the war, too, comes as Democrats are assailing Mr. McCain as having an overly optimistic view of conditions in Iraq, where he toured a Baghdad market while clad in a bulletproof vest and protected by helicopters and armed guards.</p>
        <p>Democrats suggested that Mr. McCain had become so committed to building up forces, a stance he has long favored, and that he had linked his fortunes to the war so much that he failed to appreciate what was happening there now.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain's aides disputed that contention on Tuesday, saying that he was relying on the assessment provided by Gen. David H. Petraeus, commander of the American forces in Iraq. They said he was mainly chastising reporters in Baghdad as focusing on bad news coming out of that country, and disregarding what Mr. McCain said were encouraging turns of events there.</p>
        <p>''These are things that General Petraeus -- not John McCain, but General Petraeus -- says are happening that is encouraging,'' said Mark Salter, a longtime senior adviser to Mr. McCain.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain's advisers said they expected that the senator would come under fire from opponents for turning to big money-raisers; he has already said the campaign would not take the federal funds that go to candidates who accept spending limits. But they called the criticisms unfair.</p>
        <p>''During the course of the campaign, there will be all manners of unfair criticism,'' Mr. Schmidt said. ''But John McCain's record as a reformer -- and as an agent for good government -- stands second to none. He believes that people who give generously of their resources to causes they believe in is a good thing.''</p>
        <p>Joining Mr. Schmidt, Wayne Berman, a longtime supporter of Mr. Bush, has been named a vice chairman of the McCain campaign. Mr. Berman, like others of Mr. McCain's advisers, said they were at a loss to explain why Mr. McCain had failed to hold more big-donor events early in the quarter, but said that would change now.</p>
        <p>''A lot of us on the fund-raising end gave advice which turned out to be wrong, which is we could do a lot of fund-raising without events,'' Mr. Berman said. ''We forgot -- and I bear as much blame for this as anyone -- that high-dollar presidential fund-raising is event-driven.''</p>
        <p>The McCain campaign is adopting many of the tools, like daily counts of fund-raising receipts and methodical tracking of the success of e-mail and general mail appeals. Those types of efforts were used extensively by Mr. Bush's campaign in 2004.</p>
        <p>Mr. Weaver was dismissive of the success of Mitt Romney, the former governor of Massachusetts, who stunned many Republicans by raising more than $20 million, compared with $12.5 million for Mr. McCain and $15 million for a third major Republican candidate, Rudolph W. Giuliani. Mr. Weaver noted that Mr. Romney continued to trail in polls.</p>
        <p>''He's raised about $7 million per Gallup point,'' Mr. Weaver said. ''He's a great salesman, there's no doubt about it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
