<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reader Responses</title>
    <meta content="04leonhardt-response" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/business/04leonhardt-response.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837919"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05EED9163FF937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2657" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reader Responses</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Reader Responses</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID LEONHARDT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The following are excerpts to David Leonhardt's April 4 column on the layoffs at Circuit City and the corporate safety net:</p>
        <p>David, I'm surprised you would suggest there is no economic logic to increased pay for more experienced workers. If the only measure of worker quality were efficiency, it might follow that greybeards with bad knees aren't worth the extra pay. But workers are not just machines -- even workers who run machines all day -- and the quality of their work can't just be tracked empirically on a flow chart.</p>
        <p>Experienced workers who interact with customers can generate goodwill along with increased sales. Those who work in the "back room" (or on the factory line) can contribute important suggestions for jobsite improvements. They are also typically more reliable than younger workers.</p>
        <p>But there is another economic logic behind more pay for more age. In one sense a career can be thought of as a wasting asset--when it "expires" (at retirement or death), that's it. Game over. Thus it stands to reason that individuals want to feel like their career "asset" is increasing in value before it expires. You'd expect the same from an oil field.  -- Max Alexander</p>
        <p>Max, I do think that there are some solid economic reasons pay rises more rapidly than productivity over a person's career. For one thing, it inspires loyalty (a point that Ed Lazear, the current chairman of President Bush's Council of Economic Advisers, has made in his academic work). But I think it's also in part a social custom. And more companies seem to be deciding it's a social custom they no longer want to follow. -- David Leonhardt</p>
        <p>Your article, while well-intentioned, lacks a certain completeness in analysis that undermines your credibility. It is agreed that social safety nets can help dampen the otherwise harsh effects of pure capitalism, especially when those effects have an impact on our older, presumably wiser population. However, your assertion that government should step in and "save the day" without any mention of an individual's responsibility to use his/her resources (labor, education, financial) wisely is tantamount to the argument that America can "make" Iraq a democracy through the increased use of force. That is, it is simply ridiculous.</p>
        <p>The fact that U.S. savings rates are near zero if not negative, that our nation has elected an administration whose priorities are squarely aligned with further enriching the wealthy, and that so many have purchased homes beyond their means suggests that the real issue is individual accountability by Americans. No amount of government meddling can overcome people who are unwilling to show a little restraint and discipline.  -- Cecyl Hobbs</p>
        <p>Great article, thank you. I found Home Depot used similar tactics with my wages when I invested three years of my life with them. After getting a score of 4, out of a possible 5, I received a $0.00 raise, after which my efforts as a sales associate where negatively impacted.</p>
        <p>This, after making a real effort, was more than a person should be subjected to, in terms of being treated with "decency".  - Colin Campbell</p>
        <p>There a few things that need to be done: Begin career development earlier in the education process in order to graduate a workforce that can fill the higher level positions that go begging, and as a result are filled by foreign workers, create a robust training program, increase awareness around skills, continuing education for those people already in the workforce, and revise the current healthcare system.  - Steve Guine</p>
        <p>A critical thing that I think got left out of this cold-hearted calculation of worker's worth, is how much it costs to hire and train new workers. I simply won't shop in places where the sales associates don't know the product, especially for technical gadgets and consumer electronics. It's far more helpful to do my research online and shop there. If the local retailers can't pay there people enough to educate them and retain their experience, I won't patronize them.</p>
        <p>So there's the cost of hiring, the cost of training, and the cost of lost sales no wonder Circuit City is doing badly, and my local CompUSA just went out ot business. Perhaps if they tried a more win-win model like personal service to counteract online sales they would build CUSTOMER loyalty. But you have to build WORKER loyalty first.  - Michele Matossian</p>
        <p>Your article also explains why, when you wish to buy something at Circuit City, the knowledge of their employees and the service, if you find what you need to purchase, is dreadful. Waiting in line for 1 clerk, that handles internet sales, store sales, and returns is a challenge. It is also why I no longer shop at Circuit City or Wall Mart.  - Linda Metnetsky</p>
        <p>I first heard the retraining panacea trotted out years ago by Robert Reich, on public radio. I was a young IT professional then, and already skeptical of the whole notion of retraining, knowing just how fast things change, how easy it was to fall behind, and how much harder it is to learn with passing time -- just a glance at my parents struggling with every new device and social change, and it was obvious. Now that I am an older IT professional in a far more merciless corporate environment than then, I cringe when I hear the words "retraining" clopping around at the back of the mental barn of liberal economists, like the vague afterthought it always is. It is no more viable a solution now than it was then.</p>
        <p>I am sorry, but the option that is not viable here is to let massive companies like Circuit City treat their employees like last year's stock. At least if we want to maintain the thin veneer of living in a civilization, as opposed to a Victorian industrial slum. Placing some controls over what companies do to their employees and how they can do it, even at the cost of higher unemployment and a welfare state, would be tragic only to folks who'd like to see us return to a 6x12 hour work week.  -- Robert Guido</p>
        <p>Sometimes I wonder at the arrogance of the bottom-line mentalities in American enterprises. What makes these policy-makers worth enormous salaries while making judgments about people they never see and don't know, in business situations they never enter themselves. If this is what stockholders want--a quick return versus a good, steady, respected business, they will reap what they sow. When you disrespect your employees, you end up harming your business reputation--they disrespect customers and, since they have nothing to lose, don't treat co-workers collegially or treat other business contacts well. The enterprise gets a reputation as a lousy place to work, awful with suppliers, and many long-term customers feel dirty dealing with it--just look at Wal-Mart.  -- Carl Ian Schwartz</p>
        <p>When companies provide perverse incentives to their management in the form of bonuses tied to improving productivity, reducing operating expenses, and "wringing out inefficiencies", you can bet your bottom dollar that unbridled greed and selfishness will come to the fore. No longer is the prospect of a pat on the back, a promotion, or a salary increase sufficient motivation. The chance for the (personal) big score, by those in middle management on up to the CEO, ensures that any sense of morality and righteousness be damned. For the right price, most people in power can rationalize anything. This is the difference between capitalism in America today and how it was 20 years ago. And it's frightening.  - Richard Surwilo</p>
        <p>I notice you did not mention that the CEO did not take a pay cut of his overly lavish salary, which in comparison is 3 timesthe amount of the Best Buy CEO's base salary. The debate for the coming decade will be not about the pension and health insurance but about how badly (and gleefully) are the CEO's going to squeeze their employees to their own (and the company's) benefit. Logic would dictate that firing your best sales people is counter productive to sales over the long term. If you have bad sales help selling merchandise, overall customer service will suffer.  - Thanos Perlegas</p>
        <p>My experience as both a corporate employee and a consumer of corporate stuff leads me to believe that corporations are grossly (qualitative standard) ineffective at exploiting the experience of their workers. To offset that failure, the companies dumb down their products, services and marketing along with the requirements for the resources (people) who produce the goods or deliver the services.</p>
        <p>The "Salesperson" who's familiar with the contents of the entire store is replaced by the "Hardware Associate" who knows a bit about what's in the hardware section. The Associate is replaced by the "Door Hardware Aisle Expert" who is, in turn, replaced by the "Doorstop Genius". The job descriptions get loftier, The pay and morale gets lower. The products become more generic and less diverse. After-market service and support, for which there is no substitute for experience, disappears entirely. The cost of goods rarely goes down.</p>
        <p>I suppose that I'm bothered by reading an article that employs a dubious business model to explain away corporate behavior which is not only extraordinarily greedy (qualitative again), but often self-destructive. I'd much rather read an piece about why Circuit City didn't fire the managers who couldn't control cost while improving service or one about what Investment Bankers and their ilk really do that justifies their apparent exemption from your analysis.  -- David Cohen</p>
        <p>It took 60 years for us to realize that Karl Marx was wrong about Communism; it has taken 20 years for us to realize he was right about Capitalism.  - Bob Dolsen</p>
        <p>Circuit City employees did it to themselves. Have you ever tried to buy anything there? The employees fall in right behind the airlines as incompetent and totally disengaged. I would drive by a Circuit City and go 15 miles out of my way to find products that I need versus stopping at one of their stores. The employee population of Circuit City needs to look in the mirror and admit to themselves "it isn't about usit is about our customers". By the way, I am not saying that Best Buy and Comp-USA are significantly better. They are simply less "worse" than Circuit City.  - Tom DeGroff</p>
        <p>It's incredulous that someone writing for the New York Times to not mention the decline of labor unions as a reason for the cuts at Circuit City and general decline of wages and benefits across the board for working Americans.</p>
        <p>Did you actually think corporations gave all those benefits out of the kindness of their hearts? No, those benefits were forced out of corporations with the threat of withholding labor. The simple fact is that corporations hold a lot more of the cards. This isn't about economics, it's about raw power and the working person's lack of it these days.  -- Steve Dondley</p>
        <p>What people seem to failing to notice about this is the statement is making to the consumers. Circuit City, already not known for its customer service, is telling all of us that they can serve us, the customer, with anyone off the street. The people they are letting go are the cream of their crop; the people who know how to do the returns, how to fill out warranties, and provide what little service Circuit City feels like providing. This company sounds like it is run by a management team that has never purchased, or shopped, in Circuit City, much less worked in the store to know how things should be run.  - Steve Kline</p>
        <p>The stock price of Circuit City is basically unchanged in the last 5 years ($20/share). What has the board done about management and what have shareholders done about the Board? They have problems a lot larger than 3,400 overpaid ($18/hr average) workers.  -- Jack Stock</p>
        <p>Great article. This really isn't a new occurrence. I went to work for Sears Roebuck in the early 70's as a sales person. After a period of about 6 months as a 'part time' worker, I was put on at full time.</p>
        <p>(Part time was a joke of sorts. They would put you on the work schedule for 40 hours a week for a few of months. As the full 40 hour work week approached where they would have to begin to offer benefits, retirement plans, etc., they would move you to a 29 hour work week avoiding the pay-out of the benefits.)</p>
        <p>Then, in the mid 70's, all the legitimate full time sales employees were laid off. Some of the sales staff had 15 to 20 years of service and were no longer in the prime hiring age. The department managers were unaffected by this. Sears then hired all part time sales staff.</p>
        <p>No benefits, retirement, etc. I don't think my mom has shopped at Sears since.  - Kent McLaughlin</p>
        <p>You list several things that the government was going to need to do, but nothing about changing the way businesses are taxed, like the little game of going off-shore to avoid taxes and such.  -- A.M. Solomon</p>
        <p>Recently, my wife and I went into Circuit City to buy a new laptop for my son. The salesperson we were dealing with was professional and pretty much knew what he was talking about. The problem was that while we were talking two young guys, sales people, had the stereo's system on so loud we could hardly hear. They were also goofing off and wrestling. Needless to say, it was unprofessional. My wife and I mentioned it and the volume went down - a little. We finally left and decided not to buy the laptop at Circuit City.</p>
        <p>Week later, we went to Best Buy. Very professional staff, well organized, and we ended up buying from them. Is there a lesson here?  -- Philip E. Quigley</p>
        <p>It is curious to note that while the "safety nets"for the average worker are being drastically cut for the sake of corporate efficiency, the "safety net" for the average executive is being drastically raised, in many cases this occurs in spite of poor performance. The average worker assumes , probably correctly, that the two are connected.  - Lars Borgeson</p>
        <p>I respectfully disagree with your statement that "If companies aren't going to provide health insurance, the government will need to." This either/or dichotomy is a phony one, since there are other options. Namely, how about if individuals buy their own insurance and health care in a competitive free market? To begin with, people need to be educated about the real purpose of insurance: spreading the risk to protect against catastrophic loss. Expecting insurance to pick up the tab for routine exams and check-ups is as unreasonable as expecting car insurance to pick up the tab for routine auto maintenance, repairs, and fill-ups. Furthermore, having a third-party pick up the tab -- as if there is such a thing as a "free lunch" -- seriously distorts price mechanisms because consumers don't know the cost of the services they are receiving, don't care what the cost is, and there is no incentive for them to shop around for a better deal.  - Heidi Crimmin</p>
        <p>I very much enjoyed your excellent article. But please don't perpetuate the false dichotomy about the possibilities for universal health insurance. A single-payer system and a pool for the uninsured are not the only choices. I'm an American citizen who has lived in Europe (Germany and the Netherlands) for many years. Health insurance is simply compulsory. For those with jobs, the premiums are paid by employer and employee. For students, the unemployed, etc., there are special low rates and the government helps out. The result: there are virtually no ''uninsured'' residents!  - Joel Ethan Fried</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The following are excerpts to David Leonhardt's April 4 column on the layoffs at Circuit City and the corporate safety net:</p>
        <p>David, I'm surprised you would suggest there is no economic logic to increased pay for more experienced workers. If the only measure of worker quality were efficiency, it might follow that greybeards with bad knees aren't worth the extra pay. But workers are not just machines -- even workers who run machines all day -- and the quality of their work can't just be tracked empirically on a flow chart.</p>
        <p>Experienced workers who interact with customers can generate goodwill along with increased sales. Those who work in the "back room" (or on the factory line) can contribute important suggestions for jobsite improvements. They are also typically more reliable than younger workers.</p>
        <p>But there is another economic logic behind more pay for more age. In one sense a career can be thought of as a wasting asset--when it "expires" (at retirement or death), that's it. Game over. Thus it stands to reason that individuals want to feel like their career "asset" is increasing in value before it expires. You'd expect the same from an oil field.  -- Max Alexander</p>
        <p>Max, I do think that there are some solid economic reasons pay rises more rapidly than productivity over a person's career. For one thing, it inspires loyalty (a point that Ed Lazear, the current chairman of President Bush's Council of Economic Advisers, has made in his academic work). But I think it's also in part a social custom. And more companies seem to be deciding it's a social custom they no longer want to follow. -- David Leonhardt</p>
        <p>Your article, while well-intentioned, lacks a certain completeness in analysis that undermines your credibility. It is agreed that social safety nets can help dampen the otherwise harsh effects of pure capitalism, especially when those effects have an impact on our older, presumably wiser population. However, your assertion that government should step in and "save the day" without any mention of an individual's responsibility to use his/her resources (labor, education, financial) wisely is tantamount to the argument that America can "make" Iraq a democracy through the increased use of force. That is, it is simply ridiculous.</p>
        <p>The fact that U.S. savings rates are near zero if not negative, that our nation has elected an administration whose priorities are squarely aligned with further enriching the wealthy, and that so many have purchased homes beyond their means suggests that the real issue is individual accountability by Americans. No amount of government meddling can overcome people who are unwilling to show a little restraint and discipline.  -- Cecyl Hobbs</p>
        <p>Great article, thank you. I found Home Depot used similar tactics with my wages when I invested three years of my life with them. After getting a score of 4, out of a possible 5, I received a $0.00 raise, after which my efforts as a sales associate where negatively impacted.</p>
        <p>This, after making a real effort, was more than a person should be subjected to, in terms of being treated with "decency".  - Colin Campbell</p>
        <p>There a few things that need to be done: Begin career development earlier in the education process in order to graduate a workforce that can fill the higher level positions that go begging, and as a result are filled by foreign workers, create a robust training program, increase awareness around skills, continuing education for those people already in the workforce, and revise the current healthcare system.  - Steve Guine</p>
        <p>A critical thing that I think got left out of this cold-hearted calculation of worker's worth, is how much it costs to hire and train new workers. I simply won't shop in places where the sales associates don't know the product, especially for technical gadgets and consumer electronics. It's far more helpful to do my research online and shop there. If the local retailers can't pay there people enough to educate them and retain their experience, I won't patronize them.</p>
        <p>So there's the cost of hiring, the cost of training, and the cost of lost sales no wonder Circuit City is doing badly, and my local CompUSA just went out ot business. Perhaps if they tried a more win-win model like personal service to counteract online sales they would build CUSTOMER loyalty. But you have to build WORKER loyalty first.  - Michele Matossian</p>
        <p>Your article also explains why, when you wish to buy something at Circuit City, the knowledge of their employees and the service, if you find what you need to purchase, is dreadful. Waiting in line for 1 clerk, that handles internet sales, store sales, and returns is a challenge. It is also why I no longer shop at Circuit City or Wall Mart.  - Linda Metnetsky</p>
        <p>I first heard the retraining panacea trotted out years ago by Robert Reich, on public radio. I was a young IT professional then, and already skeptical of the whole notion of retraining, knowing just how fast things change, how easy it was to fall behind, and how much harder it is to learn with passing time -- just a glance at my parents struggling with every new device and social change, and it was obvious. Now that I am an older IT professional in a far more merciless corporate environment than then, I cringe when I hear the words "retraining" clopping around at the back of the mental barn of liberal economists, like the vague afterthought it always is. It is no more viable a solution now than it was then.</p>
        <p>I am sorry, but the option that is not viable here is to let massive companies like Circuit City treat their employees like last year's stock. At least if we want to maintain the thin veneer of living in a civilization, as opposed to a Victorian industrial slum. Placing some controls over what companies do to their employees and how they can do it, even at the cost of higher unemployment and a welfare state, would be tragic only to folks who'd like to see us return to a 6x12 hour work week.  -- Robert Guido</p>
        <p>Sometimes I wonder at the arrogance of the bottom-line mentalities in American enterprises. What makes these policy-makers worth enormous salaries while making judgments about people they never see and don't know, in business situations they never enter themselves. If this is what stockholders want--a quick return versus a good, steady, respected business, they will reap what they sow. When you disrespect your employees, you end up harming your business reputation--they disrespect customers and, since they have nothing to lose, don't treat co-workers collegially or treat other business contacts well. The enterprise gets a reputation as a lousy place to work, awful with suppliers, and many long-term customers feel dirty dealing with it--just look at Wal-Mart.  -- Carl Ian Schwartz</p>
        <p>When companies provide perverse incentives to their management in the form of bonuses tied to improving productivity, reducing operating expenses, and "wringing out inefficiencies", you can bet your bottom dollar that unbridled greed and selfishness will come to the fore. No longer is the prospect of a pat on the back, a promotion, or a salary increase sufficient motivation. The chance for the (personal) big score, by those in middle management on up to the CEO, ensures that any sense of morality and righteousness be damned. For the right price, most people in power can rationalize anything. This is the difference between capitalism in America today and how it was 20 years ago. And it's frightening.  - Richard Surwilo</p>
        <p>I notice you did not mention that the CEO did not take a pay cut of his overly lavish salary, which in comparison is 3 timesthe amount of the Best Buy CEO's base salary. The debate for the coming decade will be not about the pension and health insurance but about how badly (and gleefully) are the CEO's going to squeeze their employees to their own (and the company's) benefit. Logic would dictate that firing your best sales people is counter productive to sales over the long term. If you have bad sales help selling merchandise, overall customer service will suffer.  - Thanos Perlegas</p>
        <p>My experience as both a corporate employee and a consumer of corporate stuff leads me to believe that corporations are grossly (qualitative standard) ineffective at exploiting the experience of their workers. To offset that failure, the companies dumb down their products, services and marketing along with the requirements for the resources (people) who produce the goods or deliver the services.</p>
        <p>The "Salesperson" who's familiar with the contents of the entire store is replaced by the "Hardware Associate" who knows a bit about what's in the hardware section. The Associate is replaced by the "Door Hardware Aisle Expert" who is, in turn, replaced by the "Doorstop Genius". The job descriptions get loftier, The pay and morale gets lower. The products become more generic and less diverse. After-market service and support, for which there is no substitute for experience, disappears entirely. The cost of goods rarely goes down.</p>
        <p>I suppose that I'm bothered by reading an article that employs a dubious business model to explain away corporate behavior which is not only extraordinarily greedy (qualitative again), but often self-destructive. I'd much rather read an piece about why Circuit City didn't fire the managers who couldn't control cost while improving service or one about what Investment Bankers and their ilk really do that justifies their apparent exemption from your analysis.  -- David Cohen</p>
        <p>It took 60 years for us to realize that Karl Marx was wrong about Communism; it has taken 20 years for us to realize he was right about Capitalism.  - Bob Dolsen</p>
        <p>Circuit City employees did it to themselves. Have you ever tried to buy anything there? The employees fall in right behind the airlines as incompetent and totally disengaged. I would drive by a Circuit City and go 15 miles out of my way to find products that I need versus stopping at one of their stores. The employee population of Circuit City needs to look in the mirror and admit to themselves "it isn't about usit is about our customers". By the way, I am not saying that Best Buy and Comp-USA are significantly better. They are simply less "worse" than Circuit City.  - Tom DeGroff</p>
        <p>It's incredulous that someone writing for the New York Times to not mention the decline of labor unions as a reason for the cuts at Circuit City and general decline of wages and benefits across the board for working Americans.</p>
        <p>Did you actually think corporations gave all those benefits out of the kindness of their hearts? No, those benefits were forced out of corporations with the threat of withholding labor. The simple fact is that corporations hold a lot more of the cards. This isn't about economics, it's about raw power and the working person's lack of it these days.  -- Steve Dondley</p>
        <p>What people seem to failing to notice about this is the statement is making to the consumers. Circuit City, already not known for its customer service, is telling all of us that they can serve us, the customer, with anyone off the street. The people they are letting go are the cream of their crop; the people who know how to do the returns, how to fill out warranties, and provide what little service Circuit City feels like providing. This company sounds like it is run by a management team that has never purchased, or shopped, in Circuit City, much less worked in the store to know how things should be run.  - Steve Kline</p>
        <p>The stock price of Circuit City is basically unchanged in the last 5 years ($20/share). What has the board done about management and what have shareholders done about the Board? They have problems a lot larger than 3,400 overpaid ($18/hr average) workers.  -- Jack Stock</p>
        <p>Great article. This really isn't a new occurrence. I went to work for Sears Roebuck in the early 70's as a sales person. After a period of about 6 months as a 'part time' worker, I was put on at full time.</p>
        <p>(Part time was a joke of sorts. They would put you on the work schedule for 40 hours a week for a few of months. As the full 40 hour work week approached where they would have to begin to offer benefits, retirement plans, etc., they would move you to a 29 hour work week avoiding the pay-out of the benefits.)</p>
        <p>Then, in the mid 70's, all the legitimate full time sales employees were laid off. Some of the sales staff had 15 to 20 years of service and were no longer in the prime hiring age. The department managers were unaffected by this. Sears then hired all part time sales staff.</p>
        <p>No benefits, retirement, etc. I don't think my mom has shopped at Sears since.  - Kent McLaughlin</p>
        <p>You list several things that the government was going to need to do, but nothing about changing the way businesses are taxed, like the little game of going off-shore to avoid taxes and such.  -- A.M. Solomon</p>
        <p>Recently, my wife and I went into Circuit City to buy a new laptop for my son. The salesperson we were dealing with was professional and pretty much knew what he was talking about. The problem was that while we were talking two young guys, sales people, had the stereo's system on so loud we could hardly hear. They were also goofing off and wrestling. Needless to say, it was unprofessional. My wife and I mentioned it and the volume went down - a little. We finally left and decided not to buy the laptop at Circuit City.</p>
        <p>Week later, we went to Best Buy. Very professional staff, well organized, and we ended up buying from them. Is there a lesson here?  -- Philip E. Quigley</p>
        <p>It is curious to note that while the "safety nets"for the average worker are being drastically cut for the sake of corporate efficiency, the "safety net" for the average executive is being drastically raised, in many cases this occurs in spite of poor performance. The average worker assumes , probably correctly, that the two are connected.  - Lars Borgeson</p>
        <p>I respectfully disagree with your statement that "If companies aren't going to provide health insurance, the government will need to." This either/or dichotomy is a phony one, since there are other options. Namely, how about if individuals buy their own insurance and health care in a competitive free market? To begin with, people need to be educated about the real purpose of insurance: spreading the risk to protect against catastrophic loss. Expecting insurance to pick up the tab for routine exams and check-ups is as unreasonable as expecting car insurance to pick up the tab for routine auto maintenance, repairs, and fill-ups. Furthermore, having a third-party pick up the tab -- as if there is such a thing as a "free lunch" -- seriously distorts price mechanisms because consumers don't know the cost of the services they are receiving, don't care what the cost is, and there is no incentive for them to shop around for a better deal.  - Heidi Crimmin</p>
        <p>I very much enjoyed your excellent article. But please don't perpetuate the false dichotomy about the possibilities for universal health insurance. A single-payer system and a pool for the uninsured are not the only choices. I'm an American citizen who has lived in Europe (Germany and the Netherlands) for many years. Health insurance is simply compulsory. For those with jobs, the premiums are paid by employer and employee. For students, the unemployed, etc., there are special low rates and the government helps out. The result: there are virtually no ''uninsured'' residents!  - Joel Ethan Fried</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
