<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Corzine's Signature, Taxpayers' Burden Lightens</title>
    <meta content="04property" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/nyregion/04property.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837870"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tax Credits, Deductions and Exemptions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Comptrollers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smothers, Ronald</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Policy Perspective</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hughes, James W</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Shure, Jon</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Roberts, Joseph J Jr</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Codey, Richard J</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E6DF163FF937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="809" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Corzine's Signature, Taxpayers' Burden Lightens</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With Corzine’s Signature, Taxpayers’ Burden Lightens</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smothers, Ronald</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, April 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov Jon s Corzine signs bills to give tax credit of up to 20 percent to New Jersey homeowners and force municipalities to cap annual local tax increases at 4 percent; predicts new strictures will prompt creative cost savings by local governments and entrepreneurial approaches to raising revenue; Republican legislators, including some who voted for bills, condemn them as unsustainable fixes and election-year gimmick; measures are part of package of legislation that also creates appointed state comptroller, changes public employee pensions, establishes process to streamline and consolidate local governments and school districts and holds annual wage increases in pending labor contract at 3 to 3.5 percent (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Culminating a nine-month effort to bring some measure of relief to property owners in New Jersey, Gov. Jon S. Corzine on Tuesday signed into law the centerpiece of a package of bills that will give a tax credit of up to 20 percent to homeowners and force municipalities to cap annual local tax increases at 4 percent.</p>
        <p>The effort began last summer with a series of hearings around the state by committees made up of lawmakers, who had been urged by the governor and their own leaders to come up with a broad array of ways to overhaul property taxes. It ended in the current legislative session amid compromises and recriminations in partisan votes in the Senate and the Assembly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The tax credit culminates a nine-month effort to bring some measure of relief to property owners in New Jersey.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Culminating a nine-month effort to bring some measure of relief to property owners in New Jersey, Gov. Jon S. Corzine on Tuesday signed into law the centerpiece of a package of bills that will give a tax credit of up to 20 percent to homeowners and force municipalities to cap annual local tax increases at 4 percent.</p>
        <p>The effort began last summer with a series of hearings around the state by committees made up of lawmakers, who had been urged by the governor and their own leaders to come up with a broad array of ways to overhaul property taxes. It ended in the current legislative session amid compromises and recriminations in partisan votes in the Senate and the Assembly.</p>
        <p>''We have laid down a framework that if we execute it will make a difference,'' Mr. Corzine said.</p>
        <p>Under the tax credit measure, homeowners will receive a tax credit of $1,100 on average, and elderly homeowners will receive a credit up to $1,250. In all, 1.9 million taxpayers with annual incomes up to $250,000 -- or 95 percent of all property owners -- will receive a tax credit, and 800,000 renters will receive a credit of up to $350.</p>
        <p>And there is the 4 percent cap on local taxes, although towns and school districts will be able to apply for exemptions to seek voter approval to exceed the limit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine predicted that the new strictures would prompt creative cost savings by local governments and entrepreneurial approaches to raising revenue.</p>
        <p>In a ceremony at the War Memorial here, Mr. Corzine and the Democratic leaders, Assembly Speaker Joseph Roberts Jr. and Senate President Richard J. Codey, acknowledged that the measures were the result of compromise and fell short of what many had hoped would result.</p>
        <p>But the governor insisted that the bills represented ''extraordinary'' progress on a problem that has bedeviled the state for more than 30 years and which has resulted in average 7 percent annual increases in local property taxes in the last five years.</p>
        <p>He called attention to other parts of the tax package and said that when combined with the credits to homeowners and the caps on municipal taxes, the state had created the beginnings of lasting reform.</p>
        <p>He was referring to the creation of an appointed state comptroller; changes in public employee pensions; establishment of a process to streamline and consolidate local governments and school districts; and a pending labor contract that holds annual wage increases at 3 to 3.5 percent.</p>
        <p>''It will take years to see if this unfolds as we hope, but the tax relief is real and the credits are on their way,'' Mr. Corzine said.</p>
        <p>But before the ink was dry, Republican legislators -- including some who had approved the measures -- condemned them as unsustainable fixes and an election-year gimmick.</p>
        <p>''It is disgraceful that after all the grandiose promises, the governor and the Trenton Democrats have made that the best they could deliver,'' said the Assembly minority leader, Alexander DeCroce of Morris County, who voted for the plan.</p>
        <p>The Senate minority leader, Leonard Lance of Ewing, who voted against the tax credit measure, called the package ''modest tax relief but not property tax reform.''</p>
        <p>Observing that recent estimates by the state treasurer and the Legislature's own experts foresee a deficit of $2.5 billion in the years to come, he said, ''I have the greatest concern about its sustainability in Year 2 and onward.''</p>
        <p>Nor was Mr. Lance alone in his concerns. James W. Hughes, the dean of the Edward J. Bloustein School of Planning and Public Policy at Rutgers University, said that he would not call the series of actions ''property tax reform as yet.''</p>
        <p>Taking account of the state's projected budget deficits and increases in debt service, Mr. Hughes said the current economic projections suggested that ''it will be difficult for us to grow ourselves out of the structural deficit'' with rising tax receipts.</p>
        <p>This prospect, he added, made it seem likely that the Legislature would seriously have to consider Mr. Corzine's idea of selling or leasing such state assets as the Turnpike and the lottery to continue the tax credits, a move that Democrats and Republicans alike are wary of.</p>
        <p>Jon Shure, president of New Jersey Policy Perspective, a nonpartisan research group, said that the group was certain that Mr. Corzine and others were ''not deluding people by trying to sell this as the ultimate in property tax reform.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Shure emphasized that real reform rested in deciding how to shift the financing of education from local property taxes to more broadly based state and county taxes.</p>
        <p>''If you want to spend half as much or twice as much,'' he said, ''you need a fair and adequate way to raise the money, and we aren't much closer to that today than we were before this bill was signed.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
