<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Jumble of Instruments, A Sound as Smooth as Glass</title>
    <meta content="04amii" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/arts/music/04amii.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070405T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837950"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iceland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Iceland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Musical Instruments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Musical Instruments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iceland</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E3D81F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="577" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Jumble of Instruments, A Sound as Smooth as Glass</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Jumble of Instruments, a Sound as Smooth as Glass</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN RATLIFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ratliff, Ben</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Amiina is an Icelandic string quartet whose members also make music with wordless vocals, keyboards, zither, saw, vibraphone, echoed-up music boxes, guitar, mandolin, xylophone and tuned, brightly colored desk bells, like the kind you ring for the concierge.</p>
        <p>During the group's show on Monday night at the Good Shepherd-Faith Presbyterian Church, near Lincoln Center, each musician changed instruments for almost every song. All this branching out could rupture the purity of the string-quartet ideal, you'd think. But Amiina's sound seemed to grow purer and more weightless as its instrumentation spread. At its best, the group set up even striations of plinkiness on the higher levels: the thinnest being the zither, then the xylophone or vibraphone, or both. A cello and one or two violins were on the bottom.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Amiina, an Icelandic string quartet whose members make music using a small army of odd instruments, brought a pure and weightless sound to the Good Shepherd-Faith Presbyterian Church on Monday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Amiina is an Icelandic string quartet whose members also make music with wordless vocals, keyboards, zither, saw, vibraphone, echoed-up music boxes, guitar, mandolin, xylophone and tuned, brightly colored desk bells, like the kind you ring for the concierge.</p>
        <p>During the group's show on Monday night at the Good Shepherd-Faith Presbyterian Church, near Lincoln Center, each musician changed instruments for almost every song. All this branching out could rupture the purity of the string-quartet ideal, you'd think. But Amiina's sound seemed to grow purer and more weightless as its instrumentation spread. At its best, the group set up even striations of plinkiness on the higher levels: the thinnest being the zither, then the xylophone or vibraphone, or both. A cello and one or two violins were on the bottom.</p>
        <p>Amiina developed over the last few years as the string section for Sigur Ros, the Reykjavik band that orchestrates large-scale cathedral rock, and so the four musicians in the group -- Edda Run Olafsdottir, Hildur Arsaelsdottir, Maria Huld Markan Sigfusdottir and Solrun Sumarlidadottir -- know about elegant repetitions, and about playing directly on the emotions. Alone, though, Amiina doesn't do rock dynamics.</p>
        <p>The show was the fifth of the innovative new concert series called Wordless Music, which is elegantly intersecting rock and classical music, and Amiina makes good sense to classical-music audiences. The violin parts were often in unison or close harmony, and the writing tended to be consonant and diatonic, with unprepossessing, steady rhythmic cycles: a little Michael Nyman was in there, perhaps.</p>
        <p>If you were cruel enough to pick apart such a small thing, you might find a lack of tone. Amiina's music feels scrubbed clean of all grain, the surface of living things; it's smooth as glass, even with the four-part vocal harmonies, even with its more folkish instruments. But this is the sound the group is seeking, and it gets it with efficacy.</p>
        <p>Opening for Amiina was Eluvium, a k a the American musician and composer Matthew Cooper, who writes his soft or loud minimalism for electric guitar, keyboard and laptop computer. He played two kinds of pieces. One was repeated, finger-picked guitar melodies, backed by wavelike, unbroken guitar counterlines, recorded and coming from the laptop, which grew in volume. Eventually the laptop music, fed through digital delay, took over with brute force, drowning out the real-time playing, and finished the piece. And then there were simple, consonant and repetitive piano études, limper and less dramatic. To put the audience in the right clear-mind state, there were film projections of birds flying in a blue sky.</p>
        <p>With a delay box and a few records by Erik Satie and My Bloody Valentine, Mr. Cooper could go on making pieces like this forever. But they were a little anemic, especially compared with what they had followed. Representing the classical-conservatory tradition, the Swiss-born pianist Gilles Vonsattel started the evening with two short pieces -- Ravel's ''Ondine'' and Bartok's ''Out of Doors'' -- and they contained some rippling rhythms and bits of layered repetition that naturally connected them to Eluvium and Amiina. But it wasn't lotus-eating, ear-tickling music. The polyrhythm and polytonality of this music, especially in the Bartok, put it in a species of complexity that neither Eluvium or Amiina was interested in reaching.</p>
        <p>The next concert in the Wordless Music Series features two ensembles, the Books and Real Quiet, and takes place April 20 at the New York Society for Ethical Culture, 2 West 64th Street; wordlessmusic.org.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 5, 2007, Thursday  Because of an editing error, schedule information yesterday with a music review of a concert in the Wordless Music Series misstated the date of the next concert in the series. It is April 30, not April 20, at the New York Society for Ethical Culture on West 64th Street in Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 5, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, schedule information yesterday with a music review of a concert in the Wordless Music Series misstated the date of the next concert in the series. It is April 30, not April 20, at the New York Society for Ethical Culture on West 64th Street in Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
