<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hernández Does It All, On the Mound And at the Plate</title>
    <meta content="04mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/sports/baseball/04mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837904"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">St Louis Cardinals</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hernandez, Orlando</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CEEDF163FF937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="915" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hernández Does It All, On the Mound And at the Plate</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hernández Does the Job on the Mound and at the Plate for Mets</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shpigel, Ben</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS, April 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Orlando Hernández has more arm angles than an octopus and only slightly more career hits. And yet when he strode to the plate with the bases loaded in the sixth inning against the Cardinals on Tuesday night, it somehow seemed plausible -- expected, almost -- that Hernandez would drive in a few runs.</p>
        <p>Nothing about Hernández surprises the Mets anymore, particularly how easily he dispatched the Cardinals in their 4-1 victory at Busch Stadium. He allowed one run and five hits in seven splendid innings and at the plate notched two hits, including the two-run double that gave the bullpen some additional comfort when things turned hairy for a few moments in the eighth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Orlando Hernández allowed one run and five hits in seven splendid innings and also added two hits, including a two-run double that supplied the bullpen with some additional comfort.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Orlando Hernández has more arm angles than an octopus and only slightly more career hits. And yet when he strode to the plate with the bases loaded in the sixth inning against the Cardinals on Tuesday night, it somehow seemed plausible -- expected, almost -- that Hernandez would drive in a few runs.</p>
        <p>Nothing about Hernández surprises the Mets anymore, particularly how easily he dispatched the Cardinals in their 4-1 victory at Busch Stadium. He allowed one run and five hits in seven splendid innings and at the plate notched two hits, including the two-run double that gave the bullpen some additional comfort when things turned hairy for a few moments in the eighth.</p>
        <p>''Just good luck,'' said Hernández, who also singled in the third. ''If I hit, that's O.K. But I'm more happy that I threw seven innings.''</p>
        <p>Hernández carved through the Cardinals' lineup with precision. Again and again he changed speeds on his fastball, mixing in some change-ups, too, although his best pitch was his curveball. It measured as slow as 65 m.p.h, and almost every time he threw it for a first-pitch strike, setting up the hitter for a rough at-bat.</p>
        <p>''When a guy throws that pitch, it locks you in, especially at 0-0,'' catcher Paul Lo Duca said. ''At 0-1, he can throw you four pitches, all for strikes.''</p>
        <p>Cardinals Manager Tony LaRussa said, ''Early in the season if you have command of your off-speed stuff, it's a big advantage against hitters.''</p>
        <p>On opening night, the Mets watched the Cardinals' world championship banner sail up the flagpole, then answered by beating them decisively. They treated Tuesday's pregame ring ceremony, the final installment of the Cardinals' prolonged celebration, with similar nonchalance, and then went out and beat them soundly again. Over the past six years, the Mets have won only four regular-season games here. They are now a victory away from sweeping the defending World Champions.</p>
        <p>All through the spring, as the losses piled up, the Mets never got flustered. But at the same time, more than one player expressed concern that, as much as they wanted to, the Mets could not just wake up one morning and decide that they were going to win that day. And yet, that is almost exactly what has happened. The fielding has been slick, the hitting has been timely and the starting pitching has been excellent: Hernández and Tom Glavine have combined to allow two runs in 13 innings.</p>
        <p>About five weeks ago, Hernández abruptly left spring training because of an arthritic neck and the Mets worried that he would be all right for the start of the season. Upon returning, he allayed those fears by resuming his training regimen and gradually regaining the feel of his pitches. He threw only 12 spring innings, and 10 came against the Cardinals. That familiarity did not seem to help them much.</p>
        <p>Hernández induced three double-play grounders -- the Cardinals have hit into seven in two games -- and until Scott Rolen's leadoff homer in the seventh, only one Cardinal reached second base -- Albert Pujols -- and he was stranded there after hitting a first-inning double.</p>
        <p>''It's almost like he does it on purpose to lull you into a false sense,'' Randolph said of Hernández's ability to pitch with runners on base.</p>
        <p>The Cardinals tried capitalizing on Hernández's departure by mounting a two-out, eighth-inning rally off Scott Schoeneweis, as David Eckstein walked and moved to third on Chris Duncan's single. With Pujols up next, Randolph replaced Schoeneweis with a right-hander, Aaron Heilman. They went back and forth --ball, strike; ball, strike; ball -- before Heilman unleashed a fastball that tailed inside on Pujols. He got jammed just enough to fly out to center.</p>
        <p>''You want him to put the ball in play,'' Heilman said. ''Hopefully you have a good sequence where he's not able to square the ball up.''</p>
        <p>The Cardinals' starter, Kip Wells, struck out seven in six innings, but committed a regrettable mistake by walking the leadoff hitter José Reyes in the first inning. Reyes danced off the bag, pretending he was going to steal, drawing Wells's attention. After nearly picking off Reyes, Wells threw the ball away, allowing him to advance to second. With Reyes in scoring position, what ensued was almost expected: Lo Duca sacrifice, Carlos Beltran sacrifice fly, and the Mets led, 1-0.</p>
        <p>They added their second run in the fifth, and again Reyes's speed played a role. After lashing a two-out single, he bolted toward second. The catcher Yadier Molina double-clutched, giving Reyes an extra split-second to slide in safely. Lo Duca followed by sending a liner toward right field that Skip Schumaker, a surprise starter, appeared to have lined up. He stuck his glove up while lunging forward, and the ball sailed over his head for a two-base error.</p>
        <p>The Mets extended their lead with two outs in the sixth when, with Carlos Delgado and David Wright on base, Wells threw a wild pitch that left open first base. The Cardinals intentionally walked Jose Valentin to pitch to Hernández. A wise move in theory. But Hernández smoked the pitch down the third-base line, scoring Delgado and Wright. It was career hit No. 12 for Hernández, and in the dugout the Mets started cracking up. But, as Lo Duca said later, they weren't surprised. They just weren't.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Cardinals ace Chris Carpenter will miss Friday's scheduled start against Houston because of inflammation in his right elbow and will be replaced by Adam Wainwright.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
