<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chase Is Said To Plan Tower Near 9/11 Site</title>
    <meta content="04rebuild" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/nyregion/04rebuild.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837895"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Morgan, J P, &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Port Authority of New York and New Jersey</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bagli, Charles V</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Morgan, J P, Chase &amp; Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EFDF163FF937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="927" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chase Is Said To Plan Tower Near 9/11 Site</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Chase Is Said to Plan Tower Near 9/11 Site</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES V. BAGLI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bagli, Charles V</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>JPMorgan Chase is negotiating with state and city officials to build 50-story, 1.3-million-square-foot tower near site of World Trade Center and bring thousands of employees to Lower Manhattan from Midtown; deal would signal remarkable turnaround for neighborhood whose future seemed so dismal after 9/11, when many experts predicted that business district would never recover from terrorist attack; Chase seeks hefty incentive package, or subsidy; city, state and Port Authority appear eager to complete deal (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JPMorgan Chase is in negotiations with state and city officials to build a 1.3 million-square-foot skyscraper near ground zero and bring thousands of employees downtown from Midtown, according to government officials involved in the negotiations.</p>
        <p>If the deal is completed, it will represent a remarkable turnaround for a neighborhood whose future seemed so dismal after Sept. 11, when many experts predicted that the business district would never recover from the terrorist attack.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The bank would build a 1.3 million-square-foot skyscraper near ground zero and bring thousands of employees downtown from Midtown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JPMorgan Chase is in negotiations with state and city officials to build a 1.3 million-square-foot skyscraper near ground zero and bring thousands of employees downtown from Midtown, according to government officials involved in the negotiations.</p>
        <p>If the deal is completed, it will represent a remarkable turnaround for a neighborhood whose future seemed so dismal after Sept. 11, when many experts predicted that the business district would never recover from the terrorist attack.</p>
        <p>Chase wants a hefty incentive package, or subsidy, to build the 50-story tower on the site of the Deutsche Bank building, the officials said. The building would have to cantilever over a planned park along Liberty Street to accommodate large trading floors, and that could stir community opposition.</p>
        <p>But officials say the bank has already agreed to pay the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey as much as $300 million for the development rights on the parcel at the corner of Cedar and Greenwich Streets. The Deutsche Bank building, which now sits on the land, was heavily damaged in the attack on the trade center and, after a series of delays, is being demolished.</p>
        <p>City, state and Port Authority officials appear eager to complete the deal, something that could be accomplished in a couple of weeks. But few officials were willing to discuss the matter for fear of disrupting the talks over the incentive package.</p>
        <p>''We're continuing negotiations,'' Stephen Sigmund, a Port Authority spokesman, said in a terse statement. ''Any agreement would need to bring substantial value to the Port Authority and be good for Lower Manhattan and the region.''</p>
        <p>Michael Fusco, a spokesman for JPMorgan Chase, declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Eric J. Deutsch, president of the Alliance for Downtown New York, a business group, was ebullient. ''It's enormously encouraging for Lower Manhattan,'' he said. ''It proves that this is an ideal location for major financial services firms. Only a few years ago, many were concerned about the viability of Lower Manhattan as a central business district.''</p>
        <p>After Sept. 11, downtown stalwarts like Lehman Brothers fled the area for Midtown, prompting many urban planners and landlords to wonder what would become of the city's historic financial district. More than 12 million square feet of office space was destroyed in the attack, and an additional 13 million square feet was later converted to apartments. As a result, Lower Manhattan slipped from the third to the fourth largest central business district in the country, behind Midtown Manhattan, Chicago and Washington.</p>
        <p>Only a year ago, with commercial vacancy rates downtown still relatively high, rebuilding officials suggested that four new office towers on the World Trade Center site were more than enough; the Deutsche Bank site, at 130 Liberty Street, could be used for a residential tower, they said.</p>
        <p>But as office rents soared in Midtown, downtown became a more attractive alternative, and the vacancy rate dropped. The Freedom Tower is under construction at ground zero, and Goldman Sachs is building a new, two-million-square-foot headquarters across West Street, in Battery Park City. Real estate executives say that Merrill Lynch, another downtown investment bank, is considering expanding at Battery Park City, by building enlarged trading floors on land behind 2 World Financial Center, or moving to a new tower at the trade center site.</p>
        <p>Last November, JPMorgan Chase approached the Port Authority about building a skyscraper for trading, investment bank and research operations on the Deutsche Bank land, which is known as Site 5. Officials say that the bank would bring thousands of employees downtown, from the 51-story tower it occupies at 277 Park Avenue, at 47th Street, and consolidate some offices downtown. The bank's headquarters would remain across the street at 270 Park Avenue.</p>
        <p>Officials say that the bank initially said it wanted an incentive deal comparable to the one given Goldman Sachs in 2005. In return for building a $2 billion tower, state and city officials gave Goldman Sachs the right to sell $1.67 billion in tax-free bonds and tens of millions of dollars in tax breaks in what critics described as an egregious example of corporate welfare.</p>
        <p>Both Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg and Gov. Eliot Spitzer have told companies that that they will never duplicate that level of benefits. Officials say that talks are continuing.</p>
        <p>Only six years ago, Chase agreed to sell its tower at 60 Wall Street, and was leasing space at 1 Chase Manhattan Plaza downtown to other companies and moving employees to Midtown and Jersey City. But Midtown has become very expensive.</p>
        <p>The bank, however, has chosen the smallest of five possible building sites downtown. Officials say JPMorgan Chase was not interested in two other sites at the trade center, where the developer Larry A. Silverstein plans to build three office towers, preferring to control its own building.</p>
        <p>But some real estate executives complained that the Port Authority had effectively undercut Mr. Silverstein by allowing the bank to buy another site, which will not easily accommodate trading floors.</p>
        <p>Because the site is relatively small, some upper floors of the proposed tower would have to jut over a planned park and church on Liberty Street, as well as over Cedar Street. It would require public hearings and a change in the plan to rebuild Lower Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Julie Menin, the chairwoman of Community Board 1 in Lower Manhattan, said she had not seen the plans, but would object to a tower that overshadows a rare bit of parkland downtown. ''We have a dearth of open space in Lower Manhattan,'' she said. ''Anything that throws shadows is of concern to us.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
