<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Blames Democrats For Impasse Over Iraq Bills</title>
    <meta content="04prexy" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/washington/04prexy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837997"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reid, Harry (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rutenberg, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
        <org class="online_producer">House of Representatives</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Reid, Harry</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E0D71F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1062" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Blames Democrats For Impasse Over Iraq Bills</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bush Blames Democrats for Impasse Over Iraq Bills</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM RUTENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rutenberg, Jim</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush says Congressional Democrats have undercut troops by passing legislation that ties continued war financing to mandated timelines for withdrawal of American combat units from Iraq; Sen Harry Reid, majority leader, blames Bush for forcing deadlock; Sen Hillary Rodham Clinton begins online petition opposing veto that Bush has threatened to bills that include timelines (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The political brinkmanship over Iraq war spending intensified Tuesday, as President Bush said Congressional Democrats had ''undercut the troops'' by passing legislation that ties continued war financing to mandated timelines for the withdrawal of American combat units.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush used a morning news briefing to renew his promise to veto emergency war spending bills with the withdrawal provisions that have passed in the House and the Senate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The president said Congressional Democrats had “undercut the troops” by passing legislation that ties war financing to the withdrawal of combat units.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The political brinkmanship over Iraq war spending intensified Tuesday, as President Bush said Congressional Democrats had ''undercut the troops'' by passing legislation that ties continued war financing to mandated timelines for the withdrawal of American combat units.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush used a morning news briefing to renew his promise to veto emergency war spending bills with the withdrawal provisions that have passed in the House and the Senate.</p>
        <p>He blamed Democrats for a growing impasse, saying they had been irresponsible in pushing bills they knew he would not sign. ''Instead of passing clean bills that fund our troops on the front lines,'' he said, ''the House and Senate have spent this time debating bills that undercut the troops.''</p>
        <p>By speaking Tuesday from the Rose Garden, Mr. Bush was seeking to seize the stage in an increasingly heated standoff over war financing that carries political risks for both sides. Democrats immediately struck back, blaming the president for forcing a deadlock that has delayed the release of money for operations in Iraq and Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>''We represent the American people's views on this failed war,'' Senator Harry Reid, the Senate majority leader, said in his home state, Nevada, where he toured a National Guard complex. Mr. Reid released a statement that said: ''The president's policies have failed, and his escalation endangers our troops and hurts our national security. Neither our troops nor the American people can afford this strategy any longer.''</p>
        <p>The remarks from each side were among the most heated in the confrontation so far. They were made while Congress was in recess for the Easter holiday, but with Democrats unwilling to give Mr. Bush an open shot while they were away.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush warned that a failure by Congress to approve the $100 billion he had requested for the wars in Iraq and Afghanistan would prolong some tours in Iraq and shorten time at home between tours for others. ''That is unacceptable to me,'' he said. ''And I believe it is unacceptable to the American people.</p>
        <p>''It's one thing to object to the policy, but it's another thing when you have troops in harm's way not to give them the funds they need,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Among the signs of Democrats fighting back are an online petition begun by the presidential campaign of Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton of New York, expressing opposition to the veto that Mr. Bush has threatened for the bills that would attach timelines for withdrawal to the release of the war financing. ''Mr. President, please work with us,'' Mrs. Clinton said in a statement on Tuesday. ''Don't veto the will of the American people.''</p>
        <p>In his appearance on Tuesday, Mr. Bush alternately exhibited playfulness and annoyance, but issued a similarly pointed call for cooperation. ''If Democrat leaders in the Congress are bent on making a political statement, then they need to send me this unacceptable bill as quickly as possible when they come back,'' he said. ''I'll veto it, and then Congress can get down to the business of funding our troops without strings and without delay.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said during the news briefing that the wrangling over the language of the war financing bills threatened to have a serious effect on the troops themselves.</p>
        <p>He said that if he did not receive a bill he could sign by mid-April -- and he has said he can only sign a bill ''with no strings attached'' -- then the Army would be forced to consider curtailing equipment purchases and repairs and delay the training of National Guard and Reserve units.</p>
        <p>If the standoff goes into mid-May, he said, the Army would have to delay the training of active-duty units, which would affect tour schedules by prolonging the stays of personnel already in Iraq and Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>Democrats have argued that Mr. Bush made no such complaint last year when Congress, then held by Republicans, did not approve an emergency war spending measure until late spring. And the bill in the House, they said, would mandate that the president follow Pentagon policy limiting deployments and requiring a set period of rest between deployments -- one year for the Army; 210 days for the Marines -- or obtain waivers to ignore them.</p>
        <p>Each side is betting that it is correctly gauging the public mood. White House officials and Republican allies in Congress say they believe that the Democrats will lose the public if they overplay their position and are perceived to be putting troops at risk, while Democrats say election results that put them in power, and polls since, indicate that the public wants to pull out of Iraq and expects them to force a withdrawal.</p>
        <p>''I think the voters in America want Congress to support our troops who are in harm's way,'' Mr. Bush said. ''They don't want politicians in Washington telling our generals how to fight a war.''</p>
        <p>But even as he engaged in openly partisan battle, Mr. Bush at one point seemed to consciously back away from describing his opponents as ''the Democrat Party,'' a formulation that they take as a slight. ''It's irresponsible for the Democrat leadership -- Democratic leadership -- in Congress to delay for months on end while our troops in combat are waiting for the funds,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He was also faced with questions about recent critiques from his former allies: Matthew Dowd, the chief strategist of his 2004 campaign, who issued a broad critique of Mr. Bush in an interview last week, and Robert Novak, the conservative columnist who has called Mr. Bush extraordinarily isolated.</p>
        <p>''I respect Matthew,'' Mr. Bush said, ''He was an integral part of my 2004 campaign.'' But, noting that Mr. Dowd has a son in the Army who is awaiting deployment, Mr. Bush added, ''I understand his anguish over war; I understand this is an emotional issue for Matthew, as it is for a lot of other people in our country.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush seemed visibly annoyed when asked about Mr. Novak, saying first, ''How did he define 'isolated?' '' But, he said, ''I think you're going to find that the White House and the Hill are going to work in close collaboration, starting with this supplemental'' spending bill.</p>
        <p>No immediate progress is expected. Mr. Bush noted that the Democrats ''have left Washington for spring recess without finishing the work.'' The president himself will travel to Crawford, Tex., on Wednesday night to begin his own Easter break.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
