<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Takeoff for M.L.S., With Beckham In the Wings</title>
    <meta content="04soccer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/sports/soccer/04soccer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837900"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER: EXTRA TIME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Los Angeles Galaxy</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Major League Soccer</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Beckham, David</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406EEDF163FF937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1208" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Takeoff for M.L.S., With Beckham In the Wings</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Takeoff for M.L.S., With Beckham in the Wings</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK BELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bell, Jack</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is little doubt that 2007 is the Year of Beckham in Major League Soccer.</p>
        <p>While the Los Angeles Galaxy's signing of David Beckham appears to be the shot bent 'round the world, his arrival in July will merely be the biggest development for a league starting its 12th season Saturday. Although soccer is still a smudge on the radar of most American sports fans, M.L.S. has established itself as a fixture on the landscape, one that is poised to grow in a country of changing demographics and sporting tastes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although soccer still is a smudge on the radar of most American sports fans, M.L.S. is poised to grow in a country of changing demographics and sporting tastes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is little doubt that 2007 is the Year of Beckham in Major League Soccer.</p>
        <p>While the Los Angeles Galaxy's signing of David Beckham appears to be the shot bent 'round the world, his arrival in July will merely be the biggest development for a league starting its 12th season Saturday. Although soccer is still a smudge on the radar of most American sports fans, M.L.S. has established itself as a fixture on the landscape, one that is poised to grow in a country of changing demographics and sporting tastes.</p>
        <p>''It's fair to say that we at the league office never intended that this would be the only story of our off-season,'' Commissioner Don Garber said Monday during a conference call, referring to the signing of Beckham, 31, from Real Madrid. ''The Beckham story has taken on a life of its own.</p>
        <p>''But we don't believe any one thing will make soccer or M.L.S. one of the dominant sports in this country in the short term. A lot of individual things are happening at a slow, steady pace. Over the next 5, 10, 20 years, we have no doubt that this will be a dominant league in this country. It is not a matter of if, but when.''</p>
        <p>Where the league once had two groups (Anschutz Entertainment and Hunt Sports) controlling a majority of the clubs, there are 10 owners for 13 teams, with the addition of Toronto F.C. (There are new owners in Kansas City and Washington.) After struggling in cavernous stadiums where teams garnered little if any additional revenue, seven teams play in stadiums designed for soccer. Colorado and Toronto will open new buildings to start the season.</p>
        <p>The league, which dropped two teams before the 2002 season, has steadily added new clubs, with Toronto F. C. making it 13 this year with the expectation of growth to 16 teams in 2010. This season, for the first time, all games will be televised and the league will earn rights fees from ABC, ESPN, Univision and Fox.</p>
        <p>On the field, M.L.S. has begun an initiative called Game First, which will deal with matters as mundane as a uniform length for the grass at stadiums. M.L.S. has hired a full-time consultant based in South America who will aid in scouting and will institute a youth academy system that should enable teams to retain the rights to some players they develop.</p>
        <p>Yet a measured approach is no substitute for the jolt of publicity when Beckham finally arrives.</p>
        <p>The Rule</p>
        <p>David Beckham's signing became possible when M.L.S. officials approved the Designated Player Rule, which enables each team to sign a star player for a salary that exceeds the league maximum of about $300,000. M.L.S., which still owns all player contracts under its single-entity system, will pay the first $400,000 in salary; the rest is up to the club.</p>
        <p>Beckham, who will reportedly earn about $5.5 million before endorsements and incentives, will give the league a higher profile, but his ultimate impact is harder to gauge. He must perform on the field, of course. But he is more likely to excel as a tireless ambassador of the game in the United States.</p>
        <p>The New York metropolitan area no longer will be the league's black hole. The Red Bulls hired Coach Bruce Arena, the former coach of the United States national team, after last year's World Cup. The club brought the veteran midfielder Claudio Reyna home to New Jersey as one of its designated players and reacquired an older and hopefully wiser striker, Clint Mathis. In addition, Arena traded for midfielder Dave van den Bergh and signed goalkeeper Ronald Waterreus.</p>
        <p>The Red Bulls have broken ground on a stadium, which is probably 15 months to 2 years away, they have a new (albeit interim) practice home in northern New Jersey and they seem finally to have a blueprint for success.</p>
        <p>Yesterday the Fire, which plays in an area with a large Mexican population, played to the crowd when it announced the signing of the mercurial Mexican striker Cuauhtémoc Blanco, 34, who plays for Club América and is not expected to join Chicago until July. More than 5,000 fans turned out Monday night for Blanco's informal introduction at the Fire's stadium in Bridgeview, Ill.</p>
        <p>D.C. United, one of the league's most successful clubs, traded two promising young Americans -- Freddy Adu to Real Salt Lake and Alecko Eskandarian to Toronto F.C. The club continues to look south for players, with the signing of the Brazilians Luciano Emilio and Fred, added to a roster that includes Jaime Moreno of Bolivia and the Argentines Christian Gómez (last year's league most valuable player) and Facundo Erpen.</p>
        <p>New Team Up North</p>
        <p>Then there is Canada. Since the demise of the North American Soccer League, the game north of the border has experienced some crushing defections (for example, Owen Hargreaves grew up in Canada, plays for a club in Germany and internationally for England), desolation and the United Soccer Leagues. That changes this year when Toronto F.C. begins play in a stadium on the city's waterfront.</p>
        <p>Coached by Mo Johnston, Toronto has been aggressive, landing the American Conor Casey (back from Germany), the Welsh international Carl Robinson and the Irish midfielder Ronnie O'Brien in a trade with F. C. Dallas. Toronto cut off season-ticket sales at 14,000.</p>
        <p>In the West, the Galaxy is in the strange position of having its schedule backloaded with road games to showcase Beckham. Cobi Jones, the only player who has been with the same club since the league's inception, will retire after the season. Landon Donovan should thrive playing with Beckham.</p>
        <p>Houston, the defending league champion, has made few changes to its roster from last season and returns a strong core that includes Brian Ching, Dwayne DeROSARIO, Paul Dalglish, Brad Davis and Brian Mullan.</p>
        <p>Chivas USA and Real Salt Lake begin their third season. Chivas made the playoffs last year but lost its coach, Bob Bradley, to the United States national team. It acquired the moody midfielder Amado Guevara from the Red Bulls, but will be without Jonathan Bornstein, the 2006 rookie of the year, to start the season because of a knee injury. Real Salt Lake, which will soon begin work on a new stadium, acquired Freddy Adu to run its midfield.</p>
        <p>In the Summertime</p>
        <p>After years of interesting but not really meaningful games against foreign clubs (M.L.S. All-Stars vs. Chelsea; D.C. United vs. Barcelona), M.L.S. will inaugurate the SuperLiga.</p>
        <p>Modestly modeled on the European Champions League, the SuperLiga will bring together four teams from Mexico's First Division (Chivas Guadalajara, Pachuca, Club América and Monarcas Morelia) and four M.L.S. teams (Houston, D.C. United, F. C. Dallas and Los Angeles) in a two-group round-robin format in July and August.</p>
        <p>In addition, M.L.S. clubs are again chasing a berth in December's FIFA Club World Cup in Japan with their participation in the Concacaf Champions Cup. D.C. United was in Mexico last night, losing to Chivas Guadalajara, 3-2 on aggregate, and Houston will play at Pachuca tomorrow in the second leg of its semifinal series. To date, the results have not been much to the liking of M.L.S., but the goal is to participate, plant the flag and gain experience.</p>
        <p>SOCCER: EXTRA TIME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
