<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Iowa Library's Cat Has a Rich Second Life as a Biography</title>
    <meta content="04cat" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/books/04cat.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837951"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Iowa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Iowa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Grand Central Publishing</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E3D81F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Iowa Library's Cat Has a Rich Second Life as a Biography</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Iowa Library’s Cat Has a Rich Second Life as a Biography</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MOTOKO RICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Motoko, Rich</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Watch out, Marley.</p>
        <p>In a hotly contested deal, the life story of Dewey, a rescued cat who lived for 19 years in a library in a small town in Iowa, has sold for about $1.25 million to Grand Central Publishing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a hotly contested deal, the life story of Dewey, a rescued cat who lived for 19 years in a library in a small town in Iowa, has sold for about $1.25 million to Grand Central Publishing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Watch out, Marley.</p>
        <p>In a hotly contested deal, the life story of Dewey, a rescued cat who lived for 19 years in a library in a small town in Iowa, has sold for about $1.25 million to Grand Central Publishing.</p>
        <p>With an eye toward creating the feline answer to the best-selling ''Marley &amp; Me,'' John Grogan's memoir of his misbehaving yellow Labrador retriever, Grand Central bought the book, currently titled ''Dewey, a Small Town, a Library and the World's Most Beloved Cat,'' on Monday by making an offer high enough to pre-emptively shut down an auction.</p>
        <p>''You can't underestimate the market out there for people who love animals,'' said Karen Kosztolnyik, the senior editor at Grand Central who will edit the book; co-authors will be Vicki Myron, the head librarian in Spencer, Iowa; and Bret Witter, a former editorial director at Health Communications, the publisher of the ''Chicken Soup for the Soul'' books.</p>
        <p>''You look at 'Marley &amp; Me,' and that book has been a publishing phenomenon,'' Ms. Kosztolnyik said. ''I think there are equally as many cat lovers out there. We see this as having that kind of potential.''</p>
        <p>The authors' advance raised some eyebrows in the publishing industry, given that ''Marley &amp; Me'' reportedly sold to William Morrow less than three years ago for an advance of about $200,000. To date it has sold 1.85 million copies in hardcover, according to Nielsen Bookscan, which tracks book sales in most bookstores and online retailers, although not mass-market outlets like Wal-Mart.</p>
        <p>''It's stunning, the advances being paid,'' said Robert S. Miller, president of Hyperion, a publisher that looked at the ''Dewey'' proposal but declined to bid. ''If it might be the next 'Da Vinci Code' or the next 'Marley &amp; Me,' the ante just increases,'' Mr. Miller said. ''The problem is that even as the biggest best sellers sell more copies, there are fewer of them, so the publishers paying these advances do so at increasing risk.''</p>
        <p>According to publishing executives, ''Dewey'' will need to sell at least 250,000 copies in hardcover to cover the cost of the advance. Sales to foreign publishers or paperback sales could offset some of that cost.</p>
        <p>''Dewey,'' which was sold on the basis of a 45-page proposal with about 10 photos of the fluffy orange cat, will tell the story of how the kitten was found in the late-night book drop of the public library in Spencer, a town in the northwest part of the state, and adopted by Ms. Myron and the other librarians. Slowly, over the course of his 19-year life, Dewey became a town mascot who lifted the spirits of residents hit hard by the 1980s farming crisis. In the process he attracted the attention of tourists, cat-calendar makers and filmmakers. He appeared in ''Puss in Books: Adventures of the Library Cat,'' a 1997 documentary, and another film made by Japanese documentarians. When he died last November, his obituary ran in more than 250 publications, including USA Today and The Washington Post.</p>
        <p>Jamie Raab, publisher of Grand Central (formerly called Warner Books), said she was hooked on ''Dewey'' just two pages into the proposal, which she read last Thursday. Ms. Raab said she was so excited by the proposal that she got out of bed at midnight to send e-mail to Ms. Kosztolnyik, saying, ''Let's buy this book.''</p>
        <p>''To me it was just about how animals can bring out the humanity in us, and I loved that,'' she said, comparing ''Dewey'' to books like ''The Bridges of Madison County'' and titles by the novelist Nicholas Sparks, all best sellers for the publisher. ''It was one of those books where I thought, 'We know how to sell this.' ''</p>
        <p>Peter McGuigan, Ms. Myron's and Mr. Witter's agent at Sanford J. Greenburger Associates, said that the pitch was ''one of the best proposals I'd ever read on any subject at a commercial level.'' He sent it out last week and expected to run an auction this week, but found himself juggling dueling, escalating offers on Friday while he was on a bike trip from Los Angeles to Santa Barbara. He concluded the deal with Grand Central, he said, while waiting in the airport for his flight back to New York on Monday.</p>
        <p>Ms. Raab said she wasn't nervous about the risk she was taking. ''It's a gut thing,'' she said. ''When you talk yourself into something it's often problematic, but when you feel something so strongly and instinctually, my experience has been that those are the books that work.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
