<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Favorite (Woods) and the Favorite Son (Howell)</title>
    <meta content="04masters" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/sports/golf/04masters.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837901"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Howell, Charles</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800EEDF163FF937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Favorite (Woods) and the Favorite Son (Howell)</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">It’s Howell’s Hometown, but Woods Is the Favorite</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hack, Damon</byline>
      <dateline>AUGUSTA, Ga., April 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A few zigzag turns from Augusta National Golf Club, at the end of a cul-de-sac on a leafy street, sits the house where Charles Howell III grew up.</p>
        <p>When he was 7, his parents took him to the Masters tournament for the first time, and a local player named Larry Mize beat Greg Norman and Seve Ballesteros in a playoff. Howell's parents took him to the tournament the next year, and the next and the next. It all seemed so ordinary.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Charles Howell III is carrying the blessings and burdens of being a hometown favorite at Augusta National in the era of Tiger Woods.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A few zigzag turns from Augusta National Golf Club, at the end of a cul-de-sac on a leafy street, sits the house where Charles Howell III grew up.</p>
        <p>When he was 7, his parents took him to the Masters tournament for the first time, and a local player named Larry Mize beat Greg Norman and Seve Ballesteros in a playoff. Howell's parents took him to the tournament the next year, and the next and the next. It all seemed so ordinary.</p>
        <p>''I didn't have the appreciation for it as a kid that I do now,'' Howell said in a recent telephone interview. ''It was just the hometown tournament. Little did I know.''</p>
        <p>Twenty years after his first trip to the Masters, Howell has swapped a patron's ticket for a player's badge and is carrying the blessings and burdens of being a hometown favorite in the era of Tiger Woods.</p>
        <p>After Woods and Phil Mickelson, Howell may be the player who is predicted most to win the Masters, which begins Thursday, but he brings a unique biography and distinct pressures to Augusta National. Howell is one of a generation of golfers who have been influenced by and measured against Woods and his accomplishments.</p>
        <p>Since moving to Orlando, Fla., after turning professional, Howell has seen Woods's tenacity on the golf course and in the gym. In head-to-head practice matches at Isleworth Country Club in Orlando, where they are members, Howell has never beaten him.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, on the PGA Tour, Howell has been asked to match him.</p>
        <p>''In that age group, when you think of young players in that generation, with the quality of game and their pedigree, Charles is the first name you think of,'' David Leadbetter, Howell's swing instructor, said. ''It's a lot of weight to carry, but he's the guy looked at most as being the guy who is going to give Tiger a run for his money.''</p>
        <p>In chasing Woods, Howell has had his game get lost in the wilderness. A year ago, after a spate of poor finishes to start the season, Howell split with Leadbetter and sought a new direction. He found a new swing teacher. At the Masters, in front of old neighbors and classmates, Howell shot 80-84 to finish last in a field of 90 players. A few months later, Howell called Leadbetter and the two reconciled.</p>
        <p>''It was easy to come back,'' Howell said. ''The little bit of time we spent apart was probably a good thing. There always comes a time when a golfer panics. That's a strong word, but you just start wondering: Am I where I should be? Is this going to lead me to get better? I started to go out and tried to get better, but now it's solidified that I'm in the right place with David.''</p>
        <p>Leadbetter, who has been teaching Howell for 15 years, said he agreed that the break was good for their relationship. ''Things get stale, and it gave us a chance to reflect,'' he said. ''We sat down and figured it out.''</p>
        <p>With a simpler approach to his swing, Howell opened the season with two runner-up finishes before shooting a final-round 65 at the Nissan Open in February and defeating Mickelson in a playoff for his second PGA Tour win.</p>
        <p>''I guess for a lot of people, the feeling is happiness -- for me, it was total relief,'' Howell said. ''I wouldn't call myself a huge golf historian, but I know that you are judged by winning golf tournaments and more by winning majors. Ten second-place finishes is good, but at the end of the day, there is a huge gap between first and second. It's an important gap.''</p>
        <p>Howell readily acknowledges that he watches Woods and tries to pick out parts of his game and his lifestyle that he may use.</p>
        <p>Since joining the Tour at 140 pounds, Howell recently began using a weight program with EAS products, which supplies health supplements for the National Football League. His time in the gym is only eclipsed by his time on the range.</p>
        <p>Howell guessed that he had put on 13 pounds of muscle, a number Woods jokingly disputed.</p>
        <p>''He's probably put on 1.5 pounds,'' Woods said. ''He has gotten a lot stronger and he understands how to play the game a lot more. That's one of the things I truly admire about him. He's not only a great kid, but his work ethic, his dedication, his passion to try and improve, it's exciting to watch and you're starting to see the fruition of that now. He's starting to put it together.''</p>
        <p>Howell said of Woods: ''I've picked his brain for so long. Tiger knows I have a tremendous amount of respect for him, not only for his golf game but for how he works at his game and his passion for working at it.''</p>
        <p>Howell's passion is evident at any mention of the Masters. Woods has won four of them. Howell would gladly take one.</p>
        <p>''I've actually joked that if I win the Masters, I'd retire,'' Howell said. ''That would be as good a thing that I could ever achieve. It would be my wildest dream come true.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
