<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Museum of Artifacts, Tainted or Not</title>
    <meta content="04hall" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/sports/baseball/04hall.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837882"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Memorabilia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Baseball Hall of Fame</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bonds, Barry</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Palmeiro, Rafael</person>
        <person class="online_producer">McGwire, Mark</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E2DF163FF937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1070" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Museum of Artifacts, Tainted or Not</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Artifacts Tied to Steroids Find Place in Hall’s Museum</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <dateline>COOPERSTOWN, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If Barry Bonds climbs within a handful of homers of Hank Aaron's record of 755 this season, Jeff Idelson of the National Baseball Hall of Fame and Museum will become his shadow. Once Bonds moves close to Aaron, Idelson will leave here to be closer to Bonds in hopes of securing some worthwhile mementos.</p>
        <p>Commissioner Bud Selig has not said if he will attend the games that could be record-tying or record-setting affairs for Bonds, but the Hall of Fame already knows it will have Idelson in the stands. Idelson, a vice president for communications and education at the Hall, said he would be thrilled to get a bat or a jersey from Bonds, anything that chronicles the memorable moments.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is the Hall of Fame’s mandate to present the artifacts that have shaped baseball history and allow fans to interpret them, even if that means presenting items from players linked to steroid use.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If Barry Bonds climbs within a handful of homers of Hank Aaron's record of 755 this season, Jeff Idelson of the National Baseball Hall of Fame and Museum will become his shadow. Once Bonds moves close to Aaron, Idelson will leave here to be closer to Bonds in hopes of securing some worthwhile mementos.</p>
        <p>Commissioner Bud Selig has not said if he will attend the games that could be record-tying or record-setting affairs for Bonds, but the Hall of Fame already knows it will have Idelson in the stands. Idelson, a vice president for communications and education at the Hall, said he would be thrilled to get a bat or a jersey from Bonds, anything that chronicles the memorable moments.</p>
        <p>''Our job is to present the game's history,'' Idelson said. ''Our fans expect us to do that.''</p>
        <p>Selig's ambivalence about Bonds is in clear contrast to the Hall's approach, but Major League Baseball has no intention of telling the Hall, and its president, Dale Petroskey, to curtail recognition of Bonds should he surpass Aaron.</p>
        <p>''If Bonds is breaking home run records, we have the responsibility to record it,'' Petroskey said.</p>
        <p>Petroskey and Idelson said it was the Hall's mandate to present the artifacts that have shaped history and allow fans to interpret them. So if that means presenting items from players who have been linked to steroid use, as Bonds has, or who have tested positive for steroids, as Rafael Palmeiro has, they will do just that.</p>
        <p>A recent tour of the 68-year-old museum found items on display from Palmeiro, who tested positive for steroids with the Baltimore Orioles in 2005, and Jose Canseco, who wrote a book in which he admitted to using steroids and accused teammates like Palmeiro, Mark McGwire, Juan González and Iván Rodríguez of using them, too. Bats belonging to McGwire -- whose evasive testimony about steroid use before Congress greatly damaged him in the public eye -- are featured in the Hall, too.</p>
        <p>Selig has often said that his goal is ''zero tolerance'' when it comes to the use of performance-enhancing drugs.</p>
        <p>In that sense, it may strike people as curious that Palmeiro, in particular, is honored by the Hall, with the bat he used for his 500th home run now on display. Why, after all, should a player who adamantly told a Congressional committee he had never used steroids only to later test positive for them be given space in the Hall?</p>
        <p>The answer, major league officials say, is that they have nothing to do with selecting what will be displayed in the Hall.</p>
        <p>''We don't tell the Hall of Fame what to do,'' said Pat Courtney, a spokesman for Major League Baseball. ''We think that's a good thing.''</p>
        <p>Idelson agreed. ''Baseball doesn't tell us what artifacts to take,'' he said. ''We have a great relationship with them, but we're completely independent of M.L.B.''</p>
        <p>Selig had no comment when asked about specific items on display in the Hall.</p>
        <p>But as Petroskey sees it, the Hall of Fame is two things in one. The Hall is where players are enshrined for what they have accomplished in their careers and where judgments about a player's behavior can come into play. The museum, on the other hand, is where achievements on the field are recognized.</p>
        <p>The distinction explains why Pete Rose and Joe Jackson, two players who are on baseball's permanently ineligible list, are not in the Hall but are given recognition in the museum.</p>
        <p>Rose, the career hits leader, who was barred from baseball for gambling on the sport, has several items here, including the bat from his 4,000th hit. His gambling is also noted. Jackson, a .356 career hitter, was barred, along with seven other members of the Chicago White Sox, for conspiring to throw the 1919 World Series. Jackson's uniform is in the museum, but the Black Sox scandal is cited, too.</p>
        <p>''You can't tell the story of baseball without telling Pete Rose's story or Shoeless Joe Jackson's story,'' Petroskey said. ''Just because they don't have plaques on the wall, that doesn't mean you're not a part of history.''</p>
        <p>In a section of the museum on the second floor called ''Today's Game,'' there are lockers for all 30 major league teams. It is there that Palmeiro's bat can be found in the locker of the Texas Rangers, the team he was playing for on May 11, 2003, when he hit home run No. 500. There is a piece of white tape on the knob of the Old Hickory Custom Pro bat and the residue of pine tar on the handle.</p>
        <p>''Palmeiro did hit 500 homers,'' Petroskey said. ''He did donate his bat. He's in that club. We don't make judgments on the players.''</p>
        <p>In the locker beside Palmeiro sits the blue helmet Canseco wore when he bashed his 400th homer for the Tampa Bay Devil Rays. Canseco became the first player born outside the United States to get 400 -- he was born in Cuba -- but now he is best known for writing a book that offered intimate details about steroid use.</p>
        <p>Across from Canseco's helmet is a ball linked to Terrmel Sledge, a journeyman player who is now with the San Diego Padres. In 2005, Sledge hit the first homer for the Washington Nationals. Now the ball is in Cooperstown.</p>
        <p>But Sledge is also known for having failed a drug test at the United States Olympic training camp in October 2003, resulting in a two-year suspension from international competition. The suspension was announced in January 2004. A year later, Sledge hit the historic two-run homer for Washington.</p>
        <p>Rob Manfred, baseball's executive vice president for labor relations and human resources, knew about Sledge's failed test and about his home run with Washington. But Manfred was unaware that the ball was in Cooperstown.</p>
        <p>''That relates to a decision another organization made,'' Manfred said. ''I'm not going to comment on that.''</p>
        <p>At some point, Idelson said the museum would probably do an educational exhibit about steroids in baseball.</p>
        <p>He said that it would be ''insulting to our fans'' to edit out items from the Hall linked to players who had achieved significant milestones but were under a cloud because of steroids.</p>
        <p>So, if Bonds passes Aaron, Idelson will be there, hoping to acquire items for the Hall of Fame. It will be history, Idelson said.</p>
        <p>Others can decide if they feel it is good or bad.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
