<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ukraine's Premier Defies Order to Dissolve Parliament</title>
    <meta content="04ukraine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/world/europe/04ukraine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837968"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ukraine</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yanukovich, Viktor F (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yushchenko, Viktor A (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kramer, Andrew E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ukraine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Ukraine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Ukraine</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Yanukovich, Viktor F</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Yushchenko, Viktor</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E6D71F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="665" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ukraine's Premier Defies Order to Dissolve Parliament</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ukraine’s Premier Defies Order to Dissolve Parliament</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW E. KRAMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kramer, Andrew E</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, April 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prime Min Viktor F Yanukovich and his Cabinet resist order by Pres Viktor A Yushchenko to disband Ukraine's Parliament; thousands gather near Parliament to support Yanukovich; standoff leads to confusion over who is controlling day-to-day operations of government; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Viktor F. Yanukovich and his cabinet remained defiant Tuesday, resisting an order by Ukraine's president, Viktor A. Yushchenko, to disband the Parliament, while thousands gathered near the Parliament building in support of the prime minister.</p>
        <p>The cabinet, which is loyal to Mr. Yanukovich, responded early Tuesday to the presidential decree disbanding Parliament by ordering government agencies to disregard it. Mr. Yushchenko responded Tuesday with his own decree invalidating the cabinet's order.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The standoff led to confusion over who is controlling the day-to-day operations of the government.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prime Minister Viktor F. Yanukovich and his cabinet remained defiant Tuesday, resisting an order by Ukraine's president, Viktor A. Yushchenko, to disband the Parliament, while thousands gathered near the Parliament building in support of the prime minister.</p>
        <p>The cabinet, which is loyal to Mr. Yanukovich, responded early Tuesday to the presidential decree disbanding Parliament by ordering government agencies to disregard it. Mr. Yushchenko responded Tuesday with his own decree invalidating the cabinet's order.</p>
        <p>The standoff led to confusion over who is controlling the day-to-day operations of the government and represented a reversal in fortunes from the Orange Revolution just two years ago, when Mr. Yushchenko swept to power in a wave of protests against Mr. Yanukovich's fraudulent election victory.</p>
        <p>The rivalry between the men, Mr. Yushchenko a pro-Western reformer and Mr. Yanukovich favoring closer ties with Russia, reflects a broad division in the society of Ukraine, a country of 47 million people balanced between Russia and the West.</p>
        <p>They met for four hours on Tuesday, during which Mr. Yushchenko said he reminded the prime minister that under the Constitution the president controls the country's army, according to a statement from the presidential news service.</p>
        <p>''Viktor Yushchenko, as commander in chief of Ukraine's armed forces, also stressed he would allow no use of force in the country,'' the news service said in a statement after the meeting.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yanukovich said before the meeting that he hoped the president would reverse his order. ''We shall do everything to persuade the president of Ukraine to recall his decree,'' he said, in remarks carried on Russian state television. ''If he does not do it, I think in this case not only parliamentary but also presidential elections will be inevitable.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Yushchenko reaffirmed after the meeting that he would not rescind his decree.</p>
        <p>An eight-month-old power-sharing deal between Mr. Yushchenko and Mr. Yanukovich collapsed Monday when Mr. Yushchenko disbanded Parliament, Mr. Yanukovich's power base, and called new elections for May 27, less than two months from now.</p>
        <p>Parliament responded by passing a resolution forming a separate Central Election Committee, a maneuver challenging Mr. Yushchenko's authority.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, however, a district court in Kiev suspended that resolution.</p>
        <p>Germany, which holds the rotating presidency of the European Union, issued a statement on Tuesday calling for Ukrainian politicians to resolve their dispute in compliance with ''the Constitution and democratic rules.''</p>
        <p>In Washington, the State Department spokesman, Sean McCormack, said Ukrainian leaders should ''take full responsibility for their supporters' actions'' in any street protests.</p>
        <p>The turnout in Kiev's squares and parks on a balmy spring day was modest. Several thousand supporters of Mr. Yanukovich rallied at three sites in the city and erected roughly 100 tents on Independence Square, the focus of the 2004 Orange Revolution. But the crowds were orderly and there was no evidence of a major police presence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yushchenko's news service said Tuesday that disbanding Parliament was justified under Ukrainian law because Mr. Yanukovich had recruited individual deputies to join his coalition, in violation of the Constitution, which says a parliamentary coalition can be formed only among parties.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yanukovich had been working to win a veto-proof, two-thirds majority of 300 in Parliament, known as the Rada. His supporters argued that the Constitution specified only three circumstances when a president could disband Parliament, none of which applied Monday.</p>
        <p>The Constitutional Court posted a statement on its Web site saying it would decide within 15 days whether to hear an appeal by Parliament that it rule on the constitutionality of Mr. Yushchenko's decree dissolving it.</p>
        <p>Taras Kuzio, a political science professor at George Washington University and a Ukraine specialist, said Mr. Yushchenko controlled the variables that mattered in Ukraine's young political system -- the army, the security service and popular support in the capital, Kiev.</p>
        <p>''I don't think there is stomach for a fight with the president,'' Mr. Kuzio said of Mr. Yanukovich and his supporters in a telephone interview from Kiev. ''The president holds more cards.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
