<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Competition Defines a Friendship</title>
    <meta content="04araton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/sports/ncaabasketball/04araton.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837902"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey</org>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Tennessee</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Stringer, C Vivian</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Summitt, Pat</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EEDF163FF937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="953" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Competition Defines a Friendship</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Competition Defines a Friendship</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
      <dateline>CLEVELAND</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What was Pat Summitt supposed to say to her longtime friend C. Vivian Stringer?</p>
        <p>Too bad we annihilated you on the offensive boards with bigger, more aggressive players? Forgive us for stealing Nicky Anosike and Shannon Bobbitt from New York City, from right under your nose?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tennessee Coach Pat Summitt and Rutgers Coach C. Vivian Stringer are bonded by their competitive zeal as well as a lifer’s passion for the cause of elevating their sport.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What was Pat Summitt supposed to say to her longtime friend C. Vivian Stringer?</p>
        <p>Too bad we annihilated you on the offensive boards with bigger, more aggressive players? Forgive us for stealing Nicky Anosike and Shannon Bobbitt from New York City, from right under your nose?</p>
        <p>Excuse us for having Candace Parker, the most talented all-around player in the country?</p>
        <p>All Summitt could do after Tennessee's 59-46 victory last night, after her seventh N.C.A.A. championship was secured, was take a slow walk down the sideline and give Stringer a warm embrace and a pat on the back. Winning the national championship means never having to say you're sorry.</p>
        <p>Don't be fooled by the touchy-feely sentimentality that preceded last night's game. The truth of the matter is that Summitt and Stringer would have taken the last cookie from each other's cupboard if it meant an extra sugar rush for the last lap of the race to the trophy. Bonded by their competitive zeal as well as a lifer's passion for the cause of elevating their sport, they had been recounting shared experiences, decades of support and the occasional late-night telephone call that dragged into the wee morning hours.</p>
        <p>''Vivian can talk,'' Summitt said. ''And I don't mean for a few minutes.''</p>
        <p>Even Stringer succinctly summed up Tennessee's advantage when she appeared in the interview room as subdued as the players sitting next to her. She mentioned how Parker, the tournament's most outstanding player, picked apart Rutgers's vaunted defense with her passing out of double-teams from the post. How Anosike dominated the boards with 16 rebounds. How the cat-quick Bobbitt, all of 5 feet 2 inches, hit a trio of second-half 3-pointers just as the Scarlet Knights looked ready to make a run.</p>
        <p>She described her team as overcome by the occasion, like ''deer stuck in the headlights.'' For the third straight tournament, Summitt's team vanquished Stringer's, and considering that this time Stringer was denied her first national championship in her 36th year on the job, it made sense that Summitt would have preferred to beat anyone else.</p>
        <p>Some Tennessee folks swear that Summitt was a bit glassy eyed after the Lady Vols knocked out Rutgers last spring in the Round of 16. Maybe. But Summitt had not won this title since 1998, a gap that must have felt like 36 years for a person with her credentials and expectations. You can believe that she was quite capable of giving Stringer her hug and not looking back. That's what fierce competitors do.</p>
        <p>Monday, I asked Summitt at her news conference if she had ever experienced career fatigue, given all she had achieved and the demands of the work. She looked directly at me, her eyes narrowing, and said: ''This may seem a little strange, but I've never thought about not doing what I do. I love it. I live for it.''</p>
        <p>Why would she suggest that I might think that strange? Could be because she has spent the last three-plus decades carrying the fight for women's athletics and gender equity from Knoxville, Tenn., which turned out to be far more progressive, and much sooner, than most places.</p>
        <p>People like Summitt and Stringer have helped bring their sport a long, long way, but if the recent uproar over Elizabeth Edwards's encouraging her husband, John, to continue running for president while she deals with Stage 4 breast cancer told us anything, it was that many among the masses still haven't cracked the mystery of the driven, multidimensional woman.</p>
        <p>I can admit to wondering how and even why Stringer persevered in her career when being a single parent since her husband's death 15 years ago sounded so challenging. Her daughter has suffered from the disabling effects of spinal meningitis since infancy, and still lives with her mother. Stringer's two sons have had to deal with early adulthood trauma.</p>
        <p>''That woman has handled adversity better than anyone else I know in this profession,'' Summitt said.</p>
        <p>Maybe a shared understanding of complexity and compromise is why Summitt and Stringer became trusted confidantes. Stringer is the daughter of a Pennsylvania coal miner who grew up to be urbane and outspoken. Summitt is a country girl from modest origins who has had to manage her ambition while honoring the mores of Southern gentility.</p>
        <p>Monday, someone asked her why, given that the Tennessee women have far outpaced the men, her team must still be differentiated as Lady Vols?</p>
        <p>''I don't think that will ever change at Tennessee,'' Summitt said. ''That's who we are.''</p>
        <p>Her insistence that tradition outweighed political correctness got me to thinking that the women shouldn't automatically reject having to distinguish themselves from the men, even with labels. In several ways, their sport is better, or at least truer to the amateur sports mission.</p>
        <p>Consider how people in Atlanta celebrated the Florida Gators' defense of their men's title Monday night with the same starting five as last year. On the women's side, where professional riches do not await the gifted and talented, that is the case every year. Unless Parker shocks Summitt by putting her name in today's W.N.B.A. draft -- she told the Tennessee fans after the game not to worry about it -- Tennessee will return all but one of its core players next season. Stringer will lose no one.</p>
        <p>With the right draw, the addition of a skilled recruit and a bit of luck, Summitt and Stringer may even make it all the way back next April to tell the same stories before trying to steal each other's cookies. On championship night, there is only respect, no remorse. It is opponent first and nothing else next, just as it would be for the Gentlemen Knights and Vols.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
