<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Buyers Seek Historic or Period Homes</title>
    <meta content="04GH-historic" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/realestate/greathomes/04GH-historic.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837916"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E5DE163FF937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1142" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Buyers Seek Historic or Period Homes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Buyers Seek Historic or Period Homes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN BRASS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Adams, the second president of the United States and the son of a Puritan, would undoubtedly blush at the makeover planned for his former London residence.</p>
        <p>While the developer is maintaining the historical features of Adams's three-story house, including a broad ballroom with high ceilings and an ornate fireplace, he is also adding the latest in high-tech gadgetry. Improvements will include Lutron-brand controlled lighting, electrically operated curtains, underfloor heating and an audio-video system throughout the structure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>From Panama to Shanghai, buyers are paying top dollar for properties with pedigrees and developers are prioritizing careful renovations of historic buildings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John Adams, the second president of the United States and the son of a Puritan, would undoubtedly blush at the makeover planned for his former London residence.</p>
        <p>While the developer is maintaining the historical features of Adams's three-story house, including a broad ballroom with high ceilings and an ornate fireplace, he is also adding the latest in high-tech gadgetry. Improvements will include Lutron-brand controlled lighting, electrically operated curtains, underfloor heating and an audio-video system throughout the structure.</p>
        <p>''If you're buying a property like this, you're definitely interested in period fixtures,'' said Ben Carson, the London-based developer who paid 3.5 million pounds, or almost $6.9 million, earlier this year for the house in Mayfair, in Grosvenor Square, where Adams lived from 1785 to 1788 when he was the first United States minister to the Court of St. James's. ''But at the same time, people spending this kind of money also want the sophisticated audio-video system'' and other amenities. (It is too soon to say what the sale price will be.)</p>
        <p>Around the world, from Panama to Shanghai, buyers are seeking historic or period houses, and are willing to pay high prices for them, spurring owners to spend time and money on sensitive renovations that often include modern improvements, brokers say. But finding properties worthy of such effort can be a challenge.</p>
        <p>''The demand for property that is historic or period has never been higher,'' said Mark Lawson, a partner in the Buying Solution, a London-based agency that represents prospective buyers. Sixty percent of the historic properties handled by his company are bought before they are even formally listed, he said.</p>
        <p>In Tuscany, it is ''nearly impossible'' to find the classic old farmhouse or cottage worthy of restoration, said Marie Josèphe Mucchielli, general director of Kalliste, a real estate company that specializes in renovating older properties in Italy.</p>
        <p>Books and movies depicting idyllic Tuscan living set off a buying spree of properties over the last 10 years, depleting the supply and driving up prices, she said. So prospective buyers are looking to less heralded regions, like Sardinia and Umbria. ''In Umbria,'' Ms. Mucchielli said, ''you can still find ruins or monuments to be renovated at a reasonable price.''</p>
        <p>But deals vary, depending on availability. For example, Prestige Property Group currently lists a 1,970-square-foot fully restored stone farmhouse in Tuscany with terra-cotta floors and wood-beam ceilings for $372,400, but a rustic two-story 1,600-square-foot farmhouse in need of restoration in Umbria lists for $399,000.</p>
        <p>In Panama, investment is flooding into beachfront projects. But Conservatorio, a real estate developer, is one of several companies focusing instead on renovating buildings in Casco Antiguo, Panama City's old quarter.</p>
        <p>''I think there have been so many success stories that a lot of people 'get it,' '' said K. C. Hardin, manager of Conservatorio. ''When a market matures, the old apartments are much more valuable than the towers. They are collectible, not a commodity.'' And in Casco Antiguo, demand for renovated historic property far outstrips supply, Mr. Hardin added.</p>
        <p>Victoria Yee, a Florida-based software developer, and David Shore, her partner, paid $330,000 for a one-bedroom apartment in one of Conservatorio's projects, an 80-year-old building that once housed a department store called Benedetti Hermanos.</p>
        <p>Ms. Yee says she explored neighborhoods around the world before settling on Casco Antiguo, which reminded her of the French Quarter in New Orleans.</p>
        <p>''You find very few places around the world like that that have been somewhat preserved,'' she said. And at Casco Antiguo, ''there are not a lot of units flooding the market in the area, which is a nice thing.''</p>
        <p>Conservatorio is rebuilding the department store's original glass facade and transforming the interior to create 10 lofts with a pool and indoor parking.</p>
        <p>The lofts will range from 185 to 370 square meters, or 2,000 to 4,000 square feet, and have bamboo flooring, high ceilings and modern appliances. The unsold units are priced from $400,000 to $700,000; the penthouse already sold for $805,000 -- the high end of the scale for Panama City.</p>
        <p>The price escalation of historic and period properties can be seen around the world, brokers say. Much as in Europe and Latin America, prices in Shanghai are ''skyrocketing'' for older homes, in large part because of an ever-dwindling supply, according to Tess Johnston, co-founder of the Shanghai Historic House Association.</p>
        <p>Over all, Shanghai's expensive property values actually dropped last year, but demand for the older, historic properties remained high, because of interest from Chinese citizens and foreign buyers, she said. (That may change in coming months as foreign buyers now face new restrictions, which require at least a year's residency in Shanghai before a purchase. The regulations also impose a hefty tax if they sell in less than five years.)</p>
        <p>Because of Shanghai's extensive redevelopment, the number of shikumen -- residences that combine Eastern and Western elements with carved stone door frames and open courtyards -- is expected to fall to 50,000 in 2010 from 650,000 in 2002, according to a recent study. Buyers are paying $500,000 and more for ''fixer uppers'' in the traditional lilong, or narrow lane, neighborhoods, Ms. Johnston said.</p>
        <p>''More people are chasing the old villas than there are old villas available on the market,'' she added.</p>
        <p>To buyers, a formal historic designation for a property can be both a blessing and a curse, providing prestige but also adding layers of bureaucracy and confusion to any renovation plans. Within a country, guidelines for work on such structures can differ dramatically from jurisdiction to jurisdiction.</p>
        <p>''If you don't have experience, you'll be pulling your hair out,'' said Tim Sargeant, chief executive officer of City &amp; Country Group, a Britain-based development company specializing in historic properties.</p>
        <p>His company prefers to focus on large-scale projects, in some cases taking advantage of the British government's recent decision to sell some of its old buildings. For example, City &amp; Country is renovating a collection of towering 160-year-old Victorian buildings in Essex that once housed a hospital.</p>
        <p>After it bought the property three years ago, crews began uncovering the buildings' original brickwork and a vaulted stone roof that was once part of a water tower. ''The original historic features tend to be covered up after years of government ownership,'' Mr. Sargeant said.</p>
        <p>The original elements are incorporated in City &amp; Country's plans for 131 apartments, which will feature modern bathrooms and kitchens with stainless-steel appliances. The first phase, designed around the hospital's vast entryway and clock tower, opened in December and includes 13 apartments ranging from one to three bedrooms, priced from 229,000 to 500,000 pounds, or $451,000 to $985,000.</p>
        <p>One apartment was built around elements of an original clock tower, including the clock's stone pendulum and wood casing; there is even access to the mechanism. So, in keeping with the historic ambience, the buyer will be responsible for winding the clock each week.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
