<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Islanders Do Their Best to Impede the Rangers</title>
    <meta content="04rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/sports/hockey/04rangers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837899"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Islanders</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EEDF163FF937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="860" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Islanders Do Their Best to Impede the Rangers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Islanders Do Their Best to Impede the Rangers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinser, Lynn</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONDALE, N.Y., April 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wade Dubielewicz crouched in front of his goal in perhaps the most pressure-packed of situations Tuesday night. He needed to stop the Rangers' superstar Jaromir Jagr in a shootout to give the Islanders a 3-2 victory that they needed to save their playoff hopes.</p>
        <p>Dubielewicz not only had spent much of this season in the minors, being called up when Rick DiPietro went down with a concussion and starting because Mike Dunham struggled, but he could not look Jagr in the eye without standing on a set of telephone books.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In one move, the Islanders saved their dwindling playoff hopes, crimped the Rangers’ march to a postseason berth and earned a victory against their bitter rivals Tuesday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Wade Dubielewicz crouched in front of his goal in perhaps the most pressure-packed of situations Tuesday night. He needed to stop the Rangers' superstar Jaromir Jagr in a shootout to give the Islanders a 3-2 victory that they needed to save their playoff hopes.</p>
        <p>Dubielewicz not only had spent much of this season in the minors, being called up when Rick DiPietro went down with a concussion and starting because Mike Dunham struggled, but he could not look Jagr in the eye without standing on a set of telephone books.</p>
        <p>But Dubielewicz stood tall enough, stabbing his stick at the puck as Jagr was about to shoot. Jagr got the shot off, but Dubielewicz got just enough of it to make Miroslav Satan's shootout goal stand up.</p>
        <p>''I'm not going to lie, I was pretty happy,'' Dubielewicz said. ''He's one of the best players in the world. Anytime you can come out on the better end of that one, you've got to be pretty excited.''</p>
        <p>The Islanders kept the Rangers from clinching a playoff spot, but they still need to win their remaining three games. At 37-30-12, they have 86 points and sit in 11th place in the Eastern Conference, 4 points behind eighth-place Montreal, which holds the final playoff berth. The Islanders play ninth-place Toronto here Thursday night. Even Islanders Coach Ted Nolan called it a ''million-to-one'' chance, but it is a chance that Dubielewicz gave them.</p>
        <p>''We're not eliminated yet,'' defenseman Brendan Witt said. ''We have to take it literally one game at a time. I hate to say that stupid cliché, but it's true. We have to focus now on Toronto coming in here.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers (41-29-10) earned a point, which puts them in seventh place, tied in points with sixth-place Tampa Bay with 92 but trailing them in victories. The Rangers can clinch a playoff berth with a victory against Montreal on Thursday at Madison Square Garden, which tempered their disappointment.</p>
        <p>''It depends the way you look at it,'' Jagr said. ''If you look at it like, we had a chance tonight, it's bad we didn't win it. But if you look at it four or five weeks ago, if somebody told us with two games to go you guys need one win or a point to clinch, we would take that right away.''</p>
        <p>Part of the reason the Rangers were heartened was that they fell behind by 2-0 in the second period despite dominating the offensive chances. The Islanders jumped ahead 2 minutes 52 seconds into the game on a goal by Arron Asham, who whacked in his own rebound. Then in the second period, Alexei Yashin scored when his pass to Satan deflected off Rangers defenseman Jason Strudwick and past goaltender Henrik Lundqvist at 5:02.</p>
        <p>The Rangers used the Islanders' first power play to get back into the game when Brendan Shanahan took off on a short-handed rush. Dubielewicz saved Shanahan's first shot, but Shanahan collected the puck behind the net and bounced his next shot off Dubielewicz's back and into the goal with 10:58 left in the second.</p>
        <p>Michael Nylander tied the score after the Islanders committed a turnover in their zone. Defenseman Sean Hill missed Witt with a pass, and Jagr stole the puck and set up Nylander with 7:08 left in the second.</p>
        <p>From there, the teams battled fairly evenly. Heading into the shootout, Lundqvist seemed to have the edge, in stature and experience.</p>
        <p>Dubielewicz is generously listed at 5 feet 10 inches and 185 pounds, but he is much shorter. In the shootout, he poke-checked Nylander's attempt and got a piece of Shanahan's shot before thwarting Jagr with a poke check as well.</p>
        <p>''I tried to take his ice away,'' Dubielewicz said. ''The closer he is to me, the better chance I have of stopping him. I forced him to make a decision, and when I did that, he bobbled the puck, so I got lucky.''</p>
        <p>The Islanders left the game feeling lucky to have saved their season, at least for now, with a minor league goalie in their net. Dubielewicz did not flinch under the pressure.</p>
        <p>''I look at it as a great opportunity,'' he said. ''I don't know how else I'm going to get starts. It just goes to show I can deal with this kind of pressure, and that's a positive thing for me down the road.''</p>
        <p>The Islanders still have work to do for their future to include playoff games. After playing Toronto here, they have games at Philadelphia and at the Devils.</p>
        <p>The Rangers' road is simpler because teams are chasing them. After playing Montreal on Thursday, they play at Pittsburgh on Saturday for their regular-season finale.</p>
        <p>''Certainly the way we played and the way we battled back we would have liked to have done it tonight,'' Shanahan said. ''But I judge our team more on our effort and our approach. We're disappointed not to do it tonight, but we crept a little bit closer.''</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>Islanders defenseman Chris Campoli, who had two assists Tuesday night, left the game after blocking a shot in the third period with his foot.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
