<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Woman, 73, Is Killed by Hit-and-Run Driver in Brooklyn</title>
    <meta content="04kill" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/nyregion/04kill.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837869"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hit-and-Run Drivers</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burman, Reyzya Ratsa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lueck, Thomas J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Khan, Daryl</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Passover</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Passover</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Passover</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E6DF163FF937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="677" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Woman, 73, Is Killed by Hit-and-Run Driver in Brooklyn</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Woman, 73, Is Killed by Hit-and-Run Driver in Brooklyn</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS J. LUECK and DARYL KHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lueck, Thomas J; Khan, Daryl</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Reyzya Ratsa Burman, 73, is struck and killed by hit-and-run driver while walking across street in Brooklyn with her husband, who is also injured; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 73-year-old Brooklyn woman returning home from a Passover Seder was struck and killed by a hit-and-run driver on Monday night as she walked with her husband across a street, the police said.</p>
        <p>The woman, Reyzya Ratsa Burman, had just been dropped off by her daughter, and was crossing what neighborhood residents called a perilous stretch of Ninth Avenue, just south of 53rd Street, when she was hit about 10:30 p.m. Based on limited information gleaned from witness interviews, the police said Mrs. Burman was struck by a gold Buick sedan, probably from model years 1997 to 2002, whose driver sped away. There were no arrests as of late yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Returning from a Passover Seder, she was struck with her husband as they crossed a street.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A 73-year-old Brooklyn woman returning home from a Passover Seder was struck and killed by a hit-and-run driver on Monday night as she walked with her husband across a street, the police said.</p>
        <p>The woman, Reyzya Ratsa Burman, had just been dropped off by her daughter, and was crossing what neighborhood residents called a perilous stretch of Ninth Avenue, just south of 53rd Street, when she was hit about 10:30 p.m. Based on limited information gleaned from witness interviews, the police said Mrs. Burman was struck by a gold Buick sedan, probably from model years 1997 to 2002, whose driver sped away. There were no arrests as of late yesterday.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Burman's husband, Maurichiu, 73, was also hit, and was in stable condition yesterday at Lutheran Medical Center, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>The Burmans were crossing the street to get to their apartment building, the David Minkin Residence, a home for elderly people of limited means, where they have lived since immigrating from Moldova not long after that country declared independence from the Soviet Union, which collapsed in 1991.</p>
        <p>Fellow residents, including other immigrants from various countries, seemed stunned by the news as they gathered in the home's lobby, as well as near the site of the accident, which had been cordoned off by the police.</p>
        <p>''This is an unbelievable horror,'' said one resident, Yakov Kranitsky, 76. He said Mrs. Burman, known to her friends as Rose or Rosa, was particularly popular at the David Minkin Residence, and often went out of her way to care for others.</p>
        <p>Albert Kvint, who was visiting his parents in the David Minkin Residence for the Jewish holiday, said he arrived at the scene almost immediately after the Burmans were struck, but did not see the fleeing car or its driver.</p>
        <p>''She was in real bad condition,'' said Mr. Kvint, who had gone for a stroll around the block. As he returned, he said he saw Mrs. Burman lying near the curb with her purse and broken pieces of blue crockery, which she had apparently carried from the Seder, strewn on the ground. Then, Mr. Kvint said, he saw Mr. Burman struggling to his feet in the middle of Ninth Avenue, trying to reach his wife.</p>
        <p>''He tried to get up and go toward her,'' said Mr. Kvint, who by now had been joined by another witness and had called 911. ''We were telling him, 'Stay down, stay down,' and then he fell again. He was saying he was cold.''</p>
        <p>Neighbors said the accident happened on a stretch of road that too often becomes a speedway at night, posing a danger to the many elderly people crossing the avenue.</p>
        <p>''At night, it is like a lawless land on this avenue,'' said Mark Tang, who lives nearby. ''Sometimes, when I am walking with my kids, I am scared. The cars just don't stop.''</p>
        <p>The Burmans' building has become a highly desirable residence for elderly immigrants over the years, and provides services not usually found in many homes for the elderly, including English language classes.</p>
        <p>''This is a very multicultural building, and everyone is upset,'' said Sophia Shteyn, a social worker at the residence. ''The Chinese are upset, Americans are upset, Russians are upset, just everyone.''</p>
        <p>As Ms. Shteyn spoke, another resident, Larisa Kudchin, 75, a Russian immigrant, collapsed into a chair in Ms. Shteyn's office, and spoke in anguished tones about Mrs. Burman's death.</p>
        <p>''Why did this happen? Why did he run? Why did it have to happen to them? Why didn't he stop the car to help?'' Mrs. Kudchin called out, staring at the ceiling.</p>
        <p>Jack Niedzwiedz, the superintendent of the David Minkin Residence, said the Burmans were widely admired.</p>
        <p>''Very nice people,'' he said. ''If someone asked them for help, they would help. If someone got sick, they'd call and say, 'Rose, I am sick. Could you come and prepare some breakfast for me?'</p>
        <p>''I was shocked by this,'' Mr. Niedzwiedz said. ''It's one, two, three, you're alive, and the next second, you're dead.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
