<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Liberty and 210 Horsepower for All</title>
    <meta content="NUGGETJeepLiberty" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837921"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EED9163FF937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="267" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Liberty and 210 Horsepower for All</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERRY GARRETT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Introduced on Wednesday: Jeep Liberty midsize sport utility vehicle</p>
        <p>Is it real? Yes. The replacement for the Jeep Liberty has been long-awaited. Awaited, for some, since the vehicle was first introduced in 2002.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Introduced on Wednesday: Jeep Liberty midsize sport utility vehicle</p>
        <p>Is it real? Yes. The replacement for the Jeep Liberty has been long-awaited. Awaited, for some, since the vehicle was first introduced in 2002.</p>
        <p>What's the point? The original Liberty was homely, slow and heavy, but it became a minor hit for Jeep because it caught on with female buyers looking for a soft-offroader with a macho look.</p>
        <p>What they said: "The all-new 2008 Jeep Liberty stands out from the competition by offering customers classic Jeep design, two four-wheel-drive systems, refined on-road ride and handling, cargo and utility, as well as features that are not typically found on vehicles in the mid-size S.U.V. segment," said George Murphy, senior vice president for global marketing of the Chrysler Group.</p>
        <p>What they didn't say: As the outgoing Liberty proved, Jeep fans are willing to overlook a few warts. Since the new one is easier on the eyes, a bit more fuel-efficient and has a few new convenience features, it should continue to appeal to its soft-core demographic.</p>
        <p>What makes it tick? The best and worst of past Liberty engines have been discontinued; namely the much sought-after diesel and the anemic four-cylinders; now the only choice is a 210-horsepower V-6, with a six-speed manual or a four-speed automatic.</p>
        <p>How much, how soon? At dealerships in the third quarter of 2007, priced in line with the outgoing model, which started at $21,600.</p>
        <p>How's it look? The '08 Liberty's more angular styling and new squared-off headlights give it more of a family resemblance, and evoke another Jeep cult classic: the Cherokee.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
