<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Annual Festival of New Plays Gives America a Temperature Reading</title>
    <meta content="04huma" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/theater/04huma.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837935"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Kentucky</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Kentucky/Louisville</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Kentucky</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Humana Festival of New American Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Louisville (Ky)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Actors Theater of Louisville</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Iizuka, Naomi</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wright, Craig</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Yew, Chay</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Garces, Michael John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE6D81F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1462" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Annual Festival of New Plays Gives America a Temperature Reading</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Annual Festival of New Plays Gives America a Temperature Reading</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES ISHERWOOD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Isherwood, Charles</byline>
      <dateline>LOUISVILLE, Ky., April 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Playwrights bearing stethoscopes swarmed over this easygoing Southern city during the past month, offering diverging diagnoses for the ills that ail the country at the Humana Festival of New American Plays. One new play argues that the tensions of urban living are fraying the bonds holding families together. Another wags a finger at teenage game-playing in cyberspace, suggesting it is corrupting a generation's morals.</p>
        <p>Who's to blame? Well, maybe it's all Barbie's fault.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Playwrights bearing stethoscopes offered diverging diagnoses for the ills that ail the country at the Humana Festival of New American Plays in Louisville, Ky.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Playwrights bearing stethoscopes swarmed over this easygoing Southern city during the past month, offering diverging diagnoses for the ills that ail the country at the Humana Festival of New American Plays. One new play argues that the tensions of urban living are fraying the bonds holding families together. Another wags a finger at teenage game-playing in cyberspace, suggesting it is corrupting a generation's morals.</p>
        <p>Who's to blame? Well, maybe it's all Barbie's fault.</p>
        <p>Yes, a solo play by Sherry Kramer, ''When Something Wonderful Ends,'' proffered the fanciful notion that the popularity of that cherished symbol of innocent American childhood might just be a cause of the conflagration in the Middle East. If that seems a lot of weight to put on the pert little shoulders of a plastic doll, it's no more peculiar than some of the other notions inspiring the playwrights at this year's festival.</p>
        <p>''The As If Body Loop,'' by Ken Weitzman, stirs together football strategy, Jewish mysticism, family dysfunction and the trauma of Sept. 11. Carlos Murillo's ''Dark Play, or Stories for Boys'' asks us to believe in a Southern California kid who has reached the age of 16 without any sustained exposure to ''Law &amp; Order.'' Crazier still, in ''Batch,'' the writer Alice Tuan, the director Whit MacLaughlin and the Philadelphia-based New Paradise Laboratories boisterously strive to turn a bachelorette party into an enjoyable spectator sport. (They do not succeed.)</p>
        <p>Marc Masterson, artistic director of the Actors Theater of Louisville, the festival's host for three decades, favors plays that engage with contemporary culture and politics. That's admirable, but it can result in work that telegraphs its importance in capital letters (a failing epitomized by Craig Wright's ''Unseen''), prizes preachment over drama (as in that secret history of Barbie) or disguises a hollow core with grabby imagery (as did ''Dark Play'').</p>
        <p>Superior artistry was mostly lacking at this year's festival, unfortunately. The selections at the festival cannot be used as a barometer of contemporary American playwriting. New plays are produced by the dozens each year at regional theaters. But it was dispiriting to come away from immersion in new playwriting with little to celebrate.</p>
        <p>Naomi Iizuka's ''Strike-Slip'' was the most accomplished of the plays. Directed with a fluid sensitivity by Chay Yew, a fellow playwright, this ensemble drama explored the tensions in the lives of eight men and women in Los Angeles, where a life-altering natural disaster is always a possibility but the little rents in the fabric of existence are the everyday agents of destruction.</p>
        <p>The marriage of a white, middle-class couple -- he's a seismologist (and thus the play's metaphor-supplier), she's a social worker -- falls apart when he begins furtively exploring his true sexual nature. The generation gap in two immigrant families -- one Latino, one Korean -- becomes an unbridgeable chasm when the values of the older generation rub raw the younger's.</p>
        <p>The play has a nice, laconic rhythm and does not force home the idea that occurrences in the lives of people in a compartmentalized city eventually ripple outward to affect the destinies of those at the fringes of their orbit. But Ms. Iizuka must rely on contortions of coincidence to knit together her divergent array of characters. Structural (and thematic) similarities to the film ''Crash'' become still more obvious when a car accident briefly unites two of them.</p>
        <p>Ms. Iizuka's play is far subtler, but in straining to draw together all the strands of her story, she sometimes allows her characters to deteriorate into mechanical cogs in the machine of the narrative. Mostly, however, the play's sympathetic exploration of the struggles in their souls gives the play an emotional dimension that the others at the festival lacked.</p>
        <p>Mr. Murillo's ''Dark Play,'' directed by Michael John Garcés, began with a nifty if nasty premise. An alienated 14-year-old, Nick (Matthew Stadelmann), begins adventuring in cyberspace. Posing in a chat room as a girl named Rachel, Nick entices the 16-year-old Adam (Will Rogers), who says he's looking for love, not hookups, into a relationship that gradually turns exploitative and destructive.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stadelmann and Mr. Rogers are terrific young actors, and they keep us engaged in the plot's creepy, curvy doings long after it is clear that Mr. Murillo is really the one playing games. His disaffected youngsters sound authentic enough -- not a small achievement -- but the psychology and sexuality of our narrator, Nick, seem to evolve rather conveniently to keep the plot spinning. And having Nick assure us that some people are, like, so gullible doesn't excuse the playwright from responsibility for some of poor Adam's more preposterous behavior.</p>
        <p>Big leaps of faith are also required to maintain a connection with Mr. Weitzman's cumbersomely titled drama, ''The As If Body Loop,'' directed by Susan V. Booth. That strange string of words refers to a neuroscientific idea put forth by Antonio Damasio (a nonfictional person, by the way) suggesting that, as a character in the play ungrammatically says, ''A nearly identical biological response happens in the body of the witness as happens in the body of the actual sufferer.''</p>
        <p>Empathy, as this concept is generally known, is the big theme of Mr. Weitzman's dark whimsy about a family of healers having a little trouble keeping themselves together. When Sarah the social worker has a breakdown, her mystically inclined mother and brothers take her at her word that she's one of the Lamed Vov, the 36 virtuous people who absorb the pain of the world in times of great calamity. (This is likewise not an invention of Mr. Weitzman, who must spend a lot of time on Wikipedia.)</p>
        <p>Authentically nonfictional though they may be, these abstruse concepts feel artificial in Mr. Weitzman's convoluted play, and the drama is ultimately a sprawling tangle of contrivance.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wright, a playwright and television writer, also takes a stylized approach to the ills of the world, post-9/11, in his prison drama ''The Unseen.'' Directed by Mr. Masterson, the play finds two weary men in side-by-side solitary confinement in an unnamed country. Valdez (Gregor Paslawsky) and Wallace (Richard Bekins) maintain a high level of discourse considering their years of brutal torture. ''It seems there's some sort of paradoxical algorithm at work,'' Wallace muses about their suffering, ''an impossible material equation we're being pushed through, like meat through a chamber of slowly grinding gears.''</p>
        <p>The burden of empathy is also on Mr. Wright's mind. The play's third character, a guard, finds himself tortured -- well, really annoyed anyway -- by the suffering he's forced to inflict. In a gruesome passage late in the play, he casually describes having ripped out a prisoner's eyes and tongue before burning him alive.</p>
        <p>The play conjures disquieting suggestions of the abuses at Abu Ghraib as well as the indefinite confinement of prisoners at Guantánamo, but Mr. Wright is really aiming for more universal ideas about the human need to create meaning from chaos even in extreme circumstances. But a play that confronts us with issues of disturbing currency really should bring some psychological truth to bear on the matter; ''The Unseen,'' vaguely derivative of Kafka, Beckett and other prison-set plays like Athol Fugard's ''Island,'' is powerful neither as either allegory nor as a political statement. A more apt title would be ''The Unreal.''</p>
        <p>The driving idea behind Ms. Kramer's play -- Barbie messed up the Middle East! -- might seem the most surreal of any put forth by the playwrights at Humana this year. But Ms. Kramer's autobiographical disquisition on the clash of cultures roiling the Arab world is grounded firmly in fact.</p>
        <p>The narrator, winningly played by Lori Wilner, informs us that her friendly little lecture (helpful slideshow included) was inspired by a ''history CD.'' This admirably frank but not exactly confidence-inspiring confession typifies the show's good-humored, chatty tone.</p>
        <p>While she putters around putting piles of Barbie paraphernalia into boxes, our hostess neatly ties together the personal and the political, yoking her own history to the mess of current global politics and a loss of faith in the American ideal. Quirky and informative though the narrative is, Ms. Kramer's writing becomes flowery and clichéd when she is at her most earnest, and the recurring notes of admonishment and sermonizing grow tiresome.</p>
        <p>''When did we stop wanting a better world?'' she asks mournfully. ''When did we start thinking it was O.K. not to grow up?'' (This from a woman still in possession of Barbie's Dream Car.) The latecoming revelation that Ms. Kramer herself drives an S.U.V. comes as a startling surprise, given the play's central idea that the world's dependence on oil (it takes a lot to make plastic dolls) is the primary cause of the horrors that beset us. Shame on her! But perhaps we can forgive her on the assumption that she acquired the S.U.V. before she listened to that CD.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
