<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sidetracked Again</title>
    <meta content="04hallock" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/opinion/04hallock.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837989"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Amtrak (National Railroad Passenger Corp)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Surface Transportation Board</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hallock, Steve (Asst Prof)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Amtrak</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E3D71F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="676" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sidetracked Again</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sidetracked Again</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Steve Hallock</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hallock, Steve (Asst Prof)</byline>
      <dateline>CARBONDALE, Ill.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Steve Hallock Op-Ed article supports federal legislation to give greater authority to Surface Transportation Board to require freight trains to yield right of way to Amtrak's passenger trains; says legislation would help Amtrak run on time and thus win public and political support and repeat customers, all without increased spending</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HERE is an opportunity for the new Congress to demonstrate its commitment to energy independence, to environmental improvement and to standing up to special interests -- all without raising taxes. Call it the Amtrak test.</p>
        <p>No, this is not one more plea to throw dollars at an inefficient, unpopular mode of transportation for a minority of citizens who don't like to drive or fly. Rather, the argument here is about strengthening Amtrak as an energy-efficient alternative to transportation systems threatened by terrorism (jet travel) or that use fuel wastefully (automobiles).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Freight trains are wreaking havoc on Amtrak schedules.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HERE is an opportunity for the new Congress to demonstrate its commitment to energy independence, to environmental improvement and to standing up to special interests -- all without raising taxes. Call it the Amtrak test.</p>
        <p>No, this is not one more plea to throw dollars at an inefficient, unpopular mode of transportation for a minority of citizens who don't like to drive or fly. Rather, the argument here is about strengthening Amtrak as an energy-efficient alternative to transportation systems threatened by terrorism (jet travel) or that use fuel wastefully (automobiles).</p>
        <p>On a recent business trip by train to Pittsburgh from Chicago, I endured frequent delays of up to 30 minutes that stretched the trip from its scheduled nine and a half hours to 14 hours. Delays also caused the return trip to be five hours late.</p>
        <p>The conductor blamed freight trains for the majority of these delays. The private freight companies that own most of the tracks used by Amtrak outside the Boston-New York-Washington corridor fail to yield the rails to passenger trains -- despite a federal regulation that Amtrak is supposed to have ''preference over freight transportation'' in using tracks. According to an Amtrak spokesman, the only way for this to change is for the Justice Department, acting on behalf of Amtrak or under its own initiative, to file a lawsuit.</p>
        <p>Such a suit is unlikely for a couple of reasons. First, there's the Bush administration's hostility toward Amtrak, as demonstrated in its continued substandard budget proposals and its call for privatization of the train service. And then there's the wording of the regulation, which uses ''preference'' rather than ''top priority'' or ''maximum priority.'' This language is vague enough to stymie any successful litigation.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Amtrak riders too often are pulled off to a side track when an Amtrak train encounters a freight train coming from the opposite direction and Amtrak's engineer is ordered to wait for the freight train to pass. Or when an Amtrak train gets behind a slow-moving freight train, the freight train is not required to pull off long enough for the passenger train to pass.</p>
        <p>Here's what added insult to the injury of one recent delay: as the train I was riding waited on a siding in Indiana for a freight train to pass with its delivery of trucks, I glanced at the flatbed and hopper cars as they rumbled by. They were empty.</p>
        <p>The college dance major on the cellphone behind me was in tears. She urged her relatives to go ahead with their planned activities without her and she would meet them in Chicago later. Maybe.</p>
        <p>Such delays have become routine. Last year, David J. Hughes, who was then the acting president and C.E.O. of Amtrak, told the board of the National Association of Railroad Passengers that Amtrak's on-time performance on freight-owned tracks decreased 50 percent from 1999 to 2005. Last April, 54 percent of all system delays for long-distance trains resulted from ''freight train interference'' and ''slow orders.'' These delays give Amtrak a bad name.</p>
        <p>Bipartisan legislation, sponsored by Senators Frank Lautenberg of New Jersey and Trent Lott of Mississippi, would give greater authority to the Surface Transportation Board for track-use enforcement, lessening the reliance on the Justice Department to remedy the freight problem. It also includes fixes for Amtrak's financial and equipment woes.</p>
        <p>The result could be a public train system better able to serve its customers by running on time and thus a train system more deserving of public and political support and of repeat customers -- and a transportation alternative offering wiser use of fuel, because rail service expends less energy per passenger mile than cars and planes.</p>
        <p>The obvious questions are these: Where is the sense in discouraging use of a means of transportation that is more energy-efficient and thus friendlier to the environment than the other two primary means of transportation? Considering the terrorist threat that the Bush administration always talks about, where is the logic in discouraging an option besides jets and motor vehicles?</p>
        <p>The Lautenberg-Lott bill seems an obvious answer.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor Steve Hallock is an assistant professor of journalism at Southern Illinois University at Carbondale.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Steve Hallock is an assistant professor of journalism at Southern Illinois University at Carbondale.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
