<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>3,400 Layoffs Send a Message To Millions</title>
    <meta content="04leonhardt" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/business/04leonhardt.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837889"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ECONOMIX"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electronics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fringe Benefits</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Circuit City Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leonhardt, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fringe Benefits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Circuit City Stores Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E0DF163FF937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1164" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>3,400 Layoffs Send a Message To Millions</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">One Safety Net Is Disappearing. What Will Follow?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID LEONHARDT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leonhardt, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Leonhardt column on Circuit City's decision to lay off 3,400 experienced workers; says workers are being let go, not because they are doing bad job and not because company is eliminating their positions, but workers are being paid too much and company will replace them with new employees who would earn less; holds situation offers unusually clear window on ruthlessness of corporate efficiency; says Circuit City has gone against tradition that job experience pays off in better wages and benefits; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Over the years, American companies have built a pretty extensive social safety net for their workers. The clearest examples of it are pensions and health insurance, which became popular during the wage freeze of World War II, when employers were looking for creative ways to give raises. Today, the United States is the only major country in the world where the private sector plays such a big role in caring for the old and the sick.</p>
        <p>But the corporate version of the welfare state is not just about retirement and health care. Another, much less obvious, piece of it is the steadily increasing pay that most workers receive over the course of their careers. All else equal, a typical worker in his early 60s makes about 50 percent more than a worker in his early 30s.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Layoffs at Circuit City last week suggest that experience isn’t as valuable as we would like to think.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Over the years, American companies have built a pretty extensive social safety net for their workers. The clearest examples of it are pensions and health insurance, which became popular during the wage freeze of World War II, when employers were looking for creative ways to give raises. Today, the United States is the only major country in the world where the private sector plays such a big role in caring for the old and the sick.</p>
        <p>But the corporate version of the welfare state is not just about retirement and health care. Another, much less obvious, piece of it is the steadily increasing pay that most workers receive over the course of their careers. All else equal, a typical worker in his early 60s makes about 50 percent more than a worker in his early 30s.</p>
        <p>This arrangement produces some enormous benefits for society. It allows Americans to enjoy ever-rising living standards over their lives and helps them pay some big expenses, like their children's college tuition and their parents' elder care, that start to hit in middle age.</p>
        <p>In strictly economic terms, however, paying people based on their age is a bit skewed. Sixty-year-olds are indeed more productive than 30-year-olds, studies have shown, but not 50 percent more productive. Experience isn't quite as valuable as we might like to believe. In effect, most companies are underpaying their younger workers and overpaying their older ones.</p>
        <p>This somewhat uncomfortable fact was a big part of the extraordinary layoff announcement  from Circuit City Stores last week. On Wednesday, the company dismissed 3,400 people, or about 8 percent of its work force, not because they were doing a bad job and not because the company was eliminating their positions. Instead, executives said the workers were being paid too much and that the company would replace them with new employees who would earn less. It was the second such layoff at Circuit City in the last five years, and it offered an unusually clear window on the ruthlessness of corporate efficiency.</p>
        <p>Whatever you think of the urge behind that efficiency -- whether you see it as the wellspring of American competitiveness or the source of middle-class insecurity -- there's no question that it is a cause of the dismantling of the private-sector safety net that has served the country well over the last half century. What, then, is going to replace that safety net?</p>
        <p>The laid-off Circuit City employees worked in the company's stores and warehouses, selling electronics, unloading boxes and the like. They generally earned $10 to $20 an hour, making them typical of the broad middle of the American work force. Nationwide, the median hourly wage  of all workers is about $15.</p>
        <p>''We just bought our first house about two or three months ago, and I'm afraid I'm going to lose it,'' Alan Hartley, a car-stereo installer in the Charlotte, N.C., area told the local NBC affiliate after he'd been let go. ''I'm not sure what I'm going to do. I'm hurt mainly because I love this company. I planned on retiring from it. I feel I've taken very good care of them, and I can't believe they did this.''</p>
        <p>Like a lot of companies, Circuit City sets ''pay ranges'' for its various jobs. Once associates reach the top of the range, they are not supposed to get further raises -- beyond the basic cost-of-living increases that also push up the pay range -- unless they are promoted.</p>
        <p>But Circuit City's store managers found it hard to stick to the policy. When they were divvying up the yearly pool of raise money, they would often increase the pay of all workers who had done a good job, even those at the range's ceiling, said Bill Cimino, Circuit City's chief spokesman. It just seemed like the decent thing to do.</p>
        <p>''It's hard to say no,'' Mr. Cimino told me. ''It's only 3 or 4 percent.''</p>
        <p>Eventually, though, the company's executives decided they couldn't afford decency for decency's sake. In recent months, there has been a price war over flat-panel televisions that's an excellent case study of the benefits and drawbacks of globalization. The price cuts have made the televisions, which are manufactured in Asia and Mexico, affordable to many more families, but have also squeezed Circuit City's margins.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the company has to reckon with cut-throat competition from Wal-Mart and Best Buy. Wal-Mart, in fact, has also been taking steps that seem aimed at pushing out more experienced workers, like setting wage caps for certain jobs and requiring people to work nights and weekends. In 2005, a top executive wrote Wal-Mart's board a memo, which McKinsey &amp; Company helped put together, noting that ''the cost of an associate with 7 years of tenure is almost 55 percent more than the cost of an associate with 1 year of tenure, yet there is no difference in his or her productivity.''</p>
        <p>There is a real question about whether these chains will hurt themselves in the long run by damaging employee morale, customer service and, ultimately, productivity. (Circuit City is forcing fired workers to wait 10 weeks to reapply for their jobs, I assume because the company executives were afraid that workers whose pay had been cut wouldn't make effective sales associates.)</p>
        <p>But there's no question that corporate America is moving in the same direction as Circuit City. Companies are wringing out what they see as inefficiencies, like traditional pensions and health insurance coverage, and tying workers' pay more closely  to their performance.</p>
        <p>It's probably not possible to halt these changes. It may not even be desirable. The flexibility of the American labor force seems to be one reason that recessions have become less frequent and unemployment is less of a problem here than in Europe, notes Jason Furman, a leading Democratic economist. In this country, fast-growing companies can hire new workers without worrying that they are making a 30-year commitment.</p>
        <p>But it would also be foolish to pretend nothing is changing. The corporate safety net of the 20th century is going away, and a fundamentally different private sector will require a fundamentally different public sector.</p>
        <p>If companies aren't going to provide health insurance, the government will need to. It can do so directly, through a single-payer system similar to those in other countries, or indirectly, by pooling together the uninsured and helping them buy coverage, as Massachusetts is now planning. If companies aren't going to provide pensions, the government will have to provide better incentives to save, helping people overcome their natural instinct to choose a flat-panel TV today over an adequate retirement tomorrow. And if companies aren't automatically going to give workers raises over the course of their lives, the country will probably need a new strategy for giving older workers new skills, something considerably more ambitious than the current, meager retraining programs.</p>
        <p>This is the real message of the Circuit City layoff, and it's likely to be the great economic debate of the coming decade.</p>
        <p>ECONOMIX</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
