<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Research Model of French Train Beats a Speed Record, Hitting 357 Miles an Hour</title>
    <meta content="04train" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/business/worldbusiness/04train.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837999"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Alstom</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Alstom</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sncf (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernard, Ariane</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">France</location>
        <org class="online_producer">SNCF</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07EFD71F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="580" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Research Model of French Train Beats a Speed Record, Hitting 357 Miles an Hour</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">French Train Breaks Rail Speed Record</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ARIANE BERNARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernard, Ariane</byline>
      <dateline>BEZANNES, France, April 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>French high-speed train code-named V150 breaks world speed record on rail, reaching 357 miles an hour (574.8 kilometers) in much publicized test in eastern France, exceeding expectations that it would hit 150 meters per second, or 540 kilometers an hour; train is research prototype meant to demonstrate superiority of TGV high-speed train and of its probable successor AGV, which is also manufactured by French engineering group Alstom; French railroad company SNCF and Alstom publicized event as test of 'French excellence,' building on national pride for 25-year-old bullet train; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A French high-speed train broke the world speed record on rail on Tuesday, reaching 357 miles an hour (574.8 kilometers) in a much publicized test in eastern France, exceeding expectations that it would hit 150 meters a second, or 540 kilometers an hour.</p>
        <p>The train, code-named V150, is a research prototype meant to demonstrate the superiority both of the TGV high-speed train and of its probable successor, the AGV, which is also manufactured by the French engineering group Alstom. The performance on Tuesday came close to but did not break the world speed record for any train, set by an electromagnetic train in 2003.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The train, a research prototype, broke the world speed record on rail, reaching 357 miles per hour.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A French high-speed train broke the world speed record on rail on Tuesday, reaching 357 miles an hour (574.8 kilometers) in a much publicized test in eastern France, exceeding expectations that it would hit 150 meters a second, or 540 kilometers an hour.</p>
        <p>The train, code-named V150, is a research prototype meant to demonstrate the superiority both of the TGV high-speed train and of its probable successor, the AGV, which is also manufactured by the French engineering group Alstom. The performance on Tuesday came close to but did not break the world speed record for any train, set by an electromagnetic train in 2003.</p>
        <p>The French railroad company SNCF and Alstom publicized the event as a test of ''French excellence,'' building on national pride for the 25-year-old bullet train.</p>
        <p>The train reached its maximum speed in about 16 minutes at a site about 125 miles from Paris on a specially chosen sector of tracks of the new Eastern Europe TGV line, which will begin service between Paris and Strasbourg in June. The V150 train, with a reduced number of train cars and larger wheels, incorporates technological elements from the AGV.</p>
        <p>SNCF and Alstom insist that the demonstration does not fulfill any immediate commercial purposes, but others say the speed could serve as a selling point in Asia and other markets.</p>
        <p>''This world speed record is intended for research, to improve security and performance,'' said Anne-Marie Idrac, the head of SNCF upon leaving the train. ''And today the train that runs the fastest is the Eastern TGV. We don't see the market today for such high speed.''</p>
        <p>Alstom, the world high-speed train leader, with 21 percent of the market, is hoping it might parlay the record into sales, as its competitors -- Siemens of Germany and Hitachi of Japan -- have cut into Alstom's lead in the competition for the market.</p>
        <p>But Alstom has 70 percent of the market for trains that reach 270 kilometers (168 miles) an hour or more, Patrick Kron, Alstom's chief executive, said in an interview.</p>
        <p>''There are big developments to come in Europe, but also Latin America where we just announced we are competing for an order in Argentina,'' Mr. Kron said.</p>
        <p>High-speed trains are a potentially lucrative market in developing countries -- China and India are the biggest markets, with China spending about 15 billion euros a year on its rail network, while India is looking at developing a high-speed train system.</p>
        <p>Crowds gathered on bridges overlooking the rail tracks to watch the train race by, and national television broadcast live images from the train.</p>
        <p>''It's quite an achievement; I hope it's going to help us sell a lot of TGV's,'' said Arnaud Delahaye, a 32-year-old technician from nearby Reims as he watched the V150 train from behind fences after its arrival at a purpose-built control center.</p>
        <p>The Maglev from Japan holds the world record for a train with a speed of 581 kilometers (361 miles) an hour recorded in 2003; it uses electromagnetic technology, where the train does not actually touch the rail. This technology is more costly, typically runs shorter distances and is less compatible with existing rail networks.</p>
        <p>High-speed trains have not caught on in the United States as they have in Europe, where TGV travel is generally considered faster transportation than air travel for distances that the TGV can cover in less than three hours.</p>
        <p>France operates 400 TGV trains on about 1,100 miles of track built especially for high speeds.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
