<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>So, Hard Work and Virtue Guarantee Success? Dream On</title>
    <meta content="04stew" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/arts/television/04stew.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837933"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Public Broadcasting Service</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Dreiser, Theodore</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bellow, Saul</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Steinbeck, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Fitzgerald, F Scott</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Petry, Ann</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jen, Gish</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E6D81F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="624" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>So, Hard Work and Virtue Guarantee Success? Dream On</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">So, Hard Work and Virtue Guarantee Success? Dream On</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN STEWART</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stewart, Susan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Care to watch a novel or two? ''Novel Reflections on the American Dream'' presents seven of them tonight, by writers from Theodore Dreiser to Saul Bellow, in a fast-moving presentation of the ''American Masters'' series on PBS.</p>
        <p>Excerpts are read by actors and illustrated by evocative photographic re-enactments that stay true to the era of each work. Characters and scenes from the 1900 ''Sister Carrie'' come to us through wrinkled and spotted sepia-tone pictures; scenes from ''The Street'' (1946) by Ann Petry seem to be lifted off a contact sheet of black-and-white prints. There is a home-movie feeling about the photographs of suburban life that depict ''Typical American,'' Gish Jen's 1991 novel of the immigrant experience.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Care to watch a novel or two? The “American Masters” series on PBS will present seven of them on Wednesday, by writers from Theodore Dreiser to Saul Bellow.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Care to watch a novel or two? ''Novel Reflections on the American Dream'' presents seven of them tonight, by writers from Theodore Dreiser to Saul Bellow, in a fast-moving presentation of the ''American Masters'' series on PBS.</p>
        <p>Excerpts are read by actors and illustrated by evocative photographic re-enactments that stay true to the era of each work. Characters and scenes from the 1900 ''Sister Carrie'' come to us through wrinkled and spotted sepia-tone pictures; scenes from ''The Street'' (1946) by Ann Petry seem to be lifted off a contact sheet of black-and-white prints. There is a home-movie feeling about the photographs of suburban life that depict ''Typical American,'' Gish Jen's 1991 novel of the immigrant experience.</p>
        <p>As the books unfold, scholars and writers discuss their relation to the American dream as set forth in Benjamin Franklin's autobiography, which a professor at the University of California, Los Angeles, calls the ''catechism'' of the ''secular religion'' of the United States.</p>
        <p>In a word, that religion is ambition. The belief that a person can reinvent himself through sheer effort is indigenous -- or at least that's the theory behind ''Reflections.'' But it is the nature of art to subvert and question, and each of the novelists represented here has created a twisted version of the dream, or a commentary on it.</p>
        <p>Dreiser's Carrie, a small-town girl who sold her soul to make it in the big city, broke all of Franklin's rules of thrift and diligence. She didn't get up early, and still she caught the worm; she didn't save a penny, and still she earned a few. Edith Wharton's Lily Bart in ''The House of Mirth'' (1905), on the other hand, fell from privilege because she couldn't sell her soul. These two novels make a tidy compare-and-contrast topic. If the first third of this show were an English composition, it would merit at least an A-minus.</p>
        <p>Things get murkier with ''The Great Gatsby'' (1925), its rich and beautiful characters illustrated in gorgeous tinted pictures in muted colors. F. Scott Fitzgerald, that handsome Princeton-educated wastrel, is analyzed with at least as much fervor as his novel, whose poignancy, if not its complexity, is communicated here.</p>
        <p>If you sniffle during ''Gatsby,'' you may have to leave the room during the section on ''The Grapes of Wrath'' (1939). After a heartbreaking history of the Dust Bowl and excerpts from John Steinbeck's journalism on the plight of its victims, Keith Carradine reads the novel's wrenching last scene. Pass the Kleenex.</p>
        <p>If it seems like cheating to be so moved by a précis of a novel you haven't read in years (or ever), well, maybe it is. ''Reflections'' doesn't intend to be a substitute for reading, but the truth is that it offers viewers a chance to experience many of the pleasures of literature without actually having to slog through a single chapter.</p>
        <p>The program ends with Bellow's ''Seize the Day'' (1957) and the scene in which the hapless hero finds himself at a stranger's funeral, where he finally lets down his guard, bathed in ''a great and happy oblivion of tears.''</p>
        <p>For Bellow, feeling is the point, and never mind how you get there. Times have changed since Franklin first described the way to the American dream; shortcuts have been invented. Maybe Bellow would be happy to have his work experienced through this well-made video version of Cliffs Notes. But it's a cinch that he could never have accomplished that work if he'd learned about literature from TV.</p>
        <p>American Masters  Novel Reflections on the American Dream  Tonight on most PBS stations (check local listings).</p>
        <p>Directed and written by Michael Epstein; Susan Lacy, executive producer; Julie Sacks and Mr. Epstein, producers. Produced by Thirteen/WNET New York.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
