<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Recalling a Time When a Street Divided Two Worlds</title>
    <meta content="04grim" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/books/04grim.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837931"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E6D81F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="881" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Recalling a Time When a Street Divided Two Worlds</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Recalling a Time When a Street Divided Two Worlds</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GRIMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Grimes, William</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Invisible Wall  By Harry Bernstein  297 pages. Ballantine Books. $22.95.</p>
        <p>Harry Bernstein grew up in a small world. In the Lancashire mill town of his childhood, during the teens and twenties of the last century, the poor Jews clustered along a single dead-end street, and even that was only half theirs. Christians lived on one side, Jews on the other, separated by a few feet that might as well have been hundreds of miles. ''The Invisible Wall,'' Mr. Bernstein's heart-wrenching memoir, describes two cultures cohabiting uneasily, prey to misunderstandings that distort lives on both sides. It is a world of pain and prejudice, evoked in spare, restrained prose that brilliantly illuminates a time, a place and a family struggling valiantly to beat impossible odds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Harry Bernstein’s heart-wrenching memoir describes a Jewish childhood in England marked by difference and want.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Invisible Wall  By Harry Bernstein  297 pages. Ballantine Books. $22.95.</p>
        <p>Harry Bernstein grew up in a small world. In the Lancashire mill town of his childhood, during the teens and twenties of the last century, the poor Jews clustered along a single dead-end street, and even that was only half theirs. Christians lived on one side, Jews on the other, separated by a few feet that might as well have been hundreds of miles. ''The Invisible Wall,'' Mr. Bernstein's heart-wrenching memoir, describes two cultures cohabiting uneasily, prey to misunderstandings that distort lives on both sides. It is a world of pain and prejudice, evoked in spare, restrained prose that brilliantly illuminates a time, a place and a family struggling valiantly to beat impossible odds.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bernstein's parents, like many of their neighbors from Russia and Poland, fled persecution in the Pale of Settlement and found a refuge in England. There anti-Semitism took a more modified form, usually expressed in cold contempt or muttered comments. The kind of Christian who taunted or beat Jewish children on their way to school was called a bates or, in the plural, batesemas. But the local Christians were not these. ''For the most part, our Christians were a quiet, decent lot, and the two sides got along quite well,'' Mr. Bernstein writes.</p>
        <p>The Christians owned the few shops on the street or worked in the textile mills. The Jews, like Mr. Bernstein's father, eked out a living in tailoring shops. No one had much money, but Mr. Bernstein's father, an angry, embittered man, drank most of his paycheck away, leaving his wife to beg for the leavings, which were never enough to support two girls and three boys. Young Harry slept at the foot of the bed occupied by his two brothers, dodging kicks all through the night. His illiterate mother dictated letters to relatives in Chicago, begging them to send steamship tickets so the family could emigrate to the United States.</p>
        <p>In this, his first book, the 96-year-old Mr. Bernstein tells his story, so remote in time, almost as though it were a fable, occasionally addressing the reader directly. (''I have told you before,'' he begins one sentence, characteristically.) The setting, beautifully rendered, recalls early D. H. Lawrence, with mill hands trudging off to work early in the morning, their iron-shod clogs raising sparks on the cobblestones. In Mr. Bernstein's hands, the small events of family life and the daily dramas on the street take on a shimmering, timeless quality.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bernstein's trip to the past is warm without being sentimental. The pleasures of childhood are undercut by slights, threats and grinding poverty, and even the rosiest scenes turn dark at the edges, like the game his mother made of the family wash. Standing at the bottom of the stairs, she would count to three, whereupon all five children would throw their dirty clothes from the top of the stairs and she would try to catch them.</p>
        <p>''Some she managed to catch with her open arms, others rained down on her head, hit her in the face, or scattered on the floor around her feet,'' he writes. ''After gathering them, she sewed and mended and washed under the gaslight until late in the night.''</p>
        <p>The most memorable scenes are simply awful. Lily, Mr. Bernstein's older sister, wins a scholarship to the local grammar school, finishing at the top of a highly competitive examination. When the first day of school arrives, her father drags her to the tailor's shop by her hair and puts her to work. One of Mr. Bernstein's brothers, keen to become a journalist, is summoned to Manchester by an editor who tells him to stop wasting his time looking for a job, since no newspaper in the country will hire a Jew. ''Stick to where you belong, in the tailoring shops and pawnshops and the markets,'' he tells him. ''Remember that and you'll be all right.''</p>
        <p>A Romeo and Juliet drama gradually unfolds on Mr. Bernstein's divided street. Lily falls in love with Arthur Forshaw, the son of a local shopkeeper, provoking a cultural crisis. One Jewish girl on the street has already been shipped off to Australia by her family after being caught kissing a Christian, but this is worse. Mr. Bernstein's mother, who allows only a Shabbos goy to enter her house to light the fire on Friday nights, regards marriage to a Christian as death. In a hastily dictated letter to America, she begs for a steamship ticket for Lily.</p>
        <p>''I do not want to sit shivah for my daughter,'' she pleads. ''I do not want her to die.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bernstein treats his material novelistically. He recalls in detail circumstances and conversations no 5-year-old could possibly remember, and he turns up, with uncanny frequency, close enough to witness or eavesdrop on important events. As a purely documentary record, ''The Invisible Wall'' strains credulity, but as an emotional experience and a vivid retelling of the author's past, it exerts uncommon power.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bernstein, with great economy and skill, maneuvers an extensive cast of characters onto his small stage and lets their stories play out within the larger historical and social context. In the end, that little street turns out to be very big indeed.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
