<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For the Best Falafel, Do It All Yourself</title>
    <meta content="04mini" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837928"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE MINIMALIST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/The Minimalist</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vegetables</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E7D81F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="617" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For the Best Falafel, Do It All Yourself</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mark Bittman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bittman, Mark</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YOU cannot say enough about falafel. These seasoned fritters are among the best things you can make with chickpeas, they're easy and rewarding to fry (perfect for novice deep-fryers) and they are vegetarian.</p>
        <p>Unlike other bean fritters, falafel is made from uncooked beans. The cooking goes best when the beans are soaked for a full day in plenty of water.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YOU cannot say enough about falafel. These seasoned fritters are among the best things you can make with chickpeas, they're easy and rewarding to fry (perfect for novice deep-fryers) and they are vegetarian.</p>
        <p>Unlike other bean fritters, falafel is made from uncooked beans. The cooking goes best when the beans are soaked for a full day in plenty of water.</p>
        <p>Yes, you can make falafel with canned beans, but the difference in both texture and taste is pronounced. Dried beans are the way to go.</p>
        <p>There are two keys to making good falafel. First, keep the amount of water you use when grinding the beans to an absolute minimum. More water makes grinding easier, but it also virtually guarantees that the batter will fall apart when it hits the hot oil. If this happens, bind the remaining mixture by stirring in a little flour.</p>
        <p>For this reason, a food processor or very powerful blender is essential; you don't want a blender that isn't strong enough to grind the beans without adding too much water.</p>
        <p>The second essential step is to get the oil hot enough: 350 degrees or a little higher. If you don't have a thermometer, just wait until the oil shimmers and then add a pinch of the batter. When it sizzles immediately, sinks about halfway to the bottom, then rises to the top, the oil is ready. If it sinks and stays down, the oil is too cold; if it doesn't sink at all, the oil is too hot.</p>
        <p>Once you get the batter and the oil right, your little patties or balls will brown readily and evenly; they won't spatter at all.</p>
        <p>You can serve falafel in a pita with lettuce, tomatoes, cucumbers and other raw vegetables; or with a green salad.</p>
        <p>If you want a fast tahini sauce, mix equal amounts of tahini and yogurt, and season to taste with a little salt, pepper, cumin, raw garlic if you like, and lemon juice. Not-too-hot chili paste is another good accompaniment.</p>
        <p>Falafel  Time: 1 hour, plus 24 hours' soaking</p>
        <p>1 3/4 cup dried chickpeas  2 cloves garlic, lightly crushed  1 small onion, quartered  1 teaspoon ground coriander  1 tablespoon ground cumin  Scant teaspoon cayenne, or to taste  1 cup chopped parsley or cilantro leaves  1 teaspoon salt  1/2 teaspoon black pepper  1/2 teaspoon baking soda  1 tablespoon lemon juice  Neutral oil, like grapeseed or corn, for frying.</p>
        <p>1. Put beans in a large bowl and cover with water by 3 or 4 inches; they will triple in volume. Soak for 24 hours, adding water if needed to keep beans submerged.  2. Drain beans well (reserve soaking water) and transfer to a food processor. Add remaining ingredients except oil; pulse until minced but not puréed, scraping sides of bowl down; add soaking water if necessary to allow machine to do its work, but no more than 1 or 2 tablespoons. Keep pulsing until mixture comes together. Taste, adding salt, pepper, cayenne or lemon juice to taste.  3. Put oil in a large, deep saucepan to a depth of at least 2 inches; more is better. The narrower the saucepan the less oil you need, but the more oil you use the more patties you can cook at a time. Turn heat to medium-high and heat oil to about 350 degrees (a pinch of batter will sizzle immediately).  4. Scoop heaping tablespoons of batter and shape into balls or small patties. Fry in batches, without crowding, until nicely browned, turning as necessary; total cooking time will be less than 5 minutes. Serve hot or at room temperature.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 to 8 servings.</p>
        <p>THE MINIMALIST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
