<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chevy Looks East for a Small-Scale Hatchback</title>
    <meta content="NUGGET--chevy--trax" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837924"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00EED9163FF937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="225" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chevy Looks East for a Small-Scale Hatchback</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE ULRICH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Introduced on Wednesday: Chevrolet Trax, Beat and Groove</p>
        <p>Are they real? Definitely in Asia, where one of these models will replace the current Chevy Spark around 2010. The United States remains on hold for now.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Introduced on Wednesday: Chevrolet Trax, Beat and Groove</p>
        <p>Are they real? Definitely in Asia, where one of these models will replace the current Chevy Spark around 2010. The United States remains on hold for now.</p>
        <p>What's the point? G.M.'s South Korean design studio is driving the creation of a global subcompact car, and Chevrolet is using the auto show to audition this trio of miniature hatchbacks including an American Idol-style Web vote to decide showgoers' favorite, at www.voteforchevrolet.com</p>
        <p>What they said: "It's the perfect urban S.U.V.," said G.M.'s design chief, Ed Welburn, while a group of youngsters began gyrating onstage like an iPod commercial come to life. (Note to G.M. Choreography Department: actual cool kids don't wear Rolling Stones t-shirts).</p>
        <p>What they didn't say: Whether there's a big enough market in America's supersized culture for the kind of half-pint, lightly powered cars that dominate Europe and the Far East.</p>
        <p>What makes it tick? The Trax has a 1-liter 3-cylinder engine with 50 horsepower; the Beat gets a turbo 1.4-liter 4-cylinder; and the Groove is the mileage champ with a 1-liter diesel that would top 50 miles per gallon.</p>
        <p>How much, how soon? No sooner than 2010 for the U.S., priced like your typical budget mobile around $11,000-$12,000 to start.</p>
        <p>How's it look? Not bad for starter-car subcompacts, especially the wide-eyed, pug-nosed Trax.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
