<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Salad No Rabbit Could Love</title>
    <meta content="04appe" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837943"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="A GOOD APPETITE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poultry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Salads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E4D81F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1019" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Salad No Rabbit Could Love</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Melissa Clark</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clark, Melissa</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN college, I worked at a restaurant where the owner had a low opinion of the ordering habits of his female clientele. Each time he spied a hostess seating a table of women, he curled his thin lips and hissed derisively: ''Here come the rabbits.''</p>
        <p>What he meant was that women nibbled salads, and that was to be pitied. And in the case of this particular restaurant -- an Upper West Side sports-bar-cum-steakhouse with a choice of soggy mesclun or sliced pinkish tomatoes and red onions -- it certainly was.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN college, I worked at a restaurant where the owner had a low opinion of the ordering habits of his female clientele. Each time he spied a hostess seating a table of women, he curled his thin lips and hissed derisively: ''Here come the rabbits.''</p>
        <p>What he meant was that women nibbled salads, and that was to be pitied. And in the case of this particular restaurant -- an Upper West Side sports-bar-cum-steakhouse with a choice of soggy mesclun or sliced pinkish tomatoes and red onions -- it certainly was.</p>
        <p>Ever since that experience, and in part, I'm sure, to defy it, I tend to gravitate toward salads that are as far from abstemious rabbit fodder as possible.</p>
        <p>Give me curls of prosciutto and crumbles of cheese; candied nuts and duck confit; oily, marinated artichoke hearts; fried croutons; and runny egg yolk. Oh, and some crisp, fresh greens and other vegetables, too, but because I like them and not just because they are good for me.</p>
        <p>Salads need not be advance penance for that order of chocolate fondant; dressed with enough real ranch dressing and garnished with bacon, salad can be even richer.</p>
        <p>Of all the outrageously decadent salads I can think of, Buffalo chicken wing salad is the pinnacle.</p>
        <p>I've always imagined it this way: crackling-skinned chicken wings, doused with melted butter and a fiery, vinegary hot sauce, are laid atop a mountain of pale, tender lettuces and succulent slivered celery. To mitigate the chili heat and up the lusciousness ante, homemade blue cheese dressing is drizzled over all.</p>
        <p>Truth be told, I held this lusty vision of a Buffalo chicken wing salad in my head long before I ever actually set about making one. When the craving came on full force one recent afternoon, I started poking around online, looking for a recipe that was a close enough match to my ideal.</p>
        <p>What I found was that although recipes for the chicken wings themselves didn't vary all that much (deep-fry or, occasionally, broil the wings, bathe in butter and hot sauce, serve forth with celery sticks and blue cheese dressing), the salads ran the gamut. This is probably because the wings have become a codified classic. They are open to minor edits, but not a rewrite.</p>
        <p>A Buffalo chicken salad has no such identity, so anything goes. The only thing most recipes had in common was that they veered far from the pungent, deep-fried indulgence that I craved, taking the salad-as-diet-food road. Crisp fried wings were replaced with baked or sautéed breasts; reduced-fat blue cheese dressing trumped homemade and creamy. The butter was nixed.</p>
        <p>The Internet being no help, I turned to my cookbooks for guidance, grabbing Larry Forgione's ''An American Place'' (Morrow, 1996) off the shelf. Having worked with Mr. Forgione while I was in graduate school, I knew that if anyone had a recipe for turning authentic Buffalo chicken wings into a rich and robust salad, it was he. Indeed, I found a salad pretty close to my ideal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Forgione's recipe differed from the picture in my head in one major way. I wanted real wings. He calls for boneless, skinless chicken thighs. I could see his logic. Thighs can be eaten with a knife and fork. Wings are finger food. And since salad is not usually considered finger food, thighs make the whole dish neater and more convenient.</p>
        <p>His recipe also includes tomatoes, which I didn't want. And his hot sauce measure was about an eighth of what I had planned. But Mr. Forgione's blue cheese dressing was genius. His trick? Use a bit of hot water to partially melt the blue cheese before stirring in the mayonnaise and sour cream, which makes for the creamiest of all dressings.</p>
        <p>So I merged his recipe with the vision in my head, tweaking everything. The thighs were nearly as good as the wings, and much easier to eat. In fact, this amalgam was perfect, as gilded and overstuffed as any devoted but non-dieting salad eater could possibly want. Even those with rabbit-like sensibilities will be reassured by the copious green pile of lettuce, celery, scallions and parsley.</p>
        <p>After all, we can always order the mesclun tomorrow.</p>
        <p>Buffalo-Style Chicken Wing Salad  Time: 45 minutes, plus at least 30 minutes for marinating</p>
        <p>3 pounds chicken wings, without tips, or 8 skinless, boneless chicken thighs  2 tablespoons hot sauce, preferably Frank's RedHot Original sauce, or to taste  1 tablespoon Tabasco sauce, or to taste  1 tablespoon apple cider vinegar or white wine vinegar  1/2 teaspoon salt, more to taste  Oil for deep-frying  1/2 cup crumbled blue cheese  1/2 cup buttermilk  1/2 cup mayonnaise  1 to 2 tablespoons heavy cream or milk, or to taste  1/4 teaspoon freshly ground black pepper  6 tablespoons butter  2 heads bibb lettuce, torn into pieces  2/3 cup parsley leaves  6 tender inner celery ribs with leaves, thinly sliced  4 scallions, trimmed and thinly sliced.</p>
        <p>1. Cut wings in half at joint. If using thighs, cut into 1-inch strips. In large bowl, toss chicken with 1 tablespoon hot sauce, 1/2 tablespoon Tabasco, 1/2 tablespoon vinegar and 1/2 teaspoon salt. Marinate at room temperature for 30 minutes, or 4 hours in refrigerator.  2. Heat 4 inches of oil in a large pot to 375 degrees. Mash together cheese and 11/2 tablespoons very hot water in small bowl. Cheese should partly melt, but there should be some lumps. Mix in buttermilk, mayonnaise and enough cream or milk to make dressing pourable. Stir in pepper.  3. When oil is hot enough, deep-fry chicken until golden brown all over, about 10 minutes for wings or 5 minutes for thigh strips. Be careful of splatter. Transfer to a paper-towel-lined plate to drain.  4. Melt butter in small saucepan. Stir in remaining hot sauces and vinegar. Pour into large bowl and add chicken. Toss well and season with salt and more hot sauce to taste.  5. Toss lettuce, parsley, celery and scallions in large bowl. Divide among four plates and top with chicken. Drizzle with blue cheese dressing and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>A GOOD APPETITE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
