<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It May Not Be a Pitch That Stops Bonds Short</title>
    <meta content="04roberts" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/sports/baseball/04roberts.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837905"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Selena Roberts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Perjury</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bonds, Barry</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Roberts, Selena</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E7DE163FF937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="899" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It May Not Be a Pitch That Stops Bonds Short</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">It May Not Be a Pitch That Stops Bonds Short</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a game of ''I Spy Barry Bonds,'' did you see a cheat or a victim casting muscular shadows in the sun during the Giants season opener yesterday? Did you groan when Bonds walked in the fourth or cheer when he finished without a homer?</p>
        <p>Whatever you felt, remember the feds have emotions, too.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>By inching no closer in his pursuit of Hank Aaron’s No. 755 on Tuesday, Barry Bonds simply delayed the inevitable  not the record, but his own indictment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a game of ''I Spy Barry Bonds,'' did you see a cheat or a victim casting muscular shadows in the sun during the Giants season opener yesterday? Did you groan when Bonds walked in the fourth or cheer when he finished without a homer?</p>
        <p>Whatever you felt, remember the feds have emotions, too.</p>
        <p>By inching no closer in his pursuit of Hank Aaron's No. 755, by remaining 22 home runs behind history, Bonds simply delayed the inevitable -- not the sexy record, but his own indictment.</p>
        <p>However you keep stats, remember the feds have home-run tickers, too.</p>
        <p>There is conceivably a point this summer -- with Bonds at No. 748 or No. 752 -- when federal prosecutors could decide to play legacy interruptus. There may be a convenient time this summer -- with Greg Anderson still lip-sealed in prison -- when the Balco sleuths could ride into the season and play baseball saviors by handing down an indictment of Bonds.</p>
        <p>''I think the lead investigator has been fixated with taking Barry down,'' Bonds's lawyer, Michael Rains, said yesterday in a telephone interview, referring to special agent Jeff Novitzky. ''I think he is so fixated on Barry getting the record that he would want to take him out first.''</p>
        <p>Rains is unbridled at presenting theories as distractions around the Bonds case, but it is not difficult to imagine one government agent's agenda pushing forward considering the political chaos surrounding the United States attorney's office.</p>
        <p>''It's not a healthy motivation,'' Rains said. ''It's an improper motivation. I think it would be transparent. But in some cases, I don't think the government cares if its arrogance is transparent.'' That's funny. Neither does Bonds. He is an unabashed narcissist with AT&amp;T Park as his reflecting pond. In the stands, Bonds sees nothing but adoration when he looks at Giants fans who will drive a Prius, shop at Whole Foods, but hug the tree trunk of an inorganic, aloof superstar.</p>
        <p>Bonds left after the Giants' 7-0 loss to the Padres without comment. Somehow, Giants devotees are inured to his silence. Somehow, Bonds commands unconditional love, hopeless devotion, from those near and far.</p>
        <p>The common room inside the federal correctional facility across the San Francisco Bay in Dublin, Calif., has a garden-variety television, with the channel selected by inmate consensus, the prison official Sally Swarts said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Inmates might well have tuned in to the Giants' opener. And Anderson might well have been viewing, too, as he spent yet another day of another month behind razor wire for the love of Bonds. Or is Bonds's loyal trainer selling his freedom for an eventual payback?</p>
        <p>Anderson is being held for contempt of court, unwilling to potentially out Bonds for declaring flaxseed oil as his secret power potion when it was only a beard to his steroid use. Anderson is the code-breaker for prosecutors, the snitch who could decode seized calendars. He is the key to an indictment of Bonds amid the feds' sport of perjury gotcha.</p>
        <p>Bonds owes Anderson. And yet everyone from Gary Sheffield to former business associates to charity organizers would cast Bonds as Mr. Potter of Pottersville. Rains referred to Bonds as prudent. Everyone else calls him cheap.</p>
        <p>In his grand jury testimony reported by The San Francisco Chronicle, Bonds said, ''Greg has nothing. Guy lives in his car half the time.''</p>
        <p>Bonds never felt rich-man's guilt for his buddy. Not then. So why now?</p>
        <p>''If you know anything about Barry's relationship with Greg, he paid him a terrible pittance,'' Rains said. ''I'm his lawyer, and I'm telling you, I think Barry should have paid Greg a hell of a lot more money.</p>
        <p>''If Greg was into the big payday, he'd have a book deal in the works.''</p>
        <p>Anderson isn't talking to anyone, not the news media, not the feds, not a ghost writer. There appears to be no breaking point for Anderson. An indictment of Bonds without Anderson's help may, as Rains said, ''prove the imprisonment of Greg was a harassment tactic.''</p>
        <p>An indictment may also mean Anderson's release. But this is not how Anderson would have wanted his freedom. He has kept his mouth shut and remained behind bars on a sacrifice to protect Bonds. If Anderson didn't talk, he has reasoned, Bonds could continue his march toward Aaron. The feds could ruin that plan if they step in and stop Bonds's chase short of No. 755.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't be shocked if they made a move like that,'' Rains said.</p>
        <p>In the world of Balco, nothing is unexpected. Bonds elicits so many emotions -- from joy to anger to stubborn indifference -- it wouldn't be surprising for the feds to be following their own home run ticker.</p>
        <p>In the eighth inning, Bonds lifted a deep fly ball to the warning track in left field. It was caught. With the game against the Padres long out of reach, the Giants' fans dispersed disappointed in Bonds's homerless day.</p>
        <p>Their devotion to Bonds -- like Anderson's -- is unclouded. But when it comes to the matter of Bonds versus Balco, it's more complicated: Do you pull for the self-consumed Bonds or the hubristic feds?</p>
        <p>Amid all the untidiness of the Bonds pursuit, the answer is simple: You have to pull for Hank Aaron. Baseball doesn't deserve to be saved by the feds after years of owner denial and union obstruction over steroid use in their sport, but Aaron does.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: selenasports@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: selenasports@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
