<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Do We Have the National Will to Fight Cancer?</title>
    <meta content="l04cancer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837984"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Breast</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4D71F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1504" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Do We Have the National Will to Fight Cancer?</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As the articles in ''Humans vs. Cancer: Who's Winning Now?'' illustrate (Op-Ed, April 1), there is no shortage of ideas for how to deal with cancer. What appears to be missing, however, is a sense of urgency -- an appreciation of cancer as the grave and growing crisis it is -- and the national will to confront it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As the articles in ''Humans vs. Cancer: Who's Winning Now?'' illustrate (Op-Ed, April 1), there is no shortage of ideas for how to deal with cancer. What appears to be missing, however, is a sense of urgency -- an appreciation of cancer as the grave and growing crisis it is -- and the national will to confront it.</p>
        <p>If terrorists unleashed a biological attack on American soil that started killing more than 1,500 Americans every day, as cancer does, wouldn't we mobilize every national resource to find an antidote or a cure?</p>
        <p>It is a national shame that many Americans -- racial and ethnic minorities, the poor and those with little or no health insurance -- are less likely to receive quality cancer care and therefore more likely to die.</p>
        <p>As the American public and both political parties did when launching the war on cancer more than three decades ago, we need to summon the will to make cancer a national priority once again.</p>
        <p>Nancy G. Brinker  Founder  Susan G. Komen for the Cure  Palm Beach, Fla., April 2, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As the director of an infectious diseases research institute that emphasizes the bridging of clinical and academic worlds, I applaud Susan Love's call to change the dialogue and approach to cancer research (''To Break the Disease, Break the Mold,'' Op-Ed, April 1).</p>
        <p>Scientific discovery that addresses underlying disease mechanisms requires a union of physicians and academic researchers to develop novel approaches that can adroitly explore areas like host genetics while looking out for new etiologic agents.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, such high-risk science that challenges prevailing doctrine has been a casualty in a federal fiscal environment where biomedical financing is approaching 1 in 10 grants.</p>
        <p>The cancer field may need to turn to a Gates Foundation-type approach for diseases of the developing world, one that emphasizes creativity and new paradigms to solve old problems.</p>
        <p>David Perlin  Newark, April 1, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is the director of the Public Health Research Institute.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>What should be stressed when thinking about cancer is the importance of basic science research. Currently, administrators who control resources for cancer research often place enormous emphasis on ''translational'' studies, speculating that we know enough about the basic principles of molecular, cell and organismal biology to translate the knowledge to cancer cures.</p>
        <p>But as this year's Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine has shown, we have recently gained early glimpses of mechanisms of genetic control that were wholly unanticipated from earlier studies, and it could take a dozen years or more for that information to translate to the clinic.</p>
        <p>Despite the temptation to assume that we know enough of nature's secrets to harness and prevent cancer, those of us doing basic research can see many vistas yet unexplored. It will take years, with many more unanticipated discoveries, before we should fully shift our gaze to translational science.</p>
        <p>Ken Zaret  Philadelphia, April 1, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is senior member and leader of the cell and developmental biology program, Fox Chase Cancer Center.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I am glad that politicians feel strong empathy toward both Elizabeth Edwards and Tony Snow, but none of it will count for much unless we resume the war on cancer President Richard M. Nixon began in 1971.</p>
        <p>Any candidate who cares about what this disease is doing to our people should commit to raising taxes by a specific amount that will finance the National Institutes of Health and other research institutes so that they have the resources to eradicate this disease.</p>
        <p>I know that candidates are risk-averse, but anyone who cannot stand up to the misanthropes who would not pay more taxes to save the lives of family members, friends and fellow Americans does not deserve to be president.</p>
        <p>One of the candidates should announce right now that he or she will impose a cancer tax.</p>
        <p>M. J. Rosenberg  Chevy Chase, Md., April 1, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The Op-Ed articles about cancer on April 1 didn't discuss the crushing disparities that leave ethnic minorities, the poorly educated and the economically poor failing to receive early diagnosis and timely treatment that could save many lives even with what we know today.</p>
        <p>Behavioral and public health research has shown ways to reduce these disparities, but this research gets minimal support from federal granting agencies compared with their investments in genetics and basic biological research.</p>
        <p>Behavioral and public health programs have helped millions quit smoking and could make similar contributions to reversing obesity and its risks for both cancer and heart disease. But the research and the programs are poorly financed amid heavy promotion of the dream of the genetic fix.</p>
        <p>We need a balance of research into both biological breakthroughs and behavioral and public health approaches.</p>
        <p>Edwin B. Fisher  Chapel Hill, N.C., April 1, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer, a professor of public health at the University of North Carolina, is the past president of the Society of Behavioral Medicine.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>From pesticides to plastics to cleaning and hygiene products, we spend our days in a cloud of carcinogens. For each product, we are told, the amount of poison is too small to cause cancer.</p>
        <p>But who is studying the cumulative effect of all the cancer-causing agents in the substances we touch, breathe, ingest or bathe in?</p>
        <p>Several April 1 Op-Ed writers mentioned genetic vulnerabilities, but what about the environmental factors that may trigger those vulnerabilities?</p>
        <p>I'm not surprised by the lack of research on this. The companies that finance cancer research are often polluters themselves.</p>
        <p>Patricia Gordon Lamanna  Poughkeepsie, N.Y., April 1, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Feeding the Cancer Machine,'' by Shannon Brownlee (Op-Ed, April 1): The purpose of screening is not to catch disease at its late stages, when aggressive treatment offers ''marginal benefits'' in exchange for lucrative profits, but to catch it before it has a chance to grow or spread.</p>
        <p>If caught in Stage 1, aggressive treatment can achieve five-year survival rates approaching 90 percent for both breast and prostate cancer. But most Stage 1 disease is asymptomatic. Without screening, patients show up later, with larger tumors and potentially metastatic disease. Five-year survival for Stage 3 breast cancer is 36 percent. For Stage 4, it's 7 percent. Screening isn't about profits. It's about saving lives.</p>
        <p>Suhael Momin  Cleveland, April 1, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is a medical student at Case Western Reserve University School of Medicine.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Shannon Brownlee (Op-Ed, April 1) and Ralph W. Moss (Op-Ed, April 1) denounce the profit motive that drives hospitals and pharmaceutical companies to pursue lucrative strategies and ignore other possibilities.</p>
        <p>The reduction of Medicare payments for M.R.I.'s as well as for chemotherapy seems like a futile attempt to foil the profit motive when what is needed are more screenings, more clinical trials and special support for unpatentable therapies that work.</p>
        <p>Albert Henderson  Milford, Conn., April 1, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Thank you to Betty Rollin (''Talk for the Cure,'' Op-Ed, April 1) for describing the immediate kinship that those of us who've had breast cancer feel for those who have newly received a diagnosis of the disease.</p>
        <p>Recently in a restaurant, I saw an obviously bald woman, with a scarf loosely tied around her head, sitting with that same numbed look I had on my face six years ago. I approached her and told her that ''things would get better.'' She grasped my hand and asked me how long it had been for me, and when I told her, she thanked me.</p>
        <p>Thank you, too, to Elizabeth Edwards for her candor and understanding that life must go on: this is what gives us courage. Believing otherwise makes us captives of the disease, and no one wants that.</p>
        <p>Carol G. Feldman  Boston, April 2, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Much Wider Use of M.R.I.'s Urged for Breast Exam'' (front page, March 28): A heartfelt thank you to the 969 women who agreed to have an extra diagnostic exam as part of the study that ultimately revealed that an M.R.I. scan for the contralateral breast is more effective than mammography in detecting additional breast cancer sites.</p>
        <p>They knew that they were risking a ''false positive'' reading, but 121 women went further and had biopsies, of which 30 were positive for previously unrecognized cancer.</p>
        <p>The other women who did not directly benefit from such a discovery are still rewarded in the knowledge that they have made a contribution to better health care for millions more.</p>
        <p>These women will forever be anonymous to science and to us all, so let's take this moment to thank all the volunteers who stepped up to help advance the quality and effectiveness of health care worldwide by participating in this important research.</p>
        <p>Cindy Barnard  Chicago, March 28, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is the director of quality strategies at Northwestern Memorial Hospital.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
