<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bronze Statue of McGwire Waits on Deck in Storage</title>
    <meta content="04statue" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/sports/baseball/04statue.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070411T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837883"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">St Louis Cardinals</org>
        <person class="online_producer">McGwire, Mark</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E2DF163FF937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="509" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bronze Statue of McGwire Waits on Deck in Storage</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bronze Statue of McGwire Waits on Deck in Storage</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAT BORZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Borzi, Pat</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS, April 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the corner of Eighth and Clark Streets, 10 bronze statues form a symmetrical gantlet in front of the team store at Busch Stadium.</p>
        <p>Harry Weber made the statues, almost all of them representing St. Louis Cardinals greats in various action poses. An 11th is under a canvas in Weber's downtown office, ready to join them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Cardinals have not announced plans to retire Mark McGwire’s No. 25, leaving the fate of a McGwire statue at Busch Stadium unclear.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At the corner of Eighth and Clark Streets, 10 bronze statues form a symmetrical gantlet in front of the team store at Busch Stadium.</p>
        <p>Harry Weber made the statues, almost all of them representing St. Louis Cardinals greats in various action poses. An 11th is under a canvas in Weber's downtown office, ready to join them.</p>
        <p>Whether that statue, of Mark McGwire, ever takes its place with the others remains to be seen.</p>
        <p>The statues honor nine Cardinals who have been elected to the baseball Hall of Fame or have had their numbers retired by the club. The 10th is of the Negro leagues star Cool Papa Bell.</p>
        <p>The Cardinals have not announced plans to retire McGwire's No. 25, and his chances of being elected to the Hall of Fame in the next few years appear slim, leaving the fate of the statue unclear.</p>
        <p>''It's not likely to see the light of day anytime soon,'' Weber, 64, said in a telephone interview Tuesday from his 130-acre horse farm near Wright City, Mo.</p>
        <p>But Weber said that the Cardinals were willing to wait several more years for McGwire to be elected. In January, McGwire was named on only 23.5 percent of the Hall of Fame ballots in his first year of eligibility, well short of the 75 percent needed for election.</p>
        <p>''A couple of people have come to me and said, 'I'll buy it,' '' Weber said. ''But the Cardinals own it. They paid for it.''</p>
        <p>The Cardinals' president, Mark C. Lamping, did not immediately respond to a voice message left at his office Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Last month, he told The Associated Press that any decision about the McGwire statue would be up to the Cardinals' ownership.</p>
        <p>As a rule, the Cardinals retire a player's number only if he has been elected to the Hall of Fame. The club made an exception for the popular third baseman Ken Boyer, who died of cancer in 1982 and had his number retired two years later.</p>
        <p>The Hall of Fame second baseman Rogers Hornsby played for the Cardinals before numbers came into common use. An interlocking Cardinals logo represents Hornsby in the retired numbers displays below the main scoreboard.</p>
        <p>The eventual election of McGwire, who hit 583 home runs and broke Roger Maris's single-season home run record with 70 in 1998, seemed a foregone conclusion when the Cardinals' owner, William O. DeWitt Jr., commissioned the statue in 2002. Weber said that DeWitt asked him to do it the day that Weber's statue of Ozzie Smith was unveiled</p>
        <p>''At the time, everybody thought he was a lead-pipe cinch to get in the Hall,'' Weber said of McGwire. ''I loved to see him coming to the plate. It was like he was coming out of a poem, our Mighty Casey.''</p>
        <p>Then came March 17, 2005, and McGwire's appearance before a Congressional committee investigating steroid use in baseball. ''I knew it was probably a goner the first time he opened his mouth,'' Weber said. ''He dug his own grave. It was a sad performance.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 11, 2007, Wednesday  A sports article last Wednesday about the prospect of adding a statue of Mark McGwire to those honoring great St. Louis Cardinals players gave an incorrect given name in some copies for a catcher for the old St. Louis Browns whom the creator of the statues, Harry Weber, considered a baseball hero. He was Clint Courtney, not Cliff.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 11, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A sports article last Wednesday about the prospect of adding a statue of Mark McGwire to those honoring great St. Louis Cardinals players gave an incorrect given name in some copies for a catcher for the old St. Louis Browns whom the creator of the statues, Harry Weber, considered a baseball hero. He was Clint Courtney, not Cliff.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
