<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Saturn Borrows From Opel's Cupboard</title>
    <meta content="NUGGET--SaturnAstra" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837923"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801EED9163FF937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="298" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Saturn Borrows From Opel's Cupboard</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICK KURCZEWSKI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Introduced on Wednesday: 2008 Saturn Vue and Astra</p>
        <p>Is it real? With the 2008 Vue already knocking on the front door it arrives this spring -- the Saturn Astra follows this fall, in three and five-door format.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Introduced on Wednesday: 2008 Saturn Vue and Astra</p>
        <p>Is it real? With the 2008 Vue already knocking on the front door it arrives this spring -- the Saturn Astra follows this fall, in three and five-door format.</p>
        <p>What's the point? The first-generation Vue's dowdy exterior and cheap cabin was never a match for similar-size crossovers from Toyota and Honda. G.M. has been busy pulling vehicles from Opel - its mainstream European brand - and slapping Saturn badges on them. Opels or not, Saturn needed the new cars to fix its staid image.</p>
        <p>What they said: Three visits to the Saturn show stand did not turn up a single Saturn P.R. person or a solitary press kit. Maybe G.M. has so much faith in the brand that it feels the cars speak for themselves.</p>
        <p>What they didn't say: While there was no grand unveiling, this is still a veritable love-fest of new Saturns. The Astra was introduced at the Chicago auto show, while the Vue first appeared in January, at the Detroit show. Seeing these new vehicles together for the first time lends hope that Saturn is on the rebound after years of neglect.</p>
        <p>What makes it tick? The Vue is available with four and six-cylinder engines. There will also be a hybrid model, the Vue Green Line. Astras come with a 1.8-liter inline-4, mated to a five-speed manual or four-speed automatic.</p>
        <p>How much, how soon? Expect the Astra to start at roughly $16,000. The Vue should fall in the previous generation's range of $18,000 to $25,000.</p>
        <p>How's it look? G.M. has a spotty reputation for badge-engineered autos. However, in this case we'll cut them some slack. The sharp exteriors and quality interior treatments of the Vue and Astra represent a leap forward from previous Saturns.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
