<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Season Ends, but Donovan Has One More Play to Call</title>
    <meta content="04men" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/sports/ncaabasketball/04men.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837886"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Florida</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Donovan, Billy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E1DF163FF937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="733" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Season Ends, but Donovan Has One More Play to Call</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Season Is Over, but Donovan Has One More Play to Call</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEE JENKINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jenkins, Lee</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, April 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After he stayed up all night and collected another large crystal trophy, Florida Coach Billy Donovan finally acknowledged that there was indeed a state university in Lexington, Ky., which has a basketball program he knows something about.</p>
        <p>''There is a feeling in my heart that is very strong about Kentucky,'' Donovan said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Florida and Kentucky, rivals in the Southeastern Conference, appear headed for one more showdown this season. The winner gets Coach Billy Donovan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After he stayed up all night and collected another large crystal trophy, Florida Coach Billy Donovan finally acknowledged that there was indeed a state university in Lexington, Ky., which has a basketball program he knows something about.</p>
        <p>''There is a feeling in my heart that is very strong about Kentucky,'' Donovan said.</p>
        <p>With that, nearly two weeks of tap dancing came to an end. Appropriately enough, Donovan was standing in the middle of a hotel ballroom.</p>
        <p>Florida and Kentucky, rivals in the Southeastern Conference, appear headed for one more showdown this season. The winner gets Donovan. The loser looks for a new coach.</p>
        <p>Though Florida owns the home-court advantage, Kentucky has the historical edge. Donovan was an assistant coach at Kentucky for five years, from 1989 to 1994.</p>
        <p>''My time there was very enjoyable,'' Donovan said. ''But it was 13 years ago. A lot in 13 years has changed.''</p>
        <p>Donovan said he has not talked to anyone from Kentucky and does not know if his intermediaries have talked to anyone from Kentucky.</p>
        <p>Asked how he would respond if Kentucky approaches him about its coaching vacancy, Donovan said, ''I have no idea.''</p>
        <p>After winning his second consecutive national championship Monday, Donovan hailed the Florida players who bypassed the N.B.A. draft last spring and returned to school. He said they would serve as an example to all those in college basketball who are tempted to leave for financial gain.</p>
        <p>He did not say whether they would serve as an example to him.</p>
        <p>''He's going to face a tough decision,'' said Florida's Corey Brewer, one of the potential draft picks who returned to Florida instead.</p>
        <p>Donovan, who makes about $1.7 million a year, could not pick a better time to renegotiate. He is the first coach since Duke's Mike Krzyzewski to win consecutive titles, and the second since U.C.L.A.'s John Wooden.</p>
        <p>Florida, coming off championships in both football and basketball, has the potential to match almost any offer. But even if Donovan stays, it looks as though an era is ending. Brewer, Joakim Noah, Al Horford and Taurean Green are only juniors, but it is hard to imagine them all turning down the N.B.A. again.</p>
        <p>''It can happen,'' Horford said.</p>
        <p>Donovan said he would sit down with each of the four players and discuss the options. But the players, who are part of the same class and live in the same apartment, also plan to sit down together. They are hoping to make their decision as a group.</p>
        <p>Over the next 10 days, it could be difficult for anyone to get an appointment with Donovan. He is speaking Wednesday at Marshall University, where he got his first head-coaching job. On Friday, there will be a victory party in Gainesville, Fla. Then he is going to the Dominican Republic for a week to celebrate his father-in-law's 70th birthday.</p>
        <p>Of course, a $3-million-a-year job offer from one of the most storied programs in college basketball has a way of superseding other plans.</p>
        <p>Faced with questions about the Kentucky opening, Donovan has done his best to bob and weave.</p>
        <p>''People might think I'm coy or moving around questions,'' Donovan said. ''But my intention is to be at the University of Florida.''</p>
        <p>Ten or 20 years ago, that might have stopped the speculation. But as more coaches have switched jobs, the public has become better at reading between lines. When coaches say they plan on staying, they often leave themselves just enough room to wriggle free.</p>
        <p>During his news conference Tuesday, Donovan was asked what more he could accomplish at Florida, and for a moment he looked stumped.</p>
        <p>Then he thought about the history of Florida basketball, how it used to be a sideshow. When Donovan arrived 11 years ago, fans just wanted a spot in the tournament. Now, they expect a spot in the Final Four.</p>
        <p>''There hasn't really been anything sustained for a long period of time here,'' Donovan said. ''I think there are still a lot of challenges.''</p>
        <p>Intentionally or not, he was articulating the essential difference between Florida and Kentucky. Florida basketball always ranks second in its athletic department. Kentucky basketball always ranks first.</p>
        <p>If Donovan wants to embrace the obstacles, and build his own tradition, he will probably stay. If he wants fewer obstacles, and a ready-made tradition, he will probably go.</p>
        <p>This college basketball season has one more prime-time matchup left.</p>
        <p>N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
