<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Comeback of Condrieus Is the Story of a Singular Grape</title>
    <meta content="04wine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/dining/reviews/04wine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837930"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WINES OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Wines of the Times</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Wine Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Rhone Valley</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Rhone Valley (France)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E7D81F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1483" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Comeback of Condrieus Is the Story of a Singular Grape</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Comeback of Condrieus Is the Story of a Singular Grape</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC ASIMOV</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Asimov, Eric</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FEW Old World wine regions offer so dramatic a story of success as the resurrection of Condrieu.</p>
        <p>Today, Condrieu is a fashionable wine, valued around the world for its lush, voluptuous flavors and rich, seductive texture. Yet only 35 years ago the Condrieu appellation in the northern Rhone Valley was barely alive, with only about 30 acres of grapes to its name.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Today, Condrieu is a fashionable wine, but only 35 years ago this northern Rhone Valley appellation was barely alive, with only about 30 acres of grapes to its name.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FEW Old World wine regions offer so dramatic a story of success as the resurrection of Condrieu.</p>
        <p>Today, Condrieu is a fashionable wine, valued around the world for its lush, voluptuous flavors and rich, seductive texture. Yet only 35 years ago the Condrieu appellation in the northern Rhone Valley was barely alive, with only about 30 acres of grapes to its name.</p>
        <p>What shook it from its near death slumber? In a word, viognier.</p>
        <p>Had New World producers not seized on viognier, the grape of Condrieu, in an effort to make it their own, Condrieu might have languished among the forgotten vineyards of old. Instead, the successful marketing of viognier in the New World created a demand for the original source, and Condrieu was reborn in the 1980s and '90s.</p>
        <p>From those paltry 30 acres in the early 1970s, plantings in Condrieu are now about 300 acres -- still a tiny amount, comparable to a single large Bordeaux estate, but firmly established, nonetheless.</p>
        <p>The reawakening of Condrieu has provided an Old World appellation with many of the issues that confront New World producers, except for the most important one, of course: which grape to grow where.</p>
        <p>In Condrieu, only the viognier grape is permitted. Beyond that, pretty much anything goes, as the wine panel learned in a recent tasting of 19 bottles of Condrieu. Florence Fabricant and I were joined by Bernard Sun, the beverage director for Jean-Georges Management, and Jean-Luc Le Dû, owner of Le Dû's Wines in the West Village.</p>
        <p>Without an anchor of tradition holding winemaking styles in place, Condrieu producers, like their New World counterparts, are experimenting with several different styles. As with California chardonnay, you are as likely to find a rich, viscous wine framed with new oak as you are a bone dry, crisp, minerally wine. A fair amount of sweet late-harvest wines are also being made, though we restricted our tasting to the dry side of the spectrum. Nonetheless, this was an exciting group of wines regardless of the style, exotic and sensuous, and their sheer deliciousness sets a standard that New World producers have yet to reach.</p>
        <p>I am not a fan of obvious new oak flavors in any wine, but in Condrieu new oak integrates beautifully with the viognier's tropical flavors.</p>
        <p>The new oak aging was obvious in our No. 1 wine, the 2005 from Saint Cosme. Yet it was so balanced and fresh, its oily, rich texture so captivating, that we could not fault the oak treatment. Of course, this was a rational treatment. It wasn't so uncommon in recent years to find Condrieus that were overwhelmingly oaky to the point of clumsiness, but as is usually the case, producers who use extreme techniques eventually find their way to a middle ground.</p>
        <p>By contrast, a 2005 La Loye from Jean Michel Gerin, our No. 4 wine, had pure aromas and flavors of flowers and tropical fruit unmitigated by oak, while retaining the thick, pleasing texture so characteristic of the viognier grape. It, too, was delicious.</p>
        <p>Few wines are as texturally interesting as Condrieu, a tribute to the region itself where viognier is able to ripen without sacrificing the acidity that gives it freshness and structure.</p>
        <p>Few New World producers have been able to achieve this combination apart from some of the best, like Alban Vineyards in the Edna Valley, the Calera Wine Company on Mount Harlan and Cayuse Vineyards in the Walla Walla Valley. According to John Livingstone-Learmonth, a British writer whose book ''The Wines of the Northern Rhone'' (University of California Press, 2005) is the definitive work on the region, the thin soils and hilly vineyards of Condrieu are crucial to its success with viognier.</p>
        <p>The grape itself is said to be difficult and capricious, and yields must be kept low, particularly because so many vines are young, planted in the last 10 years and prone to overcropping. Growers do not consider viognier vines to be in their prime until they are 25 years old. The combination of young vines and high yields can result in thin and shallow wines.</p>
        <p>That was not a problem with the wines we tasted. Certainly, our favorites all were sumptuous without being heavy. The conventional wisdom -- make that cliché -- about viognier is to drink it young, within three or four years of the vintage. Most of the wines we tasted were from the 2004 or 2005 vintages, but the oldest, a 2001 Côte Chatillon from Patrick &amp; Christophe Bonnefond, was superb: rich yet elegant with some mineral flavors among the exotic fruits. This six-year-old wine may be hard to find -- we just happened upon it -- but it was by no means on a downslide. Indeed, it is hard to imagine that any of our favorites will be over the hill at 10 or even 15 years of age.</p>
        <p>In the dark old days Condrieu was essentially kept alive by the Domaine Georges Vernay. Mr. Vernay kept the faith even as vineyards around him were abandoned. Today his children run the domaine.</p>
        <p>We tasted a Vernay 2005, les Terrasses de l'Empere, and found it to be a direct, modern style with spicy pineapple flavors. Nothing wrong, but it did not make our top 10.</p>
        <p>E. Guigal, the well-known Rhone négociant, has also been an important name in Condrieu. Of the two Guigals we tasted, the 2004 had pretty floral aromas and was both rich and delicate. We also tried the more expensive 2004 La Doriane, which suffered from vegetal and sulfur flavors. Maybe it was a bad bottle.</p>
        <p>Nowadays, perhaps the most frequently seen name in Condrieu is Yves Cuilleron, who has his own domaine and a partnership with two other Rhone producers, François Villard and Pierre Gaillard. The 2005 Cuilleron La Petite Côte was straightforward and juicy with a lingering touch of heat from the alcohol. A 2004 Les Terrasses du Palat from François Villard was more complex, with long, lingering flavors and a touch of honey.</p>
        <p>It is safe to say that Condrieu is never cheap. Our 19 bottles ranged from $37 to $90. Our best value, at $45, was the 2004 Les Ravines from Rémi &amp; Robert Niero, a lively wine that was refreshingly pure and precise.</p>
        <p>Perhaps that is the price of scarcity. Increasingly, it seems to be the price of quality.</p>
        <p>Tasting Report: Tropical Flavors That Never Come Cheap</p>
        <p>Saint Cosme 2005: $71 *** 1/2 [Rating: Three and a half Stars]  Beautifully rich texture with tropical flavors of coconut, citrus, peach and apricot; new oak is well integrated. (Importer: Stacole Company, Boca Raton, Fla.)</p>
        <p>Patrick &amp; Christophe Bonnefond Côte Chatillon 2001: $40 *** [Rating: Three Stars]  Rich and viscous yet elegant with exotic fruit flavors and aromas of flowers, honey and minerals. (Domaine Select, New York)</p>
        <p>Alain Paret Lys de Volan 2004: $60 *** [Rating: Three Stars]  Sumptuous yet delicate, with lingering flavors of honeysuckle, peach and melon. (Robert Kacher Selections, Washington, D.C.)</p>
        <p>Jean Michel Gerin La Loye 2005: $58 *** [Rating: Three Stars]  Thickly textured yet fresh with flavors and aromas of flowers and tropical fruit. (New Castle Imports, Pawleys Island, S.C.)</p>
        <p>François Villard Les Terrasses du Palat 2004 $57 *** [Rating: Three Stars]  Elegant and soulful, with complex aromas of flowers, spices, fruit and honey. (European Cellars, Charlotte, N.C.)</p>
        <p>BEST VALUE</p>
        <p>Rémi &amp; Robert Niero Les Ravines 2004: $45 ** 1/2 [Rating: Two and a half Stars]  Fresh and lively with pure, precise flavors of exotic fruits. (David Bowler Wine, New York)</p>
        <p>Yves Cuilleron La Petite Côte 2005: $60 ** 1/2 [Rating: Two and a half Stars]  Juicy and full-bodied with flavors of nuts, tropical fruit and a touch of alcoholic heat. (Rosenthal Wine Merchant, New York)</p>
        <p>Cuilleron Gaillard Villard La Chambée 2004: $48 ** 1/2 [Rating: Two and a half Stars]  Oaky and viscous but with pure flavors of fruit, flowers and butterscotch. (USA Wine Imports, New York)</p>
        <p>E. Guigal 2004: $48 ** 1/2 [Rating: Two and a half Stars]  Pretty floral aromas; delicate yet full-bodied. (Ex Cellars Wine Agencies, Solvang, Calif.)</p>
        <p>Jean-Luc Colombo Amour de Dieu 2004: $65 ** [Rating: Two Stars]  Fresh, lively and straightforward. (Palm Bay Imports, Boca Raton, Fla.)</p>
        <p>WHAT THE STARS MEAN:</p>
        <p>Ratings range from zero to four stars and reflect the panel's reaction to wines, which were tasted with names and vintages concealed. The panelists this week are Eric Asimov; Florence Fabricant; Bernard Sun, the beverage director for Jean-Georges Management; and Jean-Luc Le Dû, owner of Le Dû's Wines in the West Village. The tasted wines represent a selection generally available in good retail shops and restaurants and over the Internet. Prices are those paid in liquor shops in the New York metropolitan region.</p>
        <p>Tasting Coordinator: Bernard Kirsch</p>
        <p>nytimes.com  Recent wine columns from The New York Times are online: nytimes.com/wine. This week members of the panel discuss their favorite Condrieus.</p>
        <p>WINES OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
