<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For the Knicks' Thomas, The Fine Is in the Mail</title>
    <meta content="04knicks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837898"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDF163FF937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="835" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For the Knicks' Thomas, The Fine Is in the Mail</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beck, Howard</byline>
      <dateline>GREENBURGH, N.Y., April 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Isiah Thomas will soon send the National Basketball Association a check for $50,000 -- the apparent price for restoring a franchise's dignity.</p>
        <p>The Knicks last season were a punchline, a bog of bruised egos and joyless faces. When Thomas, the team president, also became the coach, he spoke of instilling confidence and regaining respect. That mission has pushed him to extremes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Isiah Thomas will soon send the National Basketball Association a check for $50,000 -- the apparent price for restoring a franchise's dignity.</p>
        <p>The Knicks last season were a punchline, a bog of bruised egos and joyless faces. When Thomas, the team president, also became the coach, he spoke of instilling confidence and regaining respect. That mission has pushed him to extremes.</p>
        <p>Thomas has bellowed at opposing players and baited other coaches. He was accused of instigating a fight. He has collected more technical fouls (nine) than his three immediate predecessors combined (five).</p>
        <p>And he has styled himself as a fierce advocate and guardian of his players, Stephon Marbury in particular. On Saturday night, Thomas began a postgame interview with an unsolicited two-minute rant about the referees' treatment of Marbury.</p>
        <p>The soliloquy was intended to get the league's attention, and the commissioner's office responded with a $50,000 fine Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Speaking three hours before the fine was announced, Thomas was unrepentant. Asked if it was worth being fined for his gesture on Marbury's behalf, Thomas said: ''It's not a gesture. I thought my perception was accurate. And I believe my perception is accurate. This isn't some good-will gesture.''</p>
        <p>The N.B.A. is highly sensitive to comments that impugn its integrity. Thomas and the Los Angeles Lakers' Phil Jackson are the only coaches this season to be fined $50,000 for an infraction. Thomas's general complaint Saturday was that the referees did not afford Marbury the same level of respect that they gave other star players, and he repeated the sentiments Monday. Thomas was more measured Tuesday, but he was unambiguous about his role as the Knicks' protector-in-chief.</p>
        <p>''It's what you're supposed to do,'' Thomas said. ''It's one of the job responsibilities I feel that the coach should have and take on. My coaches did it for me. Whether it be Coach Knight or Coach Daly, they spoke out for me.''</p>
        <p>Thomas was referring to his greatest mentors -- Bob Knight, the former Indiana coach, and Chuck Daly, the former Detroit Pistons coach.</p>
        <p>In sports parlance, the concept is known as ''having your back,'' but Thomas had his own spin on that.</p>
        <p>''I got the front,'' he said. ''I'm leery of the guys who got my back because that means I'm taking the hit.''</p>
        <p>Thomas has taken hits for his team all season -- one way in which he has contrasted himself with his immediate predecessor, Larry Brown, who frequently derided his players in public.</p>
        <p>In November, Thomas angrily criticized the defensive tactics of San Antonio's Bruce Bowen, then yelled at his players to break Bowen's feet during a game. That fueled a brief screaming match between Thomas and Spurs Coach Gregg Popovich. In December, during the final minutes of a blowout loss to Denver, Thomas warned the Nuggets' Carmelo Anthony not to drive to the basket; seconds later, a fight erupted when Mardy Collins committed a flagrant foul against J. R. Smith of Denver.</p>
        <p>Thomas has been comparatively demure since. But his technical foul total is the highest by a Knicks coach in 17 years, since Stu Jackson earned 11 in the 1989-90 season. Jackson is now the league's executive vice president for basketball operations -- and the man who issued the fine to Thomas.</p>
        <p>Off the court, Thomas has been a tireless booster for his players, promoting Eddy Curry as an All-Star candidate and praising Marbury for his evolution as a player and a person. Thomas said Monday that Marbury deserved greater latitude from referees and the public.</p>
        <p>''I think he's grown and matured a lot and there needs to be some type of acceptance and tolerance for his growth,'' Thomas said. ''Whatever he was two or three years ago as a player and person is not what he is today, and that needs to be acknowledged.''</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, perhaps seeking to tone down his rhetoric, Thomas said: ''I don't believe that this league or the officials favor anybody. I believe that everyone gets a fair look on that night. However, I do believe that perceptions can sometimes cloud judgment.''</p>
        <p>The Knicks' playoff hopes were damaged over the weekend in consecutive losses in Dallas and in Oklahoma City. The common element was Marbury's failure to draw a foul call in the closing seconds of regulation. That seemed to prompt Thomas's now-costly monologue. Last season, the Knicks lost a franchise-record 59 games and Brown feuded with his players.</p>
        <p>The team will soon conclude a sixth consecutive losing season. But with nine games left, the Knicks have a modestly improved record (31-42) and an outside shot at the playoffs. And Thomas said he believed that they were on the way to winning the battle to regain respect.</p>
        <p>''I think we're still fighting to do that,'' he said. ''I do think the one thing that has changed, we're not a gimme game anymore. We're not a team where people come in just saying, 'That's a win,' and chalking it up. I think they know they have to play and compete for it.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
