<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>We Shall Know You by Your Footstool</title>
    <meta content="04bell" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/arts/television/04bell.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837941"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Filicia, Thom</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E5D81F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="552" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>We Shall Know You by Your Footstool</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">We Shall Know You by Your Footstool</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINIA BELLAFANTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bellafante, Ginia</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is difficult to pinpoint the precise moment when home design ceased merely to reflect the influences of a particular age, class or geographic vernacular, but something about decorating principles seems to have undergone a dramatic shift recently, as Thom Filicia's new show, ''Dress My Nest,'' makes patently clear. Mr. Filicia, a ''Queer Eye for the Straight Guy'' alumnus, understands that home design requires a lot more narcissism that it once did, and he has correctly identified the problem of translating a person's essence into footstools and swatches as one of the prevailing issues of our time.</p>
        <p>There was a period not long ago when a young, urban professional could maintain an apartment with a functional Pottery Barn sofa and walls painted in quiet neutrals and still be considered someone of reasonably good taste. Today he might well face criticism that he lacked imagination and soul, that he was a slave to an outdated aesthetic that sacrificed personal eccentricity to a collective right: the dream of demure, unsullied affluence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thom Filicia’s new show, “Dress My Nest,” correctly identifies one of the prevailing issues of our time  the problem of translating a person’s essence into footstools and swatches.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is difficult to pinpoint the precise moment when home design ceased merely to reflect the influences of a particular age, class or geographic vernacular, but something about decorating principles seems to have undergone a dramatic shift recently, as Thom Filicia's new show, ''Dress My Nest,'' makes patently clear. Mr. Filicia, a ''Queer Eye for the Straight Guy'' alumnus, understands that home design requires a lot more narcissism that it once did, and he has correctly identified the problem of translating a person's essence into footstools and swatches as one of the prevailing issues of our time.</p>
        <p>There was a period not long ago when a young, urban professional could maintain an apartment with a functional Pottery Barn sofa and walls painted in quiet neutrals and still be considered someone of reasonably good taste. Today he might well face criticism that he lacked imagination and soul, that he was a slave to an outdated aesthetic that sacrificed personal eccentricity to a collective right: the dream of demure, unsullied affluence.</p>
        <p>A magazine like Domino implicitly tells us that chic spaces must project tension: between the old and the new, the generic and the particular. Good design is temerity, the brazen decision to put a chrome end table beside a Louis XVI chair, the submission to a life-size ceramic Labrador. Within these parameters you must always be sure that you are expressing you -- the you who loves the Red Sox and Douglas Sirk and Tuscany in May.</p>
        <p>In ''Dress My Nest,'' Mr. Filicia makes apartments look like their owners by using what they wear as his inspiration. He is quite good at this. He can take a look at a pretty pharmaceutical sales representative, know that she really loves a vintage raffia purse and turn that love into a woven sea grass wall covering. He can figure out that a 29-year-old woman who cherishes her Hello Kitty earmuffs (and toaster and blanket) just a little too much needs a living room with a pink couch and more cheerful lighting to live more plausibly as a grown-up.</p>
        <p>It is beyond Mr. Filicia why anyone would not appoint a home with lots of spunk.</p>
        <p>''Your sofa is just one big blob of green, and that's just so not you,'' he says to a singer-songwriter in one episode. ''I just don't get it.''</p>
        <p>The apartments he reconfigures seem to belong primarily to single young women. But the young women he finds are already living pretty originally, which is to say that they are living like bachelors in bland, blocky starter apartments where you would expect to find only beer and old lo mien in the fridge.</p>
        <p>Mr. Filicia's makeovers strip them of this coolness, this aversion to really caring about how things look. Instead he tarts up their apartments so that the women end up seeming like advertisements for Bloomingdale's theme months: Bohemian chic, globe-trotting eclecticism.</p>
        <p>You will cheer for his clients to mess it all up and bring back the dull, bulky furnishings of mail-order catalogs.</p>
        <p>Dress My Nest  Style, tonight at 11, Eastern and Pacific times; 10, Central time.</p>
        <p>Developed by Elaine Brooks, senior vice president for Style development and new series, and Sarah Weidman, executive producer, Style development and new series; Thom Filicia, host. Produced by PB&amp;J Television Inc.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
