<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Blair Seeking Diplomatic Solution to Iran Standoff</title>
    <meta content="04britain" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/world/europe/04britain.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837977"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Larijani, Ali</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyall, Sarah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Iran</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Blair, Tony</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E4D71F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="487" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Blair Seeking Diplomatic Solution to Iran Standoff</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Blair Seeking Diplomatic Solution to Iran Standoff</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH LYALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyall, Sarah</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, April 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prime Min Tony Blair says next 48 hours will be critical to diplomatic effort to secure release of 15 British sailors and marines seized by Iran; welcomes comments by Ali Larijani, top Iranian security official, that there is no need for trial and that matter can be resolved bilaterally (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Tony Blair said Tuesday that he was still hoping to secure through diplomatic means the release of the 15 British sailors and marines captured by Iran, and that the next 48 hours would be ''fairly critical'' in resolving the dispute.</p>
        <p>''All the way through this, we've had two tracks on this,'' Mr. Blair said in an interview with Real Radio in Glasgow. ''One is to make sure Iran understands that the pressure is there available to us if this thing has to be hard and tough and long.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Tony Blair said that the next 48 hours would be “fairly critical” in resolving the dispute over 15 British sailors and marines captured by Iran.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prime Minister Tony Blair said Tuesday that he was still hoping to secure through diplomatic means the release of the 15 British sailors and marines captured by Iran, and that the next 48 hours would be ''fairly critical'' in resolving the dispute.</p>
        <p>''All the way through this, we've had two tracks on this,'' Mr. Blair said in an interview with Real Radio in Glasgow. ''One is to make sure Iran understands that the pressure is there available to us if this thing has to be hard and tough and long.''</p>
        <p>The other option is a peaceful resolution, the prime minister said. ''We're not looking for confrontation over this,'' he said. ''Actually, the most important thing is to get the people back safe and sound, and if they want to resolve this in a diplomatic way, the door is open.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair said that comments made by Ali Larijani, a top Iranian security official, on British television on Monday that ''there is no need for a trial'' and that ''this issue should be resolved bilaterally'' offered some prospect of a way to proceed. ''But we need to hear from them direct,'' the prime minister said, referring to the Iranians.</p>
        <p>Iran promised on Monday not to broadcast additional images of the British captives, but on Tuesday released photographs of several of them, looking relaxed and smiling, through the state news agency.</p>
        <p>The Britons were seized at gunpoint on March 23 in disputed waters in the northern Persian Gulf. Iran contends that they illegally entered Iranian territorial waters. Britain argues that they were in Iraqi waters on a routine antismuggling patrol at the invitation of the Iraqi government and the United Nations.</p>
        <p>Some of the captives, possibly under duress, have admitted to trespassing, and it appears that Iran has made such an admission a condition of their release.</p>
        <p>''Certainly, if Britain accepts that they have illegally trespassed into Iran and guarantees that they won't repeat it, the issue will obviously become negotiable and can be resolved through a rational process,'' Iran's vice president, Parviz Davoudi, said Tuesday, the British Press Association reported.</p>
        <p>While the remarks from Iran have seemed softer in recent days, throughout the dispute its statements have veered between conciliatory and angry, and it is hard to get a clear sense of what the government is actually thinking -- or indeed whether the government is speaking with one voice. The president, Mahmoud Ahmadinejad, postponed until Wednesday a news conference originally planned for Tuesday.</p>
        <p>In Washington, President Bush described the Iranian action as ''indefensible'' and said that he, too, hoped to see the situation resolved peacefully. But he said Britain should not bargain for the captives' release.</p>
        <p>''We are in close consultation with the British government,'' he said at a news conference at the White House. ''I also strongly support the prime minister's declaration there should be no quid pro quos when it comes to the hostages.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
