<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chicken Meets Fingerlings, and Trumps Lobster</title>
    <meta content="04pair" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837929"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PAIRINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poultry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E7D81F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="510" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chicken Meets Fingerlings, and Trumps Lobster</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fabricant, Florence</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I STILL remember my first taste of Condrieu. It was at Lutèce umpteen years ago, and it accompanied a warm lobster salad. Ever since then, to me, Condrieu and lobster were like pearls and a black dress.</p>
        <p>So naturally, luxuriating in the honeysuckle, melon, candied lemon and floral flavors in our wonderful array of Condrieus, I assumed lobster would star in my pairing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I STILL remember my first taste of Condrieu. It was at Lutèce umpteen years ago, and it accompanied a warm lobster salad. Ever since then, to me, Condrieu and lobster were like pearls and a black dress.</p>
        <p>So naturally, luxuriating in the honeysuckle, melon, candied lemon and floral flavors in our wonderful array of Condrieus, I assumed lobster would star in my pairing.</p>
        <p>That was until I had dinner at Frederick's Madison a few weeks ago, and ordered Vincent Chirico's chicken with fingerling potatoes and cipollini onions. It's not often that I clean my plate, but the dish provided such a delectable balance of richness and acidity, with hints of herb and garlic, that I threw restraint to the winds.</p>
        <p>Though I drank red wine with the chicken that evening because my dining partner insisted, I kept thinking about the Condrieus that I had tasted just the day before. So I forgot about lobster and requested the recipe, and now you have it.</p>
        <p>The braise is made with dark chicken meat, which retains its succulence better than white, making it a perfect dinner party dish, suitable for preparing an hour or two in advance and reheating ever so gently. The olive oil used for poaching the potatoes can be strained and refrigerated to recycle as an herbed oil for other cooking purposes.</p>
        <p>Though the red we drank was fine with the dish, a white, like a rich viognier with a pedigree -- a Condrieu, of course -- suits it in far better style.</p>
        <p>Braised Chicken With Fingerlings  Adapted from Frederick's Madison  Time: 1 hour 15 minutes</p>
        <p>1/2 pound cipollini onions, unpeeled  1 head garlic, cloves peeled  12 ounces small fingerling potatoes  1 1/2 cups plus 1 tablespoon extra-virgin olive oil  8 sprigs thyme  3 1/2 pounds dark meat chicken parts, 8 thighs, 4 legs  Salt and ground black pepper  1/2 cup chardonnay  2 cups rich chicken stock (or 11/2 cups chicken, 1/2 cup veal stock)  3 tablespoons unsalted butter, preferably high fat  2 tablespoons minced tarragon.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat oven to 300 degrees. Roast onions in a pan for 30 minutes. Cool.  2. Meanwhile, place garlic cloves and potatoes in a saucepan, add 11/2 cups olive oil and the thyme, and cook over very low heat 20 minutes, until potatoes are tender. Cool in pan.  3. Season chicken with salt and pepper. Heat remaining tablespoon oil in a large sauté pan. Add chicken and brown. Remove chicken, pour off all fat and return chicken to pan. Add wine and stock, bring to a simmer and braise, covered, about 20 minutes, until chicken is done. Peel onions.  4. Remove chicken from pan. Cook liquid until reduced to 13/4 cups. Over very low heat, add butter bit by bit, whisking it in. Season with salt and pepper if needed and stir in tarragon.  5. Return chicken to pan. Remove potatoes and garlic from oil with a slotted spoon and add to pan. Add onions. Gently reheat, then serve in shallow soup bowls.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>PAIRINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
