<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Keeping Passover, Easter and a Space to Park</title>
    <meta content="04suspend" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/nyregion/04suspend.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837868"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Passover</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Easter and Holy Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parking</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Parking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Parking Meters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Passover</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Passover</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Easter and Holy Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weights and Measures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E6DF163FF937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="912" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Keeping Passover, Easter and a Space to Park</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Keeping Passover, Easter and a Space to Park</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON; Ann Farmer and Cassi Feldman contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barron, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Confluence of Passover and Easter Week creates unusually long stretch of days in which New York's alternate-side parking rules will be suspended, to delight of car owners and dismay of people who want streets swept regularly (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a city that has done the alternate-side parking dance since the days of sock hops, Eren Hock knew just what she had found as soon as she put the transmission in park and turned off the engine on Monday: a space on her Manhattan block where she could leave her car for up to 11 days.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hock, 23, knew that she would not have to do what she often does -- structure her evenings around hunting for a parking space that would be legal longer than her current one. Until -- when else? -- Friday the 13th, no one would mistake her for a character in ''Tepper Isn't Going Out,'' Calvin Trillin's 2001 novel about a man who is always after the most desirable parking space.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A confluence of religious holidays has created an unusually long stretch when some drivers can take a break from worrying about alternate parking rules.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a city that has done the alternate-side parking dance since the days of sock hops, Eren Hock knew just what she had found as soon as she put the transmission in park and turned off the engine on Monday: a space on her Manhattan block where she could leave her car for up to 11 days.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hock, 23, knew that she would not have to do what she often does -- structure her evenings around hunting for a parking space that would be legal longer than her current one. Until -- when else? -- Friday the 13th, no one would mistake her for a character in ''Tepper Isn't Going Out,'' Calvin Trillin's 2001 novel about a man who is always after the most desirable parking space.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hock lives on West 138th Street, where, she said, the alternate-side rules prohibit parking on Tuesdays and Fridays from 11 a.m. to 12:30 p.m. But she knew that because of a confluence of religious holidays, the city's alternate-side rules would be suspended yesterday and today (for the beginning of Passover), tomorrow and Friday (for Holy Thursday and Good Friday) and next Monday and Tuesday (for the end of Passover).</p>
        <p>That has created an unusually long stretch when some drivers can sleep late or, like Ms. Hock, do something else in the hours they usually spend circling their neighborhoods. And circling. And circling, strategizing and cursing the car that got there a moment sooner and snapped up that just-vacated space.</p>
        <p>''It's bliss,'' said Janine Nichols, the singing half of a bass-and-voice duo called Split the Lark and the owner of a 20-year-old Volvo.</p>
        <p>She said that over the weekend, her mind drifted to ''all the amazing occurrences'' that seemed to be coinciding, or at least falling within a day or two of one another -- ''the full moon, opening day in baseball, April Fool's.''</p>
        <p>''I kept saying, 'There's another one, but I can't remember what it is,' '' recalled Ms. Nichols, who lives in Park Slope, Brooklyn, on a street where the alternate-side rules prohibit parking on Thursdays and Fridays from 8 to 11 a.m. ''And then, when I awoke and the radio said alternate-side parking was suspended for a week, I thought I was still dreaming.''</p>
        <p>People who dream of clean streets -- or less congested ones -- are dreaming a different dream. ''Street cleanliness is not next to godliness during these two weeks,'' said Paul Steely White, the executive director of Transportation Alternatives, an advocacy group. ''We can surmise the streets will be dirtier.''</p>
        <p>The Sanitation Department surmises the same thing. ''It will be impossible to sweep those areas,'' said a spokesman, Vito A. Turso.</p>
        <p>He said that street sweepers would concentrate on commercial areas, where there would be more turnover at the curb. That is because the alternate-side suspensions do not apply to spaces governed by parking meters or Muni-Meter machines.</p>
        <p>On the streets where the rules will be suspended and there might be an empty parking space here or there, like a mouth with missing teeth, sending in the sweepers would be pointless, Mr. Turso said.</p>
        <p>''By the time you turn into the curb and turn out, you've not swept anything,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Which is about what Ms. Hock said, still pleased about her space on West 138th Street.</p>
        <p>''I usually get pretty jazzed when it's a couple of days in a row,'' she said. ''I think it will be interesting to see how dirty the streets get since that's the reason behind the alternate-side parking, even though I don't feel my street is that much cleaner when the rules are in effect.''</p>
        <p>As with so many things in New York, the phrase ''location, location, location'' comes to mind. Where and when people can take advantage of the suspended rules differs from neighborhood to neighborhood because the rules differ from neighborhood to neighborhood, day to day and even hour to hour.</p>
        <p>And, as Mr. Turso of the Sanitation Department pointed out, the rules will not be suspended on Saturday.</p>
        <p>Of course, it remains to be seen how drivers will adapt to so many days without the Darwinian free-for-all that pretty much defines parking on the street in New York.</p>
        <p>''Any break we can get is a great thing,'' said Annette Marshall, 42, a fifth-grade teacher who parked on 78th Street between Columbus and Amsterdam Avenues. ''Spaces are like gold.''</p>
        <p>There were drivers who were thrilled about not having to find another parking space for days to come. ''It feels better than good,'' said Ronnie Mae Painter, an artist whose Nissan Pathfinder is on Lincoln Place in Park Slope.</p>
        <p>All over New York, there are Christians who know when the Jewish holidays fall, and Jews who know when the Christian holidays fall. They are drivers.</p>
        <p>''Thank God for Jewish holidays,'' said Charlie Moon, 63, an interior designer who celebrates Easter.</p>
        <p>He appreciates ''all those wonderful obscure Jewish holidays that I profit from,'' and mentioned holidays like Shemini Atzeret and Simchas Torah, for which alternate-side rules will be suspended on Oct. 4 and 5.</p>
        <p>But Andy DeBaun, 46, a social worker at a high school in Riverdale in the Bronx, said there was a flip side to suspending the alternate-side rules. He had trouble hunting down a parking space on the Upper West Side yesterday.</p>
        <p>''Everybody's stuck in their spots,'' he said after finally finding a space on West 73rd Street, ''and all the tourists are in town.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
