<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Smithsonian Scrambles To Regain Its Footing</title>
    <meta content="04smit" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/arts/design/04smit.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070405T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837942"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington (DC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Smithsonian Institution</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Museum of Natural History</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Zoo</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Samper, Cristian</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Small, Lawrence M</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Burke, Sheila P</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE5D81F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1506" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Smithsonian Scrambles To Regain Its Footing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Smithsonian Scrambles to Regain Its Footing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN POGREBIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pogrebin, Robin</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the Smithsonian's museum directors filed into a conference room at the organization's headquarters here Wednesday for their monthly meeting, Cristián Samper had some difficulty getting in the door. That's because so many people stopped him in the hallway to shake his hand and wish him luck. ''I feel like I'm on a receiving line,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In a way, he was. Just two days before, Mr. Samper, 41, had been catapulted from director of the Smithsonian's National Museum of Natural History to acting secretary of the entire Smithsonian Institution. He was the emergency replacement for Lawrence M. Small, 65, who resigned after a tumultuous seven-year tenure that concluded with an internal audit showing that the museum complex had paid for his extravagant personal expenses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a tumultuous period, the nation’s museum focuses on earning the trust of the people.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the Smithsonian's museum directors filed into a conference room at the organization's headquarters here Wednesday for their monthly meeting, Cristián Samper had some difficulty getting in the door. That's because so many people stopped him in the hallway to shake his hand and wish him luck. ''I feel like I'm on a receiving line,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In a way, he was. Just two days before, Mr. Samper, 41, had been catapulted from director of the Smithsonian's National Museum of Natural History to acting secretary of the entire Smithsonian Institution. He was the emergency replacement for Lawrence M. Small, 65, who resigned after a tumultuous seven-year tenure that concluded with an internal audit showing that the museum complex had paid for his extravagant personal expenses.</p>
        <p>In addition, just before Mr. Small resigned, an external review committee identified some major problems facing the Smithsonian, concluding: ''The Smithsonian's art institutions have reached a critical point. Drastically underfunded, they are unable to lead the nation during a time when their creativity and high visibility give them vast potential to affect the lives of our citizens.''</p>
        <p>As a result, over the next few months the Smithsonian will be grappling with fundamental questions far beyond just issues of governance and oversight. The institution will also consider how to tackle buildings in dire need of repair, questionable collections at some of its art museums, a lack of money that makes it difficult to compete and the need to improve fund-raising strategies.</p>
        <p>With a board made up of august but potentially overextended public officials like the vice president of the United States, can the Smithsonian establish sufficiently rigorous day-to-day oversight? Does an organization with a $1 billion annual budget, 19 museums, 9 research centers and the National Zoo ultimately defy the effective leadership of a single executive at the top? Can the Smithsonian incorporate increasingly popular private-sector fund-raising strategies even as it receives 70 percent of its budget from Congress and has a board appointed by the government?</p>
        <p>First and foremost, however, the Smithsonian is concerned with winning back the confidence of the American people. ''We need to restate and reaffirm that this is, in fact, a public trust,'' said Sheila P. Burke, the Smithsonian's deputy secretary and chief operating officer, a candidate to succeed Mr. Small. ''I think we have some work to do in restoring that trust.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Small, a former president and chief operating officer of Fannie Mae, has been a lightning rod since he came on the job in 2000 and alienated many longtime Smithsonian scientists with his corporate approach.</p>
        <p>He made a series of controversial moves, including planning to close the National Zoo's world-class research center in Virginia -- a decision he reversed after a national outcry from scientists and members of Congress.</p>
        <p>He also had to change course after promising the donor Catherine B. Reynolds a say in choosing the prominent Americans to be honored in a ''Spirit of America'' exhibition in exchange for her $38 million donation. The show was canceled in response to virulent protests, and Ms. Reynolds withdrew her gift.</p>
        <p>Last year, Mr. Small drew the ire of filmmakers, television executives and academics for making a deal with Showtime Networks to set up an on-demand cable station whose programming would feature Smithsonian programs and collections.</p>
        <p>Last June, the Smithsonian's inspector general resigned, saying that shrinking resources for her office had diminished its effectiveness and independence. She later said Mr. Small had tried to head off an audit of the organization's business ventures division, a claim he denied.</p>
        <p>Four museum directors resigned during Mr. Small's tenure.</p>
        <p>The external review committee, in a report presented last month, found that ''Smithsonian museums have made many contributions, but their collections are far from representing the world's artistic heritage, and they have seldom lived up to their 'national' designation.''</p>
        <p>''Their potential for collaborative ventures has scarcely been tapped,'' it added.</p>
        <p>The external committee's report raised questions about specific institutions, like the Cooper-Hewitt National Design Museum in New York. ''We remain concerned about the museum's future viability even with additional space and increased levels of funding, given the modest size of audience, limited programs, and scope of collection,'' the report said.</p>
        <p>On the National Gallery, the report said, ''The museum's chief weakness is the later 20th-century and contemporary collection, which has evidently been formed much more by opportunism than by strategy.''</p>
        <p>Ned L. Rifkin, the Smithsonian's under secretary for art, who commissioned the report, said he welcomed the findings. ''There are many very helpful insights and recommendations,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The committee was made up of seven leaders of prominent art museums, including Glenn D. Lowry, the director of the Museum of Modern Art in New York, and Michael E. Shapiro, the director of the High Museum of Art in Atlanta.</p>
        <p>The latest headlines have focused on Mr. Small's salary -- which more than doubled, to $915,698, during his tenure -- and his personal spending on housing, trips and chauffeured cars, along with extras like $15,000 for new French doors and $12,000 for swimming pool service. The board has defended Mr. Small's expenses as ''reasonable.'' He left on March 26, without a severance package.</p>
        <p>Mr. Small's conduct comes to light just as Congress is preparing to decide the Smithsonian's annual appropriation. The White House has requested $678.4 million for the institution for the fiscal year that begins Oct. 1. House appropriation hearings begin in June.</p>
        <p>The Senate Rules and Administration Committee will hold an oversight hearing on the Smithsonian next Wednesday. The Smithsonian's Board of Regents, the institution's governing body, had already created a three-member independent review committee to examine the inspector general's reports on Mr. Small's compensation, expenses and donations as well as how the regents responded.</p>
        <p>The board has also established a new permanent Committee on Governance to evaluate the Smithsonian and measure it against the best practices of comparable institutions. The committee plans to submit a preliminary set of recommendations by the first week of May. ''What we're trying to do is step back a bit,'' said Patty Stonesifer, co-chairwoman of the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation, who is leading the governance committee. ''Are we doing things in the best possible way?''</p>
        <p>Here at the Smithsonian, the reaction to Mr. Small's departure was far from pure relief. He consolidated the management structure and hired good executives, some said. He made a point of renovating dilapidated Smithsonian museums and building new ones, like the National Museum of the American Indian, which opened in 2004, and the Patent Office Building -- home to the Smithsonian's National Portrait Gallery and its American Art Museum -- which reopened in July.</p>
        <p>''He came in with a focus on making the buildings great,'' said Elizabeth Broun, director of the Art Museum. ''It was just what we needed at the time.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Small also realized the importance of fund-raising from the private sector. He raised $1 billion in private money, a record for the institution. Although the Smithsonian gets generous financing from the government -- about $634.9 million this fiscal year -- that money goes only toward operations andupkeep. The individual Smithsonian organizations have to raise the rest for their programming.</p>
        <p>Mr. Samper and Ms. Burke are considered candidates to replace Mr. Small. The Smithsonian board has formed a search committee but is not expected to name someone for six months to a year.</p>
        <p>Ms. Burke was the top aide to Bob Dole when he was the Senate majority leader and went on to serve as executive dean at the John F. Kennedy School of Government at Harvard University.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Small represented the consummate departure for the institution, Mr. Samper would seem to represent a return to its roots. He was deputy director and staff scientist at the Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute in Panama and before that led a national biodiversity research institute in Colombia.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Samper is not unfamiliar with the nuts and bolts of running an institution; the Natural History Museum has the Smithsonian's largest staff. He said he was comfortable fund-raising and often approached donors with Mr. Small. ''Yes, Larry brought a corporate culture, but I think the Smithsonian needed some of that,'' Mr. Samper said.</p>
        <p>Staff members at the Smithsonian say they still take pride in working for an institution that offers free admission to some 23 million visitors a year. ''Everyone would accept this is a difficult time for the Smithsonian; it may be the most difficult time it's ever been in,'' said Lonnie Bunch, the director of the Smithsonian's newest addition, the National Museum of African American History and Culture. ''But it's also a good institution. While we don't do change well, I think change is incumbent on us for our success.''</p>
        <p>Other longtime staff members, who have seen the Smithsonian weather earlier storms, say the institution is resilient. ''My sense is, people across America want the Smithsonian to succeed and they feel they own it,'' Ms. Broun said. ''If the institution can clear up the issues and set a strong course again, I think the people will be forgiving.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 5, 2007, Thursday  Because of an editing error, an article in The Arts yesterday about problems facing the Smithsonian Institution misidentified the museum criticized by experts as having as its chief weakness its later-20th-century and contemporary collection. It is the Smithsonian American Art Museum -- not the National Gallery of Art, which is not part of the Smithsonian.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 5, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article in The Arts yesterday about problems facing the Smithsonian Institution misidentified the museum criticized by experts as having as its chief weakness its later-20th-century and contemporary collection. It is the Smithsonian American Art Museum -- not the National Gallery of Art, which is not part of the Smithsonian.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
