<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nearing a Plea in the Case Of the Fake Veterinarian</title>
    <meta content="04vet" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/nyregion/04vet.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837972"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Veterinary Medicine</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Impersonations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cruelty to Animals</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vassall, Steven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brick, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cruelty to Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Veterinary Medicine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cruelty to Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Veterinary Medicine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E5D71F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="539" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nearing a Plea in the Case Of the Fake Veterinarian</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nearing a Plea in the Case of the Fake Veterinarian</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL BRICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brick, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Steven Vassall, who was charged in 2006 with unlicensed practice of veterinary medicine and torture of animals, takes procedural step toward admission to Brooklyn Mental Health Court, experiment in jurisprudence for defendants who demonstrate serious and persistent mental illness; lawyer says trial is unlikely (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his day, Detective Fred the Cat was lionized from Grand Rapids, Mich., to Japan. There was a law enforcement award; there was an appearance on Broadway. The Sunday Mercury of Birmingham, England, described his exploits under the headline ''Crazy World.''</p>
        <p>Now the legacy of his law enforcement career, such as it was, draws near a close. Fred's most famous collar appeared in Brooklyn Supreme Court yesterday for a psychiatric evaluation that could lead to a plea bargain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The legacy of the law enforcement career of a cat draws near a close in a case in Brooklyn Supreme Court.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his day, Detective Fred the Cat was lionized from Grand Rapids, Mich., to Japan. There was a law enforcement award; there was an appearance on Broadway. The Sunday Mercury of Birmingham, England, described his exploits under the headline ''Crazy World.''</p>
        <p>Now the legacy of his law enforcement career, such as it was, draws near a close. Fred's most famous collar appeared in Brooklyn Supreme Court yesterday for a psychiatric evaluation that could lead to a plea bargain.</p>
        <p>The defendant, Steven Vassall, 29, has been charged with the unlicensed practice of veterinary medicine and the torture of animals. His hearing was a procedural step toward admission to Brooklyn Mental Health Court, a 5-year-old experiment in jurisprudence for defendants who demonstrate a ''serious and persistent mental illness.''</p>
        <p>A lawyer for Mr. Vassall, Royce Russell, said a trial was unlikely.</p>
        <p>''He's being evaluated for a jail alternative,'' Mr. Russell said in an interview. ''The jury's still out on whether he'll be eligible.''</p>
        <p>The saga of Mr. Vassall's apprehension bears some recounting:</p>
        <p>In the summer of 2005, prosecutors say, Mr. Vassall, an unemployed lab technician who presented himself as a veterinarian, performed surgery on a Boston terrier named Burt, who had been in his regular care for about four years. Burt was left bleeding from an open wound; Burt's master called the district attorney's office.</p>
        <p>A sting was arranged, but a sting needs a drag. Fred Wheezy was the adopted pet of a deputy district attorney, Carol Moran, who had nursed him to such robust health as to require neutering. In February 2006, a surveillance camera captured Mr. Vassall picking up Fred and a $135 cash payment. He was arrested without attempting the job.</p>
        <p>About a year ago, Fred darted into traffic and was killed instantly, bringing sorrow to his admirers and more to his caretakers, a family devoted to the nurture of sick animals.</p>
        <p>The case against Mr. Vassall continued with complaints from several pet owners, including a woman named Rosaline Arthur. In September, Justice John P. Walsh reviewed the grand jury testimony and dismissed all charges of aggravated cruelty to animals, writing that prosecutors had failed to show evidence of serious physical injury.</p>
        <p>''The only evidence the people provided in support of 'serious physical injury' was Ms. Arthur's testimony that, when the defendant returned her cat, she noticed a scar on his hind leg which did not 'look professionally done,' '' the judge wrote. Quoting Ms. Arthur, he continued: ''It looked like loops, then thread looped around the scarring and then there was like a hole toward the end where this was, it was just an open little space, a hole in there.''</p>
        <p>The charges of practicing veterinary medicine without a license remain.</p>
        <p>Court records show that Mr. Vassall has met with private psychiatrists, expressing remorse and describing a misguided intention to help others. His lawyer has submitted testimonials from supporters and satisfied pet owners. And the case has progressed toward Mental Health Court.</p>
        <p>''That speaks to what may be the ultimate resolution,'' said his lawyer, Mr. Russell.</p>
        <p>If so, an outreach group in Harlem has offered to employ Mr. Vassall with community service to AIDS patients, providing a volunteer outlet for the untrained urge to heal.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
