<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>National Titles Inspire Others at Florida</title>
    <meta content="04florida" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/sports/ncaabasketball/04florida.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837885"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gymnastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gymnastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Florida</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Meyer, Urban</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E1DF163FF937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="827" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>National Titles Inspire Others at Florida</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">National Titles Inspire Others at Florida</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crouse, Karen</byline>
      <dateline>GAINESVILLE, Fla., April 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>While 2,000 townspeople paid homage to the Florida men's basketball team Tuesday, members of the Florida women's gymnastics team honored the back-to-back national champions by staying away.</p>
        <p>In the early afternoon, when the basketball team's plane touched down at the regional airport eight miles from campus, the No. 1-ranked gymnasts were huddled around a television set inside the O'Connell Center on campus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here at the center of the college sporting scene, while other athletic programs ponder how to catch up to the Florida Gators, the Gators are busy chasing one other.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>While 2,000 townspeople paid homage to the Florida men's basketball team Tuesday, members of the Florida women's gymnastics team honored the back-to-back national champions by staying away.</p>
        <p>In the early afternoon, when the basketball team's plane touched down at the regional airport eight miles from campus, the No. 1-ranked gymnasts were huddled around a television set inside the O'Connell Center on campus.</p>
        <p>It was not the live cable telecast of the players' return from Atlanta that had their rapt attention, but a homemade video of their performance at last weekend's Southeastern Conference championships in Arkansas.</p>
        <p>The Gators' gymnasts, using the success of the university's reigning national champion football team and its resplendent men's basketball team as a springboard, vaulted Georgia and Alabama to win the title, becoming the first college other than the Bulldogs or Crimson Tide since 1989 to wear the crown.</p>
        <p>With the N.C.A.A. regionals looming in two weeks -- followed two weeks later by the national championships in Salt Lake City -- the gymnasts did not dare take a practice off, even to acknowledge the team whose success has spurred their own.</p>
        <p>Here, at the center of the college sporting scene, while other athletic programs ponder how to catch up to the Gators, the Gators are busy chasing one another. After the football team equaled the success of the basketball team, the basketball team raised the bar by repeating, becoming the first university to win the football and basketball Division I championships in the same academic year.</p>
        <p>Samantha Lutz, a senior gymnast, said, ''I feel like all the sports are feeding off each other, like the entire athletic association has caught fire.''</p>
        <p>Gators, it seems, are surfacing everywhere. Ryan Lochte, a former Florida standout, last week set an individual world record and won five medals at the World Aquatics Championships in Australia. An ex-Gator golfer, Camilo Villegas, is playing this week in his first Masters.</p>
        <p>Within the athletic department, the atmosphere is more collegial than competitive. Before the gymnasts left for the SEC championships, Urban Meyer, the second-year football coach, delivered a pep talk and showed them the same inspirational video that the football team watched before going out and beating Ohio State in the B.C.S. national title game.</p>
        <p>''When he talks to you, it's like your blood starts running faster,'' Lutz said. ''After his talk, we were ready to take on the world.''</p>
        <p>As the Gators have positioned themselves to become the first university other than Georgia, Alabama, U.C.L.A. or Utah to win the N.C.A.A. women's gymnastics title, Rhonda Faehn, the Gators' fifth-year gymnastics coach, has received a lot of good-natured ribbing.</p>
        <p>Faehn, who has guided her team to a 21-0-1 record, said: ''What I keep hearing from people is: 'Come on. What else do you want? You have the basketball title. You have the football title. Leave us alone.' ''</p>
        <p>During the Gators' 84-75 victory over Ohio State on Monday night, Faehn's in-box quickly filled up with text messages from recruits who were inspired by the Gators' performance. Anthony Nesty, Florida's associate head coach in swimming, said he was fielding e-mail messages and phone calls from recruits all night.</p>
        <p>''The winning attitude in football and basketball is like a magnet that attracts people,'' said Nesty, a four-time N.C.A.A. individual champion at Florida. He added, ''It makes our job a little easier.''</p>
        <p>Lutz, whose specialty is the uneven bars, said the general climate here had warmed perceptibly since her arrival from Ohio as a freshman in the fall of 2003. That season, the football team went 8-5 and lost to Iowa in the Outback Bowl, and the men's basketball team was upset by Manhattan in the first round of the N.C.A.A. tournament.</p>
        <p>as like an echo chamber.</p>
        <p>A seismic shift occurred in 2006 when the basketball team won the national title, the football team won its first national championship since the 1996 season and every one of the basketball starters returned to defend their championship.</p>
        <p>As the fortunes of those two revenue-producing sports rose, they lifted the entire athletic department. ''They definitely did,'' said Lutz, pointing to the attendance for women's gymnastics, which averaged nearly 5,000 for its six home dates this season.</p>
        <p>''Everyone in Gainesville is feeling so much Gator pride right now,'' Lutz said. ''It's been amazing to see that happen and be a part of it. It's just been like climbing a mountain and we've reached the top.''</p>
        <p>At the student bookstore, a long table at the front contained eight piles of white championship T-shirts. Hanging nearby on a rack were discounted Final Four basketball T-shirts.</p>
        <p>''I know everything goes in cycles,'' Nesty said. ''The Gators are hot right now. That's the ultimate challenge for me as a coach, to keep the winning going. It makes me work harder, it makes me recruit harder.''</p>
        <p>It made the gymnastics team stay inside and practice when it could have been outside welcoming the basketball players home on another postcard-perfect Florida afternoon.</p>
        <p>N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
