<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Paper Mill Playhouse Says the Show Can't Go On Without $1.5 Million</title>
    <meta content="04paper" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/nyregion/04paper.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837894"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Paper Mill Playhouse (Millburn, NJ)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Performing Arts Center (Newark)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robertson, Campbell</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Seven Brides for Seven Brothers (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Paper Mill Playhouse</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EFDF163FF937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Paper Mill Playhouse Says the Show Can't Go On Without $1.5 Million</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Financial Emergency for Celebrated Nonprofit Theater in New Jersey</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAMPBELL ROBERTSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robertson, Campbell</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Paper Mill Playhouse in Millburn, NJ, has $1.5 million shortfall that threatens its 69th season, which is supposed to begin on April 11 with Seven Brides for Seven Brothers; number of subscribers has fallen from high of 42,000 in early 1990s to 19,500, largely due to competition from reinvigorated Broadway and especially New Jersey Performing Arts Center in Newark; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If things do not change soon, there will be a last-minute substitution at the Paper Mill Playhouse in Millburn, N.J.</p>
        <p>The role of ''Seven Brides for Seven Brothers,'' the musical that was to be the next entry in the Paper Mill's 69th season, will instead be played by an empty theater, 110 out-of-work employees and a bankruptcy lawyer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Financial problems have put the rest of the season in doubt for the Paper Mill Playhouse in Millburn, N.J.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If things do not change soon, there will be a last-minute substitution at the Paper Mill Playhouse in Millburn, N.J.</p>
        <p>The role of ''Seven Brides for Seven Brothers,'' the musical that was to be the next entry in the Paper Mill's 69th season, will instead be played by an empty theater, 110 out-of-work employees and a bankruptcy lawyer.</p>
        <p>Officials at the Paper Mill, one of the premier nonprofit theaters in the region, said yesterday that because of a $1.5 million shortfall, they were not sure if ''Seven Brides,'' which is scheduled to begin performances next Wednesday, would be able to open at all. Even if that money is raised in the coming days, a slightly smaller amount will be needed to keep the theater running for the last show of the season, ''Pirates!''</p>
        <p>In August, Paper Mill's board approved a $17 million budget with a $2.8 million shortfall built in. The board said it would raise much of that as part of a capital campaign, and make up the difference with better ticket sales.</p>
        <p>Kenneth Thorn, the board chairman, said yesterday that by mid-November, about $2.5 million was pledged to the capital campaign, much of it contingent on plans for the theater's future.</p>
        <p>But on Nov. 16, Michael Gennaro, Paper Mill's president and chief executive, unexpectedly announced his resignation. The capital campaign ''came to a grinding halt,'' Mr. Thorn said. Almost none of the pledges have been collected, and ticket sales have not met projections.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gennaro, who is now the executive director of Trinity Repertory Company in Providence, R.I., said his departure should not be blamed for the theater's current problems.</p>
        <p>''You give to an institution, not an individual,'' he said. ''I don't understand why my departure would have any bearing on that.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Thorn said that the board had been confident that a bank loan, among some other measures, would cover this season's shortfall, but the bank turned down the loan last Friday, abruptly leaving the rest of the season in doubt.</p>
        <p>Theater officials and trustees have managed to raise about $100,000 recently in new pledges from donors and subscribers, and they have approached another bank about a loan.</p>
        <p>And they are reaching deep into a talent pool of actors who have passed through Paper Mill, asking them to participate in a fund-raising performance being planned at the theater on Monday night. State officials and such Broadway stars as John Lloyd Young of the hit ''Jersey Boys'' are among those being invited.</p>
        <p>The theater's financial emergency was reported yesterday in The Star-Ledger of Newark.</p>
        <p>Paper Mill officials offer many reasons for the financial emergency. One of them, they say, is the theater's lopsided income model, which Mr. Gennaro sought to change after arriving at Paper Mill in April 2003.</p>
        <p>Revenue at nonprofit theaters is usually balanced between contributions and earned income from subscriptions and single ticket sales. But contributions make up only a fifth of the Paper Mill's income in most years, and a consultant hired by the theater in 2004 reported that the board was not adequately leading the theater's fund-raising efforts.</p>
        <p>''We have to change this dynamic or the theater will not survive,'' said Diane Claussen, the theater's managing director.</p>
        <p>In the early 1990s, when the Paper Mill had a reputation as a reliable place for classic musicals with high production values, it had about 42,000 subscribers, a number that has since dropped to 19,500.</p>
        <p>The main culprit was competition. Fifteen years ago, Broadway was in the doldrums and the Paper Mill was often the nearest alternative for big musical revivals. That began to change in the late 1990s with the renovation of Times Square. Since 1994, Broadway grosses have more than doubled.</p>
        <p>The theater's real challenger arrived in 1997, when the New Jersey Performing Arts Center opened in Newark. The center became a stop for touring productions of war horse shows like ''The Sound of Music'' and ''Fiddler on the Roof,'' drawing theatergoers and millions of dollars in corporate support from the Paper Mill.</p>
        <p>''They've sort of sucked all the corporate money out,'' said Ruthi Byrne, a member of the Paper Mill board. ''The Paper Mill has been left high and dry.''</p>
        <p>In 2003, the board turned to Mr. Gennaro, the managing director at the acclaimed Steppenwolf Theater Company of Chicago, as well as a lawyer and actor with a show business lineage.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gennaro, who replaced Angelo del Rossi, a 40-year veteran of the Paper Mill, tried to draw a more diverse audience, mixing newer musicals and more obscure works. The few mainstream shows, like ''Godspell,'' sold out, but the more obscure works, like a new musical adaptation of ''Harold and Maude,'' did not do well.</p>
        <p>The schedule for next season -- which includes ''Meet Me in St. Louis,'' ''Kiss Me, Kate'' and ''Little Shop of Horrors'' -- has some of the familiar names that the subscribers seem to want. But, said Scott Fergang, who became a member of the board last year: ''If we don't have the money, then what do we do? Go out on the street?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
