<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Longer Young, but Still Turning Heads</title>
    <meta content="04rest" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/dining/reviews/04rest.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837952"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E2D81F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1393" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Longer Young, but Still Turning Heads</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">No Longer Young, but Still Turning Heads</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank Bruni</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LIKE brown eyes, mechanical incompetence and a loss of control around peanut butter, the Four Seasons was something I got from my father.</p>
        <p>When I was in college and he wanted me to experience a truly grown-up restaurant, steeped not just in fancy food but in a sweeping sense of the big money to be made and spent in this city, the Four Seasons was where we went, our ties properly cinched, our shoes freshly polished.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In spite of a few miscues, there’s a stubborn magic at the Four Seasons for anyone who’s ever seen it as the epitome of urbanity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LIKE brown eyes, mechanical incompetence and a loss of control around peanut butter, the Four Seasons was something I got from my father.</p>
        <p>When I was in college and he wanted me to experience a truly grown-up restaurant, steeped not just in fancy food but in a sweeping sense of the big money to be made and spent in this city, the Four Seasons was where we went, our ties properly cinched, our shoes freshly polished.</p>
        <p>He shook hands and traded compliments with important-looking men in expensive-looking suits. I took my first bite of roasted duck and woke up to a world of indulgence just waiting to be devoured.</p>
        <p>The lustrous French walnut walls of the Grill Room rose high around us. The metal chain curtains over the windows rippled like a slow-motion waterfall. On that visit and subsequent ones -- for a while, I made him take me back every year -- I understood the meaning of privilege in a whole new way. The Four Seasons thrilled me.</p>
        <p>Fast forward a few decades. It's a weekend night not long ago. I show up at the restaurant for the first time in a long while. Two friends and I have a reservation in the Pool Room, with its gurgling marble center and its indoor foliage, but we're plunked without apology in a far corner of a lesser annex.</p>
        <p>Our appetizers arrive perhaps five minutes after we order them, an example of an assembly-line quality that pervades the evening. One of these dishes, kabocha squash ravioli with porcini mushrooms, is a sad molehill of bland mush.</p>
        <p>Another, a seafood risotto, doesn't have much flavor either, but it does have something it isn't supposed to: a scallop. When we asked our server if there were any in the dish -- a friend wanted to make sure she didn't order a redundant entree -- his answer was an unequivocal no.</p>
        <p>He isn't so sharp. Or so smooth. To distinguish between one glass of Sancerre and another of chardonnay, he's put a plastic stirrer in the chardonnay, and he doesn't bother to remove it until he sets the wine on our table.</p>
        <p>This at a restaurant with dinner salads for more than $20, short ribs for $45 and breast of pheasant for $55? I order the pheasant, primed for poultry royalty. What I get is a commoner, dry and no more distinguished than anything from the Court of Tyson or the House of Perdue.</p>
        <p>Over the following weeks, on follow-up visits, there are much better dishes, much finer meals. But the Four Seasons remains bedeviled by an inconsistency at serious odds with the prices it charges and the legend it enjoys.</p>
        <p>The standouts on the menu aren't as numerous as they should be. The signs of a restaurant that runs on two tracks -- one for the anonymous, another for the anointed -- are too obvious.</p>
        <p>I get the sense that I've moved from the first to the second group about a third of the way into one of my dinners, with the arrival of a salad to be prepared tableside. Suddenly the romaine's lone squire is joined by several others, who fuss and fret over the cart as if what's under way isn't a Caesar but a Caesarean.</p>
        <p>No matter. The lettuce droops, the Parmesan doesn't register and the dressing has an unexpected, unappealing tang.</p>
        <p>But in spite of all the miscues, there's a stubborn magic at the Four Seasons for anyone who's ever seen it as the epitome of urbanity, and I'm hardly alone in that group.</p>
        <p>There's an irresistible majesty in its history and its iconic Philip Johnson design. When it opened in 1959, the $4.5 million cost of its construction generated headlines. The elite midday crowd that reliably gathered at the restaurant gave rise to the phrase power lunch. In time it was even designated a city landmark, and the air in there indeed feels suffused with a nonpareil importance.</p>
        <p>It was once even a culinary trailblazer, extolling seasonality long before Alice Waters raised her leafy green pompoms. But these days any restaurant with a similar sense of self updates its menu regularly, and many do so more frequently than the Four Seasons, which in this way and others is no longer a pioneer.</p>
        <p>And as I make my way through the luxuries on its French-influenced American bill of fare, I'm only intermittently able to tap into the pleasure and excitement described by Ruth Reichl when she gave it three stars in The New York Times in 1995. Since then the kitchen, under the stewardship of the chef Christian Albin for 17 years now, may well have drifted.</p>
        <p>There are lofty peaks. The fillet of bison is one, because it's so tender, and it's cloaked in the epicurean equivalent of a mink: sautéed foie gras and a reduction rich with black truffles.</p>
        <p>The roasted duck, which emerges from a Peking-style sequence of many days and steps, is as astonishing as ever, a knockout of crunchy skin and succulent meat that plunges three friends and me into a gastronomic fugue state.</p>
        <p>''What just happened?'' one of them says after a wordless 10 minutes, as we rediscover a language more nuanced than chewing and sighing.</p>
        <p>''Duck blackout,'' responds another.</p>
        <p>While the restaurant's renowned Dover sole is tepid and a tad rubbery on one night, it's as delicate as can be on another. Bison carpaccio with shavings of black truffle is opulence incarnate, suggesting a charmed relationship between this particular restaurant and this particular beast.</p>
        <p>And there's little fault to be found in a meaty rack of lamb; in a plate of Kumamoto oysters slathered with a potent anchovy butter; in the white asparagus that the restaurant begins to incorporate in various dishes as it unveils its spring menu, which brims with morels and fiddlehead ferns; or in most of the desserts.</p>
        <p>But disappointments abound. Our table's duck blackout can't redeem our pâté freakout: why, we all wondered, did two of the pâtés in an appetizer triptych have such odd textures -- chalky and spongy -- and leave such ashen aftertastes?</p>
        <p>The duck doesn't excuse an overcooked piece of swordfish with few discernible hints of the ginger trumpeted as its splashy accomplice. Or overly sugary soufflés. Or an uninspired selection of only about half a dozen wines by the glass. Or the way a server barks at a friend and me to tell us that we're sitting just a few millimeters too close to his passageway to and from the bar.</p>
        <p>We're repeatedly yanked from heaven back down to earth, the defining rhythm of a meal at the Four Seasons, jarring enough to compete with the setting and sully the ceremony.</p>
        <p>Maybe I just didn't notice it when I was younger. Or maybe the restaurant, like so much else, isn't quite what it was.</p>
        <p>The Four Seasons  ** [Rating: Two Stars]  99 East 52nd Street; (212) 754-9494.</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- A series of landmark rooms designed by Philip Johnson and distinguished by undulating metal curtains. The wood-walled Grill Room is the capital of the power lunch; the Pool Room, with its iconic, water-filled marble center, is the premium dinner real estate.</p>
        <p>SOUND LEVEL -- Moderate.</p>
        <p>RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Bison carpaccio; organic beet salad; white asparagus with morels; chilled seafood selections or platter; Dover sole; bison fillet; rack of lamb; crisp duck; chocolate velvet; hazelnut tartlet.</p>
        <p>WINE LIST -- Extensive, international and expensive, with an emphasis on France and Italy.</p>
        <p>PRICE RANGE -- Appetizers, $18 to $38; entrees, $37 to $75; desserts, $15. Pre-theater prix fixe of three courses, with dessert, $65.</p>
        <p>HOURS -- Lunch from noon to 2:30 p.m. Monday through Friday. Dinner from 5 to 9:30 p.m. Monday through Friday and to 11:30 p.m. Saturday. Closed Sunday.</p>
        <p>RESERVATIONS -- For prime dinner or lunch times, call at least two weeks ahead.</p>
        <p>CREDIT CARDS -- All major cards.</p>
        <p>WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Entrance at street level and special elevator available to second-floor Grill Room and Pool Room, with an accessible restroom.</p>
        <p>WHAT THE STARS MEAN -- Ratings range from zero to four stars and reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>PAST REVIEWS from The Times, with additional capsule reviews by Times critics:</p>
        <p>nytimes.com/dining</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
