<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Mentor Teaches How to Become Wise in the Ways of Silicon Valley</title>
    <meta content="04venture" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="DealBook" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/business/04venture.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838029"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="VENTURE CAPITAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Venture Capital</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mentors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mayfield Fund</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dalal, Yogen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Palihapitiya, Chamath</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richtel, Matt</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Venture Capital</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Leaders and Leadership</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Entrepreneurship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entrepreneurship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leaders and Leadership</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Venture Capital</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Silicon Valley (Calif)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05EED61F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1334" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Mentor Teaches How to Become Wise in the Ways of Silicon Valley</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Mentor Teaches How to Become Wise in the Ways of Silicon Valley</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT RICHTEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Richtel, Matt</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Yogen Dalal, managing director of Silicon Valley venture capital firm Mayfield Fund, plans to be mentor to his high-achieving protege Chamath Palihapitiya; goal is to help him earn trust of investors who give firm hundreds of millions of dollars, teach him to identify worthwhile start-ups and allow him to work with and inspire startups' executives without aggravating them with his youthful exuberance; photo (special section, DealBook) (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE morning after Chamath Palihapitiya won $50,000 in an all-night poker game, he walked into a BMW dealership in Virginia. The dealer, seeing an unkempt 26-year-old, did not allow him a test-drive. So Mr. Palihapitiya walked across the street to a Mercedes-Benz dealer, bought a car and returned to show the BMW salesman what he had missed.</p>
        <p>Winning had been the only thing for the ultracompetitive, hyperintelligent Mr. Palihapitiya, who by age 27 was head of AOL's communication and instant-messaging division. Now at 30, he is in Silicon Valley, sitting at the feet of the venture capitalist Yogen Dalal, learning to live with failure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of Silicon Valley’s trickier rituals is nurturing a new generation of venture capitalists.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE morning after Chamath Palihapitiya won $50,000 in an all-night poker game, he walked into a BMW dealership in Virginia. The dealer, seeing an unkempt 26-year-old, did not allow him a test-drive. So Mr. Palihapitiya walked across the street to a Mercedes-Benz dealer, bought a car and returned to show the BMW salesman what he had missed.</p>
        <p>Winning had been the only thing for the ultracompetitive, hyperintelligent Mr. Palihapitiya, who by age 27 was head of AOL's communication and instant-messaging division. Now at 30, he is in Silicon Valley, sitting at the feet of the venture capitalist Yogen Dalal, learning to live with failure.</p>
        <p>The two are involved in one of Silicon Valley's trickier rituals: nurturing a new generation of venture capitalists.</p>
        <p>For the next few years, Mr. Dalal, 57, a managing director at Mayfield Fund, plans to focus and tame Mr. Palihapitiya's talents. The goal is to help him earn the trust of investors who give the firm hundreds of millions of dollars, teach him to identify worthwhile start-ups and allow him to work with and inspire the start-ups' executives without aggravating them with his youthful exuberance.</p>
        <p>The passing of the torch does not always work.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dalal said that among his biggest challenges is teaching his Type A trainees that the venture capital business requires patience and, because of the huge risks involved in investing in start-ups, has failures.</p>
        <p>''The rule of thumb is that your first investment will fail,'' he said. ''Your enthusiasm is likely to be ahead of reality.'' The fear of failure, he said, can lead young VCs to overextend themselves.</p>
        <p>''The biggest issue young people have is persuading them they're not the C.E.O.,'' Mr. Dalal added, noting, ''When you've been the king yourself, it's hard to learn the new set of rules.''</p>
        <p>Despite the learning curve, there are good reasons to bring in new blood. Older venture capitalists can lose their vigor, develop other interests or want to enjoy their money. As with Mr. Dalal, they also want to keep their firms and legacies alive.</p>
        <p>But the old guard also must come to terms with parting with some of the hefty management fees and -- if the start-ups they invest in are major successes, like Google -- to share in the kind of big money that lets people buy vineyards and yachts.</p>
        <p>''The torch is so expensive and lovely that you don't really want to give it up,'' said Rory O'Driscoll, a managing director at Scale Venture Partners. ''It's hard for the old guard to say, 'Here's my $5 million a year.' ''</p>
        <p>Another challenge to succession is that pension funds and other big investors want to invest only with the most successful venture capitalists. Can they trust young turks with their tens of millions of dollars?</p>
        <p>David York, the chief executive and managing director of Paul Capital Investments, a limited partner that invests millions with venture capitalists, said he watched the successions carefully within venture firms when deciding where to invest and how much. ''You want to see if the secret sauce is still there,'' he said. ''You're constantly looking at the younger crop to see it they're going to grow up to be the next John Doerr.''</p>
        <p>Some industry analysts said that in recent years, it had been tough for outsiders to gauge the success of the newest partners, given the struggles of venture capitalists since the dot-com bust.</p>
        <p>''The reality is that pretty much everyone who has been in the business for seven years or less has not had an exit,'' said Paul Kedrosky, the executive director of the Von Liebing Center, which studies venture capital funds. ''That means you have an entire 'next generation' of partners who don't deserve to be partner.''</p>
        <p>There is also resistance sometimes from entrepreneurs -- the founders and executives whose start-ups are financed by venture capital money and who may not take advice easily from people just starting out.</p>
        <p>''They've got to deal with supersuccessful people, older people,'' Mr. Dalal said. ''Sometimes, the question comes up, Do the entrepreneurs respect these guys?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dalal earned his own stripes over many years. As a computer science and electrical engineering doctoral student at Stanford University, he was an author of the TCP/IP protocol used in Internet communications. At Xerox PARC, he was on a team that developed the Ethernet standard. He joined Mayfield in 1991, investing in enterprise start-ups, including Tibco.</p>
        <p>Besides Mr. Palihapitiya, Mr. Dalal has also mentored Rajil Kapoor, 36, a 1996 Harvard M.B.A. graduate who founded and served as chief executive of Snapfish, an online photo site, before engineering its sale for about $300 million.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kapoor, once the lead singer of the band Indian Elvis, lived through the dot-com bust. He oversaw the downsizing of Snapfish to 23 employees from 120, then helped rebuild it. ''It was the nuclear winter, and I was living it,'' he said. ''How many VCs in a position of influence have been C.E.O.'s through the ups of the craziness and the downs of near death?''</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Palihapitiya has shown a knack for numbers and reading people. His skills led him to become head of AOL's instant-messaging division, with more than 200 employees, in 2004 and, before that, vice president for product strategy at AOL's music division.</p>
        <p>At one point, he considered leaving AOL to try to make a living playing poker. ''I can sit across from someone and see in their eyes their strengths and weaknesses,'' Mr. Palihapitiya said. ''I feel like I can see their whole lives flash before me.''</p>
        <p>He added that he would rather identify capable entrepreneurs and their ideas ''than use that knowledge to face someone to deal with a $100,000 pot.''</p>
        <p>But he said he felt something lacking in his earlier successes. Immediately upon meeting Mr. Dalal, he said, he felt he could learn better composure and a focused style of thinking, talking and carrying himself.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dalal said his goal was to help the pair discover and develop their ''unfair advantages,'' which could give them and Mayfield a leg up in persuading start-ups to take money and guidance from them rather than other big-name firms.</p>
        <p>Mr. Palihapitiya's biggest strength, he said, is sensing what technologies will come next. Mr. Kapoor's strength, Mr. Dalal said, is that he knows how to help entrepreneurs through tough times.</p>
        <p>Each has vulnerabilities, too, he said. Mr. Dalal told an anecdote about a chief executive of an Internet company making a PowerPoint presentation to Mayfield recently. Mr. Kapoor had 10 questions before the executive could get through a slide.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kapoor ''wasn't trying to be the alpha dog, he was just trying to show the C.E.O. he'd thought through the issues,'' Mr. Dalal said. He added that the young VCs ''have to learn that it's just as important to listen as to engage.''</p>
        <p>Since he started as a junior partner with Mayfield in June 2005, Mr. Kapoor has been lead investor in five start-ups, including Wize.com, a consumer product research portal, and Tagged.com, a social networking site.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Palihapitiya, who joined as a principal in January 2006, the two investments so far have been Jaxtr, an Internet telephone start-up, and Consorte Media, a Hispanic online media company.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Palihapitiya was considering the Jaxtr investment, Mr. Dalal offered him advice.</p>
        <p>''He said, 'Don't flinch,' '' Mr. Palihapitiya said. He added that he wasn't sure what that meant and that Mr. Dalal explained that when making an investmentthis risky, there will be ups and downs and that it is important not to feel or send the message to the start-up that you have doubts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dalal might do well to take the same advice regarding his two protégés. And it sounds like he has.</p>
        <p>''I don't know how it'll turn out,'' he said. ''I'm betting on my own experience. Are my instincts good enough? I think these guys can make it, but I need to be the coach and get the very best out of these guys.''</p>
        <p>VENTURE CAPITAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
