<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nonprofit Doesn't Mean You Can't Wheel and Deal</title>
    <meta content="04urban" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/realestate/commercial/04urban.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838004"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SQUARE FEET"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Urban Justice Center</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fraxy (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lasdon, Douglas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pristin, Terry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Urban Justice Center</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Lasdon, Douglas</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EED71F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1010" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nonprofit Doesn't Mean You Can't Wheel and Deal</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nonprofit Doesn’t Mean You Can’t Wheel and Deal</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TERRY PRISTIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pristin, Terry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Urban Justice Center founder-executive director Douglas Lasdon has created sizable nest egg for his nonprofit organization that caters to New York's homeless population through series of shrewd real estate maneuvers; Lasdon signed contract last month to sell office condo that Urban Justice Center has occupied for decade to fashion copany Fraxy for $5.7 million, or nearly 10 times what he paid for it in 1997; his group will move into 20,000 square feet of newly renovated space at 123 William Street at below-market annual rent of $27 per square foot; other real estate deals noted; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Running the Urban Justice Center -- an organization founded more than two decades ago to advocate for New York's homeless population -- might not seem like the best credential for making a killing in real estate.</p>
        <p>In recent years, the center's client base has expanded to include prostitutes, street vendors, victims of domestic violence and others among those it calls society's ''most deprived and abused people.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Urban Justice Center has managed to create a sizable nest egg through a series of shrewd real estate maneuvers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Running the Urban Justice Center -- an organization founded more than two decades ago to advocate for New York's homeless population -- might not seem like the best credential for making a killing in real estate.</p>
        <p>In recent years, the center's client base has expanded to include prostitutes, street vendors, victims of domestic violence and others among those it calls society's ''most deprived and abused people.''</p>
        <p>Raising money to support such causes can be a challenge. And, in fact, no individual donor has ever contributed more than $10,000 to the nonprofit group, said Douglas Lasdon, the founder and executive director.</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Lasdon has managed to create a sizable nest egg for his organization through a series of shrewd real estate maneuvers. Along the way, he has absorbed some harsh lessons about real estate transactions and has also learned how to drive a hard bargain, even with his brokers.</p>
        <p>''The school of hard knocks in the not-for-profit world has taught him to be really tough,'' said Jeffrey D. Haroldson, the president of HDG Mansur Capital Group, an international real estate company, and an Urban Justice Center board member who met Mr. Lasdon at Cornell Law School.</p>
        <p>In his biggest coup so far, Mr. Lasdon signed a contract last month to sell the office condo that Urban Justice Center has occupied for a decade -- 7,700 square feet at 666 Broadway, at the corner of Bond Street -- to a fashion company, Fraxy, for $5.7 million, or nearly 10 times what he paid for it in 1997.</p>
        <p>This week, his group will move into 20,000 square feet of newly renovated space at 123 William Street at the below-market annual rent of $27 a square foot.</p>
        <p>An unlikely wheeler-dealer, Mr. Lasdon does not own a cellphone or home computer, much less a BlackBerry.</p>
        <p>He paid no rent at all when he moved into his first office in 1984, in a burned-out building in East Harlem. ''For five years, they renovated around me,'' he said. For the next decade, he gradually traded up, moving to the area around the then drug-infested Tompkins Square Park and then to the Flatiron district.</p>
        <p>In 1996, when his lease was about to expire and comparable space was renting for about $18 a square foot, a broker offered him the opportunity to buy the 10th floor at 666 Broadway in NoHo for $700,000. Mr. Lasdon said he realized that if he could pare the price to $600,000, his annual mortgage and maintenance costs would total only $11 a square foot.</p>
        <p>At the time, few businesses, nonprofit or otherwise, were buying their own space. ''I asked myself, 'What is the reason I shouldn't do this?' '' Mr. Lasdon said. ''I couldn't find one.''</p>
        <p>Arnold B. Peinado III, a board member and partner at the law firm of Milbank, Tweed, Hadley &amp; McCoy, said the directors weighed the question carefully. ''The organization's mission is not to be in the real estate business, but instead to serve its clients,'' he said. ''It seemed at the time to be a bit daring, but probably economical, to go ahead and take a chance on buying a floor.''</p>
        <p>The seller had agreed informally on the $600,000 price but later tried to raise it, Mr. Lasdon recalled. ''We had a handshake deal,'' he said. ''I said, 'I'm not going to do it, as a matter of principle.' '' A week later, he got the price he wanted. The down payment was $100,000.</p>
        <p>''It was the deal of the century,'' said the broker who handled the purchase, David N. Lebenstein, now the director of the nonprofit division at Colliers ABR. ''We hit the timing right. But even then, he was trying to cut the price down.''</p>
        <p>As the Urban Justice Center grew -- it now employs 62 people and has an annual budget of $4.5 million -- it rented additional space in the same building. But last year, when additional space there was not available, Mr. Lasdon decided it was time to move. Twice he came close to buying space in Lower Manhattan -- in one case, the seller changed its mind after agreeing to a sale. ''Nothing's a deal until it's signed'' was the lesson that Mr. Lasdon said he drew.</p>
        <p>A couple of other disappointments followed, eventually leading him to conclude that condo space was out of reach.</p>
        <p>Nonprofit organizations that find themselves occupying valuable real estate often face similar obstacles, Mr. Lebenstein said. ''The problem is, where do they go?'' he said. Clients need to find new quarters, as Mr. Lasdon did, before giving up the space they have, he said.</p>
        <p>In October, Mr. Lasdon agreed to a lease at 123 William Street after getting the landlord to reduce the rent and his new broker, Mark Mandell, a senior director at Cushman &amp; Wakefield, to cut his commission.</p>
        <p>Initially, Mr. Lasdon planned to rent out the office at 666 Broadway, but he found no takers. ''It was a bit of a mess,'' Mr. Mandell recalled. ''It didn't show as well as it might have if it were vacated, or even demolished.''</p>
        <p>Then, in the fall, the fashion company, Fraxy, offered to buy the space for $5 million. ''I said, 'If they're willing to pay $5 million, let's see how high they're going to go.' '' But as the price began to rise, Mr. Lasdon said, ''I started to get nervous. I was going to outsmart myself.'' Mr. Lasdon also negotiated with another potential buyer.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, Mr. Lasdon was able to drive up the price to $5.7 million. He also got Mr. Mandell to reduce his commission by one-third. (Mr. Mandell would not discuss the commissions he received.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Lasdon said he would have to set aside $200,000 a year in income from this windfall to cover the increase in rent, but will have plenty left over for programs.</p>
        <p>And maybe some real estate. He said he would like to develop a building for the sole use of nonprofit organizations.</p>
        <p>The real estate world can be ''frustrating and maddening,'' he said. ''But if it works out, it's terrific.''</p>
        <p>SQUARE FEET</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
