<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nuclear Drill Performance Raises Issues On Safety</title>
    <meta content="04nuke" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/us/04nuke.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838014"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vogtle Nuclear Power Plant (Ga)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Southern Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nuclear Regulatory Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Nuclear Regulatory Commission</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E2D61F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="705" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nuclear Drill Performance Raises Issues On Safety</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nuclear Drill Performance Raises Issues on Safety</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Southern Co makes unusual appeal to top Nuclear Regulatory Commission officials to revise its poor grade on March 2006 nuclear accident drill at company's Vogtle Nuclear Plant near Augusta, Ga; contends penalizing it for making tough call within short time allotted will have chilling effect on rest of industry and lead to reactor operators' being too slow in giving public safety officials their assessments of what is happening (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As a simulated nuclear accident unfolded at a Georgia power plant, the drill called for a pump shaft to break and to dump metal parts into the reactor coolant system.</p>
        <p>Radiation in the containment building levels was to rise and the water level was to start dropping so fast that the regular pumps could not keep up. The emergency director concluded that there might have been a pipe break, and declared a site-area emergency, the second-highest classification of accident.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Vogtle Nuclear Plant near Augusta received a poor grade on a simulated nuclear accident by the Nuclear Regulatory Commission.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As a simulated nuclear accident unfolded at a Georgia power plant, the drill called for a pump shaft to break and to dump metal parts into the reactor coolant system.</p>
        <p>Radiation in the containment building levels was to rise and the water level was to start dropping so fast that the regular pumps could not keep up. The emergency director concluded that there might have been a pipe break, and declared a site-area emergency, the second-highest classification of accident.</p>
        <p>But the script for the drill, held March 22, 2006, at the Vogtle Nuclear Plant near Augusta, did not include a pipe break, and the staff of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission graded the performance of the plant's owner, the Southern Company, poor. It said afterward that the emergency director had overdiagnosed the problem. Further, the commission said, the company had failed to spot the mistake and had therefore failed to identify its own weakness.</p>
        <p>Now, the company has made an unusual appeal to top commission officials to revise its grade on the drill. Southern argued that it was not reasonable for the commission staff, which had read the script in advance, to second-guess the emergency director, for whom the script was a secret and whose job was to develop an accurate picture of an unfolding ''accident'' based on fragmentary bits of information.</p>
        <p>The company contends that penalizing it for making a tough call within the short time allotted will have a chilling effect on the rest of the industry and lead to reactor operators' being too slow in giving public safety officials their assessments of what is happening.</p>
        <p>''In accordance with our plans and our procedures,'' the emergency director ''had no choice but to declare a site-area emergency,'' said Jeffrey T. Gasser, the executive vice president and chief nuclear officer of the Southern Nuclear Operating Company, which operates the Vogtle plant.</p>
        <p>The commission's finding, Mr. Gasser said, would make the emergency manager in a real accident ''take longer to evaluate conditions, before making a classification.'' And that, he said, could delay putting an emergency plan into effect.</p>
        <p>But the commission said the emergency director and the control room crew should have responded to the indications in their simulator control room ''in a methodical manner, assessing the event and utilizing the diagnostics in such a manner to ensure that 'undue haste' did not result in misdiagnosis, misoperation, or undesired plant conditions.''</p>
        <p>The indications that the emergency director used to diagnose a possible water leak were ambiguous. The water level in a reactor can fall for a variety of reasons; one is that when a reactor shuts down, its water cools and, like a piece of metal, shrinks.</p>
        <p>The radiation level in the containment building was up, according to the simulation, but that did not prove there was a leak, Mr. Gasser said, because the elevated readings came from water that was still inside the reactor. The water had higher readings because the fuel had been damaged by the loose metal parts, in the simulation.</p>
        <p>The reactor has a water sensor, but it is nine inches off the floor. David Lochbaum, a nuclear engineer at the Union of Concerned Scientists, a group that is often critical of nuclear safety regulation, said that a leak of 150 gallons per minute would take 90 minutes for the sensor to detect.</p>
        <p>But the emergency director is supposed to categorize the event in the first 15 minutes. Mr. Lochbaum said this raised the question of whether the sensor was in the right place, or should be nearer the floor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gasser said that if the sensor was too near the floor, debris that might be present during an accident could affect its operation.</p>
        <p>The commission pays close attention to how the industry and the public react to nuclear events. Last November, a Tennessee school district sent children home after an instrument at the Watts Bar Nuclear Plant indicated (falsely, as it turned out) there might be a leak. Commission officials said the reaction was unwarranted.</p>
        <p>For Southern, the impact of the poor rating could be enhanced scrutiny by regulators, which could in turn make Southern's stock price fall or make it harder for the company to raise money.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
