<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After the Buyouts, Lawyers Prepare to Wrap Bandages</title>
    <meta content="04skadden" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="DealBook" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/business/04skadden.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838031"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="LEGAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EED61F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="960" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After the Buyouts, Lawyers Prepare to Wrap Bandages</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After the Buyouts, Lawyers Prepare to Wrap Bandages</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER EDMONSTON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS the chiefs of private equity pull off one highflying buyout after another, bankruptcy lawyers are beginning to get their safety nets and first-aid kits ready.</p>
        <p>Many Chapter 11 casualties are expected to come from the dozens of companies that have been taken private in the last few years in debt-financed transactions. Anticipating that the long lull in corporate bankruptcies may finally be over, law firms are bulking up their bankruptcy and restructuring groups.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the chiefs of private equity pull off one highflying buyout after another, bankruptcy lawyers are beginning to get their safety nets and first-aid kits ready.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS the chiefs of private equity pull off one highflying buyout after another, bankruptcy lawyers are beginning to get their safety nets and first-aid kits ready.</p>
        <p>Many Chapter 11 casualties are expected to come from the dozens of companies that have been taken private in the last few years in debt-financed transactions. Anticipating that the long lull in corporate bankruptcies may finally be over, law firms are bulking up their bankruptcy and restructuring groups.</p>
        <p>Harvey Miller, perhaps the nation's pre-eminent bankruptcy lawyer, said in March that he would leave the investment bank Greenhill &amp; Company to return to the law firm Weil Gotshal &amp; Manges. Later, four Weil Gotshal bankruptcy partners jumped to Cadwalader, Wickersham &amp; Taft, the counsel to Northwest Airlines in its Chapter 11 case.</p>
        <p>Skadden Arps Slate Meagher &amp; Flom, adviser to some of the biggest companies in bankruptcy, including Kmart, Polaroid and US Airways, is also hunting for restructuring talent. J. Gregory Milmoe, a co-head of Skadden's corporate restructuring group, said he thought a bankruptcy surge was coming soon. ''We are hiring people and training them with the expectation that it is going to be happening this year,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He suggested that the ocean of capital that has kept many companies afloat in recent years might begin to dry up. This is especially likely, he said, if investors are rattled by more hedge fund collapses, like the one last year at Amaranth Advisors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Milmoe, who led the Skadden team that advised Refco, the commodities broker that collapsed into bankruptcy in October 2005, was asked recently about the next wave of bankruptcies. Following are excerpts from the discussion.</p>
        <p>Q. Why has corporate bankruptcy activity been so slow?</p>
        <p>A. It's part of a normal cycle. Over 35 years, give or take, we see high levels of activity every five to seven years with some regularity. The deals most easily charted are the ones that are a function of economic policies: easy money versus tight money. At the moment, we are experiencing a massive amount of available cash, and that cash for investment has been available for two and a half to three years. What we're predicting is that companies who were bailed out of a difficult situation two or three years ago are now coming up on a situation where they will have gotten in trouble again. Some percentage of those companies will continue to be rescued by available capital. But with others, people will say, ''This was a bad investment, and we're not going to throw more good money after bad.''</p>
        <p>Q. When you look at the recent boom in leveraged buyouts, do you think of it as bankruptcy work in the making?</p>
        <p>A. During the last cycle there was -- or there used to be -- a stigma associated with private equity firms' having their portfolio companies go into bankruptcy. But if you look back at the period from 1999 to about 2002, enough portfolio companies went in that a flippant kind of remark gained some currency: ''If at least one of your companies doesn't go into bankruptcy, you're not trying hard enough.'' The analogy is: ''You're not going to hit home runs unless you strike out.'' Of course, I'm a lawyer, and I bill by the 10th of an hour. There are multibillionaires out there who got to be multibillionaires by taking risks, identifying companies that had the wherewithal to load up on leverage and still make wonderful equity returns. Still, you hate to see decisions being made that are not wise.</p>
        <p>Q. How has the proliferation of hedge funds affected the bankruptcy business?</p>
        <p>A. I think that it's likely there will be a few more situations like Amaranth. There are so many hedge funds that as those situations come to light, the pools of capital will become a bit more cautious about investing in risky situations. Which would mean that the portfolio companies that were being bailed out at these extremely high-leverage ratios will not be able to be bailed out at those extremely high ratios anymore. Some of them will have to go into bankruptcy and undergo a very painful right-sizing of their business and their capital structure.</p>
        <p>Q. How has the new bankruptcy code changed the Chapter 11 process?</p>
        <p>A. One of the much-talked-about provisions was a prohibition, except under very strict conditions, of KERPs -- key employee retention programs, what we used to call golden parachutes. Reasonable people can debate this as a matter of social policy and business sense, but it is not an easy job to run a troubled or bankrupt company. So to the extent a company has an opportunity to prepare for bankruptcy, what you need to do is plan to have the appropriate people assured, or reassured, that they should stay there and help rather than doing what's best for their families by getting out while the getting is good. That's significantly more difficult now under the new program.</p>
        <p>Q. What will you do until the bankruptcy wave hits?</p>
        <p>A. I personally am enjoying a much more relaxed schedule. I'm speaking at symposia and catching up on scholarship, which I just did not have time to do in the last 14 to 16 months. On a firmwide basis, our group is underutilized and, perhaps counterintuitively, we are actively seeking to expand. Skadden has the luxury of being able to plan and to invest, so we are trying to get terrific lawyers on board and get them trained. We're running internal seminars on things to think about from a restructuring and bankruptcy perspective. This is really a good thing -- because when the onslaught comes, there's not a lot of time to think.</p>
        <p>LEGAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
