<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Money Binge</title>
    <meta content="04money" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="DealBook" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/business/04money.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838030"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Institutional Investors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04EED61F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1070" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Money Binge</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Money Binge</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Multitrillion-dollar infusion of money into private equity and hedge funds is remaking deal economy and corporate America, creating buyout boom not seen since 1980s; much of capital for these transactions is flowing from institutional investors and pension funds, which have pulled out of stock market in search of higher returns; some recent transactions discussed; photo (special section, DealBook) (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LESS than a decade ago, Stephen A. Schwarzman, the chairman of the Blackstone Group, used to spend his days flying from city to city to drum up money for his private equity funds. ''If I could raise $10 million, that was a good day,'' he recalled recently.</p>
        <p>How times have changed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cheap debt and big investors clamoring for a cut of the action are fueling a record buyout boom.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LESS than a decade ago, Stephen A. Schwarzman, the chairman of the Blackstone Group, used to spend his days flying from city to city to drum up money for his private equity funds. ''If I could raise $10 million, that was a good day,'' he recalled recently.</p>
        <p>How times have changed.</p>
        <p>''Now, someone who doesn't know you will just come into our office and say, 'I'd like to give you $200 million,' '' Mr. Schwarzman told a conference in January.</p>
        <p>The shift shows partly how Blackstone has grown in size and reputation. Mr. Schwarzman co-founded the firm in 1985 with $400,000; it now manages more than $78 billion and is planning to go public.</p>
        <p>But the change also reflects the deluge of money that has washed over private equity and hedge funds in recent years. The multitrillion-dollar infusion is remaking the deal economy and corporate America, creating a buyout boom not seen since the 1980s, when Michael R. Milken helped takeover artists finance deal after deal with seemingly unlimited cash.</p>
        <p>But where is this money storm coming from? How long will it last?</p>
        <p>Mr. Schwarzman, whose firm recently closed a $39 billion takeover of Equity Office Properties Trust, said at the conference: ''You look at these numbers, and they are stunning. It's like an out-of-body experience.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Milken, in a rare interview, recently compared the latest buyout wave with the one he helped set off. ''You have substantially more debt than you did 20 years ago,'' he said. He noted, however, that debt is far cheaper and may be less risky this time around because interest rates are so much lower.</p>
        <p>Nine of the 10 largest leveraged buyouts in history have been announced in the last year and a half. These include the proposed $45 billion buyout of the Texas energy giant TXU; the $33 billion acquisition of the hospital operator HCA; and the proposal on Monday of a $29 billion acquisition of the payment processor First Data.</p>
        <p>Much of the capital for these transactions is flowing from institutional investors and pension funds, which have pulled money out of the stock market in search of higher returns. Just as important, though, are the banks that are willing to lend huge sums on friendly terms. These lenders have allowed buyers to leverage their investments with cheap debt to new levels. Hoping to win lucrative business from private equity firms, banks are taking extraordinary steps. Besides loans, some banks are agreeing to provide ''equity bridges'' -- contributions toward the equity portion of a deal -- akin to a mortgage lender covering part of a down payment. The banks' appetite for risk shows little sign of fading, but if it did, the private equity deal machine would lose an important fuel source.</p>
        <p>If there is anyone to thank -- or blame -- for the free-flowing credit, it is Alan Greenspan, the former chairman of the Federal Reserve, who brought interest rates to near-record lows, allowing borrowings to hit record highs. ''Low risk-free, long-term rates worldwide seem to be one factor driving investors to reach for higher returns,'' Mr. Greenspan said in 2005, when he was chairman. ''The search for yield is particularly manifest in the massive inflows of funds to private equity firms and hedge funds.''</p>
        <p>All that low-cost credit has allowed private equity firms to leverage their investments, amplifying their buying power to some $1.5 trillion, according to Morgan Stanley. Blue-chip companies that once seemed out of reach are now relatively easy targets for a take-private transaction.</p>
        <p>In an odd twist, all the money going to private equity has helped buoy shares of public companies. Nearly every day seems to bring another rumor of a multibillion-dollar buyout opportunity, prompting investors to pile into shares of companies they expect to be acquired.</p>
        <p>The speculative investing creates another potential obstacle to the private equity juggernaut because it forces buyout firms to pay even more for companies they take private, which could end up crimping their returns.</p>
        <p>The top buyout firms appear to be producing remarkable profits.</p>
        <p>When Blackstone filed for its initial public offering two weeks ago, it disclosed a 30.8 percent annual rate of return on its private equity funds since 1987, far outpacing the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index during the same period. (After Blackstone took its fees, the returns were 22.8 percent, much higher than the S.&amp; P., which was about 11.1 percent.)</p>
        <p>Some have suggested that the above-market returns enjoyed by Blackstone and other firms are mostly a result of leverage -- which can supercharge returns but only by adding risk -- as opposed to smart investing by fund managers.</p>
        <p>Steven Kaplan, a professor of entrepreneurship and finance at the University of Chicago, has estimated that if similar leverage were applied to investments in the S.&amp; P. 500 index, the returns would exceed those of private equity.</p>
        <p>Whatever the reason for their success, these glittering returns are a major reason investors have reallocated more of their money into the industry. Consider one of the larger pension funds, the Employee Retirement System of Texas, which manages $23 billion of state workers' retirement plans. It has put 7 percent to 8 percent of its funds into private equity investments to help balance its budget.</p>
        <p>In some cases, there is a whiff of desperation in pension funds' leap into private equity. Many funds have fallen behind on their future obligations to workers, so they are plowing money into higher-risk assets to try to close the gap. More than 51 of 64 state pension plans were underfinanced last year, compared with about 25 in 2000, according to a recent report by Wilshire Associates.</p>
        <p>Less often acknowledged in the recent deal boom is the role of hedge funds, which have also been raising huge sums from institutional investors and rich individuals. In search of higher returns, these funds have been increasingly buying stakes in companies and then pressuring them to sell themselves, so they can pocket the premium when a buyer emerges.</p>
        <p>The result is more companies on the auction block, ripe for acquisition by private equity investors.</p>
        <p>With so many investors jumping into the private equity game, some are wondering if the buyout business's best days might be over.</p>
        <p>''It's hard to imagine it can get better than it is,'' Mr. Schwarzman said to the audience at Wharton School of the University of Pennsylvania in January. ''We're at maximum advantage in all probability right around now.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
