<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Asia's Automakers Show Sizable March Sales Gains</title>
    <meta content="04sales" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070405T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838001"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ward's Auto Info Bank</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Daimlerchrysler Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Toyota Motor Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Honda Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hyundai Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bunkley, Nick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DEFD71F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="734" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Asia's Automakers Show Sizable March Sales Gains</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICK BUNKLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bunkley, Nick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ward AutoInfoBank figures show that dealership sales declined at General Motors, Ford Motor and Chrysler division of DaimlerChrysler, even though all three said they would cut back on deliveries to rental car companies to focus on more profitable sales to individual consumers and were offering some of largest discounts in months; Toyota sales increased 7.7 percent, to record 242,675 vehicles; Honda and Hyundai both set March records for sales; Toyota took 15.7 percent of US vehicle market, up from 14.2 percent year ago; GM's share fell to 22.2 percent, from 23.3 percent, while Ford's declined to 16 percent, from 17.8 percent; Detroit companies held 51.6 percent of market, while Asian brands accounted for total of 41.9 percent; charts; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Detroit's automakers stumbled in March while their Asian competitors took a sizable leap forward.</p>
        <p>Figures released yesterday showed that dealership sales declined at General Motors, Ford Motor and the Chrysler division of DaimlerChrysler, even though all three said they would cut back on deliveries to rental car companies to focus on more profitable sales to individual consumers and were offering some of the largest discounts in months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Detroit's automakers stumbled in March while their Asian competitors took a sizable leap forward.</p>
        <p>Figures released yesterday showed that dealership sales declined at General Motors, Ford Motor and the Chrysler division of DaimlerChrysler, even though all three said they would cut back on deliveries to rental car companies to focus on more profitable sales to individual consumers and were offering some of the largest discounts in months.</p>
        <p>Toyota's sales, meanwhile, increased 7.7 percent, to a record of 242,675 vehicles, according to Ward's AutoInfoBank. The Toyota Prius, a hybrid car once viewed as a niche product, was one of the top-selling models over all last month as its sales more than doubled.</p>
        <p>Honda and Hyundai both set March records for sales.</p>
        <p>''The import brands are winning because they're more competitive,'' said Ron Pinelli, president of the Autodata Corporation, an industry statistics firm in Woodcliff Lake, N.J. ''The products that the import brands have are just the ones that are hitting a chord with Americans right now. The domestic makers, the reason their sales are down is they're still dependent on their trucks.''</p>
        <p>Over all, vehicle sales were down 3 percent from last March, which was the industry's peak month in 2006.</p>
        <p>Toyota took 15.7 percent of the United States vehicle market in March, up from 14.2 percent a year ago, and ahead of DaimlerChrysler's 13.4 percent, Autodata's figures show. G.M.'s share fell to 22.2 percent, from 23.3 percent, while Ford's declined the most, to 16 percent, from 17.8 percent.</p>
        <p>Together, the Detroit companies held 51.6 percent of the market, one of their worst showings ever, while the Asian brands accounted for a total of 41.9 percent.</p>
        <p>The Detroit automakers expect lower sales nearly every month this year, compared with the month a year earlier, largely because of their plans to cut deliveries to rental car companies. In January and February, however, they still managed to increase sales at dealerships, even though overall totals were down.</p>
        <p>But in March, G.M. said its dealership sales fell 6.2 percent, and Ford's declined 10 percent. Chrysler executives said retail sales were lower, but would not give a specific number.</p>
        <p>Those decreases occurred despite higher discounts aimed at drawing in shoppers. Chrysler discounted its vehicles an average of $4,351 in March, when the company offered truck buyers a free upgrade to its more powerful Hemi engine, according to Edmunds.com, a Web site that gives car-buying advice to consumers. Ford and G.M. each discounted their vehicles about $3,000, roughly three times as much as Toyota and Honda.</p>
        <p>''The problem is they're running out of options for what to do with incentives,'' said Alex Rosten, Edmunds.com's manager of pricing and market analysis. ''Rebates have lost their luster, and everybody's tightening their lending requirements.''</p>
        <p>Asian automakers are also using heavy discounts to sell some of their larger vehicles, but they are having more success than the Detroit companies.</p>
        <p>''The dealers are blowing these things out at a few hundred dollars over invoice,'' Mr. Pinelli said. ''But you're not going to blow them out unless American consumers want the product.''</p>
        <p>Ford's chief sales analyst, George Pipas, said the company would have done better in March if dealers had had more F-series pickups available. He said Ford, which has cut F-series production several times because of lower demand, might need to increase output later this year to avoid missing out on possible sales.</p>
        <p>''This is a category that has become intensely competitive,'' Mr. Pipas said in a conference call with reporters and analysts yesterday afternoon.</p>
        <p>A reason for the competition is the recent introduction of new trucks by General Motors and Toyota. Toyota officials said yesterday that they were pleased with the first two months of sales for their truck, the Tundra, although they conceded that most buyers had been people who already owned a Toyota rather than converts from a Detroit brand.</p>
        <p>G.M.'s sales analyst, Paul Ballew, said, ''We're not seeing a big impact from the Tundra.''</p>
        <p>Chrysler officials said the company's sales had been affected by uncertainty surrounding its future. Its parent, DaimlerChrysler of Germany, said in February that it would consider selling Chrysler, and board members are expected to receive a barrage of questions from shareholders about a sale at the company's annual meeting in Berlin today.</p>
        <p>A Chrysler spokesman, Jason Vines, said most consumers who live outside of Germany and the Detroit area ''wouldn't know anything about it.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 5, 2007, Thursday  A chart yesterday on auto sales in March gave incorrect rankings on "How Automakers Fared." A corrected chart appears below.</p>
        <p>DAIMLERCHRYSLER  March 2007 Sales: 228,047  Adjusted Change*: - 7.5%  Market Share: 14.9%</p>
        <p>FORD  March 2007 Sales: 255,444  Adjusted Change*: -13.5  Market Share: 16.7</p>
        <p>GENERAL MOTORS  March 2007 Sales: 345,668  Adjusted Change*: - 7.4  Market Share: 22.5</p>
        <p>HONDA  March 2007 Sales: 143,392  Adjusted Change*: + 7.4  Market Share: 9.3</p>
        <p>HYUNDAI  March 2007 Sales: 41,984  Adjusted Change*: - 3.1  Market Share: 2.7</p>
        <p>NISSAN  March 2007 Sales: 111,141  Adjusted Change*: + 3.9  Market Share: 7.2</p>
        <p>TOYOTA  March 2007 Sales: 242,675  Adjusted Change*: + 7.7  Market Share: 15.8</p>
        <p>Sales for DaimlerChrysler include Mercedes; sales for Ford include Volvo and Land Rover; sales for General Motors include Saab.</p>
        <p>*Based on average daily sales adjusted for any differences in the number of selling days in a month.</p>
        <p>(Source by Ward's AutoInfoBank)</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 5, 2007, Thursday  A chart in Business Day yesterday with an article about auto sales in March gave incorrect rankings in the ''How Automakers Fared'' section. A corrected chart is on Page C2 today. The chart also misidentified the make and model of a car shown as the ''Biggest Gainer.'' It was a Toyota Prius, not a Chevrolet Impala.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 5, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>A chart yesterday on auto sales in March gave incorrect rankings on "How Automakers Fared." A corrected chart appears below.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;DAIMLERCHRYSLER</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;March 2007 Sales: 228,047</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;Adjusted Change*: - 7.5%</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;Market Share: 14.9%</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;FORD</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;March 2007 Sales: 255,444</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;Adjusted Change*: -13.5</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;Market Share: 16.7</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;GENERAL MOTORS</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;March 2007 Sales: 345,668</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;Adjusted Change*: - 7.4</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;Market Share: 22.5</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;HONDA</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;March 2007 Sales: 143,392</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;Adjusted Change*: + 7.4</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;Market Share: 9.3</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;HYUNDAI</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;March 2007 Sales: 41,984</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;Adjusted Change*: - 3.1</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;Market Share: 2.7</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;NISSAN</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;March 2007 Sales: 111,141</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;Adjusted Change*: + 3.9</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;Market Share: 7.2</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;TOYOTA</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;March 2007 Sales: 242,675</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;Adjusted Change*: + 7.7</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;Market Share: 15.8</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;Sales for DaimlerChrysler include Mercedes; sales for Ford include Volvo and Land Rover; sales for General Motors include Saab.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;*Based on average daily sales adjusted for any differences in the number of selling days in a month.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;(Source by Ward's AutoInfoBank)</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>Correction: April 5, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>A chart in Business Day yesterday with an article about auto sales in March gave incorrect rankings in the ''How Automakers Fared'' section. A corrected chart is on Page C2 today. The chart also misidentified the make and model of a car shown as the ''Biggest Gainer.'' It was a Toyota Prius, not a Chevrolet Impala.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
