<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A $16 Billion Bid for Australian Retailer</title>
    <meta content="04shop" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/business/worldbusiness/04shop.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838002"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wesfarmers Ltd</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Coles (Retail Chain)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Macquarie Bank</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pacific Equity Partners</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Permira</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, Tim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Australia</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Wesfarmers Ltd</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05EED71F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="592" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A $16 Billion Bid for Australian Retailer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A $16 Billion Bid for Australian Retailer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM JOHNSTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnston, Tim</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, April 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Consortium of companies led by Wesfarmers, diversified business group, bids for retailer Coles on terms that value it at $16 billion, which would be largest takeover attempt in Australia; other members of consortium include Macquarie Bank, Pacific Equity Partners and Permira; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A consortium of companies offered on Tuesday to buy the troubled retailer Coles on terms that value it at $16 billion, which would be the largest takeover attempt in Australia.</p>
        <p>The bidding consortium, led by Wesfarmers, a diversified business group, bought an 11.3 percent stake in Coles on Monday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A consortium of companies offered to buy the troubled retailer Coles, which would be the largest takeover attempt in Australia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A consortium of companies offered on Tuesday to buy the troubled retailer Coles on terms that value it at $16 billion, which would be the largest takeover attempt in Australia.</p>
        <p>The bidding consortium, led by Wesfarmers, a diversified business group, bought an 11.3 percent stake in Coles on Monday.</p>
        <p>Coles, the second-largest retailer in Australia after Woolworths, put itself up for sale in February after announcing disappointing half-year results and cutting its earnings forecast for the year by 10 percent.</p>
        <p>''We believe the acquisition of Coles would be a very positive step for the shareholders of both companies,'' Richard Goyder, managing director of Wesfarmers, said Tuesday in a filing with the Australian Securities Exchange.</p>
        <p>The Wesfarmers bid of 16.47 Australian dollars a share ($13.38) for the rest of Coles is a small premium over the Monday closing share price of 16.11 Australian dollars.</p>
        <p>Many analysts have valued the company's shares at 15.90 Australian dollars to 16 dollars a share, but some said that the company could be worth up to 21 dollars a share if it were better managed.</p>
        <p>''The right management could lift the share price by 30 percent,'' said Scott Marshall of Shaw Stockbroking in Sydney.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Wesfarmers, Keith Kessell, said that the company bought some of its stake Monday on an escalator basis, which means that if the bid price rises, Wesfarmers will pay extra for some of shares it has already secured.</p>
        <p>The other members of the consortium include Macquarie Bank, based in Sydney; Pacific Equity Partners, an Australasian private equity firm; and Permira, a European private equity company that recently bought a number of Spanish retailers.</p>
        <p>Few analysts doubt that Coles has substantial potential for improvement. Last year, the group sold its underperforming Myer department store unit to the private equity firm Texas Pacific Group for 1.4 billion Australian dollars ($1.13 billion). Last week, Myer announced an 84 percent increase in half-year earnings.</p>
        <p>''Prospective buyers will look at Myer as reassurance that good and focused management ought to be able to add substantial value to businesses that have carried the dead weight of a distant and bloated bureaucracy'' at Coles, said Stephen Bartholomeusz, a columnist for The Age, a Melbourne newspaper.</p>
        <p>Wesfarmers already has retail experience. It owns Bunnings, the largest chain of home improvement shops in Australia, along with diversified assets in a range of industries including coal, insurance and gas.</p>
        <p>Wesfarmers, based in Perth, told the securities exchange Tuesday that it intended to hold about 50 percent of Coles's food, liquor and general merchandise businesses and to completely take over the Officeworks and Target divisions, which sell office supplies and home wares, respectively.</p>
        <p>Coles has been a frequent takeover target. A private equity consortium led by Kohlberg Kravis Roberts made two unsuccessful bids last year. The Coles board rejected the last bid in October, saying that the bid of 15.25 Australian dollars a share undervalued the company.</p>
        <p>This time, Coles has tried to control the sales process. To encourage more participants in the auction, and therefore a better price, the company said it would consider breaking up the group. It has also tried to limit the number of private equity participants in any one bid.</p>
        <p>But Wesfarmers' new stake is likely to put off other potential bidders, because any other buyer would have to negotiate with the Wesfarmers consortium.</p>
        <p>Although there have been no formal declarations of interest, the Australian media have speculated that other retail groups like Tesco of Britain and Carrefour of France might also consider a bid.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
