<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Will a Hedge Fund Become the Next Goldman Sachs?</title>
    <meta content="04citadel" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="DealBook" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/business/04citadel.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838026"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="STRATEGIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Citadel Investment Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Goldman Sachs Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Griffin, Kenneth C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Subprime Lending</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Citadel Investment Group</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EFD61F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1465" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Will a Hedge Fund Become the Next Goldman Sachs?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Will a Hedge Fund Become the Next Goldman Sachs?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNY ANDERSON</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Citadel Investment Group, one of most powerful and fastest-growing companies in hedge fund business, with more than $13.5 billion of capital, has elements of investment bank such as Goldman Sachs disguised as hedge fund, minus investment bankers; Citadel has stock loan department and has become one of largest options market makers in industry besides trading for itself; Citadel chief executive Kenneth C Griffin comments; photos (special section, DealBook) (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN 1988, a very young-looking 19-year-old Harvard student sneaked past the receptionist at the Boston office of Merrill Lynch, found the manager in charge of convertible bonds and struck up a conversation about the technical aspects of valuing those bonds.</p>
        <p>A few weeks and some discussions later, the student, Kenneth C. Griffin, asked Terrence J. O'Connor, the convertibles expert, to open an institutional trading account with $100,000 he had collected from his grandmother and his dentist, among others. At the time, the size of the average institutional account was $100 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Citadel Investment Group has become one of the most powerful and fastest-growing companies in the hedge fund business, with more than $13.5 billion of capital.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN 1988, a very young-looking 19-year-old Harvard student sneaked past the receptionist at the Boston office of Merrill Lynch, found the manager in charge of convertible bonds and struck up a conversation about the technical aspects of valuing those bonds.</p>
        <p>A few weeks and some discussions later, the student, Kenneth C. Griffin, asked Terrence J. O'Connor, the convertibles expert, to open an institutional trading account with $100,000 he had collected from his grandmother and his dentist, among others. At the time, the size of the average institutional account was $100 million.</p>
        <p>''My boss thought I was crazy,'' recalled Mr. O'Connor, who nevertheless persuaded his boss to let him open the account.</p>
        <p>That gamble doesn't look so crazy today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Griffin is the chief executive of Citadel Investment Group, one of the most powerful and fastest-growing companies in the hedge fund business, with more than $13.5 billion of capital. One of its two flagship funds, Citadel Kensington, had an average annual rate of return of 20.34 percent from 1998 through 2006 -- making it among the best-performing funds over time. Success, however, has forced Citadel to face the fact that it straddles two different worlds: the freewheeling world of hedge funds and the intensely scrutinized world of grown-up financial service companies with pesky shareholders and layers of conflicts of interest.</p>
        <p>It is a challenge faced by other big alternative investment companies, like the Blackstone Group, which recently filed plans for a public offering.</p>
        <p>If Goldman Sachs is sometimes accused of being a hedge fund masked as an investment bank, Citadel has elements of an investment bank disguised as a hedge fund, minus the investment bankers.</p>
        <p>Besides trading for itself, Citadel has a stock loan department and has become one of the largest options market makers in the industry.</p>
        <p>It runs two reinsurance companies and recently disclosed that it would provide administration services to other hedge funds, a lucrative business that is usually offered for hedge funds, and not by them.</p>
        <p>In December, a Citadel unit raised $500 million in debt, a groundbreaking move for a hedge fund that further enhances its independence from Wall Street.</p>
        <p>Mr. Griffin has ''institutionalized much of his business along the lines of an investment bank,'' said Richard S. Fuld Jr., the chairman and chief executive of Lehman Brothers, which does extensive business with Citadel. ''He's certainly involved in some of the same activities that a hedge fund is, but he's built more than that. He also acts as a broker-dealer and creates liquidity for investors. We have found many good ways to work together.''</p>
        <p>At 38, Mr. Griffin is straight from hedge fund central casting, with a lanky six-foot frame, steely blue eyes and an affection for Ferraris and modern art. (He recently paid $80 million for Jasper Johns's ''False Start.'') Born in Daytona Beach, Fla., he lived in Texas and Wisconsin as a child, and returned to Boca Raton for middle school and high school. His father was a project manager for General Electric.</p>
        <p>His wife is Anne Dias, a multilingual Harvard Business School graduate who runs Aragon Global Management, a smaller, value-focused hedge fund. Their wedding took place in the gardens of Versailles. The couple recently donated $19 million to the Art Institute of Chicago, where part of the Renzo Piano-designed addition will be named the Kenneth and Anne Griffin Court.</p>
        <p>Mr. Griffin has said that he and his wife enjoyed one of their first dates at the museum. ''For us, our relationship with this great, encyclopedic museum can be described as 'love at first sight,' '' he said.</p>
        <p>Art and love aside, Mr. Griffin has not made his fortune with charm and grace. Interviews with more than a dozen people who have invested with or worked beside or for Mr. Griffin paint a similar picture: arrogant, unapologetic and extremely smart.</p>
        <p>''Is Ken the nicest boss in the world?'' asked Mark W. Yusko, a former chief investment officer at the University of North Carolina's endowment fund, and now the president of Morgan Creek Capital Management, an investment advisory firm. ''He won't win that award. But he's a great guy to work for because if you buy into the philosophy and the process and the system, you will be part of a great organization.''</p>
        <p>Like most great investors, Mr. Griffin seeks disruptions in normal patterns to make money. When Enron collapsed, he sent a team around the country to interview hundreds of energy traders, meteorologists and quantitative researchers. He hired seven to start an energy trading business.</p>
        <p>When Amaranth, the $9.5 billion hedge fund, blew up on bad natural-gas bets last summer, Citadel teamed up with J. P. Morgan to buy the book of energy trades. Citadel made a killing on the transaction, investors say. Now, as the market for subprime mortgages has imploded, Citadel has been on a shopping spree, acquiring assets and a portfolio of loans from ResMae, a bankrupt mortgage originator; and bought a 4.5 percent stake in Accredited Home Lenders, a troubled mortgage company.</p>
        <p>''When everyone is running away, he is adjusting his portfolio and buying more,'' said Mr. Yusko, a longtime investor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Griffin declined to comment for this article.</p>
        <p>His beginnings are the stuff of hedge fund legend. Mr. Griffin started trading options as a Harvard freshman. To get price feeds, he had a satellite dish installed on the side of Cabot House dormitory.</p>
        <p>While it is widely thought that Mr. Griffin did not graduate from Harvard, he in fact did, a year early with an economics degree.</p>
        <p>Frank Meyer, then the head of Glenwood Investment Corporation, an alternative investment group in Chicago, met Mr. Griffin, was impressed and gave him $1 million to trade. Mr. Griffin, just old enough to drink legally, produced returns of 70 percent trading convertible bonds. In November 1990, he opened Citadel with $4.6 million. After three blowout years, the convertible bond market crashed, his returns cratered and investors pulled out a lot of their money. At an unusually young age, Mr. Griffin learned an important lesson: Liquidity -- access to money to be able to make trades -- is critical, and in times of distress, is often unavailable.</p>
        <p>During the 1990s, Mr. Griffin instituted strict lockups, meaning that his investors had to trust him with their money for longer periods. The last lockups were put in place less than a month before Long-Term Capital Management melted down in 1998, causing the Federal Reserve to organize a Wall Street bailout of the hedge fund. That year, the other Citadel flagship fund, Citadel Wellington, had a return of more than 30 percent, partly because Mr. Griffin had the capital to play in a confused  market.</p>
        <p>After the financial crises of 1998, Mr. Griffin accelerated a process already under way: cutting Wall Street out at every possible turn. That meant securing sources of money through lockups, thinking about how to tap the public markets and starting businesses like stock lending.</p>
        <p>Mr. Griffin's funds grew as he posted big-number returns: Citadel Wellington had a gain of more than 45 percent in 1999 and about 53 percent in 2000.</p>
        <p>By 2006, reflecting both the explosive growth of hedge funds over all as well as its own mediocre returns in 2005, Citadel was the 11th-largest fund with $12 billion. Forbes listed Mr. Griffin as the 204th-richest American in 2006, with $1.7 billion.</p>
        <p>Success has not come without blips. Rush Simonson, a mentor and friend, sued Mr. Griffin in 2006, accusing him of stealing a business plan the two had put together. He later dropped his suit. Mr. Simonson's lawyer, Edward A. Wallace, declined to comment. Citadel helped finance a group of investors, including the Republican lobbyist Jack Abramoff, in the purchase of SunCruz Casinos, a fleet of gambling boats.</p>
        <p>Mr. Griffin has not been involved in the day-to-day trading for years; instead, he manages the more than 1,000 employees of Citadel. But he does get involved with decisions in each of the firm's seven businesses. For example, in 2005, when the convertible arbitrage world was tanking, he came down to the desk and took over.</p>
        <p>As assets continue to flood the industry, and as Citadel continues to grow, returns will be harder to come by. Mr. Griffin conceded that point in a 2005 interview with the Harvard College Investment Magazine.</p>
        <p>''I don't think any industry has attracted as much capital over such a short period of time throughout history,'' he told the magazine. ''With that much capital flowing into the business, it is reasonable to conclude that the prospect for better than market returns going forward is bleak.''</p>
        <p>Of course, he aims to be the exception.</p>
        <p>''He's just as intense today as he was 20 years ago,'' said Mr. O'Connor, now a managing director at Merrill Lynch. ''He still wants to be the best.''</p>
        <p>STRATEGIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
