<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pettitte Can Still Hear Cheers From 2003</title>
    <meta content="04yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/sports/baseball/04yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838015"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Devil Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pettitte, Andy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E2D61F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pettitte Can Still Hear Cheers From 2003</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Yankees’ Pettitte Can Still Hear Cheers From 2003</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There have been no World Series games in the Bronx since Oct. 25, 2003, and no more games there for the losing pitcher that night, Andy Pettitte.</p>
        <p>It was mostly quiet then, the crowd of 55,773 not quite believing that the mighty Yankees bats could manage no runs against the Florida Marlins' Josh Beckett in Game 6. If there was a hero in pinstripes, it was Pettitte, allowing one earned run over seven sturdy innings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After three years in Houston  and another trip to the World Series  Andy Pettitte resumes his Yankees career Thursday against the Tampa Bay Devil Rays.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There have been no World Series games in the Bronx since Oct. 25, 2003, and no more games there for the losing pitcher that night, Andy Pettitte.</p>
        <p>It was mostly quiet then, the crowd of 55,773 not quite believing that the mighty Yankees bats could manage no runs against the Florida Marlins' Josh Beckett in Game 6. If there was a hero in pinstripes, it was Pettitte, allowing one earned run over seven sturdy innings.</p>
        <p>''I really wanted that one bad because I did so bad in the '01 World Series,'' Pettitte said Monday. ''Boy, I wanted that one bad. And I was proud of the way I pitched. I hated that I went out on a loss, but it was a good game, and that was a special moment for me.''</p>
        <p>Pettitte lost twice to Arizona in 2001, missing a chance to clinch the Series in Game 6 when he accidentally telegraphed his cutter to Diamondbacks hitters. His earned run average in two starts against Arizona was 10.00; two years later against the Marlins, it was 0.57.</p>
        <p>The fans let Pettitte know how much they appreciated it. On an otherwise dreary night, they saluted Pettitte, who was a free agent to be.</p>
        <p>''I don't get caught up in a whole lot,'' Pettitte said, ''but the crowd was chanting my name the whole last inning I was out there. I remember that. That was a special part of it for me.''</p>
        <p>Pettitte said it reminded him of the chants for Paul O'Neill during the fifth game of the 2001 World Series, the last home game of O'Neill's career. O'Neill was retiring; Pettitte was simply changing his baseball address, though no one knew it at the time.</p>
        <p>After three years in Houston -- and one more trip to the World Series -- Pettitte resumes his Yankees career today, weather permitting, against the Tampa Bay Devil Rays. The Yankees won their opener against Tampa Bay on Monday, 9-5, and Pettitte was introduced to thunderous applause from the crowd before the game. The reaction when he takes the mound should be just as intense.</p>
        <p>''I think the fans are going to let him know how much we've missed him and they've missed him,'' Manager Joe Torre said.</p>
        <p>''When they look at Andy Pettitte, they associate him with the championships that we've had here in recent years. I know he's excited to be back, and his family is very, very excited to be back. It's great. He's coming back here, basically, as a senior citizen, to sort of look after this pitching staff along with Mike Mussina.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees did not sign Pettitte for sentiment; if they made moves for that reason, they would have guaranteed a spot to Bernie Williams. They signed Pettitte because he pitched well last season -- he was 7-4 with a 2.80 E.R.A. after the All-Star Game break -- and because they were leery of chasing less-proven pitchers for longer-term deals.</p>
        <p>Pettitte signed a one-year contract for $16 million, with a player option for the same amount in 2008. Asked Monday how many bullets he had left, with his 35th birthday coming June 15, Pettitte laughed.</p>
        <p>''Oh, man, I don't know,'' he said. ''I think I've got plenty enough to get me through this year, and that's all I'm worried about. We'll re-evaluate the situation. But everything feels great right now.''</p>
        <p>Over and over Monday, Pettitte was asked if he would be excited. He answered the questions politely and affirmatively, insisting he was ready to go.</p>
        <p>But exactly how ready is unknown. Pettitte's last spring training game was March 17, just before he injured his back while lifting weights.</p>
        <p>While Pettitte recovered, Torre considered altering his schedule so that Pettitte could start opening day over Carl Pavano. Instead, Pettitte worked a four-inning, 66-pitch tune-up in a minor league game last Friday, giving him the regular four days off before his first turn.</p>
        <p>Torre said he was looking for only five innings today, but Pettitte would rather work longer.</p>
        <p>''I'm hoping I can go deeper than that,'' Pettitte said. ''We'll just see. Hopefully, the cold weather will help me keep my stamina. That and the intensity of the game, how the game's going, will dictate all that.''</p>
        <p>Before Monday's game, each player had a 2007 Yankees yearbook and game program placed in his locker. The program features a close-up shot of Pettitte, cap pulled low, staring straight ahead, the picture of focus.</p>
        <p>Pettitte has relied on that focus for years, though his reputation for October greatness is probably overstated. His winning percentage and E.R.A. are better in the regular season than in the postseason, and while his postseason numbers are strong (14-9, 4.08), he has not always been able to block out distractions.</p>
        <p>''There've been times, plenty of them, when I haven't been able to focus like I need to,'' Pettitte said. ''But hopefully, as quickly as possible, I can block out whatever emotions are there after I take the mound and be able to get in a good rhythm as quickly as I possibly can.''</p>
        <p>There are 161 games remaining until the postseason. But for Pettitte, the prodigal Yankee, the atmosphere could be nearly as electric.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
