<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Answering the Unanswerable: Tips for That First Interview</title>
    <meta content="04candidates" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="DealBook" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/business/04candidates.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838023"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OPENING BID"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Business Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">De La Merced, Michael J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Business Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Employment Agencies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Employment Agencies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Business Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Graduate Schools and Students</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EFD61F30F937A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="942" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Answering the Unanswerable: Tips for That First Interview</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Answering the Unanswerable: Tips for That First Interview</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL J. de la MERCED</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">De La Merced, Michael J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Five questions, culled from archives of business schools' career services offices, for business school graduates first job interview; drawings (special section, DealBook) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FEW investment-bank careers today begin like that of Michael Lewis, as he described it two decades ago in his book ''Liar's Poker'': a dinner with British royalty, ''wet scrambled eggs'' with a director of recruiting and a London job offer given sotto voce.</p>
        <p>Most graduate business school students today need to run a gantlet of interviews with recruiters, a process that has not gotten easier over the years. Officials at several business schools said they began preparing students for the recruiting method even before they stepped on campus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The focus for graduate business school students remains the interview, a 45-minute session with a recruiter that has been known to provoke a few anxiety attacks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FEW investment-bank careers today begin like that of Michael Lewis, as he described it two decades ago in his book ''Liar's Poker'': a dinner with British royalty, ''wet scrambled eggs'' with a director of recruiting and a London job offer given sotto voce.</p>
        <p>Most graduate business school students today need to run a gantlet of interviews with recruiters, a process that has not gotten easier over the years. Officials at several business schools said they began preparing students for the recruiting method even before they stepped on campus.</p>
        <p>Much of a business student's life is consumed with networking at cocktail parties, poring over the histories and specialties of the different banks and visiting scores of headquarters to observe the daily rituals of each firm. But the focus for students remains the interview, generally a 45-minute session with a recruiter that has been known to provoke a few anxiety attacks.</p>
        <p>Questions can be divided into two broad categories. One is technical: ''Organize these three companies by their betas,'' or ''Walk me through how you would value this company in a prospective strategic merger.''</p>
        <p>The other assesses personality. Maryellen Lamb, Wharton's senior associate director of M.B.A. career management, calls it ''the airport test.'' That is, would a banker feel comfortable spending hours in a departure lounge with the candidate?</p>
        <p>But at least a few questions are a little offbeat, as a few recruiters have begun asking creative questions once associated with, say, management consulting firms.</p>
        <p>All tend to put students on the spot, making them think on their feet and shaking them from memorized responses. ''Firms are constantly looking for their future leaders,'' said Pamela B. Mittman, assistant dean of career services at New York University's Stern School of Business.</p>
        <p>Here are five questions, culled from the archives of business schools' career services offices.</p>
        <p>How many gas stations are in the United States?</p>
        <p>A classic brainteaser. Virtually no recruiter expects a student to have the correct answer, said Jackie Wilbur, the director of the M.B.A. career development office at the Sloan School of Management at M.I.T. The recruiters probably do not know the answer themselves.</p>
        <p>The point is to guide a recruiter through a student's thought process. The worst way to answer the question? Sit back and deliver an answer like ''9'' without sharing your deliberations.</p>
        <p>''They want to be the smartest kid around and always have the right answer,'' Ms. Wilbur said.</p>
        <p>If you could stack up enough pennies to reach the top of the Empire State Building, could you fit them all into a room?</p>
        <p>Another brainteaser. Ms. Mittman of New York University said that with that type of question, students should pause for a second and be unafraid to respond with questions of their own. An important step, she said, was to gauge the recruiter's responses to the questions and react accordingly. Those skills would prove equally important when walking a client through a deal pitch.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Mittman said that investment bankers tend to avoid gimmicky questions, and instead ask questions like, ''If you had the option to purchase an asset worth x or y with equal probability, how much would you pay for each asset, and which valuation model would you use?''</p>
        <p>What's the most controversial belief you hold?</p>
        <p>This is a way to get fresh insight into a candidate's personality. Recruiters already have an applicant's résumé and transcripts. They know students have polished answers about their life experiences and expectations to gleaming sound bites.</p>
        <p>But some students have managed to transform their responses into thoughtful, comprehensive answers that address multiple concerns at once. Ms. Lamb said that a recruiter had told her of one student who said she believed that car safety devices were unnecessary. The student, a former engineer, then walked the interviewer through all the aspects of her argument, from the mechanics of cars to the financial costs to the sociological and legal ramifications.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, the student argued, dropping seat belts would put more responsibility on a driver but would decrease energy use and the price of cars. Ms. Lamb said the recruiter was impressed with the answer.</p>
        <p>But such questions are rare, Ms. Lamb said. ''I really think a lot of banks and bankers are reluctant to ask questions that are that thought-provoking,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Are you interviewing outside of investment banking?</p>
        <p>Though a seemingly innocuous inquiry, the question has a specific purpose, Ms. Lamb said: ''They're looking to see if you have the confidence to get an investment banking job.''</p>
        <p>So an admission that a candidate is also applying to, say, management consulting, may broadcast loud and clear that he or she is unsure of getting in -- potentially a kiss of death.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Lamb said some alternatives may be acceptable. Students who are applying to the mergers-and-acquisitions practices of a technology company could still signal their commitment to a banking job.</p>
        <p>How much would you pay to play the coin-toss game?</p>
        <p>Aimed at applicants for sales and trading desks, the question gauges how much risk students can stomach. It also tests how quickly students make snap decisions, the sort that professionals make hundreds of times a day. ''It really gets at the culture of sales and trading,'' Ms. Wilbur said.</p>
        <p>An ideal way to prepare for this kind of quick-decision question is to brush up on analytical and math skills, she said.</p>
        <p>Students should think through beforehand what their risk appetite is. And they should consult alumni and study each firm's culture. The worst response is to take a highly aggressive position with a conservative trading desk, or vice versa.</p>
        <p>OPENING BID</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
