<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Pangs of Two Becoming One</title>
    <meta content="28online" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/technology/28online.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843357"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WHAT'S ONLINE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Personal Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Google Inc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">DoubleClick Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E6D9123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="657" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Pangs of Two Becoming One</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Pangs of Two Becoming One</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Dan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GOOGLE'S $3.1 billion deal for the online advertising firm DoubleClick could put the company at odds with itself.</p>
        <p>Internal conflicts often happen in finance, when investment banks find themselves advising both sides in a merger. And it happens in agribusiness, energy and other industries where giant companies with fingers in many pies are both buyers and sellers of the same commodity. But it is particularly common in technology and media.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Google’s $3.1 billion deal for the online advertising firm DoubleClick could put the company at odds with itself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GOOGLE'S $3.1 billion deal for the online advertising firm DoubleClick could put the company at odds with itself.</p>
        <p>Internal conflicts often happen in finance, when investment banks find themselves advising both sides in a merger. And it happens in agribusiness, energy and other industries where giant companies with fingers in many pies are both buyers and sellers of the same commodity. But it is particularly common in technology and media.</p>
        <p>The DoubleClick deal has prompted Microsoft and I.B.M. and others to ask the Federal Trade Commission to investigate the deal on antitrust grounds. And privacy advocates worry that Google will not live up to its pledge to keep the customer data collected by DoubleClick out of the hands of Google's search managers.</p>
        <p>But the thorniest conflicts could arise from DoubleClick's Performics division.</p>
        <p>Performics helps its clients get better position in search results. Essentially, it works to game the systems of Google, Yahoo and other search engines.</p>
        <p>''Google is treading in dangerous waters right now,'' writes Ross Dunn of WebProNews.com. Google's search results ''are supposed to be unbiased and highly relevant,'' but with Performics, ''Google is put into the conflicted position of trying to generate profits by providing result-oriented organic ranking services for its own 'unbiased' organic search results.''</p>
        <p>The worry, in other words, is that Google's search results could be compromised by operating a division with an interest in skewing those results in favor of clients.</p>
        <p>This seems unlikely. Reliable search results are the core of Google's franchise. Industry-watchers, including Kevin Newcomb of SearchEngineWatch.com, tend to think Google will likely sell off part or all of Performics.</p>
        <p>That's an easy choice for the leading company in a growing industry. What about a struggling company in a deeply troubled industry? Warner Music is thought to be preparing to acquire Front Line Management, the nation's largest artist-management firm whose roster includes Aerosmith and Christina Aguilera.</p>
        <p>Traditionally, record labels and artist-managers negotiate with one another. Putting them under the same roof is a radical notion. If the deal goes through, it could ''offer a new economic model for the major record companies,'' Tim Arango of Fortune magazine wrote this week (money.cnn.com). The idea, he added, ''has its skeptics.''</p>
        <p>One of them is Bruce Houghton. ''Can two sides that have traditionally been adversaries live under one roof?'' he asked on Internet Financial News this week (internetfinancialnews.com). ''How protected is an artist if so much of his career is controlled by a signal entity?''</p>
        <p>ADS AND STEREOTYPES -- The recent promotion of the rice mascot Uncle Ben from chief cook to chief executive prompted Slate this week to offer a fascinating slide-show essay on ''the strange history of racist spokescharacters.'' (slate.com)</p>
        <p>''Nasty stereotypes have helped move the merchandise for more than a century,'' David Segal writes, ''and the history of their use and abuse offers a weird and telling glimpse of race relations in this country.''</p>
        <p>The essay shows that while things have improved since the turn of the 20th century, there is still a way to go. Back then, a maker of rat poison could get away with depicting a Chinese man in Confucian-era garb gobbling up a rat (to ''exploit the then-popular urban legend that Chinese people eat rats,'' Mr. Segal explains). But as recently as the early 1990s, Stroh Brewery was peddling Crazy Horse malt liquor -- disregarding the fact that the 19th-century American Indian leader Crazy Horse was a teetotaler who preached abstinence. In 2001, the brewery sold off the brand and apologized.</p>
        <p>WELL, DUH! -- A new study has confirmed what most of us already knew: Wealth and intelligence have little to do with each other.</p>
        <p>ScientificAmerican.com spoke with Jay L. Zagorsky, a research scientist at Ohio State University, who analyzed the data. There seems to be a correlation between income and intelligence, Mr. Zagorsky said, but ''for wealth, there is no relationship.'' He concluded that ''even smart people don't save.''</p>
        <p>DAN MITCHELL</p>
        <p>WHAT'S ONLINE Complete links are at nytimes.com/business. E-mail: whatsonline@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Complete links are at nytimes.com/business. E-mail: whatsonline@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
