<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush and Congress Easing Tone of Debate on War Bill</title>
    <meta content="28CONG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/washington/28CONG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843426"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vetoes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Luo, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vetoes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E7D7123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush and Congress Easing Tone of Debate on War Bill</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bush and Congress Easing Tone of Debate on War Bill</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL LUO and SHERYL GAY STOLBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay; Luo, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>War spending bill, and its timetable for withdrawing US troops, is headed for presidential veto, but Pres Bush and Democratic leaders have hinted at willingness to compromise; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the $124 billion war spending bill, and its timetable for withdrawing American troops, headed for a presidential veto early next week, both President Bush and Democratic leaders yesterday toned down the talk of the last several weeks and hinted at a willingness to compromise.</p>
        <p>While warning Congress not to test his will by sending him another bill that includes a withdrawal date, President Bush said: ''I invite the leaders of the House and the Senate, both parties, to come down, you know, soon after my veto so we can discuss a way forward.'' He later issued an official invitation for Congressional leaders to meet at the White House on Wednesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush and Democratic leaders hinted at a willingness to compromise on the war spending bill.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the $124 billion war spending bill, and its timetable for withdrawing American troops, headed for a presidential veto early next week, both President Bush and Democratic leaders yesterday toned down the talk of the last several weeks and hinted at a willingness to compromise.</p>
        <p>While warning Congress not to test his will by sending him another bill that includes a withdrawal date, President Bush said: ''I invite the leaders of the House and the Senate, both parties, to come down, you know, soon after my veto so we can discuss a way forward.'' He later issued an official invitation for Congressional leaders to meet at the White House on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The boldness of Senate Democrats has only seemed to swell as the war debate has worn on. Yesterday, they said they remained committed to carrying out what they believed to be the will of the American people to change direction in Iraq. But, like Mr. Bush, they also indicated a readiness to negotiate.</p>
        <p>''We are legislators,'' said Harry Reid of Nevada, the Senate majority leader, speaking to reporters in New York where members of his party gathered yesterday for their annual policy retreat. ''We understand legislation is the art of compromise, consensus building. We are willing to sit down and talk with the president, but we have certain things we believe to be important to the country. I'm sure he does too.''</p>
        <p>Republicans inside and outside the White House signaled yesterday that Mr. Bush, though still adamantly opposed to accepting any bill that has timetables in it, was ready to move on.</p>
        <p>''We're entering a different phase in which I think the statements have been made, the votes have been cast,'' said Dan Bartlett, the counselor to Mr. Bush, ''and while the president still has the responsibility to veto this bill, today's statement demonstrates that he's looking beyond the veto to how we can get the funding to our troops.''</p>
        <p>Exactly when Mr. Bush vetoes the measure depends on when Congressional leaders send it to him. They may do so on Tuesday, on the fourth anniversary of his 2003 appearance under a ''mission accomplished'' banner on an aircraft carrier.</p>
        <p>While Democrats concede they have nowhere near the two-thirds vote needed from both chambers to override a veto, the House may still make the attempt. A notice yesterday from the office of Representative Steny H. Hoyer of Maryland, the majority leader, advised lawmakers that the House could attempt to override it as early as Tuesday. Senate officials have indicated they would take no similar action if the House effort falls short.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reid noted that Senator Mitch McConnell of Kentucky, the Republican leader, reached out to him on Thursday morning, before the Senate voted on the spending bill, to begin preliminary discussions of what to do next. He said they would meet again on Monday.</p>
        <p>The challenge is how to bridge the gap between hard and fast positions. On one pole is the president's call, which he repeated yesterday during a news conference at Camp David, for a spending bill that simply finances the troops' needs. On the other is Democrats' desire to act on a mandate they believe they received in the November midterm elections by taking steps to end the war.</p>
        <p>An area of common ground that appears to be emerging is that of setting benchmark goals for the Iraqi government to meet in the coming months. Benchmarks are included in the war spending bill being sent to the president, but are currently tied to deadlines for troop withdrawals.</p>
        <p>Charlie Black, a Republican strategist close to the administration, said if Democrats sent Mr. Bush a bill with nonbinding benchmarks in it, the president would have to consider it. ''I don't think he'll accept anything that's binding,'' Mr. Black said. ''If they want to put something in there that says the Iraqis should do the following things by certain benchmarks, language that's just advisory and nonbinding, I would think he'd have to look at it.''</p>
        <p>But tying benchmarks to consequences to give them weight, which antiwar Democrats are sure to insist on, are ''a little more divisive,'' Mr. McConnell said in a conference call with reporters. ''Exactly how we would craft them remains to be seen.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Reid offered little hint yesterday of Democrats' post-veto strategy. But he said they had an obligation to the American people, the troops and their families, ''recognizing we are the difference between changing course and not changing course.''</p>
        <p>THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
