<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After a War Bill Veto, Then What?</title>
    <meta content="l28iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843376"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Central Intelligence Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harbater, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thalman, T R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lorton, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weingast, Stan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Annacone, Thomas J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maher, Thomas Jude</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thomas, Brant</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tenet, George J</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">At the Center of the Storm (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE2D9123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After a War Bill Veto, Then What?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Letters from David Harbater, T R Thalman, William Lorton, and Stan Weingast support Democrats' antiwar spending bill; Thomas J Annacone opposes it; drawing; letters from Thomas Jude Maher and Brant Thomas comment on former CIA Dir George Tenet's new book, At the Center of the Storm</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Senate Passes Bill Seeking Iraq Exit; Veto Is Expected'' (front page, April 27):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Senate Passes Bill Seeking Iraq Exit; Veto Is Expected'' (front page, April 27):</p>
        <p>As you report, there is no consensus in Congress on how to respond to the expected veto of the Iraq war financing bill. It became clear last fall, though, that there was an emerging consensus in the country for carrying out the recommendations of the bipartisan Iraq Study Group.</p>
        <p>Any war financing bill that Congress takes up after the anticipated presidential veto should therefore mandate the recommendations appearing in that study group's report.</p>
        <p>Doing so could help bridge the gap between the positions of the two political parties, as well as better reflect the views and wishes of the American people.</p>
        <p>David Harbater  Philadelphia, April 27, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As a Republican for more than 50 years, I am astounded that Republicans who voted against the bill to limit the Iraq war do not realize that most Americans no longer support this war. They will find the results of their vote when we voters have our next chance to vote.</p>
        <p>T. R. Thalman  Chapel Hill, N.C., April 27, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Dana Perino, the White House deputy press secretary, dares to call the Democrats ''cynical'' for timing delivery of their antiwar spending bill to make the clearest possible statement to the president?</p>
        <p>If doing so is ''cynical,'' what on earth is lying about connections between Saddam Hussein and Al Qaeda, misrepresenting Cpl. Pat Tillman's friendly-fire death in Afghanistan and making a joke out of looking for weapons of mass destruction under the Oval Office desk? I'd love to know.</p>
        <p>William Lorton  Los Angeles, April 27, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>For any guy (and gal) who has ever served in the military, one of the most demoralizing letters he or she could receive was a ''Dear John'' letter from a loved one back home announcing (in the words of a country song) that ''my love for you is gone.''</p>
        <p>This week, Congress sent a Dear John letter to the United States military serving in Iraq. As is usual in such cases, it has found a more important love -- in this case, political advantage.</p>
        <p>Thomas J. Annacone  Yorktown Heights, N.Y.  April 27, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''U.S. Commander Says Fall Pullback in Iraq Would Lead to More Sectarian Killings'' (news article, April 27):</p>
        <p>Gen. David H. Petraeus appears to be a capable, dedicated and plain-spoken military man. As President Bush's man in Iraq, he has been asked to see the war through to a ''successful'' conclusion.</p>
        <p>He has returned from Iraq to report that the situation is grim but that he can succeed at his task if given resources of time, money and lives, both American and Iraqi.</p>
        <p>He seems certain that the president' goals, however ill defined, can be achieved.</p>
        <p>The general's sincerity and high hopes belie the fact that ''success'' in Iraq can hardly be defined, let alone achieved.</p>
        <p>The majority of American voters spoke loudly and clearly last November. We do not want the war to continue. We do not want to see the death toll rise even higher.</p>
        <p>General Petraeus may be a good soldier with a ''can do'' attitude, but President Bush has sent him on a fool's errand.</p>
        <p>Congress must weigh the voice of the people against that of the general.</p>
        <p>Stan Weingast  Croton-on-Hudson, N.Y.  April 27, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Ex-C.I.A. Chief, in Book, Assails Cheney on Iraq'' (front page, April 27):</p>
        <p>I am glad that George J. Tenet has confirmed that this administration never conducted a ''serious debate'' about whether Saddam Hussein was an imminent danger to this country. His assertions at this late date, however, appear merely vindictive.</p>
        <p>If he had told us what he knew during the buildup to the war or at least before the 2004 election, he could have changed history. Instead, his silence has helped prolong the disaster and the deaths.</p>
        <p>Thomas Jude Maher  Port Washington, N.Y.  April 27, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Memory is an amazing thing; events can be recalled with clarity or not at all.</p>
        <p>Contrast George J. Tenet's ability to recall the episode before the war at the White House where his ''slam dunk'' comment was born with Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales's inability to remember anything about his role in the firing of federal prosecutors.</p>
        <p>Could it be that memory correlates to one's agenda?</p>
        <p>Brant Thomas  Brooklyn, April 27, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
