<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Fatal Wound From a Colleague's Weapon Is Rare, but Always a Risk</title>
    <meta content="28friendly" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/nyregion/28friendly.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843421"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01EED8123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="491" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Fatal Wound From a Colleague's Weapon Is Rare, but Always a Risk</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Fatal Wound From a Colleague’s Weapon Is Rare, but Always a Risk</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANAHAD O'CONNOR and SABRINA PACIFICI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pacifici, Sabrina; O'Connor, Anahad</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The accidental shooting of David C. Brinkerhoff, the New York state trooper who was killed by a bullet from a fellow trooper confronting a suspect inside a Catskill farmhouse on Wednesday, puts Trooper Brinkerhoff in a small minority of police officers killed in the line of duty.</p>
        <p>In the annals of law enforcement history, cases of officers dying at the hands of their own colleagues have been exceedingly rare. According to the National Law Enforcement Officers Memorial Fund, from 1893 through 2006, about 18,000 officers were killed on the job -- but only 198 of them at the hand of a fellow officer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A New York state trooper struck by a fellow trooper’s bullet is in a small minority of police officers killed in the line of duty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The accidental shooting of David C. Brinkerhoff, the New York state trooper who was killed by a bullet from a fellow trooper confronting a suspect inside a Catskill farmhouse on Wednesday, puts Trooper Brinkerhoff in a small minority of police officers killed in the line of duty.</p>
        <p>In the annals of law enforcement history, cases of officers dying at the hands of their own colleagues have been exceedingly rare. According to the National Law Enforcement Officers Memorial Fund, from 1893 through 2006, about 18,000 officers were killed on the job -- but only 198 of them at the hand of a fellow officer.</p>
        <p>Put another way, slightly more than 1 percent of all officers killed in the line of duty were killed by bullets fired by their colleagues. In the last decade, in fact, more officers have died in traffic-related accidents than by gunfire of any kind.</p>
        <p>About 57,000 officers are assaulted every year, but with the introduction of Kevlar body armor in 1974, the number who suffer fatal injuries has decreased.</p>
        <p>Experts said yesterday that many deaths involving gunfire from colleagues were caused by crossfire between teams of officers who were firing at the same assailant. In Trooper Brinkerhoff's case, the police said that as he entered a farmhouse in pursuit of a suspect near Margaretville, N.Y., the suspect fired at him, hitting Trooper Brinkerhoff's body armor. That bullet threw him off balance, and he was then hit once in the head during the gunfire that followed from three other troopers.</p>
        <p>That situation mirrored others in recent years. Earlier this month, a veteran F.B.I. agent was killed in New Jersey when he was hit by a bullet from another agent's gun as the agents swarmed a group of robbery suspects outside a bank. Three years before that, in June 2004, a deputy sheriff in Los Angeles was accidentally shot in the neck by a fellow officer as they surrounded a gunman outside a motel and opened fire.</p>
        <p>''There is not one moment that is not potentially life threatening,'' said Craig W. Floyd, chairman and chief executive of the Officers Memorial Fund. ''You are equipped; you are taking all possible precautions and you have the best training possible, but this is not enough to protect an officer all the time.''</p>
        <p>Among those officers killed accidentally by their colleagues, statistics show that 43 of the 198 were killed because of mistaken identity and 14 were killed in training exercises. But the No. 1 factor is accidental discharge of another officer's weapon. That was the case in Kennesaw, Ga., in 2005, for example, when an officer was killed at the North Central Georgia Law Enforcement Academy. During a firearms training session, a training instructor's firearm discharged as he performed a demonstration, shooting and killing a 23-year-old officer.</p>
        <p>Even under the most benign circumstances, officers can be shot and killed, Mr. Floyd said. ''It's the nature of the job.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
