<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After 2 Solid Periods, Defense Betrays Rangers</title>
    <meta content="28rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/sports/hockey/28rangers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843460"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Buffalo Sabres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Buffalo Sabres</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Hockey League</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E5D6123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="725" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After 2 Solid Periods, Defense Betrays Rangers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After 2 Solid Periods, Defense Betrays Rangers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinser, Lynn</byline>
      <dateline>BUFFALO, April 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For two periods, the Rangers followed the precise, defense-first plan they had drawn up, only to have it torn to shreds in 24 seconds. Two passes -- one errant, one perfect -- turned a one-goal lead into a Buffalo Sabres comeback.</p>
        <p>Rangers defenseman Marek Malik made a bad pass from behind his net that was intercepted by Sabres defenseman Toni Lydman. A split second later the puck was bouncing off center Chris Drury's stick and into the Rangers' goal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thomas Vanek  the star of Game 1  scored the winning goal for Buffalo on a terrific pass from Drew Stafford in the third period.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For two periods, the Rangers followed the precise, defense-first plan they had drawn up, only to have it torn to shreds in 24 seconds. Two passes -- one errant, one perfect -- turned a one-goal lead into a Buffalo Sabres comeback.</p>
        <p>Rangers defenseman Marek Malik made a bad pass from behind his net that was intercepted by Sabres defenseman Toni Lydman. A split second later the puck was bouncing off center Chris Drury's stick and into the Rangers' goal.</p>
        <p>It took another goal -- by Thomas Vanek midway through the third period -- for the Sabres to win Friday night's game, 3-2, and dig a 2-0 hole for the Rangers. The series returns to Madison Square Garden for Game 3 on Sunday.</p>
        <p>''We have to keep fighting,'' the Rangers captain Jaromir Jagr said. ''We don't have any luck on our side. But we didn't have any in the middle of the season and we kept battling and our luck changed on the ice. Hopefully, it will happen the same way.''</p>
        <p>The Sabres posted the N.H.L.'s best regular-season record and won a first-round series against the Islanders by playing games just like this. They did not dominate. They did not dictate play. But they turned a few mistakes into goals.</p>
        <p>The one came so early in the third, after the Rangers held them to nine shots in the first two periods, was devastating.</p>
        <p>''What it does for us is great,'' Buffalo Coach Lindy Ruff said. ''But what it does for the other team, too, all of a sudden you can't nurse the one-goal lead. That's erased in the first minute of play. It's great for us and does harm to them, for their psyche.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers' psyche had been impenetrable during a late-season drive to the playoffs and in their first-round sweep of Atlanta. It has taken several dents in Buffalo.</p>
        <p>''It's tough because you're down 2-0 and if you lose two more games, you're done,'' forward Martin Straka said. ''We just have a few breakdowns every game and it cost us.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers, bolstered by the return of defenseman Michal Rozsival after he injured his knee in Game 1, got a power-play goal by Straka in the first period, but the Sabres responded with a power-play goal by defenseman Brian Campbell.</p>
        <p>A second-period power play ended in another Rangers goal, on a shot by defenseman Paul Mara. All three goals followed the same pattern: long shots eluding goalies who were screened by forwards.</p>
        <p>Otherwise, though, Buffalo's Ryan Miller and the Rangers' Henrik Lundqvist were having different experiences. The Rangers were peppering Miller with shots, which he turned away, while Lundqvist faced only a handful.</p>
        <p>That all changed on the first shift of the third. When Malik tried to clear the puck from behind his net, his backhand pass went right to the stick of Lydman. When Drury's deflection went in, Lundqvist swung his stick in frustration.</p>
        <p>That tied the score, which is not where the Rangers felt it should have been. Then, with 9 minutes 49 seconds left, the Rangers were caught in their own zone for an extended shift by their fourth line. Drew Stafford got the puck in front of the Rangers' zone, made a pass behind him and through the legs of Rangers center Blair Betts to Vanek, who had eluded Mara.</p>
        <p>''It's extremely frustrating,'' Mara said. ''We played very, very, very well for two periods and most of the third period we did as well. There were a couple breaks that they got that ended up in the back of our net.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers scrambled to try to tie the score, with Jagr getting the best chance in front of Miller with 1:59 left. Miller sprawled to save the shot off his backhand.</p>
        <p>''Something is going to happen,'' Jagr said. ''You never know. We're down 2-0. They probably think it's over. That's O.K. You never know, a series can change in one play, in one minute, one period. You could be up 3-0 and you give up one goal and all of a sudden everything's coming. You just never know.''</p>
        <p>Miller, though, said the Sabres would take nothing for granted.</p>
        <p>''We're going to go into Madison Square Garden, play good hockey and see where it takes us,'' Miller said. ''By no means is this series over.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers hope he is right.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
