<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>One Bad Inning for Matsuzaka Doesn't Derail Win</title>
    <meta content="28redsox" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/sports/baseball/28redsox.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843466"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Japan</location>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Matsuzaka, Daisuke</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4D6123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="714" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>One Bad Inning for Matsuzaka Doesn't Derail Win</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On Night of Firsts, a Second Win Over the Yankees for Matsuzaka</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There were 14 million baseball fans in Japan still sipping their coffee or yawning through a Saturday morning when Daisuke Matsuzaka faced the Yankees last night. They wanted to see Matsuzaka, so forfeiting some sleep was worth it. Or so they thought.</p>
        <p>That was, until the fourth inning. Who was this pitching imposter walking three straight batters and permitting four runs? Who was this Matsuzaka lookalike who needed 41 pitches and 27 minutes to snag three outs? And why was J. C. Romero warming up? The Japanese would have chosen their pillows over Romero.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Matsuzaka rebounded from a forgettable fourth inning to retire six consecutive batters and stymie the Yankees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There were 14 million baseball fans in Japan still sipping their coffee or yawning through a Saturday morning when Daisuke Matsuzaka faced the Yankees last night. They wanted to see Matsuzaka, so forfeiting some sleep was worth it. Or so they thought.</p>
        <p>That was, until the fourth inning. Who was this pitching imposter walking three straight batters and permitting four runs? Who was this Matsuzaka lookalike who needed 41 pitches and 27 minutes to snag three outs? And why was J. C. Romero warming up? The Japanese would have chosen their pillows over Romero.</p>
        <p>Eventually, Matsuzaka finished the fourth. Eventually, Matsuzaka tossed six innings, only one of them a fiasco. Eventually, Matsuzaka and the Red Sox stopped the Yankees, 11-4, at Yankee Stadium. Matsuzaka was not superb, but he defeated the Yankees, his newest enemies, for the second time in six days.</p>
        <p>Still, when Matsuzaka was asked if he derived any personal satisfaction from outlasting the Yankees twice, he acted as if someone had squirted vinegar in his face.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't say that there's any personal satisfaction in beating the Yankees, but, as a team, I'm very happy we won,'' Matsuzaka said through an interpreter.</p>
        <p>Matsuzaka has described himself as a slow starter, saying he usually did not pitch his best in Japan until the summer. So Matsuzaka theorized the same thing would happen with Boston. The more Matsuzaka pitched, he said, the better he would get.</p>
        <p>While Matsuzaka knows that he needs to adjust to the harder ball, to the strong American lineups and to pitching every fifth day instead of every sixth day, he is also extremely confident. It is unlikely that Matsuzaka thought that he would experience so many growing pains.</p>
        <p>Yet there was Matsuzaka, the $103 million pitcher, wobbling through a brutal fourth. He looked unsteady as his fastballs sailed out of the strike zone and his breaking pitches fooled no one. Matsuzaka rubbed his forehead and kicked the pitching rubber.</p>
        <p>It took Matsuzaka 42 pitches to navigate through three innings and 41 to complete the fourth. The inning featured three walks, three hits and four runs. Manager Terry Francona said he was wondering how much longer he could stay with Matsuzaka.</p>
        <p>''The good news is he competes and he gathers himself,'' Francona said. ''That was a tough inning.''</p>
        <p>Matsuzaka can be shaky with runners on base, but he was not specific about what ailed him.</p>
        <p>''If I got into all the things that happened in the fourth, it would be a long story and it would sound like a lot of excuses,'' Matsuzaka said. ''To keep a long story short, I'd say there are few things technically I still need to work on.''</p>
        <p>But Matsuzaka showed the Red Sox another side of his pitching personality by rebounding from the forgettable fourth to retire six batters in a row. As badly as Matsuzaka pitched, he regrouped, watched the Red Sox jump ahead with a three-run fifth and did not let one inning destroy him. Matsuzaka allowed four runs on five hits, struck out seven and walked four. He is now 3-2 with a 4.36 earned run average.</p>
        <p>''He's going through a lot of firsts,'' catcher Jason Varitek said.</p>
        <p>Matsuzaka experienced some more firsts last night. It was his first start at Yankee Stadium and the first time he had faced Hideki Matsui, another Japanese icon, in the major leagues.</p>
        <p>Matsui, who was 2 for 17 against Matsuzaka in Japan, went 0 for 2 with a walk. Matsuzaka said he treated Matsui like any other hitter.</p>
        <p>On a soggy night where there were more empty seats than usual at the start of the game, Matsuzaka said the fans were as loud as any he has heard. But they did not unnerve him.</p>
        <p>Matsuzaka considered himself a slow starter in Japan, but he actually was 20-9 with a 2.35 E.R.A. in Aprils there. Those statistics are comparable to his overall numbers. Apparently, Matsuzaka recalls having rockier starts. He is having a rough one here, by his standards, but he expects to get better soon.</p>
        <p>''The sort of pitching you saw today may be the pitching you see as I get used to the lineups,'' Matsuzaka said. ''But, that being said, it's the type of pitching I'd like to avoid.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
