<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Citigroup Goes Global In Ad Effort</title>
    <meta content="28citi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/business/media/28citi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843452"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Slogans and Mottoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Customer Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customer Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Slogans and Mottoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Citigroup Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E6D6123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="655" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Citigroup Goes Global In Ad Effort</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Citigroup Goes Global in Ad Effort</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC DASH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dash, Eric</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For years, Citigroup has promised its customers better service and its investors better results. Now, Citigroup is pitching a new message: ''Let's Get It Done.''</p>
        <p>Citigroup is expected to introduce the tagline and advertising campaign next Sunday in the company's first global branding effort since it was formed nearly a decade ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Citigroup will introduce a new message in the company’s first global brand campaign since it was formed nearly a decade ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For years, Citigroup has promised its customers better service and its investors better results. Now, Citigroup is pitching a new message: ''Let's Get It Done.''</p>
        <p>Citigroup is expected to introduce the tagline and advertising campaign next Sunday in the company's first global branding effort since it was formed nearly a decade ago.</p>
        <p>The campaign, with ads on television, online and in major publications in 10 markets, will cost up to $30 million for the first two months, according to a person close to the situation. The ads are the latest in Citigroup's rebranding effort that began last year. With the Citigroup account worth more than $600 million, the campaign also marks a major shift for one of the biggest advertisers in the financial services industry.</p>
        <p>The campaign was led by the Seattle office of Publicis, which will also take over the management of the bank's large consumer advertising account from Fallon in Minneapolis. Both agencies, however, are part of the Publicis Groupe of Paris.</p>
        <p>Unlike past Citigroup ads, which have relied on humor, the new ones are expected to have a more emotional tone and prominently feature the red arc that replaced the red umbrella as the company's logo. As the umbrella stood for protection, bank executives hope the arc comes to represent connection.</p>
        <p>Some of the new ads present it as a three-dimensional bridge linking Citigroup's customers to their financial goals.</p>
        <p>The slogan is similar to a line that is a catchphrase for Larry the Cable Guy, a blue-collar standup comedian, who exclaims, ''Git-R-done''</p>
        <p>Citigroup executives say they hope the new slogan is viewed as an invitation to customers to use more of the bank's services, not as an signal that, at long last, things will finally get done.</p>
        <p>Still, the new tagline and campaign seems to be a call for action at a crucial time for the company and its chief executive, Charles O. Prince III. Over the last three years, he has embarked on an ambitious strategy to overhaul the company and better integrate its sprawling businesses. But under pressure from investors, Mr. Prince has taken some of his most notable steps yet in the last three months.</p>
        <p>He has shaken up his management team, bringing in a new finance chief and head of alternative investments. This month, he announced the biggest restructuring effort in the company's history, streamlining its internal operations and eliminating 17,000 jobs. And with the new advertising campaign, Mr. Prince is unifying its marketing efforts and looking to change the way customers relate to the bank.</p>
        <p>The new campaign, which will be featured worldwide, came together in the last three months.</p>
        <p>Armed with research from the rebranding effort, Citigroup advertising executives began meeting in January with representatives from Fallon and Publicis. The challenge was to create a campaign that would be appropriate for customers of its retail and credit card businesses, its largest advertisers, and clients of its investment bank.</p>
        <p>Within the bank, some executives were pulling to restore the memorable ''Citi never sleeps'' tagline that was used by Citicorp from the 1970s to the early 1990s. While some argued the phrase was even more resonant in today's 24-7 global environment, others wanted to distance themselves from the past.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Fallon presented plans for advertising that prominently featured the arc. But its chances were diminished after a bungled television spot for its consumer businesses that featured a spokesman who resembled the lead character from the movie comedy ''Borat.''</p>
        <p>In the end, Citigroup executives hired Publicis to manage both the global corporate brand campaign, which will run in May and June, and a bigger consumer campaign that will follow.</p>
        <p>In 2005, Citigroup spent about $623 million on all advertising, according to TNS Media Intelligence, before scaling back last year as the company retooled its brand.</p>
        <p>Citigroup's campaign follows the Bank of America's retooling of its brand advertising in late February, with the slogan, ''Bank of Opportunity.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
