<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Recalling Former Bat Boy Who Made News</title>
    <meta content="28batboy" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/sports/baseball/28batboy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843453"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Magadan, Dave</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E6D6123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="686" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Recalling Former Bat Boy Who Made News</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Recalling Former Bat Boy Who Made News</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY; Ben Shpigel and Michael S. Schmidt contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dave Magadan did not remember Kirk Radomski. But as soon as Magadan, the batting coach for the Boston Red Sox, learned that Radomski's nickname was ''Murdoch,'' he immediately recalled the former Mets clubhouse attendant and bat boy.</p>
        <p>''He was huge,'' Magadan said. ''I mean, huge.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Former Mets recalled that Kirk Radomski, who pleaded guilty Friday to distributing steroids to baseball players, was a musclebound, avid weightlifter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dave Magadan did not remember Kirk Radomski. But as soon as Magadan, the batting coach for the Boston Red Sox, learned that Radomski's nickname was ''Murdoch,'' he immediately recalled the former Mets clubhouse attendant and bat boy.</p>
        <p>''He was huge,'' Magadan said. ''I mean, huge.''</p>
        <p>Radomski pleaded guilty yesterday in United States District Court to charges of distributing steroids to dozens of major league players and to money laundering. He faces a 25-year sentence and a $500,000 fine. He has also created something of an earthquake for a sport whose image has been tarnished by the issue of steroids.</p>
        <p>''That's not good,'' Magadan said of the guilty plea.</p>
        <p>Radomski worked for the Mets from 1985 to 1995 while Magadan, a good hitter with a great eye and little power, played for them from 1986 to 1992.</p>
        <p>As Magadan discussed Radomski before the Yankees played the Red Sox last night, he made repeated references to Radomski's physique. Still, Magadan said he never witnessed anything questionable involving Radomski and the Mets.</p>
        <p>''It was toward the early 90s and you started hearing about steroids and stuff like that,'' Magadan said. ''Did I physically see him give something to a player? No.''</p>
        <p>Other than recalling that Radomski was an avid weight lifter, Magadan did not remember much else.</p>
        <p>''He did his job in the clubhouse,'' Magadan said. ''You threw the jocks on the floor. He picked them up. He was good at what he did.''</p>
        <p>Magadan was far more relaxed in talking about Radomski than were the Mets, who, understandably, were made uncomfortable by the news that a former employee, even one with relatively low-level jobs, had been directly linked to baseball's steroids problem.</p>
        <p>The Mets issued a statement saying that they were ''disappointed'' to hear about the guilty plea and that ''the conduct in question is diametrically opposed to the values and standards of the Mets organization and our owners.''</p>
        <p>In addition, the Mets added that they ''are and always have been adamantly opposed to the use of performance-enhancing drugs and continue to support Major League Baseball's efforts to eradicate any such use in our game.''</p>
        <p>The Mets have had their own recent encounter with steroids use. Reliever Guillermo Mota, acquired by the Mets in the middle of the 2006 season and a key pitcher in the postseason, was suspended by baseball for a positive drug test shortly after the World Series ended.</p>
        <p>The suspension will keep Mota out of the first 50 games of this season, at which point he can rejoin the Mets, who signed him to a new contract not long after the suspension was announced. At the time, the Mets internally debated the public-relations fallout of re-signing Mota, but were impressed by his public apology for the positive test.</p>
        <p>Mota, of course, is not the issue for the Mets right now. Radomski is.</p>
        <p>Al Leiter, who played for the Mets after Radomski left the organization and now works as a broadcaster for the Yankees, said he had a vague recollection of a burly individual with the ''Murdoch'' nickname. Leiter said that he found out about Radomski's guilty plea in a call from Gene Orza, who is the chief operating officer of the Players Association.</p>
        <p>''I think he was calling some former Mets to tell them about it,'' Leiter said. ''Not to tell them that they have been implicated, but just to make them aware of it.''</p>
        <p>Howard Johnson, the Mets' first base coach, and Ron Darling, one of their announcers, played for the Mets while Radomski worked in the clubhouse. Johnson called him a ''nice kid'' who he did not know much about. Darling did not recall him.</p>
        <p>Philip Deblasi, a neighbor of Radomski's in Manorville in Suffolk County, said in a telephone interview last night that Radomski was a ''muscular guy'' who appeared to work out of his house.</p>
        <p>''I saw him during the day a lot,'' Deblasi said.</p>
        <p>As for Magadan, even though he seemed surprised at the day's news, he said that he was not.</p>
        <p>''Nothing shocks me anymore,'' he said.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
