<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Group of 3 Banks Informs ABN of Rival Bid to Come</title>
    <meta content="28bank" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/business/worldbusiness/28bank.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843402"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">ABN AMRO Holding NV</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Royal Bank of Scotland Plc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Barclays Plc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E3D8123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="818" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Group of 3 Banks Informs ABN of Rival Bid to Come</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">3 Banks Press ABN to Consider Rival Bid</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIA WERDIGIER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Werdigier, Julia</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, April 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The board of ABN Amro was dealt a double challenge on Friday, as a consortium of three European banks submitted official notification that they are preparing an unsolicited bid and, separately, an investor association said that it was taking ABN Amro to court.</p>
        <p>On Monday, the board of ABN Amro agreed to sell the bank to Barclays for about 64 billion euros, or nearly $87.21 billion. The Royal Bank of Scotland and its two partners on Friday told the board of ABN Amro, which is based in the Netherlands, that it intends to make an offer for the bank, topping the friendly bid from Barclays.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The banks, led by Royal Bank of Scotland, said they would make a bid worth more than an earlier offer from Barclays for $87 billion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The board of ABN Amro was dealt a double challenge on Friday, as a consortium of three European banks submitted official notification that they are preparing an unsolicited bid and, separately, an investor association said that it was taking ABN Amro to court.</p>
        <p>On Monday, the board of ABN Amro agreed to sell the bank to Barclays for about 64 billion euros, or nearly $87.21 billion. The Royal Bank of Scotland and its two partners on Friday told the board of ABN Amro, which is based in the Netherlands, that it intends to make an offer for the bank, topping the friendly bid from Barclays.</p>
        <p>The official notice starts a countdown toward the submission of a final bid. Dutch regulations make the counterbidding process a bit complicated for the consortium, which also includes Banco Santander Central Hispano of Spain and Fortis, the Belgian banking group. The rules include a silent period during which the consortium is not allowed to disclose more specific details of its takeover price for seven days, or before May 3, even to ABN Amro.</p>
        <p>But ABN Amro has committed to another deadline that requires the consortium to make a final offer before May 6. That is the day ABN Amro has said that it would sell LaSalle Bank, the American unit that the Royal Bank group is most interested in. That means the consortium has only a three-day window to make a formal bid with a final price.</p>
        <p>ABN Amro is currently soliciting bids for LaSalle that would top a $21 billion offer from Bank of America. The Royal Bank of Scotland group said it would bid for ABN Amro only if it got LaSalle as well.</p>
        <p>The rival bidding pits ABN Amro's board, which has made clear that it preferred the Barclays bid, against some of ABN Amro's largest shareholders, who have put pressure on the board to consider a rival approach, and the Royal Bank of Scotland group, which has yet to make a formal offer for ABN Amro.</p>
        <p>''ABN shareholders are a bit frustrated now,'' said Guy de Blonay, a fund manager at New Star Asset Management in London. ''But under Dutch regulation, the board has to pay equal attention to what is best for employees, and they are doing a good job balancing the two issues, which is very difficult.''</p>
        <p>VEB, a Dutch investors' association with more than 40,000 members, said Friday that it had filed a petition against management at ABN Amro on Thursday at the Enterprise Chamber of the Amsterdam Court of Appeals.</p>
        <p>The association says that management failed to follow ''principles of sound management'' and deliberately sought to frustrate the possibilities of a bid from the banking consortium by selling LaSalle to Bank of America.</p>
        <p>Jochem van de Laarschot, a spokesman at ABN Amro, said Friday that the bank believes it has met all the legal requirements and that the sale of LaSalle is a transaction that is in the interest of ABN Amro shareholders.</p>
        <p>Rijkman W. J. Groenink, the chief executive of ABN Amro, and the rest of the management came under fire from shareholders on Thursday at the company's annual general meeting for their handling of the sale of the Dutch bank, the largest in the country, to Barclays.</p>
        <p>Mr. Groenink said earlier that he preferred a deal with Barclays because that would create a global bank rivaling HSBC Holdings, as opposed to the approach by the three banks in the consortium, which plans to break up the 183-year-old lender in three parts and divide the assets among themselves. He said, however, that he remains open to consider any rival bid on the table, but so far there is none.</p>
        <p>While some ABN Amro shareholders applauded Mr. Groenink for trying to avoid a breakup of the bank, others accused the management of hindering a constructive bidding competition and depriving shareholders of getting a higher price for their shares.</p>
        <p>ABN Amro shareholders voted Thursday in favor of a motion put forward by the Children's Investment Fund, an activist hedge fund in London that holds less than 3 percent of ABN Amro, to break up the bank if it maximizes shareholder value.</p>
        <p>The vote for the motion ''is an endorsement of the consortium's proposal and an encouragement to make a formal offer,'' Jean-Pierre Lambert, an analyst at Keefe, Bruyette &amp; Woods in London, wrote in a research note on Friday.</p>
        <p>The three banks said Friday that they continued to believe that their proposal offered a higher value for ABN Amro shareholders.</p>
        <p>If management at ABN Amro declines their offer, the Royal Bank of Scotland consortium can still take its offer directly to shareholders. Such hostile banking takeovers are challenging, though, analysts said.</p>
        <p>''At the end of the day, banking is still a people-centered business,'' said Derek Chambers, an anayst at Standard &amp; Poor's in London. ''It's important not to take over a disruptive management.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
