<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With A.M.D., Riding Waves Of Volatility</title>
    <meta content="28values" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/business/28values.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843360"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET VALUES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computer Chips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Chips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Intel Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Advanced Micro Devices Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6D9123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With A.M.D., Riding Waves Of Volatility</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With A.M.D., Riding Waves of Volatility</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONRAD DE AENLLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">De Aenlle, Conrad</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF the semiconductor industry were a seesaw, Intel would be anchored close to the middle, experiencing relatively gentle ups and downs. Advanced Micro Devices would be on one of the ends, clinging with both hands.</p>
        <p>The shocks of this highly cyclical business are less easy to absorb for A.M.D. because it is much smaller than Intel, which is the world's largest chip maker, and less financially secure. Any change in market conditions or in the competitive balance between them would vary the size of Intel's profit, but for A.M.D. it can mean the difference between a big profit and a big loss.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Any change in market conditions would vary the size of Intel’s profit, but for A.M.D. it can mean the difference between a big profit and a big loss.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF the semiconductor industry were a seesaw, Intel would be anchored close to the middle, experiencing relatively gentle ups and downs. Advanced Micro Devices would be on one of the ends, clinging with both hands.</p>
        <p>The shocks of this highly cyclical business are less easy to absorb for A.M.D. because it is much smaller than Intel, which is the world's largest chip maker, and less financially secure. Any change in market conditions or in the competitive balance between them would vary the size of Intel's profit, but for A.M.D. it can mean the difference between a big profit and a big loss.</p>
        <p>Look at recent history: Intel's net income from continuing operations -- a measure of profits that factors out accounting noise -- rose 15 percent in 2005, then fell 42 percent last year, a turnaround that is not out of the ordinary for such a cyclical industry. During the last three years the stock has traded in a narrow range with little net change.</p>
        <p>So-so is far better than A.M.D.'s results during the same period. Its stock underwent a moon shot and a painful re-entry, moving from less than $11 to $42, then back to $13. It is currently trading at around $14.30 a share on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>The company's profits rose 81 percent in 2005, to $165 million, then last year it lost all that and a bit more. Over the last five years, A.M.D. has turned a profit twice; Intel is a perfect five for five.</p>
        <p>A.M.D. finds it hard to beat its nemesis because it keeps beating itself, analysts and fund managers who follow the chip industry say. The company is known for accomplishing the critical aspects of semiconductor production flawlessly -- but seldom all at the same time.</p>
        <p>''A.M.D. is a company that has really struggled to execute on all cylinders,'' said Telis D. Bertsekas, manager of the MFS Technology fund. ''Historically, it would have windows of technology leadership, then it would flub the manufacturing and distribution. Customers could never really trust them.''</p>
        <p>In the latest episode of the rise and fall of A.M.D., the company seemed on the verge of slashing into Intel's leadership late in 2004, when it developed a microprocessor that produced less heat than others available at the time, a feature that made it ideal for use in industrial servers.</p>
        <p>''A.M.D. came out with a product that happened to be exactly what the market needed,'' Mr. Bertsekas said. ''It was a better product than Intel had for that kind of server. A.M.D. gained share, and the perception was that it would continue to gain share.''</p>
        <p>Then came the reality of distribution hiccups and a next generation of products that were not the world beaters that shareholders had expected. As investors continue to wait for an encore, the stock languishes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bertsekas said he owns Intel and not A.M.D., which he called ''the more high-risk, high-reward play on the microprocessor industry.''</p>
        <p>Kevin Landis, a portfolio manager for the Firsthand family of technology funds, also holds only Intel. A.M.D. ''is clearly the cheaper stock,'' he said, but it deserves to be. If the rivalry between the Silicon Valley chip makers is a game of leapfrog, Mr. Landis said, A.M.D. is ''the frog that hasn't leaped in a while.'' Its researchers ''apparently emptied out their pipeline of products and good news. While they're still a viable competitor to Intel, they need to come up with something to crow about.''</p>
        <p>But he is not ready to write the company off, and did a bit of crowing on its behalf. He pointed to ventures that allow A.M.D. to share manufacturing facilities with other suppliers, potentially cutting costs and limiting production problems.</p>
        <p>WHAT it chooses to manufacture is critical. Mr. Landis would advise A.M.D. to carve out niches for itself, such as low-heat microprocessors, and not to be Intel Jr. If A.M.D. were to ''try to do everything Intel does and go toe to toe with them, that would be a very bad idea,'' he said.</p>
        <p>If a few good ideas come off the drawing board or if sales of computers using Microsoft's Vista operating system catch a second wind, raising demand for chips, he said, A.M.D. could be back in favor on Wall Street.</p>
        <p>''If we get a nice Vista updraft later this year or some nice, new competitive products come out of A.M.D., you've got a nice little story there,'' Mr. Landis said. ''It's got a chance to be a real rewarding stock given how beaten down it has been.''</p>
        <p>MARKET VALUES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
