<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Nation Bound By Colorful Dinnerware</title>
    <meta content="28fies" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/theater/reviews/28fies.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843338"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bellafante, Ginia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tomlinson, Steven</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">American Fiesta (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Vineyard Theater</org>
        <object.title class="online_producer">American Fiesta (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2DA123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="715" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Nation Bound By Colorful Dinnerware</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Nation Bound by Colorful Dinnerware</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINIA BELLAFANTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bellafante, Ginia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ginia Bellafante reviews Steven Tomlinson one-man show American Fiesta; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''American Fiesta,'' a new one-man show written and performed by Steven Tomlinson, is as topically ambitious a theatrical effort as you will experience Off Broadway right now. It clips along with the energy of someone whose very metabolism seems to run on a hunger to understand himself and the world better.</p>
        <p>Staged at the Vineyard Theater, the play counts as its themes the current ruptures in American civic life and politics; the psychological roots of consumer choice; the neuroscience of desire; gay marriage; the greater meaning of eBay; the search for human fraternity, neighborhood, community; the perils of focus grouping; and the sorrows of family life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“American Fiesta” is as topically ambitious a theatrical effort as you will experience Off Broadway right now.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''American Fiesta,'' a new one-man show written and performed by Steven Tomlinson, is as topically ambitious a theatrical effort as you will experience Off Broadway right now. It clips along with the energy of someone whose very metabolism seems to run on a hunger to understand himself and the world better.</p>
        <p>Staged at the Vineyard Theater, the play counts as its themes the current ruptures in American civic life and politics; the psychological roots of consumer choice; the neuroscience of desire; gay marriage; the greater meaning of eBay; the search for human fraternity, neighborhood, community; the perils of focus grouping; and the sorrows of family life.</p>
        <p>You might be tempted to joke that ''American Fiesta'' seems to be about everything but the kitchen sink, except that it is about that too, or at least what falls into it. Mr. Tomlinson constructs his narrative around the development of his interest in Fiestaware, Depression-era ceramics whose potential for metaphor he finds inexhaustible.</p>
        <p>Fiestaware was the invention of the Homer Laughlin China Company, which in the 1930s decided that what Americans needed to cheer themselves up was colorful, cost-efficient dinnerware, whose pieces could be purchased individually. If you broke one salad plate, you didn't have to replace your whole set. I know all this not because I did a Wikipedia search, but because Mr. Tomlinson enthusiastically supplies us with the china's history. He isn't quite so much wary of consumer markets as he is enthralled by their ingenuity.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tomlinson holds a doctorate in economics from Stanford. He is a university lecturer in business and finance, a corporate consultant and a lay preacher. He could also add to his curriculum vitae that he is an affable, engaging performer. But the cleverness of his writing deflates amid his effusions of feeling.</p>
        <p>''American Fiesta'' is full of well-observed moments and supremely tired ones. (No human being mentioning a feminine side should ever, for instance, refer to Barbie's Dream House.) The story that Mr. Tomlinson tells revolves around an announcement he makes to his parents that he will marry his partner, Leon, in Canada.</p>
        <p>His mother and father, who live in rural Oklahoma, love him but don't see why this is necessary. Their disapproval leaves him desperate for familial closeness, and so he begins to collect Fiestaware, prompted by the memory of a big blue bowl that seemed to occupy a prominent role in his childhood.</p>
        <p>Soon he can think of nothing but the dishes and cups he doesn't have. An eBay addiction follows, and Mr. Tomlinson writes evocatively about the way the quest for things, and collecting specifically, can pull us too far away from treading the waters of real life.</p>
        <p>The play, with its elegant set of open shelves holding pretty bowls, begins with a screen image of the human brain and Mr. Tomlinson talking about the chemistry of retail appetite. ''Its classic proportions register here,'' he says of Fiestaware, ''in your cerebral cortex.''</p>
        <p>When he finds out that a certain strain of Fiestaware contained a potentially dangerous form of uranium, he submits to the paranoia of a whole online subculture devoted to it. He examines PayPal records and eBay user profiles. ''The typical transaction is a 60-year-old woman in a Midwestern town selling to an urban bachelor on the coast,'' he announces. ''It's a plot!''</p>
        <p>Regrettably, Mr. Tomlinson is not wedded to this kind of levity throughout. He draws connections to his new passion for collecting that are trite, tenuous or overstated. He meets a blind woman who collects flawed pieces, and you know where this is going: to a self-inquiry on his insistence on perfection. He is compelled to spell out why certain collectors must possess every piece of Fiestaware, as if the allegory weren't obvious enough: they need to feel whole, and he does too.</p>
        <p>What Mr. Tomlinson wants, ultimately, is for everyone to get along, for the whole country to feel put back together, red Fiestaware Americans and blue Fiestaware Americans. In the end his effort is merely tepid advocacy theater and a byproduct of the very impulse for niftily aggressive packaging that he seems to wish our culture would squelch.</p>
        <p>''American Fiesta'' continues through May 20 at the Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, Flatiron district; vineyardtheatre.org or (212) 353-0303.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
