<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Comrade's Shot Killed Trooper In the Catskills</title>
    <meta content="28trooper" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/nyregion/28trooper.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070502T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843449"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Margaretville (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foderaro, Lisa W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brinkerhoff, David C (State Trooper)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trim, Travis D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gombosi, Matthew (State Trooper)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Trim, Travis D</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7D6123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1132" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Comrade's Shot Killed Trooper In the Catskills</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Comrade’s Shot Killed New York State Trooper</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA W. FODERARO; Nicholas Confessore and Sabrina Pacifici contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Foderaro, Lisa W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Comrade's Shot Killed Trooper In the Catskills** Bullet that killed New York State Trooper David C Brinkerhoff during shootout in farmhouse near Margaretville came from gun of fellow officer, not suspect they had cornered; police say that suspect, Travis D Trim, who was hiding in house after shooting another trooper day before, fired one bullet at Brinkerhoff, but that it hit his body armor; say that Trim appears to have died during gunfight, not when house went up in flames; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The bullet that killed a New York state trooper during a shootout Wednesday morning in a farmhouse in the Catskill Mountains came from the gun of a fellow officer, not the suspect they had cornered, the state police said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The police said that the suspect, who was hiding in the house after shooting another trooper the day before, fired one bullet at the slain trooper, David C. Brinkerhoff, but that it hit his body armor. That bullet knocked Trooper Brinkerhoff onto one knee. He was then struck once in the back of the head, fatally, during the fusillade of bullets that followed from three other troopers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The state police had believed that David C. Brinkerhoff was killed by a suspect he and other officers had cornered.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The bullet that killed a New York state trooper during a shootout Wednesday morning in a farmhouse in the Catskill Mountains came from the gun of a fellow officer, not the suspect they had cornered, the state police said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The police said that the suspect, who was hiding in the house after shooting another trooper the day before, fired one bullet at the slain trooper, David C. Brinkerhoff, but that it hit his body armor. That bullet knocked Trooper Brinkerhoff onto one knee. He was then struck once in the back of the head, fatally, during the fusillade of bullets that followed from three other troopers.</p>
        <p>''As you can imagine, this new information is a source of great consternation and sadness,'' Preston L. Felton, the acting superintendent of the state police, said in a news conference in Albany. ''While it is clear that something went wrong, nothing can detract from the bravery and dedication of the men who entered'' the house.</p>
        <p>The state police also said that the suspect, Travis D. Trim, a 23-year-old college dropout from North Lawrence, N.Y., appeared to have died during the gunfight, having been shot once in the face and twice in the chest -- not when the house went up in flames Wednesday night after being surrounded by scores of heavily armed police officers for most of the day.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trim, who had a minor criminal record, was armed with a rifle and a handgun when the troopers encountered him on the second floor of the house about 8:30 a.m. Wednesday. He had apparently broken into the unoccupied house, on a country road at the edge of Margaretville, N.Y., a tiny village, to hide after shooting a trooper, Matthew Gombosi, in the chest during a traffic stop on Tuesday afternoon. Trooper Gombosi, who was wearing a bulletproof vest, was unhurt.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, police officials said that they suspected that Mr. Trim might have died during the morning gunfight, but that they could not be sure since the troopers' focus was on removing Trooper Brinkerhoff and another officer, Richard G. Mattson, who was shot in the arm, from the house.</p>
        <p>The tense nine-hour standoff that followed -- in which the police fired several tear gas canisters into the house and searched it room by room with a robotic camera -- ended in an accidental fire that destroyed the farmhouse, a weekend home belonging to a New Jersey family. Mr. Felton said yesterday afternoon that the blaze appeared to have started when a final tear gas round fired into the house landed on a bed.</p>
        <p>On learning that his brother, who was 29 and had a 7-month-old daughter, was killed by a colleague's bullet, Michael Brinkerhoff, who lives in the Buffalo area, said in a telephone interview: ''It doesn't change anything. Regardless of how it went down, I still believe it was the result of Travis Trim's actions.''</p>
        <p>Similarly, Gov. Eliot Spitzer said in a written statement that ''nothing should detract from Trooper Brinkerhoff's honor and dedication to duty, or that of his fellow M.R.T. team members,'' referring to the state police Mobile Response Team. He added, ''We owe this fallen trooper and his colleagues a full appraisal of the facts as well as our continuing respect and gratitude.''</p>
        <p>While deaths by fire from comrades are common in war zones, they are less so among police officers in the United States. Since 1893, there have been 198 such fatalities, according to the National Law Enforcement Officers Memorial Fund. Since 2000, 18 such deaths have been documented.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trim's family and friends portrayed him this week as a troubled man with a paranoid disposition and a recent history of drug use. He had no felony convictions, and those who knew him expressed shock that he was capable of shooting a police officer.</p>
        <p>The police say they do not know why he was in a remote corner of the Catskills, almost 300 miles from his home in upstate New York near the Canada border. He apparently stole a Dodge Caravan minivan from a friend at the State University of New York campus in Canton on April 20, and Trooper Gombosi pulled him over on Tuesday in Margaretville because the van's license plate was missing, the police said.</p>
        <p>Responding to the developments in the case yesterday, Mr. Trim's grandmother, Ruth Trim of Dickinson Center, N.Y., told The Associated Press: ''It would make me feel a lot better, but I'm still disgusted that he would be shooting at troopers. We need our troopers. It's an awful world out there.''</p>
        <p>At the news conference, Mr. Felton said the police had not completed their analysis of the shootout, but based on the information from an autopsy and a preliminary forensic review, he said the fatal wound to Trooper Brinkerhoff was ''made by a .223 tactical round, and this round is believed to have been fired'' by a member of the Mobile Response Team, an elite group akin to a SWAT team. The troopers had been drawn to the house by a tripped burglar alarm.</p>
        <p>He said Trooper Mattson had been ''shot in the arm by the assailant,'' possibly by Mr. Trim's .30-30 rifle.</p>
        <p>Seven troopers in all were in the house during the gunfight, and four of them fired their weapons, discharging a total of 69 rounds. Mr. Felton said it was unclear who first entered the room where Mr. Trim was clutching the rifle. But he said that Trooper Brinkerhoff was probably the first to realize that Mr. Trim had opened fire.</p>
        <p>''In a firefight such as this, Trooper Brinkerhoff was struck in the chest and was knocked back to one knee,'' Mr. Felton said. ''Other members came to his aid and started to return fire at the shooter, and at some point Trooper Brinkerhoff ended up getting hit with a round somewhere across the line of fire.'' He said that Trooper Brinkerhoff had been wearing his Kevlar helmet.</p>
        <p>''There is no more volatile or unpredictable situation than one presented by an unstable individual who is heavily armed and intent on causing harm,'' Mr. Felton said.</p>
        <p>''This is made even more serious when that individual has exhibited an inclination to harm police officers,'' he said, adding, ''Tragedy is often the result, as it was here.''</p>
        <p>Last fall Trooper Brinkerhoff spent days tracking another fugitive, Ralph J. Phillips, who, in a strange foreshadowing of the Travis Trim case, had killed one state trooper and shot two others. But after learning that his wife, Barbara, was about to give birth, Trooper Brinkerhoff left the manhunt to return home, and Mr. Phillips, who is known as Bucky, was captured the day Trooper Brinkerhoff's daughter was born.</p>
        <p>Trooper Brinkerhoff is to be buried on Wednesday near Coxsackie, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 2, 2007, Wednesday  A front-page article on Saturday about an announcement by the New York State Police that the bullet that killed a trooper during a shootout with a fugitive in a Catskills farmhouse came from the gun of a fellow trooper -- not from the fugitive -- gave an incorrect surname at one point in some copies for the acting state police superintendent. He is Preston L. Felton, not Mr. Preston.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 2, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A front-page article on Saturday about an announcement by the New York State Police that the bullet that killed a trooper during a shootout with a fugitive in a Catskills farmhouse came from the gun of a fellow trooper -- not from the fugitive -- gave an incorrect surname at one point in some copies for the acting state police superintendent. He is Preston L. Felton, not Mr. Preston.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
