<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Corzine Says He Will Leave The Hospital Within Days</title>
    <meta content="28corzine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/nyregion/28corzine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070501T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843447"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E7D6123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="999" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Corzine Says He Will Leave The Hospital Within Days</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Corzine Says He Will Leave the Hospital Soon</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID KOCIENIEWSKI and DAVID W. CHEN; David Kocieniewski reported from Camden, and David W. Chen from Trenton.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kocieniewski, David; Chen, David W</byline>
      <dateline>CAMDEN, N.J., April 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Jon S. Corzine told the state's top two legislators on Friday that he expected to be released from the hospital on Tuesday or Wednesday and that he would continue his recuperation at Drumthwacket, the governor's mansion in Princeton, instead of at the Hoboken condominium where he lives.</p>
        <p>The State Senate president, Richard J. Codey, who is serving as acting governor, and Assembly Speaker Joseph J. Roberts Jr. were the first elected officials to meet with the governor since he was seriously injured in a traffic accident on April 12.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New Jersey’s top two legislators said Gov. Jon S. Corzine was not interested in talking about policy or politics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Jon S. Corzine told the state's top two legislators on Friday that he expected to be released from the hospital on Tuesday or Wednesday and that he would continue his recuperation at Drumthwacket, the governor's mansion in Princeton, instead of at the Hoboken condominium where he lives.</p>
        <p>The State Senate president, Richard J. Codey, who is serving as acting governor, and Assembly Speaker Joseph J. Roberts Jr. were the first elected officials to meet with the governor since he was seriously injured in a traffic accident on April 12.</p>
        <p>Mr. Codey and Mr. Roberts -- both Democrats, like Mr. Corzine -- spent about 30 minutes in Mr. Corzine's room at Cooper University Hospital here, and they said he was not interested in talking about politics.</p>
        <p>Instead, Mr. Corzine told them that he saw himself as a changed man since the accident. The governor also said he would take at least another week before deciding when he would resume his official duties.</p>
        <p>''I think that he views this, very literally, as a second lease on life,'' Mr. Roberts said. ''In many ways, I think Governor Corzine is a different person than he was before all this happened.'' Mr. Codey added, ''He told me, 'I've never been at peace with myself the way I have been since this happened.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Codey said that when he mentioned critical news articles about the circumstances of the accident, Mr. Corzine replied, ''Those things don't matter to me the way they did before.'' Articles have focused on the fact that Mr. Corzine was not wearing a seat belt, as state law requires, and that his state vehicle was traveling at 91 miles per hour, 26 m.p.h. above the limit.</p>
        <p>For now, Mr. Corzine -- who broke 11 ribs, his left femur, clavicle, sternum and a lower vertebra -- told the lawmakers he would focus on settling into Drumthwacket, an 1835 Greek Revival mansion that must be modified to accommodate the governor's rehabilitation equipment and his limited mobility.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine will pay for his medical treatment, which could total hundreds of thousands of dollars, even though he is covered by the state health insurance plan, said Anthony Coley, the governor's communications director.</p>
        <p>The governor just bought a van with his money that will be modified to make traveling easier for someone using a walker, and he plans to renovate the executive mansion's pool to make it heated for use during physical therapy, Mr. Coley said.</p>
        <p>Since Drumthwacket does not have an elevator, a staircase will be equipped with a mechanical lift to allow the governor to travel up to the private second-floor residence, Mr. Coley added.</p>
        <p>The medical bills won't hurt Mr. Corzine's bank account much. In his 2005 financial disclosure with the United States Senate, where he served before being elected governor, Mr. Corzine reported assets valued at up to $261 million. Last year, he earned an estimated $6.1 million from his investments. He is eligible to make $175,000 a year as governor, but is accepting only $1.</p>
        <p>Mr. Codey and Mr. Roberts -- who brought a get-well card larger than a tabloid newspaper signed by Democrats in the Assembly -- said they were impressed by Mr. Corzine's vigor. The visit came one day after Mr. Corzine sat for his first news photograph since the accident. In it, he wore red workout pants and a polo shirt and hardly looked as if he had suffered life-threatening injuries just two weeks before.</p>
        <p>''I expected to see him tentative and frail, and I did not see that,'' Mr. Roberts said. ''He was himself in every way.'' Mr. Codey agreed: ''He looks very good. He sounds very good.''</p>
        <p>Contradicting reports from Mr. Corzine's aides earlier this week that the governor does not remember the accident, which occurred on the Garden State Parkway, just north of Atlantic City, the legislators said he talked about it with them on Friday.</p>
        <p>The governor told them that he had been taking notes just before the crash. He also said that he was grateful that State Trooper Robert J. Rasinski, who was driving the Chevrolet Suburban, spun the vehicle so that the initial impact did not occur where the governor was sitting.</p>
        <p>''He couldn't have been more praiseworthy of the troopers who were with him that night,'' Mr. Codey said of Mr. Corzine. ''As far as he's concerned, the trooper was a hero for putting his life on the line, and probably saved his life.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine sat up in a chair and ate a cheeseburger on Tuesday and took his first steps with the aid of a walker on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Or so the public has been told. Mr. Corzine was kept out of view until Thursday, when an Associated Press photographer was granted five minutes to take a few still pictures. The governor has not spoken with reporters since the accident.</p>
        <p>Jennifer Duffy, a senior editor with the Cook Political Report, a nonpartisan newsletter in Washington, said that the Corzine administration's initial reports that the governor's injuries were not life-threatening -- soon contradicted by his doctors -- ''damaged his credibility a little bit.''</p>
        <p>''So when he's ready to go back to work, he's got to be really ready,'' she said, ''because people are going to wonder.''</p>
        <p>Justin Blake, an executive vice president with the public relations firm Edelman, and an expert in crisis management, praised the way Mr. Corzine's recuperation has been handled.</p>
        <p>''I think the strategy was totally spot-on for yesterday's photo op,'' he said on Friday. ''While news organizations might be frustrated by the staged nature of it, I think people understand that his recovery is paramount. This is a man who might look vigorous but is still recovering, and I think people were glad to see him looking well.''</p>
        <p>During Mr. Corzine's recuperation, there are no plans to limit public access to Drumthwacket, which welcomes visitors every Wednesday, said Beverly Mills, executive director of the Drumthwacket Foundation.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 1, 2007, Tuesday  An article on Saturday about plans by the injured New Jersey governor, Jon S. Corzine, to leave a Camden hospital early this week and continue his recovery at Drumthwacket, the governor's mansion in Princeton, gave an erroneous figure in some copies for the estimated value of his assets, as reported in a 2005 financial disclosure form for the United States Senate, where he served before being elected governor. He said his assets were worth up to $261 million, not up to $61 million. An article about Governor Corzine's discharge from the hospital yesterday appears today on Page B1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 1, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article on Saturday about plans by the injured New Jersey governor, Jon S. Corzine, to leave a Camden hospital early this week and continue his recovery at Drumthwacket, the governor's mansion in Princeton, gave an erroneous figure in some copies for the estimated value of his assets, as reported in a 2005 financial disclosure form for the United States Senate, where he served before being elected governor. He said his assets were worth up to $261 million, not up to $61 million. An article about Governor Corzine's discharge from the hospital yesterday appears today on Page B1.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
