<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hazy Clouds of Sound, Halfway Intelligible Vocals</title>
    <meta content="28deer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/arts/music/28deer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843340"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Pop</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Rock Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rock Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E1DA123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="459" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hazy Clouds of Sound, Halfway Intelligible Vocals</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hazy Clouds of Sound, Halfway Intelligible Vocals</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KELEFA SANNEH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanneh, Kelefa</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Was that blood? Probably not, but it wasn't easy to tell. Bradford Cox was onstage at the Mercury Lounge on Thursday night, leading his Atlanta-based band, Deerhunter, through an impressive and slightly disconcerting set. The place was packed, though it got a bit less packed as the night wore on.</p>
        <p>No doubt some of the people were there out of curiosity: Deerhunter's immersive ''Cryptograms'' (Kranky), released in January, has emerged as one of the year's most talked-about indie-rock albums, and the music Web site Pitchfork has been particularly enthusiastic. But Deerhunter isn't the kind of band that aims to convert casual (or unadventurous) listeners, and in any case the live show is much more savage than the album.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Was that blood? Probably not, but it wasn’t easy to tell with the Atlanta-based band Deerhunter onstage at the Mercury Lounge on Thursday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Was that blood? Probably not, but it wasn't easy to tell. Bradford Cox was onstage at the Mercury Lounge on Thursday night, leading his Atlanta-based band, Deerhunter, through an impressive and slightly disconcerting set. The place was packed, though it got a bit less packed as the night wore on.</p>
        <p>No doubt some of the people were there out of curiosity: Deerhunter's immersive ''Cryptograms'' (Kranky), released in January, has emerged as one of the year's most talked-about indie-rock albums, and the music Web site Pitchfork has been particularly enthusiastic. But Deerhunter isn't the kind of band that aims to convert casual (or unadventurous) listeners, and in any case the live show is much more savage than the album.</p>
        <p>So: that red stuff, whatever it was, was all over Mr. Cox's face and hands. And while his bandmates struck up a series of brisk, efficient grooves, he put a microphone through its paces, often processing his yelps using digital effects; sometimes the microphone disappeared into his mouth entirely, like some small but dangerous animal looking for a warm home. Mr. Cox is, as he once put it, ''really, really thin,'' and he's a riveting presence onstage, careering into his nonchalant bandmates with that cord coming out of his mouth.</p>
        <p>''Cryptograms'' is the second full-length Deerhunter album, and it demonstrates that a once-jagged band has fallen hard for haziness. Clouds of sound slowly form and dissipate, and Mr. Cox's processed vocals are only half intelligible, or less than half. Some songs, like the furious ''Lake Somerset,'' seem propelled by some obscure malevolent energy; others, like the dreamy ''Hazel St.,'' are pretty and open-ended. A new mini-CD, ''Fluorescent Grey'' (Kranky), includes ''Like New,'' which is unexpectedly soft and delicate, but just as mysterious.</p>
        <p>For years, Pitchfork's reviews have been indie rock's most influential, and a glowing review can earn a formerly obscure band lots of attention, not all of it kind. In the case of Deerhunter, boosters and bashers alike are waiting to see what happens next. What exactly is a high Pitchfork score worth these days? How many people want to watch a man eat a microphone? How big a venue can Deerhunter sell out? And how many people will last till the end?</p>
        <p>Needless to say, none of this is Deerhunter's fault. Certainly the members didn't look very concerned on Thursday night. If they had seen the industry-heavy room get a little roomier during their set, they probably would have been amused. And while it's easy to chuckle at the microcycles of praise and backlash that characterize the Internet music age, it's not hard to see the upside. In an earlier era, a weird, intense band like Deerhunter might well have remained a secret. Not these days.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
