<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Warriors Have Toppled Bay Area Pecking Order</title>
    <meta content="28warriors" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843428"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Dallas Mavericks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Golden State Warriors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E6D7123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="863" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Warriors Have Toppled Bay Area Pecking Order</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beck, Howard</byline>
      <dateline>OAKLAND, Calif., April 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The bridge linking the Golden State Warriors' last heyday to their current renaissance starts with Don Nelson and ends with Don Nelson, with nothing but potholes in between.</p>
        <p>The potholes had names, most of them long forgotten -- Felton Spencer, Carlos Rogers, Victor Alexander, Donald Royal, Todd Fuller, Duane Ferrell, Rusty LaRue, Cedric Henderson, Vonteego Cummings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The bridge linking the Golden State Warriors' last heyday to their current renaissance starts with Don Nelson and ends with Don Nelson, with nothing but potholes in between.</p>
        <p>The potholes had names, most of them long forgotten -- Felton Spencer, Carlos Rogers, Victor Alexander, Donald Royal, Todd Fuller, Duane Ferrell, Rusty LaRue, Cedric Henderson, Vonteego Cummings.</p>
        <p>Others are remembered all too well, for all the wrong reasons -- the coach-choking star guard (Latrell Sprewell), the hapless general manager (Garry St. Jean), the budding superstar who got away (Gilbert Arenas).</p>
        <p>Bad trades, bad attitudes and bad luck filled the 13 years between Warriors playoff appearances. But there was a simple, charming symmetry when the Warriors -- in their first home playoff game in more than a decade -- took the court Friday night against the Dallas Mavericks.</p>
        <p>Nelson strode the sideline, much as he did in 1994, if perhaps a little more slowly. The most celebrated figure in the arena was Chris Mullin -- now the executive vice president, then a sweet-shooting small forward.</p>
        <p>For a fiercely loyal fan base, the night figured to be a raucous, deafening celebration -- a group primal scream to end more than a dozen years of angst and humiliation.</p>
        <p>''I have an idea,'' Nelson said, anticipating what the game meant here. ''I think this place is going to be rocking. It's been a long time since we've played a game like this.''</p>
        <p>The last foray into the postseason ended in a 3-0 sweep by the Phoenix Suns. Compared with the infamy and misery that followed, that seems like the good old days.</p>
        <p>''I remember -- it's like yesterday, man,'' said Mavericks Coach Avery Johnson, who was a 29-year-old point guard for that Warriors team.</p>
        <p>There was a lot of promise then. The Warriors won 50 games behind the dynamic floor play of Sprewell and the low-post presence of their prized rookie, Chris Webber, the No. 1 pick of the 1993 draft.</p>
        <p>''We had a pretty good year that year,'' Johnson said, smiling.</p>
        <p>A thousand things had changed since Nelson and Mullin last united to make the Warriors respectable. None of them were good.</p>
        <p>Nelson, who was also the general manager, famously clashed with Webber and in November 1994 traded him to Washington for Tom Gugliotta. Two months later, Nelson stepped down as the coach and general manager. Days later, the franchise traded Gugliotta for Donyell Marshall, continuing a string of ill-conceived trades that stemmed from the rash decision to dump Webber.</p>
        <p>In the years that followed, Webber blossomed into an All-Star for the Sacramento Kings, upstaging the Warriors from 70 miles up the road. Nelson rebuilt the Mavericks into a Western Conference powerhouse. Sprewell -- who in 1997 choked Coach P. J. Carlesimo -- was sent to the Knicks in another lopsided trade that netted the Warriors only spare parts. Sprewell became an instant folk hero in New York.</p>
        <p>And the Warriors slipped further and further in the Bay Area sports pecking order. The San Francisco 49ers had their five Super Bowl championships and the Oakland Raiders had their mystique, the Giants had Barry Bonds and the Athletics had their plucky, low-budget playoff teams and their ''Moneyball'' general manager. On any given day, the Warriors could be overshadowed by Stanford football, Cal basketball or even the N.H.L.'s San Jose Sharks.</p>
        <p>Even the Warriors' arena, gutted and renovated in 1997, spoke to their relative anonymity in the marketplace. For years, it was called simply, somewhat pathetically, The New Arena in Oakland.</p>
        <p>It is now known as the Oracle Arena, bearing the moniker of a software giant whose very name implies divine wisdom.</p>
        <p>The turnaround began in earnest last summer, when Mullin brought back Nelson, his former coach and longtime friend. The bigger splash came in January, when Mullin sent two of his favorite players, forwards Troy Murphy and Mike Dunleavy, to the Indiana Pacers in a blockbuster trade that brought Al Harrington and Stephen Jackson to Oakland.</p>
        <p>The new Nelson-led Warriors bear some similarity to the Nelson-led Warriors of the early 1990s. They play small, with the 6-foot-8 Harrington holding down the center position and Jackson playing power forward, where he lines up against the 7-foot Mavericks All-Star Dirk Nowitzki. Guards Baron Davis, Jason Richardson and Monta Ellis, round out the league's smallest starting unit. Nelson's gimmickry, deployed properly, still produces entertaining results.</p>
        <p>Still, it took a victory in Portland on the final night of the regular season to clinch the final playoff spot and end the N.B.A.'s longest postseason drought. Amazingly, in the lean years between postseason appearances, the unnamed arena remained mostly full on most nights.</p>
        <p>On the final night of the regular season, 4,000 loyal fans came to the arena, just to watch the Warriors claim a playoff berth on the video scoreboard. Warriors playoff tickets were the hottest and most expensive in any N.B.A. city, according to ticket brokers quoted by The San Francisco Chronicle.</p>
        <p>''Hopefully, we can use that emotion and energy,'' Mullin said, although he was not sure the Warriors had yet repaid the fans for their enduring loyalty through 13 painful seasons. ''I don't think the debt has been paid, but it's at least a little down payment.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
