<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>11 Soldiers Face Charges of Attacking Couple</title>
    <meta content="28drum" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843418"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03EFD8123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="742" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>11 Soldiers Face Charges of Attacking Couple</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MANNY FERNANDEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fernandez, Manny</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A soldier stationed at the Fort Drum Army base in upstate New York and his wife were attacked by nearly a dozen fellow soldiers at the couple's off-base apartment this week in retaliation for a restraining order the wife recently filed against another soldier, the authorities said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The couple -- Carl Laws, 22, and Emily Hernandez, 21 -- were inside their apartment on Virginia Smith Drive in Calcium, N.Y., on Wednesday shortly before 10 p.m., the New York State police said, when a group of soldiers came in and attacked them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A soldier stationed at the Fort Drum Army base in upstate New York and his wife were attacked by nearly a dozen fellow soldiers at the couple's off-base apartment this week in retaliation for a restraining order the wife recently filed against another soldier, the authorities said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The couple -- Carl Laws, 22, and Emily Hernandez, 21 -- were inside their apartment on Virginia Smith Drive in Calcium, N.Y., on Wednesday shortly before 10 p.m., the New York State police said, when a group of soldiers came in and attacked them.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hernandez was punched and struck in the face with a glass bottle. Mr. Laws was knocked down and kicked in the body and in the head. Both were treated at Samaritan Medical Center in Watertown and released, the state police said.</p>
        <p>Eleven soldiers from Fort Drum -- five women and six men -- were arrested on Thursday for their roles in the attack, the authorities said. All were charged with second-degree burglary, and one woman was also charged with second-degree assault for striking Ms. Hernandez with the bottle, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>The military police are not handling the investigation because the attack happened off base, and the state police said more charges were possible. Investigators with the state police in Watertown said the attack stemmed from a restraining order Ms. Hernandez had filed against another soldier, Kerry Q. McCline, 21.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hernandez accused Mr. McCline in court documents of harassing her for about nine months. The restraining order, issued in March, forbids Mr. McCline from communicating in person or by mail, telephone or electronically with Ms. Hernandez. Mr. McCline violated the restraining order on Tuesday night when he called her, the authorities said. He was arrested for criminal contempt, according to the documents, and is in custody awaiting a court hearing Monday. Ms. Hernandez said that she heard Mr. McCline say that he was going to ''burn her place down,'' among other things.</p>
        <p>The state police declined to elaborate on the nature of the dispute between Ms. Hernandez and Mr. McCline. He was not among those who assaulted the couple on Wednesday night, the state police said. Neither Mr. McCline, Mr. Laws nor Ms. Hernandez could be reached for comment last night.</p>
        <p>Fort Drum, a few miles northeast of Watertown, is home to the 10th Mountain Division. More than 7,000 of the 17,000 soldiers at the base are deployed in Iraq and Afghanistan. The 11 soldiers arrested Thursday are members of the division, as is Mr. McCline.</p>
        <p>The state police identified them as: Shalota N. Williams, 22; Tyson D. Tucker, 20; Martin J. Johnson, 22; Jason U. Cofield, 25; Erica S. Hodges, 19; Shavonn D. Wynne, 22; Vianka S. DelCid, 19; Tyrone Lihpai, 22; James E. Skinner, 27; Carlton R. Causey, 28; and Randi G. Bush, 18. The ranks for all the soldiers, including Mr. Laws and Mr. McCline, were not immediately available.</p>
        <p>Ms. Williams, who drove the group to the apartment but did not go inside, and Ms. Hodges, who entered the apartment but did not take part in the attack, were released, investigators said. The others were being held in the Jefferson County jail in $5,000 bail each, including Ms. Wynne, the soldier charged with second-degree assault.</p>
        <p>Benjamin Abel, a Fort Drum spokesman, said the Army was assisting the authorities and conducting its own investigation. He said any disciplinary actions against those arrested would depend on the outcome of the criminal prosecutions. ''Actions like this are completely against the Army values and the high standards that we expect and we see out of our soldiers,'' Mr. Abel said.</p>
        <p>The arrests came as soldiers at the base were already reeling from other grim news. Since April 19, Fort Drum has lost six men at home and abroad.</p>
        <p>A 35-year-old information systems operator, Sgt. Keoki Suerth, was killed April 19 when he lost control of his motorcycle not far from Fort Drum. A 21-year-old 10th Mountain Division soldier, Pvt. Richard W. Therrien of Howell, N.J., died April 20 of unknown causes after he was found unresponsive at a friend's on-base residence. A 35-year-old Army police officer, Charles E. Patterson, was killed April 21 in a motorcycle accident in St. Lawrence County.</p>
        <p>In addition, three 10th Mountain Division soldiers were killed in combat in Iraq: Chief Warrant Officer Dwayne L. Moore, 31, on April 19, and Staff Sgt. Steven R. Tudor, 36, and Cpl. Ray M. Bevel, 22, on April 21.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
