<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Steroids Are a Stain That Is Hard to Erase</title>
    <meta content="28araton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/sports/baseball/28araton.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843462"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Testosterone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Testosterone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Testosterone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hormones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Major League Baseball</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E4D6123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="875" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Steroids Are a Stain That Is Hard to Erase</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Steroids Are a Stain That Is Hard to Erase</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The red-stained sock had its nice little run, but by late yesterday afternoon it was being dismissed as a significant news event by Joe Torre.</p>
        <p>''Ancient history,'' Torre said, a tacit acknowledgment that the issue had long ago been settled and that Red Sox fans -- who for decades were inclined to believe in a dead man's curse -- were not going to let some grandstanding television announcer put a fresh coat of skepticism over their wondrous Curt Schilling saga.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Baseball’s shame of widespread steroid abuse has once again resurfaced in the form of a former Mets clubhouse employee.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The red-stained sock had its nice little run, but by late yesterday afternoon it was being dismissed as a significant news event by Joe Torre.</p>
        <p>''Ancient history,'' Torre said, a tacit acknowledgment that the issue had long ago been settled and that Red Sox fans -- who for decades were inclined to believe in a dead man's curse -- were not going to let some grandstanding television announcer put a fresh coat of skepticism over their wondrous Curt Schilling saga.</p>
        <p>These days there are altogether different levels of baseball believability, ranging from the sweet to the sinister, the dopey to the doping, the lore to the lies.</p>
        <p>If only the sport's shame of widespread steroid use would dry up like the red stuff on Schilling's sock on the October 2004 night he went to the mound at Yankee Stadium and won Game 6 of the American League Championship Series with three sutures to hold dislocated ankle tendons in place.</p>
        <p>If only baseball could stop the ongoing scandal from springing leaks it always fears will turn into the flood. If only it could keep the names of its players out of federal court documents in criminal cases, and keep the focus and the blame for its now-documented era of rampant and unregulated performance enhancement on Barry Bonds.</p>
        <p>Much too conveniently, Bonds has become baseball's appointed pariah, more so as the Balco Bambino bears down on Hank Aaron's career home-run record. But if the commissioner, Bud Selig, doesn't wish to watch Bonds slime history based on leaked grand jury testimony and other related evidence that includes no failed drug tests, how many more active major leaguers will he have to steer clear of once Kirk J. Radomski gets done talking?</p>
        <p>Radomski , 37, admitted to the felony charges of distributing steroids and laundering money yesterday in San Francisco. He is a former Mets clubhouse employee, another person we never heard of until he showed up in federal court yesterday, accused of distributing to dozens of major leaguers all those now-familiar baseball scourges: deca-durabolin, testosterone, human growth hormone.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors said Radomski began peddling illegal substances in 1995 and continued until 2005, reportedly expanding his business after the rival Bay Area Laboratory Cooperative was shut down. None of the players he serviced were named, but we've seen this drill before: their identities were redacted on the court documents, whetting our imaginations for the news bulletins to come.</p>
        <p>So set your timer to see how long it takes before more names begin finding their way into print.</p>
        <p>Or maybe this time, those names will soon be dumped on Selig's desk, if it is true that Radomski, under the conditions of his guilty plea and the instruction of the prosecutors, will cooperate with the in-house investigation baseball has been conducting under the leadership of the former Senator George Mitchell.</p>
        <p>''We are encouraged that the U.S. Attorney has instructed Mr. Radomski to cooperate with Senator George Mitchell's investigation as a condition of the plea agreement,'' Bob Dupuy, baseball's president and chief operating officer, said last night in a statement. ''We urge all personnel connected with Major League Baseball to come forward with whatever information they may have that will assist Senator Mitchell in his investigation.''</p>
        <p>Good luck with that one. Even if Radomski gives every player up, that doesn't mean any of them are likely to walk into Mitchell's office and say, ''O.K., you've got me, what else would you like to know?''</p>
        <p>With a criminal case pending in San Francisco, union lawyers will keep the players quiet, you can count on that. But at the very least, a long list of names -- and possibly those of other distributors and suppliers -- would be the first major break for Mitchell in what has been a frustrating, and most likely futile, process without subpoena power.</p>
        <p>He could wind up with a list that could fill a few rosters. At this point, who knows how many players Radomski did his dirty business with? Three dozen? Four? Six?</p>
        <p>However many are eventually implicated, baseball may finally be close to fully understanding the scope of cheating that its no-test, no-tell policies produced for at least a decade. It may finally have to acknowledge that none of this began with Bonds, and that to hide from his record home runs would be the height of hypocrisy. With some deft handling, some honest reflection, it may even find a way to bring closure to its years of denial and disgrace.</p>
        <p>For now, it's just another leak that threatens to blow the dam, one more shoe dropping like a wind-blown fly while we wait for a meteor to crash.</p>
        <p>Here in New York, Yankee Stadium was packed last night as the surging Red Sox handed the Yankees their seventh straight defeat, pounding them, 11-4. Daisuke Matsuzaka faced Hideki Matsui for the first time in the United States and beat Andy Pettitte, Torre's old reliable.</p>
        <p>Schilling was in town to stare down anyone who would accuse him of painting his sock, of being a fake.</p>
        <p>Across the country, on a Friday afternoon in San Francisco, Kirk Radomski walked into court and admitted to another, more insidious kind of fakery. One more time, the face of the sport was painted red.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
