<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Violent Night, Estonia Removes a Soviet-Era Memorial</title>
    <meta content="28estonia" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/world/europe/28estonia.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843389"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Estonia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tallinn (Estonia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myers, Steven Lee</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Estonia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/Moscow</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Estonia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Estonia/Tallinn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Estonia</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Moscow (Russia)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EFD9123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="559" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Violent Night, Estonia Removes a Soviet-Era Memorial</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After Violent Night, Estonia Removes a Soviet-Era Memorial</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN LEE MYERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Myers, Steven Lee</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, April 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Estonia's government removes Soviet-era war memorial after night of protests and violence that killed one person, injured dozens and left swath of shattered windows and cars overturned in center of capital, Tallinn; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Estonia's government removed a Soviet-era war memorial early on Friday morning after a night of protest and violence that killed one person, injured dozens and left a swath of shattered windows and overturned cars in the center of the capital, Tallinn, officials there said.</p>
        <p>The removal of the monument, which includes a six-and-a-half-foot sculpture known as the Bronze Soldier, prompted a renewed diplomatic fury in neighboring Russia, where officials have repeatedly declared that tampering with the monument amounted to blasphemy and even the glorification of Nazism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The removal of the monument prompted a renewed diplomatic fury in neighboring Russia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Estonia's government removed a Soviet-era war memorial early on Friday morning after a night of protest and violence that killed one person, injured dozens and left a swath of shattered windows and overturned cars in the center of the capital, Tallinn, officials there said.</p>
        <p>The removal of the monument, which includes a six-and-a-half-foot sculpture known as the Bronze Soldier, prompted a renewed diplomatic fury in neighboring Russia, where officials have repeatedly declared that tampering with the monument amounted to blasphemy and even the glorification of Nazism.</p>
        <p>Russia's lower and upper houses of Parliament called on President Vladimir V. Putin to sever relations or to impose sanctions on Estonia, which was part of the Soviet Union from its absorption during World War II until its independence in 1991. The foreign minister, Sergey V. Lavrov, veered from the language of diplomacy to call the monument's removal ''disgusting.''</p>
        <p>The monument, to commemorate the defeat of Nazi Germany, was erected in 1947, at the outset of what most Estonians consider the country's occupation by the Soviet Union. It has been the source of diplomatic tensions for months, reflecting Russia's uneasy relations with the former Soviet republics or satellites that have moved to integrate themselves more deeply in the European Union and NATO. Estonia, like Lithuania and Latvia, joined both organizations in 2004.</p>
        <p>As with American plans to base missile defenses in Poland and the Czech Republic, which Mr. Putin sharply denounced Thursday and again on Friday, the fate of the monument has become a proxy for broader grievances with the United States and NATO generally. Mr. Putin's Kremlin has recently shown a willingness to voice those sentiments far more forcefully than in the past.</p>
        <p>''This is blasphemous, and will have serious consequences for our relations with Estonia,'' Mr. Lavrov said during a news conference in Oslo, where he attended a meeting with NATO foreign ministers, according to Interfax.</p>
        <p>The violence erupted late on Thursday after workers erected a fence and a tent around the monument, located in a small triangular park near Tallinn's Old Town. The declared reason was to start excavations to determine whether the remains of Soviet soldiers were buried there, though some suspect that the government's actual intent was to begin the monument's removal. More than 1,000 protesters, most of them apparently Estonians of Russian descent, gathered around the park and soon began to clash with the police, who used tear gas and water cannons as the protest turned to rioting, vandalism and looting.</p>
        <p>''All this had nothing to do with the inviolability of graves or keeping alive the memory of men fallen in World War II,'' the Estonian president, Toomas Hendrik Ilves, said in a statement on Friday. ''The common denominator of last night's criminals was not their nationality, but their desire to riot, vandalize and plunder.'' At least 300 people were detained and most now face criminal charges, the government of Prime Minister Andrus Ansip, who had led the push for the monument's removal, said in a statement. At least 44 protesters and 13 police officers were injured.</p>
        <p>The statement said a fight between young men resulted in the stabbing of one of them, identified only as Dmitri, who died during surgery in a Tallinn hospital. As the violence subsided, Mr. Ansip met with ministers early on Friday and ordered the monument's hasty removal.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
