<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Urban to the Core, Storm Evacuees Give Farming a Try</title>
    <meta content="28village" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/us/28village.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843468"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Katrina (Storm)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mobile Homes and Trailers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organic Foods and Products</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Simmesport (La)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canadaville (La)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Louisiana</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Orleans (La)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eaton, Leslie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stronach, Frank</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana/New Orleans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mobile Homes and Trailers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organic Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mobile Homes and Trailers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Orleans (La)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3D6123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1207" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Urban to the Core, Storm Evacuees Give Farming a Try</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Urban to Core, Storm Evacuees Give Farm a Try</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE EATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eaton, Leslie</byline>
      <dateline>SIMMESPORT, La.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frank Stronach, controversial Canadian automobile-parts magnate, has established $2.4 million farming project just outside Simmesport, La, for Hurricane Katrina evacuees; 791 acres is one of many items procured on behalf of evacuees by Stronach; result is small mobile home park and fledgling organic farm that is called Canadaville; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Faced with the televised devastation of New Orleans and the despair of Hurricane Katrina victims, many people have sent them charitable checks.</p>
        <p>Frank Stronach bought them a $2.4 million farm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Canadian businessman bought former residents of New Orleans a $2.4 million, 791-acre sugar cane field to create “an environment of opportunity.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Faced with the televised devastation of New Orleans and the despair of Hurricane Katrina victims, many people have sent them charitable checks.</p>
        <p>Frank Stronach bought them a $2.4 million farm.</p>
        <p>Well, more of a farm to be, 791 acres of sugar cane fields just outside this town 130 miles northwest of New Orleans. The property is one of the many items, including 49 mobile homes, two police cars and a flock of chickens, procured on behalf of hurricane evacuees by Mr. Stronach, a colorful and controversial Canadian automobile-parts magnate.</p>
        <p>His goal was to create ''an environment of opportunity,'' where former residents of New Orleans could be helped to help themselves, said Dennis J. Mills, who spearheaded the effort and is vice chairman of several Stronach companies. A result is a small mobile home park and a fledgling organic farm that everyone here calls Canadaville.</p>
        <p>The farm has about 190 residents, who have to perform eight hours a week of community service and look for work or go to school. In return, they can live rent free in a three-bedroom two-bath mobile home. A free shuttle bus takes residents to the local Piggly Wiggly supermarket. Weekly outings to the Wal-Mart in Marksville, 20 miles away, cost $5.</p>
        <p>Although not all the residents will become organic farmers, said Shane Carmichael, an events planner from Toronto who manages the project, ''the goal is for everybody at least to do a garden, collect the eggs.''</p>
        <p>So far, the project is a cross-cultural experiment, as residents of some of the most urban and insular neighborhoods of New Orleans are encouraged by PowerPoint-wielding outsiders to till the soil and cultivate crawfish. The program is also coping with longtime residents of the area who liked their small town the way it was and are uncomfortable with the experiment.</p>
        <p>Plunking down traumatized people from the Lower Ninth Ward of New Orleans on a farm in the middle of nowhere may sound like the premise for a reality television show or, as Mr. Carmichael said, ''an African-American version of 'Green Acres,' '' the television series in which Eva Gabor resisted going rustic. The village residents, in fact, while grateful for the generosity, suggest that the situation is odd, and sometimes uncomfortable.</p>
        <p>Allen C. Wyman, who with his family tried to ride out Hurricane Katrina at a house a couple of blocks from the Industrial Canal, was a cook at Harrah's casino in New Orleans. Mr. Wyman is now the manager of the Canadaville demonstration farm.</p>
        <p>Describing his thoughts when he arrived, he said: ''Man, we're in the country. That's not going to last long. The whole kind of plantation vibe was going through people's heads.''</p>
        <p>Though he has grown to like his work, Mr. Wyman is not sure he will stay. For one thing, his wife longs to go home to New Orleans. ''And wherever her heart leads her,'' he said, ''I'm right behind.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stronach is involved in a bid to buy Chrysler, and an aide said he was too preoccupied to discuss Canadaville. Mr. Mills said the farm experience, which the Stronach companies have promised to support for five years, is meant to be therapeutic and practical; he rejected any suggestion the idea might be paternalistic.</p>
        <p>''We've heard that from people who weren't really involved in the desperation that existed at the moment,'' Mr. Mills said. ''There's nothing paternalistic about our attempt to create an environment outside of the hurricane zone.''</p>
        <p>New Orleans ''was underwater,'' he said, adding, ''We did the best we could with the land we could find.''</p>
        <p>Some residents seem determined to grab every opportunity that the philanthropists have offered and are encouraging others to do the same. Especially Lisa A. Johnson, who fled the storm with her husband, two children ''and three hundred and some dollars in our pockets,'' she said.</p>
        <p>A manager at a fancy hotel in New Orleans, Ms. Johnson is now the office manager at Canadaville. ''I tell them, 'You can be whatever you want to be,' '' she said of her fellow residents.</p>
        <p>Her goal, she says, is to open a jewelry business -- if she does not run for mayor of Simmesport in a few years.</p>
        <p>That position may indeed be vacant, because Mayor James T. Fontenot is threatening to leave town if Canadaville grows any bigger. A Simmesport native, Mr. Fontenot said he had cautiously welcomed as many as 300 new residents to his town of 2,300.</p>
        <p>Now, he said, he is disillusioned. He says the philanthropists have not lived up to their promises. He received the police cars, for example, but not money for officers' salaries.</p>
        <p>Worse, he said, the influx from New Orleans has changed the small-town atmosphere, and he faults the urbanites for increases in fistfights and business break-ins. Evoking his own set of television references, Mr. Fontenot said, ''I used to call this town Mayberry R.F.D. Now I call it Peyton Place.''</p>
        <p>The problem is not that the newcomers are mostly black, said the mayor, who is white.</p>
        <p>''Simmesport is about half black,'' he said. ''It's taking people from an urban environment with a McDonalds or Burger King on every corner, lots of entertainment, and putting them in a cane field.''</p>
        <p>The accusations are unfair, Mr. Carmichael said. Although some residents have been asked to leave because of drug use, he said, any problems ''have been more around the social compact, not keeping the house clean, music at all hours of the night, not going out to get a job.''</p>
        <p>As former cane fields go, Canadaville's is beautiful, studded with pecan trees and live oaks. One shallow pond is for raising crawfish; another is for catfish. Tidy fences pen the chickens and some goats.</p>
        <p>The roomy homes, tan or grey rectangles, all have porches and foundation plantings. Some have little decorative shutters. It is a far cry from the bleak government trailer parks for evacuees.</p>
        <p>In a field on the road to downtown Simmesport, a shiny sign promises the community center, a baseball diamond, tennis courts, a swimming pool and sports fields. But the park is limited so far to a basketball court with lights, and there is not much for children to do, residents say.</p>
        <p>Of course, as the mayor pointed out, there is not much for adults to do, either, at least not by New Orleans standards. The choices including visiting a wildlife management area north of town, attending church and stopping in for a snack of pickled pigs lips at Bordelon's Superette.</p>
        <p>Nor has finding employment been easy, residents say. Fishing, logging and working at prisons are the traditional occupations in Simmesport, which is home to a women's prison. The state penitentiary in Angola is not far away.</p>
        <p>Farming does not seem to be an alluring vocation to many at Canadaville. Few want to raise chickens, said Harold Brooks, vice president of the residents' association. ''We cook chickens,'' Mr. Brooks said. Asked whether the farm concept was a good fit with the evacuees' needs, Mr. Carmichael said its biggest benefit was instilling a strong work ethic.</p>
        <p>''That's what we're about,'' he said. ''You're in charge of your own destiny, and as soon as you're ready to move to a higher level, good luck with it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
