<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scolded by Nascar, Stewart Backs Off Criticism</title>
    <meta content="28nascar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/sports/othersports/28nascar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843399"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Officiating (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn of Stock Car Auto Racing</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Stewart, Tony</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E6D8123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="633" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scolded by Nascar, Stewart Backs Off Criticism</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Scolded by Nascar, Stewart Backs Off Criticism</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAY GLIER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glier, Ray</byline>
      <dateline>TALLADEGA, Ala., April 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three days after accusing Nascar of using bogus caution flags to create more competitive racing and likening the sport to professional wrestling, Tony Stewart emerged from a meeting with Nascar officials Friday morning and said he had it all wrong.</p>
        <p>Stewart criticized Nascar on his satellite radio show Tuesday night, but his position had drastically changed after a meeting at 6 a.m. with Nascar officials, who would not allow Stewart's team to unload his car for Sunday's race here until Stewart went to the meeting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three days after likening the sport to professional wrestling, Tony Stewart emerged from a meeting with Nascar officials saying he had it all wrong.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three days after accusing Nascar of using bogus caution flags to create more competitive racing and likening the sport to professional wrestling, Tony Stewart emerged from a meeting with Nascar officials Friday morning and said he had it all wrong.</p>
        <p>Stewart criticized Nascar on his satellite radio show Tuesday night, but his position had drastically changed after a meeting at 6 a.m. with Nascar officials, who would not allow Stewart's team to unload his car for Sunday's race here until Stewart went to the meeting.</p>
        <p>''Tuesday night I was sick and still ended up saying things that I didn't want to say or shouldn't have said and got in trouble for,'' Stewart said. ''The meeting this morning was a good meeting. It's a little tender for me to sit down right now.''</p>
        <p>Stewart, a two-time series champion, met with Nascar's president, Mike Helton; Robin Pemberton, the vice president for competition; and John Darby, the Nascar Nextel Cup series director. Those three officials are in the scoring tower and part of the team that decides when caution flags should come out on the track.</p>
        <p>On his radio show Tuesday, Stewart said Nascar officials used the excuse of debris on the track to wave caution flags and bunch up the field to create closer racing.</p>
        <p>''I don't know that they have run a fair race all year,'' Stewart said on his show.</p>
        <p>Stewart finished second in the race at Phoenix on Saturday night after leading 132 laps. He did not attend a postrace news conference, which drivers are required to do if they finish in the top three. He was fined $10,000 and placed on probation until Dec. 31 for failing to meet news media obligations.</p>
        <p>The timing of caution flags has long been a controversial issue in Nascar, but the criticism has never been so public or been brought by a driver as prominent as Stewart.</p>
        <p>''It's going to be hard to measure whatever impact his comments are going to have on the sport,'' said Jim Hunter, Nascar's vice president for corporate communications. ''It's every sound bite, it's every headline. I don't know what the end result is going to be.''</p>
        <p>On Friday morning, a contrite Stewart said he probably damaged the sport's credibility. ''I'm sure I did hurt the integrity of it, and unfairly,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Stewart said he was satisfied with explanations from Nascar about why they brought out caution flags.</p>
        <p>Other drivers here said that the use of caution flags was a legitimate issue to discuss, but that Stewart might have gone too far with his comments.</p>
        <p>''I didn't agree with his comparison to wrestling and saying Nascar hasn't run a fair race,'' Jeff Burton said. ''The conversations about cautions is O.K. to have. TV is talking about it. I think that's a reasonable conversation. I think he overexaggerated some of the things. I think he meant some good by it.</p>
        <p>''Our sport is an interesting sport. We don't have timeouts; we don't have two-minute warnings. I believe this sport has benefited from having cautions, especially early in the race. Stoppage in play does help how many cars can be competitive. As a rule, it gives more teams a chance to get their stuff together.''</p>
        <p>Jimmie Johnson, the 2006 champion, said it was difficult to say whether there could be a productive discussion with Nascar about the use of caution flags.</p>
        <p>''Everybody has a different opinion about cautions, why they come out, when they come out,'' Johnson said. ''It's tough, but they've done a great job growing our sport year after year.''</p>
        <p>Jamie McMurray said: ''I think everyone wonders sometimes like, 'What was that caution for?' Everyone has joked around about that, but Nascar, typically, when they throw a caution, it's more than likely for a safety reason.''</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
