<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a Switch, Consistency From Pérez Isn't Enough</title>
    <meta content="28mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/sports/baseball/28mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843429"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Washington Nationals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Washington Nationals</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National League</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pérez, Oliver</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6D7123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="756" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a Switch, Consistency From Pérez Isn't Enough</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In a Switch, Consistency From Pérez Isn’t Enough</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shpigel, Ben</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In pondering their 4-3 loss to the Washington Nationals on Friday night, the Mets faced a philosophical dilemma fit for baseball's sages: If Oliver Pérez, the king of inconsistency, pitches well but the team loses, is it a good night?</p>
        <p>The short answer is somewhere between yes and no. The Mets had visions of marching into R.F.K. Stadium and sweeping the last-place Nationals, and losing Friday night ruined those plans. But if they were assured of Pérez pitching like this every time -- seven innings, four runs, nine strikeouts and, yet again, no walks -- they would have to assume that they could usually score more than three runs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Oliver Pérez, the king of inconsistency, pitched well but the Mets couldn’t find the offense to complement his performance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In pondering their 4-3 loss to the Washington Nationals on Friday night, the Mets faced a philosophical dilemma fit for baseball's sages: If Oliver Pérez, the king of inconsistency, pitches well but the team loses, is it a good night?</p>
        <p>The short answer is somewhere between yes and no. The Mets had visions of marching into R.F.K. Stadium and sweeping the last-place Nationals, and losing Friday night ruined those plans. But if they were assured of Pérez pitching like this every time -- seven innings, four runs, nine strikeouts and, yet again, no walks -- they would have to assume that they could usually score more than three runs.</p>
        <p>After allowing a three-run homer to Austin Kearns in the first, Pérez regrouped to allow only four base-runners until Ryan Church hit a run-scoring single in the sixth. In his last 13 2/3 innings, Pérez has struck out 18 batters and walked none.</p>
        <p>''Just trying to be consistent,'' Pérez said.</p>
        <p>The Mets entered Friday with a 5-0 record in games in which the opponent started a left-hander, and boasted the majors' highest average (.352) against lefties. But they were unable to put together any sustained rallies against the rookie left-hander Matt Chico and floundered against the Nationals' bullpen. They scored single runs in the third, fourth and eighth, and stranded nine runners on base, including the tying run on second with no outs in the eighth.</p>
        <p>''It's a frustrating loss,'' Shawn Green said. ''Oliver did a great job of keeping us in the game, and we couldn't break it open.''</p>
        <p>Mired in a 2-for-25 funk, David Wright led off the eighth against the Nationals' 6-11 right-hander, Jon Rauch, by ripping a double into the right-field corner. His approach during the at-bat -- letting the ball get deep, then lining it to the opposite field -- suggested he was emerging from his tailspin. Wright scored on Moises Alou's double, bringing up Green.</p>
        <p>He wanted to hit the ball on the ground to the right side and move Alou to third, but after falling behind, 0-2, he said he tried to make contact. He flied out. After José Valentín flied out, Manager Willie Randolph tapped Julio Franco, a right-handed hitter, to pinch-hit for Pérez. Randolph had left-handed options on the bench in Endy Chávez and David Newhan.</p>
        <p>''Franco's my best pinch-hitter,'' Randolph said.</p>
        <p>Franco flied out to end the inning, and the Mets went down in order in the ninth against closer Chad Cordero.</p>
        <p>''We were kind of in an uphill battle all game,'' Wright said. ''We had our chances, we just couldn't cash in.''</p>
        <p>The lack of clutch hitting prevented Pérez from leaving the game with more than just confidence. Coming off an outstanding performance Saturday against the Braves, when he also struck out nine without walking a batter in six and two-thirds innings, Pérez faced an important start. Another solid outing would help to prove that he is coming around. A not-so-solid one would give credence to the idea that he may always be unpredictable.</p>
        <p>''If he goes out there and throws a gem, that doesn't necessarily mean that he'll do it next time,'' Randolph said before the game.</p>
        <p>Asked how many starts Pérez needed to make before he could get a good read on him, Randolph said: ''At least the All-Star break. When you're a young player, you're never really out of the woods.''</p>
        <p>That was the case in the first inning, when Pérez allowed two singles within the first four batters to bring up the Nationals' hottest hitter, Kearns, with two outs.</p>
        <p>He sent a 1-1 splitter deep over the left-center field fence for a three-run homer, marking the first time the Nationals had scored in the first inning this season, ending a National League-record 22 consecutive games to begin the season.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Mike Pelfrey jeopardized his spot in the rotation after allowing six runs in three innings Wednesday to raise his earned run average to 7.90, but General Manager Omar Minaya and Manager Willie Randolph discussed the situation and decided to give him another start, Tuesday against the Florida Marlins at Shea Stadium. ''I think it's all been a mental thing with me,'' Pelfrey said. ''I made the mental commitment in spring training, and the results were there. I need to continually go out there and pitch how I know I can pitch.'' The Class AAA outfielder Lastings Milledge will miss four to six weeks after spraining ligaments in his right foot. Minaya said he did not know how Milledge sustained the injury.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
