<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Objected to Cancellation of Bribery Investigation in Britain</title>
    <meta content="28london" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/world/europe/28london.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070502T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843387"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Defense Contracts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Saudi Arabia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bae Systems</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Defense Contracts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Defense Contracts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="online_producer">BAE Systems Plc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFD9123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="537" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Objected to Cancellation of Bribery Investigation in Britain</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Objected to Scuttling of Bribery Inquiry in Britain</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, April 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>British government confirms that it received two diplomatic protests from US in January after it canceled inquiry into allegations of bribery by Britain's top military contractor, BAE Systems, to secure contracts in Saudi Arabia; Britain, with support of Prime Min Tony Blair, canceled its inquiry, saying investigation jeopardized relations with Saudis (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The British government confirmed Friday that it received two diplomatic protests from the United States in January after it canceled an inquiry into allegations of bribery by Britain's top military contractor to secure contracts in Saudi Arabia.</p>
        <p>With the support of Prime Minister Tony Blair, Britain in December canceled its inquiry into allegations that BAE Systems paid bribes to secure those contracts, saying the investigation jeopardized relations with the Saudis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The U.S. protests came after Britain canceled an inquiry into allegations of bribery by Britain’s top military contractor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The British government confirmed Friday that it received two diplomatic protests from the United States in January after it canceled an inquiry into allegations of bribery by Britain's top military contractor to secure contracts in Saudi Arabia.</p>
        <p>With the support of Prime Minister Tony Blair, Britain in December canceled its inquiry into allegations that BAE Systems paid bribes to secure those contracts, saying the investigation jeopardized relations with the Saudis.</p>
        <p>Saudi Arabia had halted negotiations with BAE over a deal to buy 72 Eurofighter Typhoon aircraft, and threatened to switch the contract to a French arms supplier.</p>
        <p>A Foreign Office spokesman, speaking in return for customary anonymity, said Friday that a first ''expression of concern'' was made at a meeting of the Paris-based Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development that was held to assess the way Britain handled the case.</p>
        <p>At that meeting, the United States ''expressed its concern that the investigation had been dropped,'' the British official said. At a later meeting in London, an official from the United States Embassy made the same point to a junior British official. The American was below the rank of ambassador or deputy chief of mission, the British official said. ''It was delivered orally; there was no piece of paper,'' the official said.</p>
        <p>Britain argues that halting its own investigation was in line with practices permitting countries to defend their national interest, and that it did not breach an antibribery convention that the O.E.C.D. oversees.</p>
        <p>''We had already given our response: the decision was based on considerations of national and international security,'' the British official said.</p>
        <p>An American Embassy official with knowledge of the case said Washington's main interest was ''not so much about the case, but about the convention,'' which was established by the O.E.C.D. to combat bribery of foreign public officials in international business transactions.</p>
        <p>''We think it's an important document, an instrument for transparency,'' the official said. The official confirmed that the issue had been discussed in Paris and figured in at least one direct contact with the British.</p>
        <p>The United States wants to determine how the British handling of the BAE case, which covered accusations of bribery under a huge arms contract known as Al Yamamah and spanned 20 years of arms supplies to Saudi Arabia, ''comports with the convention,'' the official said.</p>
        <p>Despite the cancellation of the Saudi inquiry, Britain said in February that the Serious Fraud Office was actively pursuing investigations into allegations of corruption by British companies, including BAE, in Qatar, South Africa, Tanzania, Romania, Chile and the Czech Republic.</p>
        <p>Britain stopped the Saudi investigation, saying it would damage Britain's cooperation with Saudi Arabia in gathering intelligence about Al Qaeda and cut off a crucial source of intelligence from the Middle East.</p>
        <p>Lobbyists opposed to the inquiry said a loss of the Eurofighter contract would cost thousands of British jobs and jeopardize British efforts to maintain access to a major arms market.</p>
        <p>At the time, Lord Peter Goldsmith, the attorney general, announced the cancellation of the inquiry with the words: ''It has been necessary to balance the rule of law against the wider public interest. No weight has been given to commercial interests or to the national economic interest.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 2, 2007, Wednesday  An article on Saturday about American diplomatic protests over the cancellation of a British government inquiry into bribery by BAE Systems, Britain's top military contractor, to secure contracts in Saudi Arabia, misattributed the announcement of the cancellation when it was first made in January. It was made by the Serious Fraud Office -- not by Lord Peter Goldsmith, the attorney general.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 10, 2007, Thursday  An article on April 28 about American diplomatic protests over the cancellation of a British government inquiry into bribery by BAE Systems, Britain's top military contractor, to secure contracts in Saudi Arabia, misattributed the announcement of the cancellation. Also, because of an editing error, a correction in this space on May 2 misstated the month the announcement was made. The Serious Fraud Office made the announcement, not Lord Peter Goldsmith, the attorney general. The announcement was made in December, not January.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 2, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article on Saturday about American diplomatic protests over the cancellation of a British government inquiry into bribery by BAE Systems, Britain's top military contractor, to secure contracts in Saudi Arabia, misattributed the announcement of the cancellation when it was first made in January. It was made by the Serious Fraud Office -- not by Lord Peter Goldsmith, the attorney general.</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>Correction: May 10, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article on April 28 about American diplomatic protests over the cancellation of a British government inquiry into bribery by BAE Systems, Britain's top military contractor, to secure contracts in Saudi Arabia, misattributed the announcement of the cancellation. Also, because of an editing error, a correction in this space on May 2 misstated the month the announcement was made. The Serious Fraud Office made the announcement, not Lord Peter Goldsmith, the attorney general. The announcement was made in December, not January.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
