<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Ratings System, Built To Endure</title>
    <meta content="28lega" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/movies/28lega.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843365"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEWS ANALYSIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Valenti, Jack</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE4D9123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="860" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Ratings System, Built To Endure</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Ratings System, Built to Endure</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL CIEPLY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cieply, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, April 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As David S. Goyer readied his new movie for release this weekend, he joined the long list of filmmakers who have been frustrated, flummoxed or downright infuriated by what may turn out to be Jack Valenti's most enduring legacy, the film rating system.</p>
        <p>On its first run through the ratings board, Mr. Goyer's ''Invisible,'' a supernatural thriller whose central characters are teenagers and that deals with teenage suicide, was assigned an R for, among other things, what Mr. Goyer described as ''dark themes.'' Some tinkering and a bit of dialogue with the raters eventually got the movie its PG-13 rating, essential if its young target audience were ever to see it in theaters. But not before the director had spent considerable time puzzling over a ratings rationale that seemed ambiguous enough to have put the tale of the sad orphan in ''Bambi'' at risk of an R.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many filmmakers have been frustrated, flummoxed or downright infuriated by what may turn out to be Jack Valenti’s most enduring legacy, the film rating system.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As David S. Goyer readied his new movie for release this weekend, he joined the long list of filmmakers who have been frustrated, flummoxed or downright infuriated by what may turn out to be Jack Valenti's most enduring legacy, the film rating system.</p>
        <p>On its first run through the ratings board, Mr. Goyer's ''Invisible,'' a supernatural thriller whose central characters are teenagers and that deals with teenage suicide, was assigned an R for, among other things, what Mr. Goyer described as ''dark themes.'' Some tinkering and a bit of dialogue with the raters eventually got the movie its PG-13 rating, essential if its young target audience were ever to see it in theaters. But not before the director had spent considerable time puzzling over a ratings rationale that seemed ambiguous enough to have put the tale of the sad orphan in ''Bambi'' at risk of an R.</p>
        <p>''The paradox is, the more realistically and more accurately you try to portray something, the heavier it becomes,'' said Mr. Goyer, whose film opened on Friday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Valenti, who died on Thursday at 85, created what is officially named the Classification and Rating Administration 38 years ago in one of his first policy initiatives upon taking charge of the Motion Picture Association of America. Since then the ratings board has been accused of Star Chamber-like censorship, compared to a fussy church lady tougher on sex than violence, and perennially second-guessed in its decisions.</p>
        <p>But the system is almost certain to long survive Mr. Valenti. And that is precisely because of a remarkable fluidity -- some would say capriciousness -- that would have let it shut the young out of ''The Invisible'' this year if not for the director's changes, while having waived such changes two years before, in the PG-13-rated ''Batman Begins,'' of which Mr. Goyer was a writer.</p>
        <p>''In the end, it endures because it works,'' Sidney Ganis, a film producer and president of the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences, said of the ratings system. For the major studios the system has been a bulwark against outside interference, though it has often galled filmmakers and hasn't done enough for many parents, who increasingly want to know more about what their children are going to see in a picture. When the ratings administration was founded, in 1968, two years after Mr. Valenti joined the movie association, it warded off a threatened surge in locally imposed ratings. In later years periodic retooling -- like a 1996 shift in which NC-17 became more restrictive by switching its prohibition from those under 17 to those 17 and under -- helped to keep the culture wars and the politicians at bay.</p>
        <p>That did not happen, of course, without a thwacking now and then by sophisticates, as in Kirby Dick's 2006 documentary critique, ''This Film Is Not Yet Rated,'' or an occasional accommodation of the family-values crowd, like the industry-sponsored Web site pauseparentplay.org, which links to supplemental ratings.</p>
        <p>Mostly, filmmakers complain that they must work against muddled or moving boundaries. And parents' groups grouse about ''ratings creep,'' a perceived tendency for a category like PG-13 to permit ever more violence, sex and profanity over the years to reach impressionable youth. Yet it was Mr. Valenti's genius to have devised an apparatus that is not bound by precedent, changes its definitions at will and, ultimately, serves the motion picture industry by becoming, at any given moment, as permissive or restrictive as the prevailing climate seems to demand.</p>
        <p>Under Dan Glickman, who in 2004 succeeded Mr. Valenti as the motion picture association's top officer, the ratings board, which is overseen jointly with the National Association of Theater Owners, has become more generous in explaining itself to the public. In the description now posted on the mpaa.org Web site, the board says its dozen or so raters, all parents, are expected to judge films according to ''factors that parents consider when deciding whether to allow their children to view that motion picture.''</p>
        <p>Meeting that loose, impressionistic and ever-changing standard has been about as much fun for filmmakers as talking sex with Mom and Dad, and real understanding has just as often been lost in the process. Extreme verbal crudity initially tagged ''Clerks'' with the dreaded NC-17 restriction in 1994, but more of the same and flat-out bestiality did not keep ''Clerks II'' from waltzing to an R in 2006.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ganis has had his own misadventures with the raters, recalling making six trips to the board in a failed effort to reverse an R rating on his ''Deuce Bigalow: Male Gigolo.'' Still, Mr. Ganis remains a defender of the system, even with what he called its ''strange ways.''</p>
        <p>And Mr. Goyer, though frustrated by a standard that is ''a moving target,'' said he could see the wisdom in letting standards quietly ''expand and contract, based on the public acceptance of things.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, for nearly 40 years, Mr. Valenti's raters have largely kept politicians and busybodies out of the film business, even if that meant playing somewhat unpredictable busybodies themselves. They haven't always been fair, and not entirely pleasant to deal with. But in the end, theirs was no mean achievement.</p>
        <p>NEWS ANALYSIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
