<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>N.F.L. Draft: 10 Years Later</title>
    <meta content="2nfldraft" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843406"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E2D8123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1068" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>N.F.L. Draft: 10 Years Later</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN BRANCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Branch, John</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Those drafted in the first round of the N.F.L. draft will wonder what lies ahead. A look back at the 1997 class provides a glance, both promising and sobering. Of the 30 players chosen in the first round that day, 13 are still in the league. One is dead, and another is in prison. The rest are moving on with their lives.</p>
        <p>''Enjoy it -- you've earned it,'' said Tommy Knight, a cornerback from Iowa chosen ninth over all in 1997, on what he would tell this year's class. Knight, who played seven seasons, lives in Chandler, Ariz., and hopes to build a broadcasting career. ''But be smart with your money, plan for your future and enjoy your time.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Those drafted in the first round of the N.F.L. draft will wonder what lies ahead. A look back at the 1997 class provides a glance, both promising and sobering. Of the 30 players chosen in the first round that day, 13 are still in the league. One is dead, and another is in prison. The rest are moving on with their lives.</p>
        <p>''Enjoy it -- you've earned it,'' said Tommy Knight, a cornerback from Iowa chosen ninth over all in 1997, on what he would tell this year's class. Knight, who played seven seasons, lives in Chandler, Ariz., and hopes to build a broadcasting career. ''But be smart with your money, plan for your future and enjoy your time.''</p>
        <p>Hindsight shows how quickly some bright futures turn dark, if only temporarily. Yatil Green, a Miami receiver chosen 15th by the Dolphins, blew out his right knee during the first week of training camp. He had eight operations and made his N.F.L. debut in Year 3. He played in 9 games and caught 18 passes before his career ended.</p>
        <p>Green lives in Miami, has a stake in a trucking company and walks with a limp. He cheerfully acknowledged that it took time to fight off self-pity.</p>
        <p>''After a while, I came to grips -- it wasn't in the cards for me,'' he said. His advice?  ''Don't for any reason take it for granted,'' Green said. ''Because as quickly as it comes, it can be taken away.''</p>
        <p>JOHN BRANCH</p>
        <p>TEAM -- PLAYER (COLLEGE) -- * STILL PLAYING</p>
        <p>1. St. Louis -- *Orlando Pace, OT (Ohio State)  WHAT HAPPENED: Probably will make the Pro Football Hall of Fame. He has been in seven Pro Bowls and still starts for the Rams.</p>
        <p>2. Oakland Darrell Russell, DT (Southern California)  WHAT HAPPENED: After two Pro Bowls and several violations of the league substanceabuse policy, he died in a 2005 car crash.</p>
        <p>3. Seattle *Shawn Springs, CB (Ohio State)  WHAT HAPPENED: Solid, but rarely spectacular starter, with one Pro Bowl, he has played for Washington since 2004.</p>
        <p>4. Baltimore Peter Boulware, LB (Florida State)  WHAT HAPPENED: Defensive rookie of the year played nine seasons and holds a spot in the Ravens' Ring of Honor.</p>
        <p>5. Detroit Bryant Westbrook, CB (Texas)  WHAT HAPPENED: Had six interceptions in 2000, but an injured Achilles' tendon helped limit his career to two more seasons.</p>
        <p>6. Seattle *Walter Jones, OT (Florida State)  WHAT HAPPENED: Has made the past seven Pro Bowls, and could join Pace in the Hall of Fame.</p>
        <p>7. Giants *Ike Hilliard, WR (Florida)  WHAT HAPPENED: In eight seasons with the Giants and two with Tampa Bay, he has 437 receptions but no 1,000-yard seasons.</p>
        <p>8. Jets *James Farrior, LB (Virginia)  WHAT HAPPENED: After five years with the Jets, he has flourished with the Steelers, starting for the 2005 Super Bowl champions.</p>
        <p>9. Arizona Tommy Knight, CB (Iowa)  WHAT HAPPENED: Bounced around for two seasons after five years with the Cardinals, ultimately slowed by hamstring injuries.</p>
        <p>10. New Orleans *Chris Naeole, G (Colorado)  WHAT HAPPENED: A consistent performer for the Saints and the Jaguars, he still starts on the right side.</p>
        <p>11. Atlanta Michael Booker, CB (Nebraska)  WHAT HAPPENED: Played three seasons with the Falcons, then two with Tennessee, collecting eight interceptions.</p>
        <p>12. Tampa Bay *Warrick Dunn, RB (Florida State)  WHAT HAPPENED: Has built a résumé of all-around statistics like Tiki Barber, who was drafted in 1997's second round.</p>
        <p>13. Kansas City *Tony Gonzalez, TE (California)  WHAT HAPPENED: Eight-time Pro Bowler has had at least 63 receptions every season since 1999.</p>
        <p>14. Cincinnati Reinard Wilson, DE (Florida State)  WHAT HAPPENED: Had nine of his 24 career sacks in 2001, none in 2002, and was out of football for good in 2003.</p>
        <p>15. Miami Yatil Green, WR (Miami)  WHAT HAPPENED: A knee injury during the first week of his rookie training camp helped limit him to 18 receptions, all in 1999.</p>
        <p>16. Tampa Bay Reidel Anthony, WR (Florida)  WHAT HAPPENED: Performance fell after third season, and he averaged 29 receptions in five seasons for the Buccaneers.</p>
        <p>17. Washington *Kenard Lang, DE (Miami)  WHAT HAPPENED: Has averaged five sacks a year for three teams; now plays with the Broncos.</p>
        <p>18. Tennessee Kenny Holmes, DE (Miami)  WHAT HAPPENED: Did not play again after a knee injury with the Giants in 2003, finishing with 38 career sacks.</p>
        <p>19. Indianapolis *Tarik Glenn, OT (California)  WHAT HAPPENED: What a draft for left tackles; a 10-year starter, he has made the past three Pro Bowls.</p>
        <p>20. Minnesota Dwayne Rudd, LB (Alabama)  WHAT HAPPENED: With Browns, he infamously threw helmet at end of 2002 opener. Game wasn't over; penalty allowed winning field goal.</p>
        <p>21. Jacksonville *Renaldo Wynn, DE (Notre Dame)  WHAT HAPPENED: Never more than three sacks with the Jaguars and the Redskins, but quietly entering his 11th season.</p>
        <p>22. Dallas David LaFleur, TE (Louisiana State)  WHAT HAPPENED: Never quite caught on: 4 years, 85 catches, 729 yards for the Cowboys.</p>
        <p>23. Buffalo Antowain Smith, RB (Houston)  WHAT HAPPENED: Nine-year career with four teams, he had 1,000-yard seasons in Buffalo and in New England.</p>
        <p>24. Pittsburgh *Chad Scott, CB (Maryland)  WHAT HAPPENED: Spent eight seasons with the Steelers and the past two with the Patriots, where he is a reserve.</p>
        <p>25. Philadelphia Jon Harris, DE (Virginia)  WHAT HAPPENED: Regarded as one of the big busts in Eagles history, he lasted two seasons before bouncing around and out of league.</p>
        <p>26. San Francisco Jim Druckenmiller, QB (Virginia Tech)  WHAT HAPPENED: Career with the 49ers lasted two seasons before he moved on to arena football.</p>
        <p>27. Carolina Rae Carruth, WR (Colorado)  WHAT HAPPENED: Three years in N.F.L., now serving 18 years in prison for conspiring to murder his girlfriend in a drive-by shooting.</p>
        <p>28. Denver *Trevor Pryce, DE (Clemson)  WHAT HAPPENED: After nine years and four Pro Bowls with Broncos, he signed with Baltimore and had 13 sacks in 2006.</p>
        <p>29. New England Chris Canty, CB (Kansas State)  WHAT HAPPENED: Cut after two seasons; finished with four interceptions in four seasons for three teams.</p>
        <p>30. Green Bay Ross Verba, G (Iowa)  WHAT HAPPENED: Started at tackle in Super Bowl as a rookie and managed a decadelong career with three teams, but missed 2003 and 2005 seasons.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
