<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ex-Hollinger Audit Panel Member Testifies</title>
    <meta content="28black" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/business/28black.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843349"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Hollinger Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Black, Conrad M</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEEDA123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="660" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ex-Hollinger Audit Panel Member Testifies</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ex-Hollinger Audit Panel Member Testifies</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC FERKENHOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ferkenhoff, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, April 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A former audit committee member of Hollinger International began testifying Friday in the criminal trial of Conrad M. Black, the former chairman, with prosecutors portraying her as a talented economist who had been duped while the defense suggested she had failed to carry out her financial duties.</p>
        <p>The witness, Marie-Josee Kravis, who was a director for more than 10 years, told the federal jury that Mr. Black and other company officials skirted corporate and government oversight, lining their pockets with millions of dollars in shareholder cash to finance a lavish lifestyle that the government said included costly birthday parties and trips to second homes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prosecutors portrayed the former audit committee member as a talented economist who had been duped.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A former audit committee member of Hollinger International began testifying Friday in the criminal trial of Conrad M. Black, the former chairman, with prosecutors portraying her as a talented economist who had been duped while the defense suggested she had failed to carry out her financial duties.</p>
        <p>The witness, Marie-Josee Kravis, who was a director for more than 10 years, told the federal jury that Mr. Black and other company officials skirted corporate and government oversight, lining their pockets with millions of dollars in shareholder cash to finance a lavish lifestyle that the government said included costly birthday parties and trips to second homes.</p>
        <p>Ending the sixth week of testimony in the fraud trial of Mr. Black and three former colleagues, Ms. Kravis, the wife of the financier Henry Kravis, exhibited the collected personality and financial know-how that have landed her on the society circuit and boards of several top-tier corporations, including Seagram &amp; Sons, the Ford Motor Company and the toy company Hasbro, as well as the Museum of Modern Art.</p>
        <p>She testified that Mr. Black, 62, F. David Radler, his former partner, and other company officials had sold off and bought companies with special clauses that allowed them to keep small percentages totaling millions of dollars for themselves.</p>
        <p>In doing so, Ms. Kravis testified, the officials violated company protocol that dictated detailed scrutiny by the auditing committee she sat on, as well as board approval.</p>
        <p>Neither occurred in the open fashion it should have, she said.</p>
        <p>As questions began to mount about the sales, Ms. Kravis asked Mr. Black to be a little more humble, in his public and private dealings, she testified, and in return, Mr. Black sent her an e-mail message in 2003, before the criminal investigation was revealed, assuring her that he, Mr. Radler and others were doing business both legally and in the interest of the company's stockholders.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kravis's testimony came a day after another audit committee member, Richard Burt, testified that he had been misled by company officials about management's dealings at Hollinger.</p>
        <p>Mr. Black and his top lieutenants are accused in the case, which is being tried in Federal District Court in Chicago, of pocketing more $60 million in noncompete payments beginning in the mid-1990s.</p>
        <p>The government has said and Ms. Kravis echoed the charge Friday, that the money should have belonged to shareholders of the company.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kravis, who studied economics in Ottawa, served on Canada's largest bank, and did economic research for, among others, the Hudson Institute, said: ''I was not advised of the transactions.'' The transactions, according to testimony, were approved by an executive committee consisting of Mr. Black and Mr. Radler and one other Hollinger director, Richard Perle.</p>
        <p>She said she did not know why the payments were made by a committee rather than the full board.</p>
        <p>When first told of the accusations, Ms. Kravis said she thought they were inadvertent oversights and applauded Mr. Black and other company officials for admitting mistakes.</p>
        <p>In opening their cross-examination against Ms. Kravis on Friday, defense lawyers exhibited memos and e-mail messages they say showed that she should have known the agreements were not only routine but were well documented in company paperwork.</p>
        <p>Although she testified that she must have seen some memos shown by the defense in evidence calling attention to noncompete clauses at the heart of the case, she could not explain why she had not alerted other board members or government officials.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kravis testified for about four hours, with the defense just beginning its cross-examination in her final 45 minutes on the stand.</p>
        <p>Testimony is expected to continue next week with the various defendants' lawyers expected to question Ms. Kravis.</p>
        <p>The former Illinois governor, James R Thompson, who, along with Mr. Burt made up the Hollinger audit committee, is also scheduled to testify.</p>
        <p>Mr. Radler, the former president who has since agreed to prison time and restitution, could testify next week as well.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
