<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Lack of Interest (and Candidates) in New System's School Parent Councils</title>
    <meta content="28schools" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/nyregion/28schools.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843448"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">School Administration and Community Role</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Education Department</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bloomberg, Michael R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E7D6123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1324" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Lack of Interest (and Candidates) in New System's School Parent Councils</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Lack of Interest (and Candidates) in New System’s School Parent Councils</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIE BOSMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bosman, Julie</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The stage was set for the candidates' forum. Andrew Baumann, one of nine candidates on the ballot for a school parent council in southwest Queens, was the first person to arrive.</p>
        <p>And he was alone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Parents say that the councils, which replaced New York City’s community school boards, have no real authority and no influence with the Department of Education.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The stage was set for the candidates' forum. Andrew Baumann, one of nine candidates on the ballot for a school parent council in southwest Queens, was the first person to arrive.</p>
        <p>And he was alone.</p>
        <p>''Not a single person,'' Mr. Baumann said disgustedly of the recent nonevent in Community School District 27. ''One candidate showed up. Me.''</p>
        <p>Elections begin on Monday for the 34 parent councils that replaced New York City's community school boards when Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg won control of the school system in 2002.</p>
        <p>The councils are intended to give parents a voice in running the schools, and to be even more representative of their interests than the old school boards, which were often criticized as rife with political patronage and corruption.</p>
        <p>But with parents fuming that the councils have no real authority, no power to institute policy and no influence with the Department of Education, the elections, which run through May 8, have been foreshadowed by skimpy attendance at candidate forums. And in some cases, there is a distinct lack of candidates to run for vacant seats.</p>
        <p>While there are nine elected seats on each council, in at least two districts only four or five candidates are on the ballot. (Two additional members of each council are appointed by the borough president.)</p>
        <p>So few parents wanted to run that the deadline to become a candidate was extended this year. Two weeks ago, the Chancellor's Parent Advisory Council -- a citywide parent group separate from the district councils -- urged a boycott of the vote until the Department of Education ''modifies the present election process'' to do things like better inform candidates.</p>
        <p>Unlike the old school board elections, open to all registered voters, current state law restricts this election so that only the top three officers of each school's parent association vote for council members. Parents serving on the district councils are ineligible to be officers in the parent associations of their own schools.</p>
        <p>Many parents who have been elected to the councils say they feel out of the loop, disrespected by an education department that, they say, decides first and asks later.</p>
        <p>And several council presidents said they were frustrated by a perceived lack of support from school principals, many of whom do not even know who their council members are.</p>
        <p>''The principals feel they don't have to deal with the education councils,'' said James Dandridge, the council president of District 18 in Brooklyn. ''It's like: 'Who are you? You can't hire or fire me. You have no pull.' ''</p>
        <p>The Department of Education says that it is trying to improve the councils, and has scheduled a meeting for May 22 between Chancellor Joel I. Klein and the council presidents. It also hopes to increase voter turnout in the coming election.</p>
        <p>''There clearly is more work to be done,'' said Tom Huser, the director of the councils at the Department of Education. ''There definitely is some sense out there that we need to do a better job of bringing the parents into the fold and reaching out to them as we plan programs and make policy for the department.''</p>
        <p>But in a sign of how useless even the most active parents consider the councils, some districts with long legacies of heavily involved parents have shown the least interest in the coming elections.</p>
        <p>In District 2, covering the East Side and much of Lower Manhattan, only two people attended a recent candidates' forum, said Michael Propper, the district's council president.</p>
        <p>''By and large, parents don't even know the council exists,'' Mr. Propper said, adding that he would not be running for another term this year.</p>
        <p>Rob Caloras, the council president in District 26 in northeast Queens, a district known for its excellent schools and high levels of activism by parents, said that only five people were running for the parent council.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of sad,'' Mr. Caloras said. ''We've lost people who were on the council. They went back to the PTA because they feel it's much more important to be active in their children's schools than waste their time here.''</p>
        <p>According to David Cantor, a spokesman for the Education Department, the first parent council election in 2004 attracted roughly 1,200 parents who signed up to run. In 2005, more than 1,000 parents signed up; this year, there are 744 candidates.</p>
        <p>In several districts, the list of candidates is unusually long. District 17 in Brooklyn has 67 parents on the ballot; District 7 in the South Bronx has 44 candidates; District 22 in Brooklyn has 34.</p>
        <p>Frances Torres, a parent support officer in District 7, said that she had been doing ''tremendous outreach'' for months to recruit candidates. (A parent support officer is a staff job that involves providing services to parents.)</p>
        <p>But some parents said even many of the listed candidates had no intention of serving on the councils. One parent in Brooklyn, Betsy Dabney, said she signed up on the ballot for District 17, in Crown Heights and Flatbush, at the urging of a parent coordinator, but was not briefed on many details of the commitment. ''I'm not even sure how long the term is supposed to be,'' Ms. Dabney said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dandridge in Brooklyn said the Education Department was determined to show that the councils were improving and to put pressure on schools to recruit candidates. The result, he said, is parents who have little real interest.</p>
        <p>''One candidate came to the first meeting and never came back,'' he said. ''One candidate never showed up. They don't even understand what they're signing up for.''</p>
        <p>Some potential candidates have been deterred by the financial disclosure forms required of candidates, which ask for employment and personal investment information.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people, as soon as they see that on the form, they get really turned off,'' said Calvin Diaz, an office administrator for District 9 in the Bronx. ''Once people see that they have to put down how much money they make, they just feel that that's personal. And they get scared.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Huser said the Department of Education was working on changing the state law requiring financial disclosure forms. ''We do recognize that it is both an unnecessary burden to serving on the council,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The lack of interest in the coming elections is ''an indication of how bad things are,'' said Tim Johnson, the chairman of the Chancellor's Parent Advisory Council, the group that called for the elections to be boycotted. ''I think over all, the Department of Education really doesn't want parents at the table advising them on much of anything. Nothing they do seems to get any attention.''</p>
        <p>Still, some parents defend the councils, saying that they have seen progress. There is a full council in District 31, which encompasses all of Staten Island, where parents have had a strong voice in their schools. Rajiv Gowda, the council president there, said 28 people were running for seats in the coming election.</p>
        <p>''We do have some power,'' he said, adding that his council passed eight resolutions in the last year.</p>
        <p>But even after the elections are over, many parents expect to face the same problems of limited attendance and interest.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baumann of District 27, who by day is the president and chief executive of New York Families for Autistic Children, said that to lure parents to the meetings in the past, he invited their children to sing, dance and even recite poetry. Parents still grumbled that their attendance was pointless, he said, because the Department of Education did not listen to their complaints.</p>
        <p>''The mayor and the chancellor really don't want us involved,'' said Mr. Baumann, who calls himself a reluctant candidate for a third term. ''When you're running a big corporation, you don't ask the guys on the loading dock what their opinions are. The way I see it, we're just pushing a box from one side to the other in a warehouse.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
