<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Film in Review; Kickin' It Old Skool</title>
    <meta content="28roun-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/movies/28skoo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843431"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Movie Review | 'Kickin It Old Skool'"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Genzlinger, Neil</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glazer, Harvey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Jamie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alvarado, Aris</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Kickin' It Old School (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Kickin It Old School (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E4D7123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="437" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Film in Review; Kickin' It Old Skool</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Breaking for Laughs</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL GENZLINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genzlinger, Neil</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Neil Genzlinger reviews film Kickin' It Old School, directed by Harvey Glazer; Jamie Kennedy and Aris Alvarado star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Opened yesterday nationwide.  Directed by Harvey Glazer  107 minutes</p>
        <p>The catalytic plot point in the Jamie Kennedy comedy ''Kickin' It Old Skool'' also serves as a sort of metaphorical review of the movie. A young break dancer named Justin tries a particularly dazzling move at an elementary school talent show, and at first it's very entertaining to watch. But alas, the kid misses the gymnastic final back flip, smashes into the floor and ends up in a coma.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“Kickin’ It Old School” is actually much more amusing than it has a right to be, considering that you know exactly what’s coming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Opened yesterday nationwide.  Directed by Harvey Glazer  107 minutes</p>
        <p>The catalytic plot point in the Jamie Kennedy comedy ''Kickin' It Old Skool'' also serves as a sort of metaphorical review of the movie. A young break dancer named Justin tries a particularly dazzling move at an elementary school talent show, and at first it's very entertaining to watch. But alas, the kid misses the gymnastic final back flip, smashes into the floor and ends up in a coma.</p>
        <p>That said, ''Kickin' It'' is actually much more amusing than it has a right to be, considering that you know exactly what's coming. Justin's break-dancing accident occurs in 1986, and 20 years go by before he emerges from his coma, grown and looking like Mr. Kennedy. So of course there will be many references by the adult Justin to things that were current when he was last conscious but are ancient history now, and there will be much befuddlement on his part at the modern world.</p>
        <p>But this somewhat shopworn gimmick is worked with surprising subtlety by Mr. Kennedy and the scriptwriters, Trace Slobotkin, Josh Siegal and Dylan Morgan. When the despondent adult Justin tries to kill himself, what does he use? Cola and Pop Rocks.</p>
        <p>Justin is dismayed by the huge medical bills his parents incurred on his behalf. (They did not, however, spring for physical therapy while he was comatose, giving Mr. Kennedy some amusing Jerry Lewis moments as he tries to get his rubbery limbs to work.) So, with an eye on the $100,000 prize in a competition, he reassembles his old dance crew: Darnell (Miguel A. Núñez Jr.), Aki (Bobby Lee) and Hector (Aris Alvarado).</p>
        <p>Time has not been kind to them, especially the obese Hector. ''Is that Hector?'' Justin asks when he and Darnell finally find him, working as a meter maid.</p>
        <p>Darnell replies, ''Or some dude that ate Hector.''</p>
        <p>The film, though, becomes more stupid as it rolls along toward the dance competition, and shuttling from one comic bit to another requires Mr. Kennedy's character to be annoyingly inconsistent: sometimes he seems to be about 6, sometimes he's a hormonal teenager, sometimes he sounds brain-damaged. (How about a constitutional ban on retardation jokes?)</p>
        <p>A romantic subplot (Maria Menounos is Justin's love interest) is formulaic, and, most disappointing, the break-dance sequences don't sizzle, though the film's director, Harvey Glazer, is known for his music videos. Keep an eye out, however, for some nutty cameos.</p>
        <p>NEIL GENZLINGER</p>
        <p>''Kickin' It Old Skool'' is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has a few bare backsides and a lesson in heavy petting.</p>
        <p>Movie Review | 'Kickin It Old Skool'</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
