<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE WHITE HOUSE SCALES BACK TALK OF IRAQ PROGRESS</title>
    <meta content="28prexy" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/washington/28prexy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843427"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maliki, Nuri Kamal Al- (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E7D7123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1072" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE WHITE HOUSE SCALES BACK TALK OF IRAQ PROGRESS</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The White House Scales Back Talk of Iraq Progress</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bush administration will not try to assess whether troop increase in Iraq is producing signs of political progress or greater security until September, and many of Pres Bush's top advisers anticipate that any gains by then will be limited; senior administration officials say that White House is gradually scaling back its expectations for government of Pres Nuri Kamal al-Maliki; say that timetables being discussed suggest that White House may maintain increased numbers of US troops in Iraq well into 2008; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bush administration will not try to assess whether the troop increase in Iraq is producing signs of political progress or greater security until September, and many of Mr. Bush's top advisers now anticipate that any gains by then will be limited, according to senior administration officials.</p>
        <p>In interviews over the past week, the officials made clear that the White House is gradually scaling back its expectations for the government of President Nuri Kamal al-Maliki. The timelines they are now discussing suggest that the White House may maintain the increased numbers of American troops in Iraq well into next year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The administration will not try to assess whether the troop increase is producing signs of political progress or greater security until September, officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Bush administration will not try to assess whether the troop increase in Iraq is producing signs of political progress or greater security until September, and many of Mr. Bush's top advisers now anticipate that any gains by then will be limited, according to senior administration officials.</p>
        <p>In interviews over the past week, the officials made clear that the White House is gradually scaling back its expectations for the government of President Nuri Kamal al-Maliki. The timelines they are now discussing suggest that the White House may maintain the increased numbers of American troops in Iraq well into next year.</p>
        <p>That prospect would entail a dramatically longer commitment of frontline troops, patrolling the most dangerous neighborhoods of Baghdad, than the one envisioned in legislation that passed the House and Senate this week. That vote, largely symbolic because Democrats do not have the votes to override the promised presidential veto, set deadlines that would lead to the withdrawal of combat troops by the end of March 2008.</p>
        <p>On Friday, during an appearance with Japan's prime minister at Camp David, President Bush said that he would invite congressional leaders to the White House on Wednesday, immediately after his expected veto message, to talk about a ''way forward.'' [Page A10.]</p>
        <p>Several American officials who have spoken recently with Mr. Maliki say they believe that he would like to achieve the kind of political reconciliation that Mr. Bush outlined in January as the ultimate goal of the troop increase. But they say the Iraqi prime minister appears to have little ability to manage the required legislation, including bills requiring fair distribution of oil revenues among Iraq's Sunnis, Shiites and Kurds, and reversing the American-led de-Baathification that barred many Sunnis from participation in the new government.</p>
        <p>Even as administration officials have been telling Congress that Mr. Bush would accept no time limits on success, they have been pushing Mr. Maliki to move faster.</p>
        <p>''He is trying to fight fires coming from every direction,'' Ryan C. Crocker, the newly arrived American ambassador to Iraq, said of Mr. Maliki this week, speaking by telephone. ''We have to be clear to him on where our priorities are, so that we can buy him the time he needs. And we have to buy the time now because he is going to need it in the future.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Crocker said that he had told Mr. Maliki that evidence of progress ''is important in American terms'' because ''to sustain American support we have to be able to see that Iraqis are stepping up to hard challenges.''</p>
        <p>But the new view of Mr. Maliki's limitations was put bluntly by Gen. David H. Petraeus, the American commander in Iraq, who spent the week pressing Congress not to put limits on either the timing or conduct of his operations, as he described what he discovered upon returning to Iraq after a two-year hiatus.</p>
        <p>''He's not the Prime Minister Tony Blair of Iraq,'' General Petraeus said of Mr. Maliki on Thursday. ''He does not have a parliamentary majority. He does not have his ministers in all of the different ministries,'' and they ''sometimes sound a bit discordant in their statements to the press and their statements to other countries. It's a very, very challenging situation in which to lead.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush was careful when he announced his new strategy in January to avoid public estimates of how quickly Mr. Maliki might take steps toward political reconciliation. Even now, White House officials are being careful not to describe with any precision the mix of benchmarks they expect Mr. Maliki to deliver.</p>
        <p>By the time Ambassador Crocker and General Petraeus complete a comprehensive assessment of progress in September, three months after the troop increase has been fully in place, American officials are hoping that some of the pieces of crucial legislation will have passed.</p>
        <p>But Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates found himself pressing Mr. Maliki last week to keep Parliament from taking a two-month summer break. If lawmakers remain in Baghdad, said one senior American official who did not want to be identified because he was discussing internal White House deliberations, ''we'll have some outputs then.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''That's different from having outcomes,'' drawing a distinction between a sign of activity and a sign of success, which could take considerably longer.</p>
        <p>In public, Mr. Bush has remained enthusiastic about Mr. Maliki, with whom he talks over a secure video link every few weeks. But Mr. Bush was also publicly supportive of several of Mr. Maliki's predecessors, even though White House officials now dismiss many of them as ill-suited for the job.</p>
        <p>In January, Mr. Bush characterized Mr. Maliki as an architect of the troop increase plan, even while telling visiting Congressional leaders that ''I said to Maliki this has to work or you're out,'' according to two officials who were in the room. Pressed on why he thought the new strategy would succeed where previous efforts had failed, Mr. Bush shot back, ''Because it has to.''</p>
        <p>That, in short, is the same position he is taking now with Congress. In interviews, his aides said Mr. Bush is convinced that once he vetoes the troop funding plan, because of its timetable for withdrawal, he will have the upper hand in negotiations.</p>
        <p>''There is a segmented market'' among the Democrats, the senior American official said. ''Harry Reid has declared the war is lost, but there are a lot of people in his own party who have said they do not agree. Some of them are telling us privately that if they see some progress by the fall they would support us, because they do want this to succeed.''</p>
        <p>But the Democrats say that if there is no measurable success by August, they believe several more Republicans will defect from Mr. Bush's camp and vote for a staged pullout. Moderate Republicans like Senator Susan Collins of Maine, who grudgingly backed the administration in the Senate vote this week, have said they are not willing to back an open-ended commitment.</p>
        <p>Other Republicans have urged Mr. Bush to explain the political strategy more clearly, arguing that the troop increase is merely a tactic, and not one that can be sustained for long.</p>
        <p>''We've tried that with the president several times,'' said a Republican who spoke with him about the issue in the past week. ''But he knows that it doesn't pay to say what you expect Maliki to get done.''</p>
        <p>THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
