<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>San Francisco Bay Area Reacts Angrily to Series of Immigration Raids</title>
    <meta content="28immig" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/washington/28immig.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843370"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Illegal Immigrants</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">San Francisco Bay Area (Calif)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">San Rafael (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckinley, Jesse</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reyes, Kebin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/San Francisco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">San Francisco (Calif)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E3D9123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="956" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>San Francisco Bay Area Reacts Angrily to Series of Immigration Raids</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">San Francisco Bay Area Reacts Angrily to Series of Immigration Raids</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JESSE McKINLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mckinley, Jesse</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, April 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal immigration officials are conducting raids in San Francisco Bay Area as part of government's Operation Return to Sender, in which over 23,000 people have been arrested nationwide; while raids have upset many pro-immigration groups, that displeasure has been particularly acute in Bay Area, region where many cities consider themselves sanctuaries for illegal immigrants; much of debate has been focused in San Rafael, city of about 56,000 residents, quarter of whom are Latino; photo of Kebin Reyes, 7, American citizen who was held with his father after raid (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was not the typical Bay Area morning. Before dawn on March 6, dozens of federal immigration agents conducted surprise raids in San Rafael and nearby Novato, two comfortable Marin County suburbs where the idea of early morning excitement usually involves a trip to Starbucks.</p>
        <p>The raids are part of the government's Operation Return to Sender, in which more than 23,000 people have been arrested nationwide, including more than 1,800 in Northern and Central California, immigration officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The raids are part of the government’s Operation Return to Sender, in which more than 23,000 people have been arrested nationwide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was not the typical Bay Area morning. Before dawn on March 6, dozens of federal immigration agents conducted surprise raids in San Rafael and nearby Novato, two comfortable Marin County suburbs where the idea of early morning excitement usually involves a trip to Starbucks.</p>
        <p>The raids are part of the government's Operation Return to Sender, in which more than 23,000 people have been arrested nationwide, including more than 1,800 in Northern and Central California, immigration officials said.</p>
        <p>And while the raids have upset many pro-immigrant groups nationwide, that displeasure has been particularly acute in the Bay Area, a region that generally bends left politically and where many cities consider themselves so-called ''sanctuaries'' for illegal immigrants.</p>
        <p>''These people have been here many, many years and they have an investment in the community,'' said Mayor Al Boro of San Rafael, a city of about 56,000 residents, a quarter of whom are Latino. ''And we need to respect that.''</p>
        <p>Several city councils have passed resolutions expressing their anger about the raids, and local religious leaders have issued stern proclamations. The Roman Catholic Archdiocese of San Francisco, for example, said in late March that they were inhumane and called for their immediate end. The raids have also led to protests in several cities, with another round planned for Tuesday in the area's three largest cities: San Francisco, San Jose and Oakland.</p>
        <p>The raids have even upset people in more conservative regions to the east. In Mendota, an agricultural town in the Central Valley that calls itself the ''Cantaloupe Center of the World,'' the City Council passed a resolution last month condemning them. The raids, according to the resolution, had driven much-needed migrant workers underground and caused ''emotional turmoil and financial hardship.''</p>
        <p>In Richmond, another economically challenged city just east across the bay from San Francisco, Mayor Gayle McLaughlin, a member of the Green Party, wrote a bill restating an ordinance that prohibits city employees from cooperating with federal immigration authorities. It passed the City Council unanimously in February.</p>
        <p>That sanctuary sentiment was also echoed on Sunday in a speech by Mayor Gavin Newsom of San Francisco, a Democrat, who repeated his city's noncooperative status, a move that drew a rebuke from a Republican lawmaker in Washington, Representative Tom Tancredo of Colorado, who called the mayor's actions ''a clear and direct violation of the law.''</p>
        <p>The anti-raid sentiments have also energized some opponents of immigration. A recent protest in San Rafael was also attended by nearly 100 members of anti-immigrant groups, including members of the Northern California chapter of the Minuteman Civil Defense Corps, a group that advocates stronger borders.</p>
        <p>Much of the debate has been focused in San Rafael, a genial bayside commuter city about 20 miles north of San Francisco. Shortly after the raids, Mr. Boro sent a letter to Senator Dianne Feinstein, Democrat of California, saying they had ''left our city in turmoil,'' with residents now distrustful of the police and children fearful of losing their parents.</p>
        <p>''Waking people up in the dark of night, at 5 a.m., in their homes seems more like a scare tactic than a law enforcement necessity,'' Mr. Boro wrote.</p>
        <p>Calls to the local police have decreased in recent weeks, Mr. Boro said, and he attributed the dropoff to the immigration raids' ''chilling effect because people think our police were involved.''</p>
        <p>Educators in San Rafael said the raids sent schools into ''a state of emergency'' as American-born children were suddenly without one or both parents who had been caught up in the sweeps. Shortly afterward, absenteeism at school spiked, and school officials asked teachers and others to ride buses with students to make sure a caregiver picked them up.</p>
        <p>A school board member, Jenny Callaway, said she feared that test scores of anxiety-ridden students would suffer. ''Our charge is to provide a quality education regardless of citizenship,'' Ms. Callaway said. ''How do we do this when children are afraid to come to the bus stop?''</p>
        <p>One student caught up in the raids was 7-year-old Kebin Reyes, who was with his father, Noe, when he was arrested early in the morning of March 6. Mr. Reyes, 37, a Guatemalan, said that after his arrest, he was not allowed to call relatives to come to pick up his son, and that they both were held all day in a locked room at the offices of Immigration and Customs Enforcement in San Francisco, an experience he says left his son traumatized.</p>
        <p>''Before the arrest, my son was very friendly and would speak to most anyone, very active,'' Mr. Reyes said, through a translator. ''Since the day of the arrest, Kebin has turned to be very reserved and quiet and not as open to speak to anyone.''</p>
        <p>On Thursday, the American Civil Liberties Union filed suit on behalf of Kebin, who was born in the United States and is an American citizen, charging that federal authorities had violated his constitutional rights. Immigration officials would not comment on the specifics of the case, but said agents had acted appropriately.</p>
        <p>''When we encounter minors in the course of an enforcement action, we will not leave them unattended,'' said Virginia Kice, a spokeswoman for the immigration agency. ''This young man was not arrested; he was transported along with this father to the I.C.E. office, where he was supervised until a family member came to get him.''</p>
        <p>Immigration agency officials say Mr. Reyes was ordered deported in 2000, the same year his son was born. He is fighting that order, and a hearing is scheduled in June. But there is no question, Mr. Reyes said, about his son's status.</p>
        <p>''My son has the same rights as any American citizen,'' he said. ''He is born here in California.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
