<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Return Of Sea Lions, A Rebirth At Bronx Zoo</title>
    <meta content="28zoo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/nyregion/28zoo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Zoos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Bronx Zoo Wildlife Conservation Park</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Aquarium</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DEFD8123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Return Of Sea Lions, A Rebirth At Bronx Zoo</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With Return of Sea Lions, a Rebirth at Bronx Zoo</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STACEY STOWE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stowe, Stacey</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Having a home renovated is never easy. But at least Adrienne, Cleo and Indie, who normally live in the Bronx, were fortunate enough to have been on an extended vacation in Brooklyn during the noise and dust of their construction project.</p>
        <p>In June, these three female sea lions will return from an 18-month sojourn at the New York Aquarium in Coney Island to their restored pool at the Bronx Zoo Wildlife Conservation Park. The pool is one part of the $6.7 million renovation of Astor Court, which dates to the zoo's early years. As a bonus, a new male suitor is expected to arrive a few weeks later.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three sea lions will return from an 18-month sojourn at the New York Aquarium in Coney Island to the Bronx Zoo Wildlife Conservation Park.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Having a home renovated is never easy. But at least Adrienne, Cleo and Indie, who normally live in the Bronx, were fortunate enough to have been on an extended vacation in Brooklyn during the noise and dust of their construction project.</p>
        <p>In June, these three female sea lions will return from an 18-month sojourn at the New York Aquarium in Coney Island to their restored pool at the Bronx Zoo Wildlife Conservation Park. The pool is one part of the $6.7 million renovation of Astor Court, which dates to the zoo's early years. As a bonus, a new male suitor is expected to arrive a few weeks later.</p>
        <p>Under a steady rain yesterday, landscapers laid sod in the Peacock Garden for the June 1 reopening of the 22,000-square-foot mall at Astor Court, whose formal steps and terra cotta balustrades lead to a panoramic view of the zoo's original Victorian designs. Astor Court is being renovated in stages, with different dates for completion.</p>
        <p>The areas being renovated include an Italian garden of boxwoods and roses; the Rockefeller Fountain, which has provided a welcome spritzing to many of the two million annual visitors; and a suite of Beaux-Arts-style buildings considered to be the heart of the 265-acre zoo.</p>
        <p>One of those buildings, the Lion House, which opened in 1903 and was designed by the New York architects Heins and LaFarge, has been closed for more than two decades, and the lions roam an outdoor exhibit.</p>
        <p>The Lion House, which is expected to open next year, will be converted into a 40,000-square-foot, $49 million exhibit on Madagascar, an island off the southeastern coast of Africa and home to 1 percent of the world's biodiversity. Visitors will be able to see a 13-foot Nile crocodile, ring-tailed lemurs and the fossa mammal.</p>
        <p>Construction workers inside the building yesterday were busy scaling ladders while artists painted the trunks of fake baobab trees. In a feature of the exhibit sure to resonate uncomfortably with city dwellers, hundreds of hissing cockroaches will live inside the trunk of one of the fake baobab trees.</p>
        <p>''They eat kibble, banana peels, pretty much anything,'' said James Breheny, director of the zoo, holding one of the four-inch-long insects, whose shell appeared shellacked in the mahogany hue of a cello.</p>
        <p>The renovations, designed by FXFowle Architects, are part of the zoo's 25-year master plan and meant to maintain its mission to educate visitors about wildlife and nature and to protect declining wildlife, said Steven Sanderson, the president of the Wildlife Conservation Society, which operates the zoo.</p>
        <p>Along with improving the zoo's appearance, the Astor Court renovations are also being done with the environment in mind. The Lion House is expected to be the first landmark building in New York City restored in accordance with the environmentally sensitive guidelines of the United States Green Building Council, a nonprofit organization dedicated to sustainable building design and construction, Mr. Sanderson said.</p>
        <p>One of the environmental solutions is a storage and filtration system that recycles water from the zoo's laboratories. It would save more than 140,000 gallons of water a year.</p>
        <p>''At the end of the 25-year plan, we'll set the standard in green materials and conservation and be able to link our guest experience to the mandate we have: to conserve wildlife around the globe,'' Mr. Sanderson said.</p>
        <p>As part of the project, a variety of lighting styles were replaced with energy-saving Victorian reproduction lighting, and slatted benches yielded to wrought iron and wooden versions, said Sue Chin, director of planning and design for the zoo.</p>
        <p>Like the sea lions, the peacocks that once lived in Astor Court were moved during renovations, in this case, to the Children's Zoo. The birds will eventually be able to roam the entire zoo, but zookeepers hope that the mirrored Victorian ''gazing balls'' that are going to dot Astor Court will entice them to stay there.</p>
        <p>''We're going to try to attract them here with those,'' Ms. Chin said, ''so they can gaze at their beautiful image.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
