<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Making the Flight, Without the Stress</title>
    <meta content="28shortcuts" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/business/28shortcuts.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843358"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SHORTCUTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Industry News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E6D9123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1260" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Making the Flight, Without the Stress</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Making the Flight, Without the Stress</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALINA TUGEND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tugend, Alina</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In my vast experience with relationships, it is not money, nor sex, nor raising children that causes the bitterest disputes between couples, but how early you really need to get to the airport.</p>
        <p>One partner, it seems, always wants to get there two days before the flight leaves (my husband), and one thinks 20 minutes before takeoff is just perfect (me).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is not money, nor sex that causes the bitterest disputes between couples, but how early you really need to get to the airport.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In my vast experience with relationships, it is not money, nor sex, nor raising children that causes the bitterest disputes between couples, but how early you really need to get to the airport.</p>
        <p>One partner, it seems, always wants to get there two days before the flight leaves (my husband), and one thinks 20 minutes before takeoff is just perfect (me).</p>
        <p>All right, I exaggerate. But as with most people, I hate spending any more time than absolutely necessary in overly bright terminals with uncomfortable seats and noisy children (particularly if they are mine).</p>
        <p>But, more times than I care to admit, I have been in the position of racing down the hall, frantically looking for Gate 1,000, banging into people with my carry-on and swearing that I will leave earlier for the airport next time.</p>
        <p>We're working on getting the balance right.</p>
        <p>Because, nowadays, there are many more hurdles you must leap over to get to your plane on time than there used to be. There are, of course, the ever-changing rules of post 9/11 security; a greater possibility you won't get a nearby parking spot and will have to spend precious minutes frantically looking for Lot Z; and a need to stock up on food as most airlines do not serve meals on domestic flights.</p>
        <p>For Joe Brancatelli, editor of the travel Web site www.joesentme.com, the bottom line is, you must show up at least two hours before your domestic flight -- and three hours before your international flight -- is scheduled to take off.</p>
        <p>Cut it any closer and you are playing with fire.</p>
        <p>My friend Chris, a lawyer, sees getting to the airport as matter of knocking down stress points.</p>
        <p>These are: waking up on time, traffic, parking, checking in baggage, security line and boarding area.</p>
        <p>''I'm not going to get anything done at home if I'm worried about getting to the airport,'' he said. ''The quicker I can eliminate the stress points, the quicker I can relax.''</p>
        <p>Of course, sitting for an hour by yourself enjoying a magazine or typing into your BlackBerry at a gate can be much more pleasurable than, say, trying to entertain two children who keep whining, ''Are we there yet?'' But Chris said he would still rather do the time in the terminal than sit panic-stricken in a car stuck in traffic.</p>
        <p>''I want to be the guy on the plane reading a book when the guy stumbles on the plane sweating profusely carrying four bags and trying to squeeze into the last seat,'' he said. ''I want to shake my head knowingly and go back to my book.''</p>
        <p>TRAFFIC ALERTS -- At the risk of pointing out the obvious: before leaving the house (assuming the alarm did go off on time), check for possible serious congestion on the way to the airport, especially if you are driving in a city where you are not familiar with the traffic patterns.</p>
        <p>I really do not want to re-live the time we were in a dead halt because of a major accident, along with hundreds of other frantically late passengers five miles from Kennedy International Airport. Incredibly skillful and probably illegal driving on the back roads by my husband got us there with a whisper to spare.</p>
        <p>Once you have made it to the airport, is there parking? All too often now, you cannot take that for granted.</p>
        <p>Part of the reason is the overall increase in the number of people flying; there have been two years of consecutive increases in worldwide passenger traffic, according to the International Air Transport Association.</p>
        <p>''The introduction of JetBlue and Southwest has also really pulled people into the marketplace,'' said Tom Lombardi, president of AirportParkingReservations.com, an online service that allows you to reserve parking at 200 parking lots at 50 airports in the United States and Canada.</p>
        <p>On top of the travel crush, add frequent airport construction that can cut into parking capacity, or security alerts that might lop off whole sections of parking structures or thoroughfares.</p>
        <p>The parking situation has ''gone from bad to worse,'' said David M. Rowell, founder of the Web site The Travel Insider. ''You can spend 10 minutes trying to find a spot, give up, go to long term, which takes 20 minutes, then wait for a shuttle -- you've just dropped 40 minutes.''</p>
        <p>One option is curbside valet parking, Mr. Lombardi said, which is offered in a number of large airports, but which ''costs an arm and a leg'' -- around $30 a day.</p>
        <p>Other choices are Web sites like parknflynetwork.com  and airportparking.com, which allow you to reserve an off-airport parking spot over the Internet. AirportParkingtReservations.com, for example, charges a $5 reservation fee, and the first day of parking ahead of time, but gives a full refund if you cancel within 48 hours. Most of the lots offer free shuttles and are substantially cheaper than on-site parking.</p>
        <p>SECURITY -- You have finally made it into the airport. Dress for success, or at least for a quick trip through the security line.</p>
        <p>''Anybody who wears a hat in an airport is a fool,'' Mr. Brancatelli said. Avoid as much as possible bulky jackets and vests; if you are flying from someplace cold to someplace warm, leave your outerwear in the car.</p>
        <p>''I don't even wear a belt -- I put it in my carry-on and put it on after I get through security,'' Mr. Brancatelli said, to avoid setting off security alarms because of metal buckles. Slip-on shoes are ideal, but if not, at least avoid those with lots of tedious laces. Know what the current requirements are. Check the Transportation Security Administration site (www.tsa.gov) to see what currently is allowed to be carried on, so you don't have to throw things out or repack.</p>
        <p>''I cannot emphasize this enough,'' Mr. Brancatelli said. ''Everything has changed 10 times since 9/11.''</p>
        <p>A tip for men in particular: Use the time you are waiting in the security line to put all your loose change and items in your pockets into a clear plastic bag or your carry-on so you don't have lots of quarters or hard candy rolling around in the trays.</p>
        <p>SUSTENANCE -- For those who have not flown recently, it is difficult to change the mind-set that once you board a plane, your basic needs -- food, drinks, a few peanuts -- will be taken care of. It may not have been particularly tasty, but it did the job, and, to be honest, I was one of those who actually looked forward to airplane meals.</p>
        <p>Now, for those of us who fly economy, we are lucky to get a drink on most domestic flights.</p>
        <p>So remember to build in time to make food at home (avoid overly smelly stuff as a courtesy to your fellow passengers), pick up something on the way, or invest in the hugely overpriced sandwiches at the airport.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brancatelli has another suggestion. Forget about packing a meal.</p>
        <p>''Unless you have a medical condition, fasting won't kill you,'' he said. ''Throw some nuts and pretzels into a bag.''</p>
        <p>More important, bring water on board, because the flight attendants are usually too overworked to run back and forth bringing you drinks, and staying hydrated is more crucial than eating.</p>
        <p>But, since you cannot bring liquids through security, ''stop whining and once you clear security, go and pay too much for water,'' he said. ''I just paid $2.85 for a bottle of water. I'm sorry if you paid 15 cents for a bottle at Costco. You can't bring it on.''</p>
        <p>SHORTCUTS E-mail: shortcuts@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: shortcuts@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
