<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>They'll Keep the Smoking Sign On</title>
    <meta content="28offline" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/business/28offline.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843356"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WHAT'S OFFLINE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Industry News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Extended Stay Hotels</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E6D9123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="701" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>They'll Keep the Smoking Sign On</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">They’ll Keep the Smoking Sign On</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL B. BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Paul B</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN a classic example of basic marketing -- if everyone is zigging, it may be a good time for you to zag -- Extended Stay Hotels is embracing smokers. The chain, which operates 682 North American properties under, among others, the Extended Stay America, Homestead Studio Suites and Crossland Economy Studios brands, recently announced it planned to keep its smokers welcome policies in place, Hotels magazine reports.</p>
        <p>''Smokers are still welcome to light up in common areas and designated rooms,'' the magazine writes. Tim Groves, Extended Stays executive vice president for sales and marketing, says there are no plans to restrict smoking anytime soon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Extended Stay Hotels recently announced it planned to keep its smokers welcome policies in place.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN a classic example of basic marketing -- if everyone is zigging, it may be a good time for you to zag -- Extended Stay Hotels is embracing smokers. The chain, which operates 682 North American properties under, among others, the Extended Stay America, Homestead Studio Suites and Crossland Economy Studios brands, recently announced it planned to keep its smokers welcome policies in place, Hotels magazine reports.</p>
        <p>''Smokers are still welcome to light up in common areas and designated rooms,'' the magazine writes. Tim Groves, Extended Stays executive vice president for sales and marketing, says there are no plans to restrict smoking anytime soon.</p>
        <p>''Among our guests there are a lot of smokers, and we would like them to know that they can go to any of our hotels in the U.S. and Canada and be able to smoke there,'' Mr. Groves said.</p>
        <p>This policy flies in the face of smoking bans both nationwide and within major hotel chains. For example, Westin and Marriott International have banned smoking, the magazine reports.</p>
        <p>Some 15 percent of the customers of the Extended Stay chain, which the Lightstone Group is in the process of acquiring from Blackstone for $8 billion, smoke, Mr. Groves said, adding that since the average customer stays 20 nights, forcing him to go outside every time he wanted a cigarette would not work.</p>
        <p>Mr. Groves says there have been few complaints from nonsmokers about the company's smoking policy.</p>
        <p>MATCH GAME -- ''Elite status on one airline can often be parlayed into elite status on another,'' Jean Chatzky writes in Travel + Leisure.</p>
        <p>Say you have achieved elite status on Continental, but all things being equal, you would rather fly on Delta. Call Delta and say you would love to give them your business, if they match the perks you get from Continental.</p>
        <p>They'll usually do it, Ms. Chatzky writes, if you put your request in writing and send a copy of your last mileage statement.</p>
        <p>SAIL AWAY -- Not sure how to spend your summer vacation? Showboats International has some suggestions:</p>
        <p>For $298,798 a week, plus expenses, you can rent the 204-foot Force Blue, which has ''one of the largest and most elaborate spas we have seen.''</p>
        <p>If dancing is more your speed, for about the same price, there's the 192-foot Magna Grecia, which has a ''huge alfresco disco on the bridge deck.''</p>
        <p>And would-be moguls can rent the 289-foot Maltese Falcon for $454,692 a week, plus expenses. The boat is owned by the venture capitalist Thomas Perkins.</p>
        <p>You could always split the cost. It sleeps 12.</p>
        <p>WHAT'S NEW? -- Among the 10 new products Business 2.0 highlights in the current issue is a technology that replaces electric wires; cellphones that give the ability to watch TV in real time, and the widespread introduction of what can only be described as smell-o-vision.</p>
        <p>''Powercast and its first major partner, electronics giant Philips, are set to launch their first device powered by electricity broadcast through the air,'' the magazine writes. ''A transmitter plugs into the wall, and a dime-size receiver can be embedded into any low-voltage devices. The receiver turns radio waves into DC electricity, recharging the device's battery at a distance of up to three feet.''</p>
        <p>The technology could make chargers, like the ones used for cellphones, obsolete.</p>
        <p>Speaking of cellphones, by the end of this year AT&amp;T and Verizon will be offering services that broadcast live TV channels, like MTV, ESPN, CBS and Fox, to your cellphone. This raises the question of whether you really want to watch anything on a two-inch screen.</p>
        <p>And this month, 100 gas stations in California will be auditioning technology that ''wafts coffee aroma at the pump'' in an effort to increase sales at the stations' convenience stores; Clear Channel is experimenting with scented billboards and Wal-Mart is introducing experimental DVDs that release ''the odor of a burning building, say, or a freshly fired gun, at precisely timed moments during the movie.''</p>
        <p>FINAL TAKE -- This from Entrepreneur, citing work done by Kelton Research: Some 65 percent of Americans spend more time with their home computers than they do with their spouse or significant other.</p>
        <p>PAUL B. BROWN</p>
        <p>WHAT'S OFFLINE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
