<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Needed Most, Pettitte Can't Steady The Sliding Yankees</title>
    <meta content="28yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/sports/baseball/28yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843464"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <org class="online_producer">American League</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pettitte, Andy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E4D6123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1103" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Needed Most, Pettitte Can't Steady The Sliding Yankees</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">When Needed Most, Pettitte Can’t Steady the Sliding Yankees</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The season is too young to be slipping away from the Yankees. But it has gotten ugly quickly, with the team on its longest losing streak since 2000. The voices in the organization that grumble about Manager Joe Torre, whose contract expires after the season, will grow louder if the losses keep mounting.</p>
        <p>Yet there are some nights Torre seems helpless, when stalwarts like Andy Pettitte and Mariano Rivera let him down. Last night the Yankees gave a lead to Pettitte, their best starter, in the middle innings. But with a burst of wildness by a veteran, another game got away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees gave a lead to Andy Pettitte in the middle innings on Friday, yet their best starter couldn’t hold the lead and yet another game slipped away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The season is too young to be slipping away from the Yankees. But it has gotten ugly quickly, with the team on its longest losing streak since 2000. The voices in the organization that grumble about Manager Joe Torre, whose contract expires after the season, will grow louder if the losses keep mounting.</p>
        <p>Yet there are some nights Torre seems helpless, when stalwarts like Andy Pettitte and Mariano Rivera let him down. Last night the Yankees gave a lead to Pettitte, their best starter, in the middle innings. But with a burst of wildness by a veteran, another game got away.</p>
        <p>''This is as frustrating as you can get,'' Pettitte said. ''It's embarrassing, is what it is.''</p>
        <p>Pettitte walked four Red Sox in the fifth inning, dooming the last-place Yankees to an 11-4 defeat and shoving them six and a half games behind Boston in the American League East. The Yankees' losing streak reached seven, their longest since a seven-game skid on the eve of the 2000 playoffs.</p>
        <p>''This is when you find out how good a team is,'' shortstop Derek Jeter said. ''We'll see how good we are.''</p>
        <p>The 2000 team rallied to win its fourth title in five years. There have been no parades since then, and there will not be another without drastic improvement from the pitching staff.</p>
        <p>For the 11th time in 21 games, the Yankees' starter failed to complete five innings last night. Plagued by injuries and inexperience, the woeful rotation is wasting the Yankees' offense, which led the majors in runs coming into last night's game.</p>
        <p>''Now, it seems like everything is going wrong,'' Rivera said, ''which it is.''</p>
        <p>Pettitte had pitched well in his past two starts, but Rivera blew the save both times and struggled in a mop-up role last night. Rivera, who has no saves, faced five hitters, allowing four runs on three hits and a walk, recording only one out in the ninth.</p>
        <p>Torre pulled Rivera with the bases loaded to preserve him for the rest of the series. Mike Myers let all the runners score.</p>
        <p>By then, the Yankees were too far behind to come back. Despite the total of runs -- an average of 5.9 a game -- the offense is not blameless, either. Johnny Damon is 3 for 22 during the losing streak. Bobby Abreu is 2 for 26. Doug Mientkiewicz is batting .140.</p>
        <p>''We're not playing good baseball right now,'' Jason Giambi said. ''We just can't get in sync. Whenever we score a lot of runs, we seem to give up a lot of runs. And whenever we seem to get in a dogfight, we can't score enough runs.''</p>
        <p>Pettitte's presence instills confidence in the Yankees, who have used five rookie starters, including three who had never before pitched in the majors. It had been more than 50 years since three starters made their debuts so early in the season for the same team.</p>
        <p>But Pettitte's experience could not save him this time. He said that he felt off all night, yet through four innings he had allowed only a two-run homer to Kevin Youkilis.</p>
        <p>That put the Yankees in a 2-0 hole, but they scored four times against Daisuke Matsuzaka in the fourth inning to take a 4-2 lead, capitalizing on three walks to lead off the inning.</p>
        <p>But Pettitte gave it all back in the fifth, walking in a run, allowing another on a wild pitch, and giving up two singles to go with the four walks before leaving with two outs and the bases loaded.</p>
        <p>''It's a joke that I can't go out there and get through six or seven innings right there, when the team needs me to do that as bad as they do,'' Pettitte said. ''I've been throwing the ball well, I've been feeling great, and I felt absolutely horrible tonight mechanically. The ball wasn't going where I wanted it to.''</p>
        <p>All through the fifth inning, Posada said that he would call for pitches down in the zone, and Pettitte would leave them up. Torre said that Pettitte was probably too strong; he had not started in a week, and that might have hindered his command.</p>
        <p>As for himself, Torre said that there was not much he could do. He will use Giambi at first base today, shifting Damon to designated hitter and starting Melky Cabrera in center field. Only in rare cases does Torre rage at his players, and now is not one of those times.</p>
        <p>''I'm just going to put a lineup card out there,'' he said. ''These guys are professionals. They know what's at stake. They know what they have to do. They have high expectations; we all do. I expect they'll come out here and fight for it.''</p>
        <p>For Pettitte, the loss was still raw after the game, and he did not expect the feeling to go away soon. He had a responsibility and he failed, performing not much differently than the untested rookies in his midst.</p>
        <p>''It makes you sick to your stomach,'' Pettitte said. ''I'm probably not going to sleep good tonight, that's for sure.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Joe Torre said Phil Hughes would make his second major league start Tuesday in Texas. Andy Pettitte and Mike Mussina will follow Hughes, if Mussina's strained left hamstring responds well to another test today. Mussina threw about 60 pitches in an indoor cage yesterday and will practice covering bases today.  Hughes became only the second top draft choice by the Yankees to pitch for the team. The other was Bill Burbach, who was the Yankees' first choice in the inaugural draft of 1965 and pitched in 37 games from 1969 to 1971. After Burbach, the Yankees used 14 top picks on pitchers until they drafted Hughes in 2004, but none pitched for the team.</p>
        <p>Red Sox pitcher Curt Schilling offered $1 million to anyone who could prove it was not blood that blotted his sock in the 2004 playoffs, and he criticized members of the news media in a blog on his Web site yesterday. The controversy over what stained Schilling's sock was reignited this week when Baltimore Orioles broadcaster Gary Thorne said that Red Sox catcher Doug Mirabelli had told him it was paint, not blood, and that it was done for a publicity stunt. Mirabelli called that a lie, and Thorne said Thursday that he had misreported what Mirabelli said. Schilling, who had a surgical procedure on his ankle that allowed him to pitch in the Series, blasted Thorne and the news media in general yesterday in his first public statement since Thorne's on-air comments.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
