<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Weighing Jobs's Role In a Scandal</title>
    <meta content="28nocera" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843350"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TALKING BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEEDA123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1778" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Weighing Jobs's Role In a Scandal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE NOCERA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nocera, Joe</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In June 2001, Fortune magazine put Steven P. Jobs on its cover. This, I realize, is not exactly breaking news; the magazine put Mr. Jobs on its cover with shameless regularity.</p>
        <p>This time was different, though. The headline read, ''Inside the Great CEO Pay Heist,'' and Mr. Jobs, Apple's legendary chief executive, was showcased not because he had some slick new product to peddle, but because in January 2000, he had been granted 10 million stock options.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In June 2001, Fortune magazine put Steven P. Jobs on its cover. This, I realize, is not exactly breaking news; the magazine put Mr. Jobs on its cover with shameless regularity.</p>
        <p>This time was different, though. The headline read, ''Inside the Great CEO Pay Heist,'' and Mr. Jobs, Apple's legendary chief executive, was showcased not because he had some slick new product to peddle, but because in January 2000, he had been granted 10 million stock options.</p>
        <p>Fortune valued the grant, disclosed in Apple's 2001 proxy statement, at $872 million, making it ''by far'' the largest option grant ever. (Apple's stock split in June 2000, giving Mr. Jobs 20 million options.)</p>
        <p>The reason I remember that cover is because I worked on it. As a Fortune editor, I was part of a team that put together a package of articles about the ''highway robbery''-- to use our phrase -- that executive compensation had become. I also recall being quite happy with the cover.</p>
        <p>What a delicious surprise to discover that Mr. Jobs, who had ostentatiously taken only $1 in salary since returning to Apple in 1997, had a stock option package bigger than any ever bestowed on such well-known greed heads as Sanford I. Weill of Citigroup or Michael D. Eisner of Disney.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jobs, however, was not so happy. He railed about the ''unfairness'' of the cover. And he wrote a scornful letter to the editor, asserting that because Apple's stock had fallen almost $20 a share since the options grant was made, they weren't worth $872 million -- ''they are worth zero.''</p>
        <p>That is not how options are valued, but never mind. In a tone dripping with sarcasm, Mr. Jobs offered to sell Fortune the options for half their supposed $872 million value.</p>
        <p>What we didn't know at the time was that the article so infuriated Mr. Jobs that he began agitating to have the options package canceled. The options were so far underwater that he felt it wasn't worth the bad press to hold onto them.</p>
        <p>Did that mean that Mr. Jobs was willing to go back to his $1 a year salary? Hardly. At the same time, he and the board began negotiating a new package: 7.5 million stock options this time, at a price of $17.83.</p>
        <p>Those options were agreed to by the board in August 2001, barely two months after the Fortune article, but the final negotiations with Mr. Jobs weren't completed until mid-December.</p>
        <p>And although those options also never paid off for him, and were finally replaced in 2003 by a huge restricted stock grant, they had enormous consequences. They were one of two big options grants that ultimately embroiled Apple and its leader in the backdating scandal.</p>
        <p>Among other things, an Apple underling created fictitious board minutes, two of Mr. Jobs's closest associates were forced out of the company and faced charges brought by the Securities and Exchange Commission, and Mr. Jobs's own actions and ethics were brought into question.</p>
        <p>Rarely have so many avoidable problems been created by one man's obsession with his own image. Then again, this is Steve Jobs we're talking about.</p>
        <p>THIS has been quite the week for Apple shareholders. The company reported an incredible quarter, with profits up 88 percent, blowing past analysts' estimates. Its stock pushed above $100 a share for the first time ever. (It closed yesterday at $99.92.)</p>
        <p>And then there was this week's options backdating news: The S.E.C. brought formal charges against Apple's former general counsel, Nancy Heinen, and its former chief financial officer, Fred Anderson.</p>
        <p>(Mr. Anderson settled the charges against him for $3.5 million without admitting or denying guilt, while Ms. Heinen's lawyers vowed to fight the charges against her.)</p>
        <p>These were the two executives the Apple board has been pointing the finger at ever since it completed its internal investigation last fall.</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. seemed to agree: its body language this week strongly suggested that it had zero interest in pursuing Mr. Jobs.</p>
        <p>The agency's position seems to be that the financial chief and general counsel are the ones who are supposed to ensure that options are handled correctly, and therefore both Mr. Jobs and the Apple board are off the hook.</p>
        <p>But almost immediately upon settling the charges, Mr. Anderson pointed the finger right back at his old boss.</p>
        <p>Mr. Anderson had been involved in an options grant that Mr. Jobs made to his executive team in early 2001 -- it was the second big grant under scrutiny -- and he claimed that he told Mr. Jobs there might have to be an accounting charge if the options were not handled correctly.</p>
        <p>There is not much doubt that Mr. Anderson made his statement this week because he felt unfairly scapegoated by Apple and Mr. Jobs.</p>
        <p>With all the finger-pointing, it is difficult to parse whether Mr. Anderson, a wealthy, widely respected figure in Silicon Valley, did something deserving of government sanction. What is clear, however, is that Mr. Jobs does not deserve the free ride he's been getting from the Apple board, the company's investors and government regulators.</p>
        <p>I am not saying Mr. Jobs committed a crime. What I am saying is that it is pretty obvious by now that he was extremely involved in both of the options grants that have become such problems.</p>
        <p>So it is hard to see how he doesn't deserve his share of the blame for what happened.</p>
        <p>Let's start with the ''executive team'' grant that Mr. Anderson was involved in. At the time, Mr. Jobs was under pressure to make large grants to key executives to keep them from leaving. (Remember, this was the tail end of the dot-com bubble.) The board gave him free rein to hand out options as he saw fit.</p>
        <p>The directors approved the grants, a total of 4.8 million options, which were set to go into effect on Jan. 2.</p>
        <p>So far, so good. But then Ms. Heinen suggested the date be changed to later in January to move it past the company's MacWorld event. She didn't want it to look as if Apple executives were taking options in anticipation of a stock bump. Mr. Jobs agreed.</p>
        <p>At the end of January, after some back and forth, he chose Jan. 17 as the new date, according to an e-mail message Ms. Heinen sent around at the time.</p>
        <p>The board, in turn, approved the Jan. 17 options on Feb. 7. By then, though, Apple's stock price had indeed bumped up, by $3.94 more than the Jan. 17 strike price. Which meant, of course, the options had been backdated, and should have been both expensed and disclosed. Neither happened.</p>
        <p>There are lots of people in Silicon Valley who strongly believe that this sequence of events is hardly worth a parking ticket, much less a big-time S.E.C. investigation. But the S.E.C. clearly viewed it as serious enough to charge Mr. Anderson.</p>
        <p>So why not Mr. Jobs? He's the one who made the grants in the first place. He was clearly involved in choosing the new date -- two weeks after it had come and gone. And as chairman of the board, he knew -- or should have known -- that the grants weren't final until Feb. 7.</p>
        <p>To conclude that Mr. Anderson, but not Mr. Jobs, did something wrong requires some serious mental gymnastics.</p>
        <p>Now let's look at the other grant: the 7.5 million options to Mr. Jobs himself. This was the case in which one of Ms. Heinen's subordinates drew up fictitious board minutes to make it appear that the Apple board had approved the grant in October when the real date was December.</p>
        <p>(The underling says she was instructed to do so by her boss, which Ms. Heinen denies.) Certainly, you can't blame Steve Jobs for that.</p>
        <p>What you can blame him for is creating an atmosphere in which these things could happen in the first place.</p>
        <p>Consider, first, Mr. Jobs's desire to replace the 20 million options with the 7.5 million options. What he was really trying to do was reprice his options without actually admitting that -- because repricing would entail an accounting expense. To avoid the expense, he was supposed to wait six months and a day after the cancellation of the first package before Apple gave him the new package.</p>
        <p>But he was Steve Jobs, and he wasn't about to go optionless for six months and a day.</p>
        <p>The Apple directors would later claim that they didn't want him to go optionless either -- because then he would have an incentive to drive down the stock price until he got his new options package. (Have you ever heard a nuttier rationale?)</p>
        <p>In any case, Mr. Jobs held onto the 20 million options while negotiating at length for a better vesting schedule for the 7.5 million. If he had accepted a normal vesting schedule -- he wound up getting a quarter of his options vested immediately -- the issue would have been avoided.</p>
        <p>Instead, the negotiations went on so long that they bumped into a new fiscal year, causing all kinds of problems for people like Nancy Heinen.</p>
        <p>You get the strong impression that nobody dared to say no to Mr. Jobs, a notoriously difficult and abrasive chief executive. One imagines the trepidation of the compensation committee members -- or Ms. Heinen -- in telling him that he couldn't get a low option price because the stock had risen during the negotiations.</p>
        <p>So instead, they found a date in October that approximated the stock price in August -- and an underling created phony board minutes.</p>
        <p>What is particularly galling is the double standard. You hear from lots of sophisticated investors that it would be terrible if Mr. Jobs were forced out at Apple. How, they say, would that help Apple shareholders?</p>
        <p>But lots of other chiefs have lost their jobs because of options backdating, and several have even been indicted. However indispensable he may be, the notion that Mr. Jobs can't be touched because he's Steve Jobs is something terribly corrosive.</p>
        <p>If the S.E.C. is coming to the view that options backdating is just a peccadillo, as Silicon Valley has claimed all along, it should say so. But if it believes this is serious stuff, then it shouldn't be making excuses for Steve Jobs, as it appears to be doing.</p>
        <p>As for Mr. Jobs, as hard as he's worked to convey the image of an above-the-fray visionary, that's not quite the reality, is it? I recently stumbled across this comment from him, circa 1985: ''I'm at a stage where I don't have to do things just to get by. But then I've always been that way, because I've never really cared about money.''</p>
        <p>Yeah, right.</p>
        <p>TALKING BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
