<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Men's and Women's Apparel, All Tariffs Aren't Created Equal</title>
    <meta content="28gender" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/business/28gender.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843450"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barbaro, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E6D6123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1005" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Men's and Women's Apparel, All Tariffs Aren't Created Equal</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Apparel, All Tariffs Aren’t Created Equal</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL BARBARO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barbaro, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tariffs on imported clothing, which penalize men in some instances and women in others, may be last legal form of sex discrimination in US; several major apparel makers are challenging tariffs in lawsuits against federal government that have broad implications for clothing industry; clothing companies could reclaim close to $1 billion worth of tariffs based on gender differences if they prevail; case could help unravel one of greatest mysteries in retailing: why similar clothing for men and women is priced so differently; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Congress, it turns out, plays fashion favorites.</p>
        <p>Take bathing suits. It slaps a 28 percent tax on men's imports, but just 12 percent on women's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The fees tacked onto clothing as it enters the U.S. may be the last legal form of sex discrimination in the country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Congress, it turns out, plays fashion favorites.</p>
        <p>Take bathing suits. It slaps a 28 percent tax on men's imports, but just 12 percent on women's.</p>
        <p>Or overalls. The government imposes a 14 percent tariff on women's, but only 9 percent on men's.</p>
        <p>Woven wool shirts? Men's are hit with an 18 percent duty, more than twice as much as women's.</p>
        <p>There is no apparent pattern to the tariffs, which penalize men in some instances, and women in others. But the fees tacked onto clothing, shoes and swimwear as they enter the country's ports may be the last legal form of sex discrimination in the United States, approved year after year by lawmakers and passed on to consumers.</p>
        <p>For decades, apparel companies have grudgingly tolerated the peculiar disparities, writing them off as a vestige of smoke-filled, backroom trade negotiations.</p>
        <p>But now, several major apparel makers, like Steve Madden, Asics and Columbia Sportswear, are challenging the tariffs in lawsuits against the federal government that have broad implications for the clothing industry, not to mention the battle of the sexes.</p>
        <p>If the clothing companies prevail, they could reclaim close to $1 billion worth of tariffs based on gender differences. For example, the lawsuit claims that the government earned $2.5 million last year from discriminatory tariffs on underpants (penalizing women), $93 million for cotton shirts (penalizing men), $16 million for silk shirts (penalizing women) and $71 million for shoes with leather tops (women again).</p>
        <p>The case also could help unravel one of the greatest mysteries in retailing: why similar clothing for men and women is priced so differently.</p>
        <p>What the lawyers do not know -- and what they hope their lawsuit reveals -- is precisely why these glaring disparities exist.</p>
        <p>Theories abound. Since the first appearance of gender differences in the tariff system dates back to the mid-1800s, plain old sexism is one hypothesis. An effort to protect American textile manufacturers from imports is another.</p>
        <p>But after years of poring over dusty tariff lists, international trade court records and Congressional testimony, lawyers have found nothing that explains why, say, the tariff on an imported wool suit is 8.5 percent for a woman and zero for a man.</p>
        <p>''It's irrational,'' said Peter Bragdon, the general counsel at Columbia Sportswear, one of the companies suing the government.</p>
        <p>Columbia Sportswear imports a rugged hiking boot from China called the Diamond Peak. The men's and women's boots are virtually identical. But the tariff on the women's version is 1.5 percentage points higher than the men's (10 percent, compared with 8.5 percent).</p>
        <p>''I think any first-year law student would have the same gut reaction we did -- wait, you cannot do that,'' Mr. Bragdon said.</p>
        <p>The government's only known opinion on the matter appeared in 1960, during a study of the United States tariff system -- and it appears to help the clothing companies' legal case, rather than hurt it.</p>
        <p>Describing the gender disparities on shoes, federal regulators conceded that ''their economic justification is questionable.''</p>
        <p>Today, few in the government want to discuss the issue. Spokesmen for the Office of the United States Trade Representative and the Justice Department said they would not comment on the role of gender in determining tariffs because of the pending lawsuit.</p>
        <p>The existence of different tariffs for men and women, imposed on similar clothing, would most likely have remained out of public view if not for a Manhattan lawyer named Michael T. Cone, who has spent nearly a decade researching the topic.</p>
        <p>After all, thousands of clothing companies, fully aware of the disparities, have accepted it as a fact of life. ''You grin and bear it,'' said Alan Geller, president of Teri Jon Apparel, which makes women's suits (with a higher tariff rate than for men's) for Saks, Neiman Marcus and Bloomingdale's.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Cone, from the firm Neville Peterson, found the differences ''offensive'' and likened them to a federal sales tax based on gender. ''Who would stand for that? If you were to buy a shirt and it was 5 percent more only because you are a man or a woman you would be outraged -- and people should be equally outraged at what is happening with tariffs.''</p>
        <p>His lawsuit, filed on behalf of Totes-Isotoner, the glove maker, asserts that different tariff rates for similar men's and women's clothing violate the Constitution's guarantee of due process and equal protection. (The tariff on seamed leather gloves, a top seller for Totes-Isotoner, is 14 percent for men's and 12.6 percent for women's.)</p>
        <p>After years of resistance -- no major apparel brand wants to sue the government if it can avoid it -- several companies have come around to Mr. Cone's opinion.</p>
        <p>The prospect of a big payoff does not hurt either. Lawyers and apparel companies stand to win tens of millions in refunded tariffs -- not to mention future profits from lower tariffs, which they hope to secure in a settlement with the government.</p>
        <p>There is a chance, however slim, that the case could backfire if the government chooses to eliminate sex differences by raising the lower tariffs, rather than reducing the higher ones.</p>
        <p>Clothing executives said they had consumers' interests in mind, too. Tariffs based on gender, they said, discourage them from making dozens of products with the higher tariffs for either men and women, limiting shoppers' options.</p>
        <p>''You have to work around them,'' said Bob Africa, director of footwear at Pearl Izumi, which makes athletic clothing.</p>
        <p>The current system leaves apparel makers with few enviable options, executives said. They can stop making a product with a higher tariff, charge more for it or make less money on it.</p>
        <p>Pearl Izumi, for example, makes a cycling sneaker in China called the Vagabond for men and women, charging $85 for both. But the company pays a tariff of 4.3 percent for the men's version, and zero for women. As a result, it makes less money on every Vagabond sold to a man.</p>
        <p>Mr. Africa says he is baffled by the differences: ''I see no logical reason for it. It simply does not add up.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
