<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rolling Homes Aren't Just for the Rich</title>
    <meta content="28interview" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/business/28interview.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843405"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SATURDAY INTERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recreational Vehicles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recreational Vehicles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mobile Homes and Trailers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Winnebago Industries Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3D8123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="913" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rolling Homes Aren't Just for the Rich</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rolling Homes Aren’t Just for the Rich</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUSTON JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jones, Juston</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Recreational vehicles are not just toys for the rich, says Bruce D. Hertzke, 55, chairman and chief executive of Winnebago Industries, a big maker of R.V.'s and motor homes. Blue-collar workers, who have saved for retirement and travel make up a big chunk of the company's business. Mr. Hertzke spoke recently about those customers, about feeling the pain of high gas prices and about how some people save the fancy trimmings for their R.V. instead of their house. Following are excerpts:</p>
        <p>Q. What is your biggest month for sales?</p>
        <p>A. Actually, it's more so the whole season, not a single month. The spring and summer periods have always been our strongest. From April to July are our biggest months of selling to the wholesale dealers. The summer shutdown of schools, when people are planning their vacations, are when most of the sales occur.</p>
        <p>Q. So does that translate to those periods being your strongest quarters for profits?</p>
        <p>A. Yes. In our fiscal year, those months fall in our third and fourth quarters, and they are our strongest.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you know the profile of your typical customer?</p>
        <p>A. It is someone 55 to 70 years of age, who has been in retirement mode, or who is looking for an R.V. for leisure travel, or wants one to help with pursuing another hobby -- like following the Nascar circuit or tailgating at a favorite football team on weekends. R.V.'s are no longer just for camping.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bruce D. Hertzke, chairman and chief executive of Winnebago Industries, spoke about high gas prices and about how some people save the fancy trimmings for their R.V. instead of their house.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Recreational vehicles are not just toys for the rich, says Bruce D. Hertzke, 55, chairman and chief executive of Winnebago Industries, a big maker of R.V.'s and motor homes. Blue-collar workers, who have saved for retirement and travel make up a big chunk of the company's business. Mr. Hertzke spoke recently about those customers, about feeling the pain of high gas prices and about how some people save the fancy trimmings for their R.V. instead of their house. Following are excerpts:</p>
        <p>Q. What is your biggest month for sales?</p>
        <p>A. Actually, it's more so the whole season, not a single month. The spring and summer periods have always been our strongest. From April to July are our biggest months of selling to the wholesale dealers. The summer shutdown of schools, when people are planning their vacations, are when most of the sales occur.</p>
        <p>Q. So does that translate to those periods being your strongest quarters for profits?</p>
        <p>A. Yes. In our fiscal year, those months fall in our third and fourth quarters, and they are our strongest.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you know the profile of your typical customer?</p>
        <p>A. It is someone 55 to 70 years of age, who has been in retirement mode, or who is looking for an R.V. for leisure travel, or wants one to help with pursuing another hobby -- like following the Nascar circuit or tailgating at a favorite football team on weekends. R.V.'s are no longer just for camping.</p>
        <p>Even after 70, we have a lot of people who continue to use R.V.'s. And we even have people as young as 35, who want to use them to tailgate, or for supporting other hobbies.</p>
        <p>Q. Do some Winnebago owners live in R.V.'s year-round?</p>
        <p>A. Yes. In fact, our company has a 365 Club for customers who use their Winnebagos as their full-time home.</p>
        <p>Q. What is the average price of a Winnebago?</p>
        <p>A. Around $90,000 to $100,000. We have some that go up to $300,000 or more, and some that start at $60,000.</p>
        <p>Q. Is an R.V. basically a toy for rich people?</p>
        <p>A. No, we have a lot of blue-collar workers who are our customers, who have worked hard, saved their money and are ready to retire and do some traveling. It makes it a lot easier for them to buy a motor home and take food and other essentials with them instead of going to a resort.</p>
        <p>Another thing that helps this customer, for a person to buy a motor home, one can actually qualify for a second home loan. They can use the loan for an R.V. instead of using it to buy a condo in Florida or somewhere. A lot of people want to see more of America this way.</p>
        <p>Q. Your sales and net income have been falling over the past few years. How do you expect to get them to start growing again?</p>
        <p>A. If you look at the results of our last eight years, there was steady growth until reaching record revenues and profits in 2004. Since then, gas prices shot up, there were 17 interest-rate hikes and consumer confidence dropped. We felt the brunt of that.</p>
        <p>But we believe that we have a growing market. In the United States, our estimates suggest that we have people turning 50 at a rate of 350,000 per month. That is more than four million per year, and this is our target market. With these favorable demographics -- it's baby boomers who buy our products -- we expect our sales and profits to return to a growth cycle.</p>
        <p>Q. When will that growth cycle begin?</p>
        <p>A. It's really retail-market dependent. Without knowing where the economy is headed, I'm unable to put a defined time frame on it.</p>
        <p>Q. You announced you will soon be paying a cash dividend, and your stock price is only a few dollars from a 52-week high. Why do you think investors are confident in the stock?</p>
        <p>A. Many of our investors have followed us over time. They understand that we are a cyclical industry. As much as I hate to say it, people don't have to buy a $100,000 R.V., not like milk and bread. People sometimes go into a wait-and-see mode. That hesitancy puts us into periods where things go flat for a while.</p>
        <p>Q. Have high gas prices affected your sales?</p>
        <p>A. Yes, and I don't know if it's just gas prices, or the drop in consumer confidence. It's a combination.</p>
        <p>Q. Detroit and Washington alike are concentrating on ways to reduce emissions. Is that an issue for your company, too?</p>
        <p>A. Winnebago is very pleased that we have developed a diesel motor home that gets 17 to 19 miles per gallon, one of the highest gas mileage R.V.'s in the industry. It has been a very successful product because of the fuel efficiency. That motor home gets better gas mileage than my Ford pickup.</p>
        <p>Q. What new features have you been adding to motor homes?</p>
        <p>A. You can get washers and dryers and dishwashers, ceramic floor tiles, security cameras outside your coach, Sony surround-sound systems for at least two TVs -- one in the bedroom in the back and one in the front -- computer hookups and DVD players. We make sure that nobody's roughing it too much.</p>
        <p>SATURDAY INTERVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
