<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Moral Plots and Subplots in the Latest Ruling on Abortion</title>
    <meta content="28beliefs" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843362"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BELIEFS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E4D9123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="953" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Moral Plots and Subplots in the Latest Ruling on Abortion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER STEINFELS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinfels, Peter</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Life today is lived on slippery slopes. Which ones seize our attention and crystallize our fears? What moral outrages or absurdities, lurking at the bottom, stir our energies? How steep is the incline? Where can we throw up a railing, dig a trench, clear a landing, keep our footing? Questions like these determine a great deal of public moral debate.</p>
        <p>That fact was amply demonstrated by the Supreme Court's decision upholding the constitutionality of the Partial-Birth Abortion Ban Act of 2003 and the reactions the ruling engendered. There was wide agreement that the ruling would directly affect few abortions but wide disagreement on what the ruling meant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Life today is lived on slippery slopes. Which ones seize our attention and crystallize our fears? What moral outrages or absurdities, lurking at the bottom, stir our energies? How steep is the incline? Where can we throw up a railing, dig a trench, clear a landing, keep our footing? Questions like these determine a great deal of public moral debate.</p>
        <p>That fact was amply demonstrated by the Supreme Court's decision upholding the constitutionality of the Partial-Birth Abortion Ban Act of 2003 and the reactions the ruling engendered. There was wide agreement that the ruling would directly affect few abortions but wide disagreement on what the ruling meant.</p>
        <p>Constitutional experts naturally and properly subjected the court's opinions to fine-grained analyses, revealing in the process how much abortion law has come to resemble the challenge of lacing a shoe with a shoelace already knotted in several places. But the general public mainly cast the decision in terms of two larger stories focusing on two different slippery slopes.</p>
        <p>One story was summed up by Justice Ruth Bader Ginsburg's phrase, in her dissenting opinion, that the decision threatened ''to chip away'' previous affirmations of abortion rights, standard safeguards for women's health and even women's newly won place as equal and morally autonomous actors in public life.</p>
        <p>Justice Ginsburg was hardly alone in framing the matter this way. This was the story framing most news reports on the decision. It was the framework put forward by Planned Parenthood, the National Abortion Federation and other groups active in defense of legal abortion. That the court was chipping away at abortion rights was also the view of some abortion opponents, although they welcomed that process as a slow ascent rather than decrying it as a slippery slope.</p>
        <p>This was also the framework of much commentary, whether about the practical limits of the decision or whether Justice Anthony M. Kennedy, in his majority opinion, patronized women with his reference to ''the bond of love the mother has for her child'' or the possibility that ''some women come to regret their choice to abort the infant life they once created and sustained.''</p>
        <p>Public division and debate over the Partial-Birth Abortion Ban Act and the court's ruling on it cannot be understood, however, without recognizing another story, the drama of another slippery slope.</p>
        <p>That story played a central role in the passage of the law -- and in Justice Kennedy's opinion defending it: ''The act proscribes a method of abortion in which a fetus is killed just inches before completion of the birth process,'' he wrote. Having found that this method had a ''disturbing similarity to the killing of a newborn infant,'' Congress was acting reasonably, Justice Kennedy concluded, in drawing ''a bright line that clearly distinguishes abortion and infanticide.''</p>
        <p>Not even the title of the disputed law can be understood apart from this fear by some that the nation might be slouching toward infanticide, the rejection of which has been one of those landmark developments in humankind's moral progress.</p>
        <p>The Associated Press report on the Supreme Court's decision mentioned both the majority's defense of ''drawing a bright line between abortion and infanticide'' and the dissenters' image of chipping away at abortion rights. But a number of major papers ran reports of the decision, including versions of The A.P.'s dispatch, with no reference to infanticide. Some mentioned the word only in quotes from anti-abortion leaders. In this paper, the word appeared in a letter to the editor from an official of an Orthodox Jewish organization.</p>
        <p>Justice Ginsburg recognized the importance of this issue and took it on directly. Noting that alternative methods of late-term abortion not banned by the law may involve tearing the fetus apart and ripping off its limbs, she quoted Justice John Paul Stevens's opinion in a previous case that it was ''simply irrational'' to think that ''either of these two equally gruesome procedures'' was ''more akin to infanticide than the other.''</p>
        <p>Supporters of the law could agree, of course, that alternative abortion methods were similarly gruesome but still disagree that gruesomeness was the only relevant grounds for banning a particular procedure.</p>
        <p>To be sure, many advocates of abortion rights dismiss this anxiety about sliding toward infanticide as a charade. After all, don't anti-abortion forces consider all abortion to be infanticide or something morally equivalent to it, whether or not the procedure is gruesome or whether or not the fetus is just short of being born?</p>
        <p>That is doubtlessly true of the organized anti-abortion movement and its legal and moral theorists. It is not true, however, of many among those rallying to outlaw this procedure because its ''disturbing similarity to the killing of a newborn infant'' seemed to blur the line between abortion and infanticide.</p>
        <p>It was Daniel Patrick Moynihan, after all, Senator Hillary Clinton's predecessor and, like her, a supporter of abortion rights, who voted for an earlier version of the current law, calling the banned procedure ''just too close to infanticide.''</p>
        <p>Yet to be seen is whether the anti-abortion movement can convince Americans whose intuitions were like Mr. Moynihan's that their negative judgment should, in fact, be extended to other categories of abortion, possibly, at the outside, to all of them. It is an incongruous side effect of the clashing Supreme Court opinions that abortion opponents can find more support in Justice Ginsburg's opinion than in Justice Kennedy's for the conviction that all abortions are essentially similar.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, anyone hoping to understand the moral and political passions surrounding the Partial-Birth Abortion Ban Act and the Supreme Court's ruling on its constitutionality must realize that not just one but two stories, not just one but two ethical slippery slopes, are at work in the minds of Americans.</p>
        <p>BELIEFS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
