<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Passion for Seeing What the Body Can Do</title>
    <meta content="28mama" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/arts/dance/28mama.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843342"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">La MaMa ETC</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E1DA123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="462" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Passion for Seeing What the Body Can Do</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Passion for Seeing What the Body Can Do</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROSLYN SULCAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sulcas, Roslyn</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just naming the nine programs in the La MaMa Moves! festival must have been exhausting; it's hard to imagine the other logistics that the co-curators, Nicky Paraiso and Mia Yoo, must have dealt with in putting together this 50-company event. The first program, ''New Virtuosity,'' on Thursday night at La MaMa's Annex Theater, augured well for the rest of the festival, and wasn't an altogether inappropriate title for an evening of impassioned, first-rate dancing.</p>
        <p>In Patrick Corbin's ''Reach,'' set to Philip Glass's String Quartet No. 5, eight dancers from his CorbinDances company continually swirl around and away from a ninth, Orlando Martinez, a stocky, powerfully built man in loose acid-green pants. Mr. Corbin was ballet trained, then a star in Paul Taylor's company. But his blend of aerial jumps and sudden falls, and the loose, arm-flinging calligraphy of his upper body seem all his own in this well-made piece, which moves dancers seamlessly on- and offstage while slowly building to a striking close.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just naming the nine programs in the La MaMa Moves! festival must have been exhausting; it’s hard to imagine the other logistics that the co-curators must have dealt with.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just naming the nine programs in the La MaMa Moves! festival must have been exhausting; it's hard to imagine the other logistics that the co-curators, Nicky Paraiso and Mia Yoo, must have dealt with in putting together this 50-company event. The first program, ''New Virtuosity,'' on Thursday night at La MaMa's Annex Theater, augured well for the rest of the festival, and wasn't an altogether inappropriate title for an evening of impassioned, first-rate dancing.</p>
        <p>In Patrick Corbin's ''Reach,'' set to Philip Glass's String Quartet No. 5, eight dancers from his CorbinDances company continually swirl around and away from a ninth, Orlando Martinez, a stocky, powerfully built man in loose acid-green pants. Mr. Corbin was ballet trained, then a star in Paul Taylor's company. But his blend of aerial jumps and sudden falls, and the loose, arm-flinging calligraphy of his upper body seem all his own in this well-made piece, which moves dancers seamlessly on- and offstage while slowly building to a striking close.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corbin doesn't always manage adequate responses to the driving score, but when he does -- dancers flopping their bodies on the ground like fish out of water, or Mr. Martinez alone, arms raised, as the others wheel away -- they are entirely persuasive.</p>
        <p>Dusan Tynek's ''Fleur-de-lis'' is a beautiful work, full of poetry and surprise. It is set to Heinrich von Biber's Sonata No. 6 for violin, and the exquisite Passagalia for solo violin, and Mr. Tynek hardly put a foot wrong through the two sections shown on Thursday, ''Annunciation'' and ''Resurrection.'' The work is full of the religious imagery that these titles suggest, but there is no narrative -- simply a cascade of haunting moments that seem perfectly in accord with the music.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tynek has a gift for creating movement that looks physically impossible; men cantilever off the women's bodies; a woman floats away from a man, her legs flying out behind her. He also makes beautifully architectural dance, often weaving a diagonal line of dancers through a vertical one, and he has an acute musical sensibility evinced in a strangely effective stop-and-start section to the surging violin in ''Resurrection.''</p>
        <p>The Nicholas Andre Dance Theater performed Nick Seligson-Ross's ''Dwelling,'' a nicely made, vigorous work with a slightly ritualistic air, to a twangy percussive score by Peter Sivalia.</p>
        <p>The final piece, Sunhwa Chung's ''Ascending Timeless,'' danced by the Ko-Ryo Dance Theater, was clumsily constructed and far too long, but had its moments of gestural power.</p>
        <p>Like the other works, it suggested a passion for movement, for the pleasures of discovering what the body can do, that is -- oddly enough -- not found all that often onstage.</p>
        <p>The La MaMa Moves! festival continues through May 12 at La MaMa, 74A East Fourth Street, East Village; (212) 475-7710, lamama.org.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
