<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Very Voice of History in WNYC Archives</title>
    <meta content="28about" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/nyregion/28about.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843440"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ABOUT NEW YORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/About New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/About New York/About New York - Dwyer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Archives and Records</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archives and Records</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">WNYC</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E0D7123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="749" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Very Voice of History in WNYC Archives</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Very Voice of History in WNYC Archives</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM DWYER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dwyer, Jim</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The voice crackles out of computer speakers.</p>
        <p>''Harry and I had a speech code that was only known to two,'' Theodore Hardeen can be heard saying. It is 1939, and Mr. Hardeen is talking about his brother, Harry Houdini, who had made his final escape and disappearance 13 years earlier.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As WNYC prepares to move, an archivist is hunting down every element of sound captured over eight decades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The voice crackles out of computer speakers.</p>
        <p>''Harry and I had a speech code that was only known to two,'' Theodore Hardeen can be heard saying. It is 1939, and Mr. Hardeen is talking about his brother, Harry Houdini, who had made his final escape and disappearance 13 years earlier.</p>
        <p>He does not believe in spiritualism, Mr. Hardeen says, because he has gone to many seances and Harry has never once used their secret code to speak to him from the where-ever-after.</p>
        <p>His story and voice live in a file on the shelves of a room on the 33rd floor of the Municipal Building, one of the cramped spaces used as an archive by WNYC, the city's first public radio station. Mr. Hardeen was interviewed on the station by Ezra Macintosh (''the voice of the theater, bringing you the latest news and gossip'').</p>
        <p>Now, as WNYC prepares to move out of the space it has occupied at One Centre Street since 1924, the station archivist, Andy Lanset, is hunting down every element of sound that was captured over eight decades.</p>
        <p>Thumb through the binders and folders along his shelves, and the 20th century -- the first in history to leave great quantities of actual sound to posterity -- speaks up, loud and clear. So much of memory resides in sound, far more than in what is seen. When they move Mr. Lanset's files across town, time itself will be packed on the trucks.</p>
        <p>In its 83 years, WNYC has survived any number of death warrants by mayoral fiat, and its archives are a source of primary material for history, social and political and cultural.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lanset rescued ''Here's Heidi,'' a 1949 children's series (''Mom and I lived in a little house there. And every weekend Dad came out from the city to see us.'') that had been tucked in next to a mesmerizing feed from the Marshall Islands during an atom bomb test on Bikini Atoll in 1946. (Voice 1: ''Firing time: 30 seconds.'' Voice 2: ''The final switches have been thrown. No one can stop it. The atomic bomb is about to explode.'' Voice 1: ''Firing time: 20 seconds.'')</p>
        <p>Starting with acetate platters that require a turntable equipped with a special tone-arm needle, the WNYC sounds survive on a half-dozen dead or dying storage mediums.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lanset finds ways to transfer the most valuable to digital formats, but many of the station's treasures are crumbling. He is a methodical man, in a flat-out sprint to save the station's historical riches.</p>
        <p>He found scripts, but no audio, for a 1945 broadcast called ''Wartime Housewife,'' a show on public affairs and practical advice with Gladys Bashler as host; after the war ended, her show became known as ''Mrs. Citizen.''</p>
        <p>The audio files include mayors, of course, because the city owned the station until 1997, after Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani proposed selling its license commercially but a foundation supported by listeners bought it. There are hundreds of hours of the talk and music show hosts.</p>
        <p>In a series of one-minute essays, Kurt Vonnegut, who died this month, holds forth as the station's ''reporter on the afterlife.''</p>
        <p>He portrays a man who had gone to death's door with the help of almost-lethal drugs supposedly administered by Dr. Jack Kevorkian. His reporting, Mr. Vonnegut says, was made possible ''thanks to a controlled near-death experience.''</p>
        <p>Leadbelly interviews Woody Guthrie. Years later, a young Bob Dylan spins a long fib to Oscar Brand, the folksinger and radio host, about being raised in a carnival. The recordings are on the shelves.</p>
        <p>Alfred E. Smith, governor and political force in New York through the 1940s, urges that people not indulge in the ''evil luxury'' of bigotry under war-time hardships.</p>
        <p>His words are lyric; his all-but-extinct New York accent suggests a day when politicians may have been proudly unpolished and unhomogenized.</p>
        <p>People from all over the world -- ''the woild,'' as Mr. Smith renders it -- ''came to America to find the chance that the countries of their birth never gave them.'' That would be countries of their ''boith.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lanset unlocked an archive cabinet and slid out a disc: ''Old Penn Station NYC announcements/ambiance -- circa 1950.''</p>
        <p>The old Pennsylvania Station, a masterwork, was demolished in 1963; in 56 seconds recorded more than half a century ago, WNYC captured the rhythms of the ordinary, the murmurs and gate announcements and footfall, all landing in a place that, Thomas Wolfe wrote, was ''vast enough to hold the sound of time.''</p>
        <p>ABOUT NEW YORK E-mail: dwyer@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: dwyer@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
