<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>More Like An Air Ball</title>
    <meta content="28dowd" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/opinion/28dowd.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843346"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Columnist"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Central Intelligence Agency</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Times</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dowd, Maureen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tenet, George J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hussein, Saddam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rice, Condoleezza (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Alison</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">At the Center of the Storm (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Maureen Dowd</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington (DC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Central Intelligence Agency</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Woodward, Bob</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bremer, L Paul III</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Zubaydah, Abu</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mitchell, Alison</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06EEDA123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="808" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>More Like An Air Ball</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">More Like an Air Ball</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAUREEN DOWD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dowd, Maureen</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Maureen Dowd Op-Ed column notes that former CIA Dir George Tenet writes in his new book, At the Center of the Storm, that CIA found no linkage between Saddam Hussein and 9/11, but Sec of State Condoleezza Rice made him call New York Times reporter Alison Mitchell in Oct 2002 and tell her that nothing in CIA report contradicted Pres Bush's case for war (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Poor Slam Dunk.</p>
        <p>Not since Madame Butterfly has anyone been so cruelly misunderstood and misused. Slam Dunk says that when he pantingly told the president that fetching information on Saddam's W.M.D. would be a cinch, he did not mean let's go to war.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Slam-Dunk, a k a George Tenet, shows us his tender side, a sniveling C.I.A. chief bullied by “remote” Condi.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Poor Slam Dunk.</p>
        <p>Not since Madame Butterfly has anyone been so cruelly misunderstood and misused. Slam Dunk says that when he pantingly told the president that fetching information on Saddam's W.M.D. would be a cinch, he did not mean let's go to war.</p>
        <p>No matter how eager Slam Dunk was to tell W. what he wanted to hear while polishing the president's shoes, the intelligence they craved did not exist. ''Let me say it again: C.I.A. found absolutely no linkage between Saddam and 9/11,'' the ex-Head Spook writes in his new book, self-effacingly titled ''At the Center of the Storm.'' Besides, Junior and Darth had already decided to go to war to show the Arabs their moxie.</p>
        <p>The president and vice president wanted Slam Dunk to help them dramatize the phony case. Everyone had to pitch in! That Saturday session in December 2002 in the Oval Office was ''essentially a marketing meeting,'' Slam Dunk writes, just for ''sharpening the arguments.''</p>
        <p>Hey, I feel better.</p>
        <p>Slam Dunk always presented himself as the ultimate guy's guy, a cigar-chomping spymaster who swapped jokes with the president. But now he shows us his tender side, a sniveling C.I.A. chief bullied by ''remote'' Condi.</p>
        <p>He says Condi panicked in October 2002 and made him call a Times reporter, Alison Mitchell, who covered the Congressional debate about invading Iraq. In essence, he hypocritically told Alison to disregard the conclusions of his own agency, which had said that the links between Saddam and terrorist groups were tenuous, and that Saddam would take the extreme step of joining with Islamic fanatics only if he thought the U.S. was about to attack him. His nose growing as long as his cigar, he said nothing in the C.I.A. report contradicted the president's case for war.</p>
        <p>''In retrospect,'' Slam writes, ''I shouldn't have talked to the New York Times reporter at Condi's request. By making public comments in the middle of a contentious political debate, I gave the impression that I was becoming a partisan player.''</p>
        <p>Can't a guy be a lickspittle without being an ideologue?</p>
        <p>There were so many nasties trying to push Slam around: Vice, of course, and Wolfie, and Wolfie's neoconcubine Doug Feith. Once, Slam writes, Wolfie ''hounded'' a C.I.A. briefer to translate the diary of Abu Zubaydah, a captured Al Qaeda official, even though the C.I.A. had decided it was just misogynistic ramblings ''about what he wanted to do with women.'' Oh, that sexy beast Wolfie. Look out, Shaha!</p>
        <p>But even though he was paid a $4 million advance to settle scores, Slam can't turn on W. Maybe it's the Medal of Freedom. ''In a way, President Bush and I are much alike,'' he writes. ''We sometimes say things from our gut, whether it's his 'bring 'em on' or my 'slam dunk.' I think he gets that about me, just as I get that about him.'' (He had me at ''slam dunk.'')</p>
        <p>The worst meanie was horrid Bob Woodward. Slam socialized with Bob and gave him lots of intel for his best sellers, but then Bob ''painted a caricature of me leaping into the air and simulating a slam dunk, not once but twice, with my arms flailing. Credit Woodward's source with  a fine sense of how to make me look ridiculous, but don't credit him or her with a deep sense of obligation to the truth.''</p>
        <p>A deep sense of obligation to the truth is something Slam keenly understands, even though he scurried around like the butler in ''Remains of the Day,'' trying to toadie up to the president while, as he belatedly admits, W. was going to invade Iraq without debate or a casus belli.</p>
        <p>He says the C.I.A. warned Paul Bremer that demobilizing the Iraqi Army would be ''madness.''</p>
        <p>The two worst intelligence disasters in our history happened on his watch, but Slam says he was Cassandra. He says he gave intel to guys who wanted to ignore or warp it and make bad policy. What could he do?</p>
        <p>A C.I.A. paper was given to the president's national security team in September 2002 to sum up the possible negatives of invading Iraq, including anarchy and a breakup of Iraq, instability in the neighborhood, a surge of terrorism against U.S. interests, oil disruptions, and seething allies.</p>
        <p>But it was discreetly tucked away in the back of the briefing book, after the stuff at the beginning about how great it would be to liberate Iraq and end threats to Iraq's neighbors, and the stuff in the middle about reforming Iraq's bureaucracy.</p>
        <p>Slam gives tips to others who want to engage in public service, including: Don't forget that there are no private conversations, even in the Oval Office. Another might be: If you worry about your own survival more than your country's, you might end up as the whiny fall guy.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Columnist</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
