<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Top Tier' Candidate? Maybe Not, but Dodd Is Still Enjoying the Ride</title>
    <meta content="28dodd" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/us/politics/28dodd.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843366"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leibovich, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dodd, Christopher J (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Dodd, Christopher J</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E3D9123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1243" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Top Tier' Candidate? Maybe Not, but Dodd Is Still Enjoying the Ride</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">‘Top Tier’ Candidate? Maybe Not, but Dodd Is Still Enjoying the Ride</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK LEIBOVICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leibovich, Mark</byline>
      <dateline>ORANGEBURG, S.C., April 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Democratic presidential candidate Christopher J Dodd remains consummate happy warrior even though his campaign is not catching on; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator Christopher J. Dodd has a magnificent handshake, maybe the best in the Democratic presidential field. He grips with a brisk clench, makes masterly eye contact and tops it off with a light pat on the wrist from his nonshaking hand. It is the grip of a pro, a (perish the thought) political pro, which he is, the silvery-haired son of a senator, accomplished lawmaker, backslapper and armsqueezer.</p>
        <p>It is a typical morning in the Dodd campaign in that he is coming off a bit of a downer, Thursday night's Democratic debate here. He earned some solid reviews but failed to draw much notice. He is polling in Kucinich-land. And yet, Mr. Dodd of Connecticut remains the consummate happy warrior, intent on spinning stories, collecting belly laughs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Senator Christopher J. Dodd ambles through the early voting states, there is a decided “Why the heck not?” feel to his joyous orbit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senator Christopher J. Dodd has a magnificent handshake, maybe the best in the Democratic presidential field. He grips with a brisk clench, makes masterly eye contact and tops it off with a light pat on the wrist from his nonshaking hand. It is the grip of a pro, a (perish the thought) political pro, which he is, the silvery-haired son of a senator, accomplished lawmaker, backslapper and armsqueezer.</p>
        <p>It is a typical morning in the Dodd campaign in that he is coming off a bit of a downer, Thursday night's Democratic debate here. He earned some solid reviews but failed to draw much notice. He is polling in Kucinich-land. And yet, Mr. Dodd of Connecticut remains the consummate happy warrior, intent on spinning stories, collecting belly laughs.</p>
        <p>He bounded into the buffet line at the Chestnut Grill on Friday morning. There is a ''Dodd for President'' placard in the front window, under a ''Closed, Please Call Again'' sign.</p>
        <p>''Tip O'Neill once came down here and asked for a grit,'' Mr. Dodd said. ''That was Tip's way of connecting with the local folks, by asking for a grit.'' Mr. Dodd shakes another hand, punctuating it with a pleasing fwapp on the back of another wrist. ''A grit,'' he says again, bellowing forth.</p>
        <p>There could be a certain poignancy to Mr. Dodd's enterprise, the narrative of a man who has waited his whole career to do this -- maybe too long, past his time -- and who, for whatever reason, is not catching on. In the shoes of another character, someone who takes himself more seriously than Mr. Dodd does, it could be sad. Indeed, he could be bitter that the so-called top tier of candidates, his Senate colleagues Hillary Rodham Clinton and Barack Obama, and his former colleague John Edwards, have a combined tenure in the chamber barely half Mr. Dodd's 26 years.</p>
        <p>As he ambles through the early voting states, there is a decided ''Why the heck not?'' feel to Mr. Dodd's joyous orbit. As in, why the heck shouldn't Chris Dodd run for president, and enjoy the heck out of the ride?</p>
        <p>At 62, this could be Mr. Dodd's last chance to run. He is intent to hang around, to wear well, and he hopes, to get Democrats to say: What the heck? Why not Dodd? He is experienced, telegenic and could hold his own in any popularity contest on Capitol Hill. Which might be a handicap, but what the heck?</p>
        <p>He is a throwback to a presanctimonious era when politicians were not so intent on fashioning themselves outsiders and anti-politicians. There is no sexy novelty in Mr. Dodd's candidacy. He is yet another New England Democrat perceived as an establishment liberal. He would not be the first woman, black, Hispanic or Mormon to inhabit the White House. White male senators always run for president, almost as reliably as they lose.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Dodd insists his campaign is not without historic value.</p>
        <p>''I'm the first candidate who's spoken in Pahrump,'' Mr. Dodd boasted in an interview last week, referring to the small Nevada city he visited recently. ''I got a bump out of Pahrump,'' he added, shifting into story-telling mode, his deep voice rising. Ah, Pahrump!</p>
        <p>''So I was speaking at a firehouse in Pahrump,'' Mr. Dodd recalled. ''And I looked out this window, and there was this billboard. There are a lot of billboards in Pahrump and there was one that was advertising the Museum of Brothel Art. You wouldn't see this kind of thing in Fairfield County. It's the kind of local color you can only get by running for president.''</p>
        <p>By the same token, the mounting indignities of an also-ran candidacy can be deflating. Mr. Dodd appeared on ''The Daily Show'' and was introduced as ''the Connecticut senator and non-front-running candidate'' by the host, Jon Stewart.</p>
        <p>''Sir, you're offering competence,'' Mr. Stewart told him. ''I have to tell you, sir, I don't think people will buy it.''</p>
        <p>As the senator prepared to depart the stage, Mr. Stewart urged him to come back ''when you drop out.''</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, Mr. Dodd is more sanguine about his chances than the political smarties and smart-alecks. He often says he has been around politics long enough to know that things happen -- things like scandals, health problems, sudden changes in the political mood. He says voters he meets seem to be responding positively to him.</p>
        <p>''He was very thoughtful, very engaging,'' said Paul Johnson, who was host to a ''kitchen table'' conversation with Mr. Dodd and a group of local voters last week at his home in Nashua, N.H. (Symmetry alert: Mr. Johnson later volunteers to Mr. Dodd that his father was actually born on a kitchen table, and in Mr. Dodd's home state, Connecticut.)</p>
        <p>Earlier in the day, Mr. Dodd took a quickie tour of a Nashua firehouse, his aide lugging a sack of doughnuts behind him. Mr. Dodd loves firefighters. And doughnuts. He partook of a memorable doughnut fight years ago with a former colleague, Representative Harold E. Ford Sr. of Tennessee. ''It was a good time,'' Mr. Dodd said, declining to renounce his involvement in the doughnut debacle.</p>
        <p>''Anyone have any questions about anything?'' Mr. Dodd asked the firefighters.</p>
        <p>Silence, except for the tweeting of a bird that breached an open door.</p>
        <p>''Anyone? Anything?''</p>
        <p>Nothing.</p>
        <p>''How do you like the work?'' Mr. Dodd continued.</p>
        <p>''Like it,'' one firefighter said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dodd loves his, too, but he is prone to restlessness -- and, like many other senators, has seemingly been contemplating a run for president since he first entered the chamber, or maybe since kindergarten. There is no shortage of premature ''Dodd in 88,'' ''Dodd in 92,'' ''Dodd in 2000'' or ''Dodd in 2004'' buttons and stickers to prove it.</p>
        <p>Yes, Mr. Dodd is slightly annoyed by the ''tiering'' the news media has imposed on the 2008 race. ''But that's America,'' he said. ''It's nine months to go. It's four relatively small states. And people are showing up.''</p>
        <p>He is often accompanied on the campaign trail by his wife, Jackie, 45, whom he married in 1999 after a storied Washington bachelorhood that included courtships with Carrie Fisher and Bianca Jagger. The couple have two daughters, 5 and 2, and Mr. Dodd often brags that he is the only candidate who gets mailings from both AARP and diaper services.</p>
        <p>Before coming to the Senate in 1981, Mr. Dodd served three terms in the House and did a Peace Corps stint in the Dominican Republic. He has campaigned strenuously for colleagues, served as chairman of the Democratic Party during President Bill Clinton's 1996 re-election and spearheaded such landmark legislation as the Family and Medical Leave Act.</p>
        <p>''I'm trying to make the point that experience matters,'' Mr. Dodd said in a speech at Southern New Hampshire University in Manchester.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dodd vows to stay in the race for the duration, for what it is worth.</p>
        <p>Strolling around the Nashua fire station, hands crammed in pockets, he was looking slightly bored, or perhaps tired. It was about 10 a.m.; he is not much of a morning guy. He dutifully viewed the fire station's state-of-the-art exhaust system, the defibrillator machine, the dive suit.</p>
        <p>At the far end of the garage is the Hazmat truck, which ferried beer in a previous life, and Mr. Dodd perked up.</p>
        <p>''This used to be a beer truck?'' he said. ''Is there any beer left?''</p>
        <p>Everyone laughs, none louder than the senator.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
