<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Governor's Postpartisanship: Old-Fashioned Politicking?</title>
    <meta content="28arnold" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/us/28arnold.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843467"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEWS ANALYSIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Probation and Parole</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinhauer, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwarzenegger, Arnold (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Probation and Parole</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Schwarzenegger, Arnold</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE4D6123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="814" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Governor's Postpartisanship: Old-Fashioned Politicking?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Governor’s Postpartisanship: Old-Fashioned Politicking?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER STEINHAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinhauer, Jennifer</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, April 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>California lawmakers, facing court orders and deadline to address state's prison overcrowding, approved construction program that will add 53,000 beds and move 8,000 convicts to other states; bill did not include what Gov Arnold Schwarzenegger, experts on prison overcrowding and many Democrats had originally called for: changes to parole system and creation of sentencing guidelines board that would take into consideration how many beds are available in prisons; scaling back of bill's ambitions may have set legislative template for Schwarzenegger's final years in office; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a sunny and joyful world -- the sort that Gov. Arnold Schwarzenegger, a Republican, prefers to inhabit -- postpartisanship means that lawmakers come together without ideological bickering, score legislative victories and happily return to their districts in time for dinner.</p>
        <p>In a more realistic world, if prison legislation approved Thursday by the Democratic-controlled State Legislature is any indication, the governor's postpartisanship results in new laws that make almost everyone angry, with their efficacy left very much in question.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If prison legislation approved Thursday in California is any indication, Gov. Arnold Schwarzenegger’s postpartisanship results in new laws that make almost everyone angry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a sunny and joyful world -- the sort that Gov. Arnold Schwarzenegger, a Republican, prefers to inhabit -- postpartisanship means that lawmakers come together without ideological bickering, score legislative victories and happily return to their districts in time for dinner.</p>
        <p>In a more realistic world, if prison legislation approved Thursday by the Democratic-controlled State Legislature is any indication, the governor's postpartisanship results in new laws that make almost everyone angry, with their efficacy left very much in question.</p>
        <p>Facing court orders and an onerous deadline to address the state's prison overcrowding, California lawmakers approved a construction program that would add 53,000 beds and move 8,000 convicts to other states.</p>
        <p>But the bill did not include what Mr. Schwarzenegger, experts on prison overcrowding and many Democrats had originally called for: changes to the parole system and the creation of a sentencing guidelines board that would take into consideration how many beds are available in prisons before sending more people to fill them.</p>
        <p>The scaling back of the bill's ambitions may well have set a legislative template for Mr. Schwarzenegger's final years in office, during which he hopes to pass a far-reaching health care bill, redraw legislative districts and address the state's chronic water infrastructure problems.</p>
        <p>The prison legislation came together not through a lengthy public debate, the sort that ended in nothingness during an emergency session of the Legislature to deal with the problem last summer. Rather, it was hammered out by Republican and Democratic leaders, in consultation with the governor, and icing out the biggest outside interest group: the union that represents corrections officers.</p>
        <p>The result is more expensive than Republicans would like -- more than $8 billion in public money to pay for construction -- and far less focused on the systemic changes that Democrats would have wanted. It infuriated the prison guards' union, which rejects sending prisoners to other states. And it is far from certain to earn the nod from judges overseeing problems in the prison system, the subject of several lawsuits.</p>
        <p>The essential question, it seems, is whether Mr. Schwarzenegger's proclaimed era of postpartisanship in California triumphs over gridlock to bring the sort of trend-setting legislation that the state has been known for, or instead results in watered-down compromises hammered out with equal parts threat and capitulation in a Sacramento back room.</p>
        <p>''They are returning to an earlier level of leadership where controversial issues are decided at elite level,'' said Louis DeSipio, an associate professor of political science at the University of California, Irvine. ''I think it is an excellent thing for Arnold, but it may be bad for the state.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schwarzenegger has decided to work harder with legislative leaders after he watched his popularity plummet when he tried to push through his notions of reform. Scrambling to gain momentum for a re-election bid last year, he let the legislative leaders take the reins of an infrastructure bond deal and environmental legislation.</p>
        <p>''This is a leadership style he has adopted in the last year and a half,'' said Adam Mendelsohn, the governor's communications director, who added that he expected the coming health care bill to take a similar course.</p>
        <p>It is a technique that finds its roots in the passage of term limits in the 1990s, when experienced legislators left office by the dozens and the leaders in both houses, working with Gov. Pete Wilson, also a Republican, used the five-star system to get the budget through.</p>
        <p>''Then we saw more and more of the 'gut and amend' phenomenon,'' said Bruce Cain, director of the Institute of Governmental Studies at the University of California, Berkeley.</p>
        <p>Many view legislation of any kind a good thing for governance, even if bills have fewer policy implications.</p>
        <p>''You at least got a requisite number of people to vote for something that solves the problem that is not something any of them would have voted for alone,'' said Barbara O'Connor, the director of the Institute for the Study of Politics and Media at California State University, Sacramento.</p>
        <p>''I think you will see the same thing with health care,'' Ms. O'Connor said. ''People realize that if you don't like a bill you might get something you like even less and breaking gridlock are things the public really wants and everyone knows it.''</p>
        <p>And in truth, California had little choice but to do something. The prison system has several deadlines set by state and federal judges to reduce overcrowding or face possible federal receivership of the system and caps of population.</p>
        <p>''The threat of having to release people outright meant that everything else was off the table but building beds,'' said Joan Petersilia, director of the Center for Evidence-Based Corrections at the University of California, Irvine, who is a prisons expert. ''I am incredibly disappointed, because Schwarzenegger came in and many of us rolled up our sleeves and really thought this was going to be different.''</p>
        <p>NEWS ANALYSIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
