<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AT&amp;T Chief Who Weathered a Sea Change Is Retiring in June</title>
    <meta content="28phone" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/technology/28phone.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843401"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">AT&amp;T Corp</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Whitacre, Edward E Jr</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E3D8123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="980" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AT&amp;T Chief Who Weathered a Sea Change Is Retiring in June</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">AT&amp;T Chief Who Weathered a Sea Change Is Retiring in June</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT RICHTEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Richtel, Matt</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Edward E. Whitacre Jr. joined Southwestern Bell in 1963 as a facilities engineer, the land-line telephone was the state of the art and the Bell operating companies were dominant.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Mr. Whitacre announced that in June -- after 44 years climbing the corporate ladder -- he would retire as chief executive and chairman of AT&amp;T.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Edward E. Whitacre Jr. will be succeeded by Randall L. Stephenson, the company’s chief operating officer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Edward E. Whitacre Jr. joined Southwestern Bell in 1963 as a facilities engineer, the land-line telephone was the state of the art and the Bell operating companies were dominant.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Mr. Whitacre announced that in June -- after 44 years climbing the corporate ladder -- he would retire as chief executive and chairman of AT&amp;T.</p>
        <p>The industry he leaves is markedly changed from the one he joined, given the breakup of the Bell System, the reconsolidation of the industry and the now-powerful influence of cellphones and the Internet. The land-line telephone business is in its decline.</p>
        <p>Mr. Whitacre, 65, has not only survived the changes, but helped drive them by means of an aggressive acquisition strategy that turned AT&amp;T into the world's largest telecommunications provider.</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T said Mr. Whitacre would be succeeded by Randall L. Stephenson, currently the company's chief operating officer. Mr. Stephenson, 47, began his own career with Southwestern Bell in 1982 in information technology and has held positions in finance, performance assurance and marketing.</p>
        <p>Despite Mr. Whitacre's prominent role in shaping AT&amp;T, Wall Street investors and analysts appeared to take his departure in stride. They said AT&amp;T under Mr. Whitacre's leadership had been preparing employees and investors for a passing of the torch.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stephenson inherits a company with a $240 billion market capitalization, one that Mr. Whitacre has built into a multifaceted telecommunications giant through an aggressive acquisition strategy. Its multibillion-dollar deals -- most recently the acquisition of BellSouth -- have been in keeping with Mr. Whitacre's philosophy that his industry demands immense size and scale.</p>
        <p>The change in command was announced at AT&amp;T's annual shareholder meeting in San Antonio, where the company is based.</p>
        <p>Industry analysts said Mr. Stephenson tended to be more detail-oriented than his predecessor and had the kind of skills that would be in demand as AT&amp;T sought to focus on execution, not acquisition.</p>
        <p>The transition to Mr. Stephenson should be smooth, said Christopher C. King, a telecommunications industry analyst with Stifel Nicolaus.</p>
        <p>''I'm not sure you'll see any grand strategic shift,'' he said. Mr. Stephenson ''is very well thought of and has been a primary contact with Wall Street over the last several years.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Whitacre will leave AT&amp;T with a lucrative retirement package, according to a proxy statement filed last month. He has a pension valued at $84.7 million and has $73.8 million of previously earned pay in a deferred compensation plan.</p>
        <p>A native Texan, Mr. Whitacre has been credited with transforming Southwestern Bell, the smallest of the seven Bells when he took it over in 1990, into SBC, a giant that acquired AT&amp;T and took its name.</p>
        <p>''No one has done more to reshape the telecommunications industry than Ed Whitacre,'' said John Hodulik, an industry analyst with UBS Investment Bank. ''He took what was probably the most disadvantaged of the Baby Bells and turned it into the largest telecommunications company in the world.''</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Whitacre said recently in an interview with The New York Times that he felt comfortable at last with the breadth of his company.</p>
        <p>''I've always been trying to put all the pieces together,'' he said. ''We've got them now.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stephenson echoed that sentiment in an interview yesterday, after the announcement of his promotion.</p>
        <p>''The big building blocks are in place,'' he said. ''Our task is laid before us: execute. We have to integrate these businesses.''</p>
        <p>Wall Street has backed Mr. Whitacre's acquisition strategy by sending the stock on a steady two-year rise to the high $30s from the low $20s. The stock finished regular trading yesterday on the New York Stock Exchange at $38.64, down 32 cents.</p>
        <p>The company still faces considerable long-term challenges in light of fundamental changes overtaking the industry. Thanks in large part to Internet and mobile technology, which is allowing less expensive and more versatile communications, AT&amp;T and its competitors have been forced to find new ways to maintain a growing chunk of the lucrative monthly fees Americans pay to stay connected and entertained.</p>
        <p>The fiercest competition now comes from cable companies, which have bolstered their traditional television service with Internet and phone service.</p>
        <p>One aspect of AT&amp;T's response has been the introduction of a television service called U-verse that it has just begun introducing around the country. It has only 20,000 customers and is adding 2,000 a week.</p>
        <p>Mr. King said a crucial question facing AT&amp;T and Mr. Stephenson was whether that product, which relies on sending programming over broadband lines, would be an effective competitor in the future.</p>
        <p>''One of the major challenges is whether their video strategy, U-verse, will ultimately be enough for consumers five or 10 years down the line,'' Mr. King said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stephenson said in the interview yesterday that he saw his own greatest operational challenge as making a success of U-verse. ''That's absolutely critical,'' he said. ''We have really just begun.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stephenson said he was ''humbled'' to be following Mr. Whitacre.</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T has 66.5 million land-based telephone lines, 61 million wireless subscribers, 12 million broadband lines, and sells local phone service in 22 states. Its market capitalization is double that of the nearest American competitor, Verizon Communications, at $110 billion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Whitacre took home about $31.5 million in pay last year, according to the recent proxy filing, about 94 percent more than the $16.2 million that he earned in 2005. AT&amp;T shareholders, on the other hand, saw a total return of about 53 percent, including reinvested dividends.</p>
        <p>His compensation has rankled some corporate watchdogs who have said Mr. Whitacre was overpaid during the telecommunications downturn that followed the dot-com bust. Mr. Hodulik, the analyst from UBS, defended Mr. Whitacre's retirement package, saying it reflected a career of contribution.</p>
        <p>''Ed has worked there the majority of his life and done a huge amount to build value for shareholders,'' Mr. Hodulik said. ''Look at the length and depth of his contribution.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
