<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Recalling Lessons From Home As First Draft Approaches</title>
    <meta content="28giants" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/sports/football/28giants.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843463"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Football League</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Reese, Jerry</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E4D6123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1798" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Recalling Lessons From Home As First Draft Approaches</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Reese Recalls Lessons From Home as First N.F.L. Draft Approaches</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN BRANCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Branch, John</byline>
      <dateline>TIPTONVILLE, Tenn., April 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jerry Reese, only a polite grade-school boy then, would steady the shotgun and shoot the hog between the eyes. He slit its throat with a butcher's knife, then wrestled it into a tub of hot water, softening the coarse hair so it could be shaved off with a blade. He lifted the hog onto a hook, cut its belly, dissected it and split it into usable parts.</p>
        <p>The people who had taken the live animal to his great-grandfather's slaughterhouse would come back to retrieve the packaged pieces. And Reese would start again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In January, Jerry Reese became the third African-American general manager in N.F.L. history. Yet Saturday’s draft serves as his symbolic, public beginning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jerry Reese, only a polite grade-school boy then, would steady the shotgun and shoot the hog between the eyes. He slit its throat with a butcher's knife, then wrestled it into a tub of hot water, softening the coarse hair so it could be shaved off with a blade. He lifted the hog onto a hook, cut its belly, dissected it and split it into usable parts.</p>
        <p>The people who had taken the live animal to his great-grandfather's slaughterhouse would come back to retrieve the packaged pieces. And Reese would start again.</p>
        <p>When school vacation ended, Reese would return to the two-bedroom home he shared here with his mother, stepfather, five sisters and one younger brother. The house seemed big. Not only did it have one more bedroom than the house across Tipton Street, where the family lived until Reese was 10, but it also had indoor plumbing instead of an outhouse.</p>
        <p>Reese slept in the living room, on the couch or a cot that was stashed behind the door each the morning. After school, he sometimes shot squirrels and rabbits in the cotton fields that stretch to the nearby Mississippi River, and brought them home to skin and eat. When the river flooded and surrounded the house like a slimy moat, he sat on the porch and shot snakes swimming through the murky water.</p>
        <p>On Saturday, in the first round of the N.F.L. draft, the 43-year-old Reese will choose the name of a college football player for the Giants, who hold the 20th overall pick. Pundits and Giants fans will dissect his decision. Inevitably, some will be critical.</p>
        <p>In January, Reese became the third African-American in league history to become a general manager. But Saturday serves as the symbolic, public beginning of his tenure. Finally, the Giants will be Jerry Reese's team.</p>
        <p>''People ask me, 'Are you stressed about the draft?' '' Reese said in a telephone interview Tuesday from New Jersey. He laughed. ''Are you kidding me? Let me tell you about some stressful times.''</p>
        <p>He would not trade any of them. Discussing his childhood, his voice giddily rises and quickens. If the titles of senior vice president and general manager define who Reese is now, Tiptonville represents who he will always be.</p>
        <p>The town will soon put signs at its limits proclaiming it as the home of Jerry Reese, general manager of the Giants.</p>
        <p>''It's almost embarrassing,'' he said. ''I'm just Jerry from Tiptonville.''</p>
        <p>Tiptonville is a town of about 2,500 in northwestern Tennessee, a couple of miles from the Mississippi River to the west and the vast Reelfoot Lake to the east. The lake's shores are lined with small motels and bait shops that serve tourists who come to pull catfish and bass from the water. But the downtown is a patchwork of small businesses -- a bank, a drug store, a bar -- and empty storefronts with faded signs. Streets, many paved in only the past couple of decades, are lined by small one-story homes.</p>
        <p>Cotton and soybeans are harvested from the surrounding fields. Mills have closed, and little industry remains. Today, the area's largest employer is a state prison north of town.</p>
        <p>It is where Ozella Garland, Jerry Reese's 66-year-old mother, works as a corrections officer. She has been there nearly 20 years, since the closing of a garment factory where she rose to the level of supervisor.</p>
        <p>Miss Ozella, as she is known around town, where she is viewed with awe and respect, had her children with a man named J. C. Hillsman. He was killed in 1971 -- the year Jerry, the third child, turned 8 -- in an accident at a mill that produced oil from cottonseeds. Hillsman had other children in Tiptonville, too, and the extended family remains close. When Reese returns, everyone in town knows, and he is instantly surrounded by relatives.</p>
        <p>''We don't consider them half-brothers and half-sisters,'' Reese said. ''They're brothers and sisters.''</p>
        <p>A few streets spill gently downhill from downtown, to a low area where many of the town's black residents live. (About one-third of Tiptonville's residents are African-American.) Until a levee was built in 2000, the neighborhood flooded frequently after spring rains, at times chasing families from their homes for weeks.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes me and Jerry would stay down there,'' said Clarence Garland, the 76-year-old stepfather who added stability and an income to the family when he married Ozella Reese 34 years ago. ''You know how it is, somebody might try to vandalize the house or something. We would sit on the porch and shoot snakes and frogs.''</p>
        <p>The beige house with brown trim burned down a few years ago, after the family moved out. There is nothing at 443 Tipton Street now but a patch of dandelions and grass, and a battered shed under a few large, graceful trees that once shaded the backyard.</p>
        <p>On Monday, Garland -- Pops to the children-- sat in the living room of the yellow home with the wide porch that he and Ozella share, on the uphill side of town. He worked as a machinist at a mill that turned soybeans into oil and the leftovers into feed. When the mill closed, he spent 21 years doing maintenance at Reelfoot Lake State Park, until he retired in 1996.</p>
        <p>The inside of the house is sprinkled with family photographs. Reese helped buy the home in 1994, the year he left his job as an assistant at Tennessee-Martin to become a scout for the Giants.</p>
        <p>It is a theme, Reese doing what he can to help the family. Surrounded by poverty, the family did not realize how poor it was -- among the poorest in a county with twice the national poverty rate.</p>
        <p>''There was no sense of feeling sorry for ourselves, because everybody we lived with lived the same way,'' said Jackie Bartlett, one of Reese's sisters.</p>
        <p>Ozella Garland, with the slight build, strong cheeks and green-hued eyes that she passed to Reese, sat in a hospital waiting room in Union City, a 30-minute drive around Reelfoot Lake. Her mother, Earlene Taylor, lay in a room down the hall, stricken with cancer, and had not been expected to survive the previous night. [On Friday, Taylor was resting at a nursing home in Tiptonville, surrounded by family.]</p>
        <p>Reese visited his grandmother in a Memphis hospital two weekends ago, before she was moved closer to home. His wife, Gwen, and their two children were scheduled to go to Tiptonville on Friday.</p>
        <p>Garland blanched a bit at the suggestion that her family ever struggled, saying it was blessed by God.</p>
        <p>''It wasn't that difficult, because we were so loving a family,'' she said. ''There was always togetherness. And we were always happy.''</p>
        <p>Still, if Reese roamed the fields or the edges of the ponds beyond the house and caught something -- a raccoon, a rabbit, a squirrel, a fish or a turtle, for example -- he took it home.</p>
        <p>''If it was available, we had a way to fix it,'' Jackie Bartlett said.</p>
        <p>Bartlett and Reese, separated by little more than a year, spent many of their childhood summers and other school breaks with their great-grandparents, Swan and Callie Johnson, in Parsons, Tenn. They mowed yards and gutted fish for 10 cents a pound. Jerry worked in the slaughterhouse, and Jackie cleaned homes.</p>
        <p>''As far as Jerry is concerned, our great-grandparents molded him into who he is,'' Bartlett said. Swan Johnson died in 1977, Callie about two years ago. ''I think my great-grandfather, Swan, really was a significant person in his life. He taught him how to do basically everything he learned how to do as a little boy -- to work hard, make a living. Jerry could make a living at 6 years old if he had to.''</p>
        <p>The ethic was instilled in all the children, who passed any earnings to the family. The kids took turns doing chores. They held odd jobs. They shared one television and went to bed simultaneously at 9 p.m. They punctuated their sentences with ''sir'' and ''ma'am,'' and were regulars at church.</p>
        <p>''Jerry came from two strong, God-fearing parents who have a lot of respect from everybody in the community -- black, white, rich, poor,'' said Evan Jones, the editor and publisher of the weekly Lake County Banner.</p>
        <p>Jones was there when Reese was the left-handed quarterback of Lake County High School's 1980 state championship team. A Banner photograph showed Reese being carried off the field on his teammates' shoulders. ''The glue,'' his coach, Cliff Sturdivant, called him in a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>No one was surprised that Reese, a poor child from the poor side of a poor town, could make the town proud. It ran in the family.</p>
        <p>''They had themselves, the family, and the Lord,'' said Eddie Cain, a Lake County High math teacher who was an assistant on the 1980 team. ''Let me tell you something about Miss Ozella: Every one of those children were respectful. They were kind, courteous, and they tried their best in class.''</p>
        <p>Praise for Reese is easy to find in Tiptonville, but Garland said that the young Jerry was ''just average.'' She had higher standards. In a county where 5.4 percent of the adults have college degrees (about one-fifth the national rate), the Reeses were far from average. All seven of the children went to college. It was expected.</p>
        <p>''I just thought he would be the average young man, get a job, and work and make himself a living,'' Garland said. ''I never thought, even when he went to work for the Giants, I never thought in my wildest dreams that he would advance to this.''</p>
        <p>On Tuesday at the high school, a 16-year-old named Erin Reid was summoned to the main office. He is about 5 feet 8 inches and 150 pounds, his small and sturdy frame carrying a mix of confidence and sheepishness.</p>
        <p>Reid is the son of Reese's youngest sister, Tracy. Teachers cannot get over how much he looks and acts like a young Jerry Reese.</p>
        <p>Needing a hero to highlight for a Black History Month project, Reid chose his uncle. Three large poster boards hung in the school library, having received high marks. They showed photographs and captions of Reese as a boy, of Reese as a high school football star and of the January news conference at Giants Stadium when Reese was introduced as the general manager.</p>
        <p>Reid looked down at a picture of a young Reese standing in a light-blue suit with teammates in the school courtyard. He looked over his shoulder, at the same courtyard through the window, then back at the courtyard in the photograph. It has barely changed in 26 years.</p>
        <p>''He walked these same halls,'' Reid said, and his tone suggested that he still had trouble believing it himself. ''He came from here.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
