<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Kidd at Full Speed, Nets Cruise to Victory</title>
    <meta content="28nets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/sports/basketball/28nets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843443"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Toronto Raptors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Toronto Raptors</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Basketball Assn</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Kidd, Jason</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Carter, Vince</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E7D6123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="782" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Kidd at Full Speed, Nets Cruise to Victory</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With Kidd at Full Speed, Nets Cruise to Victory</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eligon, John</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., April 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jason Kidd virtually glided down the court Friday night, his knee tightly braced, the ball serving as an extension of hands that possessed an uncanny intuition.</p>
        <p>Vince Carter was not far behind, on a collision course with a rim he became quite comfortable with.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jason Kidd had the 10th triple-double of his playoff career, as the Nets took a 2-1 lead in their N.B.A. first-round playoff series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jason Kidd virtually glided down the court Friday night, his knee tightly braced, the ball serving as an extension of hands that possessed an uncanny intuition.</p>
        <p>Vince Carter was not far behind, on a collision course with a rim he became quite comfortable with.</p>
        <p>Kidd flicked the ball behind his back. Carter caught it in stride and threw down a one-handed dunk, taking a foul in the process.</p>
        <p>With Kidd rekindling his one-legged heroism of years past, and Carter back in flight, the Nets cruised to a 102-89 victory against the Toronto Raptors to take a 2-1 lead in their N.B.A. first-round playoff series. Game 4 of the best-of-seven series will be played Sunday night at Continental Arena.</p>
        <p>Just over 24 hours before Friday night's game, Kidd was at the doctor's office with a swollen left knee that needed surgery three years ago. That did not stop him from getting the 10th triple-double of his playoff career in style: 16 points, 16 rebounds and 19 assists. Kidd is tied with Larry Bird for the second most triple-doubles in playoff history.</p>
        <p>Carter scored 37 points, 2 more than he had in Games 1 and 2 combined.</p>
        <p>Chris Bosh, the Raptors' star forward, gave perhaps the most fitting reaction to Kidd's performance: he cracked up.</p>
        <p>''He didn't look like he had an injury,'' said Bosh, who was held to 11 points and 3-of-10 shooting Friday night. ''When you're shaken up, sometimes, that makes you play a little bit better.''</p>
        <p>Kidd, who set a Nets record for assists in a playoff game, played nearly the entire 2003-4 season with an injured left knee. In the Eastern Conference semifinals that season, Kidd was held scoreless in a Game 7 defeat against the Detroit Pistons, and he had surgery on his knee in the off-season.</p>
        <p>This most recent injury, he said, was but a minor bump. And he appeared more inspired than hobbled.</p>
        <p>By halftime, Kidd had 14 assists, and he was only 4 points and a rebound shy of a triple-double. He got his triple-double with 5 minutes 17 seconds left in the third quarter.</p>
        <p>Kidd said the injury helped him focus, ''in the sense that you might not be able to be as fast, but you just have to be smarter to get to where you have to go and anticipate.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''You just try to play the game and get a feel and try to set the tempo and keep that tempo.''</p>
        <p>Kidd became only the third player in N.B.A. history to have at least 15 points, rebounds and assists in a playoff game. He is averaging a triple-double in this series with 12.7 points, 13.7 assists and 12.3 rebounds. But he has yet to grasp the magnitude of his numbers.</p>
        <p>''What did I accomplish?'' he asked after Friday night's game. ''My teammates made open shots. My teammates let me get some rebounds. And I made a layup or two.''</p>
        <p>The Nets scored the first 9 points of the game. It took the Raptors more than two and a half minutes to get a basket.</p>
        <p>Continental Arena had anything but the raucous capacity crowd that the Nets had to deal with in Toronto. But it was a comforting setting for Carter, who, with his offensive outburst, only gave more credence to the theory that he was uncomfortable playing in front of Raptors fans. Carter spent more than six seasons in Toronto, and the fans there boo him every time he touches the ball.</p>
        <p>In two regular-season games in Toronto this season, he averaged 14.5 points and shot 28.1 percent. In Games 1 and 2 of this series, he averaged 17.5 points and shot 30.2 percent.</p>
        <p>On Friday night, Carter made 9 of his first 10 shots and had 21 points at halftime. More important, he was not settling for shots from the perimeter. Carter had only three layups in the first two games, but he had four layups in the first quarter of Game 3.</p>
        <p>''I think I attacked the basket more,'' he said. ''I was more aggressive and I just continued to play.''</p>
        <p>It was a remedy Carter had counted on all along. In the days leading up to Game 3, he dismissed any notion that the atmosphere in Toronto contributed to his struggles or that he needed to make adjustments to his game.</p>
        <p>''Why change the routine because you're missing?'' he asked after practice Thursday. ''It's worked for me all year. It's been two games. I'm still putting some points on the board, still just being aggressive. That's all that counts. It'll come.''</p>
        <p>And it did on Friday night -- for both him and Kidd -- in a big way.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
