<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Former C.I.A. Chief's Memoir Irritates Some High-Ranking Readers</title>
    <meta content="28tenet" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/washington/28tenet.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843395"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Intelligence Services</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Central Intelligence Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shane, Scott</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tenet, George J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">At the Center of the Storm (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Intelligence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Tenet, George J</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902EED9123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Former C.I.A. Chief's Memoir Irritates Some High-Ranking Readers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Former C.I.A. Chief’s Memoir Irritates Some High-Ranking Readers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SCOTT SHANE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shane, Scott</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former CIA Dir George J Tenet's book, At the Center of the Storm, portrays Bush administration as being skeptical about views of intelligence agencies; some of Tenet's critics call his version of events selective or inaccurate (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In January 2002, George J. Tenet, the man who oversaw all American spy agencies, was asked by a visiting Italian intelligence official what he knew about United States officials making contact with exiled Iranian opposition figures.</p>
        <p>''I shot a look at other members of my staff in the meeting,'' Mr. Tenet writes in his newly published memoir. ''It was clear that none of us knew what he was talking about. The Italian quickly changed the subject.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>George J. Tenet’s account of tensions between intelligence officers and Bush administration policymakers fills in new details, and some of his critics have begun to reply.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In January 2002, George J. Tenet, the man who oversaw all American spy agencies, was asked by a visiting Italian intelligence official what he knew about United States officials making contact with exiled Iranian opposition figures.</p>
        <p>''I shot a look at other members of my staff in the meeting,'' Mr. Tenet writes in his newly published memoir. ''It was clear that none of us knew what he was talking about. The Italian quickly changed the subject.''</p>
        <p>The embarrassed Mr. Tenet, then director of central intelligence, had stumbled upon a quixotic effort by a few Pentagon officials working closely with a conservative Middle East specialist, Michael A. Ledeen, to meet with Iranian dissidents living abroad. It was neither the first nor the last time he would be surprised by intelligence efforts inside the Bush administration but outside official channels.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tenet's book, ''At the Center of the Storm'' (HarperCollins), portrays an administration in which many officials were skeptical about the views of the intelligence agencies. The skepticism put pressure on C.I.A. analysts to reconsider findings that did not suit some policymakers. On occasion, it created back channels and alternative analyses that angered and frustrated Mr. Tenet.</p>
        <p>Tensions between intelligence officers and Bush administration policymakers have often been reported. But Mr. Tenet's account of such clashes fills in many new details, and on Friday, some of his critics began to reply, calling his version of events selective or inaccurate.</p>
        <p>Dan Bartlett, the counselor to President Bush, on Friday offered a mild rebuttal of Mr. Tenet's assertion that there was never a ''serious debate'' of the Iraqi threat or the consequences of a prolonged occupation.</p>
        <p>''The president did wrestle with those very questions,'' Mr. Bartlett said on NBC's ''Today'' show. He called Mr. Tenet a ''true patriot'' but said he might not have been aware of all the internal prewar debate.</p>
        <p>In the book, Mr. Tenet describes repeated inquiries before the Iraq war from I. Lewis Libby, then Vice President Dick Cheney's chief of staff, and Paul D. Wolfowitz, then the deputy secretary of defense, seeking evidence linking Al Qaeda to Saddam Hussein's Iraq.</p>
        <p>''Some of our analysts, junior and senior, chafed at the constant drumbeat of repetitive inquiries on Iraq and Al Qaeda,'' Mr. Tenet wrote.</p>
        <p>He describes the C.I.A.'s top analyst, Jami Miscik, complaining that Mr. Libby, Mr. Wolfowitz and other officials ''never seemed satisfied with our answers.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Mr. Tenet had learned about the contacts with Iranian exiles, organized by Mr. Ledeen of the American Enterprise Institute and involving two Defense Department officials. They seemed to be in touch with, among others, Manucher Ghorbanifar, an Iranian exile who had been a middleman in the Iran-contra affair in the 1980s and who the C.I.A. believed was completely unreliable.</p>
        <p>''What we were hearing sounded like an off-the-books covert-action program trying to destabilize the Iranian government,'' Mr. Tenet writes, calling such a program ''Son of Iran-contra.''</p>
        <p>He recounts how he called on Stephen J. Hadley, then deputy national security adviser, to try to stop such contacts. Mr. Ledeen said Friday night that the meeting with the exiles was held to receive information about possible Iranian plots against American troops in Afghanistan, and had nothing to do with destabilizing Iran.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tenet also directs scorn at the Pentagon intelligence analyses by Douglas J. Feith, then undersecretary of defense for policy. He describes his fury in August 2002 as he watched a slide show by Mr. Feith's staff at C.I.A. headquarters suggesting ''a mature, symbiotic relationship'' between Iraq and Al Qaeda.</p>
        <p>He said C.I.A. officers came to call such reports, in a play on words, ''Feith-based analysis.'' In an interview on Friday, Mr. Feith said Mr. Tenet's account distorts the facts of the Pentagon effort and obscures Mr. Tenet's own public statements before the war. Mr. Feith noted that Mr. Tenet, in October 2002, sent the Senate intelligence committee a letter that said, ''We have solid reporting of senior level contacts between Iraq and Al Qaeda going back a decade.'' Mr. Tenet describes Tina Shelton, who presented part of the Feith slide show at the C.I.A. in 2002, as a ''naval reservist'' and quotes her as saying in introductory remarks, ''It is an open-and-shut case.''</p>
        <p>But Ms. Shelton said Friday she was never a Navy reservist and never said such a thing. She was a Defense Intelligence Agency analyst for 22 years before retiring in October, she said.</p>
        <p>Bill Harlow, Mr. Tenet's spokesman and co-author, said they apologized for misidentifying Ms. Shelton's job. No one transcribed the meeting, Mr. Harlow said, but Mr. Tenet remembered her remarks as he describes them.</p>
        <p>THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
