<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Top Pick Could Be Building Block, or on Trading Block</title>
    <meta content="28draft" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/28/sports/football/28draft.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843400"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Football League</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, Reggie</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Young, Vince</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E4D8123EF93BA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="699" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Top Pick Could Be Building Block, or on Trading Block</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Top Pick Could Be Building Block, or on Trading Block</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This year's N.F.L. draft may not have the glamour provided last year by Reggie Bush, Matt Leinart and Vince Young. But in his role as a draft linchpin, Al Davis, the Oakland Raiders' owner, is milking his turn as a star for as long as possible.</p>
        <p>Davis has made a career of keeping the league on its toes. And his choice of the No. 1 pick today has been held so closely that few people want to guess what he will do.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In recent years, the team holding the top pick in the N.F.L. draft has tried to sign the player to a contract before the draft begins. This year isn’t so predictable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This year's N.F.L. draft may not have the glamour provided last year by Reggie Bush, Matt Leinart and Vince Young. But in his role as a draft linchpin, Al Davis, the Oakland Raiders' owner, is milking his turn as a star for as long as possible.</p>
        <p>Davis has made a career of keeping the league on its toes. And his choice of the No. 1 pick today has been held so closely that few people want to guess what he will do.</p>
        <p>In recent years, the team holding the top pick has frequently tried to sign the player to a contract before the draft begins at noon. Last year, the Texans announced that they had signed defensive end Mario Williams on the Friday night before the draft. But this year, every mock draft comes with a large caveat, and almost every draft analyst is offering an opinion with a giant disclaimer attached.</p>
        <p>''Absolutely nobody knows what he's going to do, in my opinion, including Al,'' said Mike Mayock, a draft analyst for the NFL Network.</p>
        <p>The consensus is that Davis should take Louisiana State quarterback JaMarcus Russell. When Russell was asked to provide the top five for his mock draft this week, he laughed.</p>
        <p>''I can't even give you the first one,'' Russell said.</p>
        <p>The riddle is this: The Raiders desperately need a quarterback and Russell and Brady Quinn of Notre Dame are considered the top two, with Russell ahead of Quinn in most rankings. But receiver Calvin Johnson is considered the best player in the draft, and as much as Davis is thought to favor Russell for his cannonlike arm, Johnson has equivalent big-play capabilities.</p>
        <p>Johnson is also coveted by several teams with high draft picks. Davis could smartly not tip his hand, to force teams that want Johnson to consider handing the Raiders a bounty of picks. That would be similar to what the San Diego Chargers did when they picked Eli Manning No. 1 and traded him to the Giants.</p>
        <p>The Raiders have never moved down in the first round, and after passing on quarterbacks Matt Leinart and Jay Cutler last year, Davis could finally take a player who could turn into a franchise quarterback. Mel Kiper Jr., the ESPN draft analyst, espouses what seems to be a universal philosophy in the N.F.L.</p>
        <p>''You've got to get the quarterback first and worry about receivers later,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Kiper acknowledges that he -- like almost everyone else -- was also sure that the Texans would take Bush instead of Williams.</p>
        <p>The uncertainty creates more excitement for viewers watching the draft, but it can create uncomfortable moments in the green room, where the top prospects wait with their families under the glare of a dozen spotlights. Russell has taken a calm-and-cool approach to the fact that he will probably wake up Saturday with his future still unknown.</p>
        <p>''I'd rather not know,'' he said. ''I'd rather be shocked on draft day. If I know, what's the fun?''</p>
        <p>Perhaps Russell should check with Leinart, who sat ashen faced backstage a year ago when he slipped to the 10th pick.</p>
        <p>Quinn sat in the same spot at the annual predraft luncheon Thursday that Leinart occupied last year. Like Leinart, he drew one of the biggest groups of reporters. Since Russell eclipsed Quinn in the Sugar Bowl, they have been uneasily linked -- as Young and Leinart were last year. Quinn has generally come out on the short end of the comparisons, and some have suggested that he could fall as far as ninth. Quinn's hometown team, the Cleveland Browns, pick third and need a quarterback, and that is where Quinn has said he hoped to land.</p>
        <p>Quinn, after playing in Notre Dame's high-profile program, seems at ease in front of the cameras, seemingly ready for the broadcast booth as much as the N.F.L. He is trying to exude optimism.</p>
        <p>''People ask, 'Are you going to be disappointed if you slide?' '' Quinn said. ''Why? I'd be on a better team and have a better opportunity to win right away. I know I'll be relieved to have the question answered that's been in my mind.''</p>
        <p>He, and maybe Al Davis, too.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
