<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spring In Your Steps; The Northeast's Spine</title>
    <meta content="27hikeside" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/travel/escapes/27hikeside.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843138"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Walking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Appalachian Mountains</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caldwell, Dave</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Walking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Appalachian Region</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E5D8153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1424" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spring In Your Steps; The Northeast's Spine</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Northeast’s Spine</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on five two-day hikes along spine of Northeast's Appalachian Mountains; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Appalachian Mountains provide the Northeast with a stout, ancient spine. Hiking to the top of this backbone, through wooded and rocky trails thick with vegetation and crisscrossed by brooks, is often rewarded with a breathtaking view that changes with each step. Here are five two-day hikes recommended by those who know. The first is in north-central Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>FIRST DAY -- The 27.8-mile Old Loggers Path, a loop trail through Tiadaghton State Forest., mainly in Lycoming County, is classified as easy to moderate because it follows grades cut by early logging railroaders. The trail winds through woods that blaze with orange come autumn, and also traverses Rock Run, which is called one of the prettiest streams in Pennsylvania. It has sweeping vistas of a pristine countryside that seems remote, even though it is less than an hour's drive from Williamsport, Pa. The trailhead is off State Route 87 at Masten, Pa.</p>
        <p>SECOND DAY -- The Clarion/Little Toby Trail is an 18-mile hike that runs from Ridgway to Brockway, Pa. The easy-to-navigate trail, a Pennsylvania Railroad bed from 1885 to 1968, was converted for hiking in 1992 and does not cross a highway. It follows the Clarion River to the ghost town of Carman, then follows the Little Toby Creek to Brockway. Both are renowned trout streams. Deer, wild turkeys, herons and eagles populate the area. At the ghost town of Blue Rock, a swinging bridge crosses Little Toby Creek. The trailhead is three blocks from the center of Ridgeway off State Route 948.WHERE TO STAY The Towers Victorian Inn is an Italianate mansion built in 1865. The inn has six rooms and a two-bedroom carriage house. Weekend rates are $89 to $119, with weekday rates usually $10 less. 330 South Street, Ridgway, Pa.; (814) 772-7657; www.towersinn.com.</p>
        <p>INFORMATION www.pawilds.com.</p>
        <p>Upstate New York</p>
        <p>FIRST DAY -- Algonquin Peak, near Lake Placid, is the second-highest mountain in the Adirondacks and one of the most popular to climb. The ascent becomes tougher as hikers near the top, making the 4.3-mile trek from Adirondack Loj seem longer than it really is, but the rewarding view at the summit includes Mount Colden, lakes and other peaks. Neil F. Woodworth, executive director of the Adirondack Mountain Club, recommends the hike. The trail crosses a brook and passes a waterfall before reaching timberline about a half-mile from the summit. The hike begins and ends near Heart Lake, which is off State Route 73, four miles from Lake Placid Village.</p>
        <p>SECOND DAY -- Mount Jo is a smaller mountain on the north shore of Heart Lake. The hike to the top of Mount Jo, named in 1877 for Josephine Schofield, the fiancée of Henry van Hoevenberg (who owned the land on which the original Adirondack Lodge was built), is only a little more than a mile, but the hill is steep and challenging. The mountain club's High Peaks Region Guide describes the panorama from the summit as ''one of the best views for the least effort in the Adirondacks.'' The view includes Cascade Mountain, Mount Marcy, Algonquin Peak and Indian Pass. There are two main trails to the summit of Mount Jo: the Long Trail is, indeed, longer by two-tenths of a mile, but it is less strenuous.</p>
        <p>WHERE TO STAY -- Adirondack Loj, built in 1927, is on the shore of Heart Lake and is accessible by car. It is open year-round and has private and family rooms and a coed loft. Rates range from $45 a person for a loft bunk to $145 a person for a private room, double occupancy. Three-night and five-night specials are available. Adirondack Loj Road, Lake Placid, N.Y.; (518) 523-3441; www.adk.org/ad--loj.</p>
        <p>INFORMATION www.adk.org.</p>
        <p>Southern Vermont</p>
        <p>FIRST DAY -- The Green Mountain Club suggests tackling a 3.8-mile stretch of the Long Trail, which is a part of the Appalachian Trail, at Stratton Mountain. The trail, accessible from the Stratton-Arlington Road, crosses an old logging road and passes a beaver dam. The trail is covered unevenly by rocks for four-tenths of a mile to a shelf, then climbs again, through spruce and birch, to a view of Somerset Reservoir and Mount Snow. The ascent is 1,910 feet. The panoramic view includes Glastenbury Mountain, Mount Equinox and the Taconic Range, Mount Ascutney and Mount Monadnock.</p>
        <p>SECOND DAY -- A fire tower at Bromley Mountain, less than 20 miles west of Stratton Mountain, also has 360-degree views. The trail that leads to the tower is also part of the 270-mile Long Trail, which traverses Vermont. From the intersection of State Routes 11 and 30, the hike is a 5.4-mile round trip that takes about three and a half hours. The Web site trails.com recommends strolling through the Boswell Botany Trail at the Southern Vermont Art Center in nearby Manchester Center. The paths of the Botany Trail are lined with more than 30 types of ferns and 80 types of wildflowers.</p>
        <p>WHERE TO STAY -- The Equinox Resort and Spa in Manchester Village was established in 1769 and offers shooting, fly-fishing and falconry and off-road driving schools, as well as a spa and fine dining. Rooms start at $279; the resort has spa, ski, summer and winter specials. 3567 Main Street, Route 7A, Manchester Village, Vt.; (866) 346-7625; www.equinoxresort.com.</p>
        <p>INFORMATION www.greenmountainclub.org.</p>
        <p>Central New Hampshire</p>
        <p>FIRST DAY -- Franconia Ridge is heavily trafficked, but it has spectacular views of the rugged White Mountains, which is why it is recommended by Rob Burbank, the public affairs director of the Appalachian Mountain Club. An 8.9-mile loop covers both Mount Lafayette and Mount Lincoln. Part of the Franconia Ridge Trail serves up a knife-ridged crest that has scenic views below. A portion of Franconia Ridge, from Mount Lafayette to Little Haystack, is not unusually difficult, the Appalachian Mountain Club says in its White Mountain Guide, but the guide cautions that as the trail is above tree line, it should be avoided when storms are forecast.</p>
        <p>SECOND DAY -- A 3.2-mile round trip from a parking lot off U.S. Route 302 at Saco Lake to the top of Mount Willard can take three to four hours. The Appalachian Mountain Club considers Mount Willard one of the best day hikes in the White Mountains because of the spectacular view from the top toward Crawford Notch. Steep mountains drop into a U-shaped notch, created by glaciers. Peregrine falcons nest in the cliffs on the mountain, and the trail is closed when they do.</p>
        <p>WHERE TO STAY -- The Bartlett Inn is a bed-and-breakfast surrounded by the White Mountain National Forest, making it a great base for outdoor activities. Rates range from $79 for a small inn room during the week to $225 for a cottage on Columbus Day weekend, the height of the foliage season. U.S. Route 302, Bartlett, N.H.; (800) 292-2353; www.bartlettinn.com.</p>
        <p>INFORMATION www.outdoors.org.</p>
        <p>Western Maine</p>
        <p>FIRST DAY -- The Mahoosuc Range, near Bethel, Me., includes a number of challenging hikes that use parts of the Appalachian Trail. J. T. Horn, of the Appalachian Trail Conservancy, recommends climbing Old Speck from State Route 26 in Grafton Notch State Park. This part of the Appalachian Trail, known as the Old Speck Trail, stretches for three and a half miles until it intersects with the Mahoosuc Trail. Follow that trail about a quarter-mile to the Old Speck summit and an observation tower. A loop ascends to the top of an 800-foot cliff with views of Grafton Notch below. Speck Pond is about a mile from there, and has tent platforms.</p>
        <p>SECOND DAY -- The Wright Trail leads to the Appalachian Trail at Goose Eye Mountain in the Mahoosuc Range. The Wright Trail has a strenuous climb, but the view at the topis worth the hard work. Steve Spencer, the senior land and recreation manager for the Maine Bureau of Parks and Lands, recommends a circular valley about a half-mile into the north fork of the trail. He suggests staying on the marked trail to protect fragile plants like Bigelow's sedge and boreal bentgrass.</p>
        <p>WHERE TO STAY -- The Sudbury Inn is a handsome bed-and-breakfast built in the late 1800s that has 18 rooms, which include seven two-bedroom suites and a three-bedroom apartment with a fireplace. There is a restaurant with 29 draft beers like Sebago Red and Cole Porter. Spring rates are $89 to $275 a night. 151 Main Street, Bethel, Me.; (800) 395-7837; www.sudburyinn.com.</p>
        <p>INFORMATION -- www.appalachiantrail.org.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Recommended by those who know, here are five two-day hikes in the Appalachian Mountains.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Appalachian Mountains provide the Northeast with a stout, ancient spine. Hiking to the top of this backbone, through wooded and rocky trails thick with vegetation and crisscrossed by brooks, is often rewarded with a breathtaking view that changes with each step. Here are five two-day hikes recommended by those who know. The first is in north-central Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>FIRST DAY -- The 27.8-mile Old Loggers Path, a loop trail through Tiadaghton State Forest., mainly in Lycoming County, is classified as easy to moderate because it follows grades cut by early logging railroaders. The trail winds through woods that blaze with orange come autumn, and also traverses Rock Run, which is called one of the prettiest streams in Pennsylvania. It has sweeping vistas of a pristine countryside that seems remote, even though it is less than an hour's drive from Williamsport, Pa. The trailhead is off State Route 87 at Masten, Pa.</p>
        <p>SECOND DAY -- The Clarion/Little Toby Trail is an 18-mile hike that runs from Ridgway to Brockway, Pa. The easy-to-navigate trail, a Pennsylvania Railroad bed from 1885 to 1968, was converted for hiking in 1992 and does not cross a highway. It follows the Clarion River to the ghost town of Carman, then follows the Little Toby Creek to Brockway. Both are renowned trout streams. Deer, wild turkeys, herons and eagles populate the area. At the ghost town of Blue Rock, a swinging bridge crosses Little Toby Creek. The trailhead is three blocks from the center of Ridgeway off State Route 948.WHERE TO STAY The Towers Victorian Inn is an Italianate mansion built in 1865. The inn has six rooms and a two-bedroom carriage house. Weekend rates are $89 to $119, with weekday rates usually $10 less. 330 South Street, Ridgway, Pa.; (814) 772-7657; www.towersinn.com.</p>
        <p>INFORMATION www.pawilds.com.</p>
        <p>Upstate New York</p>
        <p>FIRST DAY -- Algonquin Peak, near Lake Placid, is the second-highest mountain in the Adirondacks and one of the most popular to climb. The ascent becomes tougher as hikers near the top, making the 4.3-mile trek from Adirondack Loj seem longer than it really is, but the rewarding view at the summit includes Mount Colden, lakes and other peaks. Neil F. Woodworth, executive director of the Adirondack Mountain Club, recommends the hike. The trail crosses a brook and passes a waterfall before reaching timberline about a half-mile from the summit. The hike begins and ends near Heart Lake, which is off State Route 73, four miles from Lake Placid Village.</p>
        <p>SECOND DAY -- Mount Jo is a smaller mountain on the north shore of Heart Lake. The hike to the top of Mount Jo, named in 1877 for Josephine Schofield, the fiancée of Henry van Hoevenberg (who owned the land on which the original Adirondack Lodge was built), is only a little more than a mile, but the hill is steep and challenging. The mountain club's High Peaks Region Guide describes the panorama from the summit as ''one of the best views for the least effort in the Adirondacks.'' The view includes Cascade Mountain, Mount Marcy, Algonquin Peak and Indian Pass. There are two main trails to the summit of Mount Jo: the Long Trail is, indeed, longer by two-tenths of a mile, but it is less strenuous.</p>
        <p>WHERE TO STAY -- Adirondack Loj, built in 1927, is on the shore of Heart Lake and is accessible by car. It is open year-round and has private and family rooms and a coed loft. Rates range from $45 a person for a loft bunk to $145 a person for a private room, double occupancy. Three-night and five-night specials are available. Adirondack Loj Road, Lake Placid, N.Y.; (518) 523-3441; www.adk.org/ad--loj.</p>
        <p>INFORMATION www.adk.org.</p>
        <p>Southern Vermont</p>
        <p>FIRST DAY -- The Green Mountain Club suggests tackling a 3.8-mile stretch of the Long Trail, which is a part of the Appalachian Trail, at Stratton Mountain. The trail, accessible from the Stratton-Arlington Road, crosses an old logging road and passes a beaver dam. The trail is covered unevenly by rocks for four-tenths of a mile to a shelf, then climbs again, through spruce and birch, to a view of Somerset Reservoir and Mount Snow. The ascent is 1,910 feet. The panoramic view includes Glastenbury Mountain, Mount Equinox and the Taconic Range, Mount Ascutney and Mount Monadnock.</p>
        <p>SECOND DAY -- A fire tower at Bromley Mountain, less than 20 miles west of Stratton Mountain, also has 360-degree views. The trail that leads to the tower is also part of the 270-mile Long Trail, which traverses Vermont. From the intersection of State Routes 11 and 30, the hike is a 5.4-mile round trip that takes about three and a half hours. The Web site trails.com recommends strolling through the Boswell Botany Trail at the Southern Vermont Art Center in nearby Manchester Center. The paths of the Botany Trail are lined with more than 30 types of ferns and 80 types of wildflowers.</p>
        <p>WHERE TO STAY -- The Equinox Resort and Spa in Manchester Village was established in 1769 and offers shooting, fly-fishing and falconry and off-road driving schools, as well as a spa and fine dining. Rooms start at $279; the resort has spa, ski, summer and winter specials. 3567 Main Street, Route 7A, Manchester Village, Vt.; (866) 346-7625; www.equinoxresort.com.</p>
        <p>INFORMATION www.greenmountainclub.org.</p>
        <p>Central New Hampshire</p>
        <p>FIRST DAY -- Franconia Ridge is heavily trafficked, but it has spectacular views of the rugged White Mountains, which is why it is recommended by Rob Burbank, the public affairs director of the Appalachian Mountain Club. An 8.9-mile loop covers both Mount Lafayette and Mount Lincoln. Part of the Franconia Ridge Trail serves up a knife-ridged crest that has scenic views below. A portion of Franconia Ridge, from Mount Lafayette to Little Haystack, is not unusually difficult, the Appalachian Mountain Club says in its White Mountain Guide, but the guide cautions that as the trail is above tree line, it should be avoided when storms are forecast.</p>
        <p>SECOND DAY -- A 3.2-mile round trip from a parking lot off U.S. Route 302 at Saco Lake to the top of Mount Willard can take three to four hours. The Appalachian Mountain Club considers Mount Willard one of the best day hikes in the White Mountains because of the spectacular view from the top toward Crawford Notch. Steep mountains drop into a U-shaped notch, created by glaciers. Peregrine falcons nest in the cliffs on the mountain, and the trail is closed when they do.</p>
        <p>WHERE TO STAY -- The Bartlett Inn is a bed-and-breakfast surrounded by the White Mountain National Forest, making it a great base for outdoor activities. Rates range from $79 for a small inn room during the week to $225 for a cottage on Columbus Day weekend, the height of the foliage season. U.S. Route 302, Bartlett, N.H.; (800) 292-2353; www.bartlettinn.com.</p>
        <p>INFORMATION www.outdoors.org.</p>
        <p>Western Maine</p>
        <p>FIRST DAY -- The Mahoosuc Range, near Bethel, Me., includes a number of challenging hikes that use parts of the Appalachian Trail. J. T. Horn, of the Appalachian Trail Conservancy, recommends climbing Old Speck from State Route 26 in Grafton Notch State Park. This part of the Appalachian Trail, known as the Old Speck Trail, stretches for three and a half miles until it intersects with the Mahoosuc Trail. Follow that trail about a quarter-mile to the Old Speck summit and an observation tower. A loop ascends to the top of an 800-foot cliff with views of Grafton Notch below. Speck Pond is about a mile from there, and has tent platforms.</p>
        <p>SECOND DAY -- The Wright Trail leads to the Appalachian Trail at Goose Eye Mountain in the Mahoosuc Range. The Wright Trail has a strenuous climb, but the view at the topis worth the hard work. Steve Spencer, the senior land and recreation manager for the Maine Bureau of Parks and Lands, recommends a circular valley about a half-mile into the north fork of the trail. He suggests staying on the marked trail to protect fragile plants like Bigelow's sedge and boreal bentgrass.</p>
        <p>WHERE TO STAY -- The Sudbury Inn is a handsome bed-and-breakfast built in the late 1800s that has 18 rooms, which include seven two-bedroom suites and a three-bedroom apartment with a fireplace. There is a restaurant with 29 draft beers like Sebago Red and Cole Porter. Spring rates are $89 to $275 a night. 151 Main Street, Bethel, Me.; (800) 395-7837; www.sudburyinn.com.</p>
        <p>INFORMATION -- www.appalachiantrail.org.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
