<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Young Mozart, Classically Serious and Silly</title>
    <meta content="27fint" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/arts/music/27fint.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843146"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Juilliard Opera Center</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E4D8153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="433" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Young Mozart, Classically Serious and Silly</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Young Mozart, Classically Serious and Silly</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIVIEN SCHWEITZER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schweitzer, Vivien</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are many operas ideal for avant-garde stagings. But Mozart's ''Finta Giardiniera'' has such a ludicrously complicated plot that you are thankful for period sets and costumes, and a simple, intelligent production, like the one offered by the Juilliard Opera Center on Wednesday night at the Peter Jay Sharp Theater.</p>
        <p>It's also an opera with old-school values: stand by your man, no matter what (even if he knifes you), and marry within your social class. Mozart wrote ''La Finta,'' his first dramma giocoso (or ''jocular drama''), at 18. The music, set to a libretto of indeterminate origin, is an astonishing feat for a teenager and almost as elaborate as the convoluted plot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Juilliard Opera Center offered a simple, intelligent production of Mozart’s ludicrously complicated piece on Wednesday at the Peter Jay Sharp Theater.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There are many operas ideal for avant-garde stagings. But Mozart's ''Finta Giardiniera'' has such a ludicrously complicated plot that you are thankful for period sets and costumes, and a simple, intelligent production, like the one offered by the Juilliard Opera Center on Wednesday night at the Peter Jay Sharp Theater.</p>
        <p>It's also an opera with old-school values: stand by your man, no matter what (even if he knifes you), and marry within your social class. Mozart wrote ''La Finta,'' his first dramma giocoso (or ''jocular drama''), at 18. The music, set to a libretto of indeterminate origin, is an astonishing feat for a teenager and almost as elaborate as the convoluted plot.</p>
        <p>The comedic moments of this opera, which blends serious and silly elements, rarely descended into slapstick in the director Jay Lesenger's mostly serious approach. Thwarted love, while often the butt of buffa jokes, is rarely funny in real life, and this staging elicited both sympathy and laughter.</p>
        <p>The strong cast provided much to admire. Erin Morley was superb as Sandrina (a k a the ''fake gardener''), singing with an agile, bright soprano and dramatic vulnerability. As Count Belfiore (her love interest), Timothy Fallon wasn't her vocal equal, but acted convincingly, particularly in the mad scene in which he and Sandrina lapse into delirium.</p>
        <p>Isabel Leonard was an excellent Ramiro, singing with a creamy, expressive mezzo and aptly conveying the young man's earnestness and anguish. As Arminda, Ramiro's (eventual) intended, Brenda Rae was coquettish and vocally able. The two buffa servant characters, Ariana Wyatt as Serpetta and David McFerrin as Nardo, were also strong, with a particularly amusing multilingual courting scene. The Mayor, left lovelorn at the end amid the happily reunited couples, was sung with panache by Jeffrey Behrens.</p>
        <p>Peter Harrison's elegantly simple sets featured sliding mirrored doors and painted backdrops depicting classical, naturalistic and romantic gardens. A backdrop with shapes that swirled into a face that looked like Munch's ''Scream'' coincided with the deluded howl of Sandrina and the Count at the end of Act II. The classical backdrop returned at the end of Act III to signify the restoration of order.</p>
        <p>The first act sometimes seemed static, but the pace quickened, and the singers warmed up considerably in the final two. The Juilliard Orchestra was in top form, with Gary Thor Wedow leading a focused, musical and detailed performance. Tempos were never breathless, and the collaboration between singer and orchestra was usually commendable.</p>
        <p>''La Finta Giardiniera'' will be performed again tonight and Sunday at the Peter Jay Sharp Theater at Juilliard; (212) 721-6500, juilliard.edu.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
