<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knee Injury May Leave Kidd on Sideline for Game 3</title>
    <meta content="27nets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/sports/basketball/27nets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843287"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Toronto Raptors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Toronto Raptors</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Kidd, Jason</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bosh, Chris</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E5DD123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="512" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knee Injury May Leave Kidd on Sideline for Game 3</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Knee Injury May Keep Kidd Out of Game 3</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eligon, John</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., April 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jason Kidd is questionable for Game 3 of the Nets' first-round playoff series against the Toronto Raptors on Friday night.</p>
        <p>Kidd strained his left knee when Raptors power forward Chris Bosh collided with him on the first play of Game 2 on Tuesday night. Kidd, a point guard, finished with 14 points, 11 rebounds and 7 assists, but the sixth-seeded Nets lost, evening the best-of-seven series at 1-1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kidd strained his left knee when Raptors power forward Chris Bosh collided with him on the first play of Game 2 on Tuesday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jason Kidd is questionable for Game 3 of the Nets' first-round playoff series against the Toronto Raptors on Friday night.</p>
        <p>Kidd strained his left knee when Raptors power forward Chris Bosh collided with him on the first play of Game 2 on Tuesday night. Kidd, a point guard, finished with 14 points, 11 rebounds and 7 assists, but the sixth-seeded Nets lost, evening the best-of-seven series at 1-1.</p>
        <p>''When there's something wrong with one of your top players, you're always concerned about it,'' Rod Thorn, the Nets' president, said in a telephone interview Thursday. ''We'll have to see what tomorrow brings. We're optimistic that he'll be able to play.''</p>
        <p>Kidd played nearly the entire 2003-4 season with a bad left knee. He had microfracture surgery on the knee after the season and has not had any major problems since.</p>
        <p>''He's one of the toughest guys in sports,'' Thorn said. ''I'm sure if he can go, he will end up going.''</p>
        <p>With or without Kidd, the Nets will need more from Vince Carter, who averaged 17.5 points and shot 30.2 percent in the first two games of the series. Carter might find comfort in returning to New Jersey. The Toronto fans heckled him mercilessly because, after he spent more than six seasons with the Raptors, they believe he gave up on the team. He was traded to the Nets in December 2004.</p>
        <p>Escaping Toronto might have a bigger impact on Carter than the support he will get from the home crowd. Since 2002, the Nets have been host to 13 first-round playoff games, selling out only 5 of them.</p>
        <p>As of Thursday evening, many tickets remained for Game 3. A scattered crowd would stand in contrast to the scene at the Air Canada Center. The arena was packed, the noise was nonstop, most of the fans wore red T-shirts and, for Game 2, they waved flags. It was a scene from a European soccer stadium.</p>
        <p>''It was great; I love that,'' Nets forward Bostjan Nachbar said of the atmosphere in Toronto. Nachbar, who is from Slovenia, started his career in Europe.</p>
        <p>''For me, that's something that I kind of missed the last couple years,'' he said. ''Any crowd is going to pump me up, whether it's cheering for me or against me.''</p>
        <p>During the regular season, the Nets averaged 16,926 fans at home, which ranked 20th out of 30 N.B.A. teams. Their arena seats a little more than 20,000.</p>
        <p>Even when there is not a sellout, Continental Arena is always a bit more electric during the postseason, said Richard Jefferson, who has been to the playoffs with the Nets every year since his rookie season in 2001-2. Since then, the Nets are 20-13 in home playoff games.</p>
        <p>''The crowds are more into it, they're a bit more excited,'' Jefferson said. ''I think more should be said about why we play so well at home, even given the lack of attendance. That's the way it's always been, so if you don't know any better, there's no need to worry about it.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
