<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>California to Address Prison Overcrowding With Giant Building Program</title>
    <meta content="27prisons" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/us/27prisons.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843218"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinhauer, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Construction and Maintenance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404EEDF123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="928" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>California to Address Prison Overcrowding With Giant Building Program</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">California to Address Prison Overcrowding With Giant Building Program</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER STEINHAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinhauer, Jennifer</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, April 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>California approves biggest single prison construction program in nation's history, in move to ease chronic overcrowding; will send 8,000 convicts to other states; plan will cost $8.3 billion and add 53,000 beds; state prisons house 173,000 inmates; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a move to ease chronic overcrowding, California lawmakers on Thursday approved the largest single prison construction program in the nation's history and agreed to send 8,000 convicts to other states.</p>
        <p>The plan, which would cost $8.3 billion and add 53,000 beds, has the strong backing of Gov. Arnold Schwarzenegger, a Republican, who is eager to avert a federal takeover of the state's prison system, one of the most dysfunctional in the nation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a move to alleviate chronic overcrowding, lawmakers have approved the largest single prison construction program in the nation’s history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a move to ease chronic overcrowding, California lawmakers on Thursday approved the largest single prison construction program in the nation's history and agreed to send 8,000 convicts to other states.</p>
        <p>The plan, which would cost $8.3 billion and add 53,000 beds, has the strong backing of Gov. Arnold Schwarzenegger, a Republican, who is eager to avert a federal takeover of the state's prison system, one of the most dysfunctional in the nation.</p>
        <p>California prisons are so overcrowded -- 16,000 inmates are assigned cots in hallways and gyms -- that the governor recently took the highly unusual step of declaring a state of emergency in the system. The state's prisons house 173,000 inmates -- far ahead of Texas, which has the next largest state prison system with 152,500 inmates -- and has an $8 billion budget.</p>
        <p>The California prisons are the subject of several lawsuits, their medical program is in federal receivership, and various other components of the system are under court monitoring. The courts had given the state until this spring to come up with an overpopulation plan or face possible receivership.</p>
        <p>Under the plan that narrowly passed both houses of the Democratic-controlled State Legislature, the state will move prisoners out of 17,000 temporary beds in places like gymnasiums and day rooms, either through transfers to prisons in other states or to older, unused jails in California that need repairs to be brought up to building and safety codes.</p>
        <p>The plan, aimed primarily at easing the prison population, would also free space for rehabilitative programs for inmates, lawmakers said.</p>
        <p>Further, the state will add the 53,000 beds over the next five years by building additions to existing prisons and through construction of so-called re-entry centers, or smaller buildings where prisoners would spend the last few months of their sentences in the towns and cities where they would eventually be paroled.</p>
        <p>The plan calls for two phases of construction, with the financing of the second phase contingent on benchmarks like the start of rehabilitation and mental health programs. The plan would be paid for over two phases with $7.1 billion in state bonds and $1.2 million in local money.</p>
        <p>Missing from the plan were a proposed sentencing commission and a program to reduce the number of parolees who re-enter the system, components that had been embraced by Democratic lawmakers and prison reform advocates, and, this year, by the governor. Seven of 10 inmates released from California prisons return, one of the highest recidivism rates in the country.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Schwarzenegger, made anxious by the watchful eyes of judges around the state, backed off the contentious proposals to change the parole structure and to examine sentencing practices, handing a victory to Republicans in the Legislature who would abide neither.</p>
        <p>''The things we didn't want to have in this bill are not in it,'' said Senator George Runner, chairman of the Republican caucus in the Senate. ''We need a program that keeps people incarcerated and tries to rehabilitate them. But if they can't be rehabilitated, then we need enough beds to bring them back.''</p>
        <p>The Democrats who ultimately voted for the plan despite its perceived shortcomings appeared to calculate that they would avoid looking soft on crime while leaving any legal fallout at the governor's door.</p>
        <p>The state had until the middle of May to convince the courts that it had a plan to relieve some of the overcrowding or face a takeover and the potential imposition of caps on the size of the prison population.</p>
        <p>It was unclear on Thursday whether the bill would pass muster with the courts. For instance, recent moves by the state to send prisoners to other jurisdictions around the nation was ruled unconstitutional by a state judge; lawmakers said language in the new bill would address the judge's concerns.</p>
        <p>The plan also does little to change the structural problems that have led to overcrowding, like the unusual parole system, which sends former inmates with minor infractions back to prison. Further, the state's sentencing structure is blind to the problem of prison population, meaning new inmates keep arriving regardless of the ability to accommodate them.</p>
        <p>Don Specter, the director of the Prison Law Office, which has filed a class-action lawsuit against the state over prison conditions, said the plan did not address many of the most serious concerns raised in the courts.</p>
        <p>''It won't do anything to provide short-term relief on the overcrowding,'' Mr. Specter said.</p>
        <p>Like many other states, California has had large prison building programs over the years, but few come close to the size or speed of this program. For example, since 1987 when Texas began to use general obligation bonds to build prisons, the state has used $2.3 billion in such bonds to do that.</p>
        <p>Some California lawmakers who voted against the plan expressed outrage on Thursday.</p>
        <p>''This is not a plan,'' said the Senate majority leader, Gloria Romero, Democrat of Los Angeles. ''This is a classic Hollywood prop that the governor wants to have when he walks into court on May 15. All we have done is dig ourselves into a deeper hole. This plan is not workable, and I fully expect a constitutional challenge.''</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Schwarzenegger seemed ebullient.</p>
        <p>''For the first time in a decade, we can add prison beds in California,'' he said in a statement. ''And that does not just include traditional beds. We will add beds with programs, education, drug and mental health treatment so that the California Department of Corrections and Rehabilitation can truly live up to the rehabilitation part of its name.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
