<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bristol-Myers Removes 'Interim' From Chief's Title</title>
    <meta content="27bristol" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/business/27bristol.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843215"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Bristol-Myers Squibb Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E0DF123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="887" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bristol-Myers Removes 'Interim' From Chief's Title</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bristol-Myers Removes ‘Interim’ From Chief’s Title</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE SAUL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Saul, Stephanie</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bristol-Myers Squibb's new boss is the same as the old boss. And investors are not exactly cheering.</p>
        <p>After an eight-month search for a new chief executive, the drug maker Bristol-Myers said it would go with the interim chief, James M. Cornelius. His contract will be for two years, until May 2009, when Mr. Cornelius will be 65.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The drug maker said it would go with the interim chief, James M. Cornelius, extending his contract for two years until he turns 65.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bristol-Myers Squibb's new boss is the same as the old boss. And investors are not exactly cheering.</p>
        <p>After an eight-month search for a new chief executive, the drug maker Bristol-Myers said it would go with the interim chief, James M. Cornelius. His contract will be for two years, until May 2009, when Mr. Cornelius will be 65.</p>
        <p>Despite the company's also announcing better-than-expected first-quarter earnings, the stock fell on the news of the contract. The shares ended the day at $29.23, down 47 cents or 1.58 percent.</p>
        <p>Andrew R. J. Bonfield, the company's chief financial officer, explained the decline as investors' taking the contract news as a sign that Bristol-Myers was no longer a takeover candidate.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Cornelius seemed to describe a go-it-alone strategy for now.</p>
        <p>''We are trying to run the business as a freestanding independent company and to do the right things for the long-term value of the shareholders,'' he told investment analysts yesterday.</p>
        <p>But several analysts said that the appointment of Mr. Cornelius to a two-year position should have little bearing on whether the company might still be ripe for a takeover.</p>
        <p>Instead, they read Mr. Cornelius's appointment as a sign that Bristol-Myers's executive search had yielded no strong -- or at least strongly interested -- candidates.</p>
        <p>''Gee, I wonder why people aren't jumping up and down to take that job,'' said Barbara Ryan, a pharmaceutical industry analyst for Deutsche Bank Securities, noting the company's challenges. They include a government antitrust investigation; a pending federal court decision on a patent dispute over its key product, Plavix; and a federal monitoring agreement that is similar to criminal probation.</p>
        <p>''We view this as a purely cosmetic move to minimize the distractions/questions created by his interim status,'' Ms. Ryan wrote in a note to Deutsche Bank clients.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ryan elaborated on her remarks in a telephone interview. ''It's difficult to have someone for a sustained period of time as the 'interim' leader,'' she said. ''All organizations need leaders.''</p>
        <p>Another analyst, Tim Anderson of Prudential Equity Group, told clients that he continued to think that a takeover might happen, with the most likely bidder Sanofi-Aventis, a French company that co-markets Plavix with Bristol-Myers Squibb.</p>
        <p>Speculation on such a deal has kept shares in the company trading at a 25 percent ''take-out'' premium over its peers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cornelius had said all along he was not interested in running the company on a permanent basis. After he was credited with helping engineer the $27 billion sale of the medical device maker Guidant to Boston Scientific in early 2006, Mr. Cornelius had planned to spend more time at his second home in Maui.</p>
        <p>But last September, he was selected from the Bristol-Myers board to take over temporarily for Peter R. Dolan, who was fired as chief after Federal Bureau of Investigation agents searched the company's Manhattan headquarters. The raid was part of an investigation into allegations the company lied to the Federal Trade Commission about its dealings with Apotex, a Canadian generic drug maker.</p>
        <p>Since then, Mr. Cornelius has called himself a reluctant volunteer.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, though, he described a change of heart. ''The longer I was here,'' Mr. Cornelius said, ''the more interested and confident I became that the prospects and opportunities were worth redeciding my retirement plans.''</p>
        <p>In his interim role, Mr. Cornelius appears to have attacked the job with zeal, making a point of scheduling visits to all the company's units. At a baby formula division in Indiana that is owned by Bristol-Myers, employees several months ago gave Mr. Cornelius a life-size statue of Peyton Manning, the quarterback for the Indianapolis Colts. Mr. Cornelius, who lives in Indianapolis, owns Colts season tickets.</p>
        <p>''I've thrown myself into the job 24/7 -- other than the Super Bowl,'' Mr. Cornelius said yesterday.</p>
        <p>James. D. Robinson III, the company's chairman, praised Mr. Cornelius's efforts.</p>
        <p>''He's restored momentum, moved quickly to streamline operations, build the business, and hold down costs,'' Mr. Robinson said. ''Our performance in the quarter is evidence of the solid progress we've made under Jim's leadership.''</p>
        <p>Bristol-Myers yesterday reported earnings per share of 38 cents, some 15 cents higher than analysts had expected, in large part because sales of Plavix, an anticlotting medicine, had held up better than many had feared.</p>
        <p>Sales for the quarter were down 4 percent, to $4.48 billion, partly from residual weakness in Plavix, which had been hurt by intense competition from Apotex. In three weeks last August, Apotex flooded the market with a six-month supply of a generic version of the drug.</p>
        <p>A federal judge ordered a halt to Apotex's shipments, but pills already in the distribution pipeline were not recalled.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Apotex's challenge of the Plavix patent continues to play out in federal court in Manhattan, where a decision is expected as early as June. Many analysts predict Bristol-Myers will win that case.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the company said it had overestimated the amount of Apotex's generic product in the market, which was part of the reason it raised its original earnings guidance for the year by 10 cents, revising it to $1.30 to $1.40 per share.</p>
        <p>The company also announced a partnership with Pfizer to develop and market the experimental product apixaban, also for blood clots. The partnership is seen as continuing Bristol-Myers's strategy to spread research and development risks, as well as marketing costs.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
