<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Listings: April 27 - May 3</title>
    <meta content="27theater" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843120"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EFDB153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="15020" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Listings: April 27 - May 3</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY ON THE VINE' In previews; opens on Wednesday. Zak Berkman's romantic fable follows a man falling in love with a budding star of right-wing radio (2:10). Clurman Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'CORAM BOY' In previews; opens on Wednesday. An adaptation of Jamila Gavin's novel about two orphans is the latest National Theater hit to move from London to Broadway (2:30). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'CYMBELINE' Opens on Wednesday. Declan Donnellan stages this Cheek by Jowl production of one of Shakespeare's last plays (2:40). Harvey Theater, Brooklyn Academy of Music, 651 Fulton Street, Fort Greene, (718) 636-4100.</p>
        <p>'DIXIE'S TUPPERWARE PARTY' In previews; opens on May 10. Dixie Wingate has left her Alabama trailer park to sell Tupperware in New York in this irreverent comedy (1:15). Ars Nova, 511 West 54th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444.</p>
        <p>'DEUCE' In previews; opens on May 6. The grandes dames Angela Lansbury and Marian Seldes play retired tennis players in this new Terrence McNally comedy. Michael Blakemore directs (1:45). Music Box Theater, 239 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'LEGALLY BLONDE' In previews; opens on Sunday. Laura Bell Bundy plays the smiling, ditsy sorority girl who takes Harvard Law by storm in this musical adaptation. Jerry Mitchell directs (2:20). Palace Theater, 1564 Broadway, at 47th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'LOVEMUSIK' In previews; opens on Thursday. The Tony winners Michael Cerveris and Donna Murphy star in a musical about the relationship between Kurt Weill and Lotte Lenya (with songs by Weill). Harold Prince directs (2:40). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'110 IN THE SHADE' In previews; opens on May 9. Audra McDonald stars in the Roundabout's revival of the musical version of N. Richard Nash's ''Rainmaker.'' Studio 54, 254 West 54th Street, (212) 719-1300.</p>
        <p>'PASSING STRANGE' Previews start on Tuesday. Opens on May 14. The Joe's Pub veteran and pop singer Stew tries his hand at musical theater, with a rock-theme score and a story about the journey of a bohemian (2:30). Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555.</p>
        <p>'RADIO GOLF' In previews; opens on May 8. The last play in August Wilson's cycle is set in 1997 and centers on the vital question of what will be done with the fabled Aunt Esther's house. Tonya Pinkins (''Caroline, or Change'') stars (2:30). Cort Theater, 138 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'A CHORUS LINE' If you want to know why this show was such a big deal when it opened 31 years ago, you need only experience the thrilling first five minutes of this revival. Otherwise, this archivally exact production, directed by Bob Avian, feels like a vintage car that has been taken out of the garage, polished up and sent on the road once again (2:00). Schoenfeld Theater, 236 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE COAST OF UTOPIA' Lincoln Center Theater's brave, gorgeous, sprawling and ultimately exhilarating production of Tom Stoppard's trilogy about intellectuals errant in 19th-century Russia. A testament to the seductive powers of narrative theater, directed with hot and cool canniness by Jack O'Brien and featuring a starry cast (Brian F. O'Byrne, Jennifer Ehle, Martha Plimpton, Josh Hamilton and Ethan Hawke, among others) in a tasty assortment of roles. Vivian Beaumont Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'COMPANY' Fire, beckoning and dangerous, flickers beneath the frost of John Doyle's elegant, unexpectedly stirring revival of Stephen Sondheim and George Furth's era-defining musical from 1970, starring a compellingly understated Raúl Esparza. Like Mr. Doyle's ''Sweeney Todd,'' this production finds new clarity of feeling in Sondheim by melding the roles of performers and musicians (2:20). Barrymore Theater, 243 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CURTAINS' This musical comedy about a musical-comedy murder -- featuring songs by John Kander and Fred Ebb and a book by Rupert Holmes -- lies on the stage like a promisingly gaudy string of firecrackers, waiting in vain for a match. The good news is that David Hyde Pierce, playing a diffident Boston detective, steps into full-fledged Broadway stardom. Scott Ellis directs a talent-packed cast that includes Debra Monk and Karen Ziemba. (2:30). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'FROST/NIXON' Frank Langella turns in a truly titanic performance as Richard M. Nixon in Peter Morgan's briskly entertaining, if all-too-tidy, play about the former president's annihilating television interviews with the British talk show host David Frost (the excellent Michael Sheen). Michael Grandage directs with the momentum of a ticking-bomb thriller and the zing of a boulevard comedy (1:40). Jacobs Theater, 242 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'GREY GARDENS' Christine Ebersole is absolutely glorious as the middle-aged, time-warped debutante called Little Edie Beale in this uneven musical adaptation of the notorious 1975 documentary of the same title. She and the wonderful Mary Louise Wilson (as her bedridden mother), in the performances of their careers, make ''Grey Gardens'' an experience no passionate theatergoer should miss (2:40). Walter Kerr Theater, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'INHERIT THE WIND' Doug Hughes's wooden revival of this worthy war horse, based on the Scopes ''monkey'' trial of 1925, never musters much more velocity than that of a drugstore fan. Be grateful that the cast includes Christopher Plummer, in savory form as a Will Rogers of jurisprudence. An oddly subdued Brian Dennehy plays his pompous adversary (2:00). Lyceum Theater, 149 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'JOURNEY'S END' A splendid revival of R. C. Sherriff's 1928 drama of life in the trenches during World War I. Acutely staged (by David Grindley) and acted by a fine ensemble led by Hugh Dancy and Boyd Gaines, this production offers an exemplary presentation of that theatrical rarity, an uncompromising, clear-eyed play about war and the experience of day-to-day combat. An essential ticket (2:40). Belasco Theater, 111 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MARY POPPINS' This handsome, homily-packed, mechanically ingenious and rather tedious musical, adapted from the P. L. Travers stories and the 1964 film, is ultimately less concerned with inexplicable magic than with practical psychology. Ashley Brown, who sings prettily as the family-mending nanny, looks like Joan Crawford trying to be nice and sounds like Dr. Phil. Directed by Richard Eyre and Matthew Bourne (2:30). New Amsterdam Theater, 214 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LES MISÉRABLES' This premature revival, a slightly scaled-down version of the well-groomed behemoth that closed only three years ago, appears to be functioning in a state of mild sedation. Appealingly sung and freshly orchestrated, this fast-moving adaptation of Victor Hugo's novel isn't sloppy or blurry. But its pulse rate stays well below normal (2:55). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'A MOON FOR THE MISBEGOTTEN' Kevin Spacey gives a bizarre, beat-the-clock performance, as lively as a frog on a hot plate, as James Tyrone in this off-kilter revival of Eugene O'Neill's last play. Mercifully, he does not block the view of Eve Best, who maps the contradictory levels of Tyrone's strapping love interest with clarity and intelligence (2:50). Brooks Atkinson Theater, 256 West 47th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PIRATE QUEEN' How to river-dance your way to the bottom of the ocean, courtesy of the songwriters of ''Les Misérables'' (2:30). Hilton Theater, 213 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' Duncan Sheik and Steven Sater's bold adaptation of the Frank Wedekind play is the freshest and most exciting new musical Broadway has seen in some time. Set in 19th-century Germany but with a ravishing rock score, it exposes the splintered emotional lives of adolescents just discovering the joys and sorrows of sex. Performed with brio by a great cast, with supple direction by Michael Mayer and inventive choreography by Bill T. Jones (2:00). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'TALK RADIO' The most lacerating portrait of a human meltdown this side of a Francis Bacon painting. Playing an abrasive radio talk show host with a God complex, the astounding Liev Schreiber seems to fill the air as inescapably as weather in Robert Falls's gut-grabbing revival of Eric Bogosian's 1987 play (1:40). Longacre Theater, 220 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE YEAR OF MAGICAL THINKING' Joan Didion's arresting but ultimately frustrating adaptation of her best-selling memoir about being blindsided by grief, starring Vanessa Redgrave. The tension between style and emotional content that made the book such a stunner does not translate to the stage. The substance here is in the silences, when the focus shifts from words to Ms. Redgrave's wry, wounded face (1:40). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE ACCOMPLICES' Bernard Weinraub, a former reporter for The New York Times, has chosen a worthy subject for his first play: In 1940, the young Zionist Peter Bergson was determined to persuade the United States government to open its arms to Jewish refugees fleeing the Nazis. Unfortunately, this production takes a hagiographic approach to its protagonist, emphasizing his heroism at the expense of more complex characterization. (2:00). Acorn Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200. (David Ng)</p>
        <p>'ALL THE WRONG REASONS: A TRUE STORY OF NEO-NAZIS, DRUG SMUGGLING AND UNDYING LOVE' John Fugelsang's amiable solo show mixes memoir and stand-up comedy in a tale of family, faith and Roman Catholic guilt. Slight but engaging (1:30). New York Theater Workshop, 79 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 460-5475. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'APOSTASY' Gino Dilorio's fearless play about a dying white Jewish woman who falls under the spell of a black televangelist is pretty good; the acting that delivers it is terrific, especially Susan Greenhill as the woman, and Susan Louise O'Connor as her daughter (2:00). Urban Stages, 259 West 30th Street, (212) 868-4444. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'BE' A high-energy, low-content Israeli show that blends music, dance and sex appeal in the latest attempt to tap into the ''Stomp'' market (1:30). Union Square Theater, 100 East 17th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 307-4100. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'THE BIG VOICE: GOD OR MERMAN?' Think of two gifted and smart gay men with years of life together deploying their considerable talents from the two pianos you happen to have in your living room. The result is a hilarious and very touching memoir of two decades of love and the funky glories of show business life (2:00). Actors Temple Theater, 339 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Honor Moore)</p>
        <p>'BILL W. AND DR. BOB' This insightful new play about the founders of Alcoholics Anonymous subtly makes the claim that the recovery movement was born as a series of accidents. Patrick Husted is excellent as Bob Smith, Bill Wilson's partner in combating addictions (2:15). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Ginia Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'BIOGRAPHY' A revival of S. N. Behrman's hoary 1932 comedy about a society portraitist and the men who keep trying to reign her in feels slight as a needlepoint pillow. As the play's supposedly beguiling heroine, Marion Froude, Carolyn McCormick never beguiles (2:15). The Pearl Theater, 80 St. Mark's Place, at First Avenue, East Village, (212) 598-9802. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>* 'BLACKBIRD'  David Harrower's stunning new drama looks back at a sexual relationship -- between a 40-year-old man and a 12-year-old girl -- that transforms, cripples and paralyzes. Jeff Daniels and Alison Pill, both extraordinary, peel their characters down to their barest souls. Joe Mantello is the masterly director (1:30). Manhattan Theater Club at City Center Stage I, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE FANTASTICKS' A revival -- well, more like a resuscitation -- of the Little Musical That Wouldn't Die. This sweet-as-ever production of Tom Jones and Harvey Schmidt's commedia-dell'arte-style confection is most notable for Mr. Jones's touching performance (under the pseudonym Thomas Bruce) as the Old Actor, a role he created when the show opened in 1960. Mr. Jones also directs (2:05). Snapple Theater Center, 210 West 50th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'IN THE HEIGHTS' Lin-Manuel Miranda's joyous songs paint a vibrant portrait of daily life in Washington Heights in this flawed but enjoyable show. Essentially a valentine to the barrio -- conflict of a violent or desperate kind is banished from the picture -- the musical contains a host of funny performances and brings the zesty sound of Latin pop to the stage. (2:10). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE J.A.P. SHOW: JEWISH AMERICAN PRINCESSES of comedy' Laughs along with longueurs (1:30). Actors Temple Theater, 339 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'A JEW GROWS IN BROOKLYN' You don't have to be Jewish or Brooklynish to empathize with Jake Ehrenreich, but in terms of fully appreciating his essentially one-man show, it probably helps. Especially the Catskills jokes (2:05). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 560-8912. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>* 'SPALDING GRAY: STORIES LEFT TO TELL' A disarming collage of selections from the monologues and journals of Mr. Gray, the ultimate stand-up solipsist, who died in 2004. Directed by Lucy Sexton, and read by five performers, none of whom resemble Mr. Gray, with an affection that shrewdly stops short of hero worship (1:30). Minetta Lane Theater, 18 Minetta Lane, Greenwich Village, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE VIEW FROM K STREET STEAK' An attempt at political satire that misses with just about every shot, this play ends up being simply confusing and boring, neither funny nor timely (1:50). Altered Stages, 212 West 29th Street, Chelsea, (212) 352-3101. (Wilborn Hampton)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'DENIAL' An engrossing and timely legal drama about a Holocaust denier being defended by a Jewish lawyer, this play examines the moral and ethical dilemma inherent in the First Amendment and asks how much sufferance can a free society give its crackpots and maintain its individual liberties (2:30). Metropolitan Playhouse, 220 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 995-5302. (Hampton)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden Theater, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' Singing CliffsNotes for Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' Often more entertaining than the real thing (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS'  The biomusical that walks like a man (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT'  A singing scrapbook for Monty Python fans (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' ''A Chorus Line'' with pimples (1:45). Circle in the Square, 254 West 50th Street, Manhattan, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'DEFENDER OF THE FAITH' This grim tale by Stuart Carolan of low-level I.R.A. agitators trying to identify the informer in their midst features some visceral performances and a set by Charles Corcoran that makes excellent use of the Irish Rep's small stage. If only the cause itself didn't feel so small in these days of global terrorism (1:30). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737; closes on Sunday. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>* 'DYING CITY' Christopher Shinn's crafty and unsettling play about grief and violence, set in the shadow of the Iraq war. Directed by James Macdonald and fiercely acted by Pablo Schreiber and Rebecca Brooksher, this quiet, transfixing production turns passive aggression into a theatrical dynamic (1:30). Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-7600; closes on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'EXITS AND ENTRANCES'  Athol Fugard casts a tender glance back at an actor whose dedication to theater helped spark his own in this warm if insubstantial stage memoir. Morlan Higgins capably excavates the emotional core of a role that might have seemed generic, playing an aging gay actor reckoning with the end of an up-and-down career. William Dennis Hurley plays the Fugard stand-in (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200; closes on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'JACK GOES BOATING' Bob Glaudini's gentle comedy about pothead losers in love is a reminder of how engrossing uneventful lives can be in the hands of the right actors. Peter DuBois directs the easygoing ensemble, brilliantly led by Philip Seymour Hoffman (2:00). Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555; closes on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LA MAGNANI' Theresa Gambacorta reincarnates the Italian film star Anna Magnani in this one-woman show, which reveals her to be more irritating than interesting: loud and self-absorbed (1:10). Arclight Theater, 152 West 71st Street, (212) 279-4200; closes on Sunday. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'MARIE ANTOINETTE: THE COLOR OF FLESH' Joel Gross's intriguing play features impeccable performances by Amanda Jones, Samantha Ives and Jonathan Kells Phillips as the three corners of a triangle of love and friendship caught up in the French Revolution. It's no ordinary triangle: Ms. Jones plays Marie Antoinette, and Ms. Ives the real portraitist who often painted her (1:30). The 45th Street Theater, 354 West 45th Street, Clinton, (212) 254-9533; closes on Sunday. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'MUD BLOSSOM' This brooding drama about three generations of suffering Southern women wallows in its own despair (1:50) Walkerspace, 46 Walker Street, near Church Street, SoHo, (212) 352-3101; closes tomorrow. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>'A DIOS MOMO' (No rating, 108 minutes, in Spanish) Directed by Leonardo Ricagni, this crude, sugary melodrama follows the uplifting misadventures of Obdulio (Mathias Acuña), an 11-year-old newspaper boy. Obdulio is illiterate and refuses to go to school, but he's obsessed with the Murgas, a troupe of traveling singers. He learns to read when his newspaper's watchman, Barrilete (Jorge Esmoris), dispatches him to the singers' practice room to scrawl Barrilete's lyrics on a chalkboard. This fairy-tale touch might work if the movie weren't so pleased with its own pie-eyed naïveté, and so eager to imitate the stalest aspects of films by the director's chief inspiration, Federico Fellini. (Matt Zoller Seitz)</p>
        <p>* 'ALICE NEEL' (No rating, 82 minutes) The fascinating documentary ''Alice Neel'' -- a biography of this influential, emotionally troubled portrait artist, by her grandson Andrew Neel -- juxtaposes relaxed interview footage and archival clips with more ragged, personal footage that reveals a filmmaker struggling to define an indefinable woman. The result is a film that seems more unfinished -- and thus more present tense -- than other examples of its type, and makes its subject, who died in 1984, seem very much alive. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>'AQUA TEEN HUNGER FORCE COLON MOVIE FILM FOR THEATERS' (R, 87 minutes) Not as funny as the title or the Cartoon Network series on which it's based. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>'Blades of Glory' (PG-13, 93 minutes) In this fast, light, frequently funny comedy about a male figure-skating team, Will Ferrell and Jon Heder stake an early claim to being the comedy couple of the year. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>'DISTURBIA' (PG-13, 104 minutes) A pleasant, scary, well-directed variation on the killer-next-door theme, with the engaging Shia LeBeouf as Kale, a young man who turns house arrest into an occasion for voyeurism and crime-fighting. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'ELECTION' (No rating, 100 minutes, in Cantonese) This intricate gangster entertainment, the first episode in a two-part sequence from the prolific Hong Kong action maestro Johnnie To, offer some acute lessons in the pitfalls of democracy. Also a feast of fighting, humor and fine acting, in particular from Simon Yaw, who plays a soft-spoken, businesslike candidate for chairman of Hong Kong's oldest criminal organization. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'FRACTURE' (R, 111 minutes) A glib entertainment that offers up the spectacle of that crafty scene-stealer Anthony Hopkins mixing it up with that equally cunning screen-nibbler Ryan Gosling. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE GLAMOROUS LIFE OF SACHIKO HANAI' (No rating, 90 minutes, in Japanese) A wayward bullet turns a hooker into a brainiac in this Japanese clutter of soft-core political parody, hard-core narrative nonsense, breezy sexism and penny-ante surrealism. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'GRINDHOUSE' (R, 180 minutes) A double feature, complete with fake previews for schlocky exploitation pictures, that pays nostalgic tribute to disreputable traditions of moviemaking and moviegoing. Robert Rodriguez contributes ''Planet Terror,'' a purposely incoherent zombie gross-out flick that flaunts is own badness the way Rose McGowan (as a go-go dancer named Cherry Darling) shows off her weaponized prosthetic leg. For his part, Quentin Tarantino, more of a connoisseur than his collaborator (and a much better filmmaker), turns out a brutal, talky and satisfying car-chase revenge movie in ''Death Proof,'' starring Kurt Russell. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'THE HOAX' (R, 115 minutes) A first-rate performance by Richard Gere drives this true story of Clifford Irving (Mr. Gere), who claimed to be the authorized biographer of Howard Hughes. Shadowed by the paranoia of its period (the early '70s), this movie, crisply directed by Lasse Hallstrom from an excellent script by William Weaver, is less a morality play than an entertaining portrait of a literary gambler. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'HOT FUZZ' (R, 121 minutes) A British parody of Hollywood-style action flicks from the wits behind ''Shaun of the Dead.'' Think of it as ''The Full Monty'' blown to smithereens. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'IN THE LAND OF WOMEN' (PG-13, 98 minutes) This meek, mopey comedy is the film equivalent of a sensitive emo band with one foot in alternative rock and the other in the squishy pop mainstream. The movie would like to think of itself as a softer, fuzzier ''Garden State.'' (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'KILLER OF SHEEP' (No rating, 83 minutes) Largely hidden from view for three decades, Charles Burnett's lyrical film about a working-class family living in a broken-down home in a bombed-out stretch of Los Angeles is an American masterpiece, independent to the bone. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'LONELY HEARTS' (No rating, 100 minutes) This beautifully photographed remake of Leonard Kastle's 1970 cult B movie ''The Honeymoon Killers'' succeeds better than many modern crime dramas in balancing the philosophical with the visceral, although its villains' dirty deeds still trump its deeper strain of melancholy. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'PATHFINDER' (R, 100 minutes) It's all grunting, all goring in this witless period flick about some Norsemen of the apocalypse come to wreak bloody ruin in the New World. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'PERFECT STRANGER' (R, 109 minutes) There is enough of a grain of truth in this noirish, paranoid thriller set in the New York media world that even after it lurches from the farfetched into the preposterous, the movie leaves a clammy residue of unease. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'PRIVATE FEARS IN PUBLIC PLACES' (No rating, 120 minutes, in French) A film from the venerable French auteur Alain Resnais about love and cinematic spaces, elegant camera moves and six heavenly bodies as seen through a mighty telescope. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'RED ROAD' (No rating, 113 minutes) Andrea Arnold's first feature falls into melodrama and implausibility at the end, but along the way it is a remarkably assured and complex piece of work, anchored by the director's formal control and by Jackie Dick's quietly heartbreaking performance as a Glasgow video-surveillance officer with an unhappy past. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'ROCK THE BELLS' (No rating, 103 minutes) Casey Suchan and Denis Henry Hennelly's lively documentary follows the independent music promoter Chang Weisberg as he struggles to reunite the original members of the Wu-Tang Clan for a 2004 hip-hop concert. Capturing onstage and off with equal energy, the movie is a fascinating glimpse of a dreamer and a music culture that has always depended on them. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'STEPHANIE DALEY' (R, 91 minutes) There is a fine line between a human drama with an autonomous life and an issue-oriented dramatic essay. If this drama about a teenage girl prosecuted for murdering her baby didn't have its ear so perfectly attuned to the tone and language of intergenerational dialogue, it would come across as a dry, cinematic essay. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'SYNDROMES AND A CENTURY' (No rating, 105 minutes, in Thai) Apichatpong Weerasethakul, a Thai director who has become a star of the international festival circuit, makes films that are difficult, abstract and mysterious in the best art-cinema tradition, but at the same time characterized by unusual warmth and generosity of spirit. ''Syndromes,'' suggested by the lives of the filmmaker's parents and the music of Mozart, is a two-part invention on the themes of chance and longing, shot with an intoxicating mix of suavity and sensuality. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'TRIAD ELECTION' (No rating, 93 minutes, in Cantonese) The surfaces gleam as luxuriously in Johnnie To's exemplary gangster thriller ''Triad Election'' as those in a similarly slicked-up Hollywood film, but the blood on the floor here seems stickier, more liable to stain. A brutal look at the shadows darkening the Hong Kong triads, the film picks up the narrative line first coiled and kinked in Mr. To's companion thriller, ''Election.'' (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'VACANCY' (R, 80 minutes) This banal horror retread involves a couple of critters (Luke Wilson, Kate Beckinsale) flailing inside a sticky trap for what is, in effect, the big-screen equivalent of a roach motel. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'THE VALET' (PG-13, 85 minutes, in French) If you love to hate the superrich, this delectable comedy, in which the great French actor Daniel Auteuil portrays a piggy billionaire industrialist facing his comeuppance, is a sinfully delicious bonbon, a classic French farce with modern touches. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'YEAR OF THE DOG' (PG-13, 97 minutes) Mike White's touching comedy about a woman who loses a dog and finds herself is funny ha-ha but firmly in touch with its downer side, which means that it's also funny in a kind of existential way. Molly Shannon stars alongside a menagerie of howling scene-stealers. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'ZOO' (No rating, 76 minutes) Robinson Devor's heavily reconstructed documentary is, to a large extent, about the rhetorical uses of beauty. It is, rather more coyly, also about a man who died after having sex with a stallion. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>avant-garde features (Tonight) Anthology Film Archives, the East Village repository of avant-garde cinema, begins this monthly series devoted to that least commercial of formats, the feature-length experimental film. The initial offering, ''La Raison Avant la Passion,'' Joyce Wieland's 80-minute film from 1969, is a reflection on the author's home country, Canada. It consists of images from a cross-country trip on the Trans-Canada Highway combined with anagrams drawn from the title phrase, a quotation from a speech by Pierre Trudeau. Anthology Film Archives, 32 Second Avenue, at Second Street, East Village, (212) 505-5181, anthologyfilmarchives.org; $8. (Dave Kehr)</p>
        <p>* COMMITMENT AND GRACE: THE FILMS OF CARLOS SAURA (Tomorrow, Sunday, Monday and Wednesday) Mr. Saura is, of course, one of Spain's greatest filmmakers. But for those who love dance, he will always be an artist who speaks vivid new truths about Spanish dancing and the relationship of film and dance. This tribute covers 50 years of work. (Through May 3.) Mr. Saura's magisterial ''Flamenco,'' as much about a nation as about a national dance form, will be shown tomorrow at 9:30 p.m. and Monday at 3 and 7 p.m. Sunday programs are devoted to dance, with ''Blood Wedding'' and ''Sevillanas'' shown at 2 p.m., ''Carmen'' at 4:25 p.m. and ''El Amor Brujo'' (''Love the Magician'') at 6:30 p.m. Wednesday's dance films are ''Blood Wedding,'' at noon; ''Carmen,'' at 1:30 p.m.; and ''El Amor Brujo'' at 3:30 p.m. Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5600, filmlinc.com; $11; $7 for students with ID; $7 for 65+ at weekday screenings before 6 p.m. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>FARES TO REMEMBER (Friday through Sunday) This monthlong series of films set in and around taxicabs comes to an end at the IFC Center with two prime examples of this curious sub-genre: Phil Karlson's first-rate film noir ''99 River Street'' (1953), with John Payne as a taxi-driving former heavyweight champ who finds himself accused of his wife's murder, and Jim Jarmusch's 1991 ''Night on Earth,'' five tales of nocturnal taxi rides set in New York, Paris, Los Angeles, Helsinki and Rome. IFC Center, 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 924-7771, ifccenter.com; $10.75. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>FILMMAKERS AT MACDOWELL: THE STUDIO SYSTEM RECONSIDERED (Wednesday and Thursday) MoMA begins a series of 26 films and video pieces from directors who have passed through the fellowship program at the MacDowell Colony in New Hampshire with a newly commissioned work, ''Seasons of MacDowell.'' It is a four-part film that features contributions by Michael Almereyda, George Griffin, David Petersen and Elisabeth Subrin. (The four filmmakers, along with the chairman of MacDowell, Robert MacNeil, will be present for the Wednesday night screening.) Films being shown on Thursday include work by Cindy Stillwell, Joel Katz, Chris Schiavo, Fern Seiden and Stacey Steers. The series continues through May 16. Museum of Modern Art Roy and Niuta Titus Theaters, (212) 708-9400, moma.org; $10. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>'MANY FACES OF CHIKA' (Tuesday) The North American premiere of the one fiction feature directed by the pre-eminent Japanese documentary filmmaker Kazuo Hara (''The Emperor's Naked Army Marches On''). Anticipating Todd Solondz's ''Palindromes,'' Mr. Hara uses four different actresses to play a single character, that of a woman who abandons her husband and infant son to wander the chaotic world of Japan in the late 1960s and early '70s. After the 7 p.m. screening, Mr. Hara and his longtime writing and producing partner, Sachiko Kobayashi, will participate in a discussion led by the Village Voice film critic Ed Halter. Japan Society, 333 East 47th Street, Manhattan, (212) 715-1258, japansociety.org; $13. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>ACID MOTHERS TEMPLE (Tonight) This prolific Japanese band describes its style as ''extreme trip music,'' which basically means big, sloppy noise jams. It doesn't necessarily mean peasant frocks and long wizard's robes, but Acid Mothers Temple usually has those too. At 9, Southpaw, 125 Fifth Avenue, near Sterling Place, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0236, spsounds.com; $15. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>* KAREN AKERS (Tonight and tomorrow night, and Tuesday through Thursday) The songs in ''Simply Styne,'' Ms. Akers's beautiful tribute to the composer Jule Styne, have been arranged into a touching, tongue-in-cheek cabaret answer to ''Scenes From a Marriage.'' The pianist Don Rebic is her witty partner in deconstruction. At 9, with additional shows tonight and tomorrow night at 11:30, Oak Room at the Algonquin Hotel, 59 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212) 419-9331, algonquinhotel.com; $60 cover; $65 dinner charge at 9; $25 minimum at 11:30. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>* AWESOME COLOR, DIRTY PROJECTORS, DEERHUNTER, BLACK MOTH SUPER RAINBOW (Tonight) Awesome Color's gruff, retro garage-blues is self-consciously noisy as only New York rock can be, but it is also indebted -- and seems partly a homage -- to the vintage Detroit proto-punk of the Stooges and the MC5. Dirty Projectors builds elaborate ''glitch operas'' with stark pluckings of strings and precise, ecstatic harmonies, all arranged slightly out of whack. Deerhunter, from Atlanta, weaves sweet guitar and vocal melodies into patterns that seem both florid and evil. Black Moth Super Rainbow, from Pittsburgh, delivers its shimmering psychedelia through a screen of pulsating keyboards and blissed-out, robotic vocals. At 10, Silent Barn, 915 Wyckoff Avenue, at Hancock Street, Bushwick, Brooklyn, toddpnyc.com; $8. Black Moth Super Rainbow also plays tomorrow at midnight at Pianos, 158 Ludlow Street, near Rivington Street, Lower East Side, (212) 505-3733, pianosnyc.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BELMONT PLAYBOYS (Tomorrow) A sturdy quartet from Charlotte, N.C., the Belmont Playboys play rockabilly forged in a punk esthetic, with energy and respect. At 10:30 p.m., Rodeo Bar, 375 Third Avenue, at 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 683-6500, rodeobar.com; no cover. (Ben Ratliff)</p>
        <p>BISHOP ALLEN (Tomorrow) Borrowing from the playbook of early Jonathan Richman, this Brooklyn band puts a boyish smile on spunky, angst-ridden guitar-pop, and nurses worries about the slow crawl toward the workaday adult life: ''Burn, calendar, burn.'' With Miguel Mendez. At 6:30 p.m., Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3132, knittingfactory.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* BJORK (Wednesday) It's been a long time since Bjork's combination of wailing indie-rock, eroticized electronica and use of random musical props -- Inuit choirs, African kora players -- has been truly avant-garde, or even surprising. But her latest album, ''Volta'' (Elektra), still sounds fresh and energized, with every sound becoming her exotic plaything, whether somber brass, tribal rhythms or staticky beats by Timbaland. At 8 p.m., Radio City Music Hall, (212) 307-7171, radiocity.com; $61 to $86. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CANNIBAL CORPSE (Sunday) The guttural grind of this veteran Buffalo band comes with a punishing regularity, like some nightmarish war machine. Onstage the band is ragged and battle-ready, with guitars clutched like weapons and long hair swirling in ritualistic synchronization. With Behemoth, the Red Chord, Job for a Cowboy and Psyopus. At 7 p.m., Fillmore New York at Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800; $22 in advance, $24 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CRIBS (Wednesday and Thursday) Jeez, the Strokes really are an incredibly influential band. This British trio, with two albums under its belt and a third coming in July, sounds awfully familiar playing those sneering melodies and sharp, uptight chords. The Cribs do it well, and seem to be having a great, sweaty time with it, but still, haven't we been through this before? At 10 p.m., Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700, mercuryloungenyc.com; $15. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>THE KILLERS (Tomorrow) Not many young bands have the songwriting chops to back up their big-league arrogance the way the Killers do. Three years ago this Las Vegas quartet became instant stars with ''Hot Fuss,'' whose adrenalized update of new-wave rock cloaked some of the blasé cynicism of its lyrics (''Dreams aren't what they used to be''). ''Sam's Town'' (Island/Def Jam), released last fall, is grandiose and aloof where its predecessor was sharp and hungry, though it still has a few songs you won't easily get out of your head. At 8 p.m., Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741, thegarden.com; $30 and $45. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PAMELIA KURSTIN, BARBEZ, BIG LAZY (Tonight) Ms. Kurstin plays the theremin, the eerie-sounding electronic instrument ubiquitous in 1950s horror movies, which is controlled by gesturing in the air around two metal rods. It's not easy to develop a recognizable style on the instrument, but she has earned a reputation for her lyrical solos and walking bass lines (really). Here, celebrating the release of her solo album, ''Thinking Out Loud'' (Tzadik), she is joined by Barbez, an avant-cabaret band she plays in; and Big Lazy, whose instrumentals taste of twangy rockabilly and the gutter jazz of the Lounge Lizards. At 9, Brooklyn Lyceum, 227 Fourth Avenue, at Union Street, Park Slope, (718) 857-4816, brooklynlyceum.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* LIGHTNING BOLT, SUN RA ARKESTRA (Tonight) At first it's hard to believe that all the glorious chaos of Lightning Bolt is being made by only two people. But as the sound comes into focus, a playful give-and-take becomes clear, as the bassist Brian Gibson and the drummer and vocalist Brian Chippendale toss back and forth gigantic metal riffs and giggly high notes, creating rainbows of dissonance. In the kind of smart cross-genre pairing that happens all too rarely, the band is playing with the Sun Ra Arkestra, which carries on its namesake's legacy of liberating cacophony. At 6, Pratt Institute Main Lawn, 200 Willoughby Avenue, between Hall Street and Emerson Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, toddpnyc.com; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MAD PROFESSOR (Tuesday) Mad Professor is a master of dub reggae, the music of subterranean bass lines, eerie echoes and unexplained fissures in the fabric of space-time. At 10 p.m., S.O.B.'s, 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940, sobs.com; $22. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>NELLIE McKAY (Tonight) Since her ejection from the mainstream record industry a year ago, Ms. McKay has been keeping busy with other projects: a stint on Broadway, appearances at Lincoln Center. She's doing O.K. Tonight she brings her winky-wink amalgam of American Songbook pop, rap and '50s-style bubblegum (''I'm gonna pounce/Meow/Like a pussy cat'') to Zankel Hall. At 8:30, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $38 to $43. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* MODEST MOUSE (Sunday and Monday) A band so emblematic of 21st-century indie rock that it was mentioned by name in the Supreme Court's decision on MGM v. Grokster two years ago, Modest Mouse, from Issaquah, Wash., links antsy, catchy guitar lines to vocals that are always just a few shrieks away from a destructive tantrum. The addition of Johnny Marr, the innovative former guitarist of the Smiths, has thickened the band's sound without making it any less volatile. At 8 p.m., United Palace Theater, 4140 Broadway, at 175th Street, Washington Heights, (212) 307-7171, bowerypresents.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MOE (Wednesday and Thursday) One chord is all Moe needs to start one of its nimble, quick-fingered jams. Its music starts with the Grateful Dead-Allman Brothers hybrids that most jam bands use, and from there it takes off toward Southern rock, spacey interludes or the borderline of funk. At 9 p.m., Highline Ballroom, 431 West 16th Street, Chelsea, (212) 414-5994, highlineballroom.com; sold out. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>VAN MORRISON (Sunday) Jazz, penitent country and lots of tasty, Celtic-favored R&amp;B fuel Mr. Morrison's incantatory performances, which can smolder intensely or rest in a meditative stillness according to his mood. At 7:30 p.m., Theater at Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741, thegarden.com; $90 and $175. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>GRAHAM PARKER AND THE LATEST CLOWNS (Tonight) Emerging from England just before the arrival of punk rock, Mr. Parker used the sturdy structures of soul and '60s rock, spitting out angry, articulate songs that chafed against dishonesties large and small. These days he's less furious and more cranky, but he's still holding the world around him to high standards. At 8, Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3132, knittingfactory.com; $25. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>Shahid Parvez (Tomorrow) Shahid Parvez carries on a legacy of sitar playing that goes back seven generations in his family. He is one of India's more celebrated younger musicians, prized especially for the vocalistic phrasing of his raga improvisations. He is to play duets with Aditya Kalyanpur on tabla. At 8 p.m., Philip Coltoff Center, 219 Sullivan Street, near West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 477-5239, virsaonline.com; $25. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>* PETER BJORN AND JOHN; FUJIYA &amp; MIYAGI (Tuesday and Wednesday) The latest sharp and impeccably stylish import from Sweden, Peter Bjorn and John sets breathy, heavy-hearted vocals over peppery band arrangements that recall 1960s folk-pop. Fujiya &amp; Miyagi, a British trio -- ''We are only pretending to be Japanese,'' goes one lyric -- plays bubbly perpetual-motion figures of guitar and keyboard. Its sound has been heard plenty of times before (Stereolab, Neu!), but it's too fun and innocuous to ever tire of. At 8 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* LOU REED (Monday) Representing the best of New York rock's past, Lou Reed might seem an odd choice to open a new club. But hey, it's Chelsea 2007, and that means glitz and fame and velvet ropes, so Mr. Reed, 65, is the first booking in the 700-capacity new Highline Ballroom. His onstage manner, never exactly warm, has stiffened in recent years, but he still expertly walks a line between aloof cynicism and naked, affecting vulnerability. With Okkervil River, a hyperliterate band from Austin, Tex. At 9 p.m., 431 West 16th Street, Chelsea, (212) 414-5994, highlineballroom.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ROSE HILL DRIVE (Tomorrow) Like the blues-rock power trios of yore, Rose Hill Drive, from Boulder, Colo., puts all its attention to bruising, jammable riffs, leaving the edges deliberately rough. At 8:30 p.m., Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700, mercuryloungenyc.com; $15. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Keely Smith (Tonight and tomorrow night) This ''queen of swing,'' as she has been nicknamed, may be the last surviving top-of-the-line entertainer from the Rat Pack era of Las Vegas. She is still in reasonably good voice. At 8:45 and 10:45, Café Carlyle, Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212) 744-1600, thecarlyle.com; $75 to $125. (Holden)</p>
        <p>AMON TOBIN (Tomorrow) A decade ago this Brazilian D.J.'s warped, flagellum rhythms seemed about as far out as dance-based music could get. His new album, ''Foley Room'' (Ninja Tune), is just as squiggly and disorienting, though it has lost what it now appears was its most significant trait: novelty. At 9 p.m., Blender Theater at Gramercy, 127 East 23rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171; $23. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>TRANS AM (Thursday) This trio from Washington plays tightly coiled, retro-futuristic electronic rock like a band stuck in the light matrix of ''Tron'' (or at least one with a serious Kraftwerk fetish). With Zombi and Psychic Paramount. At 8 p.m., Studio B, 259 Banker Street, between Meserole Avenue and Calyer Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 389-1880, clubstudiob.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* YO LA TENGO (Sunday) The model of indie-rock perseverance, Yo La Tengo is led by its songwriters, the husband-and-wife team of Ira Kaplan on guitar and Georgia Hubley on drums. They prize succinct, tuneful songs about the modest pains and pleasures of daily life and love; they also love excursions into feedback and fuzz-tone. With the Brooklyn psych-rock masters Oneida. At 7:30 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; $25. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>REZ ABBASI'S BAZAAR (Tonight) On his most recent album, ''Bazaar'' (Zoho), the guitarist Rez Abbasi infuses Southeast Asian motifs with rock bombast and jazz flexibility. At midnight, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $10, with a $10 minimum. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>ANDY BISKIN (Tomorrow) Mr. Biskin is a clarinetist who often spikes his sturdy compositions with a wily sense of humor. He presents new music for a quartet with Shane Endsley on trumpet, Eivind Opsvik on bass and Take Toriyama on drums. At 8, the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ABRAHAM BURTON/ERIC McPHERSON GROUP (Tomorrow) The saxophonist Abraham Burton and the drummer Eric McPherson share a brisk command of post-bop traditions, as they prove with this quartet. At midnight, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $10, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TAYLOR HO BYNUM SEXTET (Tonight) On his new album, ''The Middle Picture'' (Firehouse 12), the cornetist Taylor Ho Bynum advances an avant-garde chamber music jostling with odd intervals and useful frictions. Most of the musicians joining him here, like the guitarist Mary Halvorson and the drummer Tomas Fujiwara, are longtime compatriots with an established rapport. At 9 and 10:30, Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE DAVIS QUINTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) ''Update'' (Criss Cross), a recent album by the trombonist Steve Davis, earns its title by gently bringing 1950s hard bop into a modern sphere. Mr. Davis undertakes a similar process with his quintet, which features the saxophonist Mike DiRubbo. At 8 and 9:45, Kitano Hotel, 66 Park Avenue, at 38th Street, (212) 885-7119, kitano.com; cover, $25, with a $15 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* JOEL FRAHM (Tuesday through Thursday) Mr. Frahm's tenor saxophone playing has rarely sounded roomier or more relaxed than it does on ''We Used To Dance'' (Anzic), an album featuring Kenny Barron on piano, Rufus Reid on bass and Victor Lewis on drums. That group begins an engagement at Sweet Rhythm next Wednesday; on the previous night, Mr. Frahm holds down his regular trio engagement at the Bar Next Door. Tuesday at 8 and 10 p.m., Bar Next Door, 129 MacDougal Street, West Village, (212) 529-5945, lalanternacaffe.com; cover, $8, with a one-drink minimum. Wednesday and Thursday at 8 and 10 p.m., Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212) 255-3626, sweetrhythmny.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* KENNY GARRETT (Tomorrow, Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Garrett is a terror on the alto saxophone, and an artisan on the soprano; he uses both instruments to explore aesthetic territory associated with John Coltrane. Tomorrow he shares a bill in Newark with the fine post-bop trumpeter Nicholas Payton, each leading a quartet. On Wednesday he begins an engagement with a band featuring the tenor saxophonist and Coltrane contemporary Pharoah Sanders, who appeared on Mr. Garrett's last album, ''Beyond the Wall.'' Tomorrow at 7:30 p.m., New Jersey Performing Arts Center, 1 Center Street, Newark, (888) 466-5722, njpac.org; $44 to $54. Wednesday and Thursday (Through May 6) at 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $40, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JERRY GRANELLI, JAMIE SAFT AND J. ANTHONY GRANELLI (Sunday) The drummer Jerry Granelli and his son J. Anthony Granelli, a bassist, have teamed up on a number of worthy projects, including ''The Sonic Temple'' (Songlines), an atmospheric live album. They collaborate here with Mr. Saft, a texture-minded keyboardist. At 8:30 p.m., Center for Improvisational Music, 295 Douglass Street, between Third and Fourth Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (212) 631-5882, schoolforimprov.org; cover, $12; $8 for students. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ROY HARGROVE BIG BAND (Thursday) The trumpeter Roy Hargrove has been a paragon of small-group hard bop since the early 1990s. But he has also led a powerful big band, on and off, for roughly the same span of time. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $25; $10 for members. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>THE HEATH BROTHERS (Wednesday and Thursday) Two years after the loss of their brother Percy, a bassist and cellist, the saxophonist Jimmy Heath and the drummer Albert (Tootie) Heath soldier on. The pianist Jeb Patton and the bassist David Wong round out the band. (Through May 5.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $40, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>FREDDIE HUBBARD AND FRIENDS (Tonight through Sunday night) The sleek and fiery hard-bop of Mr. Hubbard's trumpet-playing prime provides source material for this all-star affair, which variously includes longtime peers (like the trombonist Slide Hampton) and worthy inheritors (like the bassist Christian McBride). At 8:30 and 10:30, with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow night, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $40 ($35 tonight), with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SUSIE IBARRA AND ROBERTO RODRIGUEZ (Wednesday) Ms. Ibarra is a drummer with a passion for texture and abstraction, and a composer committed to the idea of cultural exchange. ''Electric Kulintang,'' her percussive collaboration with Mr. Rodriguez, adds a contemporary sheen to the chiming kulintang music of the Philippines. At 9:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 539-8778, joespub.com; cover, $15, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MICHAEL MUSILLAMI TRIO +1 (Wednesday) As he demonstrates on his recent album, ''Fragile Forms,'' the guitarist Michael Mussillami favors a bright and slippery variety of post-bop. So his trio should provide a hospitable environment for the sharply expressive violinist Mark Feldman. At 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE NELSON (Tonight and tomorrow night) Mr. Nelson, a vibraphonist best known of late for his role in the Dave Holland Quintet, brings thoughtful poise to this top-flight ensemble with another powerful bassist, Robert Hurst III. At 8, 10 and 11:30, Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662, smokejazz.com; cover, $28. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JEFF NEWELL'S NEW-TRAD OCTET (Tonight) This aptly named band, led by the saxophonist Jeff Newell, celebrates the release of its first album, ''Brownstone,'' with a respectfully revisionist set of early jazz, gospel and parade music. At 8, Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; cover, $10 suggested donation. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JEREMY PELT QUARTET (Tuesday through Thursday) Jeremy Pelt, a trumpeter with a big tone and bracing technique, leads a locomotive band with Danny Grissett on piano, Derek Nievergelt on bass and Willie Jones III on drums. (Through May 6.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LUIS PERDOMO TRIO (Tomorrow) On ''Awareness'' (RKM), his most recent album, the pianist Luis Perdomo plays with exploratory urgency, and his compositions take unforced yet unexpected turns. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* PIANO PARTY: 80 AND ONWARD (Tomorrow) The pianist Dick Hyman, an emeritus presence at the 92nd Street Y, celebrates his new octogenarian status there with help from friends like the trumpeter Joe Wilder, the pianists Bill Charlap and Derek Smith, the guitarist Bucky Pizzarelli and the clarinetist Evan Christopher. At 8 p.m., 92 Street Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue, (212) 415-5500, 92y.org; $45. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>KURT ROSENWINKEL (Sunday) Mr. Rosenwinkel is a guitarist with a fluid technique and a resonant, warm-blooded tone. Making an infrequent appearance at the club where he honed his craft roughly a dozen years ago, he leads an intuitive trio. At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., Smalls, 183 West 10th Street, West Village, (212) 252-5091; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PONCHO SANCHEZ (Tonight through Sunday night) Mr. Sanchez, a high-spirited conga player, has been a leading figure in Latin jazz for over 20 years, thanks to this working band. At 8 and 10:30, Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $35 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVE SCOTT (Wednesday) Mr. Scott, a trumpeter, presents a version of the hard-bop quintet heard on his new album, ''Naiveté'': Rich Perry on tenor saxophone, Jacob Sacks on piano, John Hebert on bass and Take Toriyama on drums. At 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* KENDRICK SCOTT ORACLE (Tuesday) Kendrick Scott is a drummer conversant in an ultramodern sense of propulsion, and as he proves on a new album called ''The Source,'' he's a thoughtful composer as well. His band, Oracle, includes versatile peers like the alto saxophonist and bass clarinetist Myron Walden, the guitarist Mike Moreno and the pianist Aaron Parks. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>EMILIO SOLLA AND NY TANGO (Tonight and tomorrow night) The pianist Emilio Solla fashions a modern jazz translation of the popular music of his native Argentina, with help from the saxophonists Donny McCaslin and Chris Cheek, the accordionist Victor Prieto, the bassist Pablo Aslan and the drummer Jeff Ballard. At 8:30 and 10:30, Smalls, 183 West 10th Street, West Village, (212) 675-7369, fatcatjazz.com; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>E. J. STRICKLAND QUINTET (Tonight) Crisp and assertive post-bop from the drummer E. J. Strickland and a capable crew: John Ellis and Miguel Zenon on saxophones, Luis Perdomo on piano and Massimo Biolcati on bass. At 10, 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, near Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BEN WALTZER QUINTET (Tomorrow) Ben Waltzer manages a brand of pianistic modernism that coexists peaceably with a buoyant, un-self-conscious sense of swing. In this group he features a pair of excellent saxophonists, Bill McHenry and J. D. Allen. At 9 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* CASSANDRA WILSON (Wednesday and Thursday) A jazz singer by training and temperament, Ms. Wilson takes obvious pleasure in a boundless repertory, a tendency borne out vividly on her most recent album, ''Thunderbird.'' She makes a rare nightclub appearance with some estimable longtime colleagues: the guitarist Marvin Sewell, the drummer Herlin Riley and the bassist Reginald Veal. (Through May 5.) At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $55 at tables, $35 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE WILSON'S GENERATIONS (Tonight through Sunday night) It has been nearly a decade since the release of ''Generations,'' a rewarding album by the alto saxophonist Steve Wilson featuring Mulgrew Miller on piano, Ray Drummond on bass and Ben Riley on drums. The quartet has regrouped periodically, always with sturdy results. At 7:30 and 9:30, with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow night, Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $30; $25 on Sunday. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* JAN WRoBLEWSKI QUARTET (Tuesday) Mr. Wroblewski, the tenor saxophonist and composer, has been one of the most celebrated jazz musicians in Poland for the last four decades. Now in his 70s, he has a new album, ''Supercalifragilistic,'' and a strong rhythm section, with Wojciech Niedziela on piano, Jacek Niedziela on bass and Marcin Jahr on drums. This performance, sponsored by the Polish Cultural Institute, is a rare opportunity to hear him in person. At 7 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>* 'IL BARBIERE DI SIVIGLIA' (Monday) Bartlett Sher's breezy production, introduced at the Metropolitan Opera in November, conveys the comic confusions of the story through its fluid staging and a wonderfully abstract set: a matrix of movable doors, staircases and potted orange trees, behind which the characters spy on one another. The heated sexuality in this tale of romantic intrigue also comes through strongly, thanks to Mr. Sher's subtle directing of a handsome cast, notably the captivating young mezzo-soprano Joyce DiDonato, a vocally agile and feisty Rosina. Lawrence Brownlee, in his debut role with the company, sings Almaviva, and the hardy baritone Russell Braun sings Figaro. At 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; sold out. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* 'GIULIO CESARE' (Tonight) The Metropolitan Opera's successful run of John Copley's production of Handel's ''Giulio Cesare'' closes tonight. The countertenor Lawrence Zazzo, who was a fine Tolomeo in previous performances this season, his debut season at the Met, takes over from David Daniels in the difficult title role. The Australian soprano Danielle de Niese takes over from Ruth Ann Swenson as Cleopatra. The rest of the cast is unchanged: the mezzo-soprano Alice Coote is excellent as Sesto, and so is Patricia Bardon in her role as Cornelia. Harry Bicket, a Handel specialist, conducts an elegant performance. At 7:30, Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $15 to $320. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* 'ORFEO ED EURIDICE' (Wednesday) The Met is wrapping up an innovative, colorful season with what may be an innovative, colorful production: Mark Morris, the choreographer, is making his company debut, along with Isaac Mizrahi as costume designer. Gluck's so-called ''reform'' opera, calm and tuneful and slightly static, is something of a departure for James Levine, who conducts, but not at all for the countertenor David Daniels, who is having a great year at the Met and will sing Orpheus. The four performances of this piece are dedicated to the memory of the singer Lorraine Hunt Lieberson. At 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; sold out. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>* 'IL TRITTICO' (Tomorrow and Tuesday) The Met's new ''Trittico,'' Puccini's triptych of one-act operas, is now the most elaborate production in the company's repertory. The director Jack O'Brien has created grandly old-fashioned yet insightful and effective stagings of these three very different operas: ''Il Tabarro,'' a grim love triangle aboard a barge in Paris; ''Suor Angelica,'' a tender, mystical and ultimately devastating story of a young nun's yearning to be with her dead child; and ''Gianni Schicchi,'' an irreverent comedy about the avaricious relatives of a miserly old man. Maria Guleghina as the beleaguered barge-owner's wife, Barbara Frittoli as Sister Angelica, and Alessandro Corbelli as Schicchi are stand-outs, though the powerhouse mezzo-soprano Stephanie Blythe almost steals each show playing three supporting roles. James Levine conducts vibrant and beautifully refined performances. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., Tuesday at 7:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; sold out. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'TURANDOT' (Tomorrow and Thursday) Puccini's extravagant image of a mythical East, made more extravagant in Franco Zeffirelli's grandiose production, offers another look at the soprano Erika Sunnegardh, who stepped in for Andrea Gruber in the title role a few weeks ago, just as she stepped in for Karita Mattila in ''Fidelio'' a year ago. Tomorrow at 8:30 p.m., Thursday at 7:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; sold out. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>* AMERICAN COMPOSERS ORCHESTRA (Tonight) The composer John Adams leads this specialist orchestra in a program of his own works, including ''My Father Knew Charles Ives,'' ''The Wound-Dresser'' and ''The Violin Concerto.'' The violinist Leila Josefowicz and the bass-baritone Eric Owens are the soloists. At 8, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $16 to $43. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>AMERICAN FESTIVAL OF MICROTONAL MUSIC (Sunday and Wednesday) For fans of microtonal music -- music in non-standard tunings -- this annual festival opens on Sunday with a performance by MicroJam, an ensemble from Boston, and Dave Taylor, the trombonist, who will perform Johnny Reinhard's ''Zelig Mood Ring'' and stay on for a jam with Mr. Reinhard and MicroJam. The second installment, on Wednesday, includes more music by Mr. Reinhard and works by Elodie Lauten, Kyle Gann and Joseph Pehrson. At 10 p.m., Bowery Poetry Club, 308 Bowery, at Bleecker Street, East Village, (212) 517-3550, afmm.org; $10. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* AUSTRALIAN CHAMBER ORCHESTRA (Sunday) This excellent orchestra and its artistic leader, the violinist Richard Tognetti, play concertos by Vivaldi and Corelli in their program at Zankel Hall, an acoustically lively space for chamber ensembles. The arresting and intelligent Dutch cellist Pieter Wispelwey is the soloist in Haydn's Concerto in C. The program ends with Tchaikovsky's beguiling ''Souvenir de Florence.'' At 7:30 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $32 and $44. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* CHAMBER MUSIC SOCIETY OF LINCOLN CENTER (Tonight and Sunday) The British composer Nicholas Maw, born in 1935, is associated with the Neo-Romantic movement in contemporary music. But it is hard to categorize his elegantly written and strikingly personal music, which is multilayered, complex and spiked with modernistic elements. The Chamber Music Society presents the premiere of Mr. Maw's Sextet for Strings on a smartly conceived program that offers works by composers who have inspired him: Haydn, Schumann, Bruckner, Strauss and Britten. Tonight at 8 and Sunday at 5 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5788, chambermusicsociety.org; $28 to $50. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>CURTIS ORCHESTRA (Wednesday) If the standards of other training orchestras that have passed through Carnegie Hall recently are any measure, the Curtis Orchestra surely won't disappoint. The orchestra, conducted by Christoph Eschenbach, the Philadelphia Orchestra's music director, will be joined by Roberto Díaz, a violist and the new president of the Curtis Institute, in Penderecki's Viola Concerto. The program also includes Bernstein's ''Symphonic Dances'' from ''West Side Story'' and Stravinsky's ''Sacre du Printemps.'' At 8 p.m., (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $15 to $100. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>'GOOD NIGHT ALICE' (Monday) Alice Tully was so identified with her most visible act of patronage that a possibly apocryphal story has a partygoer addressing her as ''Miss Hall.'' It's that hall that's now being sent off musically to slumber in a cocoon of reconstruction: it will be closed for a season, reopening in late 2008. Its lullaby is a benefit concert for Lincoln Center's redevelopment project featuring the Juilliard Orchestra, led by David Robertson, in a program that arcs from Bernstein to Bernstein, with other works by Messiaen, Wynton Marsalis and Mozart. Tom Brokaw will serve as host of the event, which PBS will broadcast nationwide on Thursday. At 7 p.m, Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $1,500 and up for gala tickets, which include cocktails and a post-concert dinner. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>SERGEI KHACHATRYAN (Monday) This talented Armenian violinist, winner of both the Sibelius competition in Helsinki and the Queen Elizabeth Competition in Brussels, makes his New York recital debut with Lusine Khachatryan, his sister, as his accompanist. The program includes Bach's Chaconne in D minor from the Violin Partita No. 2; Franck's Sonata in A; and Shostakovich's Sonata. At 7:30 p.m., Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; sold out. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>EVGENY KISSIN (Thursday) In sheer talent, Mr. Kissin may be the most gifted pianist of his generation. Here he brings his big, Romantic, if somewhat inflexible approach to music by Beethoven, Brahms, Schubert and Chopin. At 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $44 to $140. (Holland)</p>
        <p>KRONOS YOUNG ARTISTS CONCERT (Tomorrow) Four emerging quartets will perform repertory they have studied in workshops this past week with the innovative Kronos Quartet, which champions contemporary music and frequently commissions new works. The lineup features pieces either written for or arranged for Kronos, including Steve Reich's ''Triple Quartet,'' John Zorn's ''Cat o' Nine Tails'' and Alexandra du Bois's String Quartet, as well as arrangements by Osvaldo Golijov and others. At 7:30 p.m., Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $15. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* LOS ANGELES PHILHARMONIC (Tomorrow, Sunday, Wednesday and Thursday) Esa-Pekka Salonen recently announced that he would turn over the podium of the orchestra he has rejuvenated over the last several years, so it will be good to see him lead it in a week of concerts in (and near) New York. The visit begins tomorrow at the New Jersey Performing Arts Center, when Mr. Salonen leads a suite from Prokofiev's ''Romeo and Juliet''; a work of his own, ''Helix''; and Ravel's Concerto for the Left Hand, with Jean-Yves Thibaudet. That program is repeated at Avery Fisher Hall on Sunday. On Wednesday Mr. Salonen leads one of his most successful recent endeavors, ''The Tristan Project,'' a semistaged version of Wagner's ''Tristan und Isolde'' with video by Bill Viola and a cast that includes Christian Franz and Christine Brewer in the title roles. And on Thursday the soprano Renée Fleming sings music of Strauss and Korngold with the orchestra, and Mr. Salonen leads Sibelius's ''Lemminkainen'' Suite. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., New Jersey Performing Arts Center, 1 Center Street, Newark, (888) 466-5722, njpac.org; $24 to $88. Sunday at 3 p.m., Wednesday at 6 p.m. and Thursday at 8 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $35 to $69 (Sunday and Thursday), $175 to $275 (Wednesday). (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>MANNES CONTEMPORARY MUSIC FESTIVAL (Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday) Works by the Pulitzer Prize-winner Paul Moravec; an evening of percussion that includes Steve Reich's ''Drumming''; world premieres by Davide Zannoni and others; and pieces by leading figures, like Iannis Xenakis, are all part of this festival, which takes on various aspects of the contemporary. Performers include chamber and percussion ensembles and, of course, the Mannes School Orchestra. At 8 p.m., Mannes College of Music, 150 West 85th Street, Manhattan, (212) 496-8524, mannes.newschool.edu; free. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>MAURIZIO POLLINI (Sunday) A musician of high accomplishment and uncompromising dignity, Mr. Pollini makes one of his regular stops at Carnegie Hall in a recital including Chopin pieces, Book II of the Debussy Études and the Boulez Second Sonata. At 3 p.m., (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $34 to $108. (Holland)</p>
        <p>GIL SHAHAM AND FRIENDS (Wednesday) The talented Mr. Shaham seems to be onstage playing his violin every time we look up. Here he is again with six colleagues in an all-Brahms program that includes the String Sextet. At 7:30 p.m., Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; sold out. (Holland)</p>
        <p>* DAWN UPSHAW (Sunday) This radiant soprano, who has recently begun performing again after being treated for breast cancer, opens the fifth season of Free for All at Town Hall concerts with a typically versatile program. She will sing works by American composers like Ruth Crawford Seeger and Ives, as well as pieces by Ravel, Fauré, Debussy, Schumann and Wolf. She finishes with three of William Bolcom's ''Cabaret Songs.'' Her accompanist, Gilbert Kalish, will also play a Brahms intermezzo. At 5 p.m., 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 707-8787, freeforallattownhall.org; free, but tickets are required. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>VERTAVO STRING QUARTET (Tonight) This dynamic Norwegian all-female quartet has been playing to acclaim for over 20 years. Founded in Oslo, it is known for its vibrant performances and special affinity for contemporary music. On this New York stop, though, the newest work the Vertavo will play is Bartok's Third Quartet, from 1927. Still, it should be invigorating to hear Bartok's path-breaking piece along with Haydn's inventive Quartet in D (Op. 20, No. 4) and Grieg's moody Quartet in G minor, a signature work in this ensemble's repertory. At 7:30, Weill Recital Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $44. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>VOX VOCAL ENSEMBLE (Tomorrow) George Steel's superb chamber choir, supported by the Manhattan Choral Ensemble, the Graham Ashton Brass Ensemble and the organist Robert McCormick, sings a program divided between early music (works by Allegri, Palestrina, Eccard and Isaac) and music of the 19th century (including works by Brahms, Mendelssohn, Wolf and Bruckner). At 8 p.m., Church of St. Mary the Virgin, 145 West 46th Street, Manhattan, (212) 854-7799, millertheater.com; $35. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>* ABT STUDIO COMPANY (Tonight and tomorrow) In addition to spotting the dance stars of the future while they are still hungry for stage space and choreography, these programs offer new and innovative dances as well as classics. The company will perform Antony Tudor's ''Jardin aux Lilas''; the pas de deux from August Bournonville's ''Flower Festival in Genzano''; and Brian Reeder's new ''Ghost Light,'' a collaboration with the filmmaker Elliot Caplan. Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Skirball Center for the Performing Arts, New York University, 566 La Guardia Place, at Washington Square South, Greenwich Village, (212) 279-4200, skirballcenter.nyu.edu; $28. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>CHAMECKILERNER (Tuesday through Thursday) Rosane Chamecki and Andrea Lerner, both originally from Brazil, are known for their dark, exaggerated and often raw depictions of human behavior. In their new multimedia ''EXIT,'' they create a funeral rite for themselves in which colleagues offer eulogies and flashbacks as they watch from the afterlife. (Through May 5.) At 8 p.m., the Kitchen, 512 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 255-5793, Ext. 11, thekitchen.org; $10. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CHEZ BUSHWICK PRESENTS: AMBUSH (Tomorrow) This project devoted to new works by the mostly young will present ''Notes on a Van Guard,'' which includes work by Eija-Liisa Ahtila, Nathan Davis, Light in August, Joe Levasseur, Moving Theater and Matthew Rogers and Jack Ferver, with a talk on French dance tucked in for good measure. At 8 p.m., Bushwick Starr, 207 Starr Street, between Irving and Wyckoff Streets, Bushwick, Brooklyn, info@thebushwickstarr.org; $5. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>EL COLEGIO DEL CUERPO -- LA COMPANIA (Sunday) This company of young dancers from Cartagena, Colombia, will perform ''Fragments,'' a piece drawn from 10 years of repertory created by the company directors Álvaro Restrepo and Marie France Delieuvin. At 3 p.m., Queens Theater in the Park, Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, (718) 760-0064, queenstheatre.org; $28; $20 for students. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT BALLET (Tomorrow) The company celebrates its 25th anniversary with the appropriately titled ''Razzle Dazzle!,'' a gala program featuring ballet and modern, African, flamenco and tap dance by guest artists from the United States, Brazil, Europe and West Africa. At 7:30 p.m., Rich Forum, 307 Atlantic Street, Stamford, Conn., (203) 325-4466, stamfordcenterforthearts.org; $25 to $50. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>EIFMAN BALLET (Tonight through Sunday) Boris Eifman's ''Anna Karenina'' will be performed this weekend, the close of its season at City Center. Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 2 and 7 p.m., City Center, 131 West 55th Street, Manhattan, (212) 581-1212, nycitycenter.org; $35 to $100. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'FROM TAP TO TOE!' (Tomorrow) Fifteen dance troupes will perform in this four-hour marathon, among them Hilary Easton &amp; Company, RumbaTap and Troika Ranch. At 7 p.m., Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, symphonyspace.org; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>ANDRÉ GINGRAS/KORZO PRODUCTIES (Thursday) From the Netherlands, Mr. Gingras and his company will present ''CYP17,'' a mixed-media piece that aims to present ''the 'freak show' that is our future,'' as its publicity puts it. Rock on. (Through May 5.) At 8:30 p.m., Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194, danspaceproject.org; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>KENNEDY DANCERS (Tonight and tomorrow night) Based in Jersey City, this modern-dance troupe will mark its 30th anniversary with a program of dances by the company director, Diane Dragone, with one work by a different guest group each night. Tonight, Nimbus Dance Works and Synthesis Dance Project; tomorrow, Arch Dance Company. At 7:30, Baryshnikov Arts Center, 450 West 37th Street, Manhattan, (201) 659-2190; $20; $18 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>ALONZO KING'S LINES BALLET (Tuesday through Thursday) This San Francisco company dances ballet with an unusual streamlined and extra-active body line and attack. Mr. King's new ''Moroccan Project'' is set to African drumming and oud and violin music. His ''Migration,'' also new, will be danced to music by Pharoah Sanders, Miguel Frasconi and Leslie Stuck. (Through May 6.) Tuesday and Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800, joyce.org; $40. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'LA MAMA MOVES!' (Tonight through Thursday) This modern-dance version of a three-ring circus spills out into three theater spaces at La MaMa, with nine programs featuring more than 50 companies and soloists. (Through May 13.) La MaMa E.T.C., 74A East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 475-7710, lamama.org; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>LAVA (Thursday) Sarah East Johnson and her all-female company, which specializes in acrobatic modern dance spiced with double-trapeze work, will present ''Tides,'' a new piece that incorporates time-capture video of the Rockaway shoreline and ocean-wave patterns. (Through May 27.) At 7 p.m., Flea Theater, 41 White Street, between Broadway and Church Street, TriBeCa, (212) 352-3101, theatermania.com; $10 to $30. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'LET'S SPEAK TANGO!' (Tonight through Sunday, and Thursday) Well, why not? For the record, this latest celebration of that sultry dance form was choreographed by Valeria Solomonoff, one of the show's eight performers, and directed by Carlo Magaletti. (Through May 6.) Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 3 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., American Theater of Actors, 314 West 54th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444, smarttix.com; $40. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>AMY MARSHALL DANCE (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ms. Marshall's dances will address the beauty of the human body, the last days of Joan of Arc and, to music by Mike Seeger and the New Lost City Ramblers, the textile industry in Spartanburg, S.C. Clearly this is a choreographer with eclectic interests. At 8, Ailey Citigroup Theater, 405 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444, smarttix.com; $30; $20 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* MIRO DANCE THEATER (Wednesday) The company directors, Amanda Miller, who danced with the Pennsylvania Ballet and studied choreography with Siobhan Davies, and Tobin Rothlein, a video artist and designer, do better than most at combining visuals and movement to make a third, poetically expressive form. Their new dance, ''Pitch Black,'' addresses human connections and disconnections in urban life. It is set to music for sax and boombox by JacobTV, to be performed live. At 8 p.m., Whitney Museum of Art at Altria, 120 Park Avenue, at 42nd Street, (800) 944-8639; free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>THE MOVEMENT MOVEMENT &amp; FRIENDS MOVE IN (Tomorrow and Sunday) Advance information on this event is about as unclear as its title, but it all has something to do with changing rooms, streaming video and an empty 7,000-square-foot retail space. Reassuringly, the performers include Scotty the Blue Bunny. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Sunday at 7 p.m., Front and Beekman Streets, next to 207 Fulton Street, South Street Seaport, (917) 531-1171, info@themovementmovement.org; $15; $10 ''for those that are starving.'' (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* NEW YORK CITY BALLET (Tonight, tomorrow and Tuesday through Thursday) Lincoln Kirstein, who founded the company with George Balanchine, will be celebrated in three different all-Balanchine repertory programs (tonight and tomorrow afternoon and evening). Then comes Peter Martins's eagerly awaited new production of ''Romeo and Juliet'' (Tuesday through May 13), with lead roles performed by some of City Ballet's youngest up-and-comers. Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Tuesday and Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. (no Sunday performance), Thursday at 8 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nycballet.com; $30 to $86; $15 student rush tickets available day of performance. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK THEATER BALLET (Tonight and tomorrow night) The program includes William Dollar's rarely performed piece ''Le Combat,'' Agnes de Mille's ''Carousel'' ballet and dances by Donald Mahler and Sallie Wilson. Tonight and tomorrow night at 7:30, Gould Hall, 55 East 59th Street, Manhattan (212) 355-6160, nytb.org; $30; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'THE NOTHING FESTIVAL' (Tonight and tomorrow night) The choreographer Tere O'Connor asked eight other choreographers to each contribute a new piece made from scratch, with no story, music or nondance source to guide them. The festival closes this week with works by Luciana Achugar, Walter Dundervill, Jon Kinzel and Susan Rethorst. At 7:30, Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077, dtw.org; $20. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>STREB SLAM 9 (Tonight through Sunday) Elizabeth Streb and her high-flying, death-defying performers will perform repertory favorites featuring a swivel harness, two huge plywood panels and, for the audience, popcorn and cotton candy. (Through June 17.) Tonight at 7, tomorrow at 3 and 7 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., S.L.A.M., 51 North First Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (212) 352-3101, strebusa.org; $20; $10 for children. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>VANGELINE DANCE THEATER (Tonight and tomorrow night) The program includes new Butoh dance by the company director, Vangeline, and Nicole LeGette. It also features modern dance by Eva Perotta in a program called ''La Porte Étroite: (Apothéose Mystique),'' a title drawn from a novel by André Gide. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Puffin Room, 435 Broome Street, between Broadway and Crosby Street, SoHo, (212) 343-2881; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* YOUTH AMERICA GRAND PRIX 2007 GALA (Monday) This international competition, which awards scholarships for ballet study, is usually a big, joyous mess of dancing by talented young finalists and professionals. This time the companies include the Paris Opera Ballet, the Stuttgart and the Royal Ballet, as well as several leading American dance troupes. At 7 p.m., City Center, 131 West 55th Street, Manhattan, (212) 581-1212, nycitycenter.org; $45 to $150. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'KINDRED SPIRITS: ASHER B. DURAND AND THE AMERICAN LANDSCAPE,' through July 29. This show of about 60 works by one of the greats of 19th-century American landscape painting has as its centerpiece ''Kindred Spirits'' (1849), a tribute to the landscapist Thomas Cole and his friend the poet-journalist William Cullen Bryant. A founder of the Hudson River School, Durand (1796-1886) favored the realistic approach to landscape advocated by the English critic John Ruskin. Durand explored forest interiors with close attention to the ways of trees, foliage and rocks and ground cover in smaller works, while his larger and more elaborate exhibition pictures, influenced by European masters, are Arcadian visions suffused with light, color and atmospheric perspective. If the show reveals some of Durand's weaknesses -- repetitive themes and borrowings from other artists -- it also reveals his strong sense of artistic mission and his potent role in shaping the aesthetic of 19th-century America. 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, Brooklyn, (718) 638-5000, brooklynmuseum.org. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>* JAPAN SOCIETY: 'Awakenings: Zen Figure Painting in Medieval Japan,' through June 17. Japan Society has a history of producing exquisite shows of Buddhist art. And this one, with four dozen paintings of Buddhists gods and saints hung in shrinelike alcoves, is transporting. It covers a broad swath of geography, bringing together 13th- to 16th-century hanging scrolls, not only from Japan but also from China, where Zen Buddhism, called Chan in Chinese, originated. 333 East 47th Street, (212) 832-1155, japansociety.org. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>The Jewish Museum: Dateline: Israel: 'New Photography and Video Art,' through Aug. 5. Roughly every decade, the Jewish Museum offers a survey of contemporary art from and about Israel. This year non-Israeli artists from Europe and the United States -- and a single artist from Palestine -- have been added to the mix. There's some very good work here, though, on the whole, the show grapples with crucial political issues in an indirect way. 1109 Fifth Avenue, at 92nd Street, (212) 423-3200, jewishmuseum.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* the Metropolitan Museum of Art: 'Journeys: Mapping the Earth and Mind in Chinese Art,' through Aug. 26. Every six months or so, the Met rotates all the work in its Chinese painting galleries to preserve the delicate silks and papers, and each time, the curator in charge, Maxwell K. Hearn, produces a new and illuminating thematic exhibition, as is the case with ''Journeys.'' Outward-bound and inward-bound are the directions taken by Chinese landscape painting, and it carries us on some fascinating voyages in a show that mixes classical and contemporary art. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* the met: 'Venice and the Islamic World, 828-1797,' through July 8. At its peak in the Renaissance, Venice, the Most Serene, was a giant, clamorous Costco-on-the-Rialto. All the necessities, and most of the luxuries, of life flowed into and through it, with many items arriving from Islamic Africa and the Near East. With classic Met largesse, this exhibition suggests the spectacle of two different cultures meeting in one fantastic city, in which commerce and love of beauty, those great levelers, unite them in a fruitful bond. (See above.) (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* the Museum of Modern Art: JEFF WALL, through May 14. This majestic show makes a great case for Mr. Wall as the most complete, if traditional, of the untraditional artists who emerged from the turmoil of Conceptual Art. His often immense color transparencies mounted on light boxes are enthralling visual vehicles, intent on giving pleasure while making a point or two about society, art, history, visual perception, the human animal or all of the above. An imposing blend of painting, street photography and movies, they blur reality and artifice, narrative and form, detail and the big statement. You can't stop looking at them. (212) 708-9400, moma.org. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>Studio Museum in Harlem: 'Philosophy of Time Travel,' through July 1. Many art historians consider Constantin Brancusi's ''Endless Column'' (1938), a 96-foot-tall cast-iron work designed to memorialize Romanian soldiers killed in World War I, the quintessential example of Modernist sculpture. It still stands in Tirgu Jiu, Romania. But a rendition of it is also part of this installation. The work of five artists -- Edgar Arceneaux, Vincent Galen Johnson, Olga Koumoundouros, Rodney McMillian and Matthew Sloly -- it reimagines Brancusi's sculpture. The concept began with a wish to create an installation that would symbolize the clash of African and Western cultures. The result is seven rhomboids, about the same size as the original, which appear to have torn through the gallery's ceiling, splintering the surrounding drywall and smashing into the floor. The collective succeeds in ridding ''Endless Column'' of its Modernist sanctity by turning it into something more akin to a Hollywood blockbuster than a memorial sculpture. 144 West 125th Street, (212) 864-4500. (Bridget L. Goodbody)</p>
        <p>Whitney Museum of American Art: 'Taryn Simon,' through June 24. Ms. Simon couches the show in the intellectual, power-to-the-people oratory of leftist politics, yet she clearly delights in exposing, in a quasi-tabloid fashion, America's underbelly. Though she has also worked in war-torn areas, Ms. Simon is best known for ''The Innocents,'' a series of portraits of men and women who were wrongly convicted but later cleared by DNA test results. Ms. Simon can work as long as a year to gain permission to photograph high-security zones like the government-regulated quarantine sites, nuclear waste storage facilities, prison death rows and C.I.A. offices on view in the show. There are also pictures with lighter themes: the sandpit where the Grucci family tests fireworks, ski slopes being dynamited for avalanche control and the second Death Star, from ''Return of the Jedi,'' at George Lucas's Skywalker Ranch. Ms. Simon is at her artistic best when her delight in the strangeness of American culture shines. (212) 570-3676, whitney.org. (Goodbody)</p>
        <p>* Whitney Museum of American Art: 'Lorna Simpson,' through May 6. This tight, refined and impassioned survey covers more than 20 years of Lorna Simpson's career, from her photo-and-text meditations on race and sexism in the 1980s, to her more recent short films, which unite American history and personal history in forceful and lyrical ways. It would be easy to put some of this work on a shelf as ''identity art,'' but with an African-American woman holding one of the highest offices in the United States government, an African-American man running for president, and the nation embroiled in what some people view as an ethnic war, this art is entirely of the moment. (See above.) (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>DELPHINE COURTILLOT From O. Winston Link to Anna Gaskell and ''The Blair Witch Project,'' there are far too many borrowed bits in these large watercolors based on staged photographs of people in dark, desolate landscapes. But the larger question is why the images wouldn't do just as well in their original photographic form. Tilton Gallery, 8 East 76th Street, (212) 731-2221, through May 5. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>* WALTER DE MARIA Counting and space -- important to both Minimal and Conceptual Art -- come together with unusual clarity, if a bit too much in the way of gleaming metal, in two large installations by the creator of ''The Lightning Field'' earthwork. Both pieces consist of several dozen shiny, meter-long stainless-steel rods presented in spaces that couldn't be much more pristine. Experience the spatial levitation and note the number of sides on the rods; in both cases, they increase row by row. Gagosian Gallery, 522 West 21st Street, (212) 741-1717, and 555 West 24th Street, (212) 741-1111, gagosian.com, through May 5. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Other</p>
        <p>* SOL LEWITT: DRAWING SERIES</p>
        <p>If the greatness of Sol LeWitt, the Minimal-Conceptual artist who died this month (April 7) at 78, has so far escaped you, this exhilarating show of 14 of his mind-teasing, eye-filling wall drawings from the late 1960s and early '70s may do the trick. Selected and arranged by the artist, they proceed in carefully sequenced contrasts and echoes that are both insightful and idiosyncratic. Since their generating instructions are part of their titles, they reduce the creative process to a short, highly visible straight line. But their crisp geometries, accumulating marks and radiating patterns force us to mind the gap between artistic thought and artistic action, to experience the inability of language to account fully for visual outcome. Dia:Beacon, 3 Beekman Street, Beacon, N.Y., (845) 440-0100, through Sept. 10. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>LEE BONTECOU: VACUUM-FORMED SCULPTURES AND RELATED DRAWINGS This artist has never topped her glowering black-and-white canvas reliefs of the 1960s, but these menacing fish and vigilant, thick-stalked flowers from the 1970s are second-best. The flowers, especially, amass some of the armed-and-dangerous sinisterness of the canvas reliefs behind their seemingly beatific auras. Knoedler &amp; Company, 19 East 70th Street, (212) 794-0550; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* 'C.R.E.E.P.' For its second show, this small, new bare-bones Lower East Side storefront gallery is showing work by two collaborative artists called C.R.E.E.P., who multitask as performance artists, magazine publishers, performing artists and clothing designers. One of their two pieces is big, polished and brashly self-announcing. The other is minute, hard to find and terrific. As to 127 itself, all I can say is: watch that space. 127, 127 Henry Street, near Allen Street, (646) 416-1517; closes on Sunday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>'Gifts of the Forest: Native Traditions in Wood and Bark' Drawn from the collections of the Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center in southeastern Connecticut, this show celebrates the trees of the rich forests that once covered the Northeast, yielding essential materials to the Pequot and other Eastern Woodland cultures. The objects run from ancient woodworking tools to contemporary objects that carry on tribal traditions. Many things here were made in the 19th and 20th centuries: handsome woven baskets, decorated cradle boards for carrying babies, and an elegant birch-bark hamper whose sides bear a stylized tree motif. UBS Art Gallery, 1285 Avenue of the Americas, between 51st and 52nd Streets, (212) 713-2885, ubs.com; closes today. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* Kim Gordon and Jutta Koether: 'Dead already' Two artist-musicians collaborate on a show that's partly objects, partly performance and partly in the air. The objects are paintings displayed in flip-through racks. (The ones with glitter are Ms. Gordon's; the ones done in black liquid glass, Ms. Koether's). The center of the gallery is fenced off for action: Ei Arakawa and Eleanor Erdman will do a Martha Graham piece this Sunday, bound to be memorable. Reena Spaulings Fine Art, 165 East Broadway, at Rutgers Street, Lower East Side, (212) 477-5006; closes on Sunday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL CENTER OF PHOTOGRAPHY: 'HENRI CARTIER-BRESSON'S SCRAPBOOK: PHOTOGRAPHS, 1932-46,' This show has more than 300 of the prints the photographer glued into an album and toted to New York for curators at the Museum of Modern Art to cull. Captured by the Nazis, he had been presumed dead when the Modern planned his retrospective. Then he turned up alive -- the ''posthumous'' exhibition opened, with him in attendance, in 1947. The current exhibition surveys the revolutionary work Carier-Bresson shot in Spain, Italy, Mexico, Britain and France. Here are the familiar and, more interestingly, some less familiar, shots of crowds in Hyde Park in London at George VI's coronation, of picnickers on the banks of the Marne in France and whores in Valencia, Spain. His taste for uncanny detail linked him to Surrealism and Surrealist wit, but unlike many Surrealists, he remained committed to human values. Boys mug at his camera. Prostitutes swan. Their gazes equalize them with us. 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000, icp.org; closes on Sunday. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL CENTER OF PHOTOGRAPHY: 'MARTIN MUNKACSI: THINK WHILE YOU SHOOT!' Munkacsi, who inspired Cartier-Bresson, was, by contrast, self-taught, a creature of his own devising. This is the most complete retrospective, with a thick catalog (not too well researched) and dozens of vintage prints from the 1920s through the early '60s. He favored scenes of daily life, absorbing avant-garde ideas about odd angles and abstract compositions. In 1928 he moved to Berlin, where the opportunities were better, and traveled the world on assignment to Brazil, Algeria and Egypt. Munkacsi was a stylist, and he made catchy images the only way he knew how, in a modernist mode, which, being an opportunistic form, could serve any master. He became a celebrity in America. He photographed Fred Astaire dancing and Joan Crawford poolside. In the breezy layouts of Harper's Bazaar, the work looked brilliant. (See above.) Closes on Sunday. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* 'THOMAS STRUTH: Making Time' Through the 1990s, the German photographer Thomas Struth became an art-world celebrity for his outsize, absorbing portraits of crowds interacting with artwork in the world's great museums. As a follow-up, he is presenting the American premiere of two new series of pictures of audiences beholding single masterpieces in the Museo Nacional del Prado in Madrid, and the State Hermitage Museum in St. Petersburg, Russia. The show, which cannily allows us to look safely at others looking at art, is one of the most visually sumptuous and thought-probing in the city. Marian Goodman Gallery, 24 West 57th Street, (212) 977-7160, mariangoodman.com; closes tomorrow. (Benjamin Genocchio)</p>
        <p>JAMES TURRELL: 'LIGHT LEADINGS' From an artist known for meditative light installations, a show of sped-up versions made with computerized neon and holographic works reminiscent of Malevich abstractions. They amount to gorgeous, high-priced, high-tech equivalents of lava lamps, in which color comes either in diaphanous clouds or with hard edges. PaceWildenstein Gallery, 534 West 25th Street, Chelsea, (212) 929-7000, pacewildenstein.com; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY ON THE VINE' In previews; opens on Wednesday. Zak Berkman's romantic fable follows a man falling in love with a budding star of right-wing radio (2:10). Clurman Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'CORAM BOY' In previews; opens on Wednesday. An adaptation of Jamila Gavin's novel about two orphans is the latest National Theater hit to move from London to Broadway (2:30). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'CYMBELINE' Opens on Wednesday. Declan Donnellan stages this Cheek by Jowl production of one of Shakespeare's last plays (2:40). Harvey Theater, Brooklyn Academy of Music, 651 Fulton Street, Fort Greene, (718) 636-4100.</p>
        <p>'DIXIE'S TUPPERWARE PARTY' In previews; opens on May 10. Dixie Wingate has left her Alabama trailer park to sell Tupperware in New York in this irreverent comedy (1:15). Ars Nova, 511 West 54th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444.</p>
        <p>'DEUCE' In previews; opens on May 6. The grandes dames Angela Lansbury and Marian Seldes play retired tennis players in this new Terrence McNally comedy. Michael Blakemore directs (1:45). Music Box Theater, 239 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'LEGALLY BLONDE' In previews; opens on Sunday. Laura Bell Bundy plays the smiling, ditsy sorority girl who takes Harvard Law by storm in this musical adaptation. Jerry Mitchell directs (2:20). Palace Theater, 1564 Broadway, at 47th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'LOVEMUSIK' In previews; opens on Thursday. The Tony winners Michael Cerveris and Donna Murphy star in a musical about the relationship between Kurt Weill and Lotte Lenya (with songs by Weill). Harold Prince directs (2:40). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'110 IN THE SHADE' In previews; opens on May 9. Audra McDonald stars in the Roundabout's revival of the musical version of N. Richard Nash's ''Rainmaker.'' Studio 54, 254 West 54th Street, (212) 719-1300.</p>
        <p>'PASSING STRANGE' Previews start on Tuesday. Opens on May 14. The Joe's Pub veteran and pop singer Stew tries his hand at musical theater, with a rock-theme score and a story about the journey of a bohemian (2:30). Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555.</p>
        <p>'RADIO GOLF' In previews; opens on May 8. The last play in August Wilson's cycle is set in 1997 and centers on the vital question of what will be done with the fabled Aunt Esther's house. Tonya Pinkins (''Caroline, or Change'') stars (2:30). Cort Theater, 138 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'A CHORUS LINE' If you want to know why this show was such a big deal when it opened 31 years ago, you need only experience the thrilling first five minutes of this revival. Otherwise, this archivally exact production, directed by Bob Avian, feels like a vintage car that has been taken out of the garage, polished up and sent on the road once again (2:00). Schoenfeld Theater, 236 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE COAST OF UTOPIA' Lincoln Center Theater's brave, gorgeous, sprawling and ultimately exhilarating production of Tom Stoppard's trilogy about intellectuals errant in 19th-century Russia. A testament to the seductive powers of narrative theater, directed with hot and cool canniness by Jack O'Brien and featuring a starry cast (Brian F. O'Byrne, Jennifer Ehle, Martha Plimpton, Josh Hamilton and Ethan Hawke, among others) in a tasty assortment of roles. Vivian Beaumont Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'COMPANY' Fire, beckoning and dangerous, flickers beneath the frost of John Doyle's elegant, unexpectedly stirring revival of Stephen Sondheim and George Furth's era-defining musical from 1970, starring a compellingly understated Raúl Esparza. Like Mr. Doyle's ''Sweeney Todd,'' this production finds new clarity of feeling in Sondheim by melding the roles of performers and musicians (2:20). Barrymore Theater, 243 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CURTAINS' This musical comedy about a musical-comedy murder -- featuring songs by John Kander and Fred Ebb and a book by Rupert Holmes -- lies on the stage like a promisingly gaudy string of firecrackers, waiting in vain for a match. The good news is that David Hyde Pierce, playing a diffident Boston detective, steps into full-fledged Broadway stardom. Scott Ellis directs a talent-packed cast that includes Debra Monk and Karen Ziemba. (2:30). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'FROST/NIXON' Frank Langella turns in a truly titanic performance as Richard M. Nixon in Peter Morgan's briskly entertaining, if all-too-tidy, play about the former president's annihilating television interviews with the British talk show host David Frost (the excellent Michael Sheen). Michael Grandage directs with the momentum of a ticking-bomb thriller and the zing of a boulevard comedy (1:40). Jacobs Theater, 242 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'GREY GARDENS' Christine Ebersole is absolutely glorious as the middle-aged, time-warped debutante called Little Edie Beale in this uneven musical adaptation of the notorious 1975 documentary of the same title. She and the wonderful Mary Louise Wilson (as her bedridden mother), in the performances of their careers, make ''Grey Gardens'' an experience no passionate theatergoer should miss (2:40). Walter Kerr Theater, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'INHERIT THE WIND' Doug Hughes's wooden revival of this worthy war horse, based on the Scopes ''monkey'' trial of 1925, never musters much more velocity than that of a drugstore fan. Be grateful that the cast includes Christopher Plummer, in savory form as a Will Rogers of jurisprudence. An oddly subdued Brian Dennehy plays his pompous adversary (2:00). Lyceum Theater, 149 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'JOURNEY'S END' A splendid revival of R. C. Sherriff's 1928 drama of life in the trenches during World War I. Acutely staged (by David Grindley) and acted by a fine ensemble led by Hugh Dancy and Boyd Gaines, this production offers an exemplary presentation of that theatrical rarity, an uncompromising, clear-eyed play about war and the experience of day-to-day combat. An essential ticket (2:40). Belasco Theater, 111 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MARY POPPINS' This handsome, homily-packed, mechanically ingenious and rather tedious musical, adapted from the P. L. Travers stories and the 1964 film, is ultimately less concerned with inexplicable magic than with practical psychology. Ashley Brown, who sings prettily as the family-mending nanny, looks like Joan Crawford trying to be nice and sounds like Dr. Phil. Directed by Richard Eyre and Matthew Bourne (2:30). New Amsterdam Theater, 214 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LES MISÉRABLES' This premature revival, a slightly scaled-down version of the well-groomed behemoth that closed only three years ago, appears to be functioning in a state of mild sedation. Appealingly sung and freshly orchestrated, this fast-moving adaptation of Victor Hugo's novel isn't sloppy or blurry. But its pulse rate stays well below normal (2:55). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'A MOON FOR THE MISBEGOTTEN' Kevin Spacey gives a bizarre, beat-the-clock performance, as lively as a frog on a hot plate, as James Tyrone in this off-kilter revival of Eugene O'Neill's last play. Mercifully, he does not block the view of Eve Best, who maps the contradictory levels of Tyrone's strapping love interest with clarity and intelligence (2:50). Brooks Atkinson Theater, 256 West 47th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PIRATE QUEEN' How to river-dance your way to the bottom of the ocean, courtesy of the songwriters of ''Les Misérables'' (2:30). Hilton Theater, 213 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' Duncan Sheik and Steven Sater's bold adaptation of the Frank Wedekind play is the freshest and most exciting new musical Broadway has seen in some time. Set in 19th-century Germany but with a ravishing rock score, it exposes the splintered emotional lives of adolescents just discovering the joys and sorrows of sex. Performed with brio by a great cast, with supple direction by Michael Mayer and inventive choreography by Bill T. Jones (2:00). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'TALK RADIO' The most lacerating portrait of a human meltdown this side of a Francis Bacon painting. Playing an abrasive radio talk show host with a God complex, the astounding Liev Schreiber seems to fill the air as inescapably as weather in Robert Falls's gut-grabbing revival of Eric Bogosian's 1987 play (1:40). Longacre Theater, 220 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE YEAR OF MAGICAL THINKING' Joan Didion's arresting but ultimately frustrating adaptation of her best-selling memoir about being blindsided by grief, starring Vanessa Redgrave. The tension between style and emotional content that made the book such a stunner does not translate to the stage. The substance here is in the silences, when the focus shifts from words to Ms. Redgrave's wry, wounded face (1:40). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE ACCOMPLICES' Bernard Weinraub, a former reporter for The New York Times, has chosen a worthy subject for his first play: In 1940, the young Zionist Peter Bergson was determined to persuade the United States government to open its arms to Jewish refugees fleeing the Nazis. Unfortunately, this production takes a hagiographic approach to its protagonist, emphasizing his heroism at the expense of more complex characterization. (2:00). Acorn Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200. (David Ng)</p>
        <p>'ALL THE WRONG REASONS: A TRUE STORY OF NEO-NAZIS, DRUG SMUGGLING AND UNDYING LOVE' John Fugelsang's amiable solo show mixes memoir and stand-up comedy in a tale of family, faith and Roman Catholic guilt. Slight but engaging (1:30). New York Theater Workshop, 79 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 460-5475. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'APOSTASY' Gino Dilorio's fearless play about a dying white Jewish woman who falls under the spell of a black televangelist is pretty good; the acting that delivers it is terrific, especially Susan Greenhill as the woman, and Susan Louise O'Connor as her daughter (2:00). Urban Stages, 259 West 30th Street, (212) 868-4444. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'BE' A high-energy, low-content Israeli show that blends music, dance and sex appeal in the latest attempt to tap into the ''Stomp'' market (1:30). Union Square Theater, 100 East 17th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 307-4100. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'THE BIG VOICE: GOD OR MERMAN?' Think of two gifted and smart gay men with years of life together deploying their considerable talents from the two pianos you happen to have in your living room. The result is a hilarious and very touching memoir of two decades of love and the funky glories of show business life (2:00). Actors Temple Theater, 339 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Honor Moore)</p>
        <p>'BILL W. AND DR. BOB' This insightful new play about the founders of Alcoholics Anonymous subtly makes the claim that the recovery movement was born as a series of accidents. Patrick Husted is excellent as Bob Smith, Bill Wilson's partner in combating addictions (2:15). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Ginia Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'BIOGRAPHY' A revival of S. N. Behrman's hoary 1932 comedy about a society portraitist and the men who keep trying to reign her in feels slight as a needlepoint pillow. As the play's supposedly beguiling heroine, Marion Froude, Carolyn McCormick never beguiles (2:15). The Pearl Theater, 80 St. Mark's Place, at First Avenue, East Village, (212) 598-9802. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>* 'BLACKBIRD'  David Harrower's stunning new drama looks back at a sexual relationship -- between a 40-year-old man and a 12-year-old girl -- that transforms, cripples and paralyzes. Jeff Daniels and Alison Pill, both extraordinary, peel their characters down to their barest souls. Joe Mantello is the masterly director (1:30). Manhattan Theater Club at City Center Stage I, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE FANTASTICKS' A revival -- well, more like a resuscitation -- of the Little Musical That Wouldn't Die. This sweet-as-ever production of Tom Jones and Harvey Schmidt's commedia-dell'arte-style confection is most notable for Mr. Jones's touching performance (under the pseudonym Thomas Bruce) as the Old Actor, a role he created when the show opened in 1960. Mr. Jones also directs (2:05). Snapple Theater Center, 210 West 50th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'IN THE HEIGHTS' Lin-Manuel Miranda's joyous songs paint a vibrant portrait of daily life in Washington Heights in this flawed but enjoyable show. Essentially a valentine to the barrio -- conflict of a violent or desperate kind is banished from the picture -- the musical contains a host of funny performances and brings the zesty sound of Latin pop to the stage. (2:10). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE J.A.P. SHOW: JEWISH AMERICAN PRINCESSES of comedy' Laughs along with longueurs (1:30). Actors Temple Theater, 339 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'A JEW GROWS IN BROOKLYN' You don't have to be Jewish or Brooklynish to empathize with Jake Ehrenreich, but in terms of fully appreciating his essentially one-man show, it probably helps. Especially the Catskills jokes (2:05). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 560-8912. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>* 'SPALDING GRAY: STORIES LEFT TO TELL' A disarming collage of selections from the monologues and journals of Mr. Gray, the ultimate stand-up solipsist, who died in 2004. Directed by Lucy Sexton, and read by five performers, none of whom resemble Mr. Gray, with an affection that shrewdly stops short of hero worship (1:30). Minetta Lane Theater, 18 Minetta Lane, Greenwich Village, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE VIEW FROM K STREET STEAK' An attempt at political satire that misses with just about every shot, this play ends up being simply confusing and boring, neither funny nor timely (1:50). Altered Stages, 212 West 29th Street, Chelsea, (212) 352-3101. (Wilborn Hampton)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'DENIAL' An engrossing and timely legal drama about a Holocaust denier being defended by a Jewish lawyer, this play examines the moral and ethical dilemma inherent in the First Amendment and asks how much sufferance can a free society give its crackpots and maintain its individual liberties (2:30). Metropolitan Playhouse, 220 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 995-5302. (Hampton)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden Theater, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' Singing CliffsNotes for Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' Often more entertaining than the real thing (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS'  The biomusical that walks like a man (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT'  A singing scrapbook for Monty Python fans (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' ''A Chorus Line'' with pimples (1:45). Circle in the Square, 254 West 50th Street, Manhattan, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'DEFENDER OF THE FAITH' This grim tale by Stuart Carolan of low-level I.R.A. agitators trying to identify the informer in their midst features some visceral performances and a set by Charles Corcoran that makes excellent use of the Irish Rep's small stage. If only the cause itself didn't feel so small in these days of global terrorism (1:30). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737; closes on Sunday. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>* 'DYING CITY' Christopher Shinn's crafty and unsettling play about grief and violence, set in the shadow of the Iraq war. Directed by James Macdonald and fiercely acted by Pablo Schreiber and Rebecca Brooksher, this quiet, transfixing production turns passive aggression into a theatrical dynamic (1:30). Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-7600; closes on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'EXITS AND ENTRANCES'  Athol Fugard casts a tender glance back at an actor whose dedication to theater helped spark his own in this warm if insubstantial stage memoir. Morlan Higgins capably excavates the emotional core of a role that might have seemed generic, playing an aging gay actor reckoning with the end of an up-and-down career. William Dennis Hurley plays the Fugard stand-in (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200; closes on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'JACK GOES BOATING' Bob Glaudini's gentle comedy about pothead losers in love is a reminder of how engrossing uneventful lives can be in the hands of the right actors. Peter DuBois directs the easygoing ensemble, brilliantly led by Philip Seymour Hoffman (2:00). Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555; closes on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LA MAGNANI' Theresa Gambacorta reincarnates the Italian film star Anna Magnani in this one-woman show, which reveals her to be more irritating than interesting: loud and self-absorbed (1:10). Arclight Theater, 152 West 71st Street, (212) 279-4200; closes on Sunday. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'MARIE ANTOINETTE: THE COLOR OF FLESH' Joel Gross's intriguing play features impeccable performances by Amanda Jones, Samantha Ives and Jonathan Kells Phillips as the three corners of a triangle of love and friendship caught up in the French Revolution. It's no ordinary triangle: Ms. Jones plays Marie Antoinette, and Ms. Ives the real portraitist who often painted her (1:30). The 45th Street Theater, 354 West 45th Street, Clinton, (212) 254-9533; closes on Sunday. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'MUD BLOSSOM' This brooding drama about three generations of suffering Southern women wallows in its own despair (1:50) Walkerspace, 46 Walker Street, near Church Street, SoHo, (212) 352-3101; closes tomorrow. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>'A DIOS MOMO' (No rating, 108 minutes, in Spanish) Directed by Leonardo Ricagni, this crude, sugary melodrama follows the uplifting misadventures of Obdulio (Mathias Acuña), an 11-year-old newspaper boy. Obdulio is illiterate and refuses to go to school, but he's obsessed with the Murgas, a troupe of traveling singers. He learns to read when his newspaper's watchman, Barrilete (Jorge Esmoris), dispatches him to the singers' practice room to scrawl Barrilete's lyrics on a chalkboard. This fairy-tale touch might work if the movie weren't so pleased with its own pie-eyed naïveté, and so eager to imitate the stalest aspects of films by the director's chief inspiration, Federico Fellini. (Matt Zoller Seitz)</p>
        <p>* 'ALICE NEEL' (No rating, 82 minutes) The fascinating documentary ''Alice Neel'' -- a biography of this influential, emotionally troubled portrait artist, by her grandson Andrew Neel -- juxtaposes relaxed interview footage and archival clips with more ragged, personal footage that reveals a filmmaker struggling to define an indefinable woman. The result is a film that seems more unfinished -- and thus more present tense -- than other examples of its type, and makes its subject, who died in 1984, seem very much alive. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>'AQUA TEEN HUNGER FORCE COLON MOVIE FILM FOR THEATERS' (R, 87 minutes) Not as funny as the title or the Cartoon Network series on which it's based. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>'Blades of Glory' (PG-13, 93 minutes) In this fast, light, frequently funny comedy about a male figure-skating team, Will Ferrell and Jon Heder stake an early claim to being the comedy couple of the year. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>'DISTURBIA' (PG-13, 104 minutes) A pleasant, scary, well-directed variation on the killer-next-door theme, with the engaging Shia LeBeouf as Kale, a young man who turns house arrest into an occasion for voyeurism and crime-fighting. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'ELECTION' (No rating, 100 minutes, in Cantonese) This intricate gangster entertainment, the first episode in a two-part sequence from the prolific Hong Kong action maestro Johnnie To, offer some acute lessons in the pitfalls of democracy. Also a feast of fighting, humor and fine acting, in particular from Simon Yaw, who plays a soft-spoken, businesslike candidate for chairman of Hong Kong's oldest criminal organization. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'FRACTURE' (R, 111 minutes) A glib entertainment that offers up the spectacle of that crafty scene-stealer Anthony Hopkins mixing it up with that equally cunning screen-nibbler Ryan Gosling. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE GLAMOROUS LIFE OF SACHIKO HANAI' (No rating, 90 minutes, in Japanese) A wayward bullet turns a hooker into a brainiac in this Japanese clutter of soft-core political parody, hard-core narrative nonsense, breezy sexism and penny-ante surrealism. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'GRINDHOUSE' (R, 180 minutes) A double feature, complete with fake previews for schlocky exploitation pictures, that pays nostalgic tribute to disreputable traditions of moviemaking and moviegoing. Robert Rodriguez contributes ''Planet Terror,'' a purposely incoherent zombie gross-out flick that flaunts is own badness the way Rose McGowan (as a go-go dancer named Cherry Darling) shows off her weaponized prosthetic leg. For his part, Quentin Tarantino, more of a connoisseur than his collaborator (and a much better filmmaker), turns out a brutal, talky and satisfying car-chase revenge movie in ''Death Proof,'' starring Kurt Russell. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'THE HOAX' (R, 115 minutes) A first-rate performance by Richard Gere drives this true story of Clifford Irving (Mr. Gere), who claimed to be the authorized biographer of Howard Hughes. Shadowed by the paranoia of its period (the early '70s), this movie, crisply directed by Lasse Hallstrom from an excellent script by William Weaver, is less a morality play than an entertaining portrait of a literary gambler. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'HOT FUZZ' (R, 121 minutes) A British parody of Hollywood-style action flicks from the wits behind ''Shaun of the Dead.'' Think of it as ''The Full Monty'' blown to smithereens. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'IN THE LAND OF WOMEN' (PG-13, 98 minutes) This meek, mopey comedy is the film equivalent of a sensitive emo band with one foot in alternative rock and the other in the squishy pop mainstream. The movie would like to think of itself as a softer, fuzzier ''Garden State.'' (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'KILLER OF SHEEP' (No rating, 83 minutes) Largely hidden from view for three decades, Charles Burnett's lyrical film about a working-class family living in a broken-down home in a bombed-out stretch of Los Angeles is an American masterpiece, independent to the bone. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'LONELY HEARTS' (No rating, 100 minutes) This beautifully photographed remake of Leonard Kastle's 1970 cult B movie ''The Honeymoon Killers'' succeeds better than many modern crime dramas in balancing the philosophical with the visceral, although its villains' dirty deeds still trump its deeper strain of melancholy. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'PATHFINDER' (R, 100 minutes) It's all grunting, all goring in this witless period flick about some Norsemen of the apocalypse come to wreak bloody ruin in the New World. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'PERFECT STRANGER' (R, 109 minutes) There is enough of a grain of truth in this noirish, paranoid thriller set in the New York media world that even after it lurches from the farfetched into the preposterous, the movie leaves a clammy residue of unease. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'PRIVATE FEARS IN PUBLIC PLACES' (No rating, 120 minutes, in French) A film from the venerable French auteur Alain Resnais about love and cinematic spaces, elegant camera moves and six heavenly bodies as seen through a mighty telescope. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'RED ROAD' (No rating, 113 minutes) Andrea Arnold's first feature falls into melodrama and implausibility at the end, but along the way it is a remarkably assured and complex piece of work, anchored by the director's formal control and by Jackie Dick's quietly heartbreaking performance as a Glasgow video-surveillance officer with an unhappy past. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'ROCK THE BELLS' (No rating, 103 minutes) Casey Suchan and Denis Henry Hennelly's lively documentary follows the independent music promoter Chang Weisberg as he struggles to reunite the original members of the Wu-Tang Clan for a 2004 hip-hop concert. Capturing onstage and off with equal energy, the movie is a fascinating glimpse of a dreamer and a music culture that has always depended on them. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'STEPHANIE DALEY' (R, 91 minutes) There is a fine line between a human drama with an autonomous life and an issue-oriented dramatic essay. If this drama about a teenage girl prosecuted for murdering her baby didn't have its ear so perfectly attuned to the tone and language of intergenerational dialogue, it would come across as a dry, cinematic essay. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'SYNDROMES AND A CENTURY' (No rating, 105 minutes, in Thai) Apichatpong Weerasethakul, a Thai director who has become a star of the international festival circuit, makes films that are difficult, abstract and mysterious in the best art-cinema tradition, but at the same time characterized by unusual warmth and generosity of spirit. ''Syndromes,'' suggested by the lives of the filmmaker's parents and the music of Mozart, is a two-part invention on the themes of chance and longing, shot with an intoxicating mix of suavity and sensuality. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'TRIAD ELECTION' (No rating, 93 minutes, in Cantonese) The surfaces gleam as luxuriously in Johnnie To's exemplary gangster thriller ''Triad Election'' as those in a similarly slicked-up Hollywood film, but the blood on the floor here seems stickier, more liable to stain. A brutal look at the shadows darkening the Hong Kong triads, the film picks up the narrative line first coiled and kinked in Mr. To's companion thriller, ''Election.'' (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'VACANCY' (R, 80 minutes) This banal horror retread involves a couple of critters (Luke Wilson, Kate Beckinsale) flailing inside a sticky trap for what is, in effect, the big-screen equivalent of a roach motel. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'THE VALET' (PG-13, 85 minutes, in French) If you love to hate the superrich, this delectable comedy, in which the great French actor Daniel Auteuil portrays a piggy billionaire industrialist facing his comeuppance, is a sinfully delicious bonbon, a classic French farce with modern touches. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'YEAR OF THE DOG' (PG-13, 97 minutes) Mike White's touching comedy about a woman who loses a dog and finds herself is funny ha-ha but firmly in touch with its downer side, which means that it's also funny in a kind of existential way. Molly Shannon stars alongside a menagerie of howling scene-stealers. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'ZOO' (No rating, 76 minutes) Robinson Devor's heavily reconstructed documentary is, to a large extent, about the rhetorical uses of beauty. It is, rather more coyly, also about a man who died after having sex with a stallion. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>avant-garde features (Tonight) Anthology Film Archives, the East Village repository of avant-garde cinema, begins this monthly series devoted to that least commercial of formats, the feature-length experimental film. The initial offering, ''La Raison Avant la Passion,'' Joyce Wieland's 80-minute film from 1969, is a reflection on the author's home country, Canada. It consists of images from a cross-country trip on the Trans-Canada Highway combined with anagrams drawn from the title phrase, a quotation from a speech by Pierre Trudeau. Anthology Film Archives, 32 Second Avenue, at Second Street, East Village, (212) 505-5181, anthologyfilmarchives.org; $8. (Dave Kehr)</p>
        <p>* COMMITMENT AND GRACE: THE FILMS OF CARLOS SAURA (Tomorrow, Sunday, Monday and Wednesday) Mr. Saura is, of course, one of Spain's greatest filmmakers. But for those who love dance, he will always be an artist who speaks vivid new truths about Spanish dancing and the relationship of film and dance. This tribute covers 50 years of work. (Through May 3.) Mr. Saura's magisterial ''Flamenco,'' as much about a nation as about a national dance form, will be shown tomorrow at 9:30 p.m. and Monday at 3 and 7 p.m. Sunday programs are devoted to dance, with ''Blood Wedding'' and ''Sevillanas'' shown at 2 p.m., ''Carmen'' at 4:25 p.m. and ''El Amor Brujo'' (''Love the Magician'') at 6:30 p.m. Wednesday's dance films are ''Blood Wedding,'' at noon; ''Carmen,'' at 1:30 p.m.; and ''El Amor Brujo'' at 3:30 p.m. Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5600, filmlinc.com; $11; $7 for students with ID; $7 for 65+ at weekday screenings before 6 p.m. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>FARES TO REMEMBER (Friday through Sunday) This monthlong series of films set in and around taxicabs comes to an end at the IFC Center with two prime examples of this curious sub-genre: Phil Karlson's first-rate film noir ''99 River Street'' (1953), with John Payne as a taxi-driving former heavyweight champ who finds himself accused of his wife's murder, and Jim Jarmusch's 1991 ''Night on Earth,'' five tales of nocturnal taxi rides set in New York, Paris, Los Angeles, Helsinki and Rome. IFC Center, 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 924-7771, ifccenter.com; $10.75. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>FILMMAKERS AT MACDOWELL: THE STUDIO SYSTEM RECONSIDERED (Wednesday and Thursday) MoMA begins a series of 26 films and video pieces from directors who have passed through the fellowship program at the MacDowell Colony in New Hampshire with a newly commissioned work, ''Seasons of MacDowell.'' It is a four-part film that features contributions by Michael Almereyda, George Griffin, David Petersen and Elisabeth Subrin. (The four filmmakers, along with the chairman of MacDowell, Robert MacNeil, will be present for the Wednesday night screening.) Films being shown on Thursday include work by Cindy Stillwell, Joel Katz, Chris Schiavo, Fern Seiden and Stacey Steers. The series continues through May 16. Museum of Modern Art Roy and Niuta Titus Theaters, (212) 708-9400, moma.org; $10. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>'MANY FACES OF CHIKA' (Tuesday) The North American premiere of the one fiction feature directed by the pre-eminent Japanese documentary filmmaker Kazuo Hara (''The Emperor's Naked Army Marches On''). Anticipating Todd Solondz's ''Palindromes,'' Mr. Hara uses four different actresses to play a single character, that of a woman who abandons her husband and infant son to wander the chaotic world of Japan in the late 1960s and early '70s. After the 7 p.m. screening, Mr. Hara and his longtime writing and producing partner, Sachiko Kobayashi, will participate in a discussion led by the Village Voice film critic Ed Halter. Japan Society, 333 East 47th Street, Manhattan, (212) 715-1258, japansociety.org; $13. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>ACID MOTHERS TEMPLE (Tonight) This prolific Japanese band describes its style as ''extreme trip music,'' which basically means big, sloppy noise jams. It doesn't necessarily mean peasant frocks and long wizard's robes, but Acid Mothers Temple usually has those too. At 9, Southpaw, 125 Fifth Avenue, near Sterling Place, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0236, spsounds.com; $15. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>* KAREN AKERS (Tonight and tomorrow night, and Tuesday through Thursday) The songs in ''Simply Styne,'' Ms. Akers's beautiful tribute to the composer Jule Styne, have been arranged into a touching, tongue-in-cheek cabaret answer to ''Scenes From a Marriage.'' The pianist Don Rebic is her witty partner in deconstruction. At 9, with additional shows tonight and tomorrow night at 11:30, Oak Room at the Algonquin Hotel, 59 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212) 419-9331, algonquinhotel.com; $60 cover; $65 dinner charge at 9; $25 minimum at 11:30. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>* AWESOME COLOR, DIRTY PROJECTORS, DEERHUNTER, BLACK MOTH SUPER RAINBOW (Tonight) Awesome Color's gruff, retro garage-blues is self-consciously noisy as only New York rock can be, but it is also indebted -- and seems partly a homage -- to the vintage Detroit proto-punk of the Stooges and the MC5. Dirty Projectors builds elaborate ''glitch operas'' with stark pluckings of strings and precise, ecstatic harmonies, all arranged slightly out of whack. Deerhunter, from Atlanta, weaves sweet guitar and vocal melodies into patterns that seem both florid and evil. Black Moth Super Rainbow, from Pittsburgh, delivers its shimmering psychedelia through a screen of pulsating keyboards and blissed-out, robotic vocals. At 10, Silent Barn, 915 Wyckoff Avenue, at Hancock Street, Bushwick, Brooklyn, toddpnyc.com; $8. Black Moth Super Rainbow also plays tomorrow at midnight at Pianos, 158 Ludlow Street, near Rivington Street, Lower East Side, (212) 505-3733, pianosnyc.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BELMONT PLAYBOYS (Tomorrow) A sturdy quartet from Charlotte, N.C., the Belmont Playboys play rockabilly forged in a punk esthetic, with energy and respect. At 10:30 p.m., Rodeo Bar, 375 Third Avenue, at 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 683-6500, rodeobar.com; no cover. (Ben Ratliff)</p>
        <p>BISHOP ALLEN (Tomorrow) Borrowing from the playbook of early Jonathan Richman, this Brooklyn band puts a boyish smile on spunky, angst-ridden guitar-pop, and nurses worries about the slow crawl toward the workaday adult life: ''Burn, calendar, burn.'' With Miguel Mendez. At 6:30 p.m., Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3132, knittingfactory.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* BJORK (Wednesday) It's been a long time since Bjork's combination of wailing indie-rock, eroticized electronica and use of random musical props -- Inuit choirs, African kora players -- has been truly avant-garde, or even surprising. But her latest album, ''Volta'' (Elektra), still sounds fresh and energized, with every sound becoming her exotic plaything, whether somber brass, tribal rhythms or staticky beats by Timbaland. At 8 p.m., Radio City Music Hall, (212) 307-7171, radiocity.com; $61 to $86. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CANNIBAL CORPSE (Sunday) The guttural grind of this veteran Buffalo band comes with a punishing regularity, like some nightmarish war machine. Onstage the band is ragged and battle-ready, with guitars clutched like weapons and long hair swirling in ritualistic synchronization. With Behemoth, the Red Chord, Job for a Cowboy and Psyopus. At 7 p.m., Fillmore New York at Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800; $22 in advance, $24 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CRIBS (Wednesday and Thursday) Jeez, the Strokes really are an incredibly influential band. This British trio, with two albums under its belt and a third coming in July, sounds awfully familiar playing those sneering melodies and sharp, uptight chords. The Cribs do it well, and seem to be having a great, sweaty time with it, but still, haven't we been through this before? At 10 p.m., Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700, mercuryloungenyc.com; $15. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>THE KILLERS (Tomorrow) Not many young bands have the songwriting chops to back up their big-league arrogance the way the Killers do. Three years ago this Las Vegas quartet became instant stars with ''Hot Fuss,'' whose adrenalized update of new-wave rock cloaked some of the blasé cynicism of its lyrics (''Dreams aren't what they used to be''). ''Sam's Town'' (Island/Def Jam), released last fall, is grandiose and aloof where its predecessor was sharp and hungry, though it still has a few songs you won't easily get out of your head. At 8 p.m., Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741, thegarden.com; $30 and $45. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PAMELIA KURSTIN, BARBEZ, BIG LAZY (Tonight) Ms. Kurstin plays the theremin, the eerie-sounding electronic instrument ubiquitous in 1950s horror movies, which is controlled by gesturing in the air around two metal rods. It's not easy to develop a recognizable style on the instrument, but she has earned a reputation for her lyrical solos and walking bass lines (really). Here, celebrating the release of her solo album, ''Thinking Out Loud'' (Tzadik), she is joined by Barbez, an avant-cabaret band she plays in; and Big Lazy, whose instrumentals taste of twangy rockabilly and the gutter jazz of the Lounge Lizards. At 9, Brooklyn Lyceum, 227 Fourth Avenue, at Union Street, Park Slope, (718) 857-4816, brooklynlyceum.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* LIGHTNING BOLT, SUN RA ARKESTRA (Tonight) At first it's hard to believe that all the glorious chaos of Lightning Bolt is being made by only two people. But as the sound comes into focus, a playful give-and-take becomes clear, as the bassist Brian Gibson and the drummer and vocalist Brian Chippendale toss back and forth gigantic metal riffs and giggly high notes, creating rainbows of dissonance. In the kind of smart cross-genre pairing that happens all too rarely, the band is playing with the Sun Ra Arkestra, which carries on its namesake's legacy of liberating cacophony. At 6, Pratt Institute Main Lawn, 200 Willoughby Avenue, between Hall Street and Emerson Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, toddpnyc.com; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MAD PROFESSOR (Tuesday) Mad Professor is a master of dub reggae, the music of subterranean bass lines, eerie echoes and unexplained fissures in the fabric of space-time. At 10 p.m., S.O.B.'s, 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940, sobs.com; $22. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>NELLIE McKAY (Tonight) Since her ejection from the mainstream record industry a year ago, Ms. McKay has been keeping busy with other projects: a stint on Broadway, appearances at Lincoln Center. She's doing O.K. Tonight she brings her winky-wink amalgam of American Songbook pop, rap and '50s-style bubblegum (''I'm gonna pounce/Meow/Like a pussy cat'') to Zankel Hall. At 8:30, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $38 to $43. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* MODEST MOUSE (Sunday and Monday) A band so emblematic of 21st-century indie rock that it was mentioned by name in the Supreme Court's decision on MGM v. Grokster two years ago, Modest Mouse, from Issaquah, Wash., links antsy, catchy guitar lines to vocals that are always just a few shrieks away from a destructive tantrum. The addition of Johnny Marr, the innovative former guitarist of the Smiths, has thickened the band's sound without making it any less volatile. At 8 p.m., United Palace Theater, 4140 Broadway, at 175th Street, Washington Heights, (212) 307-7171, bowerypresents.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MOE (Wednesday and Thursday) One chord is all Moe needs to start one of its nimble, quick-fingered jams. Its music starts with the Grateful Dead-Allman Brothers hybrids that most jam bands use, and from there it takes off toward Southern rock, spacey interludes or the borderline of funk. At 9 p.m., Highline Ballroom, 431 West 16th Street, Chelsea, (212) 414-5994, highlineballroom.com; sold out. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>VAN MORRISON (Sunday) Jazz, penitent country and lots of tasty, Celtic-favored R&amp;B fuel Mr. Morrison's incantatory performances, which can smolder intensely or rest in a meditative stillness according to his mood. At 7:30 p.m., Theater at Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741, thegarden.com; $90 and $175. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>GRAHAM PARKER AND THE LATEST CLOWNS (Tonight) Emerging from England just before the arrival of punk rock, Mr. Parker used the sturdy structures of soul and '60s rock, spitting out angry, articulate songs that chafed against dishonesties large and small. These days he's less furious and more cranky, but he's still holding the world around him to high standards. At 8, Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3132, knittingfactory.com; $25. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>Shahid Parvez (Tomorrow) Shahid Parvez carries on a legacy of sitar playing that goes back seven generations in his family. He is one of India's more celebrated younger musicians, prized especially for the vocalistic phrasing of his raga improvisations. He is to play duets with Aditya Kalyanpur on tabla. At 8 p.m., Philip Coltoff Center, 219 Sullivan Street, near West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 477-5239, virsaonline.com; $25. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>* PETER BJORN AND JOHN; FUJIYA &amp; MIYAGI (Tuesday and Wednesday) The latest sharp and impeccably stylish import from Sweden, Peter Bjorn and John sets breathy, heavy-hearted vocals over peppery band arrangements that recall 1960s folk-pop. Fujiya &amp; Miyagi, a British trio -- ''We are only pretending to be Japanese,'' goes one lyric -- plays bubbly perpetual-motion figures of guitar and keyboard. Its sound has been heard plenty of times before (Stereolab, Neu!), but it's too fun and innocuous to ever tire of. At 8 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* LOU REED (Monday) Representing the best of New York rock's past, Lou Reed might seem an odd choice to open a new club. But hey, it's Chelsea 2007, and that means glitz and fame and velvet ropes, so Mr. Reed, 65, is the first booking in the 700-capacity new Highline Ballroom. His onstage manner, never exactly warm, has stiffened in recent years, but he still expertly walks a line between aloof cynicism and naked, affecting vulnerability. With Okkervil River, a hyperliterate band from Austin, Tex. At 9 p.m., 431 West 16th Street, Chelsea, (212) 414-5994, highlineballroom.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ROSE HILL DRIVE (Tomorrow) Like the blues-rock power trios of yore, Rose Hill Drive, from Boulder, Colo., puts all its attention to bruising, jammable riffs, leaving the edges deliberately rough. At 8:30 p.m., Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700, mercuryloungenyc.com; $15. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Keely Smith (Tonight and tomorrow night) This ''queen of swing,'' as she has been nicknamed, may be the last surviving top-of-the-line entertainer from the Rat Pack era of Las Vegas. She is still in reasonably good voice. At 8:45 and 10:45, Café Carlyle, Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212) 744-1600, thecarlyle.com; $75 to $125. (Holden)</p>
        <p>AMON TOBIN (Tomorrow) A decade ago this Brazilian D.J.'s warped, flagellum rhythms seemed about as far out as dance-based music could get. His new album, ''Foley Room'' (Ninja Tune), is just as squiggly and disorienting, though it has lost what it now appears was its most significant trait: novelty. At 9 p.m., Blender Theater at Gramercy, 127 East 23rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171; $23. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>TRANS AM (Thursday) This trio from Washington plays tightly coiled, retro-futuristic electronic rock like a band stuck in the light matrix of ''Tron'' (or at least one with a serious Kraftwerk fetish). With Zombi and Psychic Paramount. At 8 p.m., Studio B, 259 Banker Street, between Meserole Avenue and Calyer Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 389-1880, clubstudiob.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* YO LA TENGO (Sunday) The model of indie-rock perseverance, Yo La Tengo is led by its songwriters, the husband-and-wife team of Ira Kaplan on guitar and Georgia Hubley on drums. They prize succinct, tuneful songs about the modest pains and pleasures of daily life and love; they also love excursions into feedback and fuzz-tone. With the Brooklyn psych-rock masters Oneida. At 7:30 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; $25. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>REZ ABBASI'S BAZAAR (Tonight) On his most recent album, ''Bazaar'' (Zoho), the guitarist Rez Abbasi infuses Southeast Asian motifs with rock bombast and jazz flexibility. At midnight, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $10, with a $10 minimum. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>ANDY BISKIN (Tomorrow) Mr. Biskin is a clarinetist who often spikes his sturdy compositions with a wily sense of humor. He presents new music for a quartet with Shane Endsley on trumpet, Eivind Opsvik on bass and Take Toriyama on drums. At 8, the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ABRAHAM BURTON/ERIC McPHERSON GROUP (Tomorrow) The saxophonist Abraham Burton and the drummer Eric McPherson share a brisk command of post-bop traditions, as they prove with this quartet. At midnight, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $10, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TAYLOR HO BYNUM SEXTET (Tonight) On his new album, ''The Middle Picture'' (Firehouse 12), the cornetist Taylor Ho Bynum advances an avant-garde chamber music jostling with odd intervals and useful frictions. Most of the musicians joining him here, like the guitarist Mary Halvorson and the drummer Tomas Fujiwara, are longtime compatriots with an established rapport. At 9 and 10:30, Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE DAVIS QUINTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) ''Update'' (Criss Cross), a recent album by the trombonist Steve Davis, earns its title by gently bringing 1950s hard bop into a modern sphere. Mr. Davis undertakes a similar process with his quintet, which features the saxophonist Mike DiRubbo. At 8 and 9:45, Kitano Hotel, 66 Park Avenue, at 38th Street, (212) 885-7119, kitano.com; cover, $25, with a $15 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* JOEL FRAHM (Tuesday through Thursday) Mr. Frahm's tenor saxophone playing has rarely sounded roomier or more relaxed than it does on ''We Used To Dance'' (Anzic), an album featuring Kenny Barron on piano, Rufus Reid on bass and Victor Lewis on drums. That group begins an engagement at Sweet Rhythm next Wednesday; on the previous night, Mr. Frahm holds down his regular trio engagement at the Bar Next Door. Tuesday at 8 and 10 p.m., Bar Next Door, 129 MacDougal Street, West Village, (212) 529-5945, lalanternacaffe.com; cover, $8, with a one-drink minimum. Wednesday and Thursday at 8 and 10 p.m., Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212) 255-3626, sweetrhythmny.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* KENNY GARRETT (Tomorrow, Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Garrett is a terror on the alto saxophone, and an artisan on the soprano; he uses both instruments to explore aesthetic territory associated with John Coltrane. Tomorrow he shares a bill in Newark with the fine post-bop trumpeter Nicholas Payton, each leading a quartet. On Wednesday he begins an engagement with a band featuring the tenor saxophonist and Coltrane contemporary Pharoah Sanders, who appeared on Mr. Garrett's last album, ''Beyond the Wall.'' Tomorrow at 7:30 p.m., New Jersey Performing Arts Center, 1 Center Street, Newark, (888) 466-5722, njpac.org; $44 to $54. Wednesday and Thursday (Through May 6) at 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $40, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JERRY GRANELLI, JAMIE SAFT AND J. ANTHONY GRANELLI (Sunday) The drummer Jerry Granelli and his son J. Anthony Granelli, a bassist, have teamed up on a number of worthy projects, including ''The Sonic Temple'' (Songlines), an atmospheric live album. They collaborate here with Mr. Saft, a texture-minded keyboardist. At 8:30 p.m., Center for Improvisational Music, 295 Douglass Street, between Third and Fourth Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (212) 631-5882, schoolforimprov.org; cover, $12; $8 for students. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ROY HARGROVE BIG BAND (Thursday) The trumpeter Roy Hargrove has been a paragon of small-group hard bop since the early 1990s. But he has also led a powerful big band, on and off, for roughly the same span of time. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $25; $10 for members. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>THE HEATH BROTHERS (Wednesday and Thursday) Two years after the loss of their brother Percy, a bassist and cellist, the saxophonist Jimmy Heath and the drummer Albert (Tootie) Heath soldier on. The pianist Jeb Patton and the bassist David Wong round out the band. (Through May 5.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $40, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>FREDDIE HUBBARD AND FRIENDS (Tonight through Sunday night) The sleek and fiery hard-bop of Mr. Hubbard's trumpet-playing prime provides source material for this all-star affair, which variously includes longtime peers (like the trombonist Slide Hampton) and worthy inheritors (like the bassist Christian McBride). At 8:30 and 10:30, with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow night, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $40 ($35 tonight), with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SUSIE IBARRA AND ROBERTO RODRIGUEZ (Wednesday) Ms. Ibarra is a drummer with a passion for texture and abstraction, and a composer committed to the idea of cultural exchange. ''Electric Kulintang,'' her percussive collaboration with Mr. Rodriguez, adds a contemporary sheen to the chiming kulintang music of the Philippines. At 9:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 539-8778, joespub.com; cover, $15, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MICHAEL MUSILLAMI TRIO +1 (Wednesday) As he demonstrates on his recent album, ''Fragile Forms,'' the guitarist Michael Mussillami favors a bright and slippery variety of post-bop. So his trio should provide a hospitable environment for the sharply expressive violinist Mark Feldman. At 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE NELSON (Tonight and tomorrow night) Mr. Nelson, a vibraphonist best known of late for his role in the Dave Holland Quintet, brings thoughtful poise to this top-flight ensemble with another powerful bassist, Robert Hurst III. At 8, 10 and 11:30, Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662, smokejazz.com; cover, $28. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JEFF NEWELL'S NEW-TRAD OCTET (Tonight) This aptly named band, led by the saxophonist Jeff Newell, celebrates the release of its first album, ''Brownstone,'' with a respectfully revisionist set of early jazz, gospel and parade music. At 8, Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; cover, $10 suggested donation. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JEREMY PELT QUARTET (Tuesday through Thursday) Jeremy Pelt, a trumpeter with a big tone and bracing technique, leads a locomotive band with Danny Grissett on piano, Derek Nievergelt on bass and Willie Jones III on drums. (Through May 6.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LUIS PERDOMO TRIO (Tomorrow) On ''Awareness'' (RKM), his most recent album, the pianist Luis Perdomo plays with exploratory urgency, and his compositions take unforced yet unexpected turns. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* PIANO PARTY: 80 AND ONWARD (Tomorrow) The pianist Dick Hyman, an emeritus presence at the 92nd Street Y, celebrates his new octogenarian status there with help from friends like the trumpeter Joe Wilder, the pianists Bill Charlap and Derek Smith, the guitarist Bucky Pizzarelli and the clarinetist Evan Christopher. At 8 p.m., 92 Street Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue, (212) 415-5500, 92y.org; $45. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>KURT ROSENWINKEL (Sunday) Mr. Rosenwinkel is a guitarist with a fluid technique and a resonant, warm-blooded tone. Making an infrequent appearance at the club where he honed his craft roughly a dozen years ago, he leads an intuitive trio. At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., Smalls, 183 West 10th Street, West Village, (212) 252-5091; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PONCHO SANCHEZ (Tonight through Sunday night) Mr. Sanchez, a high-spirited conga player, has been a leading figure in Latin jazz for over 20 years, thanks to this working band. At 8 and 10:30, Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $35 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVE SCOTT (Wednesday) Mr. Scott, a trumpeter, presents a version of the hard-bop quintet heard on his new album, ''Naiveté'': Rich Perry on tenor saxophone, Jacob Sacks on piano, John Hebert on bass and Take Toriyama on drums. At 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* KENDRICK SCOTT ORACLE (Tuesday) Kendrick Scott is a drummer conversant in an ultramodern sense of propulsion, and as he proves on a new album called ''The Source,'' he's a thoughtful composer as well. His band, Oracle, includes versatile peers like the alto saxophonist and bass clarinetist Myron Walden, the guitarist Mike Moreno and the pianist Aaron Parks. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>EMILIO SOLLA AND NY TANGO (Tonight and tomorrow night) The pianist Emilio Solla fashions a modern jazz translation of the popular music of his native Argentina, with help from the saxophonists Donny McCaslin and Chris Cheek, the accordionist Victor Prieto, the bassist Pablo Aslan and the drummer Jeff Ballard. At 8:30 and 10:30, Smalls, 183 West 10th Street, West Village, (212) 675-7369, fatcatjazz.com; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>E. J. STRICKLAND QUINTET (Tonight) Crisp and assertive post-bop from the drummer E. J. Strickland and a capable crew: John Ellis and Miguel Zenon on saxophones, Luis Perdomo on piano and Massimo Biolcati on bass. At 10, 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, near Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BEN WALTZER QUINTET (Tomorrow) Ben Waltzer manages a brand of pianistic modernism that coexists peaceably with a buoyant, un-self-conscious sense of swing. In this group he features a pair of excellent saxophonists, Bill McHenry and J. D. Allen. At 9 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* CASSANDRA WILSON (Wednesday and Thursday) A jazz singer by training and temperament, Ms. Wilson takes obvious pleasure in a boundless repertory, a tendency borne out vividly on her most recent album, ''Thunderbird.'' She makes a rare nightclub appearance with some estimable longtime colleagues: the guitarist Marvin Sewell, the drummer Herlin Riley and the bassist Reginald Veal. (Through May 5.) At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $55 at tables, $35 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE WILSON'S GENERATIONS (Tonight through Sunday night) It has been nearly a decade since the release of ''Generations,'' a rewarding album by the alto saxophonist Steve Wilson featuring Mulgrew Miller on piano, Ray Drummond on bass and Ben Riley on drums. The quartet has regrouped periodically, always with sturdy results. At 7:30 and 9:30, with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow night, Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $30; $25 on Sunday. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* JAN WRoBLEWSKI QUARTET (Tuesday) Mr. Wroblewski, the tenor saxophonist and composer, has been one of the most celebrated jazz musicians in Poland for the last four decades. Now in his 70s, he has a new album, ''Supercalifragilistic,'' and a strong rhythm section, with Wojciech Niedziela on piano, Jacek Niedziela on bass and Marcin Jahr on drums. This performance, sponsored by the Polish Cultural Institute, is a rare opportunity to hear him in person. At 7 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>* 'IL BARBIERE DI SIVIGLIA' (Monday) Bartlett Sher's breezy production, introduced at the Metropolitan Opera in November, conveys the comic confusions of the story through its fluid staging and a wonderfully abstract set: a matrix of movable doors, staircases and potted orange trees, behind which the characters spy on one another. The heated sexuality in this tale of romantic intrigue also comes through strongly, thanks to Mr. Sher's subtle directing of a handsome cast, notably the captivating young mezzo-soprano Joyce DiDonato, a vocally agile and feisty Rosina. Lawrence Brownlee, in his debut role with the company, sings Almaviva, and the hardy baritone Russell Braun sings Figaro. At 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; sold out. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* 'GIULIO CESARE' (Tonight) The Metropolitan Opera's successful run of John Copley's production of Handel's ''Giulio Cesare'' closes tonight. The countertenor Lawrence Zazzo, who was a fine Tolomeo in previous performances this season, his debut season at the Met, takes over from David Daniels in the difficult title role. The Australian soprano Danielle de Niese takes over from Ruth Ann Swenson as Cleopatra. The rest of the cast is unchanged: the mezzo-soprano Alice Coote is excellent as Sesto, and so is Patricia Bardon in her role as Cornelia. Harry Bicket, a Handel specialist, conducts an elegant performance. At 7:30, Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $15 to $320. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* 'ORFEO ED EURIDICE' (Wednesday) The Met is wrapping up an innovative, colorful season with what may be an innovative, colorful production: Mark Morris, the choreographer, is making his company debut, along with Isaac Mizrahi as costume designer. Gluck's so-called ''reform'' opera, calm and tuneful and slightly static, is something of a departure for James Levine, who conducts, but not at all for the countertenor David Daniels, who is having a great year at the Met and will sing Orpheus. The four performances of this piece are dedicated to the memory of the singer Lorraine Hunt Lieberson. At 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; sold out. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>* 'IL TRITTICO' (Tomorrow and Tuesday) The Met's new ''Trittico,'' Puccini's triptych of one-act operas, is now the most elaborate production in the company's repertory. The director Jack O'Brien has created grandly old-fashioned yet insightful and effective stagings of these three very different operas: ''Il Tabarro,'' a grim love triangle aboard a barge in Paris; ''Suor Angelica,'' a tender, mystical and ultimately devastating story of a young nun's yearning to be with her dead child; and ''Gianni Schicchi,'' an irreverent comedy about the avaricious relatives of a miserly old man. Maria Guleghina as the beleaguered barge-owner's wife, Barbara Frittoli as Sister Angelica, and Alessandro Corbelli as Schicchi are stand-outs, though the powerhouse mezzo-soprano Stephanie Blythe almost steals each show playing three supporting roles. James Levine conducts vibrant and beautifully refined performances. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., Tuesday at 7:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; sold out. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'TURANDOT' (Tomorrow and Thursday) Puccini's extravagant image of a mythical East, made more extravagant in Franco Zeffirelli's grandiose production, offers another look at the soprano Erika Sunnegardh, who stepped in for Andrea Gruber in the title role a few weeks ago, just as she stepped in for Karita Mattila in ''Fidelio'' a year ago. Tomorrow at 8:30 p.m., Thursday at 7:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; sold out. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>* AMERICAN COMPOSERS ORCHESTRA (Tonight) The composer John Adams leads this specialist orchestra in a program of his own works, including ''My Father Knew Charles Ives,'' ''The Wound-Dresser'' and ''The Violin Concerto.'' The violinist Leila Josefowicz and the bass-baritone Eric Owens are the soloists. At 8, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $16 to $43. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>AMERICAN FESTIVAL OF MICROTONAL MUSIC (Sunday and Wednesday) For fans of microtonal music -- music in non-standard tunings -- this annual festival opens on Sunday with a performance by MicroJam, an ensemble from Boston, and Dave Taylor, the trombonist, who will perform Johnny Reinhard's ''Zelig Mood Ring'' and stay on for a jam with Mr. Reinhard and MicroJam. The second installment, on Wednesday, includes more music by Mr. Reinhard and works by Elodie Lauten, Kyle Gann and Joseph Pehrson. At 10 p.m., Bowery Poetry Club, 308 Bowery, at Bleecker Street, East Village, (212) 517-3550, afmm.org; $10. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* AUSTRALIAN CHAMBER ORCHESTRA (Sunday) This excellent orchestra and its artistic leader, the violinist Richard Tognetti, play concertos by Vivaldi and Corelli in their program at Zankel Hall, an acoustically lively space for chamber ensembles. The arresting and intelligent Dutch cellist Pieter Wispelwey is the soloist in Haydn's Concerto in C. The program ends with Tchaikovsky's beguiling ''Souvenir de Florence.'' At 7:30 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $32 and $44. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* CHAMBER MUSIC SOCIETY OF LINCOLN CENTER (Tonight and Sunday) The British composer Nicholas Maw, born in 1935, is associated with the Neo-Romantic movement in contemporary music. But it is hard to categorize his elegantly written and strikingly personal music, which is multilayered, complex and spiked with modernistic elements. The Chamber Music Society presents the premiere of Mr. Maw's Sextet for Strings on a smartly conceived program that offers works by composers who have inspired him: Haydn, Schumann, Bruckner, Strauss and Britten. Tonight at 8 and Sunday at 5 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5788, chambermusicsociety.org; $28 to $50. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>CURTIS ORCHESTRA (Wednesday) If the standards of other training orchestras that have passed through Carnegie Hall recently are any measure, the Curtis Orchestra surely won't disappoint. The orchestra, conducted by Christoph Eschenbach, the Philadelphia Orchestra's music director, will be joined by Roberto Díaz, a violist and the new president of the Curtis Institute, in Penderecki's Viola Concerto. The program also includes Bernstein's ''Symphonic Dances'' from ''West Side Story'' and Stravinsky's ''Sacre du Printemps.'' At 8 p.m., (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $15 to $100. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>'GOOD NIGHT ALICE' (Monday) Alice Tully was so identified with her most visible act of patronage that a possibly apocryphal story has a partygoer addressing her as ''Miss Hall.'' It's that hall that's now being sent off musically to slumber in a cocoon of reconstruction: it will be closed for a season, reopening in late 2008. Its lullaby is a benefit concert for Lincoln Center's redevelopment project featuring the Juilliard Orchestra, led by David Robertson, in a program that arcs from Bernstein to Bernstein, with other works by Messiaen, Wynton Marsalis and Mozart. Tom Brokaw will serve as host of the event, which PBS will broadcast nationwide on Thursday. At 7 p.m, Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $1,500 and up for gala tickets, which include cocktails and a post-concert dinner. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>SERGEI KHACHATRYAN (Monday) This talented Armenian violinist, winner of both the Sibelius competition in Helsinki and the Queen Elizabeth Competition in Brussels, makes his New York recital debut with Lusine Khachatryan, his sister, as his accompanist. The program includes Bach's Chaconne in D minor from the Violin Partita No. 2; Franck's Sonata in A; and Shostakovich's Sonata. At 7:30 p.m., Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; sold out. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>EVGENY KISSIN (Thursday) In sheer talent, Mr. Kissin may be the most gifted pianist of his generation. Here he brings his big, Romantic, if somewhat inflexible approach to music by Beethoven, Brahms, Schubert and Chopin. At 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $44 to $140. (Holland)</p>
        <p>KRONOS YOUNG ARTISTS CONCERT (Tomorrow) Four emerging quartets will perform repertory they have studied in workshops this past week with the innovative Kronos Quartet, which champions contemporary music and frequently commissions new works. The lineup features pieces either written for or arranged for Kronos, including Steve Reich's ''Triple Quartet,'' John Zorn's ''Cat o' Nine Tails'' and Alexandra du Bois's String Quartet, as well as arrangements by Osvaldo Golijov and others. At 7:30 p.m., Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $15. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* LOS ANGELES PHILHARMONIC (Tomorrow, Sunday, Wednesday and Thursday) Esa-Pekka Salonen recently announced that he would turn over the podium of the orchestra he has rejuvenated over the last several years, so it will be good to see him lead it in a week of concerts in (and near) New York. The visit begins tomorrow at the New Jersey Performing Arts Center, when Mr. Salonen leads a suite from Prokofiev's ''Romeo and Juliet''; a work of his own, ''Helix''; and Ravel's Concerto for the Left Hand, with Jean-Yves Thibaudet. That program is repeated at Avery Fisher Hall on Sunday. On Wednesday Mr. Salonen leads one of his most successful recent endeavors, ''The Tristan Project,'' a semistaged version of Wagner's ''Tristan und Isolde'' with video by Bill Viola and a cast that includes Christian Franz and Christine Brewer in the title roles. And on Thursday the soprano Renée Fleming sings music of Strauss and Korngold with the orchestra, and Mr. Salonen leads Sibelius's ''Lemminkainen'' Suite. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., New Jersey Performing Arts Center, 1 Center Street, Newark, (888) 466-5722, njpac.org; $24 to $88. Sunday at 3 p.m., Wednesday at 6 p.m. and Thursday at 8 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $35 to $69 (Sunday and Thursday), $175 to $275 (Wednesday). (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>MANNES CONTEMPORARY MUSIC FESTIVAL (Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday) Works by the Pulitzer Prize-winner Paul Moravec; an evening of percussion that includes Steve Reich's ''Drumming''; world premieres by Davide Zannoni and others; and pieces by leading figures, like Iannis Xenakis, are all part of this festival, which takes on various aspects of the contemporary. Performers include chamber and percussion ensembles and, of course, the Mannes School Orchestra. At 8 p.m., Mannes College of Music, 150 West 85th Street, Manhattan, (212) 496-8524, mannes.newschool.edu; free. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>MAURIZIO POLLINI (Sunday) A musician of high accomplishment and uncompromising dignity, Mr. Pollini makes one of his regular stops at Carnegie Hall in a recital including Chopin pieces, Book II of the Debussy Études and the Boulez Second Sonata. At 3 p.m., (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $34 to $108. (Holland)</p>
        <p>GIL SHAHAM AND FRIENDS (Wednesday) The talented Mr. Shaham seems to be onstage playing his violin every time we look up. Here he is again with six colleagues in an all-Brahms program that includes the String Sextet. At 7:30 p.m., Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; sold out. (Holland)</p>
        <p>* DAWN UPSHAW (Sunday) This radiant soprano, who has recently begun performing again after being treated for breast cancer, opens the fifth season of Free for All at Town Hall concerts with a typically versatile program. She will sing works by American composers like Ruth Crawford Seeger and Ives, as well as pieces by Ravel, Fauré, Debussy, Schumann and Wolf. She finishes with three of William Bolcom's ''Cabaret Songs.'' Her accompanist, Gilbert Kalish, will also play a Brahms intermezzo. At 5 p.m., 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 707-8787, freeforallattownhall.org; free, but tickets are required. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>VERTAVO STRING QUARTET (Tonight) This dynamic Norwegian all-female quartet has been playing to acclaim for over 20 years. Founded in Oslo, it is known for its vibrant performances and special affinity for contemporary music. On this New York stop, though, the newest work the Vertavo will play is Bartok's Third Quartet, from 1927. Still, it should be invigorating to hear Bartok's path-breaking piece along with Haydn's inventive Quartet in D (Op. 20, No. 4) and Grieg's moody Quartet in G minor, a signature work in this ensemble's repertory. At 7:30, Weill Recital Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $44. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>VOX VOCAL ENSEMBLE (Tomorrow) George Steel's superb chamber choir, supported by the Manhattan Choral Ensemble, the Graham Ashton Brass Ensemble and the organist Robert McCormick, sings a program divided between early music (works by Allegri, Palestrina, Eccard and Isaac) and music of the 19th century (including works by Brahms, Mendelssohn, Wolf and Bruckner). At 8 p.m., Church of St. Mary the Virgin, 145 West 46th Street, Manhattan, (212) 854-7799, millertheater.com; $35. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>* ABT STUDIO COMPANY (Tonight and tomorrow) In addition to spotting the dance stars of the future while they are still hungry for stage space and choreography, these programs offer new and innovative dances as well as classics. The company will perform Antony Tudor's ''Jardin aux Lilas''; the pas de deux from August Bournonville's ''Flower Festival in Genzano''; and Brian Reeder's new ''Ghost Light,'' a collaboration with the filmmaker Elliot Caplan. Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Skirball Center for the Performing Arts, New York University, 566 La Guardia Place, at Washington Square South, Greenwich Village, (212) 279-4200, skirballcenter.nyu.edu; $28. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>CHAMECKILERNER (Tuesday through Thursday) Rosane Chamecki and Andrea Lerner, both originally from Brazil, are known for their dark, exaggerated and often raw depictions of human behavior. In their new multimedia ''EXIT,'' they create a funeral rite for themselves in which colleagues offer eulogies and flashbacks as they watch from the afterlife. (Through May 5.) At 8 p.m., the Kitchen, 512 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 255-5793, Ext. 11, thekitchen.org; $10. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CHEZ BUSHWICK PRESENTS: AMBUSH (Tomorrow) This project devoted to new works by the mostly young will present ''Notes on a Van Guard,'' which includes work by Eija-Liisa Ahtila, Nathan Davis, Light in August, Joe Levasseur, Moving Theater and Matthew Rogers and Jack Ferver, with a talk on French dance tucked in for good measure. At 8 p.m., Bushwick Starr, 207 Starr Street, between Irving and Wyckoff Streets, Bushwick, Brooklyn, info@thebushwickstarr.org; $5. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>EL COLEGIO DEL CUERPO -- LA COMPANIA (Sunday) This company of young dancers from Cartagena, Colombia, will perform ''Fragments,'' a piece drawn from 10 years of repertory created by the company directors Álvaro Restrepo and Marie France Delieuvin. At 3 p.m., Queens Theater in the Park, Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, (718) 760-0064, queenstheatre.org; $28; $20 for students. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT BALLET (Tomorrow) The company celebrates its 25th anniversary with the appropriately titled ''Razzle Dazzle!,'' a gala program featuring ballet and modern, African, flamenco and tap dance by guest artists from the United States, Brazil, Europe and West Africa. At 7:30 p.m., Rich Forum, 307 Atlantic Street, Stamford, Conn., (203) 325-4466, stamfordcenterforthearts.org; $25 to $50. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>EIFMAN BALLET (Tonight through Sunday) Boris Eifman's ''Anna Karenina'' will be performed this weekend, the close of its season at City Center. Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 2 and 7 p.m., City Center, 131 West 55th Street, Manhattan, (212) 581-1212, nycitycenter.org; $35 to $100. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'FROM TAP TO TOE!' (Tomorrow) Fifteen dance troupes will perform in this four-hour marathon, among them Hilary Easton &amp; Company, RumbaTap and Troika Ranch. At 7 p.m., Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, symphonyspace.org; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>ANDRÉ GINGRAS/KORZO PRODUCTIES (Thursday) From the Netherlands, Mr. Gingras and his company will present ''CYP17,'' a mixed-media piece that aims to present ''the 'freak show' that is our future,'' as its publicity puts it. Rock on. (Through May 5.) At 8:30 p.m., Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194, danspaceproject.org; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>KENNEDY DANCERS (Tonight and tomorrow night) Based in Jersey City, this modern-dance troupe will mark its 30th anniversary with a program of dances by the company director, Diane Dragone, with one work by a different guest group each night. Tonight, Nimbus Dance Works and Synthesis Dance Project; tomorrow, Arch Dance Company. At 7:30, Baryshnikov Arts Center, 450 West 37th Street, Manhattan, (201) 659-2190; $20; $18 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>ALONZO KING'S LINES BALLET (Tuesday through Thursday) This San Francisco company dances ballet with an unusual streamlined and extra-active body line and attack. Mr. King's new ''Moroccan Project'' is set to African drumming and oud and violin music. His ''Migration,'' also new, will be danced to music by Pharoah Sanders, Miguel Frasconi and Leslie Stuck. (Through May 6.) Tuesday and Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800, joyce.org; $40. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'LA MAMA MOVES!' (Tonight through Thursday) This modern-dance version of a three-ring circus spills out into three theater spaces at La MaMa, with nine programs featuring more than 50 companies and soloists. (Through May 13.) La MaMa E.T.C., 74A East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 475-7710, lamama.org; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>LAVA (Thursday) Sarah East Johnson and her all-female company, which specializes in acrobatic modern dance spiced with double-trapeze work, will present ''Tides,'' a new piece that incorporates time-capture video of the Rockaway shoreline and ocean-wave patterns. (Through May 27.) At 7 p.m., Flea Theater, 41 White Street, between Broadway and Church Street, TriBeCa, (212) 352-3101, theatermania.com; $10 to $30. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'LET'S SPEAK TANGO!' (Tonight through Sunday, and Thursday) Well, why not? For the record, this latest celebration of that sultry dance form was choreographed by Valeria Solomonoff, one of the show's eight performers, and directed by Carlo Magaletti. (Through May 6.) Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 3 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., American Theater of Actors, 314 West 54th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444, smarttix.com; $40. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>AMY MARSHALL DANCE (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ms. Marshall's dances will address the beauty of the human body, the last days of Joan of Arc and, to music by Mike Seeger and the New Lost City Ramblers, the textile industry in Spartanburg, S.C. Clearly this is a choreographer with eclectic interests. At 8, Ailey Citigroup Theater, 405 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444, smarttix.com; $30; $20 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* MIRO DANCE THEATER (Wednesday) The company directors, Amanda Miller, who danced with the Pennsylvania Ballet and studied choreography with Siobhan Davies, and Tobin Rothlein, a video artist and designer, do better than most at combining visuals and movement to make a third, poetically expressive form. Their new dance, ''Pitch Black,'' addresses human connections and disconnections in urban life. It is set to music for sax and boombox by JacobTV, to be performed live. At 8 p.m., Whitney Museum of Art at Altria, 120 Park Avenue, at 42nd Street, (800) 944-8639; free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>THE MOVEMENT MOVEMENT &amp; FRIENDS MOVE IN (Tomorrow and Sunday) Advance information on this event is about as unclear as its title, but it all has something to do with changing rooms, streaming video and an empty 7,000-square-foot retail space. Reassuringly, the performers include Scotty the Blue Bunny. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Sunday at 7 p.m., Front and Beekman Streets, next to 207 Fulton Street, South Street Seaport, (917) 531-1171, info@themovementmovement.org; $15; $10 ''for those that are starving.'' (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* NEW YORK CITY BALLET (Tonight, tomorrow and Tuesday through Thursday) Lincoln Kirstein, who founded the company with George Balanchine, will be celebrated in three different all-Balanchine repertory programs (tonight and tomorrow afternoon and evening). Then comes Peter Martins's eagerly awaited new production of ''Romeo and Juliet'' (Tuesday through May 13), with lead roles performed by some of City Ballet's youngest up-and-comers. Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Tuesday and Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. (no Sunday performance), Thursday at 8 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nycballet.com; $30 to $86; $15 student rush tickets available day of performance. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK THEATER BALLET (Tonight and tomorrow night) The program includes William Dollar's rarely performed piece ''Le Combat,'' Agnes de Mille's ''Carousel'' ballet and dances by Donald Mahler and Sallie Wilson. Tonight and tomorrow night at 7:30, Gould Hall, 55 East 59th Street, Manhattan (212) 355-6160, nytb.org; $30; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'THE NOTHING FESTIVAL' (Tonight and tomorrow night) The choreographer Tere O'Connor asked eight other choreographers to each contribute a new piece made from scratch, with no story, music or nondance source to guide them. The festival closes this week with works by Luciana Achugar, Walter Dundervill, Jon Kinzel and Susan Rethorst. At 7:30, Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077, dtw.org; $20. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>STREB SLAM 9 (Tonight through Sunday) Elizabeth Streb and her high-flying, death-defying performers will perform repertory favorites featuring a swivel harness, two huge plywood panels and, for the audience, popcorn and cotton candy. (Through June 17.) Tonight at 7, tomorrow at 3 and 7 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., S.L.A.M., 51 North First Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (212) 352-3101, strebusa.org; $20; $10 for children. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>VANGELINE DANCE THEATER (Tonight and tomorrow night) The program includes new Butoh dance by the company director, Vangeline, and Nicole LeGette. It also features modern dance by Eva Perotta in a program called ''La Porte Étroite: (Apothéose Mystique),'' a title drawn from a novel by André Gide. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Puffin Room, 435 Broome Street, between Broadway and Crosby Street, SoHo, (212) 343-2881; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* YOUTH AMERICA GRAND PRIX 2007 GALA (Monday) This international competition, which awards scholarships for ballet study, is usually a big, joyous mess of dancing by talented young finalists and professionals. This time the companies include the Paris Opera Ballet, the Stuttgart and the Royal Ballet, as well as several leading American dance troupes. At 7 p.m., City Center, 131 West 55th Street, Manhattan, (212) 581-1212, nycitycenter.org; $45 to $150. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'KINDRED SPIRITS: ASHER B. DURAND AND THE AMERICAN LANDSCAPE,' through July 29. This show of about 60 works by one of the greats of 19th-century American landscape painting has as its centerpiece ''Kindred Spirits'' (1849), a tribute to the landscapist Thomas Cole and his friend the poet-journalist William Cullen Bryant. A founder of the Hudson River School, Durand (1796-1886) favored the realistic approach to landscape advocated by the English critic John Ruskin. Durand explored forest interiors with close attention to the ways of trees, foliage and rocks and ground cover in smaller works, while his larger and more elaborate exhibition pictures, influenced by European masters, are Arcadian visions suffused with light, color and atmospheric perspective. If the show reveals some of Durand's weaknesses -- repetitive themes and borrowings from other artists -- it also reveals his strong sense of artistic mission and his potent role in shaping the aesthetic of 19th-century America. 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, Brooklyn, (718) 638-5000, brooklynmuseum.org. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>* JAPAN SOCIETY: 'Awakenings: Zen Figure Painting in Medieval Japan,' through June 17. Japan Society has a history of producing exquisite shows of Buddhist art. And this one, with four dozen paintings of Buddhists gods and saints hung in shrinelike alcoves, is transporting. It covers a broad swath of geography, bringing together 13th- to 16th-century hanging scrolls, not only from Japan but also from China, where Zen Buddhism, called Chan in Chinese, originated. 333 East 47th Street, (212) 832-1155, japansociety.org. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>The Jewish Museum: Dateline: Israel: 'New Photography and Video Art,' through Aug. 5. Roughly every decade, the Jewish Museum offers a survey of contemporary art from and about Israel. This year non-Israeli artists from Europe and the United States -- and a single artist from Palestine -- have been added to the mix. There's some very good work here, though, on the whole, the show grapples with crucial political issues in an indirect way. 1109 Fifth Avenue, at 92nd Street, (212) 423-3200, jewishmuseum.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* the Metropolitan Museum of Art: 'Journeys: Mapping the Earth and Mind in Chinese Art,' through Aug. 26. Every six months or so, the Met rotates all the work in its Chinese painting galleries to preserve the delicate silks and papers, and each time, the curator in charge, Maxwell K. Hearn, produces a new and illuminating thematic exhibition, as is the case with ''Journeys.'' Outward-bound and inward-bound are the directions taken by Chinese landscape painting, and it carries us on some fascinating voyages in a show that mixes classical and contemporary art. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* the met: 'Venice and the Islamic World, 828-1797,' through July 8. At its peak in the Renaissance, Venice, the Most Serene, was a giant, clamorous Costco-on-the-Rialto. All the necessities, and most of the luxuries, of life flowed into and through it, with many items arriving from Islamic Africa and the Near East. With classic Met largesse, this exhibition suggests the spectacle of two different cultures meeting in one fantastic city, in which commerce and love of beauty, those great levelers, unite them in a fruitful bond. (See above.) (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* the Museum of Modern Art: JEFF WALL, through May 14. This majestic show makes a great case for Mr. Wall as the most complete, if traditional, of the untraditional artists who emerged from the turmoil of Conceptual Art. His often immense color transparencies mounted on light boxes are enthralling visual vehicles, intent on giving pleasure while making a point or two about society, art, history, visual perception, the human animal or all of the above. An imposing blend of painting, street photography and movies, they blur reality and artifice, narrative and form, detail and the big statement. You can't stop looking at them. (212) 708-9400, moma.org. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>Studio Museum in Harlem: 'Philosophy of Time Travel,' through July 1. Many art historians consider Constantin Brancusi's ''Endless Column'' (1938), a 96-foot-tall cast-iron work designed to memorialize Romanian soldiers killed in World War I, the quintessential example of Modernist sculpture. It still stands in Tirgu Jiu, Romania. But a rendition of it is also part of this installation. The work of five artists -- Edgar Arceneaux, Vincent Galen Johnson, Olga Koumoundouros, Rodney McMillian and Matthew Sloly -- it reimagines Brancusi's sculpture. The concept began with a wish to create an installation that would symbolize the clash of African and Western cultures. The result is seven rhomboids, about the same size as the original, which appear to have torn through the gallery's ceiling, splintering the surrounding drywall and smashing into the floor. The collective succeeds in ridding ''Endless Column'' of its Modernist sanctity by turning it into something more akin to a Hollywood blockbuster than a memorial sculpture. 144 West 125th Street, (212) 864-4500. (Bridget L. Goodbody)</p>
        <p>Whitney Museum of American Art: 'Taryn Simon,' through June 24. Ms. Simon couches the show in the intellectual, power-to-the-people oratory of leftist politics, yet she clearly delights in exposing, in a quasi-tabloid fashion, America's underbelly. Though she has also worked in war-torn areas, Ms. Simon is best known for ''The Innocents,'' a series of portraits of men and women who were wrongly convicted but later cleared by DNA test results. Ms. Simon can work as long as a year to gain permission to photograph high-security zones like the government-regulated quarantine sites, nuclear waste storage facilities, prison death rows and C.I.A. offices on view in the show. There are also pictures with lighter themes: the sandpit where the Grucci family tests fireworks, ski slopes being dynamited for avalanche control and the second Death Star, from ''Return of the Jedi,'' at George Lucas's Skywalker Ranch. Ms. Simon is at her artistic best when her delight in the strangeness of American culture shines. (212) 570-3676, whitney.org. (Goodbody)</p>
        <p>* Whitney Museum of American Art: 'Lorna Simpson,' through May 6. This tight, refined and impassioned survey covers more than 20 years of Lorna Simpson's career, from her photo-and-text meditations on race and sexism in the 1980s, to her more recent short films, which unite American history and personal history in forceful and lyrical ways. It would be easy to put some of this work on a shelf as ''identity art,'' but with an African-American woman holding one of the highest offices in the United States government, an African-American man running for president, and the nation embroiled in what some people view as an ethnic war, this art is entirely of the moment. (See above.) (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>DELPHINE COURTILLOT From O. Winston Link to Anna Gaskell and ''The Blair Witch Project,'' there are far too many borrowed bits in these large watercolors based on staged photographs of people in dark, desolate landscapes. But the larger question is why the images wouldn't do just as well in their original photographic form. Tilton Gallery, 8 East 76th Street, (212) 731-2221, through May 5. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>* WALTER DE MARIA Counting and space -- important to both Minimal and Conceptual Art -- come together with unusual clarity, if a bit too much in the way of gleaming metal, in two large installations by the creator of ''The Lightning Field'' earthwork. Both pieces consist of several dozen shiny, meter-long stainless-steel rods presented in spaces that couldn't be much more pristine. Experience the spatial levitation and note the number of sides on the rods; in both cases, they increase row by row. Gagosian Gallery, 522 West 21st Street, (212) 741-1717, and 555 West 24th Street, (212) 741-1111, gagosian.com, through May 5. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Other</p>
        <p>* SOL LEWITT: DRAWING SERIES</p>
        <p>If the greatness of Sol LeWitt, the Minimal-Conceptual artist who died this month (April 7) at 78, has so far escaped you, this exhilarating show of 14 of his mind-teasing, eye-filling wall drawings from the late 1960s and early '70s may do the trick. Selected and arranged by the artist, they proceed in carefully sequenced contrasts and echoes that are both insightful and idiosyncratic. Since their generating instructions are part of their titles, they reduce the creative process to a short, highly visible straight line. But their crisp geometries, accumulating marks and radiating patterns force us to mind the gap between artistic thought and artistic action, to experience the inability of language to account fully for visual outcome. Dia:Beacon, 3 Beekman Street, Beacon, N.Y., (845) 440-0100, through Sept. 10. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>LEE BONTECOU: VACUUM-FORMED SCULPTURES AND RELATED DRAWINGS This artist has never topped her glowering black-and-white canvas reliefs of the 1960s, but these menacing fish and vigilant, thick-stalked flowers from the 1970s are second-best. The flowers, especially, amass some of the armed-and-dangerous sinisterness of the canvas reliefs behind their seemingly beatific auras. Knoedler &amp; Company, 19 East 70th Street, (212) 794-0550; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* 'C.R.E.E.P.' For its second show, this small, new bare-bones Lower East Side storefront gallery is showing work by two collaborative artists called C.R.E.E.P., who multitask as performance artists, magazine publishers, performing artists and clothing designers. One of their two pieces is big, polished and brashly self-announcing. The other is minute, hard to find and terrific. As to 127 itself, all I can say is: watch that space. 127, 127 Henry Street, near Allen Street, (646) 416-1517; closes on Sunday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>'Gifts of the Forest: Native Traditions in Wood and Bark' Drawn from the collections of the Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center in southeastern Connecticut, this show celebrates the trees of the rich forests that once covered the Northeast, yielding essential materials to the Pequot and other Eastern Woodland cultures. The objects run from ancient woodworking tools to contemporary objects that carry on tribal traditions. Many things here were made in the 19th and 20th centuries: handsome woven baskets, decorated cradle boards for carrying babies, and an elegant birch-bark hamper whose sides bear a stylized tree motif. UBS Art Gallery, 1285 Avenue of the Americas, between 51st and 52nd Streets, (212) 713-2885, ubs.com; closes today. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* Kim Gordon and Jutta Koether: 'Dead already' Two artist-musicians collaborate on a show that's partly objects, partly performance and partly in the air. The objects are paintings displayed in flip-through racks. (The ones with glitter are Ms. Gordon's; the ones done in black liquid glass, Ms. Koether's). The center of the gallery is fenced off for action: Ei Arakawa and Eleanor Erdman will do a Martha Graham piece this Sunday, bound to be memorable. Reena Spaulings Fine Art, 165 East Broadway, at Rutgers Street, Lower East Side, (212) 477-5006; closes on Sunday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL CENTER OF PHOTOGRAPHY: 'HENRI CARTIER-BRESSON'S SCRAPBOOK: PHOTOGRAPHS, 1932-46,' This show has more than 300 of the prints the photographer glued into an album and toted to New York for curators at the Museum of Modern Art to cull. Captured by the Nazis, he had been presumed dead when the Modern planned his retrospective. Then he turned up alive -- the ''posthumous'' exhibition opened, with him in attendance, in 1947. The current exhibition surveys the revolutionary work Carier-Bresson shot in Spain, Italy, Mexico, Britain and France. Here are the familiar and, more interestingly, some less familiar, shots of crowds in Hyde Park in London at George VI's coronation, of picnickers on the banks of the Marne in France and whores in Valencia, Spain. His taste for uncanny detail linked him to Surrealism and Surrealist wit, but unlike many Surrealists, he remained committed to human values. Boys mug at his camera. Prostitutes swan. Their gazes equalize them with us. 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000, icp.org; closes on Sunday. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL CENTER OF PHOTOGRAPHY: 'MARTIN MUNKACSI: THINK WHILE YOU SHOOT!' Munkacsi, who inspired Cartier-Bresson, was, by contrast, self-taught, a creature of his own devising. This is the most complete retrospective, with a thick catalog (not too well researched) and dozens of vintage prints from the 1920s through the early '60s. He favored scenes of daily life, absorbing avant-garde ideas about odd angles and abstract compositions. In 1928 he moved to Berlin, where the opportunities were better, and traveled the world on assignment to Brazil, Algeria and Egypt. Munkacsi was a stylist, and he made catchy images the only way he knew how, in a modernist mode, which, being an opportunistic form, could serve any master. He became a celebrity in America. He photographed Fred Astaire dancing and Joan Crawford poolside. In the breezy layouts of Harper's Bazaar, the work looked brilliant. (See above.) Closes on Sunday. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* 'THOMAS STRUTH: Making Time' Through the 1990s, the German photographer Thomas Struth became an art-world celebrity for his outsize, absorbing portraits of crowds interacting with artwork in the world's great museums. As a follow-up, he is presenting the American premiere of two new series of pictures of audiences beholding single masterpieces in the Museo Nacional del Prado in Madrid, and the State Hermitage Museum in St. Petersburg, Russia. The show, which cannily allows us to look safely at others looking at art, is one of the most visually sumptuous and thought-probing in the city. Marian Goodman Gallery, 24 West 57th Street, (212) 977-7160, mariangoodman.com; closes tomorrow. (Benjamin Genocchio)</p>
        <p>JAMES TURRELL: 'LIGHT LEADINGS' From an artist known for meditative light installations, a show of sped-up versions made with computerized neon and holographic works reminiscent of Malevich abstractions. They amount to gorgeous, high-priced, high-tech equivalents of lava lamps, in which color comes either in diaphanous clouds or with hard edges. PaceWildenstein Gallery, 534 West 25th Street, Chelsea, (212) 929-7000, pacewildenstein.com; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
