<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where No-Frills Fast Food (the Real Thing) Was Born</title>
    <meta content="27trip" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/travel/escapes/27trip_ready.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843131"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DAY TRIP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diners (Eating Places)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Providence (Ri)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Keller, Joel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Rhode Island/Providence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Rhode Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Providence (RI)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E6D8153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1358" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where No-Frills Fast Food (the Real Thing) Was Born</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Where No-Frills Fast Food (the Real Thing) Was Born</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOEL KELLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Keller, Joel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on day-trip to Providence, RI, and its surroundings, where 'rail car' style diner was born; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW JERSEY may be the diner capital of the world, but Rhode Island is the diner's birthplace.</p>
        <p>The Naugahyde and Formica restaurants that sizzle with breakfast all day long, and where the waitresses call you ''Hon,'' had their start in Providence more than 130 years ago. Because of Rhode Island's diner heritage, as well as its large working-class population, an estimated 75 to 80 diners and lunch counters still dot the tiny state. A dozen of them are in the ''rail car'' style, where customers get two choices of seating: if the line of booths along the windows is full, they can plop themselves on a stool at the counter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For those obsessed with the history and design of diners, Providence, R.I., and its neighbors are dream destinations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW JERSEY may be the diner capital of the world, but Rhode Island is the diner's birthplace.</p>
        <p>The Naugahyde and Formica restaurants that sizzle with breakfast all day long, and where the waitresses call you ''Hon,'' had their start in Providence more than 130 years ago. Because of Rhode Island's diner heritage, as well as its large working-class population, an estimated 75 to 80 diners and lunch counters still dot the tiny state. A dozen of them are in the ''rail car'' style, where customers get two choices of seating: if the line of booths along the windows is full, they can plop themselves on a stool at the counter.</p>
        <p>For those obsessed with the history and design of diners, Providence -- with a handful of them in and around the city -- and its neighbors are a dream destination. The city's riverfront, revitalized downtown and Colonial-era houses are also significant draws.</p>
        <p>For a main course of diner history, the first place a dinerphile should go -- after a hearty breakfast, of course -- is the Culinary Archives and Museum at the Harborside campus of Johnson &amp; Wales University, which has a school of culinary arts. The museum has 25,000 square feet of exhibition space in a converted warehouse. Visitors immediately come face to face with a stainless steel-and-neon entrance. Stepping through that threshold brings them to a large diner exhibition that takes the viewer through the history of diner style, from its humble beginnings in Providence to the sprawling retro restaurants that have opened nationwide in the last 20 years.</p>
        <p>Much of the collection, from photos and menus to stools and floor tile, is on loan from Richard J. S. Gutman, who has been acquiring diner memorabilia since 1970, when he was an architecture student at Cornell University. Johnson &amp; Wales asked Mr. Gutman, who has written four books on diners, to serve as guest curator for the exhibit, which opened in 2002; three years later, the university asked Mr. Gutman to become the museum's curator.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gutman can regale you with tales of diner history, starting in 1872 when Walter Scott parked a converted horse wagon outside various industrial locations in Providence, waiting for shift workers to leave for the day. Ask him what the closest existing relative to those first movable trailers is, and he doesn't hesitate to point you to Haven Brothers, a hot dog stand housed in a trailer parked downtown that has been in the Haven family since the 1890s.</p>
        <p>Why did Mr. Gutman, 57, devote his adult life to diners? ''I guess I was fortunate to be one of the first people to say, 'Hey! This is Americana.' This is part of what makes us a little bit different from other places around the world. This is our version of a pub or a bistro.''</p>
        <p>He spoke over breakfast at the Seaplane Diner, a 1950 Jerry O'Mahony model that sits about a mile and a half north of Johnson &amp; Wales, in an area of Providence that's still industrial. Blue-and-yellow Formica booths face the counter. It's not as polished as other diners, but the Seaplane makes a good breakfast: three eggs with linguiça, a spicy Portuguese sausage, is $5.75.</p>
        <p>The diner exhibit at the university includes a full soda fountain, along with a vintage Worcester Lunch Car Company model, on display but in the process of restoration, that last served as the Ever Ready Diner in Providence.</p>
        <p>Ask Mr. Gutman what diner to go to after touring the museum, and the first words out of his mouth will very likely be ''the Modern Diner'' in Pawtucket, an industrial suburb north of Providence. The Modern is hard to miss. Just look for the maroon-and-tan dining car that has a large neon sign perched on top. If it's the weekend, there will also be a long line snaking out the door. The diner, a Sterling Streamliner, has been a town staple since 1941, when it first sat in downtown Pawtucket.</p>
        <p>The Modern was rundown when Nick Demou, 50, with his father, Arthur, bought it in 1986 (his current partner is Frank Aguiar, 44). The town allowed Mr. Demou to move it to its current location, on a main street, soon after. ''We had regular house movers actually move it,'' said Mr. Demou, a graduate of Johnson &amp; Wales. ''And in the midst of the move all the tiles just came crumbling down. We put everything back together, and then we rechromed all the stools. The Naugahyde was all replaced.''</p>
        <p>Many people waiting in line could sit in a second dining room in a building attached to the diner, but they'd rather wait for a seat in the Streamliner. The Modern is literally a landmark; in 1978, it became the first diner to be registered in the National Register of Historic Places. Its classic details include dark wood trim and chrome backsplashes behind the counter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Demou tends to go beyond standard breakfast and lunch fare; in fact, he encourages customers to order from the specials menu -- laminated signs posted by the door each day. On weekends, the signs stretch floor to ceiling, listing combinations like crème brûlée oatmeal ($5.95) and lobster cheese grits ($9.95). Two of the most popular dishes are custard French toast ($7.25) and cranberry-almond pancakes ($6.95).</p>
        <p>Mr. Demou loves seeing the weekend crowds. ''The hot restaurants,'' he said, referring to Providence, ''they're not hot for that long. I've been hot for 21 years.''</p>
        <p>Another of Mr. Gutman's favorites is Jigger's Diner, which is in East Greenwich, about 15 miles south of Providence. It is a 1950 Worcester Lunch Car, wedged into a strip of boutiques, restaurants and local stores on Main Street. An ''Eat Here'' sign dangles below a carved sign that depicts an inviting breakfast. The highlight of the interior is the mahogany trim that runs not only the length of the diner's windowed side, but also along the ceiling. The booths are built of the same wood, complete with slotted benches and ornate coat hooks.</p>
        <p>THE diner has been around since Vilgot Lindbergh, known as Jigger, opened for business in 1917. Iva Reynhout, 39, who also trained at Johnson &amp; Wales, bought the diner in 2000 from Carol Shriner, a farmer who had returned the building to its original style in the 1990s. Ms. Reynhout's training is evident in Jigger's signature breakfasts. It is one of the few places in Rhode Island that serves johnnycakes, a simple combination of cornmeal, water and sugar about the size of a hockey puck (three for $2.25). The diner also makes its own sausages and hash, and has a tasty ''Vermontichristo'' ($4.85), made with Vermont cheddar cheese.</p>
        <p>Ms. Reynhout says she's in it for the long haul or, at least until one certain day arrives. ''I hope I can do it until the business is 100 years old,'' she said.</p>
        <p>COZY BOOTHS, SNAPPY SERVICE</p>
        <p>What'll You Have, Hon?</p>
        <p>PROVIDENCE is about three hours north and east of New York City. Take Interstate 95 to Exit 22A for downtown Providence. There is also an Amtrak station there, but you will need a rental car to get around. Arrive early enough in the day, and you can eat both breakfast and lunch at diners in and around Providence.</p>
        <p>The Culinary Archives and Museum at the Harborside campus of Johnson &amp; Wales University (315 Harborside Boulevard, 401-598-2805; www.culinary.org) is open from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Tuesday through Sunday. Admission is $7 for adults, less for seniors, children and students. Besides the diner exhibition, there are antique cookbooks, vintage stoves and a tavern re-creation.</p>
        <p>The Seaplane Diner (307 Allens Avenue, 401-941-9547) is open 5 a.m. to 3 p.m. Monday through Friday, and 7 a.m. to 1 p.m. Saturdays and Sundays.</p>
        <p>The Modern Diner (364 East Avenue, Pawtucket, 401-726-8390) is open 6 a.m. to 2 p.m. Monday through Saturday, and 7 a.m. to 2 p.m. Sundays.</p>
        <p>Jigger's Diner (145 Main Street, East Greenwich, 401-884-5388) is open 6 a.m. to 2 p.m. Monday through Saturday, and 6 a.m. to 1 p.m. Sundays; it is also open for dinner from 5 to 8 p.m. Fridays.</p>
        <p>DAY TRIP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
