<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Echoes of Terror Case Haunt California Pakistanis</title>
    <meta content="27lodi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/us/27lodi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070430T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843221"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pakistani-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lodi (Calif)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pakistan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Macfarquhar, Neil</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hayat, Umer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hayat, Hamid</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E6DE123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1249" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Echoes of Terror Case Haunt California Pakistanis</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Echoes of Terror Case Haunt California Pakistanis</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL MACFARQUHAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Macfarquhar, Neil</byline>
      <dateline>LODI, Calif., April 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pakistani community in Lodi, Calif, remains enveloped in fear that began when Umer Hayat and son Hamid were arrested on terrorism charges in 2005; son was convicted for attending training camp in Pakistan; fellow Pakistanis now distrust each other almost as much as they do outsiders, fearing informers and anything connected to government, including social service agencies; Umer Hayat was sentenced to time served for lying about money taken out of US, but not for terrorism; case against son stems from his confessions and FBI informant; other Pakistanis do not believe either was guilty, but still feel fearful and isolated; rural peasants started coming to Lodi as farm workers around 1920 and never really assimilated, preserving traditional ways through arranged marriages in Pakistan; 80 percent of town's 2,500 Muslims are Pakistanis; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Khalid Farooq has shunned the low-slung yellow bungalow that serves as the Pakistani community's mosque here for nearly two years, ever since a father and son who worshiped there were arrested on suspicion of being foot soldiers for Al Qaeda.</p>
        <p>If he runs an errand at someplace like Wal-Mart, away from the neat, tree-lined streets that constitute the heart of Lodi's Pakistani neighborhood, Mr. Farooq trades his traditional baggy clothes for standard American attire, he said, as often as four times in one day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Pakistani community in Lodi, Calif., was traumatized after the arrest of a father and son accused of terrorism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Khalid Farooq has shunned the low-slung yellow bungalow that serves as the Pakistani community's mosque here for nearly two years, ever since a father and son who worshiped there were arrested on suspicion of being foot soldiers for Al Qaeda.</p>
        <p>If he runs an errand at someplace like Wal-Mart, away from the neat, tree-lined streets that constitute the heart of Lodi's Pakistani neighborhood, Mr. Farooq trades his traditional baggy clothes for standard American attire, he said, as often as four times in one day.</p>
        <p>''Something has changed in the air; it's a scary time,'' said Mr. Farooq, who first arrived to work in the flat, black fields that surround this town 25 years ago. ''We don't want to talk; we're all afraid.''</p>
        <p>The tide of fear rolled in and has never quite receded after an informant incriminated two Lodi men, Umer Hayat, an ice cream truck driver, and his son Hamid, who were arrested in June 2005. Their trial ended a year ago with the younger Mr. Hayat, 24, convicted of providing material support for terrorism by attending a training camp in Pakistan. His lawyers recently began seeking a new trial based on arguments that the jury was tainted.</p>
        <p>Members of the Pakistani community here distrust one another almost as much as they do outsiders. Even now, residents with evidence of sudden wealth, like a new car, are immediately rumored to be on the F.B.I.'s payroll. Anything connected to the government is inherently suspect.</p>
        <p>Some people have stopped home visits by social service agencies; others have balked at writing their Social Security numbers on government documents. Some residents returning from Pakistan avoid including their Lodi addresses on their United States customs forms.</p>
        <p>''You don't use the word 'terrorist'; you don't use the word 'bomb,' because people's ears are up instantly,'' said Taj Khan, a retired engineer and an unsuccessful candidate for the Lodi City Council. ''People are looking at each other with suspicion to see who is the F.B.I. informant, who will rat on whom?''</p>
        <p>All terrorism charges were dropped against Umer Hayat, 48, who was sentenced to time served after pleading guilty to lying about the amount of money he took out of the country.</p>
        <p>The case against Hamid Hayat was built around his confessions as well as testimony from the informant, who was paid about $225,000 after telling the Federal Bureau of Investigation the somewhat improbable story that Osama bin Laden's deputy, Ayman al-Zawahri, once visited the Lodi mosque.</p>
        <p>Nobody in the Pakistani community here seems to believe that the Hayats, both American citizens, were guilty of anything beyond bad judgment. Even the prosecutor in the case, McGregor W. Scott, the United States attorney for the Eastern District of California, while endorsing the conviction, has expressed regret about using the Qaeda label.</p>
        <p>But that hardly dilutes the sense of fear and isolation. Lodi, a city of 62,000 people 72 miles east of San Francisco, is something of an anomaly among Pakistani immigrants. Most come to the United States to pursue professional careers, to become doctors or academics in large cities. But mainly rural peasants started coming to Lodi around 1920, and residents say 80 percent of the town's 2,500 Muslims are Pakistanis.</p>
        <p>They came as agricultural laborers and never really assimilated, preserving their traditional ways by dispatching the young back home for arranged marriages.</p>
        <p>''Our parents get us married too quick. You get married and you don't go to school and you don't learn anything,'' said Usama Ismail, the younger Mr. Hayat's 21-year-old cousin, who sometimes stumbles over words as he translates street slang into regular English. ''If you have a son or a daughter who gets engaged back in Pakistan, at least one parent is going to be illiterate, and if the man is illiterate, he will definitely kick it with the people from back home.''</p>
        <p>Robina Asghar was a teenage bride who sometimes waxes nostalgic about the smell of the orange groves in her native village. But she earned college degrees here and became an accomplished social worker.</p>
        <p>''We are so fearful about preserving the culture that we don't build the bridges to learn how to survive in the larger community,'' Mrs. Asghar said. ''We isolated ourselves.''</p>
        <p>One of the strongest elements in that culture is that men and women do not mingle in public. Many Pakistani girls in Lodi are taken out of the school system and taught at home once they reach puberty, school officials said. There are no Pakistani restaurants and just two shops, one selling fabric and the other a grocery specializing in items like the half-white, half-wheat flour needed to make naan bread.</p>
        <p>Razia Farooq, Mr. Farooq's wife, sells gauzy bolts of fabric in pink and tangerine and lavender. The small-town banter from other Lodi residents evaporated after the arrests, Mrs. Farooq said, with any woman walking on the street in her traditional clothes likely to hear ''Why don't you go back to your own country!'' shouted with expletives from a passing car.</p>
        <p>Her store is unmarked, and after the arrests she installed blinds because customers worried that anyone passing might notice Pakistanis and do something violent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ismail said that people shushed him when he mentioned the Hayats on the telephone, and that high school students grew instantly leery of anyone asking questions.</p>
        <p>''If somebody asks something personal like how many kids in your family, they will shut up and walk away,'' he said.</p>
        <p>It is a form of paranoia to point fingers at everyone, Mr. Ismail admitted, but his cousin's fate is the dire model. ''My cousin is locked up because of what he said, not because of what he did, so that is going through their heads,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Among high school students, two reactions to what happened to the Hayats predominated. First, Mr. Ismail said, it engendered a certain sense of pride and solidarity.</p>
        <p>''The feds came over here and they went after little kids, teenagers,'' he said. ''At most the kids might have been pot heads or thieves, but they were trying to label them as terrorists and they were following all of us around.''</p>
        <p>On the other hand, verbal harassment also spawned a gang, the O.P.C., or Original Pakistani Clique, whose members take on any student who calls a Pakistani a terrorist in the hallways of Lodi High.</p>
        <p>The tension builds upon an already deep split over control of the mosque; indeed, many suspect that one faction may have brought in the F.B.I. to smear its rivals. Two imams imported from Pakistan, the initial targets of the federal investigation involving the Hayats, were expelled on immigration charges. One faction accused them of developing a school and Islamic center that would teach radical Islam. The other faction believes that the group controlling the mosque was jealous of the budding center, so its members concocted the story and might similarly denounce others.</p>
        <p>''That's a bunch of baloney,'' said Nick Qayyum, the mosque's secretary. ''People are using this for their own purposes.''</p>
        <p>The ruckus at the mosque every Friday prompted scores of worshipers to defect some months back, and they now hold congregational prayers in a church. Umer Hayat is among them.</p>
        <p>Others are moving away altogether, viewing the prospect of life with relatives in North Carolina or Texas as better than being stained by what they call Lodi's undeserved reputation.</p>
        <p>''Once your name is out there, I don't know how that will ever go away,'' said Shakila Khan, who runs social programs here.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 30, 2007, Monday  A picture caption Friday with a front-page article about fear among Pakistanis in Lodi, Calif., after the arrest last year of two local men on terrorism charges misstated the name of a boy pictured with Raheela Hayat, whose brother, Hamid Hayat, was found guilty in the case. He is Jalal Hashim Usman, not Hamid. In some copies, the caption misstated the boy's relationship to Hamid Hayat. He is his nephew, not his son.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 30, 2007, Monday</p>
        <p>A picture caption Friday with a front-page article about fear among Pakistanis in Lodi, Calif., after the arrest last year of two local men on terrorism charges misstated the name of a boy pictured with Raheela Hayat, whose brother, Hamid Hayat, was found guilty in the case. He is Jalal Hashim Usman, not Hamid. In some copies, the caption misstated the boy's relationship to Hamid Hayat. He is his nephew, not his son.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
