<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Digging for Clams and Difficult Answers</title>
    <meta content="27digg" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/movies/27digg.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843125"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dieckmann, Katherine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rudd, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hamilton, Josh</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eldard, Ron</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marino, Ken</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Diggers (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Dieckmann, Katherine</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rudd, Paul</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Ambrose, Lauren</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Eldard, Ron</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Tierney, Maura</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Paulson, Sarah</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Diggers (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EED9153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="697" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Digging for Clams and Difficult Answers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Digging for Clams and Difficult Answers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews film Diggers, directed by Katherine Dieckmann; Paul Rudd, Josh Hamilton, Ken Marino and Ron Eldard star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A character reads ''The Hite Report.'' A newspaper headline blares ''Jimmy Carter Charts New Vision.'' The Blues Image hit ''Ride Captain Ride'' sounds like a muffled foghorn in the humid air. This is the world of ''Diggers,'' a group portrait of four guys in their 30s who work as clam diggers trolling the waters off the South Shore of Long Island. Their livelihood is imperiled when big business moves in and buys up the rights to the most productive areas.</p>
        <p>This minutely observed period piece, set in 1976, has the brave, mournful tone of a Bruce Springsteen song (''My Hometown,'' say) set in Billy Joel territory. Directed by Katherine Dieckmann from a screenplay by Ken Marino, who plays one of the principal characters, the film makes you contemplate the passage of time. When was it exactly that the recent past slipped into the more distant past and began to seem so poignantly out of reach? When did everything change?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This minutely observed period piece, set in 1976, has the brave, mournful tone of a Bruce Springsteen song set in Billy Joel territory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A character reads ''The Hite Report.'' A newspaper headline blares ''Jimmy Carter Charts New Vision.'' The Blues Image hit ''Ride Captain Ride'' sounds like a muffled foghorn in the humid air. This is the world of ''Diggers,'' a group portrait of four guys in their 30s who work as clam diggers trolling the waters off the South Shore of Long Island. Their livelihood is imperiled when big business moves in and buys up the rights to the most productive areas.</p>
        <p>This minutely observed period piece, set in 1976, has the brave, mournful tone of a Bruce Springsteen song (''My Hometown,'' say) set in Billy Joel territory. Directed by Katherine Dieckmann from a screenplay by Ken Marino, who plays one of the principal characters, the film makes you contemplate the passage of time. When was it exactly that the recent past slipped into the more distant past and began to seem so poignantly out of reach? When did everything change?</p>
        <p>''Diggers'' fulfills the promise shown by Ms. Dieckmann's 2000 directorial debut, ''A Good Baby,'' a Southern gothic-flavored tale about an abandoned infant discovered in the woods of North Carolina. Meticulously assembled, ''Diggers'' shuttles among several major characters with an ease and grace that don't waste a moment of screen time. But it doesn't feel rushed.</p>
        <p>It also demonstrates that a solid formula, no matter how frequently followed, can be refreshed if it is handled with affectionate care. From ''I Vitelloni'' to ''Diner'' to ''The Groomsmen,'' a group of aging boys clinging together as the scary future threatens their solidarity is a natural movie subject. And ''Diggers'' works that formula with such confidence and knowledge of its particular environment that you hardly notice the craft behind it.</p>
        <p>If the four friends and the women in their lives make up a stereotypical cross-section of thirtysomethings, the seamless ensemble acting and the way the screenplay captures the deeper realities bared in offhanded conversation make the characters seem alive and spontaneous.</p>
        <p>The center of the group, Hunt (Paul Rudd), is a discontented clam digger who arrives late for work one day and discovers that his father has died alone of heart failure in his rotten old tub of a boat. Guilt-stricken, Hunt is suddenly forced to face a future in which the business his family has carried on for generations may vanish. He's also an amateur photographer with vague artistic aspirations, and he strikes up a silent flirtation with Zoey (Lauren Ambrose), a haughty young Manhattan woman visiting her uncle, when his boat drifts past while she is reading on the shore. Later they begin an affair, which Hunt takes much too seriously.</p>
        <p>Cons (Josh Hamilton), the group's spaced-out hippie and part-time drug dealer, is a motormouthed intellectual showoff; he spouts theories about this and that with the zeal of a brainy crank who isn't quite as knowledgeable as he thinks he is. Jack (Ron Eldard), the hunky local Lothario, buzzes from woman to woman, including Hunt's divorced older sister, Gina (Maura Tierney), of whom Hunt is fiercely overprotective.</p>
        <p>The most fully realized and saddest of the four, Lozo (Mr. Marino), is a hothead who has fathered five children with his wife, Julie (Sarah Paulson). As he faces the crumbling of his livelihood with kids tugging at him day and night, you tremble for him. Will he snap?</p>
        <p>These diggers' lives are punctuated by small melodramas that force them to confront uncomfortable truths about their relationships, their work and the uncertain future. A quintessential American independent movie, ''Diggers'' isn't going to change the history of cinema. But it has integrity. It feels like life.</p>
        <p>''Diggers'' is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has sexual situations and some profanity.</p>
        <p>Diggers  Opens today nationwide.</p>
        <p>Directed by Katherine Dieckmann; written by Ken Marino; director of photography, Michael McDonough; edited by Malcolm Jamieson and Sabine Hoffman; production designer, Roshelle Berliner; produced by Anne Chaisson, Jason Kliot, Joana Vicente and Mr. Marino; released by Magnolia Pictures. Running time: 90 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Paul Rudd (Hunt), Lauren Ambrose (Zoey), Ron Eldard (Jack), Josh Hamilton (Cons), Sarah Paulson (Julie), Ken Marino (Frankie Lozo) and Maura Tierney (Gina).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
