<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LIVING HERE | Solar-Powered Houses; Energy Independence</title>
    <meta content="27live" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843166"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Taos (Nm)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">kipnis, deahni</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gunderson, Amy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Havens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Living Here</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions/Western States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Mexico/Taos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04EED8153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="912" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LIVING HERE | Solar-Powered Houses; Energy Independence</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">As told to Amy Gunderson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gunderson, Amy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Deahni Kipnis comments on her solar-powered house in Taos, NM; photos and brief descriptions of similar properties for sale around country (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHO -- Deahni Kipnis, 47, owner of a skin-care salon  WHAT -- 2-bedroom house  WHERE -- Taos, N.M.</p>
        <p>Taos is truly a solar capital and is very much into sustainable living. Even our local radio station is solar powered. This house isn't off the grid, but when I converted it to solar power, I effectively removed it from dependence on the local utility. I invested $50,000 in the project and took out a second mortgage to do it, but I didn't go solar expecting that I would ever recoup all of the costs. It was driven more by who I am and how I want to represent myself. That said, I do save $1,500 to $2,000 a year on electricity and propane bills.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHO -- Deahni Kipnis, 47, owner of a skin-care salon  WHAT -- 2-bedroom house  WHERE -- Taos, N.M.</p>
        <p>Taos is truly a solar capital and is very much into sustainable living. Even our local radio station is solar powered. This house isn't off the grid, but when I converted it to solar power, I effectively removed it from dependence on the local utility. I invested $50,000 in the project and took out a second mortgage to do it, but I didn't go solar expecting that I would ever recoup all of the costs. It was driven more by who I am and how I want to represent myself. That said, I do save $1,500 to $2,000 a year on electricity and propane bills.</p>
        <p>The radiant floor heating, water heater and the lights are all solar powered. I installed 16 solar photovoltaic panels that actually move with the sun during the day, and they produce about 30 percent more energy than panels that don't follow the sun. The energy is stored in a system of 24 batteries that provide power when the sun is down. I also have propane backup. There are seven panels to heat water and the floors and also a windmill that generates electricity. The only thing that is on the grid is the hot tub.</p>
        <p>I have two homes here, and this one is much larger than my primary residence. This house, which I call Casa Serena, is used as a vacation rental, for entertaining and as a place for friends and family to stay when visiting. My mother just stayed here for a week. There are tricks to living in a solar home that one eventually learns, such as not to run the television, appliances and blow dryer all at once. Even with the quirks, I fondly remember my first day on solar power. I literally felt the energy in the house change.</p>
        <p>As told to Amy Gunderson</p>
        <p>Information on properties was supplied by the listing companies.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Prescott, Ariz.  WHAT -- 2-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $595,000</p>
        <p>This 1,610-square-foot cedar-sided house was built in 1992 and has a solar panel system that collects and stores energy in batteries on the property. It also has a propane backup generator. The house, which has expansive views of Williamson Valley, is on nearly 10.5 acres. There are two bathrooms, a wood-burning stove, an office that could be used as a third bedroom, a fireplace, ceiling fans and raised garden beds. Prescott is two hours north of Phoenix. Agent: Susan Bailey, Realty Executives Prescott, (928) 899-0969; www.suzinow.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- South Lake Tahoe, Calif.  WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $1,105,000</p>
        <p>This newly built solar-paneled house is on the grid and receives credit back from the local utility for the excess power it generates. The house is 3,364 square feet has a two-car garage, two decks and granite kitchen counters. There are three bathrooms and a hot tub with mountain views. Agents: Jacke Crump and Cheryl Murakami, ReMax Realty Today, (530) 577-4048; blitzen.tahoehomeonline.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Weston, Colo.  WHAT -- 2-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $350,000</p>
        <p>Built in 2003, this 2,000-square-foot house is off the grid in a development in a juniper and pine forest. The house has 12 photovoltaic panels that can be moved into different positions to increase efficiency. The house, which has straw-bale walls, has two bathrooms and a detached garage with heating powered by its own solar panel. The property is 40 acres; the house is offered furnished. Weston is about 150 miles south of Colorado Springs. Agent: John Janus, Telluride Realty &amp; Investment, (970) 728-3205; www.janusrealestate.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Key Largo, Fla.  WHAT -- 3-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $3.5 million</p>
        <p>This waterfront house has a solar-powered electric system that gets credit from the local utility for power not used by the house. It also has a 7,500-gallon rainwater cistern. The house is 2,450 square feet and has three bathrooms, bamboo floors and two levels of wraparound balconies that look out toward a sandy beach and a deep-water dock. The property is one acre in a gated community. Key Largo is about 50 miles south of Miami. Agent: Sharon Nyman, Century 21 Prestige Realty Group, (305) 942-6886; www.sharonnyman.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Taos, N.M.  WHAT -- 1-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $369,000</p>
        <p>This off-the-grid house, 25 miles north of the center of Taos, is on 35 acres and has photovoltaic panels that track the movement of the sun. Water is provided by a catchment system on the roof that feeds a 1,200-gallon underground cistern. This house is 884 square feet and has one bathroom and a flagstone patio. The property includes a building site for a larger home and is adjacent to 120 acres of conservation land. Brokers: James Cox and Paula West, Taos Valley Real Estate, (505) 751-1898; www.taosvalleyrealestate.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Randolph Center, Vt.  WHAT -- 3-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $895,000</p>
        <p>This 4,500-square-foot house is off the grid on 15 acres of property. In addition to the solar panels there is a backup propane generator. The house, which was finished at the end of last year, has two and a half bathrooms and a two-car garage. There is a separate one-bedroom apartment with one bathroom. The property also has a small swimming pond and a brook. Agent: Brooks Barron, Vermont Country Properties Sotheby's International Realty, (802) 767-3398; www.vermontcountryproperties.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
