<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Commander Says Fall Pullback in Iraq Would Lead to More Sectarian Killings</title>
    <meta content="27military" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843211"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE REACH OF WAR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Petraeus, David H (Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maliki, Nuri Kamal Al- (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cloud, David S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gordon, Michael R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E1DF123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="909" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Commander Says Fall Pullback in Iraq Would Lead to More Sectarian Killings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID S. CLOUD and MICHAEL R. GORDON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cloud, David S; Gordon, Michael R</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US commander in Iraq Gen David Petraeus says at Pentagon news conference that troop pullback this fall, as called for in Senate's spending bill, would lead to escalation in sectarian killings and worsening violence; does not address political debate but suggests risk in pulling back before end of year; reportedly tells lawmakers of numerous obstacles to stabilization and says Prime Min Nuri al-Maliki lacks power to push through conciliatory measures and key law on sharing oil revenue (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The top military commander in Iraq, Gen. David H. Petraeus, warned Thursday that an American troop pullback this fall would lead to an escalation in sectarian killings and worsening violence.</p>
        <p>''My sense is that there would be an increase in sectarian violence, a resumption of sectarian violence, were the presence of our forces and Iraqi forces at that time to be reduced,'' General Petraeus said at a Pentagon news conference.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The top military commander in Iraq, Gen. David H. Petraeus, warned Thursday that an American troop pullback this fall would lead to an escalation in sectarian killings and worsening violence.</p>
        <p>''My sense is that there would be an increase in sectarian violence, a resumption of sectarian violence, were the presence of our forces and Iraqi forces at that time to be reduced,'' General Petraeus said at a Pentagon news conference.</p>
        <p>His comments came just hours before the Senate approved a plan calling for beginning troop reductions in October at the latest, a measure that President Bush has pledged to veto. The House passed the plan on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The administration has put forward General Petraeus, who took up his command in January and was a principal architect of the new American military approach in Iraq, at the peak of the clash between Congress and the president over Iraq, in part because he is highly regarded by many in Congress.</p>
        <p>Although General Petraeus did not address the political debate over a withdrawal deadline in his briefing or in a later interview, he suggested there would be risks to beginning a troop pullout before the end of the year.</p>
        <p>In his comments on Thursday, as well as in private briefings to lawmakers a day earlier, according to one lawmaker who was involved, he talked about numerous obstacles to stabilizing the country, including evidence of new assistance going to Al Qaeda of Mesopotamia from outside Iraq and what he called ''exceedingly unhelpful activities'' by Iranian-backed Shiite militants.</p>
        <p>American forces, he said, found evidence of this in a 22-page document on a computer seized during a raid last month that outlined details of a Jan. 20 attack on the provincial headquarters in Karbala in which five American soldiers were abducted and killed.</p>
        <p>General Petraeus also said that Prime Minister Nuri Kamal al-Maliki of Iraq lacked enough power to single-handedly push through measures sought by the United States that were aimed at easing tensions between Shiite and Sunni Arabs. In order to have any hope of results, the general said, pressure would be needed on factional leaders in the government and Parliament.</p>
        <p>Though some Democrats in Congress have insisted in recent days that Iraq had grown so unstable that an American pullback would not greatly worsen the situation, General Petraeus disagreed.</p>
        <p>''It can get much, much worse,'' he said. ''Right now it's a good bit better, but again I am not trying in any way, shape or form to indicate that this is a satisfactory situation whatsoever.''</p>
        <p>American officials, along with moderate Iraqi politicians, have said that the key to peace in Iraq and ultimately to an American withdrawal is power-sharing between Shiites, Sunni Arabs and Kurds. They are pressing Mr. Maliki and the Iraqi Parliament to remain in session this summer until the passage of legislation on sharing oil revenues, easing the purges of former Baath Party members from government positions and setting a date for provincial elections.</p>
        <p>General Petraeus said he considered passage of the oil law, which would distribute revenues from oil production among Iraq's regions, a priority among the so-called benchmark items that the Americans would like to see become law.</p>
        <p>''The hydrocarbon law is of enormous importance, and I think it is reasonably doable as well,'' General Petraeus said in the interview.</p>
        <p>Another law that has been bogged down in the Baghdad Parliament would rewrite rules on de-Baathification, the policy that makes it hard for former members of Saddam Hussein's Baath Party, mostly Sunnis, to play roles in the government.</p>
        <p>General Petraeus said he and the American ambassador to Iraq, Ryan C. Crocker, intended to stick by a vow to offer the White House and the Pentagon an assessment of the progress of the new strategy by early September. And he signaled that he hoped for political progress in Iraq, not just military improvements.</p>
        <p>''We'll have seen whether in fact our efforts in these areas have helped produce the kind of progress that they are designed in fact to produce,'' he said. ''One would certainly hope that the Iraqi legislators would match that with their own hard work. That's our expectation.''</p>
        <p>On the security issues, he cited progress in fielding more Iraqi forces, but called it a ''work in progress.''</p>
        <p>He said that sectarian killings had declined two-thirds from their level in January, in part because of construction of walls around some neighborhoods that had allowed security forces to maintain control of areas as they were cleared.</p>
        <p>But he conceded that the overall violence had not subsided, and he warned that large-scale attacks using car bombs against markets and other locations filled with civilians could still occur and set off more Sunni and Shiite revenge killings.</p>
        <p>Also worrisome, he said, was the continued evidence that Iran was providing support to Shiite militants.</p>
        <p>Citing the computer document American troops seized in the Karbala raid last month, he said that while there was no direct evidence that Iranians were involved specifically in the killing of the five American soldiers there, the document appeared to be a record of attacks by a militant cell that it intended to hand over to the Iranian Revolutionary Guard.</p>
        <p>''There are numerous documents which detailed a number of different attacks on coalition forces, and our sense is that these records were kept so they could be handed in to whoever it is who is financing them,'' General Petraeus said.</p>
        <p>THE REACH OF WAR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
