<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Strong Quarter at Microsoft, and an Upbeat '08 Outlook, Bring Wall St. a Sigh of Relief</title>
    <meta content="27soft" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/technology/27soft.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843185"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Microsoft Corp</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D6153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Strong Quarter at Microsoft, and an Upbeat '08 Outlook, Bring Wall St. a Sigh of Relief</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Strong Quarter at Microsoft, and an Upbeat ’08 Outlook, Bring Wall St. a Sigh of Relief</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE LOHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lohr, Steve</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Microsoft reported quarterly sales and profits that surpassed Wall Street's expectations yesterday, suggesting that early sales of its new Windows Vista operating system were off to a solid start.</p>
        <p>The company, which is the world's largest software maker, also delivered an outlook for its 2008 fiscal year, which begins in July, in the upper range of analysts' projections. Microsoft said that revenue in fiscal 2008 should reach $56.5 billion to $57.5 billion, and earnings were expected to be $1.68 to $1.72 a share.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Microsoft’s results suggested that early sales of its new Windows Vista operating system were off to a solid start.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Microsoft reported quarterly sales and profits that surpassed Wall Street's expectations yesterday, suggesting that early sales of its new Windows Vista operating system were off to a solid start.</p>
        <p>The company, which is the world's largest software maker, also delivered an outlook for its 2008 fiscal year, which begins in July, in the upper range of analysts' projections. Microsoft said that revenue in fiscal 2008 should reach $56.5 billion to $57.5 billion, and earnings were expected to be $1.68 to $1.72 a share.</p>
        <p>Industry analysts had been concerned that Microsoft might deliver an unsettling surprise in the quarterly report if Vista sales had been sluggish or if spending was spiking as the company struggled to catch up to Google in Internet services.</p>
        <p>But the strong quarterly results and encouraging guidance for the next year eased those worries. ''This brought a sigh of relief,'' said Sarah Friar, an analyst for Goldman Sachs.</p>
        <p>The results were announced after the Nasdaq's 4 p.m. close. In after-hours trading, Microsoft's shares rose $1.20 a share, or 4.1 percent, to $30.30 a share by 7:15 p.m., after rising 11 cents, to $29.10 a share, in regular trading.</p>
        <p>Microsoft's online services business remained a problem. Revenue in that division rose 11 percent, to $623 million, and losses rose sharply, to $200 million.</p>
        <p>Yet the quarterly results point to the underlying strength and profitability of the main engines of the company's business -- Windows desktop operating systems, Office productivity programs and, increasingly, Microsoft's server software, used in corporate data centers.</p>
        <p>''The core business is doing very well,'' said Charles DiBona, an analyst at Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>Revenue for the quarter was $14.40 billion, an increase of 32 percent from the year-earlier quarter. Quarterly sales were about $500 million higher than the Wall Street consensus, compiled by Thomson Financial.</p>
        <p>Net profit was $4.93 billion, or 65 percent higher than a year ago. Earnings were 50 cents a share. Excluding a 2 cent gain from tax benefits and 1 cent charge for legal expenses, the earnings were 49 cents a share. That was 3 cents a share higher than analysts' estimates.</p>
        <p>Revenue and profits in the quarter were inflated, as expected, by coupon programs Microsoft introduced last year when Windows Vista and Office 2007 were delayed and missed the year-end holiday season in the consumer market. The new products did not ship until the end of January.</p>
        <p>To encourage holiday sales of personal computers, Microsoft offered free or low-cost upgrades to the delayed software. So in the December quarter, the company deferred $1.67 billion of revenue. That revenue, and $1.14 billion in net profits, spilled over into the quarter ended in March, Microsoft's third fiscal quarter.</p>
        <p>Still, Microsoft's quarterly revenue would have increased 17 percent even without that one-time lift, and the Windows PC business would have been 30 percent higher than the year-earlier quarter.</p>
        <p>''There was a lot of concern about Vista, but this shows it is off to a good start, even with the ill-timed launch,'' said Andy Miedler, an analyst at Edward Jones.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Christopher P. Liddell, Microsoft's chief financial officer, said the sales of Windows Vista were $300 million to $400 million higher than the company's internal projections, and Office 2007 sales were about $200 million higher.</p>
        <p>In the online services business, where Microsoft trails its main rivals, Google and Yahoo, Mr. Liddell pointed to a 23 percent increase in ad revenue as ''encouraging progress.'' The continuing losses, he added, are regarded as investments as Microsoft tries to build that business. ''We're in investment mode, and that's going to be our strategy for the foreseeable future,'' Mr. Liddell said.</p>
        <p>And it is a big-spending financial arms race for the major companies. According to Ms. Friar of Goldman Sachs, Microsoft is expected to spend an estimated $4 billion in 2007 on online services business, excluding capital expenditures, like equipping data centers. Yahoo, Goldman estimates, plans to spend $4.7 billion, and Google, $8 billion.</p>
        <p>Sales of Microsoft's server software -- databases, e-mail systems and other products used in corporate computer centers -- rose 15 percent, to $2.75 billion, and the unit's operating income rose 32 percent, to $979 million.</p>
        <p>Sales for the entertainment and devices unit, which includes Xbox video game consoles, slipped 22 percent, to $929 million.</p>
        <p>A year ago, the new Xbox line had just been introduced. The losses in that business, at $315 million, were $87 million narrower in the year-earlier quarter. Microsoft has set fiscal 2008 as the goal for when that business should break even and turn profitable.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
