<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In an 'Absolut World,' a Vodka Could Use the Same Ads for More Than 25 Years</title>
    <meta content="27adco" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/business/media/27adco.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843183"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/World Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Trademarks and Trade Names</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trademarks and Trade Names</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Absolut</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E0D6153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1028" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In an 'Absolut World,' a Vodka Could Use the Same Ads for More Than 25 Years</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In an ‘Absolut World,’ a Vodka Could Use the Same Ads for More Than 25 Years</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STUART ELLIOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR 25 years, Absolut vodka ran the same humorous campaign celebrating its distinctive bottle, becoming renowned for the consistency of its pitches to consumers. Now, seeking to recapture lightning in a -- well, you know -- the brand is changing advertising approaches for the second time in 15 months.</p>
        <p>Next week, Absolut will discontinue a campaign introduced in January 2006, which carried the theme ''The Absolut Vodka'' and was built around puns on the brand name and the word ''absolute.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Absolut vodka will discontinue its ad campaign, changing approaches for the second time in 15 months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR 25 years, Absolut vodka ran the same humorous campaign celebrating its distinctive bottle, becoming renowned for the consistency of its pitches to consumers. Now, seeking to recapture lightning in a -- well, you know -- the brand is changing advertising approaches for the second time in 15 months.</p>
        <p>Next week, Absolut will discontinue a campaign introduced in January 2006, which carried the theme ''The Absolut Vodka'' and was built around puns on the brand name and the word ''absolute.''</p>
        <p>Those ads, which likened the vodka to stars like Marilyn Monroe and Steve McQueen and landmarks like the Statue of Liberty and the rock club CBGB, replaced the famous ''Absolut --------'' campaign that started in 1981.</p>
        <p>The ads about ''The Absolut Vodka'' kept the brand growing modestly in the United States last year, when sales increased 2 percent compared with 2005.</p>
        <p>But that was nothing like the double-digit percentage gains the brand routinely enjoyed in the '80s and '90s heyday of the ''Absolut --------'' ads, with clever concepts like ''Absolut Warhol,'' a painting of the bottle by the artist; ''Absolut L.A.,'' a swimming pool shaped like the bottle; and ''Absolut Centerfold,'' a bottle presented like a Playmate in a 1988 issue of Playboy magazine.</p>
        <p>So widely known was the offbeat bottle campaign that Absolut ran an April Fool's Day ad in 1997 proclaiming the end of the campaign. It turned out to be nine years premature.</p>
        <p>The new campaign, with a budget estimated at $33 million to $35 million, is by TBWA/Chiat/Day in New York. The agency and a predecessor have worked for Absolut for 26 years. The ads eschew the comparisons and coattail-riding of ''The Absolut Vodka'' to assert that Absolut is in a class by itself -- indeed, in a world of its own.</p>
        <p>The campaign includes commercials and video clips as well as online ads (at absolut.com), print ads, billboards and event marketing. Drinkers are invited to imbibe ''in an Absolut World,'' a fanciful, even surreal, place where common sense prevails and just deserts are always on the menu.</p>
        <p>On Planet Absolut, for instance, men can get pregnant, the Curse of the Billy Goat is lifted from the hapless Chicago Cubs and the garish billboards in Times Square are replaced by masterpiece paintings. Lying leaders are exposed by their Pinocchio noses, protesters and the police wage street fights with feather pillows, nice Manhattan apartments cost $300 a month and it takes only one exercise lap in a pool for a fatty to become a hottie.</p>
        <p>The switch in campaign tactics is indicative of the intensifying ferment in competitive marketing categories, in which the buying behavior of fickle consumers must be monitored continuously to determine whether ads are working.</p>
        <p>For example, American Express, another company known for the longevity of its campaigns, recently stopped running ads that were less than three years old. The Amex ads were replaced with a campaign that replies to rivals like MasterCard and Visa by focusing more on the benefits of being a cardholder.</p>
        <p>''There's nothing wrong with the Absolut product or the image,'' said Robert K. Passikoff, president of Brand Keys in New York, a research company that studies brand and customer loyalty, ''but they're not seeing the growth in the marketplace they'd like to see.''</p>
        <p>Absolut is confronting the same problems as other market-leading brands like Coca-Cola, he added, in that ''everybody knows who they are, but what are they known for?''</p>
        <p>According to the most recent Brand Keys survey, Mr. Passikoff said, Absolut ranks seventh in customer loyalty among brands of imported vodka, about the same as this time last year.</p>
        <p>Among those ahead of Absolut are newer, more expensive vodkas like Ciroq, Ketel One and Grey Goose, which are faring better in a category driven by consumer desire for what Mr. Passikoff described as ''novelty and uniqueness.''</p>
        <p>The ''Absolut --------'' campaign helped the brand become the best-selling imported vodka in the United States as distribution soared from 20,000 cases in 1981 to almost 5 million last year.</p>
        <p>Absolut also grew to become the No. 3 spirits brand of any kind, behind only Bacardi rum and Smirnoff (domestic) vodka. More recently, Absolut fell to fourth place over all, as Captain Morgan rum moved ahead.</p>
        <p>''We're still a very strong, very solid brand in the U.S.,'' said Tim Murphy, senior brand director for the Absolut portfolio of products at the Absolut Spirits Company in New York, part of the V&amp;S Group division of V&amp;S Vin and Sprit, the Swedish company that distills Absolut.</p>
        <p>''That said, the vodka category has changed,'' Mr. Murphy acknowledged, ''and we want to re-cement, re-establish Absolut's position in the category.''</p>
        <p>The approach centered on ''The Absolut Vodka'' was ''a great idea,'' Mr. Murphy said, ''but to put it quite frankly, if we tried to carry it on too long, consumers would say: 'I get it. You're the Absolut vodka.' ''</p>
        <p>''Now, we want to build on that,'' he added, by ''asking what if everything in the world was approached the same way Absolut approaches vodka.''</p>
        <p>Executives at TBWA/Chiat/Day, part of the TBWA Worldwide division of the Omnicom Group, say the ''Absolut World'' campaign tested well with the target audience, primarily urbanites ages 25 to 34. ''It re-engages consumers with the idea that Absolut is the quintessential vodka, the true vodka, the standard by which you judge other things,'' said Rob Smiley, worldwide creative director at TBWA/Chiat/Day.</p>
        <p>The goal is to encourage a dialogue between customers and the brand, he added, in contrast with previous advertising that was more of a top-down presentation from Absolut to its drinkers.</p>
        <p>The ads proclaim, ''This is Absolut's view of the world; you respond, you react,'' Mr. Smiley said. The campaign will include more TV spots than before as print ads decline to about 25 percent of the total media mix, compared with 60 percent to 70 percent last year.</p>
        <p>Absolut ads aimed at minority consumers will also begin to feature the ''Absolut World'' theme, Mr. Murphy said. The Axis Agency in Los Angeles, part of the Interpublic Group of Companies, creates campaigns for black and Hispanic consumers. SPI Marketing in New York creates campaigns for gay men and lesbians.</p>
        <p>ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
