<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>$8 Billion And a Twist For Harman</title>
    <meta content="27audio" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/business/27audio.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843240"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Goldman Sachs &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Harman International Industries</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">De La Merced, Michael J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peters, Jeremy W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Harman International Industries Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Goldman Sachs Group Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3DE123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="786" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>$8 Billion And a Twist For Harman</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Shareholders, a Ticket Into an $8 Billion Deal</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL J. de la MERCED and JEREMY W. PETERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Peters, Jeremy W; De La Merced, Michael J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kohlberg Kravis Roberts and Goldman Sachs will offer Harman International Industries shareholders chance to retain stake in newly private company after $8 billion buyout; more widespread use of stub provision may protect shareholders from losing out on their investments (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Private equity has done much bigger deals in the last two years. But the $8 billion buyout for Harman International Industries, the maker of JBL speakers and Harman Kardon home theater systems, may prove the most groundbreaking.</p>
        <p>The buyers, Kohlberg Kravis Roberts and Goldman Sachs, have offered Harman shareholders a chance to retain a stake in the newly private company and share in any profit made if the company is later sold or taken public.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The proposed buyout of Harman has an unusual feature, known as a stub, that lets shareholders keep a stake in newly private company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Private equity has done much bigger deals in the last two years. But the $8 billion buyout for Harman International Industries, the maker of JBL speakers and Harman Kardon home theater systems, may prove the most groundbreaking.</p>
        <p>The buyers, Kohlberg Kravis Roberts and Goldman Sachs, have offered Harman shareholders a chance to retain a stake in the newly private company and share in any profit made if the company is later sold or taken public.</p>
        <p>Under the terms of the deal, the public shareholders could hold as much as 27 percent of the private company.</p>
        <p>The offer represents a major concession to public shareholders, who have increasingly voiced concern about selling their shares to private equity firms only to watch the new owners reap large profits by flipping the companies a few years later, and in some cases a few months.</p>
        <p>The Harman deal tries to assuage stockholders by using a provision known as a stub, as in a ticket stub, apparently its first use in the United States amid the latest buyout boom.</p>
        <p>Douglas A. Cifu, a partner at the law firm Paul Weiss Rifkind Wharton &amp; Garrison, said that companies and shareholders might press harder for stub provisions in future buyouts and that private equity might be more willing to offer them.</p>
        <p>''It helps mute some of the criticism that private equity firms are taking all the upside for themselves and are quick-flip artists,'' Mr. Cifu said.</p>
        <p>Frederick E. Rowe Jr., a money manager in Dallas who derides many private equity buyouts as ''open sores,'' said last night that the use of a stub in the Harman deal was a step in the right direction. Should stubs become more prevalent, Mr. Rowe said, shareholders may no longer lose out on their investments.</p>
        <p>''Rather than just arbitrarily squeeze shareholders out, shareholders can now participate,'' he said. ''I don't see any downsides as all.''</p>
        <p>But stubs are not a panacea for shareholders.</p>
        <p>Private equity deals often take several years to realize a profit, and investors must be willing to have their holdings locked up in the interim. Moreover, not all deals make a profit, leaving buyout firms and stub holders with a loss. At the same time, the public shareholders would be at the whim of the private equity holders with little or no say in the business.</p>
        <p>The use of a stub in the Harman deal comes after a similar provision was suggested, but ultimately not used, in the sale of Clear Channel Communications, the nation's largest radio company.</p>
        <p>After two investors in Clear Channel -- Fidelity Investments and Highfields Capital Management, a hedge fund -- balked at the price, the two suitors, Bain Capital and Thomas H. Lee Partners, sent a letter to the Clear Channel board proposing alternatives to raise their offer.</p>
        <p>Among them was a stub for existing shareholders. But the bidders eventually chose to raise their offer to $27.6 billion, from $26 billion.</p>
        <p>And stubs sometimes have failed to entice shareholders into selling their companies.</p>
        <p>This month, a private equity group in Britain seeking to buy J Sainsbury, the supermarket chain, sweetened its bid by offering up to 25 percent of the company to its shareholders. In the end, the retailer's founding family, which holds 18 percent of the company's shares, rejected the offer.</p>
        <p>Beyond the stub, owners of Harman stock would receive $120 a share, a 17 percent premium over the closing price on Wednesday. Shares of Harman rose $19.94, or 19.44 percent, to $122.50, suggesting that investors may be anticipating a higher rival offer. Harman can solicit competing bids for 50 days.</p>
        <p>For Sidney Harman, the 88-year-old founder of the company, who owns about 5 percent of its stock, the sale will not end his involvement in the business, which he started in 1953. As part of the deal, which is expected to close this summer, he will remain as executive chairman.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harman has sold the company before, once for $100 million in 1977 after he joined the Carter administration as an assistant commerce secretary. (His wife, Jane Harman, is a United States representative from California.) The company performed poorly under the owner at the time, the Beatrice Company, and Mr. Harman bought it back in 1980 for $55 million.</p>
        <p>The environment for private equity has grown toxic in other ways as well.</p>
        <p>Unions in the United States and Europe, critical of the cuts in jobs or worker benefits that often accompany buyouts, have called for increased government scrutiny of the deals.</p>
        <p>This week, a report released by the Service Employees International Union, which represents nearly two million workers, suggested that lawmakers examine certain tax breaks that buyout firms enjoy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
