<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Up and Down, With No News, Before a Trip</title>
    <meta content="27nyph" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/arts/music/27nyph.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843127"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Philharmonic</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CEED9153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="532" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Up and Down, With No News, Before a Trip</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Up and Down, With No News, Before a Trip</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Speculation continues to swirl around the tight-lipped New York Philharmonic, which is poised to appoint its next music director. No announcement is expected soon, though, for the orchestra embarks next week on a European tour, returning later next month.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Lorin Maazel remains very much in control, for good and for otherwise. Conducting Wednesday night's program at Avery Fisher Hall, he again emerged as an exasperatingly unpredictable interpreter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wednesday’s exasperatingly unpredictable program included an uninspiring account of Beethoven’s “Leonore” and a compelling performance of Allan Berg’s Violin Concerto.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Speculation continues to swirl around the tight-lipped New York Philharmonic, which is poised to appoint its next music director. No announcement is expected soon, though, for the orchestra embarks next week on a European tour, returning later next month.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Lorin Maazel remains very much in control, for good and for otherwise. Conducting Wednesday night's program at Avery Fisher Hall, he again emerged as an exasperatingly unpredictable interpreter.</p>
        <p>The program opened with a perfectly executed and altogether uninspiring account of Beethoven's ''Leonore'' Overture No. 3. Passagework was cleanly delineated, rhythms crisply articulated, chords judiciously voiced. But Mr. Maazel seemed uninvolved, and the players responded with a flat performance. It is hard not to suspect that the overture was placed on the program merely to provide something familiar and stirring in advance of the challenging work that followed: Alban Berg's Violin Concerto, with Anne-Sophie Mutter as soloist.</p>
        <p>With this compelling performance of Berg's overwhelming masterpiece, it was as if the real concert had begun. Berg was commissioned to write this concerto by the violinist Louis Krasner. But when Manon Gropius, the adolescent daughter of the architect Walter Gropius and Alma Mahler (the composer's widow), died suddenly in 1935, Berg fashioned the concerto into a memorial dedicated to an angel. Though he employed a proper 12-tone row in the composition, the pitches in the series trace several diatonic triads, resulting in a harmonic language that wondrously bridges tonal and atonal sound spheres.</p>
        <p>The first movement begins as a pensive yet restless sonata form and then evolves into a portrait of Manon as a girl, complete with bittersweet strains of joyful dances and a folk tune. The second movement begins with a fitful, wrenching, dissonant outcry, like some tortured joint cadenza for violin and orchestra. The work ends with a plea, almost a prayer, as the elusive melody and four-part harmony of a Bach chorale, ''Es ist genug!'' (It is enough!) are woven into the textures of Berg's wistfully atonal music. Berg died at 50, just four months after completing this, his last work.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mutter played with great sensitivity, piercing insight, melting tone and complete technical command. If her German compatriot Christian Tetzlaff, a champion of this concerto, makes the music sound audacious, Ms. Mutter made it seem inevitable. Mr. Maazel proved an ideal conductor for this score, laying out its textures and complexities with striking clarity, letting no detail pass unnoticed, yet integrating all the parts into a glowing and affecting entity.</p>
        <p>What the second half of the program -- Stravinsky's symphonic poem ''Song of the Nightingale'' and Ravel's ''Daphnis et Chloé'' Suite No. 2 -- had to do with the first half I could not say. But the Stravinsky and Ravel scores, written in the early years of the 20th century's second decade, seemed close cousins. Both performances were incandescent and brilliant. Mr. Maazel's cool restraint in the Ravel brought out the music's sensual allure without turning it torrid. I found the playing in the Stravinsky a little cold, though. There is a big difference between a cool and a cold performance.</p>
        <p>New York Philharmonic performances continue tonight and tomorrow night at Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500; newyorkphiharmonic.org.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
