<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Best Available Player Should Fill a Hole for the Giants</title>
    <meta content="27giants" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/sports/football/27giants.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843201"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Football League</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E3DF123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="952" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Best Available Player Should Fill a Hole for the Giants</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Best Available Player Should Fill a Hole for the Giants</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN BRANCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Branch, John</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When it was time for the Giants to choose a player at last year's N.F.L. draft, they faced a classic draft-day question: pick the best available player, regardless of position, or pick one that would best fill a hole on the roster?</p>
        <p>It is a decision that confronts nearly every team. Rarely does the highest-rated player play the position where a team needs the most help.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As this year’s N.F.L. draft approaches, the Giants have plenty of needs to fill, including linebacker, cornerback, defensive tackle and offensive tackle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When it was time for the Giants to choose a player at last year's N.F.L. draft, they faced a classic draft-day question: pick the best available player, regardless of position, or pick one that would best fill a hole on the roster?</p>
        <p>It is a decision that confronts nearly every team. Rarely does the highest-rated player play the position where a team needs the most help.</p>
        <p>The Giants, who hold the 20th pick in the first round, could be positioned for such a coincidence. Having slipped from the top tier of championship contenders, they have plenty of needs, including linebacker, cornerback, offensive tackle and defensive tackle. And if their ranking of players looks like those of the draft pundits, the future stars of the N.F.L. draft may be aligned just right for the Giants.</p>
        <p>Last year, coming off an 11-5 season, a division championship and a playoff loss, the Giants had few obvious holes. Defensive end was the least of their worries, thanks to a pair of Pro Bowl players in Michael Strahan and Osi Umenyiora.</p>
        <p>But the Giants drafted defensive end Mathias Kiwanuka of Boston College because they believed he was the best player available with the 32nd choice.</p>
        <p>''We really probably didn't need a defensive end, but the guy was valued so high for us that we picked the guy,'' Jerry Reese, the Giants' general manager, said last week. Reese, who oversaw college scouting and the draft for the Giants last year as the team's director of player personnel, has not hired a replacement since he was promoted to replace Ernie Accorsi in January.</p>
        <p>Last year's discussion -- best player available or need? -- came up in the 15 minutes that the Giants had to make their decision. Reese addressed the scouts and the coaches.</p>
        <p>''I said, 'Does anybody in this room think Mathias Kiwanuka is not going to be a Pro Bowl defensive end?' '' Reese said. ''No hands went up. I said: 'We are going to pick this guy. I know we don't need him at this point, but at some point he is going to be a good player for us.' ''</p>
        <p>This draft promises to be different, and not only because Accorsi retired after nine seasons as general manager. The Giants have none of the surging confidence they carried a year ago, when they talked openly of making a run at the Super Bowl.</p>
        <p>They went 8-8 and lost six of their final eight games in the regular season, before losing a wild-card playoff game. Now Reese is in charge of the team's direction, Coach Tom Coughlin's job security is tenuous and the Giants look like a middling team riddled with holes.</p>
        <p>Reese admitted he is not an unbending believer in the best-player-available theory.</p>
        <p>''You are conscious of your needs,'' Reese said. ''You just don't go in and say that we are going to pick the best player all of the time.''</p>
        <p>For the Giants, no need is bigger than at linebacker, where Antonio Pierce is the only remaining starter. Reese cut the starting outside linebackers LaVar Arrington and Carlos Emmons, and did not re-sign the primary backup, Brandon Short. The three combined to miss 21 regular-season games because of injuries, so the Giants are looking for players who will announce their presence with speed and game-changing plays.</p>
        <p>The Giants have been hesitant to promote any of their young backups. They gave the former Chiefs linebacker Kawika Mitchell, who is more versatile than spectacular, a tepid one-year contract.</p>
        <p>It is why the so-called draft experts and scouting gurus who emerge each spring attached to a microphone or a Web site reasonably predict that the Giants will choose one of several highly touted outside linebackers -- Paul Posluszny of Penn State, Lawrence Timmons of Florida State or Jon Beason of Miami.</p>
        <p>If nothing else, it could be a nice blend of need and timing; all three are projected as middle to late first-round choices.</p>
        <p>For a similar reason, the Giants may look at a cornerback, too. Sam Madison and Corey Webster are the projected starters, but each missed multiple games last season with injuries. This year's draft is heavy with possible upgrades.</p>
        <p>Leon Hall of Michigan, Derrelle Revis of Pittsburgh, Aaron Ross of Texas and Chris Houston of Arkansas are considered first-round possibilities, and several others should be taken in the second round.</p>
        <p>Reese has been predictably coy about his intentions, suggesting that a first-round trade is a possibility. His clearest remark about the current state of the roster was when he was asked about David Diehl, a left guard who last season moved to left tackle to replace the injured Luke Petitgout, who was cut and then signed by Tampa Bay.</p>
        <p>''We have a left offensive tackle that we've won games with,'' Reese said. ''Would we like a better player at that position? Maybe so, but we've won games with the left tackle that we have now, David Diehl.''</p>
        <p>Whether it was an uncommon display of uncertainty or a well-placed smokescreen, the Giants need help. Joe Thomas of Wisconsin and Levi Brown of Penn State could be taken in the top 10. Joe Staley of Central Michigan is projected as a middle to late first-rounder.</p>
        <p>Whatever the Giants decide, it appears that a smorgasbord of viable first-round players who play positions that they need will be available.</p>
        <p>The Giants, like all teams, have poured months of research and secretive analysis into this weekend. The biggest debate of the entire process might be in the team's draft room during the 15 minutes that the Giants have to make their first selection, if the rankings of those players and the needs of the team do not perfectly align.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
