<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Good Dog, and a Good Shepherd</title>
    <meta content="27ritual" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/travel/escapes/27ritual.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843134"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="RITUALS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Busch, Charles</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E6D8153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1232" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Good Dog, and a Good Shepherd</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Good Dog, and a Good Shepherd</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES BUSCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Busch, Charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charles Busch Rituals column on his white German shepherd dog, Wolfie, who became integral part of his childhood after his mother died; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN my mother was alive, we had a black miniature poodle named Nicky. He was always driving my mother crazy, jumping up on furniture and on us, but she forgave him because he adored her.</p>
        <p>My mother died of a heart attack when I was 7. She was 41. No warning. One minute, I had this wonderful, loving mother. The next, she was gone. It was devastating. It was the defining event of my childhood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“Wolfie came into my life at a time when I was completely vulnerable. And that made me bond so intensely with him.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN my mother was alive, we had a black miniature poodle named Nicky. He was always driving my mother crazy, jumping up on furniture and on us, but she forgave him because he adored her.</p>
        <p>My mother died of a heart attack when I was 7. She was 41. No warning. One minute, I had this wonderful, loving mother. The next, she was gone. It was devastating. It was the defining event of my childhood.</p>
        <p>The day my mother died, Nicky went right outdoors and ran for miles. He took off. We looked everywhere for him, but we could never find him. It was hard because here we had lost my mother, and losing her dog was like losing another little part of her.</p>
        <p>We had no thought of getting another dog. But one night my father came home from work with this little, white, fluffy ball of fur, a German shepherd puppy. It was a big surprise for the family.</p>
        <p>My father didn't have any particular feelings for dogs. He was a perpetual 16-year-old. The death of my mother meant that he had to maintain some semblance of family life for us, and he wasn't very good at it. He was a fun and adorable guy. All the ladies he ran around with thought so. He owned a record store in Yonkers, and probably one of his customers brought in this puppy.</p>
        <p>But it was a good thing, because we were all sad about losing Nicky and thrilled with this new puppy. Here was this happy bundle of energy, kissing and licking us and romping around. We named him Wolfie.</p>
        <p>I took to him immediately. He became my best friend who never moped around, was always glad to see me, never hassled me about homework. We really bonded.</p>
        <p>They grow so quickly! In a year this tiny, fluffy puppy was an enormous, long-haired white shepherd. He knew each person in the family -- my two older sisters, my mother's two older sisters, my dad -- and he had us all figured out. He loved all of us, but he made me feel special.</p>
        <p>As a child, I felt alone, and different, at least partly because I didn't have a mother. Wolfie was my friend. He was the one who was with me the most, and all that other stuff didn't matter to him. He just loved me. He was there for me for whatever I needed.</p>
        <p>Walking down the street with Wolfie was an experience. He looked like an animal from a fantasy. With his big white body and his enormous head, you could imagine he was a unicorn. When I walked him, cars would stop and people would roll down their windows and stare at us. Here was this thin, sad little boy with this longhaired, white creature. Wolfie knew they were watching, and he was proud. He carried his head high. He had great elegance.</p>
        <p>He was so attached to me that he wouldn't let anybody get near me. He'd bark and even bite people. It was a real problem. I didn't have too many friends anyway, but one day, somebody from the neighborhood came a little too close to me as I was walking home from school, so Wolfie bit him. It was a horrible scene. Wolfie and I ran home, and later, after my father got home, the police came.</p>
        <p>My father brought the policeman into the living room, where Wolfie and I were lying on the floor in front of the television. I had my arms around him, and he was just lying there, looking peaceful.</p>
        <p>''Look at that dog,'' my father said. ''He can't possibly be the dog you got the complaint about. He's not at all aggressive.''</p>
        <p>''We should still take him in,'' the policeman said. ''He could be a danger in the neighborhood.''</p>
        <p>I was lying there, just holding on to Wolfie.</p>
        <p>I didn't know what I'd do if the police took him away. My father talked to the policeman and showed him how gentle Wolfie was, and eventually convinced him not to take Wolfie.</p>
        <p>It was interesting that he had these aggressive qualities toward strangers but he was absolutely gentle with me. I could play lion tamer and put my head in his mouth, and he would just wait. He would never think of harming me.</p>
        <p>We had a housekeeper named Beulah Baker who had come from down South, where she had been a pickle picker on a pickle farm. She never did do much housework, but she was wonderful. She sounded a little like Butterfly McQueen. She was very darling and so affectionate to me. We spent so much time in the house together, just Beulah Baker, Wolfie and me. Beulah used to teach me how to set her wigs, and I was pretty good at it.</p>
        <p>On a typical afternoon, Wolfie would be lying there on the floor, and Beulah Baker and I would be busy with combs and pins, working on one of her wigs.</p>
        <p>Later we would watch television. I loved old movies -- I still do -- and I just absorbed the tragic heroines. I tend to watch the same ones that I loved as a child over and over: ''Marie Antoinette,'' with Norma Shearer; ''Waterloo Bridge,'' with Vivien Leigh; ''I Could Go On Singing,'' with Judy Garland; ''The Hard Way,'' with Ida Lupino; ''Random Harvest,'' with Greer Garson; ''I'm No Angel,'' with Mae West; and a zillion others.</p>
        <p>Then, my favorite part of the day, my turn to perform. I would mimic back for Beulah and Wolfie these larger-than-life romantic actresses in their classic roles. The afternoon would end with Beulah sitting on the sofa with this huge white German Shepherd at her feet. And I'd be singing Judy Garland songs to her.</p>
        <p>Wolfie would sit there staring at me, very alert. He made it seem like watching this skinny little boy singing ''The Man That Got Away'' was something a dog was really meant to do. That was a typical afternoon in our house.</p>
        <p>You can see why not much housework got done. When I was 7, as a special treat, my father took me to the old Metropolitan Opera House to see Joan Sutherland in ''La Sonnambula.'' I was amazed -- it's the story of a young girl who goes walking in her sleep, and sitting there in the audience, I was watching this magnificent redheaded lady drifting through a glorious 19th-century painted landscape. When I got up in front of Wolfie and Beulah, I was trying to recreate that for them, the beauty and the dreamy quality. In a way, you could say that my entire career has been an attempt to recreate that first impression.</p>
        <p>Wolfie came into my life at a time when I was completely vulnerable. And that made me bond so intensely with him. He was enormous, he was mystical, he was white. He was the constant, strong, loving, lovable dog that took care of me. It was like he came from an enchanted land. He made me feel that I belonged to somebody.</p>
        <p>As told to Sharon Sakson. This account is adapted from ''Paws and Reflect: Exploring the Bond Between Gay Men and Their Dogs'' (Alyson Books, 2006) by Neil Plakcy and Ms. Sakson. Charles Busch's latest play, ''Our Leading Lady,'' runs through Sunday at the Manhattan Theater Club.</p>
        <p>RITUALS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
