<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spitzer Seeks Raise for Judges, Not Legislators</title>
    <meta content="27judges" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/nyregion/27judges.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843182"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Albany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Constitutional Amendments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Voter Registration and Requirements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Albany (NY)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Spitzer, Eliot L</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E0D6153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="975" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spitzer Seeks Raise for Judges, Not Legislators</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Spitzer Seeks Raise for Judges, Not Legislators</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, April 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer continued to antagonize lawmakers on Thursday by proposing to give judges, but not legislators, a pay raise, and to overhaul the way district lines are drawn.</p>
        <p>The measures were among a raft of proposals that included four amendments to the state's Constitution and changes to election law and the courts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALBANY, April 26  Gov. Eliot Spitzer continued to antagonize lawmakers on Thursday by proposing to give judges, but not legislators, a pay raise, and to overhaul the way district lines are drawn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer continued to antagonize lawmakers on Thursday by proposing to give judges, but not legislators, a pay raise, and to overhaul the way district lines are drawn.</p>
        <p>The measures were among a raft of proposals that included four amendments to the state's Constitution and changes to election law and the courts.</p>
        <p>The changes would merge overlapping layers of the court system, overhaul the way higher court judges are picked and allow voters to register on Election Day.</p>
        <p>''The legislation and constitutional amendments I am proposing today will bring long-needed reform to our court system, which is one of the most convoluted, politicized, outdated and expensive in the nation,'' the governor said in a statement.</p>
        <p>While many of the proposals were expected, the issue that attracted the most attention here in the state capital was the governor's plan to introduce legislation granting judges raises for the first time in more than eight years, a proposal likely to touch off a battle in the State Senate and the Assembly. Legislators have been eager to tie a judicial pay raise to their own salaries. They have not had an increase since 1999, though their pay is high compared with that of legislators in other states.</p>
        <p>The governor has said he would agree to a legislative pay raise only if lawmakers agree to reforms on issues like campaign finance, but he may be outnumbered in a fight over pay.</p>
        <p>The Republican-led Senate introduced a bill this week that would give raises to the judiciary but also create a commission to consider pay raises for all branches of government every four years, with appointees picked by the governor, the legislative leaders and the chief judge.</p>
        <p>The bill was sponsored by all 62 senators, implying that they could override a veto, even though Senate Democrats have been the governor's most reliable allies. The Senate's bill was patterned after a proposal made by Chief Judge Judith S. Kaye. Assembly Democrats approved a similar proposal in budget talks this year, but they must take it up again as a separate bill.</p>
        <p>''The governor's agenda is to hold up legislative raises in order to use that as a chip for something else,'' said Senator John A. DeFrancisco, an upstate Republican who is chairman of the Senate Judiciary Committee. Senate Republicans have said the governor tried to trade a pay raise for getting an agreement on the contentious issue of campaign finance reform, though the governor's staff has denied there was a direct link to the two issues.</p>
        <p>Mr. DeFrancisco said it was time to take pay out of ''the never-ending poker game of state government.''</p>
        <p>Assemblywoman Helene E. Weinstein, a Brooklyn Democrat and the chairwoman of the Assembly Judiciary Committee, said ''It's something that makes sense, to take legislative salaries out of the political trading game.''</p>
        <p>The governor's proposed pay raise would affect about 1,300 judges, from Judge Kaye to a part-time city court judge in Utica. It would increase the pay of a Supreme Court justice by nearly 21 percent to $165,200 from the current $136,700 a year -- in line with federal district court judges -- and also grant a retroactive increase to April 1, 2005, effectively giving judges a significant lump sum payment if the measure is approved.</p>
        <p>The Senate bill would grant a similar raise, but retroactive only to the beginning of this year. New York lawmakers have the third-highest level of base pay, $79,500, trailing only California and Michigan, according to the National Conference of State Legislatures. Salaries can be significantly increased by stipends for leadership and committee positions.</p>
        <p>Many of the governor's other proposals would be far more visible to the public, but most of them would require constitutional amendments, which take years to pass in two consecutive elected legislatures.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer is proposing an amendment to restructure the state court system by eliminating several layers with a two-tier structure: a Supreme Court and district courts. The Supreme Court would have six divisions: family, probate, criminal, state claims, commercial and general. The proposal closely resembles changes advocated by Judge Kaye.</p>
        <p>The governor also proposed broad changes to the way judges are picked, in response to two federal court decisions that have found that New York's system of electing judges -- through political conventions tightly controlled by party leaders -- is unconstitutional.</p>
        <p>The governor is ultimately proposing to replace the election of higher court judges with a network of commissions that would select them.</p>
        <p>Because amending the constitution is a lengthy process, the governor proposes to overhaul the existing system of conventions and to create a more competitive primary system in the interim.</p>
        <p>Judge Kaye has also proposed overhauling the existing system, but she reacted cautiously to the governor's proposal.</p>
        <p>''Chief Judge Kaye's longstanding position has been that the state is well served by our mixed system of elected and appointed judges, but she welcomes any suggestions that would improve those selection methods,'' said Gary Spencer, a spokesman for Judge Kaye.</p>
        <p>Judge Kaye has been most outspoken about a pay raise, even threatening to sue the state, though it was not clear what judge could hear the suit without creating a conflict of interest.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spencer, reacting carefully to the political dynamics, said, ''We're very pleased the governor is proposing a retroactive salary increase, and we're also very encouraged by the Senate's proposal.''</p>
        <p>On election law, the governor is proposing amending the Constitution to create an independent redistricting commission that would take the drawing of district lines out of the control of the majority parties in the Assembly and the Senate, an issue unlikely to pass muster with legislators.</p>
        <p>The governor is also proposing to provide automatic access to the state ballot for presidential candidates who qualify for federal matching funds, require polling places to keep consistent hours and reduce the number of signatures required on nominating petitions.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
