<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Parapet Falls From Building to Be Demolished for Atlantic Yards</title>
    <meta content="27atlantic" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/nyregion/27atlantic.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843205"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Machinery and Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Forest City Ratner Companies</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E2DF123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="842" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Parapet Falls From Building to Be Demolished for Atlantic Yards</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Parapet Falls From Building to Be Demolished for Atlantic Yards</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS J. LUECK and DARYL KHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lueck, Thomas J; Khan, Daryl</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>About 350 people were temporarily ordered out of a homeless shelter in Brooklyn yesterday after a 200-foot-long parapet on the roof of an adjacent building that was about to be demolished to make way for the Atlantic Yards project collapsed, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>No shelter residents, pedestrians or workers on the roof were hurt when the parapet on the vacant building, the former Ward Bread Bakery complex, at 800 Pacific Street, fell five stories about 9:30 a.m., although several cars were damaged. About 20 workers were on the roof at the time, removing asbestos that must be removed before the city will allow the building, between Carlton and Vanderbilt Avenues, to be demolished.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After the collapse in Brooklyn, about 350 people had to leave an adjacent homeless shelter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>About 350 people were temporarily ordered out of a homeless shelter in Brooklyn yesterday after a 200-foot-long parapet on the roof of an adjacent building that was about to be demolished to make way for the Atlantic Yards project collapsed, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>No shelter residents, pedestrians or workers on the roof were hurt when the parapet on the vacant building, the former Ward Bread Bakery complex, at 800 Pacific Street, fell five stories about 9:30 a.m., although several cars were damaged. About 20 workers were on the roof at the time, removing asbestos that must be removed before the city will allow the building, between Carlton and Vanderbilt Avenues, to be demolished.</p>
        <p>Tashie Sloley, a resident of the homeless shelter, the Pacific and Dean Residence Shelter, at 768 Pacific Street, said she heard ''a big boom that shook the floor'' and hurried outside with her two infant daughters when someone called out, ''Please evacuate the building and don't panic.''</p>
        <p>''When I heard 'don't panic,' I panicked,'' said Ms. Sloley, who spent several hours on the sidewalk in a line of displaced residents.</p>
        <p>By late afternoon, many had been taken to the community center of a nearby public housing complex. But by about 7:30 last night, the last of them were allowed back into the shelter.</p>
        <p>What caused the parapet to fall was unclear, although fire officials said it may have been weakened by heavy rain last week.</p>
        <p>Loren Riegelhaupt a spokesman for Forest City Ratner, the developer of the Atlantic Yards project, near Downtown Brooklyn, said the workers on the roof were using ''hand-held chippers'' to remove asbestos, but were not working on the parapet.</p>
        <p>After the collapse, the sidewalk and part of the street in front of the building were covered with smashed bricks, some of which struck several parked cars.</p>
        <p>Kate Lindquist, a spokeswoman for the Buildings Department, said it was investigating the collapse and whatever threat might be posed by the other parapets that remained in place on the roof of the 97-year-old former bakery.</p>
        <p>Late yesterday, officials of the city's Office of Emergency Management said the remaining sections of parapet would be dismantled.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lindquist said Forest City Ratner had been cited yesterday for failure to maintain an exterior wall of the building. Such citations are not unusual, and property owners are often able to avoid fines or other penalties by demonstrating that repair work has been completed.</p>
        <p>The long-planned Atlantic Yards project has been challenged by a torrent of lawsuits brought by opponents who maintain that it would overwhelm the neighborhood's streets and public services and question the state's use of eminent domain to make way for the project.</p>
        <p>The 22-acre project is to include housing, office and retail space and a professional basketball arena.</p>
        <p>The accident occurred five days after a State Supreme Court justice declined to issue a restraining order temporarily halting demolition of nine vacant buildings at the project's site.</p>
        <p>That court order had been sought by several groups opposed to the project, which argued that demolition should not be allowed before a hearing on a lawsuit challenging the state's approval of the project that is scheduled for next Thursday .</p>
        <p>Daniel Goldstein, a spokesman for Develop Don't Destroy Brooklyn, one of the groups that filed the suit, said yesterday that the collapse ''certainly raises many questions.'' He said all demolition on the project site should be halted until the city completes an investigation of what caused yesterday's collapse.</p>
        <p>Mr. Goldstein said Forest City Ratner had had ample opportunity to check the structural integrity of the former bakery complex.</p>
        <p>It was unclear yesterday what impact the accident would have on the developer's demolition schedule. No demolition permit has been issued by the city for 800 Pacific Street, because all the asbestos in the building must be removed first.</p>
        <p>Mr. Riegelhaupt said that workers had begun removing the asbestos in recent weeks, and that Forest City Ratner had hoped to have that job completed, and obtain a demolition permit, within two months.</p>
        <p>But he said the timetable would now depend on the results of the Buildings Department's investigation of the collapse.</p>
        <p>Mr. Goldstein said Forest City had removed protective sidewalk sheds from the front of the building last month that he said might have prevented the parapet from falling to the sidewalk, and asserted that it was wrong not to have a sidewalk shed in place and that the city should have made sure it was there.</p>
        <p>''Our focus is on the safety of the community and we are doing everything in our power to maintain it,'' Mr. Riegelhaupt said. He said the removal of the shed was necessary to allow access to sewer lines under the sidewalk that the city will require to be blocked before demolition of the building is begun.</p>
        <p>''So if it turns out that a heavy rain almost two weeks ago can make a parapet fall,' Mr. Goldstein said, ''isn't that all the more reason that they should have taken better precautions?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
