<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Siemens Struggles to Regain Equilibrium</title>
    <meta content="27siemens" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/business/worldbusiness/27siemens.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843191"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Siemens AG</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Kleinfeld, Klaus</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEFD6153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="767" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Siemens Struggles to Regain Equilibrium</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Siemens Struggles to Regain Equilibrium</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By G. THOMAS SIMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sims, G Thomas</byline>
      <dateline>FRANKFURT, April 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With a bribery scandal widening and its two top executives leaving, Siemens struggled on Thursday to maintain an air of somewhat normal operations, laying out ambitious growth and profit goals, even as its credit rating was put on watch and regulators in Washington expanded their investigation.</p>
        <p>A day after the chief executive, Klaus Kleinfeld, announced that he would be stepping down, Siemens warned that it expected to report a ''significant increase'' in the number of possible bribes identified in an internal investigation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With a bribery scandal widening and its two top executives leaving, the company struggled to maintain an air of normal operations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With a bribery scandal widening and its two top executives leaving, Siemens struggled on Thursday to maintain an air of somewhat normal operations, laying out ambitious growth and profit goals, even as its credit rating was put on watch and regulators in Washington expanded their investigation.</p>
        <p>A day after the chief executive, Klaus Kleinfeld, announced that he would be stepping down, Siemens warned that it expected to report a ''significant increase'' in the number of possible bribes identified in an internal investigation.</p>
        <p>Siemens, a huge German engineering and manufacturing company, said the Securities and Exchange Commission's enforcement division had upgraded its informal inquiry to a formal investigation, which gives regulators the power to issue subpoenas. It also warned that its own inquiry could result in its having to record additional charges for taxes and to change previous financial statements. It did not give figures but said the amount ''could be material,'' suggesting significant numbers.</p>
        <p>Siemens also said it ''currently cannot exclude'' the possibility of criminal or civil sanctions against the company or certain individuals. This could result in penalties, compensatory damages or the exclusion from public procurement contracts.</p>
        <p>The ratings agency Standard &amp; Poor's said Thursday that it was putting Siemens on watch for a possible downgrading. Mr. Kleinfeld's resignation, the agency said, ''creates uncertainty about Siemens' strategic and business execution, as well as the company's future strategic direction and financial policy.''</p>
        <p>The developments raised concern that the 420 million euros ($571 million) in suspected bribes announced so far might become much bigger. There were also questions whether Siemens could fulfill its promises to investors as it searched for a successor to Mr. Kleinfeld, who announced Wednesday that he would leave the company when his contract expired in September.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, Mr. Kleinfeld outlined a three-year plan and profit goals, including higher margins at the main units. At a news conference in Munich, he also said the search to replace him would be difficult. He noted that Siemens had 70 business areas, adding that a successor ''must understand technology.''</p>
        <p>The supervisory board is under pressure to quickly find a new chief and is said to be aiming for an outsider to give a fresh start to the company, which is 160 years old.</p>
        <p>''The supervisory board feels that it really needs new faces from the outside,'' said Theodor Baums, a professor at the University of Frankfurt and expert on corporate governance. ''I can understand this.''</p>
        <p>The scandals at Siemens and the fall of its top leaders, Mr. Kleinfeld on Wednesday and Heinrich von Pierer as chairman last week, have shaken corporate Germany and raised questions about how German companies do business.</p>
        <p>''It is hard to believe that something on this scale could be so organized and that no control was in place to catch it,'' Mr. Baums said. ''It shows a deficit.''</p>
        <p>Many investors are angry that the supervisory board -- similar to American directors -- seem to have given greater priority to the scandal than to the interests of investors.</p>
        <p>''The corruption affair overshadowed everything,'' said Stefan Schöppner, an analyst with Dresdner Bank. ''The supervisory board has a great burden of responsibility to quickly find a successor in the foreseeable future.''</p>
        <p>He noted that the stock price had not suffered. On Thursday, Siemens rose 1.3 percent here, to 89.53 euros. It reported a second-quarter profit Tuesday of 1.26 billion euros ($1.71 billion).</p>
        <p>The company has identified 420 million euros in suspicious payments over a seven-year period at a division that makes telecommunications equipment. Those payments may have been used as bribes to foreign officials to win contracts. Siemens said it would expand its search for similar payments to other divisions and begin looking at payments that might have been made in cash.</p>
        <p>The company is also under investigation by the Justice Department.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kleinfeld, at a conference with investors, said that the upgraded investigation by the S.E.C. was ''nothing of additional concern.''</p>
        <p>Yet the scandal is proving expensive in real terms. Siemens paid 63 million euros ($85.7 million) to outside advisers to clear up any violations of anticorruption laws.</p>
        <p>It also said it had guaranteed 4.5 million euros of a 5 million euro bond issued as bail to secure the release of Johannes Feldmayer, a member of its board of management. Mr. Feldmayer was in custody for a week as prosecutors investigated accusations that he bribed a pro-management labor union.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, Siemens raised its profit targets for 9 of 11 divisions. Mr. Kleinfeld said that management backed his plan to increase profitability and denied that his departure would knock the company off track.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
