<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hurricane Survivors to Buy U.S. Trailers or Pay Rental Fee</title>
    <meta content="27trailers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/us/nationalspecial/27trailers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843176"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mobile Homes and Trailers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Katrina (Storm)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rita (Storm)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Emergency Management Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eaton, Leslie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mobile Homes and Trailers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mobile Homes and Trailers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Emergency Management Agency</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E2D6153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="533" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hurricane Survivors to Buy U.S. Trailers or Pay Rental Fee</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hurricane Survivors to Buy U.S. Trailers or Pay Rental Fee</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE EATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eaton, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thousands of families living in trailers provided by federal government after Hurricanes Katrina and Rita will be offered opportunity to buy them for several hundred dollars, under $1 billion housing plan; those who do not buy trailers will have to pay modest rental fee starting in March 2008; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thousands of families living in the tinny white trailers provided by the federal government after Hurricanes Katrina and Rita will be offered the opportunity to buy them for a few hundred dollars, under a $1 billion housing plan announced yesterday in Washington.</p>
        <p>But those who do not buy their trailers will have to start paying a modest rent for them next March, with the payments beginning at $50 a month and escalating sharply thereafter. It was unclear what the upper limit was.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thousands of families living in government-provided trailers will be offered the opportunity to buy them for a few hundred dollars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Thousands of families living in the tinny white trailers provided by the federal government after Hurricanes Katrina and Rita will be offered the opportunity to buy them for a few hundred dollars, under a $1 billion housing plan announced yesterday in Washington.</p>
        <p>But those who do not buy their trailers will have to start paying a modest rent for them next March, with the payments beginning at $50 a month and escalating sharply thereafter. It was unclear what the upper limit was.</p>
        <p>About 86,000 families are still living in the trailers a year and a half after the storms, said R. David Paulison, director of the Federal Emergency Management Agency, which runs the trailer program. The majority of them are in Louisiana, although about 26,000 families occupy trailers in Mississippi.</p>
        <p>In addition to announcing the trailer purchase plan, officials said 33,000 evacuees, mostly in Texas, would get an extension of their rental allowances. The plans were announced by Donald Powell, the federal coordinator for Gulf Coast rebuilding.</p>
        <p>The rental allowances, which have been extended several times and were to expire in August, will now go through March 2009, officials said, although families will have to start contributing at least $50 a month starting next March.</p>
        <p>The hurricanes destroyed more than 200,000 homes, according to government estimates, including many apartments that have yet to be rebuilt. Louisiana recently announced that it had awarded $202 million in federal funds to help small landlords restore more than 5,200 rental units.</p>
        <p>With many fewer apartments available, rents along the Gulf Coast have soared, leaving many former residents of New Orleans unable to afford to return home.</p>
        <p>Officials also said yesterday that the rental assistance program, which had been run by FEMA, would be turned over to the Department of Housing and Urban Development, which has more expertise in running long-term housing programs.</p>
        <p>Acorn, the community organizing group that has sued the federal government over its post-hurricane housing programs, praised the extension of housing aid and the program's shift to the housing agency.</p>
        <p>Senator Mary L. Landrieu, Democrat of Louisiana, and other members of Congress have been pushing for the housing program to be turned over to HUD, said her spokeswoman, Stephanie Allen. The senator also supports allowing people to buy their trailers, Ms. Allen said, ''although she would prefer to see people in safer housing.''</p>
        <p>The housing agency will also help the emergency management agency try to find housing for families living in trailer parks that the government operates but would like to close. Almost 16,000 families live at group sites, but Mr. Paulison of FEMA said 80 percent of the families in trailers would not be affected because they were parked in people's driveways or yards.</p>
        <p>It is unclear how many people will want to buy their trailers, which are widely disliked for reasons both symbolic -- as reminders of what critics see as the government's inadequate response to the disaster -- and practical. Life in a trailer can be extremely cramped.</p>
        <p>''Anyone in the country can buy these if they want to,'' Mr. Paulison said, noting that the government auctions off about 800 used trailers a week, with most selling for $500 to $600.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
