<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Earnest Trooper and a New Father, Now Gone</title>
    <meta content="27trooper" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/nyregion/27trooper.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843248"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE2DE123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1068" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Earnest Trooper and a New Father, Now Gone</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Earnest Trooper Gone Too Soon</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS CONFESSORE and FERNANDA SANTOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Confessore, Nicholas; Santos, Fernanda</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ralph J. Phillips, the fugitive who killed a New York state trooper last year, did not know David C. Brinkerhoff. But Mr. Brinkerhoff knew Mr. Phillips. Mr. Brinkerhoff, a 29-year-old state trooper who was shot and killed on Wednesday, spent days tracking Mr. Phillips near the Pennsylvania border last fall, his first big assignment as part of the agency's elite Mobile Response Team.</p>
        <p>But when his wife, Barbara, called during the manhunt to tell him that she was about to give birth, Trooper Brinkerhoff knew where he was needed. He returned home and took her to the hospital.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Trooper David C. Brinkerhoff, who was shot and killed Wednesday by a fugitive in the Catskill Mountains, had recently become a father.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ralph J. Phillips, the fugitive who killed a New York state trooper last year, did not know David C. Brinkerhoff. But Mr. Brinkerhoff knew Mr. Phillips. Mr. Brinkerhoff, a 29-year-old state trooper who was shot and killed on Wednesday, spent days tracking Mr. Phillips near the Pennsylvania border last fall, his first big assignment as part of the agency's elite Mobile Response Team.</p>
        <p>But when his wife, Barbara, called during the manhunt to tell him that she was about to give birth, Trooper Brinkerhoff knew where he was needed. He returned home and took her to the hospital.</p>
        <p>His daughter, Isabella, was born the next day, the same day his fellow troopers cornered and captured Mr. Phillips.</p>
        <p>''He would have almost been side by side with the man that found him,'' his older brother Michael Brinkeroff recalled yesterday. ''But he came back the night before. Barb called and said 'You better get home.' ''</p>
        <p>They would like him to come home again. But on Wednesday, seven months after the capture of Mr. Phillips and the birth of Isabella, Trooper Brinkerhoff was fatally shot by another fugitive, Travis D. Trim, a 23-year-old college dropout, while entering a farmhouse in the Catskill Mountains where Mr. Trim had hidden.</p>
        <p>Trooper Brinkerhoff became the sixth state trooper killed during the past 13 months. Two of the troopers died in car accidents while on the job, one died in combat in Iraq, and three were shot, including Troopers Brinkerhoff and Joseph A. Longobardo, whom Mr. Phillips shot last year while he was on the run.</p>
        <p>Troopers Longobardo and Brinkerhoff had finished their Mobile Response Team training together.</p>
        <p>''It's devastating,'' said Trooper Thomas Mungeer, first vice president of the New York State Police Benevolent Association, who met Trooper Brinkerhoff while working as a union delegate for Troop F, where Mr. Brinkerhoff was assigned. ''This is a dangerous job, with more risks than most people out there would imagine, but we've had one after another, six troopers killed in the past 13 months.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Trooper Brinkerhoff's family and friends met at his home on a cul-de-sac in Coxsackie, a small town off the New York State Thruway not far south of Albany. They gathered their memories of a son, husband and father, their voices breaking over the past tense.</p>
        <p>''He was confident and sure-footed in his everyday life, and he was confident and sure-footed in his job,'' said his mother, Karen M. Howard. ''And he was a wonderful father.''</p>
        <p>It was hard to remember a time when they didn't expect him to go into law enforcement, his brother said. Trooper Brinkerhoff grew up in Boston, N.Y., outside Buffalo. His mother owned a restaurant there not far from a state police barracks. The troopers came by for coffee; soon enough, they brought their families for dinner. When his mother moved the restaurant to nearby West Seneca, the troopers followed.</p>
        <p>''The troopers were always around her and the kids, so it was only fitting that David would grow up to be one of them,'' said Tim Clark, who used to own an antiques store near the restaurant and is now the director of the Buffalo Niagara Film Commission.</p>
        <p>He was the youngest in the family but still, somehow, its fulcrum, conscientious and determined. When his two brothers and parents didn't feel like attending Sunday services, he went to church alone. In high school, when he wasn't studying or playing soccer or baseball, he trained to be an emergency responder.</p>
        <p>''He was the all-around kid. He was athletic, he played in the school band, he was good-looking,'' Michael Brinkerhoff said. ''But he meshed and blended with everyone. You won't find one person to say one bad thing about him.''</p>
        <p>When he graduated from high school in 1995, he wrote in his yearbook that he hoped one day to become an F.B.I. agent, and spent the next three years at the State University of New York at Albany, majoring in criminology. Neither parties nor girls distracted him much, his mother said, though the state trooper's exam did. He took the test when he turned 21 and passed. To enter the academy, he had to drop his college classes. But he wasn't one to leave things unfinished.</p>
        <p>''After he got out of the academy, he went right back to his degree,'' his brother said. He continued on to get a master's degree in public administration, all while serving as a state trooper.</p>
        <p>In the winter of 2002, after four years in the state police, two friends set Trooper Brinkerhoff up on a blind date with a pretty young blonde named Barbara. They fell in love, and two and a half years later they married. Living in Coxsackie, they liked to walk their dog in the hills. When they could, they flew to Cancún, Mexico, for a few days on the beach.</p>
        <p>''If I were to send you their wedding picture -- that's how they look all the time,'' said Mr. Brinkerhoff, a special education teacher who lives near Buffalo. (Daniel Brinkerhoff, the third brother, is a sheriff's deputy in Erie County.) ''They were happy,'' he said. ''They always smiled.''</p>
        <p>Duty came calling often. Trooper Brinkerhoff spent his first wedding anniversary in New Orleans, patrolling the streets ravaged by Hurricane Katrina with a volunteer detachment of New York state troopers. It was something out of a movie, he told them over the phone, empty and desolate, like another world. He would never forget the smell.</p>
        <p>When he came back, Trooper Brinkerhoff set his eyes on the Mobile Response Team. He spent six months in training: hand-to-hand combat, weapons practice, rescue operations.</p>
        <p>With his fellow trainees, he had to survive several days on Mount Marcy, the state's highest peak, with just the clothes on his back. They woke up one morning to find themselves in a foot and a half of snow, Ms. Howard recounted. They marked their unit's name, South Team, in the snow and took a picture to show back home. Last June, Trooper Brinkerhoff finished his training.</p>
        <p>Not long after, he approached his commanding officer at Troop F, Maj. Ed Raso, and invited him to the induction ceremony.</p>
        <p>''You should have seen the smile on his face,'' Major Raso said. ''This kid was just so proud to be a member of the State Police, and really, really proud that he'd be joining the M.R.T.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
