<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Wright, One Bad Swing Can Often Lead to Another</title>
    <meta content="27mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/sports/baseball/27mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843291"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wright, David</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rodriguez, Alex</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5DD123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1104" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Wright, One Bad Swing Can Often Lead to Another</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Wright, One Bad Swing Can Often Lead to Another</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shpigel, Ben</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>All his teammates had left by the time David Wright emerged from the showers late Wednesday afternoon. He dressed quickly, without a sound, and as he put on his wireless earpiece, he looked up to notice the reporters who had converged on his locker. He let out a muted sigh and said, ''Whatcha got?'' He already knew the answer.</p>
        <p>Over the past week, Wright has been asked repeated questions about an extended hitless streak (0 for 15 before it ended) and, more significantly, a season-long absence of power and runs batted in. In his third full season in the major leagues, at a moment when he has become one of baseball's most heavily promoted players, the 24-year-old Wright is encountering his first truly uncomfortable moments as a major leaguer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Amid a season-long absence of power and runs batted in, Mets third baseman David Wright is encountering his first truly uncomfortable moments as a major leaguer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>All his teammates had left by the time David Wright emerged from the showers late Wednesday afternoon. He dressed quickly, without a sound, and as he put on his wireless earpiece, he looked up to notice the reporters who had converged on his locker. He let out a muted sigh and said, ''Whatcha got?'' He already knew the answer.</p>
        <p>Over the past week, Wright has been asked repeated questions about an extended hitless streak (0 for 15 before it ended) and, more significantly, a season-long absence of power and runs batted in. In his third full season in the major leagues, at a moment when he has become one of baseball's most heavily promoted players, the 24-year-old Wright is encountering his first truly uncomfortable moments as a major leaguer.</p>
        <p>''What's so glaring about this is that this is the first time where he's looking a little confused at the plate,'' said Keith Hernandez, a former Mets star who now works as an analyst for SNY, the team's television network. ''He's taking some bad swings, and I've never seen him do that. So you go, ah, he's human, too, after all.''</p>
        <p>In an odd twist, the slump has come at the same time as New York's other All-Star third baseman, Alex Rodriguez, has seemed to liberate himself from his own insecurities at the plate by compiling a record-shattering April. Rodriguez had 14 home runs through Wednesday; Wright has only 20 hits. Rodriguez had 34 runs batted in; Wright has 4. Wright has not had an extra-base hit since April 12, and even an early-season hitting streak, which ended last Friday against Atlanta, was more of a mirage than anything else, considering his .263 average and his 20 strikeouts in 76 at-bats.</p>
        <p>Some of the hitting flaws that Rodriguez has had to correct, Wright is now working diligently to repair. Those around him see steady progress, although the results have not yet shown up in the box scores.</p>
        <p>''If all you look at is the results, then most players would be upset at least 70 percent of the time,'' said the Mets' hitting coach, Rick Down. ''You have to look at what you did during the at-bat, whether you did anything differently, how you felt. It isn't about having the perfect swing. It's about having the swing that's right for you. And David's almost there.''</p>
        <p>But for the moment, with the Mets atop the National League East and the rest of the lineup compensating for his lack of run production, there is an acute awareness that something is not right with Wright.</p>
        <p>Maybe he is trying too hard to make up for a poor postseason in 2006, in which the Mets fell just short of the World Series. Or maybe his swing has not been the same since he competed in, and nearly won, the All-Star Game's home run derby last July. Or maybe he is so bothered by his current failure to hit with runners in scoring position -- he is 3 for 21, a .143 average that is the worst among the team's regulars -- that he is exaggerating the importance of every at-bat and has begun to press.</p>
        <p>Wright disputed all these theories earlier this week, saying: ''You can't try to get it all back in one game. There has to be a process. It's a gradual one, but I'm starting to feel more comfortable.''</p>
        <p>Hours before a game, Wright can be found in the indoor batting cage taking extra swings. Then he joins his teammates for regular batting practice. That is where the process begins. It continues during the game, when, in a split second, he must identify the type of pitch, its speed, its spin and its destination. Teammates and coaches usually marvel at Wright's selectivity at the plate and his ability to create favorable hitting counts, but Down said that this had been a problem for Wright recently.</p>
        <p>''His pitch selection has been poor,'' Down said. ''He's had too much movement, and when you do that, you don't see the ball as well.''</p>
        <p>When a hitter is anxious, as Wright seems to be, he starts his swing early, often committing to a pitch before he recognizes what that pitch is. That can make a hitter vulnerable to a pitch that breaks outside. Wright has been encountering this frequently.</p>
        <p>In addition, pitchers are often working Wright inside, which also forces him to start his swing early because a hitter's bat has to travel farther to hit an inside pitch well. If Wright had his usual discipline, he might worry less about the inside pitches and take some of them, and he would have the patience to start his swing later and drive the outside pitches.</p>
        <p>''A pitch on the outside corner is a pitch that most hitters love,'' Hernandez said. ''But whenever anyone slumps, it looks like it's third down and 40. It's so far away.''</p>
        <p>In other words, when Wright commits too early because of anxiousness or a specific concern over inside pitches, he is not leaving himself in good position to hit outside ones. Wright, a natural gap hitter and not necessarily a natural home run hitter, is normally so good at covering the plate that he often excels at hitting with two strikes, particularly to the opposite field. He tends to generate a lot of topspin when he makes solid contact, causing the ball to dive, unlike someone like the Boston slugger David Ortiz, who hits with the backspin that keeps the ball aloft longer.</p>
        <p>During Wright's dry stretch last August, Manager Willie Randolph felt that he was swinging with a pronounced uppercut, perhaps to remedy a marked drop in home runs in the second half of the season. Hernandez said that he noticed it had returned recently.</p>
        <p>''I'm not saying it's dramatic or anything, but it's the difference between hitting line drives to the opposite field and a fly ball caught at the warning track,'' Hernandez said.</p>
        <p>As Wright answered questions for about five minutes after Wednesday's game, he spoke softly and mentioned that he was encouraged by a few things, namely that he walked for the eighth time in seven games and did not strike out for the second consecutive game.</p>
        <p>Asked if he felt he was on the verge of snapping his slump, Wright halted the reporter.</p>
        <p>''I don't call it a slump,'' Wright said.</p>
        <p>So what is it?</p>
        <p>''It's just a little detour from where I want to be,'' he said.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The Class AAA outfielder Lastings Milledge was placed on the disabled list with sprained ligaments in his right foot.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
