<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ABN Amro Investors Push for Higher Bid</title>
    <meta content="27bank" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/business/worldbusiness/27bank.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843187"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">ABN AMRO Holding NV</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Barclays Bank Plc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Royal Bank of Scotland Plc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EFD6153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="704" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ABN Amro Investors Push for Higher Bid</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">ABN Amro Investors Push for Higher Bid</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIA WERDIGIER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Werdigier, Julia</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, April 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ABN Amro, the bank at the center of the world's largest banking takeover battle, came under fire from shareholders Thursday for not considering a rival bid, and said it was soliciting higher bids for its American unit.</p>
        <p>The bank, the largest in the Netherlands, accepted a $91 billion takeover bid Monday from Barclays Bank of Britain. It agreed the same day to sell LaSalle Bank, its subsidiary based in Chicago, to Bank of America for $21 billion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>ABN Amro came under fire from shareholders for not considering a rival bid, and said it was soliciting higher bids for its American unit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ABN Amro, the bank at the center of the world's largest banking takeover battle, came under fire from shareholders Thursday for not considering a rival bid, and said it was soliciting higher bids for its American unit.</p>
        <p>The bank, the largest in the Netherlands, accepted a $91 billion takeover bid Monday from Barclays Bank of Britain. It agreed the same day to sell LaSalle Bank, its subsidiary based in Chicago, to Bank of America for $21 billion.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, ABN Amro said it was ''actively'' searching for a higher bidder for LaSalle, one of its most attractive assets. Its sale to Bank of America was seen as a move to deflect a higher counterbid for ABN Amro from a group of European banks led by Royal Bank of Scotland.</p>
        <p>The consortium, which also includes Banco Santander Central Hispano of Spain and Fortis, the Belgian banking group, said Wednesday that it would be willing to pay $98.5 billion for ABN Amro, mostly in cash, topping Barclays' all-share offer. But a formal bid is contingent on ABN keeping LaSalle Bank.</p>
        <p>Rijkman W. J. Groenink, ABN Amro's chief executive, defended as the preferred option a combination with Barclays, which would create one of the largest global banks. Royal Bank of Scotland and its two partners plan to break up the bank and split the assets among them.</p>
        <p>During heated discussion at ABN Amro's shareholder meeting in The Hague on Thursday, some shareholders accused management of hindering a constructive bidding competition and depriving them of a higher price for their shares.</p>
        <p>Asked about the approach by the consortium, Mr. Groenink said, ''It is our duty to consider any compelling rival offer if it exists, but at the moment there is no offer.''</p>
        <p>Some shareholders also criticized the management for selling LaSalle without open bidding and without seeking shareholder approval. But others voiced their support for ABN Amro's management and congratulated Mr. Groenink for trying to avoid a breakup of the bank.</p>
        <p>Mr. Groenink also said that ABN Amro had agreed to provide the Royal Bank of Scotland group with the same financial information Barclays had received.</p>
        <p>But the Royal Bank of Scotland group asked ABN Amro to drop a provision of the confidentiality agreement that it must sign to get access to ABN Amro's financial information. The provision prohibits the group from making an offer over the next 12 months without the written consent of ABN Amro. Should ABN deny consent, the group would have to make a hostile offer, which would go directly to the shareholders.</p>
        <p>At the shareholder meeting, Mr. Groenink rejected a shareholder's accusation that the provision was ''a trick,'' saying the same provision was included in a confidentiality agreement Barclays signed earlier.</p>
        <p>By law, ABN Amro and its financial advisers, led by UBS, have until May 6 -- 14 days from the date of the announced sale -- to look for a higher offer for LaSalle.</p>
        <p>Some analysts have said that JPMorgan Chase or other banks looking to increase their footprint in America could be interested in LaSalle. But they also pointed out that Bank of America was probably already the highest bidder for LaSalle, because acquiring it would make Bank of America the largest banking group in Chicago.</p>
        <p>If a higher bidder comes forward, Bank of America has five days to match that bid. If ABN Amro accepts a rival bid, it must pay a $200 million breakup fee to Bank of America.</p>
        <p>Separately, ABN Amro on Thursday said it was setting aside 365 million euros ($496 million) that ''will be sufficient to resolve'' a Justice Department investigation into the bank's dollar-clearing activities and compliance policies. The action will reduce ABN Amro's first-quarter profit to 1.06 billion euros, an adjustment from a figure released after the bank's bidders requested financial data to help them value the company.</p>
        <p>The criminal investigation into ABN Amro follows an $80 million civil penalty that it paid in December 2005 after federal and state banking regulators found it had violated American money-laundering laws and sanctions against Iran and Libya. Now, the bank said it was in ''advanced'' discussions with the Justice Department in what some observers suggest could foreshadow a broader sweep of the global banking industry.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
