<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Interim Premier of Somalia Claims Victory Over Insurgents</title>
    <meta content="27somalia" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/world/africa/27somalia.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843192"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Somalia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mogadishu (Somalia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ethiopia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ibrahim, Mohammed</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maxamuud, Yuusuf</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gedi, Ali Mohammed (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gettleman, Jeffrey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ethiopia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Somalia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Ethiopia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Somalia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Somalia</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Ethiopia</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EED6153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="487" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Interim Premier of Somalia Claims Victory Over Insurgents</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Interim Premier of Somalia Claims Victory Over Insurgents</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFFREY GETTLEMAN; Mohammed Ibrahim and Yuusuf Maxamuud contributed reporting from Mogadishu, Somalia.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gettleman, Jeffrey; Maxamuud, Yuusuf; Ibrahim, Mohammed</byline>
      <dateline>NAIROBI, Kenya, April 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Somalia's transitional prime minister Ali Mohammed Gedi declares turning point in battle with insurgents after month of combat that has killed more than 1,000 civilians; says Mogadishu will be under control soon; Ethiopian-led forces aligned with Somali government push deep into insurgent territory (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ali Mohammed Gedi, Somalia's transitional prime minister, declared a turning point on Thursday in his battle with insurgents after a month of heavy combat that has killed more than 1,000 civilians.</p>
        <p>''We have won,'' he said at a news conference in Mogadishu, Somalia's shell-shocked capital.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ali Mohammed Gedi declared a turning point in his battle with insurgents after a month of heavy combat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ali Mohammed Gedi, Somalia's transitional prime minister, declared a turning point on Thursday in his battle with insurgents after a month of heavy combat that has killed more than 1,000 civilians.</p>
        <p>''We have won,'' he said at a news conference in Mogadishu, Somalia's shell-shocked capital.</p>
        <p>As he spoke, Ethiopian-led forces aligned with the Somali government pushed deep into insurgent territory, much of which has been reduced to smoldering rubble. More than 100 gunmen came out with their hands up and surrendered to government troops, Mr. Gedi said.</p>
        <p>''Soon, Mogadishu will be under our control,'' he said.</p>
        <p>How soon, though, remains an open question. Witnesses said that loud gun battles resumed Thursday night in southern Mogadishu as insurgents, to cover their retreat, fired rocket-propelled grenades even after Mr. Gedi's declaration. Many neighborhoods remained deadly no-go zones, and many residents seemed decidedly more pessimistic than Mr. Gedi.</p>
        <p>''These guys will just go underground -- again,'' said Hassan Mohammed Isse, a banana seller in Mogadishu, referring to the insurgents.</p>
        <p>If the heavy fighting lets up, it will follow the pattern of this conflict since it started in December. Somalia's militias are no match, in toe-to-toe combat, for the better trained and much better equipped Ethiopian Army. The Ethiopians demonstrated that decisively in early battles when Somali militias tried frontal assaults against Ethiopian troops, who then cut them down by the truckload.</p>
        <p>Ethiopia, with covert American support, intervened in Somalia last year to overthrow an Islamist administration that controlled much of Somalia and was widely suspected of harboring anti-Ethiopian rebel groups.</p>
        <p>Major combat ended after a week of Ethiopian airstrikes, and Ethiopian troops succeeded in bringing Somalia's transitional government to the capital for the first time. But the Islamist militias, instead of joining the government, began a hit-and-run guerrilla war against government and Ethiopian forces.</p>
        <p>Their popular support seemed to grow, and the clashes intensified this past month as insurgents grew bolder and attacked in larger numbers and in daylight. The Ethiopians hit back with heavy artillery and tanks.</p>
        <p>Civilians have been caught in the cross-fire, with more than 1,000 killed and countless wounded. The understaffed and undersupplied hospitals were hardly refuges; even some of those have been shelled.</p>
        <p>The fighting has driven 350,000 people from their homes, according to the United Nations, with some evacuees fleeing to squalid camps where they have been forced at gunpoint to pay a shade tax to rest under trees. United Nations officials also said the transitional government had hindered efforts to deliver aid and even turned back a food convoy in early April.</p>
        <p>But on Thursday, the United Nations made its first major food distribution to the camps ringing Mogadishu, passing out 350 tons of corn, vegetable oil and high-protein grain.</p>
        <p>''It was a test case, and it worked well,'' said Peter Smerdon, a spokesman for the United Nations' World Food Program.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
