<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Team In Disrepair Awaits Red Sox</title>
    <meta content="27toronto" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843293"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Toronto Blue Jays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E4DD123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="743" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Team In Disrepair Awaits Red Sox</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Things are messed up around Yankee Stadium, the Yankees announced last night.</p>
        <p>This observation had nothing to do with the current losing streak, which increased to six games when the Toronto Blue Jays beat them, 6-0, while spoiling the major league debut of the pitching prospect Phil Hughes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Things are messed up around Yankee Stadium, the Yankees announced last night.</p>
        <p>This observation had nothing to do with the current losing streak, which increased to six games when the Toronto Blue Jays beat them, 6-0, while spoiling the major league debut of the pitching prospect Phil Hughes.</p>
        <p>The declaration concerned street repairs and construction of the new stadium across the street that could cause parking problems for big crowds expected to attend the three-game series with the Boston Red Sox, beginning tonight.</p>
        <p>Take public transit, the Yankees warned. Driving could be as frustrating as the losing streak, the longest since they lost six in succession from May 28 through June 3 in 2005. And while there may not be baseball panic amid the construction dust around 161st Street, some things need fixing.</p>
        <p>In the previous five defeats, the Yankees averaged 5.8 runs. But last night, they were shut out for the first time this season and managed only four hits. They played without Derek Jeter, whose thigh was not so sore that he could not dash past reporters without comment afterward.</p>
        <p>He moved faster than Jason Giambi, the Yankees' lumbering designated hitter, who was thrown out trying to stretch an opposite-field single into a double in the fourth inning. Was this a man trying too hard to inspire slumping teammates? Giambi was not available for comment after the game.</p>
        <p>Even the weather went against them. A potential home run by Alex Rodriguez was blown back by the wind. And Rodriguez grinned sheepishly in the ninth when he caught a line drive but ignored a runner who was caught off base, apparently thinking there were three outs. He, too, chose not to speak.</p>
        <p>Manager Joe Torre maintained a calm demeanor and said afterward that he did not ''want everybody in that room sensing that we are throwing our hands up frustrated that we can't win.''</p>
        <p>But Torre's actions also speak. In the first month, he has used Hughes, whom he promised the team would not promote until late in the season. He has used his closer, Mariano Rivera, in the eighth inning after vowing not to do so.</p>
        <p>And he has used his best starter, Andy Pettitte, twice in relief. The fans who drive, walk or ride the subway tonight will see Pettitte start for the last-place team in the American League East against the division-leading Red Sox and Daisuke Matsuzaka, Boston's expensive new star from Japan.</p>
        <p>The serendipity of their matchup could provide an interesting subplot. When Matsuzaka last faced the Yankees, last Sunday night at Fenway Park, he hit Jeter and Rodriguez with pitches when the Sox won, 7-6.</p>
        <p>But Pettitte said he would not seek revenge. ''I don't feel I have to establish anything,'' Pettitte said. ''No one said one word to me about it.'' Of retaliation protocol, Pettitte recalled hitting Boston's Kevin Youkilis on Friday night at Fenway Park in his last start.</p>
        <p>He said that if teams retaliated for hit batters, it was usually in the same game or in the game afterward. Matsuzaka hit the Yankees' batters two days after Pettitte hit the Boston batter. Pettitte was supposed to start Wednesday night against Toronto.</p>
        <p>But that game was rained out and Pettitte's start was pushed back until today so Hughes could make his major league debut without what Torre called the ''carnival atmosphere'' that usually accompanies a Yankees-Red Sox series.</p>
        <p>Pettitte, 1-0 with a 1.78 earned run average, has bolstered a rotation disrupted by injuries to veterans and supplanted with mixed results from five rookies.</p>
        <p>Regarding the Red Sox, he said that he had the perspective of a 34-year-old veteran. ''I don't get too worked up anymore,'' he said. ''I did a long time ago.''</p>
        <p>Speaking in general, Pettitte said: ''We are not pitching good as a staff. We've had to use our bullpen a little more than we would have liked. There's no doubt as a starting staff we need to step up. We're on the mend. We're going to be fine.''</p>
        <p>Until last night, the Yankees had led in every game of their losing streak. Johnny Damon, the former Boston star who plays center field for the Yankees, reflected on squandering three leads last weekend at Fenway Park.</p>
        <p>''When you have a shot to win all three games and lose them all, it does become frustrating,'' Damon said.</p>
        <p>''We definitely need to do better. We've just had a tough run of it.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
