<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HAVENS | Naramata, British Columbia; A Sandy Beach, a Sunny Climate and Canadian Wine</title>
    <meta content="27havens" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/realestate/greathomes/27havens_ready.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843157"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Havens | Naramata, British Columbia"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Naramata (British Columbia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">British Columbia (Canada)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mackin, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Havens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Great Homes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Luxury and Vacations/Vacation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/British Columbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">British Columbia (Canada)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E2D8153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1398" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HAVENS | Naramata, British Columbia; A Sandy Beach, a Sunny Climate and Canadian Wine</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Sandy Beach, a Sunny Climate and Canadian Wine</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB MACKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mackin, Bob</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Naramata, British Columbia, as place to live or visit; photos; maps ( M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>VINEYARDS, orchards and an almost inexhaustible supply of sun are luring second-home buyers to Naramata, a British Columbia village some 50 miles north of the United States border.</p>
        <p>It is part of a region called the Naramata Bench, which stretches north along the east bank of Okanagan Lake from the city of Penticton to the Okanagan Mountain Provincial Park. Sandy beaches dot the twisty 12-mile shore, some at the foot of imposing bluffs. It's obscure yet accessible for those seeking second homes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vineyards, orchards and great weather are luring second-home buyers to Naramata, a British Columbia village 50 miles north of the United States border.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>VINEYARDS, orchards and an almost inexhaustible supply of sun are luring second-home buyers to Naramata, a British Columbia village some 50 miles north of the United States border.</p>
        <p>It is part of a region called the Naramata Bench, which stretches north along the east bank of Okanagan Lake from the city of Penticton to the Okanagan Mountain Provincial Park. Sandy beaches dot the twisty 12-mile shore, some at the foot of imposing bluffs. It's obscure yet accessible for those seeking second homes.</p>
        <p>''There's a lot of intention in the community to preserve the character and charm of what's here,'' said Jane Shaak, a real estate agent with Royal LePage, who grew up in Naramata.</p>
        <p>In the village, the California Mission-style Heritage Inn rises at the foot of Robinson Avenue. John Moore Robinson, the namesake of the calm thoroughfare, built the hotel 99 years ago. Restored in 2001, the inn has become a catalyst for Naramata, which was known as East Summerland until the early 20th century.</p>
        <p>Mr. Robinson discovered the name during a séance led by the wife of the local postmaster. It is said that she conjured the spirit of an Indian chief who spoke lovingly of his wife, Nar-a-mat-ah. Mr. Robinson liked the way it rolled off his tongue.</p>
        <p>Wharf Park was where concertgoers destined for the local opera house disembarked from a paddle-wheeler, while fruit crates were loaded onto cars on the Kettle Valley Railway. The Sun Fresh Cooperative's fruit-packing plant remains, but the opera house and railroad tracks are gone.</p>
        <p>The arid climate and abundant sun are ideal for ripening grapes at the 16 wineries along meandering Naramata Road. These include Lake Breeze Vineyards, the producer of an award-winning pinot gris. The Okanagan Spring Wine Festival is May 3 to 6 (www.owfs.com).</p>
        <p>William Cambridge, a former Napa Valley wine concierge-cum-restaurantconsultant, sampled Seattle, Hawaii and Santa Barbara before settling on Naramata for a second home. He bought a 900-square-foot bungalow and 400-square-foot studio near Robinson Avenue with his wife, Cherie, in 2000 for 100,000 Canadian dollars..</p>
        <p>Real estate agents say that while Naramata is attracting more attention as a second-home community, it is remaining true to its practical agricultural underpinnings, even if grapes for wine overshadow peaches, apples, apricots and cherries.</p>
        <p>''People who are building here generally bring an architectural sensibility that befits the area; that is, no flights of fancy with French chateaus or Tuscan villas,'' Mr. Cambridge said. ''Rather, new houses tend to have a sturdy feel, often using timber-frame construction and using Arts and Crafts detailing.''</p>
        <p>The Scene</p>
        <p>Naramata's summer temperatures hover in the mid-80s and dip just below 32 in winter, pleasing makers of ice wines. Skiing, snowboarding and snowshoeing are available less than an hour west at the Apex Mountain resort from November to April.</p>
        <p>In warmer weather, children of all ages line up at the Naramata general store for a scoop of ice cream, and across the street, the Village Grounds Cafe doubles as community living room and sundeck.</p>
        <p>The village's spiritual and physical heart is the Naramata Centre, a 23-acre retreat and conference center of the United Church of Canada that was built in 1947. There are no gates, and the public is welcome to use the semiprivate beach.</p>
        <p>Janis Magnuson, a lawyer and publisher from Calgary, Alberta, discovered Naramata as an 11-year-old baby sitter employed by a minister at the Naramata Centre. She left the lakeside retreat with bandaged ears that summer after a bit too much fun in the sun.</p>
        <p>''My Naramata memories always come with a little pain attached,'' Ms. Magnuson said, laughing as she looked across the lake from her patio. She and husband, Ray Sobol, found a peaceful second home in the area as a refuge from Calgary.</p>
        <p>They were looking at properties in Penticton and Summerland during a winery tour in fall 2005 when they had an epiphany. ''We were on the wrong side of the lake,'' she said. They spent almost 400,000 Canadian dollars (about $348,000 at the current exchange rate of 1.15 Canadian dollars to the United States dollar) for their 1,870-square-foot house with a view of Giant's Head Mountain in Summerland. They enjoy the small-town charm and simple pleasures, like gazing at stars without the glare of city lights.</p>
        <p>Glenn Albin, who edits Ocean Drive magazine in Miami Beach, visits Naramata five times a year with his partner, Alexander Albrecht. Their 2,000-square-foot modern cedar house was built in the 1960s. It is on 3.5 acres near a mountainside and is valued at 900,000 Canadian dollars.</p>
        <p>''Naramata's a very private, behind-the-hedges sort of place, but once inside, the dinners and parties are full of creative, energetic, soulful people,'' Mr. Albin said. ''Naramata is also very accepting. It's one thing to mix orchardists and grape growers, but here there are rich and poor, straight and gay, country people and urbanites. There are more tractors than Porsches, and that's the way I'd like it to remain.''</p>
        <p>He and Mr. Albrecht plan to plant an acre of syrah vines this year.</p>
        <p>Pros</p>
        <p>The village is unincorporated, so property taxes are low, averaging 1,800 Canadian dollars a year. Penticton, with 33,000 people, is 20 minutes away at the south tip of the lake; Kelowna, population 105,000, is 90 minutes north. An ultraviolet water filtration system is expected to be completed this year.</p>
        <p>Cons</p>
        <p>Naramata has few public moorings, though Penticton has ample marina space. The village has few amenities, which means Penticton is a frequent destination. You could start a hobby winery, but large players dominate the commercial market.</p>
        <p>The Real Estate Market</p>
        <p>A 2,200-square-foot house averages 439,000 Canadian dollars, according to the South Okanagan Real Estate Board, nearly 500 percent above the average for a similar property two decades ago.</p>
        <p>Waterfront property isn't often available. A cozy, one-story waterfront cottage on a small lot was offered last year for about 1.2 million Canadian dollars, and a three-bedroom, 2,960-square-foot house on 4.5 acres with its own beach was listed at 5.1 million Canadian dollars; both were outside the village. A 10-acre organic fruit and vegetable farm near the village with a four-bedroom house was priced at nearly 1.6 million Canadian dollars.</p>
        <p>LAY OF THE LAND</p>
        <p>POPULATION -- Around 2,000 in the Naramata Bench area, according to the 2006 Canadian census.  SIZE -- The Naramata Bench area is roughly 12 square miles.  WHO'S BUYING -- Entrepreneurial couples from the Western Provinces of Canada and the Pacific Northwest of the United States.  GETTING THERE -- Naramata is roughly a five-hour drive east of Vancouver and a five-hour drive northwest of Spokane, Wash. Daily air service links Vancouver with Penticton.  WHILE YOU'RE LOOKING -- The 12-room Naramata Heritage Inn and Spa (3625 First Street, Naramata; 866-617-1188; www.naramatainn.com) was built in 1908. Rooms are 130 to 460 Canadian dollars ($113 to $400 at 1.15 Canadian dollars to the U.S. dollar). If there's no room at the inn, visit its Cobblestone Wine Bar and Rock Oven dining room. Spiller's Corner B &amp; B (475 Upper Bench Road North, Penticton; 800-610-3794; www.spillerestates.com), is open May through October. A restored 1930 bungalow, it is between a working fruit orchard and the Spiller winery. Rooms are 130 Canadian dollars.</p>
        <p>THREE FOR SALE  A Shoreline Far From Hectic Resorts and Urban Stampedes</p>
        <p>Information on properties was provided by the listing agents.</p>
        <p>WHAT -- 3-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $346,000</p>
        <p>This remodeled one-bathroom ranch-style house is in Naramata. The roof and wiring are new. The listing price is 398,000 Canadian dollars. Agents: Jeff Queen and Julius Blooomfield, ReMax Front Street Realty; (250) 486-5333; www.jeffqueen.ca.</p>
        <p>WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $686,000</p>
        <p>This four-year-old 2,700-square-foot house in Naramata has three and a half bathrooms. There are a wood-burning stove and a hot tub. The flooring and woodwork throughout the house are made of fir. The listing price is 789,000 Canadian dollars. Agent: Dianna Smith, Sutton-Power 1 Realty; (250) 490-5020; www.sutton.com.</p>
        <p>WHAT -- 1-bedroom cottage  HOW MUCH -- $1,214,000</p>
        <p>This 500-square-foot 39-year-old house is on a third of an acre in Naramata with 87 feet of frontage on Okanagan Lake. There are a bathroom and a fireplace. The property also includes a separate cabin. The listing price is 1,396,000 Canadian dollars. Agent: Julius Bloomfield, ReMax Front Street Realty; (250) 492-2233; www.frontstreetrealty.net.</p>
        <p>Havens | Naramata, British Columbia</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
