<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Welcome to Red Sock Nation</title>
    <meta content="27sock" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843289"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E5DD123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="797" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Welcome to Red Sock Nation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR and JACK CURRY; Jack Curry contributed from Baltimore, Richard Sandomir contributed from New York. Tyler Kepner and Joe Lapointe contributed reporting from New York.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard; Curry, Jack</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is heroic hosiery to Red Sox Nation, a sock bloodied in postseason combat, a symbol of Boston's first World Series victory in 86 years.</p>
        <p>This most intrepid sock, a cottony artifact of triumph, covered Curt Schilling's right foot in Game 2 of the 2004 World Series. He had had a surgical procedure on an ankle tendon, and sometime during his four-hit, six-inning performance, the sock was discolored, presumably with his blood, just as one of his socks had been during his victory over the Yankees in Game 6 of that season's American League Championship Series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is heroic hosiery to Red Sox Nation, a sock bloodied in postseason combat, a symbol of Boston's first World Series victory in 86 years.</p>
        <p>This most intrepid sock, a cottony artifact of triumph, covered Curt Schilling's right foot in Game 2 of the 2004 World Series. He had had a surgical procedure on an ankle tendon, and sometime during his four-hit, six-inning performance, the sock was discolored, presumably with his blood, just as one of his socks had been during his victory over the Yankees in Game 6 of that season's American League Championship Series.</p>
        <p>Today, the sock from the World Series is in the Baseball Hall of Fame in Cooperstown, N.Y. It has three larger dark stains, one of which resembles the ''Ghostbusters'' logo, and several smaller ones.</p>
        <p>So it was Wednesday night that the sock was a victim of what the Red Sox might call footwear blasphemy. Gary Thorne, an Orioles announcer calling the Boston-Baltimore game, said that Doug Mirabelli, a Red Sox catcher, had told him the sock had not been bloodied, but painted red.</p>
        <p>''It was all for P.R.,'' Thorne said, which Mirabelli angrily denied afterward, while also disavowing any knowledge that he knew who Thorne was.</p>
        <p>Thorne said yesterday that it was a misunderstanding arising from a brief clubhouse conversation with Mirabelli after 2004. At the end of their chat, Thorne told reporters yesterday: ''I kind of threw in a, 'Was the sock painted or not?' And I got a response that I thought, when he was talking about it, was serious.''</p>
        <p>Mirabelli said he never meant to give Thorne the impression that the legend of the sock had been perpetrated in cahoots with Sherwin-Williams, nor could he understand how Thorne could come to the conclusion he did.</p>
        <p>''He said he just assumed that that was what I meant, that that meant the sock was fake and it was all a publicity stunt,'' Mirabelli said. ''There was never any doubt in my mind that was blood on that sock.''</p>
        <p>Thorne said he now recognizes that Mirabelli was being sarcastic, yet he stood up for what he believed Mirabelli meant, but clearly did not.</p>
        <p>''I didn't say something I didn't believe,'' Thorne said. ''I would never do that.''</p>
        <p>Before the Red Sox ended their 86-year World Series drought, their lore was so much about the Curse of the Bambino. But since then, there have been commotions about artifacts of their victory: the refusal by Doug Mientkiewicz to give up the ball he caught to end the 2004 World Series, a dispute that eventually ended when he gave it to the Hall of Fame; and doubt cast over the fluid that smeared Schilling's sock.</p>
        <p>''It's disappointing because there are a faction of people who want to believe'' that Schilling had not bled from his surgical wound, said Red Sox Manager Terry Francona. ''It's a shame.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Mientkiewicz, now a Yankee, said he was certain of the blood's provenance. ''I saw him get cut open,'' he said. ''I know what he did for us and it was pretty much heroic. Schill likes attention. I don't think he likes this much attention.''</p>
        <p>Johnny Damon, another 2004 teammate of Schilling's, said, ''As far as I know, it's authentic.'' Then, he smiled.</p>
        <p>Schilling, normally loquacious, refused to discuss his blood or his sock.</p>
        <p>If serious doubt about what smeared the sock had been raised, a forensic scientist like Lawrence Kobilinsky could at least determine if it was blood. He could drive to the Hall of Fame, shave off tiny fibers from the sock, combine them with a solution in a test tube and draw out enough to test on a HemaTrace card to determine the presence of human hemoglobin. If two pinks lines appear, it is human blood.</p>
        <p>''You don't need a big piece of the sock to get enough to test,'' said Kobilinsky, the chairman of the science department at the John Jay College of Criminal Justice in Manhattan. ''It's not so holy to me that I wouldn't cut it up, but you don't need to destroy it. It's not a holy icon. It's not the Shroud of Turin.''</p>
        <p>That would not happen, even if Thorne had not misconstrued what Mirabelli said. The Hall will not let ''CSI'' slice up its artifacts. Brad Horn, a spokesman for the Hall, said: ''Curt's word is golden. We have no reason to doubt his statement and his generosity in giving the artifact to the museum.'' The color of the stain at the time it was taken to the Hall in a Ziploc bag by Schilling's in-laws ''was not red paintish,'' Horn said.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
