<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bringing the Mountain Bike to Metropolis</title>
    <meta content="27adventurer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/travel/escapes/27adventurer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843132"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ADVENTURER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mountain Biking</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Minneapolis (Minn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Regenold, Stephen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Adventurer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Biking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Minnesota/Minneapolis and St. Paul</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Minnesota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Minneapolis (Minn)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E6D8153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1000" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bringing the Mountain Bike to Metropolis</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bringing the Mountain Bike to Metropolis</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN REGENOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Regenold, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Theodore Wirth Off-Road Cycling Trail near downtown Minneapolis and other mountain biking tracks in metropolitan areas across country; photos; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ever since the mountain bikers arrived, the freaky Goth people with vampire teeth don't hang around much anymore.</p>
        <p>And the big scary naked men peering out of the woods? Fewer and farther between, said Josh Erdmann, a longtime area rider.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In several cities, bike tracks may be helping to revive parks that fell into disrepair and disrepute.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ever since the mountain bikers arrived, the freaky Goth people with vampire teeth don't hang around much anymore.</p>
        <p>And the big scary naked men peering out of the woods? Fewer and farther between, said Josh Erdmann, a longtime area rider.</p>
        <p>Indeed, at the Theodore Wirth Off-Road Cycling Trail near downtown Minneapolis, where an 18-inch-wide dirt singletrack traces circuitously through the woods, mountain biking has altered the milieu of the place.</p>
        <p>''That creepy nude beach down the hill hardly comes to mind anymore,'' Mr. Erdmann said.</p>
        <p>Across the country, in cities from Philadelphia to Santa Fe, mountain biking is gaining as a viable urban activity. Extensive trail networks designated for the knobby-tire crowd, some many miles in length, now wind through parks like Theodore Wirth in Minneapolis and Powhite Park in Richmond, Va., or under freeway viaducts in places like Seattle.</p>
        <p>Adrian Benepe, the New York parks commissioner, said the grand opening of the city's first sanctioned mountain biking trail will be on May 19. A huge volunteer effort and $100,000 in government financing built four miles of singletrack at Highbridge Park in northern Manhattan on a steep hillside where a roller coaster once stood.</p>
        <p>''Highbridge was an abandoned, scary place, with a pack of stray dogs, homeless encampments and used hypodermic needles everywhere,'' said Jamie Bogner, co-founder of the New York City Mountain Bike Association. ''Mountain biking is giving it some new life.''</p>
        <p>About 15 major metropolitan areas have legitimized mountain biking in urban parks or on municipal land, including Pittsburgh; Austin, Tex.; Louisville, Ky.; Tucson; Salt Lake City; suburban Los Angeles; and Vancouver, British Columbia.</p>
        <p>Chris Bernhardt, a consultant with the International Mountain Bicycling Association from Hood River, Ore., said the face of the sport is changing, with urban terrain receiving more attention than traditional wilderness trails in some areas.</p>
        <p>''It's great to take a weeklong bike trip to Moab or Colorado, but people want trails closer to home for riding on weekends or after work,'' said Mr. Bernhardt, who works with bike clubs, park managers and municipalities in metropolitan areas to prepare plans and build trails.</p>
        <p>The increasing desire to suit up, clip in and ride a mountain bike from home to nearby trails is prompting recreation managers to reassess a sport long outlawed in city parks.</p>
        <p>Resistance to the sport, which opponents cite as a dangerous and trail-damaging activity, was widespread for years, with hiking clubs, equestrians, birders, environmentalists and other groups regularly lobbying against mountain biking within city limits. Park boards and city governments are often preoccupied with liability and insurance concerns, Mr. Bernhardt said.</p>
        <p>But sustainable trail-building guidelines, now widely used to limit erosion, and standards promoted by IMBA -- never scare animals, leave no trace, always yield -- have helped validate the sport.</p>
        <p>Some cycling organizations cite statistics that show mountain biking to be no more dangerous than baseball.</p>
        <p>An aging cycling demographic, with many mountain bikers in their 30s or 40s, gives riders more voice, according to Lou Mazzante, editor of Bike Magazine in San Juan Capistrano, Calif. ''Mountain biking has matured, and many riders who've been at it for 15 or 20 years are now in positions of power,'' he said.</p>
        <p>IN Minneapolis, it was the mayor, R. T. Rybak, an avid cyclist, and John Erwin, a former parks commissioner, who spurred development of the city's first recognized urban singletrack. Mr. Rybak noted his desire for the city's park board to work with local cyclists at a meeting in 2003.</p>
        <p>Today, the Theodore Wirth Off-Road Cycling Trail, which had its grand opening in June 2005, includes 4.36 miles of twisting singletrack with jumps, stunts and banked turns. Up to 200 riders might pedal there on a busy Saturday, according to Shawn Sheely, president of Minneapolis Off-Road Cycling Advocates, an organization that worked with the Minneapolis Park and Recreation Board to create the trails.</p>
        <p>On a Saturday earlier this month, amid the white noise of a nearby highway, Mr. Sheely met up with a half-dozen riding friends for a lap at Theodore Wirth, which is the largest park in Minneapolis. The bikers, some dressed in jeans, others in cycling shorts, pedaled on roads or paved paths from their homes in the city to gather at the park's entrance.</p>
        <p>''First time out this year,'' said Jonathan Beale, a 36-year-old college professor, who stood adjusting a helmet strap.</p>
        <p>A golf cart tootled by on the lawn behind the bikers, motoring uphill toward the park's par-3 course.</p>
        <p>''Let's ride,'' Mr. Sheely shouted.</p>
        <p>At Wirth, where wooded little hills hide lakes and boardwalk-equipped bogs, the deep urban forest is infamous for its ability to attract recluses, weirdos or worse.</p>
        <p>''That's the old Satanic altar,'' said Mr. Erdmann, a 29-year-old film producer, only half-joking as he pointed to a decrepit, mossy table secluded in the woods.</p>
        <p>Biking has dispersed much of the riffraff, Mr. Sheely said. He believes the simple presence of more people using the park for cycling makes it safer. ''It's an interesting side benefit,'' he said. ''Some people didn't feel safe back here before.''</p>
        <p>Five minutes of pedaling brought the cyclists to Wirth's first obstacle, a 30-foot-long incline of rocks just uphill from an old garbage dump. Railroad tracks and an industrial building were just visible through the trees below.</p>
        <p>In the crisscrossing shadow of a rusty fence, Hurl Everstone, 39, a bike shop owner, spun through the rocky ramp, his front tire bouncing and weaving on the climb.</p>
        <p>Up next, April Bergman, a 35-year-old assistant at an ad agency, downshifted to pedal through. ''Crank it,'' someone yelled.</p>
        <p>Gears clicked, tires spun, but Ms. Bergman sputtered, grabbing her brakes, plopping a foot down for balance.</p>
        <p>''Dang, no luck,'' she said, pushing her bike uphill before jumping back on to ride.</p>
        <p>Winding away into the woods, the trail continued for three miles, climbing hills, dipping in and out of little ravines, banking corners on berms. The riders drifted quietly off, standing up on their pedals, twisting through trees still leaf-bare in the early spring sun.</p>
        <p>ADVENTURER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
