<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Pointillist 'Contagion' in Italy</title>
    <meta content="27gugg" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/arts/design/27gugg.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843165"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Guggenheim, Solomon R, Museum</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E0D8153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1247" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Pointillist 'Contagion' in Italy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Pointillist ‘Contagion’ in Italy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Roberta</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Painted measles'' is what one hostile critic called the efforts of the Italian followers of French Neo-Impressionism. The occasion was the first Brera Triennale in Milan in 1891. The reference was to the tiny dots of color that covered their canvases. The technique, also called Pointillism, was formulated by the Parisian Georges Seurat in the early 1880s as he assimilated the latest scientific theories about color, light and perception.</p>
        <p>The Divisionists, as they were eventually called, were reviled for introducing the ''contagion'' of a modern, foreign painting style at a point when Italy, united only since 1861, was striving to define its national identity. (The Brera exhibition was part of this strategy.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The pioneers of Italian modernism and their art are the focus of a rare, compressed, mercurial exhibition at the Guggenheim Museum.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Painted measles'' is what one hostile critic called the efforts of the Italian followers of French Neo-Impressionism. The occasion was the first Brera Triennale in Milan in 1891. The reference was to the tiny dots of color that covered their canvases. The technique, also called Pointillism, was formulated by the Parisian Georges Seurat in the early 1880s as he assimilated the latest scientific theories about color, light and perception.</p>
        <p>The Divisionists, as they were eventually called, were reviled for introducing the ''contagion'' of a modern, foreign painting style at a point when Italy, united only since 1861, was striving to define its national identity. (The Brera exhibition was part of this strategy.)</p>
        <p>They were also attacked for their pointedly political subject matter. While Seurat sometimes distanced himself from the recreational bliss of the Impressionists with images of workers and entertainers, the Divisionists were unusually conscious of social inequities and the ways industrialization was making them worse. Several of these artists embraced socialism to some degree, especially in the early 1890s, and strove to combine a radical painting style with an equally radical political outlook.</p>
        <p>History has not been much kinder than those critics to these pioneers of Italian modernism, who were also forerunners of the Futurists. But now their art is the focus of a rare, compressed, mercurial exhibition at the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum called ''Divisionism/Neo-Impressionism: Arcadia and Anarchy.''</p>
        <p>The show features artists who are little known outside Italy, including Giovanni Segantini, Emilio Longoni, Angelo Morbelli and the quirky Vittore Grubicy de Dragon, a Milanese critic, dealer and painter who championed Pointillism. The era's most famous image -- a study for it is included here -- probably is ''The Fourth Estate,'' with its MGM grandeur and sepia-toned rows of handsome Italian workers marching toward a new dawn behind two men and a woman holding a baby. It is the ''American Gothic'' of Italy, a staple of posters, advertisements and cartoons. But you probably won't know the name of Giuseppe Pellizza da Volpedo, who painted it.</p>
        <p>The Guggenheim show may end this era's obscurity, but it also helps explain it. Organized by Vivien Greene, the museum's associate curator and a scholar of Divisionism, the show pits the Italians against Seurat and his French, Dutch and Belgian followers. It shows that the Italians were stylistically all over the place, pushing Pointillism toward realism, classicism, Symbolism, class consciousness and even Impressionism. They borrowed riffs from the Pre-Raphaelites, Puvis de Chavannes and Ferdinand Hodler, and they modified their styles when government suppression threatened. All this in an exhibition of only 37 paintings, 16 of which are by non-Italians.</p>
        <p>Ultimately this selection is long on history and short on truly convincing art. But the material is so fresh and there is so much going on in terms of history, politics and painting that it almost doesn't matter. The show opens a new window on the spread of Modernism outside France. If many of the works are period pieces, they are also immensely appealing, big-hearted and physically robust.</p>
        <p>Ms. Greene has divided the show into sections on light, rural life, social problems, landscape and Symbolism that flow together almost seamlessly, despite the striking shifts in subject matter and style. For the Italians Seurat's innovation was less fixed style than a new consciousness of paint as substance. It inspired them to use it physically in ways that ranged far and sometimes wide of dots.</p>
        <p>Segantini, the first Italian to take up Divisionism, evolved a narrow, threadlike stroke that became known as the ''Segantini stitch.'' He applied its dense tweediness to an essentially realist armature, maintaining a stylistic consistency that stands out here. Usually his colors are fairly undivided if not monochromatic, as in a large, chocolaty, wonderfully tactile portrait of Carlo Rotta, a Milanese soap magnate, sitting at his desk in the russet glow of a lamp. The all-over density continues in ''Return From the Woods'' (1890), which shows a woman pulling a sled through snow toward a village; its austerity of form is broken only by a cargo of tangled branches worthy of Lucian Freud. ''Spring Pasture'' (1896) has a similar if grainier force, thanks to the tiny threads of paint that slalom across snowy peak, granite and Alpine grass.</p>
        <p>In contrast Longoni presents a different personality and style each time out. His ''Orator of the Strike'' (1890-1), which caused a furor at the Brera Triennale, shows a laborer clinging to scaffolding, raising his fist and shouting to a sea of upturned faces. It is a rarity: a near riot rendered in the juicy staccato of Impressionism. ''Reflections of a Starving Man'' (1894) in which a pauper gazes through a restaurant window at a sleek couple dining inside, is smoothly illustrational, though it caused Longoni to be threatened with charges of inciting class hatred. By 1903 he had retreated into the Symbolist reveries of ''The Sound of the Stream,'' with its violin-playing muse and immense shelf of water. But in 1905, he bounced back with the powerful ''Glacier,'' an implacable shelf of ice and rock. Its thick ribbons of paint turn the Segantini stitch into nubby weave that even an Abstract Expressionist might admire.</p>
        <p>Clearly traditional perspective tended to take precedent over the flattened protomodern serenity of Seurat. Angelo Morbelli used photographs to achieve the deep space of ''For 80 Cents!,'' which shows a row of women engaged in the back-breaking work of weeding rice paddies, while dicing the colors and brush strokes so finely they take on a conservative sheen. Morbelli keeps the space deep but roughens the surface in a far more imposing painting of a few white-haired old men dozing among the empty benches of a refractory in an old-age home; they have outlived their usefulness and their comrades.</p>
        <p>Photography also figured in Pellizza's vaguely Pre-Raphaelite ''Procession,'' as well as ''The Fourth Estate,'' which is represented here by a lush early study (the leaders minus the crowd) from 1892. (Pellizza's process is detailed in a touching display of letters, photographs and sketches at the Italian Cultural Institute at 686 Park Avenue.) Related Symbolist works include the large, saccharin paintings of Gaetano Previati, which are ripe with swooning Greek-gowned maidens, swirling forms and unearthly light, or the small, dark, far more engaging landscapes of Grubicy, who admired Whistler but might have also taken cues from Louis Comfort Tiffany. Here Divisionism all but disappears in a hard gloss that gives Grubicy's bodies of water the iridescence of mother of pearl or Favrile glass.</p>
        <p>The non-Italian artists were hardly without political impulses, as works by Camille Pissarro, Paul Signac, Henri-Edmond Cross and Maximilien Luce attest. But they stuck closer to orthodox Pointillism, with sometimes odd results. The tapestrylike evenness of Cross's luminous, mostly pastel ''Grape Harvest'' suggests a serene, idyllic Arcadia, despite the sun-baked women crouching in the field. And in ''After the Strike,'' by the Dutch artist Jan Toorop, the anguish of a family carrying their injured son is both apparent and slightly comical. A better balance of Pointillism and politics occurs in Pellizza's ''Drowned Man,'' in which a body on a stretcher is carried along a stony beach bathed in light. But for Pointillism at its best, you must still turn to Seurat, the measles' source, and especially to a purplish coastal scene with undulating clouds. His dots percolate at liberty like nothing else in this fascinating show.</p>
        <p>''Divisionism/Neo-Impressionism: Arcadia and Anarchy'' is at the Guggenheim Museum, 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3500, through Aug. 6.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
