<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Fatal Clash, Questions About Police Tactics and a Suspect's Mental State</title>
    <meta content="27catskill" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/nyregion/27catskill.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843273"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Catskills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Catskills (NYS Area)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Trim, Travis D</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E7DD123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="930" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Fatal Clash, Questions About Police Tactics and a Suspect's Mental State</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After Fatal Clash, Questions About Police Tactics and a Suspect’s Mental State</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WILSON and LISA W. FODERARO; Laura Drake contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilson, Michael; Foderaro, Lisa W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was dusk Wednesday when the roaring fire ended an extraordinary day of tragedy and the massing of police manpower, armor and technology in a quiet corner of the Catskill Mountains.</p>
        <p>Cameras stuck on poles, cameras embedded in thrown balls and even a camera mounted on a stair-climbing robot were used to track a suspect in the killing of a state trooper who may have already been shot dead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was dusk Wednesday when the roaring fire ended an extraordinary day of tragedy and the massing of police manpower, armor and technology in a quiet corner of the Catskill Mountains.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was dusk Wednesday when the roaring fire ended an extraordinary day of tragedy and the massing of police manpower, armor and technology in a quiet corner of the Catskill Mountains.</p>
        <p>Cameras stuck on poles, cameras embedded in thrown balls and even a camera mounted on a stair-climbing robot were used to track a suspect in the killing of a state trooper who may have already been shot dead.</p>
        <p>But when the smoke cleared yesterday morning, there was the skeleton of a farmhouse and an abundance of unanswered questions, and the troopers who had been side by side with their slain colleague had not yet been interviewed.</p>
        <p>''We want to give the troopers a little bit of time to get their emotions under control,'' said Maj. Kevin Molinari, commander of Troop C of the state police.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, Travis D. Trim, 23, confronted troopers searching for him, fatally shooting Trooper David C. Brinkerhoff, 29, and wounding Trooper Richard G. Mattson, the authorities said. The troopers returned fire, possibly striking Mr. Trim, before two officers fled with their two wounded comrades. That night, after troopers fired tear gas canisters into the farmhouse, a fire swept the almost century-old structure and ignited a cache of ammunition stored there by its owner, making the hills echo with explosions and keeping firefighters at bay.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, a charred body found clutching a rifle inside the house set ablaze during the deadly standoff was identified by the police as Mr. Trim, a college dropout who had stolen a friend's van days earlier.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trim's family and friends tried to reconcile the man they know -- admittedly deeply troubled, using hallucinogenic drugs and seeming paranoid -- with the man accused of killing a trooper.</p>
        <p>''Travis was crazy, but he wasn't the kind of guy who would shoot a cop,'' said Jake Ritz, 18, a student at SUNY Canton, which Mr. Trim attended before dropping out last year.</p>
        <p>An autopsy conducted yesterday at Albany Medical Center was expected to determine whether Mr. Trim died in the fire or was shot. The results were not immediately released.</p>
        <p>In addition, Major Molinari said the state police would conduct an internal investigation into the events and tactical decisions that led to the standoff and its fiery end. He defended the troopers' firing tear gas canisters into the home, one of which may have touched off the fire.</p>
        <p>''The major issue is, we had a clear and detailed and well-thought-out and methodical plan in place yesterday as to what we needed to do to remove Travis Trim safely from that residence,'' he said. ''There does come a point in time when we realized that we are going to have to go in the house.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Trim's criminal career took its first violent turn on Tuesday, when a trooper, Matthew Gombosi, pulled over the van with a missing license plate outside a service station in Margaretville, a village on the edge of Catskill Park about 140 miles northwest of New York City, the police said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trim, appearing disoriented and without identification, they said, pulled out a pistol and shot Trooper Gombosi, whose body armor spared him from serious injury. Mr. Trim then fled, the police said.</p>
        <p>Early Wednesday morning, the police responded to a burglar alarm at the nearby vacation home of Carole Chamberlain-Berman of Bergenfield, N.J. After finding a backpack and other belongings of Mr. Trim's, the police called in a team of four troopers from the Mobile Response Team, an elite and heavily armored unit.</p>
        <p>They encountered Mr. Trim on a second-story landing about 8:30 a.m. It remained unclear yesterday how many rounds were fired. Trooper Brinkerhoff was struck in the head, Trooper Mattson in the left arm.</p>
        <p>Troopers converged on the home. There were about 140 troopers, along with 40 or 50 officers from local police departments and members of the F.B.I., Major Molinari said. The troopers fired tear gas into the house for hours and called the telephone in the home, but Mr. Trim did not pick up, the major said.</p>
        <p>Eventually, Robert A. Chamberlain, Ms. Chamberlain-Berman's son, arrived and drew a diagram of its interior so that the police could send a robotic camera into the house, where it examined every room downstairs and began climbing to the second floor before tumbling back down, the major said.</p>
        <p>''Every logical step that we had laid out in an effort to safely remove him without use of force was completed,'' Major Molinari said. ''It just reached a time when we are going to execute the plan and go into the residence.''</p>
        <p>Shortly before 6 p.m., troopers could be seen donning heavy camouflage vests and packs, readying themselves for entering the home. But first, more tear gas was fired.</p>
        <p>''You have to remember, this is an individual who, within a span of 18 hours, had shot three police officers, killing one and injuring another,'' Major Molinari said.</p>
        <p>Late Wednesday night, the acting superintendent of the New York State Police, Preston L. Felton, said it was possible that the last gas canisters used had been pulled from a different batch, one that is hotter when fired.</p>
        <p>''There may have been several rounds of hot tear gas shot into the building by one of the other units, and I'm having our internal affairs look into it,'' the superintendent said. ''It's not something that we planned to do, but the use of tear gas has, on occasion, led to fires, and we're aware of that, and that's why we stationed firefighters in close proximity.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
