<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inside Art</title>
    <meta content="27voge" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/arts/design/27voge.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843158"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Inside Art"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Inside Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana/New Orleans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Barnes Foundation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Frick Collection</org>
        <org class="online_producer">PaceWildenstein</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E2D8153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="924" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inside Art</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From the Barnes, a Short List of Architects</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Carol Vogel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From the Barnes, A Short List of Architects</p>
        <p>Despite passionate opposition from art lovers, the Barnes Foundation is proceeding with its move from its original home in Merion, Pa., to downtown Philadelphia. The foundation plans to announce today the six architects being considered to design a 120,000-square-foot-building on the Benjamin Franklin Parkway. The new building will house not only the Barnes's world-class collection of Impressionist, post-Impressionist and early modern art but educational facilities, a gallery for special exhibitions and a conservation studio as well.</p>
        <p>The architects on the short list are Tadao Ando, from Osaka, Japan; Diller Scofidio + Renfro, New York; Kengo Kuma, Tokyo; Rafael Moneo, Madrid; Thom Mayne/Morphosis, Los Angeles; and Tod Williams and Billie Tsien, New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The foundation plans to announce on Friday the six architects being considered to design a 20,000-square-foot-building on the Benjamin Franklin Parkway.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From the Barnes, A Short List of Architects</p>
        <p>Despite passionate opposition from art lovers, the Barnes Foundation is proceeding with its move from its original home in Merion, Pa., to downtown Philadelphia. The foundation plans to announce today the six architects being considered to design a 120,000-square-foot-building on the Benjamin Franklin Parkway. The new building will house not only the Barnes's world-class collection of Impressionist, post-Impressionist and early modern art but educational facilities, a gallery for special exhibitions and a conservation studio as well.</p>
        <p>The architects on the short list are Tadao Ando, from Osaka, Japan; Diller Scofidio + Renfro, New York; Kengo Kuma, Tokyo; Rafael Moneo, Madrid; Thom Mayne/Morphosis, Los Angeles; and Tod Williams and Billie Tsien, New York.</p>
        <p>The board's building committee expects to announce its decision by late summer.</p>
        <p>An 'Eccentric' at the Frick</p>
        <p>Unlike large museums that present shows of work by big-name artists to increase attendance, the Frick Collection enjoys introducing its visitors to little-known masters. Over the years it has organized exhibitions of works by artists including Jean-Baptiste Greuze, an 18th-century French draftsman and painter; Willem van Tetrode, a Renaissance sculptor; and Jean-Étienne Liotard, an 18th-century Swiss painter. In October it will present yet another show on a somewhat obscure artist: the 18th-century French draftsman, etcher and painter Gabriel de Saint-Aubin.</p>
        <p>''Along with Boucher and Fragonard, he was one of the great artists of the 18th century,'' said Colin B. Bailey, the Frick's chief curator. ''He is almost an unknown figure because in his day he was regarded as something of an eccentric. The grand manner of painting eluded him, so he was better known as an ingenious illustrator.''</p>
        <p>Saint-Aubin made his reputation recording everyday Parisian life, showing everyone from recognizable faces to crowds on the street.</p>
        <p>The show, from Oct. 30 through Jan. 27, will include 54 drawings, 7 paintings and 10 engravings. It has been organized in collaboration with the Louvre, with loans from both public and private collections. ''This is the first full retrospective of the artist since one at the Jean Charpentier Gallery in Paris in 1925,'' Mr. Bailey said.</p>
        <p>Curators at the Louvre have been particularly interested in Saint-Aubin. Seven years ago the museum acquired his family album, and some of its finest drawings will be in the exhibition.</p>
        <p>Saint-Aubin is actually well represented in American collections. The Metropolitan Museum of Art, the J. Paul Getty Museum in Los Angeles, the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, and the Cleveland Museum of Art are lending to the show, as are the Musée des Beaux-Arts in Rouen, France, the National Gallery of Art in London and the State Hermitage Museum in St. Petersburg, Russia.</p>
        <p>Seldom Seen Monets</p>
        <p>What Wildenstein &amp; Company is calling ''the largest survey show of Monet's oeuvre to be held in New York in over 30 years'' opens today, filling the rooms of its Beaux-Arts building at 19 East 64th Street. And gallery executives say none of the works are for sale.</p>
        <p>The show -- called a tribute to Daniel Wildenstein, the dealer who died in 2001 and who spent 50 years assembling Monet's catalogue raisonné with Katia Granoff, the Russian-born art dealer who helped to promote Monet's final works until her death in 1989 -- has been a year and a half in the making.</p>
        <p>Some 62 paintings are on view, many on loan from museums, including five from the Musée Marmottan Monet in Paris. There is also a room of archival photographs of Monet working in and around his home and gardens in Giverny, France.</p>
        <p>Joseph Baillio, the senior vice president at Wildenstein who organized the exhibition, said that over the years the gallery has sold some of the works to the museums and collectors who own them today. Three paintings on view, from private American collections, have not been publicly exhibited before, he added, and others had never been seen in New York. The three are ''Villas at Bordighera'' (1884), ''Through the Trees, Île de La Grande Jatte'' (1878) and ''Adolphe Monet in the Garden of 'Le Coteau' at Saint-Adresse'' (1867).</p>
        <p>Most gallery exhibitions are free, but Wildenstein is charging admission: $10, or $5 for students, with proceeds benefiting the Breast Cancer Research Foundation.</p>
        <p>A Biennial for New Orleans</p>
        <p>New Orleans is out to rebuild itself not just physically but culturally, too. Dan Cameron, a former curator at the New Museum of Contemporary Art, has started U.S. Biennial Inc., a nonprofit company whose first project is ''Prospect.1, New Orleans,'' an international biennial scheduled to open on Oct. 4, 2008, in spaces throughout the city.</p>
        <p>''I've been a New Orleans zealot for more than 20 years,'' Mr. Cameron said. The biennial will include artists not just from Louisiana but from all over the country and abroad. So far, Mr. Cameron added, more than 80 artists are expected to participate.</p>
        <p>He estimates it will cost about $3 million to put the event together, and he is hoping for support from foundations, corporations and private sources. The Toby Fund, founded by Toby Devan Lewis, a philanthropist, collector and curator, has given $500,000 to kick off the project.</p>
        <p>Signing On</p>
        <p>Two of China's hottest contemporary artists, Zhang Xiaogang and Zhang Huan, have agreed to be represented in the United States by PaceWildenstein. Zhang Xiaogang, a figurative painter, is best known for his ''Bloodline Series,'' based on portraits derived from family photographs taken in the 1920s. Zhang Huan, a Conceptual artist and photographer, is part of an artists' community outside Beijing known as the East Village.</p>
        <p>Inside Art</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
