<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Romney Says Rivals Changed Minds, Too</title>
    <meta content="27repubs" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/us/politics/27repubs.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843172"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romney, Mitt</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Romney, Mitt</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E3D6153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="707" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Romney Says Rivals Changed Minds, Too</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Romney Says Rivals Changed Minds, Too</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL COOPER; Michael Luo contributed reporting from Washington.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>CHARLESTON, S.C., April 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Republican presidential hopeful Mitt Romney says better-known rivals Sen John McCain and Rudolph W Giuliani have both changed their positions on important issues over years, just as he has; contends new positions reflect additional experience; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mitt Romney directly engaged two of his better-known rivals for the Republican presidential nomination on Thursday, telling an interviewer that Senator John McCain and Rudolph W. Giuliani had both changed their positions on important issues over the years, just as he had.</p>
        <p>Mr. Romney, a former governor of Massachusetts, has been criticized by some conservatives for changing his position on abortion and gay rights in recent years as he prepared to run for president. On Thursday, he gave an interview in New Hampshire in which he sought to deflect criticism on that front, telling The Associated Press that ''everybody in this race that I know has changed their mind on certain positions, and they've done so as they gained more experience.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mitt Romney, who has been criticized for changing his position on abortion and gay rights, engaged two of his rivals for the Republican presidential nomination.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mitt Romney directly engaged two of his better-known rivals for the Republican presidential nomination on Thursday, telling an interviewer that Senator John McCain and Rudolph W. Giuliani had both changed their positions on important issues over the years, just as he had.</p>
        <p>Mr. Romney, a former governor of Massachusetts, has been criticized by some conservatives for changing his position on abortion and gay rights in recent years as he prepared to run for president. On Thursday, he gave an interview in New Hampshire in which he sought to deflect criticism on that front, telling The Associated Press that ''everybody in this race that I know has changed their mind on certain positions, and they've done so as they gained more experience.''</p>
        <p>He then went on to single out Mr. McCain and Mr. Giuliani, who have been ahead of him in recent opinion polls.</p>
        <p>''Senator McCain voted against the Bush tax cuts,'' Mr. Romney told The A.P. ''Now he's for them. He was opposed to ethanol. Now he's for it. He said he was opposed to overturning Roe v. Wade. Now he's for overturning Roe v. Wade.''</p>
        <p>''Mayor Giuliani has made a number of changes over his career, and there are places where I've made changes,'' Mr. Romney said in the interview.</p>
        <p>Mr. Romney made his remarks about his rivals as he has been trying to gain traction among Republican primary voters. Mr. Romney exceeded expectations last month when he announced that he had raised $21 million, more than his rivals. But polls often show him behind his better-known opponents.</p>
        <p>Eric Fehrnstrom, a spokesman for the Romney campaign, said Mr. Romney had gone out of his way in the interview to say that his allusions to Mr. McCain and Mr. Giuliani were not meant as criticism. ''It's a reflection of the fact that sometimes people change with the benefit of experience,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain, campaigning in South Carolina, was asked about several of the issues Mr. Romney mentioned.</p>
        <p>He told reporters that although he did not originally support President Bush's tax cuts -- which he argued at the time would lead to deficits and benefit the rich -- he had proposed his own set of more affordable tax cuts, which he said would have left money to help shore up Social Security and for contingencies, like the war in Iraq.</p>
        <p>And he explained that he did not support repealing the cuts now, because doing so would amount to a tax increase for millions of people.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain was cool toward ethanol in 2000, but has recently been promoting it as a method to help the United States become less dependent on foreign oil. He said Thursday, however, that he still opposed subsidizing it.</p>
        <p>''I'm for letting those tariffs against imported ethanol lapse,'' he said in Columbia, S.C.</p>
        <p>When it comes to abortion, Mr. Romney was apparently referring to an interview Mr. McCain, who has always opposed abortion, gave in 1999 in which he said that he would not support the repeal of Roe v. Wade.</p>
        <p>More recently, Mr. McCain has spoken in favor of a South Dakota effort to ban almost all abortions. At a rally in Columbia, on Thursday he praised the Supreme Court for its recent decision upholding the federal Partial Birth Abortion Ban Act.</p>
        <p>Asked about Mr. Romney's comments on Thursday evening, Mr. McCain said: ''I'm not going to respond to those kinds of comments now. It's too early in the campaign. I'm trying to give the people, the voters, the Republicans, my vision, my view of what we need to do for America. I'm not going to get into that.''</p>
        <p>But he noted that ''I have voted pro-life for 24 years, consistently, without any deviation.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Romney did not specify any shifts when it came to Mr. Giuliani, a former mayor of New York City. But as he has campaigned for president, Mr. Giuliani has altered his stance on gun control and illegal immigration, among other issues.</p>
        <p>Tony Carbonetti, Mr. Giuliani's chief political adviser, said in a statement that: ''Mayor Giuliani has the utmost respect for Mitt Romney and was happy to campaign on his behalf when he was asked. He considers Mitt Romney a friend.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
