<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hughes's Early Arrival Ends With Early Exit</title>
    <meta content="27yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/sports/baseball/27yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843292"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Toronto Blue Jays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Toronto Blue Jays</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hughes, Phil</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E4DD123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1018" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hughes's Early Arrival Ends With Early Exit</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hughes’s Early Arrival Ends With Early Exit</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER; Michael S. Schmidt contributed reporting</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Phil Hughes woke up in his hotel room at 8:30 a.m. yesterday. It was much earlier than he had hoped, and he stayed in bed for four more hours. Hughes is from California, and his instinct was to drive somewhere. But he could not really do that in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''I tried to nap a little bit,'' he said. ''But, constantly, I was lying in bed with my eyes open.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees want Phil Hughes to be a cornerstone of the future. On Thursday, however, he lasted just four and a third innings, allowing four earned runs on seven hits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Phil Hughes woke up in his hotel room at 8:30 a.m. yesterday. It was much earlier than he had hoped, and he stayed in bed for four more hours. Hughes is from California, and his instinct was to drive somewhere. But he could not really do that in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''I tried to nap a little bit,'' he said. ''But, constantly, I was lying in bed with my eyes open.''</p>
        <p>The big ballpark in the Bronx was waiting for Hughes. He is expected to be a pillar at the new one rising beyond the outfield façade, and he was not supposed to be at the old one so soon.</p>
        <p>But the Yankees had a hole in their rotation, and Hughes's last start, against Toronto Blue Jays' minor leaguers, had been dominant. This one, against the real Blue Jays, was not.</p>
        <p>Hughes lasted four and a third innings, allowing four earned runs on seven hits and a walk with five strikeouts in the Yankees' 6-0 loss. Asked what he would remember most, years from now, Hughes replied dryly.</p>
        <p>''Hopefully, I won't remember it too much,'' he said. ''But you only get one first. I'll definitely remember some moments, but not the outcome so much.''</p>
        <p>Playing without shortstop Derek Jeter, who took another day to rest his sore left thigh, the Yankees lost their sixth game in a row and managed only four hits in seven innings against A. J. Burnett. They open a weekend series against Daisuke Matsuzaka and the Boston Red Sox tonight.</p>
        <p>Asked if Hughes would get another start, Torre did not commit to it, but seemed to be leaning that way.</p>
        <p>''I certainly wasn't disappointed,'' Torre said. ''I didn't think he was out of his league, by any stretch of the imagination.''</p>
        <p>Hughes was the fifth rookie to start for the Yankees this season, but rarely has one brought so much hype. In spring training, Jason Giambi compared Hughes to Roger Clemens. Yet Hughes is so young that Clemens had 29 major league victories by the time he was born.</p>
        <p>In terms of raw numbers, this game was more of the same for a struggling team. For the 10th time in 20 games, a Yankees starter failed to last five innings. But the night was as much about the future as now, and the Yankees liked the glimpse.</p>
        <p>''The big thing I saw was even when he was down, he kept coming,'' catcher Jorge Posada said. ''That's the sign of a good pitcher. I was really happy.''</p>
        <p>Torre said Hughes's willingness to challenge hitters was most impressive to him. The Yankees do not question Hughes's composure.</p>
        <p>''I think of myself when I was 20,'' said Torre, who also played in the majors at that age, ''and he's miles ahead of me.''</p>
        <p>Hughes kept his spring training number, 65, and he wore his socks high. He crouched behind the mound before starting, telling himself to stay calm, he said, and saying a prayer for his family.</p>
        <p>His first pitch was a fastball, 94 miles an hour, low. His next pitch was rifled to left for a single by Alex Rios. Hughes then struck out Adam Lind, blowing a 96 m.p.h. fastball past him. Posada gave the ball to the umpire, who tossed it to the Yankees' dugout. A souvenir.</p>
        <p>Hughes, though, was scrambling. Rios had stolen second, and Hughes let Vernon Wells extend his arms to smash a fastball off the center-field wall for a double. Eleven pitches into his career, Hughes was behind.</p>
        <p>It got worse with Frank Thomas, who has been testing major league pitchers since Hughes was 4. Thomas greeted Hughes with a vintage at-bat, taking the first five pitches, including a close one on 1-2, and then fouling off a fastball before flicking a run-scoring single to right.</p>
        <p>''I thought it was a good pitch,'' Hughes said of the 1-2 fastball. ''But he's Frank Thomas. He's going to get those.''</p>
        <p>Hughes threw a wild pitch before getting two groundouts to end the inning. He easily handled the last four hitters in the order, allowing only an infield single in two trips through.</p>
        <p>Wells, who had three hits, said Hughes had a lively fastball, a good changeup and a major-league curveball. But the Blue Jays made him work; 19 of the 21 hitters to face Hughes took the first pitch.</p>
        <p>''I think our guys just did a good job waiting him out, at getting a pitch and not missing it,'' Wells said. ''That is what you have to do with a guy with that type of stuff.''</p>
        <p>When Hughes got to two strikes, the fans yelled out his name, holding the ''U'' for a while. His parents, who flew in from California, said they had never heard that cheer. His mother, Dorianne, smiled at her confusion.</p>
        <p>''I thought they were saying, 'Boo,' '' she said. ''I was worried. What did he do wrong?''</p>
        <p>The fans had fun, but the show did not last. The first inning consumed 27 pitches -- fastballs, curves and changeups -- and Hughes was finished at 91 when Wells smacked a one-out single to center in the fifth, scoring Toronto's third run.</p>
        <p>Hughes stood to the side of the mound, on the grass, as the infielders converged. Torre patted him on his backside, and Hughes walked off to the chant of his last name.</p>
        <p>The fans seemed to be cheering the effort, and the promise. It was not a winning performance, and it was another short outing that taxed a tired bullpen. But it was a start.</p>
        <p>''I definitely didn't feel overmatched,'' Hughes said.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The Yankees will start Jeff Karstens tomorrow, demoting Kei Igawa to the bullpen.  Mike Mussina (hamstring) will pitch a simulated game at Yankee Stadium today and be lined up to start next week in Texas.  The Yankees want fans to use mass transportation this weekend, with new ballpark construction causing traffic problems.  The Yankees' April 4 rainout has been rescheduled for July 21 at 7:05 p.m., as the second game of a separate-admission doubleheader.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
