<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Their Defense in Question, Rangers Look to Regroup</title>
    <meta content="27rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/sports/hockey/27rangers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843237"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Buffalo Sabres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Buffalo Sabres</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E3DE123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="844" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Their Defense in Question, Rangers Look to Regroup</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Their Defense in Question, Rangers Look to Regroup</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinser, Lynn</byline>
      <dateline>BUFFALO, April 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Rangers practiced without their top defenseman, Michal Rozsival, on Thursday, and Rozsival's defensive partner, Marek Malik, also took the day off to rest. The team was absorbing the blow of a loss in the opener of their playoff series with Buffalo, a team that seemed to thrive on every defensive mistake the Rangers made in a 5-2 victory Wednesday night.</p>
        <p>The Rangers tried to brush away any sense of doom by remembering they had been through this kind of emergency before, in February when they were in danger of missing the playoffs and were losing players to a rash of knee injuries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a 5-2 loss to Buffalo, the Rangers tried to absorb the blow of defeat and brush away any sense of doom on Thursday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Rangers practiced without their top defenseman, Michal Rozsival, on Thursday, and Rozsival's defensive partner, Marek Malik, also took the day off to rest. The team was absorbing the blow of a loss in the opener of their playoff series with Buffalo, a team that seemed to thrive on every defensive mistake the Rangers made in a 5-2 victory Wednesday night.</p>
        <p>The Rangers tried to brush away any sense of doom by remembering they had been through this kind of emergency before, in February when they were in danger of missing the playoffs and were losing players to a rash of knee injuries.</p>
        <p>''Pretty much from February on we approached each game like a must win, but we didn't win each game,'' forward Brendan Shanahan said. ''Usually we responded well after that. What this team lacks in playoff experience, it really helped to have that sort of pressure-packed run at the end of the season.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers will test their resilience in Game 2 on Friday night, against a Buffalo team heartened by its success in the first game. If the Rangers are forced to counter that without Rozsival, it makes their challenge even steeper.</p>
        <p>Rozsival is officially listed as day to day. His left knee was injured in a first-period hit by Buffalo forward Ales Kotalik. He tried to return for the second period, but lasted only one shift. On Thursday, Rozsival was walking normally and described the injury as mild. He has had two knee operations in his career, including one on his right knee that caused him to miss the 2003-4 season.</p>
        <p>His absence in Game 1 turned the Rangers' defensive efforts into a bit of a scramble. Defenseman Karel Rachunek, who had been out with a knee injury, was playing his first game in nearly seven weeks and did not immediately adapt to the speed of a playoff game. He was forced to play nearly 20 minutes, a far heavier workload than Coach Tom Renney had planned for Rachunek's debut.</p>
        <p>Malik was left without his dependable partner and the defensive pairings were thrown into a new rotation. Rozsival is the kind of player who does things so steadily that his contributions often go overlooked -- until he leaves the game.</p>
        <p>''Michal is a great player all around, offensively and defensively,'' Rangers defenseman Paul Mara said. ''He does the small things that you might not notice, but players on this team respect him so much. Losing that was a big thing in that game.''</p>
        <p>If Rozsival does not return for Game 2, Thomas Pock will be back in the lineup. He had played in place of Rachunek at the end of the regular season and in the first round of the playoffs. But Renney acknowledged that filling Rozsival's ice time -- he averaged nearly 24 minutes in the regular season and 25 minutes in the first round -- will have to be accomplished by committee.</p>
        <p>''That's hockey,'' Malik said. ''Things happen and the question is, how are we going to respond? Of course we missed him. He is a big part of our team and he is playing very well for us. To lose him, especially early in the game, is pretty huge for us. But that's what it is. We have to see how he's going to be. If he isn't back, we have to do something.''</p>
        <p>The Sabres had few such issues Thursday, although defenseman Brian Campbell, who missed about 10 minutes of ice time in the first game because of an injury, did not practice. Buffalo Coach Lindy Ruff did not detail the injury and said he believed Campbell would play Friday. Otherwise, the Sabres took mostly positive vibes out of Game 1, using their offensive depth to capitalize on the Rangers' defensive lapses. The Sabres stayed true to their form and spread the playing time among four lines of forwards.</p>
        <p>''That's why we're so dangerous,'' Buffalo center Daniel Brière said. ''There's no rest with our lineup. Any given game, any given time, any given shift you're going to have someone on the ice that's dangerous or a threat to score if you're not careful. With us having four lines that can score, you can't have too many of those letdowns because we'll take advantage of it.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers do not have the depth or the collective playoff experience of the Sabres, who reached the Eastern Conference finals last season. But the Rangers do have leaders who have been through this before. Shanahan won three Stanley Cups with Detroit; Jaromir Jagr won two with Pittsburgh. And center Matt Cullen won last year with Carolina, which defeated Buffalo in the conference finals in seven games.</p>
        <p>''I think the guys that have been through it, I think it's important that we not change anything and not panic,'' Cullen said. ''You just have to go about it like we've been going about it and show that belief that we're going to win. It's one game. We have a chance to come out tomorrow and redeem it and get back to even.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
