<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Change the World, and That Diaper</title>
    <meta content="l27work" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843231"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E5DE123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1106" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Change the World, and That Diaper</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In ''Off to Work She Should Go'' (Op-Ed, April 25), Linda Hirshman argues that while it may be ''easier in the short term'' for a new mother to leave her job and stay at home, she should resist the easy road and return to work.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In ''Off to Work She Should Go'' (Op-Ed, April 25), Linda Hirshman argues that while it may be ''easier in the short term'' for a new mother to leave her job and stay at home, she should resist the easy road and return to work.</p>
        <p>When I was a public-interest lawyer before I had my son eight months ago, I often volunteered for the most difficult assignments, in part because I thought I could do the best job (not to take anything away from my colleagues). As a student council president and then Type A Ivy League graduate, I've always put pressure on myself to tackle challenges. And let me tell you, going back to work would have been easier in the short and long term.</p>
        <p>Perhaps mothers are opting out of the work force because they believe that they can do the job of raising their children better than anyone else. We've been control freaks way too long to delegate it!</p>
        <p>Melissa Lawton  West Hollywood, Calif. April 25, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Could anyone who has ever waited on tables, sold clothes or worked for a soul-numbing large corporation find that more valuable than teaching a child to read or care about others? I doubt it.</p>
        <p>Linda Hirshman writes that women should stay in the work force after they have children ''because participation in public life allows women to use their talents and to powerfully affect society.'' Maybe for a very privileged few.</p>
        <p>Instead of continuing in a doomed, materialistic effort to overvalue salaries and career success, let's support women who choose to do the best, hardest job.</p>
        <p>A good start would be reforming no-fault divorce laws and increasing tax deductions for children.</p>
        <p>Amy Kelley  Mount Kisco, N.Y., April 25, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Yes, it was my ''highly educated'' brain that made a career possible and then found a way to juggle it with a baby at home -- at least for a while.</p>
        <p>So if Linda Hirshman concedes my powers this far, then why doesn't she respect my later choice to stay home? It came from the very same brain, trained and experienced as it is in making complex decisions.</p>
        <p>And then there's this other thing -- quite hard to measure by units: I just like being with my kids.</p>
        <p>Catherine Baker-Wingfield  Arlington, Va., April 25, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Linda Hirshman neglects to mention the fulfillment and pleasure mothers receive from caring for their children. She should spend some time at my home one day. As I'm typing away, my 3-year-old, a budding musician and songwriter, is improvising on the piano. My 5-year-old is looking at the headlines of this newspaper (hmm, maybe I should go sit with him and explain).</p>
        <p>As for the contention that staying home is ''easier,'' again, I invite Ms. Hirshman to come baby-sit any day she likes.</p>
        <p>Diane Roseman  Westborough, Mass., April 25, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Linda Hirshman argues that work allows mothers to use their talents to affect society, and that women will earn less if they take a break from work and then return.</p>
        <p>I am a mom and work full time, and neither of those are compelling reasons for me to do so. My job is stimulating, and is for a good cause, and yet I would always choose to be with my children over spending time in the office.</p>
        <p>For centuries (and still today in some cultures), mothers had their children with them as they worked. Today, very few jobs offer that flexibility.</p>
        <p>A friend who owns and runs a small organic farm brings her baby into the fields with her, and has him toddling around her feet at the farmers' markets where she sells her produce.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the collective subconscious of human mothers still desires that integration of making a living and raising a family.</p>
        <p>Karen Bassler  Madison, Wis., April 25, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I baby-sat in high school, then worked my way through college, graduate school and law school. At 38, I was glad for a break from crowded subways and from having no control over my life from 9 to 5. I became a stay-at-home mom.</p>
        <p>Now that my son is getting ready to leave for college, I find I have too much time on my hands and a weird résumé. But I don't care, because I wouldn't trade the last 18 years for a corner office and stock options any day of the week.</p>
        <p>Alice Gadeloff Graves  St. Petersburg, Fla., April 25, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>What can we do to entice the mothers of young children into the work force? Nothing, if their desire to be with their children is strong enough. Rather than pursue them, why not accommodate the mothers of older children, many of whom could easily be enticed back to the workplace under the right conditions?</p>
        <p>There are armies of highly trained, professional mothers who would return to regular employment in a heartbeat if they thought they could find a job at their appropriate level of skill -- and proportionate salary -- at what used to be considered normal work hours.</p>
        <p>Any observer who can't see that working 9 to 7, rather than 9 to 5, has inherent problems for a mother of young children has a profound lack of insight.</p>
        <p>Barbara MacDougall Harrington  Forest Hills, Queens, April 25, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Linda Hirshman says mothers are abandoning ''participation in public life'' to stay home with their young children. This is too shallow a view of the lives of mothers. Many mothers who opt out of the traditional work force are bettering public life. I certainly interact more in ''public life'' now that I am not sitting at a desk all day.</p>
        <p>We shouldn't fool ourselves into thinking that going to the office every day is participating in ''public life.'' Many mothers, myself included, have more time to be politically, socially and charitably active and in doing so set a wonderful example for our children as we take them along to rallies and lectures.</p>
        <p>My bigger concern, and one that I hear little about, is how stay-at-home mothers are preparing for retirement.</p>
        <p>Who's going to fund Mommy's 401(k) when she is working for her family?</p>
        <p>Katherine Delaney  Wauwatosa, Wis., April 25, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>If we learned nothing else from the feminist teachings of our youth, we learned that choice is key, and, for those who have the choice, we need to rally support.</p>
        <p>Susan Komisar Hausman  Stoughton, Mass., April 25, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
