<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Autistic Woman's Lessons for the Cynical</title>
    <meta content="27snow" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/movies/27snow.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843163"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Evans, Marc</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weaver, Sigourney</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rickman, Alan</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Snow Cake (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Autism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Autism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Snow Cake (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E1D8153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Autistic Woman's Lessons for the Cynical</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Autistic Woman’s Lessons for the Cynical</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews film Snow Cake, directed by Marc Evans; Sigourney Weaver and Alan Rickman star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In ''Snow Cake'' Sigourney Weaver peels off layers of urbane sophistication to play Linda Freeman, a high-functioning autistic woman living in a rural Ontario town called Wawa. With her face scrubbed clean of makeup and wearing an expression that shifts between infantile delight and childish indignation, Ms. Weaver gives a technically accomplished performance. She is so far outside her comfort zone that you scan her body language for signs of the haughty female warrior lurking behind Linda's blank innocence. But that person is nowhere to be seen.</p>
        <p>Linda, who supports herself stocking the shelves of a local grocery store, has phobias galore. Compulsively neat, she refuses to take out the garbage. When her dog vomits on the kitchen floor, she is thrown into a state of terror. Mostly, however, she takes joy in life. Behind the house is a trampoline on which she spends afternoons gleefully jumping up and down. A favorite winter pleasure is eating snow (hence the movie's title).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“Snow Cake” partly camouflages the banality of its concept with its meticulous performances.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In ''Snow Cake'' Sigourney Weaver peels off layers of urbane sophistication to play Linda Freeman, a high-functioning autistic woman living in a rural Ontario town called Wawa. With her face scrubbed clean of makeup and wearing an expression that shifts between infantile delight and childish indignation, Ms. Weaver gives a technically accomplished performance. She is so far outside her comfort zone that you scan her body language for signs of the haughty female warrior lurking behind Linda's blank innocence. But that person is nowhere to be seen.</p>
        <p>Linda, who supports herself stocking the shelves of a local grocery store, has phobias galore. Compulsively neat, she refuses to take out the garbage. When her dog vomits on the kitchen floor, she is thrown into a state of terror. Mostly, however, she takes joy in life. Behind the house is a trampoline on which she spends afternoons gleefully jumping up and down. A favorite winter pleasure is eating snow (hence the movie's title).</p>
        <p>When Linda's temperamental opposite enters her life, ''Snow Cake'' turns into a sugary life lesson: a disabled person becomes a holy innocent healing sick, world-weary souls. The object of partial redemption is Alex Hughes (Alan Rickman), an embittered middle-aged Briton recently released from prison after serving time for killing a man.</p>
        <p>It is a violent death that throws Linda and Alex together. While on the road to Winnipeg, Alex is accosted in a diner by Linda's hitchhiking 19-year-old daughter, Vivienne (Emily Hampshire), who pesters him for a ride. He sourly agrees. Shortly after they hit the highway, his car is slammed off the road by a truck, and Vivienne dies. Guilt-stricken, although the accident was not his fault, he decides it is his duty to visit his dead passenger's mother and deliver the news in person.</p>
        <p>Unaware of Linda's condition, Alex is nonplused when she shrugs off her daughter's death. He ends up staying in her house until after the funeral. They become friends and Scrabble opponents who play the game by Linda's wacky rules, which allow the use of nonexistent words like ''dezlious.''</p>
        <p>''Snow Cake,'' directed by Marc Evans (''Resurrection Man'') from a screenplay by Angela Pell, partly camouflages the banality of its concept with its meticulous performances. Ms. Weaver is convincing precisely because she doesn't oversell the upbeat life lessons her character imparts to Alex; a less gifted actor would grab every opportunity to promote Linda as the radiant incarnation of a live-in-the-moment, we-are-all-children philosophy. Even the name ''Freeman'' sends the message.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rickman's Alex is a pill. A scowling, baggy-eyed misanthrope whose grumbling tone and suspicious gaze convey defeat, he is occasionally capable of sardonic self-deprecation. ''I don't have baggage; I have haulage,'' he remarks. ''Snow Cake'' coyly holds back the whys and wherefores of his imprisonment until late in the movie, when he exchanges confessions with Linda's attractive next-door neighbor, Maggie (Carrie-Anne Moss).</p>
        <p>An anomaly among Linda's cozy neighbors, Maggie is a sex-starved divorcée who invites Alex to dinner with one thing in mind. He obliges, and they begin an affair. But Alex is so much older, and exudes such an air of crumpled exhaustion, that the relationship begs credibility.</p>
        <p>So do a lot of other elements in ''Snow Cake.'' Like ''I Am Sam,'' it is a film that tests your cynicism. Those charmed by cute contrivances like ''dezlious'' may devour ''Snow Cake'' as eagerly as Linda munches on snow.</p>
        <p>Snow Cake  Opens today in New York and Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Directed by Marc Evans; written by Angela Pell; director of photography, Steve Cosens; edited by Marguerite Arnold; production designer, Matthew J. Davies; produced by Andrew Eaton, Gina Carter, Niv Fichman and Jessica Daniel; released by IFC First Take and the Weinstein Company. In Manhattan at the Cinema Village, 22 East 12th Street, Greenwich Village. Running time: 112 minutes. This film is not rated.</p>
        <p>WITH: Alan Rickman (Alex Hughes), Sigourney Weaver (Linda Freeman), Carrie-Anne Moss (Maggie), Emily Hampshire (Vivienne Freeman), James Allodi (Clyde) and Callum Keith Rennie (John Neil).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
