<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Even Closer Scrutiny for Matsuzaka</title>
    <meta content="27redsox" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/sports/baseball/27redsox.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843288"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Matsuzaka, Daisuke</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5DD123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="990" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Even Closer Scrutiny for Matsuzaka</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Even Closer Scrutiny for the Red Sox’s Matsuzaka</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <dateline>BALTIMORE, April 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Five hundred feet from the nearest reporter, the most analyzed pitcher in the world threw a ball, breathed and then threw some more. As Daisuke Matsuzaka of the Boston Red Sox worked in the rare solitude of the center-field bullpen here Wednesday, he was meticulous about his routine. Even from 500 feet away, that was obvious.</p>
        <p>In an instant-satisfaction world where Matsuzaka's starts are scrutinized by three hungry nations (Red Sox, United States and Japan), he has been saddled with enormous expectations. With Matsuzaka, every inning, good or bad, is tossed into a blender to determine if he is validating the mountainous hype.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Saddled with enormous expectations, Daisuke Matsuzaka is still trying to prove that he can be as formidable here as he was in Japan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Five hundred feet from the nearest reporter, the most analyzed pitcher in the world threw a ball, breathed and then threw some more. As Daisuke Matsuzaka of the Boston Red Sox worked in the rare solitude of the center-field bullpen here Wednesday, he was meticulous about his routine. Even from 500 feet away, that was obvious.</p>
        <p>In an instant-satisfaction world where Matsuzaka's starts are scrutinized by three hungry nations (Red Sox, United States and Japan), he has been saddled with enormous expectations. With Matsuzaka, every inning, good or bad, is tossed into a blender to determine if he is validating the mountainous hype.</p>
        <p>But Matsuzaka is still adjusting to the majors, still trying to prove that he can be as formidable here as he was in Japan. Matsuzaka has been decent in four starts for Boston, has shown a dynamic repertory and has displayed some flaws, too.</p>
        <p>Still, because of what Matsuzaka represents as Japan's premier pitcher and because of the $103 million the Red Sox invested in him, there is a feeling that something else, something special, is still missing. The Red Sox fans hope that Matsuzaka's adjustment period will move as rapidly as one of his fastballs.</p>
        <p>''I think he hasn't fully made it yet,'' catcher Jason Varitek said. ''He's still getting into his season. I think he has more sharpness to come, or at least I hope so. At least I think that that's there.''</p>
        <p>Matsuzaka's next opportunity to enhance his reputation in this country will come when he opposes the Yankees at Yankee Stadium on Friday night. Interestingly, Matsuzaka, who outlasted the Yankees in a 7-6 victory last Sunday, was mostly silent about a game in the most hostile environment of his young major league career.</p>
        <p>Sounding like someone who studied ''Bull Durham,'' Matsuzaka simply said that he would treat the game as if he were ''facing any other opponent.'' Matsuzaka had his worst start against the Yankees, a team filled with selective hitters. So, before seeing them again, Matsuzaka was coy.</p>
        <p>Red Sox Manager Terry Francona said: ''I think that's why he wanted to sign and play here, because of this type of rivalry. I think this is why he's here.''</p>
        <p>Matsuzaka, who is 2-2 with a 4.00 earned run average, was chattier about how he could improve. Mostly, the confident Matsuzaka placed the onus on himself. It seems as if Matsuzaka believes that it does not matter what the hitters do. It matters what he does.</p>
        <p>''In my own experience, as long as I do the right things in my preparation and I don't head off track in any strange way, I'm the type of pitcher that definitely gets stronger and better adjusted to the batters as the season goes on,'' Matsuzaka said through an interpreter.</p>
        <p>Matsuzaka said that he had planned to pitch in America for a while and had not experienced any ''huge surprises,'' but he added that he was still getting used to the different ball. In fact, Matsuzaka called that one of his biggest adjustments.</p>
        <p>Matsuzaka, a right-hander, said that the Japanese ball was softer and, after using that for eight years, he has struggled with gripping the harder American ball.</p>
        <p>''I've never had to worry about slippage when I was throwing in Japan,'' Matsuzaka said.</p>
        <p>There have been numerous innings in which Matsuzaka has looked excellent and some innings in which he has looked suspect. In 27 innings, Matsuzaka has struck out 31, walked 6 and given up 25 hits, including 2 home runs. Opponents are batting .248 against him.</p>
        <p>One American League talent evaluator said that Matsuzaka was a major talent. Matsuzaka throws two-seam, four-seam and cut fastballs that range from 88 to 96 miles an hour, and he has a wicked slider and a nifty changeup that he often uses when he is ahead in the count. The evaluator said that he wished Matsuzaka was on his club.</p>
        <p>But the evaluator added that Matsuzaka also had imperfections. He said that Matsuzaka had a tendency to pitch high in the strike zone. If batters can resist those pitches, they can push Matsuzaka deeper into counts and force him to work harder. Matsuzaka pitched every six days in Japan, but is on a five-day schedule here.</p>
        <p>The evaluator also said that Matsuzaka was not as effective from the stretch position. Runners can distract any pitcher and the game slows down. Teams are batting .235 against Matsuzaka with men on base.</p>
        <p>About four hours before Matsuzaka started against the Yankees last Sunday, he had a vigorous workout in shallow right field at Fenway Park that included a session of throwing from the stretch. He also did sprints. It is rare to see such a workout by someone who is starting that night.</p>
        <p>''He comes from a background where they do things differently,'' Francona said. ''For us to bang his head against the wall and say, 'You're going to do it this way,' would be wrong.''</p>
        <p>Varitek said that Matsuzaka had the challenge of trying to outwit hitters that he had seen only on television. Varitek said that was a ''huge element'' in Matsuzaka's development. After Matsuzaka's first four starts for the Seibu Lions last season, he was 3-1 with a 1.16 E.R.A. Bobby Valentine, the manager of Japan's Chiba Lotte Marines, said that Matsuzaka would be sharper if he avoided certain pitfalls.</p>
        <p>''I think he'll get better as the season goes on if there isn't a drop-off in his stuff because of the five-man rotation and if he doesn't fall into the trap of throwing more fastballs,'' Valentine said. ''When he's right, he throws about 35 percent fastballs. That's because he has other quality pitches he can throw for strikes.''</p>
        <p>Matsuzaka sidestepped a question about pitching in a hallowed place like Yankee Stadium, saying that he needed to experience it first. Matsuzaka will have another new experience Friday, and some observers will not be 500 feet away.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
