<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lifetime Gets Second Chief in 2 Years</title>
    <meta content="27lifetime" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/business/media/27lifetime.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843195"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Lifetime Television</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E6DF123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="464" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lifetime Gets Second Chief in 2 Years</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lifetime Gets Second Chief in 2 Years</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carter, Bill</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Lifetime Channel, which has struggled with its ratings, announced its second new chief executive in two years yesterday with the appointment of a longtime ABC network executive, Andrea Wong.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wong succeeds Betty Cohen, who announced her resignation Tuesday night, just hours after Lifetime had presented a new lineup of programs to advertisers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Lifetime Channel announced the appointment of a longtime ABC network executive, Andrea Wong.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Lifetime Channel, which has struggled with its ratings, announced its second new chief executive in two years yesterday with the appointment of a longtime ABC network executive, Andrea Wong.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wong succeeds Betty Cohen, who announced her resignation Tuesday night, just hours after Lifetime had presented a new lineup of programs to advertisers.</p>
        <p>Lifetime, which brands itself as the cable network for women, was the top-rated channel in the cable industry five years ago. It has slipped to sixth place, with ratings having fallen about 7 percent from last year. The falloff was even sharper in previous years.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wong had been long been considered a possible successor to Ms. Cohen mainly because of her success in overseeing reality programming for the ABC network. The Hearst Corporation and ABC's parent, the Walt Disney Company, each own 50 percent of Lifetime Networks, which includes the Lifetime Movie Network.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wong, as an executive vice president of ABC Entertainment, was in charge of late-night entertainment programming and prime-time specials.</p>
        <p>She is best known for having championed ''Dancing With the Stars,'' which has become a hit for ABC and, after ''American Idol,'' the most successful reality show on television.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wong was also involved in the creation of several other reality series, which have provided a significant lift to ABC's prime-time performance. Among these are ''Extreme Makeover: Home Edition,'' ''The Bachelor'' and ''Wife Swap.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Ms. Wong said in an interview that she saw ''some real opportunities'' in bringing one or more reality programs to Lifetime, which has never had a true reality hit.</p>
        <p>''I do think it's right that the channel could use a signature program,'' she said. ''I've said many times, I think reality programming is here to stay.''</p>
        <p>She did not rule out a signature program coming from an area other than reality. The same day that Ms. Cohen resigned, Lifetime announced that it would introduce three drama programs this summer; Ms. Wong said she was enthusiastic about that slate of shows.</p>
        <p>One of them is ''Army Wives,'' about life among a group of women on an Army post.</p>
        <p>Even with its ratings decline, Lifetime remains the leading cable network for women viewers, well ahead of Oxygen and WE.</p>
        <p>Unlike Ms. Cohen, who had led the Cartoon Network, among other cable television positions, Ms. Wong, 40, does not have any direct experience in either running a network or working in the cable industry.</p>
        <p>But she said that she had a wide range of experience at ABC, where she worked first for ABC News and then directly for the network's top executive, Robert A. Iger, who is now the chairman of Disney.</p>
        <p>The appointment was effective immediately. ABC has not yet announced a successor for Ms. Wong in its entertainment division.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
