<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Man's Best Friend, Just the Way We Like to Design Him</title>
    <meta content="27dogs" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/arts/television/27dogs.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843139"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Public Broadcasting Service</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E5D8153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="560" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Man's Best Friend, Just the Way We Like to Design Him</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Man’s Best Friend, Just the Way We Like to Design Him</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN STEWART</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stewart, Susan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Who knew that man's best friend is a freak of nature? ''Dogs That Changed the World'' will not change the way you love your canine companion, but it may change the way you look at him.</p>
        <p>This two-part ''Nature'' production, which concludes Sunday night on PBS, began this past Sunday by explaining where dogs came from. This week, it explains where they are going. It is laden with loquacious dog people, lovely scenery from the Scottish Highlands to the jungles of Papua New Guinea and plenty of frisky puppies. (If your dog is as smart as mine, he or she will also enjoy this show.) As a lesson in genetics, ''Dogs'' is far more entertaining, and peculiar, than Gregor Mendel's peas ever hoped to be.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>PBS’s show will not change the way you love your canine companion, but it may change the way you look at him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Who knew that man's best friend is a freak of nature? ''Dogs That Changed the World'' will not change the way you love your canine companion, but it may change the way you look at him.</p>
        <p>This two-part ''Nature'' production, which concludes Sunday night on PBS, began this past Sunday by explaining where dogs came from. This week, it explains where they are going. It is laden with loquacious dog people, lovely scenery from the Scottish Highlands to the jungles of Papua New Guinea and plenty of frisky puppies. (If your dog is as smart as mine, he or she will also enjoy this show.) As a lesson in genetics, ''Dogs'' is far more entertaining, and peculiar, than Gregor Mendel's peas ever hoped to be.</p>
        <p>First, the origin of this species. We used to think ancient people created dogs by adopting and taming wolves. Now the smart money is on garbage: once ancient people started dumping their trash in communal piles, the wolves with the least fear of humans -- the ones that kept the shortest ''flight distance'' -- got the best leftovers. In a scenario familiar to anyone with a table-scrap-begging pooch, the wolves acted charming for their supper.</p>
        <p>This week, ''Dogs'' celebrates the domesticated dog in all its diversity -- ''hairy, bald, cute, wrinkled, massive, tiny'' -- and deplores the meddling that has made that diversity possible. Today, the dog no longer evolves through natural selection; he's bred through human selection, with results that are sometimes grotesque.</p>
        <p>Take the bulldog. A century ago, he looked nothing like Winston Churchill. You could almost have called him handsome. Today, a prizewinning bulldog -- one that conforms to the breed standard -- has a terrible underbite, short legs and a physique so stocky that, in the words of one expert, ''you should be able to chop their head off and fit it perfectly between their legs.'' Bulldogs are often too barrel-chested to fit through the birth canal and must be delivered by Caesarean section.</p>
        <p>When Queen Victoria received a Pekingese from the Chinese and started the lap-dog craze, dogs began to lose their identity as working animals. ''Dogs'' devotes a lot of time to working dogs, which do everything from herding sheep to sniffing out diseases in humans. In a perfect world, all dogs would have jobs and live in symbiotic harmony with their humans.</p>
        <p>But we live in a world of pets, where toy dogs, whose snub noses and big eyes remind us of infants, and odd dogs, who give us something to talk about, remain popular. The sight of a two-pound Chihuahua nestling alongside a 270-pound Great Dane illustrates the extremes of canine diversity; the wrinkly shar-pei -- which the dog behaviorist Robert Alleyne calls a ''disaster'' because of its propensity for physical problems -- illustrates the problems of overbreeding. ''We seem to have lost touch with what dogs are,'' frets an expert.</p>
        <p>But the shar-pei is delectable to look at, as are the canoodling Chihuahua and Great Dane. All the dogs on ''Dogs'' (except maybe a few hairless breeds) are adorable. The words in ''Dogs'' should scare us into outrage, but its pictures tell a cuddlier story.</p>
        <p>Nature  Dogs That Changed the World  PBS, Sunday at 8; check local listings.</p>
        <p>Fred Kaufman, series executive producer; William Grant, executive in charge. Produced by Thirteen/WNET New York and Tigress Productions; Thirteen/WNET, series producer.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
