<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jim Thorpe, A Real No. 1 Choice</title>
    <meta content="27anderson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/sports/football/27anderson.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843266"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Thorpe, Jim</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EEDE123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="860" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jim Thorpe, A Real No. 1 Choice</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With Jim Thorpe, a Real No. 1 Choice</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's 1913 and you're a pro football general manager trying to decide which player to select with the No. 1 choice in the draft.</p>
        <p>In 1913, of course, there was no National Football League and no college draft, although a few semipro teams, such as they were, did exist. There was also no videotape, no scouting combine. In choosing the best player in 1913, about all you had to go on, aside from having seen him play, was what was in the newspapers of that era, and for a running back and occasional roustabout named Jim Thorpe that was enough.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sally Jenkins’s new book “The Real All-Americans” offers new glimpses of Jim Thorpe’s football prowess before he found Olympic glory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's 1913 and you're a pro football general manager trying to decide which player to select with the No. 1 choice in the draft.</p>
        <p>In 1913, of course, there was no National Football League and no college draft, although a few semipro teams, such as they were, did exist. There was also no videotape, no scouting combine. In choosing the best player in 1913, about all you had to go on, aside from having seen him play, was what was in the newspapers of that era, and for a running back and occasional roustabout named Jim Thorpe that was enough.</p>
        <p>''Starting like a streak,'' The New York Herald-Tribune wrote of Thorpe in Carlisle's famous victory over Army in 1912, ''he shot through the line, scattering tacklers to all sides of him.''</p>
        <p>That was one of the many tributes to Thorpe's football ability unearthed by Sally Jenkins in a new book, ''The Real All-Americans'' (Doubleday, $24.95), the first up-close-and-personal view of what Thorpe and Carlisle were really like: Thorpe, from the Sac and Fox tribe in Oklahoma, Carlisle the training school for American Indians in Pennsylvania where Pop Warner coached a team that played a college schedule.</p>
        <p>Students of American sports know that Thorpe won Olympic decathlon and pentathlon gold medals in 1912 in Stockholm and that when King Gustav V proclaimed him ''the greatest athlete in the world,'' he said, ''Thanks, King.'' They know that, as the star of the Canton Bulldogs, he was football's most famous player in 1920, when he was a founder of what is now the N.F.L. But until now, only the barest details were known about him at Carlisle.</p>
        <p>When Thorpe arrived there in 1904 he was 16, a slender 5 feet 5 inches and 115 pounds, but by 1907, he was nearly 6-2 and 145, big enough to set a school high-jump record in overalls and to plead with Warner for a tryout. With 30 or 40 players spread across the field, Warner tossed the ball to Thorpe, who feinted some and outran others, as Warner said later, ''like they were old maids.'' But the coach said, ''Let's see if you can do it again, kid.''</p>
        <p>Thorpe did it again. Years later, Warner called those two runs ''an exhibition of athletic talent'' that he had never seen before or again.</p>
        <p>In Thorpe's first game in 1907, against Penn in Philadelphia, he was stopped on his first play, then burst 45 yards, and a star was born. Grantland Rice, the premier sportswriter of that era, wrote that Thorpe ''moved like a breeze.'' But he sometimes moved to his own drummer.</p>
        <p>In 1909 and 1910, he left Carlisle to play semipro baseball for $15 a week in Rocky Mount, N.C. (which led to his being stripped of his Olympic medals). His drinking problems surfaced there. When a policeman tried to arrest him, Thorpe deposited the officer headfirst in a garbage can.</p>
        <p>At a lean 180 pounds, Thorpe returned to Carlisle in 1911 after Warner lured him with the idea of training for the Olympics, but as a football player he occasionally had lazy practice habits. When he didn't run a play up the middle one day, Warner scolded him and he talked back.</p>
        <p>''What's the use of going through them,'' Thorpe told the coach, ''when I can go around them.''</p>
        <p>That season, Thorpe sprained a knee and wrenched an ankle, but against Harvard, with his bad leg wrapped in tape with a plaster cast from his toes to above his knee, he drop-kicked four field goals, including the winner in the final minutes, for an 18-15 victory.</p>
        <p>''My leg was pretty sore,'' he said, ''but it made me more deliberate.''</p>
        <p>On the ship going to the Olympics, Thorpe trained seriously, running on a cork track, but on the way home, he celebrated, drinking and shouting: ''I'm a horse! I'm a horse!'' After another bad street scene involving Thorpe when the Carlisle team's train stopped in Pittsburgh, Warner told him, ''You've got to behave yourself.'' Thorpe apologized and settled down to prepare for the Army game at West Point.</p>
        <p>For all the American Indians at Carlisle who remembered how their fathers or grandfathers had been killed or corralled on reservations by Army soldiers, this was more than a game.</p>
        <p>Army had several players who would become generals, notably Dwight D. Eisenhower, the supreme commander of the Allied forces in Europe in World War II and a two-term president, but that day Eisenhower was just one of the players dominated by Thorpe and his teammates. Thorpe's running set up three touchdowns in a 27-6 rout.</p>
        <p>Carlisle, according to The New York Times, had ''one of the most spectacular aggregations of football players, especially in the backfield, ever assembled.'' And when Walter Camp, a football authority who was as famous then as John Madden is now, mentioned that the Carlisle quarterback called plays too quickly, that he didn't study the defense, Thorpe had an answer.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Camp,'' he said, ''how can he study the defense when there isn't any defense?''</p>
        <p>Another reason why, in 1913, Jim Thorpe would have been any team's No. 1 draft choice.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
