<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Drama Of Daytime: Friendships, Feuds And Fury</title>
    <meta content="27morn" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/arts/television/27morn.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843140"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE TV WATCH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Philbin, Regis</person>
        <person class="online_producer">O'Donnell, Rosie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E5D8153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Drama Of Daytime: Friendships, Feuds And Fury</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Drama of Daytime: Friendships, Feuds and Fury</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALESSANDRA STANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stanley, Alessandra</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Regis Philbin is back. Rosie O'Donnell is leaving.</p>
        <p>Is Kelly Ripa really happy to return the spotlight to the senior co-host? Isn't Barbara Walters counting the days until Ms. O'Donnell finally takes her foot off her back?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the surface of the daytime talk show, everything is sunny and serene, but underneath lies a noisy colony roiling with slights, rifts and rivalries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Regis Philbin is back. Rosie O'Donnell is leaving.</p>
        <p>Is Kelly Ripa really happy to return the spotlight to the senior co-host? Isn't Barbara Walters counting the days until Ms. O'Donnell finally takes her foot off her back?</p>
        <p>Anyone who claims that daytime talk shows are restful is watching ''The People's Court'' on the sly. The chemistry on shows like ''The View'' and ''Live With Regis and Kelly'' is layered, a little like the hallucinations in ''I Never Promised You a Rose Garden.'' On the surface everything is sunny and serene, but underneath lies a noisy colony roiling with slights, rifts and rivalries that pop out whenever the Thorazine subsides.</p>
        <p>Mr. Philbin, who returned to his syndicated show yesterday after bypass surgery and a six-week absence, looked hale and surprisingly hearty; Ms. Ripa solicitously escorted him to their desk as if he were 100 years old and dragging an IV. Mr. Philbin teased her about her glowing star turn while he was away. ''When you're not with me, you actually shine,'' Mr. Philbin said, adding, ''You're never happier.''</p>
        <p>''What do I do to you to dim the light?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>It was a banner day for heart patients. Bill Clinton, who had a quadruple bypass in 2004, cooked whole wheat pasta with a turkey Bolognese sauce on ''Rachael Ray'' yesterday to promote healthy eating habits for children. David Letterman, who had a quintuple bypass in 2000, went on ''Regis and Kelly'' to welcome back his fellow heart patient with some advice. ''Stay away from 'The View,' '' he said. ''They're dropping like flies over there.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Carrie Ann Inaba, a judge on ''Dancing With the Stars,'' stood in for Ms. Walters and all was peachy around Ms. O'Donnell, who went back to razzing Donald Trump. On Wednesday, when she announced her departure, she received a baked Alaska send-off: sweet and warm on the outside and ice-cold at the core.</p>
        <p>When Ms. Walters began to deny any involvement in the contract negotiations, Ms. O'Donnell leaned over and fingered Ms. Walters's lip, ostentatiously removing a speck as Ms. Walters sat rigid in her chair. ''I would like to make one thing perfectly clear,'' Ms. Walters said, ignoring Ms. O'Donnell's interjections. ''I do not participate in the negotiations for Rosie.'' She predicted, correctly, that the announcement would spark another round of stories about their alleged backstage battles. ''It brings back a lot of other things I was accused of doing and did not do.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Walters appeared to be referring to collateral damage from Ms. O'Donnell's rumpus with Mr. Trump, when he accused Ms. Walters of complaining about Ms. O'Donnell to him in a private conversation.</p>
        <p>Nobody needs to eavesdrop on Ms. Walters to perceive that working with Ms. O'Donnell can be a challenge. Her career of extreme highs and lows, the raunchy speech she gave this week at an awards ceremony in New York, and her confused conspiracy theories about 9/11 suggest at the very least an untamed temperament. On ''The View'' on ABC, however, Ms. O'Donnell's high-octane persona worked wonders for the show and drove up its ratings. She was loud, abrasive, monomaniacal and exciting to watch. She gave offense, but she also poked fun at the show's sponsors and never let America forget she was a lesbian bringing up children with her lover.</p>
        <p>But she certainly stood out from the norm. Usually, television personalities spar and give offense in more subtle ways. When Ms. Ripa replaced Kathie Lee Gifford in 2001, she was a refreshing change -- sprightly, irreverent and clever at playing the adorable idiot sidekick to the irascible Mr. Philbin.</p>
        <p>She has since become a highly paid star and is visibly straining for more attention and even respect -- on an episode in November she was affronted when the ''American Idol'' star Clay Aiken playfully put his hand over her mouth to shut her up. She removed it and said that was a ''no-no,'' mugging to the camera that she didn't know where his hand had been. Sometimes internecine tensions bleed into other shows. Discussing the incident on ''The View,'' Ms. O'Donnell accused Ms. Ripa of homophobia -- even though Mr. Aiken has never publicly discussed his sexuality. Ms. Ripa then phoned in to ''The View'' while the show was on the air and reproached Ms. O'Donnell for misjudging her.</p>
        <p>Mr. Philbin, who makes a joke of looking bored when Ms. Ripa chatters, keeps her diva drive in check. In his absence, guests hosts like Anderson Cooper and Martin Short had to be more deferential, and that freedom unleashed way too much of Ms. Ripa's id. On her last show before Mr. Philbin's return, she posed alongside a row of 25 Kelly Ripa look-alikes: a hazy Marcel Duchamp-like tableau of gleaming white teeth and shiny blond hair.</p>
        <p>Mr. Letterman couldn't resist teasing Ms. Ripa, either. After comparing surgery scars with Mr. Philbin, Mr. Letterman turned to Ms. Ripa, held his thumb and index finger a millimeter apart and said, ''You came this close to getting your own show.''</p>
        <p>THE TV WATCH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
