<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Keeping the Faith With Shakespeare</title>
    <meta content="27shak" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/books/27shak.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070503T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843137"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/William Shakespeare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Shakespeare, William</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E5D8153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Keeping the Faith With Shakespeare</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Keeping the Faith With Shakespeare</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GRIMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Grimes, William</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The most compelling production of ''Antony and Cleopatra'' that I can recall took place not in a theater but in a classroom. From a distance of nearly 40 years, I can still hear the basso profundo of Melvin Plotinsky at Indiana University declaiming some of Shakespeare's most stirring lines, interspersed with brilliant commentary that began at 10 a.m. sharp and concluded precisely 45 minutes later. At that point, the thoroughly intimidating Professor Plotinsky would reach into the pocket of his suit jacket, pull out a silver cigarette case and exit stage left, leaving me slack-jawed with amazement.</p>
        <p>I must confess that I have not kept the faith. The A that I earned as a sophomore now burns like a scarlet letter, reminding me of plays not read, poems ignored and bardic thoughts unthought. This month opportunity knocks like the porter at the gate in ''Macbeth'' -- a stack of Shakespeare books released to coincide with the playwright's birthday on April 23. Such onslaughts are a time-honored ritual, but this year the pickings are unusually rich, enticing enough to motivate even a sluggard like myself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A stack of Shakespeare books have been released to coincide with the playwright’s birthday, and the pickings are unusually rich.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The most compelling production of ''Antony and Cleopatra'' that I can recall took place not in a theater but in a classroom. From a distance of nearly 40 years, I can still hear the basso profundo of Melvin Plotinsky at Indiana University declaiming some of Shakespeare's most stirring lines, interspersed with brilliant commentary that began at 10 a.m. sharp and concluded precisely 45 minutes later. At that point, the thoroughly intimidating Professor Plotinsky would reach into the pocket of his suit jacket, pull out a silver cigarette case and exit stage left, leaving me slack-jawed with amazement.</p>
        <p>I must confess that I have not kept the faith. The A that I earned as a sophomore now burns like a scarlet letter, reminding me of plays not read, poems ignored and bardic thoughts unthought. This month opportunity knocks like the porter at the gate in ''Macbeth'' -- a stack of Shakespeare books released to coincide with the playwright's birthday on April 23. Such onslaughts are a time-honored ritual, but this year the pickings are unusually rich, enticing enough to motivate even a sluggard like myself.</p>
        <p>The big book is a new one-volume edition of the complete works, commissioned by the Royal Shakespeare Company and published by the Modern Library. Two eminent Shakespeareans, Jonathan Bate and Eric Rasmussen, have applied modern editing techniques and recent scholarship to correct and update the First Folio, the first collection of the plays, published in 1623. Unlike the smaller-format editions of individual plays known as quartos, the folio edition is thought to preserve the plays as they were performed rather than as originally written, hence the interest of the Royal Shakespeare Company, which is using the updated folio version in its productions of all 36 plays in the 2006-7 season. ''In some cases, the Quartos are probably closer to Shakespeare's original manuscript draft, but the Folio is closer to his playhouse,'' Mr. Bate writes in a superb introduction that deals with Shakespeare and his world as well as textual questions.</p>
        <p>Alert readers will notice small changes. The Folio gives ''kisses'' rather than ''sighs'' in Othello's ''She gave me for my pains a world of sighs.'' But the value of the book, for nonspecialists, lies in its clean, readable presentation, with explanatory notes discreetly arranged at the bottom of the page and compact introductions by Mr. Bate prefacing each play. Mr. Bate also contributes a superb general introduction dealing with Shakespeare and his world as well as textual questions.</p>
        <p>Each prefatory essay is followed by a ''key facts'' box that includes a plot summary, sources for the play's material, the history of its composition and performance, a discussion of textual issues, a statistical breakdown of the major roles (Falstaff has 20 percent of the lines in ''Henry IV, Part I,'' with 184 speeches and eight scenes) and the relative weight of prose and poetry (''A Midsummer Night's Dream'' is 80 percent verse and 20 percent prose, with ''fairly high incidence of rhyme, including deliberately bad rhyme in 'Pyramus and Thisbe.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bate can cover only so much ground in his general introduction, which is why ''Shakespeare and Co.,'' a lively and highly entertaining introduction to Shakespeare's professional world by Stanley Wells, comes in handy. Mr. Wells, who edited the Penguin and Oxford editions of the plays, puts Shakespeare in his place -- that is, he considers him as a working professional surrounded by dozens of other playwrights and hundreds of actors, all part of a sizable entertainment industry laboring nonstop to keep Londoners amused. Mr. Wells does not draw an explicit comparison to Hollywood, as Mr. Bate does, but the similarities are inescapable. Writers like Shakespeare and others discussed by Mr. Wells -- Thomas Dekker, Ben Jonson, Thomas Middleton and John Fletcher -- were guns for hire writing as fast as they could to satisfy the insatiable appetite of the acting companies for new material.</p>
        <p>Shakespeare was a steady but not particularly speedy producer. Most of his peers spent four to six weeks on a play, sometimes working in teams. Dekker wrote or collaborated on 11 plays in 1599. The text was not sacred. As Mr. Wells speculates, some of the more celebrated comic actors might have improvised and fattened their parts, hinted at in Hamlet's instructions that ''those that play your clowns speak no more than is set down for them.'' Many of the differences between quarto and folio texts originate in changes made by acting companies as a play progressed from one performance to the next. As in Hollywood, the writer enjoyed a lowly status. Even late in his career, it seems, Shakespeare was expected to do collaborative journeyman's work, as he did in the fragmentary ''Sir Thomas More,'' a mishmash worked on by multiple writers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wells spends a fair amount of time recreating the playgoing experience in Elizabethan times. In this effort, he is aided by David Bevington, a Shakespeare scholar at the University of Chicago who has focused on the performance histories of the plays in ''This Wide and Universal Theater.'' Shakespeare has come full circle. The spare productions at the Globe, reliant on a few props and crowd scenes of perhaps five actors, evolved into the hyperrealist fantasias of the late Victorian stage, with landscaped gardens, running streams and live rabbits scampering through the enchanted forest of ''A Midsummer Night's Dream.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bevington, by focusing on the stage directions in Shakespeare's plays, shows how actors relied on words alone to suggest time, place and action, and how the stage at the Globe could be manipulated in the hands of a canny playwright. There was no balcony in ''Romeo and Juliet.'' On the other hand, since there was nothing in the way of stage décor, no intervals were needed to move from scene to scene. More recent directors, returning to Shakespeare's idea of staging, have embraced abstract spaces and let the language do the work.</p>
        <p>The most challenging Shakespeare book of the year is A. D. Nuttall's ''Shakespeare the Thinker,'' a close reading of the plays that tries to map the creases and folds in Shakespeare's mysterious, elusive brain. Mr. Nuttall, a professor of English at Oxford University who died suddenly in January at 69, is an idiosyncratic critic with an anti-academic bent. In his introduction, he describes leaving a conference of Shakespeare scholars in Stratford-on-Avon in the 1960s and walking to Anne Hathaway's cottage, wondering all the while what it was like to be Shakespeare. In his final book, he takes another stab at it, this time walking through the plays.</p>
        <p>''Shakespeare the Thinker'' is wayward and intermittently brilliant, with pithy barroom observations sharing space with arguments so fine-spun they threaten to disappear on the page. Mr. Nuttall casually drops references to ''Goodfellas,'' ''The Godfather'' and the novels of Ian McEwan as he explicates and explores, stretching interpretation in every direction. ''Marlowe is a great reductionist, forever asking 'What does it all come down to?' '' he writes in a pointed aside. ''Shakespeare, conversely, loves to ask, 'What else could be going on?' '' Those other, unexplored alternatives are Mr. Nuttall's meat and drink. This engaged, unpredictable mind can be caught in full flight in two books reissued by Yale University Press, ''Two Concepts of Allegory,'' a study of ''The Tempest,'' and ''A New Mimesis: Shakespeare and the Representation of Reality.''</p>
        <p>Shakespeare does not belong to the scholars only. In the 19th century, his words were on the lips of ordinary Americans, who, in an era passionate about political oratory and religious sermons, regarded Shakespeare as a source of moral instruction and immortal speeches. On one fateful night in 1849, popular adulation turned violent in a deadly episode recreated by Nigel Cliff in ''The Shakespeare Riots.''</p>
        <p>Two great actors dominated the stage in the middle of the century, one English and one American. Edwin Forrest, who learned his trade on the Western frontier, epitomized Jacksonian America. William Charles Macready, the pre-eminent English actor of his time, brought a more restrained, cerebral acting style that stood in stark contrast to Forrest's emotive, physical approach. The world was not big enough for both of them, and when the two, formerly friends, fell out, their quarrel took on international dimensions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cliff, a former theater and film critic for The Times of London, evokes an adolescent America besotted with Shakespeare. Ragged theatrical companies, performing on riverboats or in local taverns, took their audiences to Venice and Verona, accepting payment in potatoes or bacon if money was scarce. Shakespeare counted for a quarter of all plays performed in the United States in the 19th century, and on the frontier his popularity was second to none.</p>
        <p>In Edwin Forrest, Americans saw one of their own. ''His fans wanted a larger-than-life hero who gave them electrifying emotions and stirring sentiment, and Forrest was the genuine article, the fearless, self-reliant republican, the Jacksonian giant from the woods.'' In a nation throbbing with a sense of cultural inferiority and overrun by English actors, he represented a new beginning. ''Let us support this tender sapling and prove to the pedants of Europe that that our soil is fertile in genius and that her children know how to cherish and reward it,'' a New Orleans newspaper wrote after a Forrest appearance.</p>
        <p>The suspense mounts as Mr. Cliff traces the growing enmity between the two men and the curious way that a personal rivalry evolved into a cultural and political war. Who owned Shakespeare? Which country deserved to rule the future? Class tensions complicated the picture. Forrest had the allegiance of the working classes, while Macready was favored by sophisticates in Boston and New York. When the two actors turned up in New York at the same time, Macready at the snooty Astor Place Theater, Forrest at the Broadway Theater, the stage was set for violence, and New York's groundlings delivered it, in rioting that claimed as many as 30 lives.</p>
        <p>Such were the passions aroused by Shakespeare a century and a half ago. And how could one not sympathize with the American desire to kidnap England's national playwright and put him in an Uncle Sam suit? ''That fellow Shakespeare could sure spill the real stuff,'' one ranch hand said after hearing Julius Caesar's ''dogs of war'' speech. ''He's the only poet I ever seen what was fed on raw meat.'' Darn right.</p>
        <p>Text Messaging  Here is information about the Shakespeare books mentioned:</p>
        <p>A NEW MIMESIS: SHAKESPEARE AND THE REPRESENTATION OF REALITY, by A. D. Nuttall (Yale University Press); 209 pages; paperback, $20.</p>
        <p>SHAKESPEARE AND CO., by Stanley Wells (Pantheon); 285 pages; $26.</p>
        <p>SHAKESPEARE THE THINKER, by A. D. Nuttall (Yale University Press); 428 pages; $30.</p>
        <p>THE SHAKESPEARE RIOTS, by Nigel Cliff (Random House); 312 pages; $26.95.</p>
        <p>THIS WIDE AND UNIVERSAL THEATER, by David Bevington (University of Chicago Press); 242 pages; $25.</p>
        <p>TWO CONCEPTS OF ALLEGORY: A STUDY OF SHAKESPEARE'S THE TEMPEST AND THE LOGIC OF ALLEGORICAL EXPRESSION, by A. D. Nuttall (Yale University Press); 175 pages; paperback, $20.</p>
        <p>WILLIAM SHAKESPEARE COMPLETE WORKS, by Jonathan Bate and Eric Rasmussen (Modern Library); 2,485 pages; $65.</p>
        <p>BOOKS</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 3, 2007, Thursday  A books column in Weekend on Friday, about several books on Shakespeare released to coincide with his birthday last month, referred incorrectly to the porter's actions in ''Macbeth.'' He opens the gate; he does not knock on it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 3, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>A books column in Weekend on Friday, about several books on Shakespeare released to coincide with his birthday last month, referred incorrectly to the porter's actions in ''Macbeth.'' He opens the gate; he does not knock on it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
