<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Why Won't Companies Invest More?</title>
    <meta content="27norris" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/business/27norris.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843242"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HIGH &amp; LOW FINANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Reserve System</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Floyd Norris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E2DE123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="708" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Why Won't Companies Invest More?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Why Won’t Companies Invest More?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Low level of business investment is having negative impact on United States economy; shows lack of confidence that is less optimistic than Federal Reserve's hope that investment will increase as economy remains steady; companies continue to buy back their own stock, attempting to reduce number of outstanding shares, which fails to spur economic growth; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Federal Reserve, it is puzzling that business investment is not stronger. To business executives, it is only natural. They see relatively few opportunities for investment, and ample reason to send cash to shareholders.</p>
        <p>In a speech to a conference at the Levy Economics Institute of Bard College last week, Frederic S. Mishkin, a Fed governor, pointed to the housing slowdown as one reason for worry. But then he added that the low level of business investment was the ''second major area of concern,'' one that ''perhaps could pose noticeable downside risks.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The reality is that companies are quite happy spending their profits  and in many cases, much more  on buying back their stock.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Federal Reserve, it is puzzling that business investment is not stronger. To business executives, it is only natural. They see relatively few opportunities for investment, and ample reason to send cash to shareholders.</p>
        <p>In a speech to a conference at the Levy Economics Institute of Bard College last week, Frederic S. Mishkin, a Fed governor, pointed to the housing slowdown as one reason for worry. But then he added that the low level of business investment was the ''second major area of concern,'' one that ''perhaps could pose noticeable downside risks.''</p>
        <p>He speculated that businesses might be less optimistic about the economy than the Fed was, and voiced hope that investment would pick up as the economy continued to do fine and companies realized their pessimism was unwarranted.</p>
        <p>Perhaps so, but the reality is that companies are quite happy spending their profits -- and in many cases, much more -- on buying back their stock.</p>
        <p>I.B.M. shares spurted up this week on the news that it was planning to increase its already substantial spending on repurchases, and in addition, would raise its dividend.</p>
        <p>The dividend is nice, but at the new quarterly rate of 40 cents a share, it amounts to something like 1.6 percent of the stock price. But if the company spends all the $15 billion it set aside for share repurchases over the next year, it will retire about 10 percent of its shares.</p>
        <p>Most of the money I.B.M. spends on stock will be borrowed, a fact that reflects the friendliness of debt markets, which are quite willing to lend money at low rates to companies with far lower-quality debt than I.B.M. Its Triple-A days are long past, but it still is a high Single-A credit.</p>
        <p>''We see an opportunity here, because of the strength of the business,'' I.B.M.'s treasurer, Jesse J. Greene, told me. He figures that having gotten out of personal computers, the company's cash flows are more stable and it can easily carry more debt.</p>
        <p>I.B.M.'s planned repurchases are extraordinary, at about twice the going rate for big companies. Howard Silverblatt, the senior index analyst at Standard &amp; Poor's, estimates the payout ratio of companies in the S.&amp; P. 500 -- adding together dividends and buybacks -- is now 5.3 percent.</p>
        <p>That is well above what Treasury bonds yield, and constitutes one of the most compelling bullish arguments in the stock market now.</p>
        <p>It is also more than double the payout rate that existed in the late 1990s and 2000, before the technology stock bubble burst. Then companies saw ample opportunities for investment. Perhaps the fact that much of that money was wasted has made them more hesitant.</p>
        <p>A somewhat more cynical explanation for the lack of capital spending was offered at the Levy conference by Robert W. Parenteau, the chief United States economist and strategist for RCM, a money management firm owned by Allianz, the German bank and insurance company.</p>
        <p>''Companies are lifting their own share prices in a remarkable feat of manipulation,'' he said, suggesting stock option profits were a motivating factor.</p>
        <p>I.B.M. has sent out more than 100 percent of net income to shareholders in each of the last three years. And in the first quarter, before the big new purchase plan was announced, the figure topped 200 percent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greene of I.B.M. notes that last year the company spent about $15 billion on capital spending, research and development and acquisitions. ''We do not intend any pullback in the investments we make as a result of this decision,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Whether you accept the analysis of Mr. Mishkin, that companies simply do not see a good enough economy to justify more spending, or the much more cynical view of Mr. Parenteau, it is clear that I.B.M. is not alone in wanting to reduce the number of its shares outstanding.</p>
        <p>Such moves help to support share prices, but they do not spur economic growth, which is why the Fed is worried. And they leave corporate America more heavily indebted, a fact that may seem regrettable if, or when, the economy does turn down and profits fall.</p>
        <p>It may turn out that many of the era's big payouts to shareholders were a sign of corporate complacency, not of corporate profitability.</p>
        <p>HIGH &amp; LOW FINANCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
