<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On 4th-and-10, Russell's Star Was Launched</title>
    <meta content="27draft" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/sports/football/27draft.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070428T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843267"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Louisiana State University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Russell, JaMarcus</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEEDE123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1265" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On 4th-and-10, Russell's Star Was Launched</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On 4th-and-10, Russell’s Football Star Was Launched</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEE JENKINS; Michael S. Schmidt contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jenkins, Lee</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The play was called Razor Deep Y Snake. Even the name sounded ominous.</p>
        <p>''You can't run that play with just any quarterback,'' said Jimbo Fisher, the man who devised it. ''You can only run it with a guy like JaMarcus Russell.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>By throwing the game winning pass against Arizona State in September 2005, JaMarcus Russell became a Louisiana legend and made his first claim to becoming a franchise N.F.L. quarterback.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The play was called Razor Deep Y Snake. Even the name sounded ominous.</p>
        <p>''You can't run that play with just any quarterback,'' said Jimbo Fisher, the man who devised it. ''You can only run it with a guy like JaMarcus Russell.''</p>
        <p>Razor Deep Y Snake is not a safe play. When Fisher was the offensive coordinator at Louisiana State and Russell was his starting quarterback, the Tigers usually ran it on first down, when the stakes were low and they could take a chance downfield.</p>
        <p>But on the night of Sept. 10, 2005, with L.S.U. trailing Arizona State by 3 points and only 83 seconds left in the game, Fisher called Razor Deep Y Snake on fourth-and-10 from the opponent's 39.</p>
        <p>It was not the play that made Russell a top N.F.L. prospect. But it was the play that won the game and made him a Louisiana legend.</p>
        <p>The week before, L.S.U.'s athletic complex had served as a shelter, a hospital and a morgue for victims of Hurricane Katrina. Russell housed 23 evacuees in his two-bedroom apartment. One of them was his girlfriend's grandfather, Fats Domino.</p>
        <p>The Tigers' opening game, against North Texas, was postponed. Their second game, against Arizona State, was moved to Tempe, Ariz. L.SU. Coach Les Miles did not announce who would start at quarterback until the team arrived in Tempe.</p>
        <p>The choice came down to the sophomores Russell and Matt Flynn. Russell got the nod, but barely. If L.S.U. lost to Arizona State in the season opener -- the first major sporting event involving a Gulf Coast team after Katrina -- Russell knew the repercussions. His job might be in jeopardy.</p>
        <p>Before L.S.U.'s final offensive series of the game, Russell walked to the sideline and dropped into a crouch. He took off his helmet, emblazoned with a fleur-de-lis. Miles gently placed a hand on Russell's shaved head.</p>
        <p>''There was a lot riding on it,'' Miles said. ''There was a lot of pressure.''</p>
        <p>How Russell responded is a large reason he might be the first pick in the N.F.L. draft Saturday.</p>
        <p>Most scouts fell for Russell at the Sugar Bowl in January, when he overwhelmed Notre Dame and overshadowed his counterpart, Brady Quinn. But Russell's future was more likely determined by that fourth-and-10 from the Arizona State 39.</p>
        <p>L.S.U. had trailed by 10 points in the fourth quarter and had come back with consecutive touchdowns, on a blocked field goal and a blocked punt. Arizona State regained the lead, but Russell started to wonder if a greater force was at work.</p>
        <p>''I was thinking to myself, God put us in this position,'' Russell said. ''He got us this far and we just had to put a little extra hard work in.''</p>
        <p>L.S.U. expected Arizona State to blitz on fourth down, so Fisher wanted to call a play that would get Russell out of the pocket. L.S.U. also expected Arizona State to guard against 10-yard pass patterns, so Fisher wanted to send one receiver deep.</p>
        <p>Razor Deep Y Snake seemed to be the best option.</p>
        <p>The play was called for Early Doucet, who had already dropped three passes in the game. Doucet was instructed to make a double move, which would theoretically leave him wide open and sprinting down the middle of the field. Russell would only have to loft the ball in the air and let Doucet run under it for a touchdown.</p>
        <p>''It was such a big moment for everyone,'' said Fisher, now the offensive coordinator at Florida State. ''It was the kind of moment that makes legends.''</p>
        <p>Russell took the snap in the shotgun, but as he rolled to the right, peeking over his mammoth offensive line, he noticed a problem. Arizona State was not blitzing. The Sun Devils had dropped eight defenders into pass coverage.</p>
        <p>Doucet made his first move, easily shaking a defensive back. But as he made his second move, a safety sneaked up behind him. Doucet did not have enough separation from the safety. Russell did not believe he could complete the pass.</p>
        <p>Instead of forcing the ball into coverage, Russell tucked it and ran in the opposite direction, back to his left, crossing the field and leaving his offensive line behind. He was going to make the play on his own.</p>
        <p>''I still wake up in the middle of the night and second-guess our call,'' said Bill Miller, then the defensive coordinator at Arizona State, who is now at Western Michigan. ''In hindsight, I should have blitzed him.''</p>
        <p>With a limited rush, Russell had time to let Doucet continue his route toward the goal line. When Doucet looked back for the ball, he locked eyes with Russell.</p>
        <p>In the week leading up to the game, L.S.U. receivers had worked on a scramble drill in case their quarterback was flushed from the pocket. Doucet remembered the drill.</p>
        <p>As Russell drifted toward the left sideline, Doucet followed along, angling his route toward the left side of the end zone.</p>
        <p>Russell did not have the luxury of setting his feet. But he is a 6-foot-6 quarterback who can throw 40 yards from a seated position and 50 yards from his knees. Throwing off balance, on the run, is a minor inconvenience.</p>
        <p>''I just remember how tall he stood right then,'' said Mike Serio, a Louisiana State fan who was watching from the stands. ''He was so cool. He looked like Goliath back there.''</p>
        <p>Serio had been to every L.S.U. game for 24 consecutive seasons. He lost his house in the hurricane but still made it to Tempe, cheering the Tigers alongside evacuees from Veterans Memorial Hospital in Phoenix.</p>
        <p>By now, N.F.L. scouts have dissected all 342 passes that Russell threw at L.S.U. -- every spiral and every lame duck. Russell's pass to Doucet was not his prettiest. The ball wobbled slightly as it reached the goal line. Russell had to muscle it all 39 yards.</p>
        <p>The catch was not perfect, either. Doucet was covered by two defensive backs, Josh Barrett and Maurice London, and he appeared to bobble the ball as he fell out of bounds.</p>
        <p>But no one dared review the play. The referees signaled for a touchdown, Doucet was mobbed by cheerleaders, and the Tigers won, 35-31. It was one of eight fourth-quarter comeback victories that Russell would lead in his college career.</p>
        <p>Louisiana State historians immediately compared Russell's heave with Billy Cannon's 89-yard punt return against Mississippi that clinched the 1959 Heisman Trophy. But the Heisman is an individual award. The victory against Arizona State was for everyone.</p>
        <p>It started a statewide celebration -- in New Orleans bars, where patrons had to listen on the radio; in the Houston Astrodome, where evacuees watched on television; and in a North Carolina hotel, where the Saints were staying for the night.</p>
        <p>The Saints get most of the credit, at least among sports teams, for brightening moods after the storm. But Russell was the first post-Katrina star. His touchdown pass came more than a year before the Saints signed Drew Brees and drafted Reggie Bush.</p>
        <p>With one play, Russell demonstrated all the key characteristics of a franchise quarterback -- poise, mobility, arm strength, accuracy, and an uncanny sense of occasion.</p>
        <p>''He throws the ball better than anyone I have ever seen,'' said Tom Martinez, a quarterback coach who has worked with Russell, John Elway and Tom Brady.</p>
        <p>Elway and Brady are famous for their fourth-quarter comebacks and high-stakes touchdown passes. Together, they have won five Super Bowls.</p>
        <p>Russell has a long way to go to match them. But Razor Deep Y Snake was a start.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 28, 2007, Saturday  A sports article yesterday about quarterback JaMarcus Russell's emergence as a star at Louisiana State University referred imprecisely to one of his statistics. Russell had 342 passes during his senior season, not in his collegiate career. (His career number was 797.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 28, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>A sports article yesterday about quarterback JaMarcus Russell's emergence as a star at Louisiana State University referred imprecisely to one of his statistics. Russell had 342 passes during his senior season, not in his collegiate career. (His career number was 797.)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
