<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AHEAD | Exhibits on Human Origins; Museums, God and Man</title>
    <meta content="27ahead" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/travel/escapes/27ahead.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843130"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Ahead Exhibits | On Human Origins"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Creationism and Intelligent Design</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Considine, Austin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Archeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Creationism and Intelligent Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7D8153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="902" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AHEAD | Exhibits on Human Origins; Museums, God and Man</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Museums, God and Man</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AUSTIN CONSIDINE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Considine, Austin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on evolution and creationism exhibits at museums around country; list; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the new Hall of Human Origins at the American Museum of Natural History in New York, amid reconstructed skeletons of Neanderthals, fleshy models of Homo Erectus and films about the development of viruses, Reggie and Athena Samuel, Virginians of African-American descent, leaned in to get a closer look at a display on the evolution of racial differences. Their year-old son, Reginald, slept peacefully in the stroller beside them.</p>
        <p>''I'm sure we're going to have to answer our son's question about why are people dark-skinned versus light-skinned, and that exhibit right there went into great detail about it,'' Ms. Samuel said. ''I thought that was so interesting how it showed the science behind skin color. Now we're equipped with the knowledge to teach him.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At evolution exhibits, a growing feature of science museums around the country, the options for learning about human origins are more varied than you’d think.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the new Hall of Human Origins at the American Museum of Natural History in New York, amid reconstructed skeletons of Neanderthals, fleshy models of Homo Erectus and films about the development of viruses, Reggie and Athena Samuel, Virginians of African-American descent, leaned in to get a closer look at a display on the evolution of racial differences. Their year-old son, Reginald, slept peacefully in the stroller beside them.</p>
        <p>''I'm sure we're going to have to answer our son's question about why are people dark-skinned versus light-skinned, and that exhibit right there went into great detail about it,'' Ms. Samuel said. ''I thought that was so interesting how it showed the science behind skin color. Now we're equipped with the knowledge to teach him.''</p>
        <p>Evolution exhibits, a growing feature of science museums around the country, answer questions about human origins with explanations accepted by the great majority of scientists. And people curious about the other way of looking at things -- the creationist view -- have some options, too, including the Creation Museum, which is opening May 28 in Petersburg, Ky., just outside Cincinnati.</p>
        <p>Answers in Genesis, a Christian ministry group based in Petersburg, Ky., owns the museum, which, in nearly 70,000 square feet of space, will feature animatronic dinosaurs, Adam and Eve sculptures, a depiction of Noah's Ark, a Stargazer's Room that attempts to refute the Big Bang theory, and displays giving biblical explanations for the diversification of races and languages.</p>
        <p>Ken Ham, the museum's president, said that its staff will include people with advanced degrees in astrophysics, cell biology and other disciplines, and that an abundance of fossils will be on display. He made no distinction between the Creation Museum and a museum of science. ''All museums are religious museums,'' he said, ''because those that explain life without God -- that's a religious position, that's a faith position that everything happens by natural process.''</p>
        <p>If evolutionary science and creationism represent dueling views, however, the creationists still appear to be far overmatched on the museum front.</p>
        <p>The Field Museum in Chicago, following up on the popularity of its permanent exhibit ''Evolving Planet,'' opened last year, has just added a 7,000-square-foot temporary exhibit called ''Dinosaurs: Ancient Fossils, New Discoveries.'' On display through September, it includes an animatronic T-rex that helps explain a possible link between dinosaurs and modern birds.</p>
        <p>The touring ''Darwin'' exhibit that drew crowds in New York a couple of years ago and in other cities closes today at the Museum of Science in Boston and opens in June at the Field Museum in Chicago.</p>
        <p>The ''Explore Evolution'' exhibition, currently on display at four museums across the West and Midwest, is expanding with a fifth installation to open later this year in Austin, Tex. Evolution exhibits are also evolving themselves, incorporating information from recent research in fields from linguistics to the human genome project. Michael J. Novacek, provost of science at the American Museum of Natural History, said the most exciting part of the new Hall of Human Origins was its treatment of ''the great convergence of discovery about human origins between the fossil record and the genomic sciences.''</p>
        <p>In San Diego, the permanent exhibit ''Footsteps Through Time: Four Million Years of Human Evolution'' at the Museum of Man has expanded with displays on stem-cell research and mitochondrial DNA, and soon will add new casts of a Neanderthal skeleton and early hominid skulls found in Chad and the Republic of Georgia.</p>
        <p>Rose Tyson, the museum's curator of physical anthropology, is unfazed by the presence about 30 miles away of the Institute for Creation Research's Museum of Creation and Earth History in Santee, Calif., where ''A Walk Through History'' takes visitors through the Garden of Eden. ''I think they go along and do their thing, and we go along and do our thing,'' she said. ''We're a science museum, and we stick to that.''</p>
        <p>Mr. and Mrs. Samuel, meanwhile, felt little sense of conflict as they toured the Hall of Human Origins in New York. They are Christians who believe in evolution, they said, and would find answers for their son wherever they could. ''I think it boils down to faith,'' Mr. Samuel said. ''As I look at it, and as we've talked about it, we pretty much want to provide as many resources as possible that will allow our kids to make their own decisions.''</p>
        <p>DETAILS</p>
        <p>BOSTON -- Museum of Science; 617-723-2500, www.mos.org; $16.</p>
        <p>What: ''Darwin.''</p>
        <p>When: Closes today.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK -- American Museum of Natural History, (212) 769-5100, www.amnh.org; $14 suggested.</p>
        <p>What: Hall of Human Origins.</p>
        <p>When: Permanent exhibit.</p>
        <p>PETERSBURG, KY. -- Creation Museum; (859) 727-2222, www.answersingenesis.org/museum. $19.95.</p>
        <p>What: Displays explaining a creator-designed world.</p>
        <p>When: Opening May 28.</p>
        <p>CHICAGO -- Field Museum, 312-922-9410; www.fieldmuseum.org; $12 general admission (additional cost for special exhibitions).</p>
        <p>What: ''Dinosaurs: Ancient Fossils, New Discoveries,'' $7; ''Darwin,'' $7.</p>
        <p>When: Through September for the dinosaur fossils; June 15 through Jan. 1, 2008, for ''Darwin.''</p>
        <p>AUSTIN, Tex. -- Texas Memorial Museum, 512-471-1604; www.utexas.edu/tmm; free. (Closed for renovations June 1 to Oct. 1.)</p>
        <p>What: ''Explore Evolution,'' www.explore-evolution.unl.edu.</p>
        <p>When: Opening Oct. 1.</p>
        <p>SAN DIEGO -- Museum of Man, (619) 239-2001; www.museumofman.org, $8.</p>
        <p>What: ''Footsteps Through Time: Four Million Years of Human Evolution.''</p>
        <p>When: Permanent exhibit.</p>
        <p>SANTEE, CALIF. -- Museum of Creation and Earth History, (619) 596-6011;www.icr.org, free.</p>
        <p>What: ''A Walk Through History.''</p>
        <p>When: Permanent exhibit.</p>
        <p>Ahead Exhibits | On Human Origins</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
