<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Keeping the Old Off Off Broadway Spirit Alive</title>
    <meta content="27brig" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/theater/27brig.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843148"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Living Theater</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Brown, Kenneth H</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Malina, Judith</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE4D8153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1413" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Keeping the Old Off Off Broadway Spirit Alive</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Keeping the Old Off Off Broadway Spirit Alive</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES ISHERWOOD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Isherwood, Charles</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like all the performing arts, theater is both enduring and ephemeral. Its influence can be profound, but the act itself exists in time, and is consumed by its passing. Of the many thousands of plays written over the past couple of millenniums, only a fraction have survived, and even then they are only blueprints for three-dimensional structures that have been dismantled. The great actors from the ages before film and video are now known to us only by description.</p>
        <p>Celebrated companies, too, have life cycles. Early pioneers in forging a serious modern theater in this country -- the Provincetown Players, the Theater Guild, Eva Le Gallienne's Civic Repertory Theater -- are now histories in books, although the artists they nurtured and the work they created dug roots that fed the theater of future years in important ways.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After many years of sporadic, itinerant art-making both here and abroad, the Living Theater has settled in a permanent new home just south of the East Village.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like all the performing arts, theater is both enduring and ephemeral. Its influence can be profound, but the act itself exists in time, and is consumed by its passing. Of the many thousands of plays written over the past couple of millenniums, only a fraction have survived, and even then they are only blueprints for three-dimensional structures that have been dismantled. The great actors from the ages before film and video are now known to us only by description.</p>
        <p>Celebrated companies, too, have life cycles. Early pioneers in forging a serious modern theater in this country -- the Provincetown Players, the Theater Guild, Eva Le Gallienne's Civic Repertory Theater -- are now histories in books, although the artists they nurtured and the work they created dug roots that fed the theater of future years in important ways.</p>
        <p>And while it took place just a generation or two ago, the fertile tumult of the early years of the Off Off Broadway theater movement seems almost as distant. Wading through the tricked-out strollers clogging the streets of Greenwich Village today, it is hard to conceive that not so long ago -- well, O.K., getting on toward 50 years now -- a scrappy, determined bunch of young artists ignited a vibrant new era in theater by staging plays in local coffeehouses, churches and other commandeered spaces.</p>
        <p>The Caffe Cino on Cornelia Street is now long gone. The Judson Church on Washington Square still stands, a sturdy symbol of a time when organized religion and art were not necessarily considered antithetical forms of spiritual expression. But it is no longer a generator of aesthetic fireworks.</p>
        <p>A couple of stalwart survivors have endured. Ellen Stewart, den mother of the Off Off movement, has tenaciously held on at La MaMa. And the granddaddy of them all, the Living Theater, founded by Julian Beck and Judith Malina more than a half-century ago, made good on its name by living on to defy the changes that swept away its former confreres in theatrical -- and political -- radicalism.</p>
        <p>After many years of sporadic, itinerant art-making both here and abroad, the company has settled in a permanent new home just south of the East Village, on Clinton Street on the Lower East Side. The inaugural production in its basement space is the company's first staging since 1963 of ''The Brig,'' by Kenneth H. Brown, directed by Ms. Malina herself, who, at 80, continues to run the company. (Mr. Beck died in 1985.)</p>
        <p>The play, about the brutalizing experience of life in a Marine Corps prison, is among the most famous in the company's history because of its content; its hyperrealism, arresting at the time; and the tumultuous circumstances that attended its last performance. The authorities had shut down the theater, located on the corner of 14th Street and Avenue of the Americas, for delinquent taxes in the middle of the run, but the actors and a final audience sneaked into the padlocked theater. The tax charges were eventually dismissed, but Mr. Beck and Ms. Malina served short sentences for contempt of court. After their release, they decamped with some of the company for several years of touring in Europe.</p>
        <p>The Living Theater had been founded by the pair in 1947 to challenge the dominant forms of American theater and to rededicate it to a new purpose: connecting art and life in ways that asked audiences to feel, with a new, visceral truth, the intimate relationships between them. Although most of the first productions were plays by American and European modernists -- Brecht and Lorca, Cocteau and Gertrude Stein -- in 1959 the company charted a new way forward with Jack Gelber's play ''The Connection,'' which depicted, in meticulously naturalistic rhythms, a group of heroin addicts waiting anxiously for their dealer.</p>
        <p>''The Brig'' was likewise a work of quasi-documentary realism, lacking a traditional narrative. It presents the grinding routine of a day in the life of 10 imprisoned marines under the humiliating watch of steel-souled guards. A chain-link cage surrounds the prisoners, jammed together in bunk beds with just enough space to stand between them. Another layer of barbed wire puts a symbolic wall between the marines and the audience.</p>
        <p>Watching the play today, in the tight confines of the Living Theater's underground space, you can easily sense how arrestingly strange its methods must have seemed four decades ago. Time drips by slowly as the prisoners go through rigidly choreographed routines to dress, to bathe, to perform menial chores. Referred to only by numbers, the grunts jump to attention, glazed eyes front at all times, like animals instinctively reacting to the threat of physical abuse. (Minor infractions are greeted by a swift punch to the stomach.)</p>
        <p>The prisoners move in an exaggerated, almost comic jog. ''Knees up!,'' a guard barks, if they fall into a lazy amble. They are forbidden to exchange even the briefest of small talk. Virtually all of their dialogue consists of shouted requests for permission to cross a series of white lines marking the boundaries between the cell and various public areas. Although they are referred to as maggots, worms and insects by the guards, the prisoners' blank faces never register a flicker of resentment, even as their uniforms become drenched in sweat.</p>
        <p>As the men are put through their relentless, often pointedly pointless paces, the numbing effect of energy expended in the absence of thought begins to anesthetize the audience's response to the behavior on view. Watching men stripped of all but the will to avoid punishment by obeying orders is itself a dehumanizing experience, and therefore a disturbing one. When, late in the play, one of the prisoners suddenly has an emotional breakdown, it unsettlingly strikes you as an aberrant disruption in a perfectly ordered pattern.</p>
        <p>At a time when public views of military life were still largely wholesome and adulatory, the casual brutality so nakedly exposed in ''The Brig'' was clearly shocking. Today outrage is not so easily generated. A disillusioned, skeptical view of military practices is one of the legacies of the Vietnam debacle, and few contemporary audiences will come to the play with a romanticized view of life in the military. The behavior of the guards in ''The Brig'' certainly cannot compare in grim sadism to the graphic pictures from Abu Ghraib.</p>
        <p>In a note in the program Ms. Malina implicitly ties the play to Abu Ghraib and other current events. ''In 'The Brig' we see the discipline and the training to obedience that suppresses free will and makes it possible for good-hearted young women and men to commit the atrocities that armies everywhere commit,'' she writes.</p>
        <p>But the play itself shows us only the mechanism by which this occurs, not the process itself, since the degeneration of the prisoners' humanity seems to have taken place before the action begins. We too know them only as numbers, not men whose moral energies are destroyed before our eyes. In this sense ''The Brig'' is fundamentally undramatic. (Also, it could be argued that the will-warping effect of military discipline was only one of several contributing factors to the horror of Abu Ghraib.)</p>
        <p>The absence of traditional theatrical trappings -- characters, narrative, dialogue -- was of course what made ''The Brig'' and similar 1960s experiments (Andy Warhol's movies, the choreography associated with the Judson Church) so radical and attention-grabbing. This kind of work suggested that only a thin membrane separated life and art, and that one way to create art was simply to recontextualize natural human behavior.</p>
        <p>It was an influential movement, but one that spent itself quickly as some of its methods were absorbed into the mainstream. Today the two hours of seemingly unstructured experience put onstage in ''The Brig'' don't seem particularly revolutionary. Not when you can watch a cheddar cheese age live on the Internet, 24/7, thanks to the wonder of 21st-century technology.</p>
        <p>But anyone with a serious interest in the history of the American theater will want to see ''The Brig,'' if only for the rare opportunity it provides to revisit a moment when theater was in the forefront of both aesthetic and political radicalism. The moment is now long past, but the fervent performances of the young actors in Ms. Malina's new production suggest that the energy it drew on -- the belief that art should make us all break into a sweat -- has hardly been extinguished.</p>
        <p>''The Brig'' continues through June 3 at the Living Theater, 21 Clinton Street, near Stanton Street, Lower East Side; (212) 792-8050, livingtheatre.org.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
