<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>One of the Best Recruiters in the Neighborhood</title>
    <meta content="27diaspora" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/business/27diaspora.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843204"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Wasserstein Perella</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Perella, Joseph R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E2DF123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="535" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>One of the Best Recruiters in the Neighborhood</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">One of the Best Recruiters in the Neighborhood</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He may be known as a deal maker, but Joseph R. Perella has also shown himself to be one of the financial industry's sharpest recruiters.</p>
        <p>Many of Wall Street's top talents got an early start when Mr. Perella discovered and helped train them in the 1980s. His first hot pick was Bruce Wasserstein. Together, at First Boston and then at Wasserstein Perella, they created a dynasty of bankers and executives that has spread throughout Wall Street and corporate America.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>He may be known as a deal maker but Joseph R. Perella is also one of the financial industry’s sharpest recruiters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He may be known as a deal maker, but Joseph R. Perella has also shown himself to be one of the financial industry's sharpest recruiters.</p>
        <p>Many of Wall Street's top talents got an early start when Mr. Perella discovered and helped train them in the 1980s. His first hot pick was Bruce Wasserstein. Together, at First Boston and then at Wasserstein Perella, they created a dynasty of bankers and executives that has spread throughout Wall Street and corporate America.</p>
        <p>Every December, the group has a reunion called the Associates' Lunch. Since the death of one of its stars, Gordon Rich -- who had become a co-head of mergers and acquisitions at Credit Suisse and was killed in a car accident in 2000 -- the group has held another annual gathering to raise money for a scholarship in his name.</p>
        <p>Other Wall Street firms have produced their own high-profile diasporas. For example, Lehman Brothers turned out Peter Peterson and Stephen A. Schwarzman of Blackstone; Roger C. Altman of Evercore Partners; and Eric Gleacher of Gleacher Partners, among others.</p>
        <p>But the Wasserstein Perella generation has reached especially far and wide -- and many of them have not finished rising.</p>
        <p>Robert S. Wiesenthal went from providing technical support as a summer intern at First Boston to becoming the chief financial officer of the Sony Corporation of America; Mr. Wasserstein had hired him as a banker after Mr. Wiesenthal fixed his printer. Raymond J. McGuire is now the co-head of global investment banking at Citigroup. Douglas L. Braunstein, who left the firm to work for Chase in the 1990s, became head of the combined investment banking operation after Chase merged with J.P. Morgan.</p>
        <p>Others went into their family businesses. David Simon, the son of Mel Simon, founder of the Simon Property Group, left Wasserstein Perella in 1990 and is now the chief executive of Simon Property. Howard Kerzner, the son of the hotel magnate Sol Kerzner, joined his father's company, Kerzner International, in 1992. He became the company's chief executive but died in a helicopter accident last year.</p>
        <p>Some of Wall Street's most talented women got their start with Mr. Perella and Mr. Wasserstein. Deborah C. Wright, who started as a banking analyst, is now chief executive of Carver Federal Savings Bank, one of the nation's largest African-American financial institutions. Before that, she had been New York City's housing commissioner. Gail Zauder, the first woman promoted to managing director in Credit Suisse's mergers and acquisitions group, founded a boutique investment bank, Elixir Advisors, in 2002.</p>
        <p>There are dozens of other success stories: Michael J. Biondi is co-chairman of investment banking at Lazard; Hugh McGee runs Lehman Brothers' investment bank while Mark G. Shafir runs its mergers practice; Walid A. Chammah is head of investment banking at Morgan Stanley. Daniel M. Dickinson is a managing partner at Thayer Capital Partners; James R. Maher is chief executive of BlackRock Kelso Capital.</p>
        <p>Of course, many remain at Credit Suisse, while others have followed their mentors to Lazard and Perella Weinberg. Some have left corporate life, though. Paul Mercurio, who was an analyst at First Boston, went on to become a comedian; Anne Lutz became a high school English teacher in Connecticut.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
