<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Corzine Is Seen in the Hospital, Counting Up His Blessings</title>
    <meta content="27crash" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/nyregion/27crash.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843206"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E2DF123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="925" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Corzine Is Seen in the Hospital, Counting Up His Blessings</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Corzine Can Be Seen, Counting His Blessings</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID KOCIENIEWSKI and RICHARD G. JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kocieniewski, David; Jones, Richard G</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>His voice still weakened by the serious chest injuries he suffered in a traffic accident two weeks ago, Gov. Jon S. Corzine yesterday made his first public statements since the crash, saying that he felt blessed to have survived.</p>
        <p>''I'm the most blessed person who ever lived,'' Mr. Corzine told a photographer from The Associated Press, who was allowed a five-minute photo session at Cooper University Hospital in Camden. It offered the first glimpse the public has had of the governor since the April 12 crash on the Garden State Parkway.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Jon S. Corzine of New Jersey made his first public statements Thursday since he was injured in a traffic accident two weeks ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>His voice still weakened by the serious chest injuries he suffered in a traffic accident two weeks ago, Gov. Jon S. Corzine yesterday made his first public statements since the crash, saying that he felt blessed to have survived.</p>
        <p>''I'm the most blessed person who ever lived,'' Mr. Corzine told a photographer from The Associated Press, who was allowed a five-minute photo session at Cooper University Hospital in Camden. It offered the first glimpse the public has had of the governor since the April 12 crash on the Garden State Parkway.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine, 60, spent eight days on a ventilator. He broke his thigh bone, sternum, collarbone and 11 ribs and chipped a vertebra, and was removed from intensive care on Monday. He took his first steps with the aid of a walker on Wednesday, and yesterday he was able to sit up in a chair and shake hands with the photographer.</p>
        <p>Wearing a polo shirt and warm-up pants, and with one needle attached to his hand and no visible intravenous lines, Mr. Corzine appeared upbeat, the photographer said.</p>
        <p>The governor declined to be interviewed by an A.P. reporter, and his staff members have repeatedly refused requests by The New York Times and other news organizations to photograph or talk to Mr. Corzine.</p>
        <p>His chief of staff, Tom Shea, said this week that it was unclear when Mr. Corzine would be healthy enough to handle the rigors of a full interview, and doctors said the governor did not appear to recall the accident or his week in intensive care.</p>
        <p>The photo session came on the same day that a self-proclaimed gadfly filed a formal complaint in Municipal Court in Galloway Township, where the accident took place, asking a judge to issue a summons and fine the governor for not wearing a seat belt, as required by New Jersey law. Mr. Corzine was hurled from the front seat to the back when his sport utility vehicle, speeding with emergency lights flashing at 91 miles per hour -- 26 above the limit -- collided with a pickup truck, then slammed into a guardrail.</p>
        <p>The state attorney general and the state police are investigating the accident, but have not yet issued a traffic citation to either Mr. Corzine or the driver of the S.U.V., State Trooper Robert J. Rasinski.</p>
        <p>The gadfly, Larry Angel, a lifeguard from Egg Harbor Township who is known for his long speeches at public meetings, said he filed the complaint because he feared that the governor's image was being tarnished by the perception that he was receiving preferential treatment.</p>
        <p>''I'm a fan of the governor -- I voted for him for senator, for governor and I'd vote for him again today,'' Mr. Angel said in an interview. ''But I don't think it's healthy for society for people to think that someone in power is treated differently than other people. I think if the governor were in his full faculties, wasn't in rehabilitation and on medication, he'd ask for them to write him the ticket and just move on.''</p>
        <p>Under New Jersey law, passengers in the front seat who fail to wear a seat belt can be ticketed and fined $20 ($46 including court costs), and the governor's staff members have said since the days after the crash that Mr. Corzine should be subject to such a fine.</p>
        <p>Roseanne Lugg, the court administrator in Galloway Township, said that any citizen is permitted to file a complaint against anyone, and that a judge will order a hearing if he finds probable cause.</p>
        <p>When traffic accidents cause personal injuries, ticketed drivers or passengers are required to appear at such hearings, Ms. Lugg said, although they can be excused by filing an affidavit explaining why appearing would be a hardship.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine, who is still receiving a substantial amount of pain medication, is expected to remain in the hospital until Monday, and his staff members said he would not seek to return to his official duties at least until then. On Wednesday, Mr. Corzine spoke by phone for the first time with the man who has been acting governor since the crash, Richard J. Codey, the State Senate president.</p>
        <p>''He seemed to be in good spirits,'' Mr. Codey said yesterday afternoon at a news conference in Trenton. ''His voice is not like it was before the accident, but clearly I could hear him loud and clear, there's no question about that. He seemed to be in as good a mood as anyone in that position could possibly be.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Codey said that he expected to visit Mr. Corzine at the hospital in the next couple of days, and that Mr. Corzine did not indicate when he might return to work.</p>
        <p>Mr. Codey said that Mr. Corzine told him, ''Dick, I want to thank you for stepping up and doing what you've done.''</p>
        <p>''He thanked me,'' Mr. Codey said. ''It was a very gracious conversation on both sides.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Codey said the conversation lasted six minutes and that Mr. Corzine was interested in discussing state business.</p>
        <p>''He wanted to talk about the budget,'' Mr. Codey said. ''A pretty good sign that he was getting better. He said, 'I was able to take a couple of steps.' He talked to me about the progress he made from where he was when he was wheeled into the hospital. It was a very upbeat conversation.''</p>
        <p>Asked where he was when he took Mr. Corzine's call, Mr. Codey said, ''I was on the parkway -- with my seat belt on.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
