<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>China Needs An Einstein. So Do We.</title>
    <meta content="27friedman" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/opinion/27friedman.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070505T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843244"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Columnist"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Censorship</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mathematics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Friedman, Thomas L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Einstein, Albert (1879-1955)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Isaacson, Walter</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Einstein: His Life and Universe (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Thomas L Friedman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mathematics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Censorship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Speech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mathematics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Einstein, Albert</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Isaacson, Walter</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E2DE123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>China Needs An Einstein. So Do We.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">China Needs an Einstein. So Do We.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS L. FRIEDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Friedman, Thomas L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thomas Friedman Op-Ed column on Walter Isaacson's new biography of Albert Einstein and relationship between freedom and creativity; draws connection to issue of whether China can become as innovative as America when it maintains tight political controls while establishing market economy; says second question is how US, no matter how free, competes when so many young Chinese are studying math and science and so many Americans are dropping out; quotes Isaacson's view that theme of twentieth century and Einstein's life is about people who fled oppression to be able to think and express themselves; concludes that both US and China have homework to do</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I've been thinking about China as I read Walter Isaacson's new biography of Albert Einstein. China isn't even mentioned in the book -- ''Einstein: His Life and Universe'' -- but Mr. Isaacson's stimulating and provocative retelling of Einstein's career plays into two very hot debates about China.</p>
        <p>First, what does Einstein's life tell us about the relationship between freedom and creativity? Or to put it bluntly: Can China become as innovative as America, can it dominate the 21st century, as many predict, when China censors Google and maintains tight political controls while establishing its market economy?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Albert Einstein’s life is a testimony to the unbreakable link between human freedom and creativity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I've been thinking about China as I read Walter Isaacson's new biography of Albert Einstein. China isn't even mentioned in the book -- ''Einstein: His Life and Universe'' -- but Mr. Isaacson's stimulating and provocative retelling of Einstein's career plays into two very hot debates about China.</p>
        <p>First, what does Einstein's life tell us about the relationship between freedom and creativity? Or to put it bluntly: Can China become as innovative as America, can it dominate the 21st century, as many predict, when China censors Google and maintains tight political controls while establishing its market economy?</p>
        <p>Second, how do we compete with China, no matter how free we are, when so many of China's young people are studying math and science and so many of ours are dropping out? Or to put it more bluntly: If Einstein were alive today and learned science the boring way it is taught in so many U.S. schools, wouldn't he have ended up at a Wall Street hedge fund rather than developing theories of relativity for a Nobel Prize?</p>
        <p>Mr. Isaacson's take on Einstein's life is that it is a testimony to the unbreakable link between human freedom and creativity.</p>
        <p>''The whole theme of the last century, and of Einstein's life,'' Mr. Isaacson said in an interview, ''is about people who fled oppression in order to go places to think and express themselves. Einstein runs away from the rote learning and authoritarianism of Germany as a teenager in the 1890s and goes to Italy and Switzerland. And then he flees Hitler to come to America, where he resists both McCarthyism and Stalinism because he believes that the only way to have creativity and imagination is to nurture free thought -- rebellious free thought.''</p>
        <p>If you look at Einstein's major theories -- special relativity, general relativity and the quantum theory of light -- ''all three come from taking rebellious imaginative leaps that throw out old conventional wisdom,'' Mr. Isaacson said. ''Einstein thought that the freest society with the most rebellious thinking would be the most creative. If we are going to have any advantage over China, it is because we nurture rebellious, imaginative free thinkers, rather than try to control expression.''</p>
        <p>My gut tells me that's right, but my mind tells me not to ignore something Bill Gates said in China the other day: that putting PCs, education and the Internet in the hands of more and more Chinese is making China not only a huge software market, ''but also a contributor to this market. Innovation here is really at a rapid pace.''</p>
        <p>Will China hit a ceiling on innovation because of its political authoritarianism? That's what we need to watch for.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, we should heed another of Mr. Isaacson's insights about Einstein: he found sheer beauty and creative joy in science and equations. If only we could convey that in the way we teach science and math, maybe we could nurture another Einstein -- male or female -- and not have to worry that so many engineers and scientists in our graduate schools are from China that the classes could be taught in Chinese.</p>
        <p>''What Einstein was able to do was to think visually,'' Mr. Isaacson explained. ''When he looked at Maxwell's equations as a 16-year-old boy, he visualized what it would be like to ride alongside a light wave and try to catch up. He realized those equations described something wondrous in reality.</p>
        <p>''By being able to visualize and think imaginatively about science, he was able to see what more academic scientists failed to see, which is that as you try to catch up with a light beam, the waves travel just as fast, but time slows down for you. It was a leap that better-trained scientists could not make because they did not have the visual imagination.''</p>
        <p>If we want our kids to learn science, we can't treat science as this boring or intimidating thing. ''We have to remind our kids  that a math equation or a scientific formula is just a brush stroke the good Lord uses to paint one of the wonders of nature,'' Mr. Isaacson said, ''and we should look at it as being as beautiful as art or literature or music.''</p>
        <p>My favorite Einstein quotation is that ''imagination is more important than knowledge.'' A society that restricts imagination is unlikely to produce many Einsteins -- no matter how many educated people it has. But a society that does not stimulate imagination when it comes to science and math won't either -- no matter how much freedom it has.</p>
        <p>So my sense, from reading Mr. Isaacson's book, is that if Einstein were alive today, he would be telling both America and China that they have homework to do.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Columnist</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 5, 2007, Saturday  From Thomas L. Friedman's column on April 27: Albert Einstein won the Nobel Prize for his ''services to theoretical physics and especially for his discovery of the law of the photoelectric effect,'' not specifically for relativity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 5, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>From Thomas L. Friedman's column on April 27: Albert Einstein won the Nobel Prize for his ''services to theoretical physics and especially for his discovery of the law of the photoelectric effect,'' not specifically for relativity.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
