<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Elias Out Sick, the Devils Have No Remedy</title>
    <meta content="27devils" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/sports/hockey/27devils.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843270"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Ottawa Senators</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Ottawa Senators</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Gomez, Scott</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Elias, Patrik</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E7DD123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="732" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Elias Out Sick, the Devils Have No Remedy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With Elias Out Sick, the Devils Have No Remedy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., April 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The pads in Patrik Elias's dressing room stall were untouched Thursday morning, a freshly laundered pair of red socks draped over the center hook. Elias, the Devils' captain, had gone home, still ailing from the flu.</p>
        <p>The rest of the team, or at least the version of the team that usually sweats the details, was also absent from Thursday night's game. The Ottawa Senators pounced on the Devils, scoring four goals on their first eight shots en route to a 5-4 victory in the opener of their N.H.L. Eastern Conference semifinal series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Ottawa Senators scored four goals on their first eight shots, then held off a New Jersey rally for a victory in the opener of their Eastern Conference semifinal series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The pads in Patrik Elias's dressing room stall were untouched Thursday morning, a freshly laundered pair of red socks draped over the center hook. Elias, the Devils' captain, had gone home, still ailing from the flu.</p>
        <p>The rest of the team, or at least the version of the team that usually sweats the details, was also absent from Thursday night's game. The Ottawa Senators pounced on the Devils, scoring four goals on their first eight shots en route to a 5-4 victory in the opener of their N.H.L. Eastern Conference semifinal series.</p>
        <p>''We certainly didn't expect to put ourselves in that situation, but we did,'' said Lou Lamoriello, the Devils' general manager and interim coach.</p>
        <p>Elias missed practice Tuesday and Wednesday, and Lamoriello scratched him from the lineup Thursday after he did not participate in the morning skate. Lamoriello said that he hoped Elias would return Saturday, when the series resumes here. Games 3 and 4 will be Monday and Wednesday at Ottawa.</p>
        <p>Lamoriello will be hoping that other Devils return to their old form, or it will be a short series. By the 17-minute mark of the first period, the Senators had amassed a 4-0 lead through several errors.</p>
        <p>''We were overconfident, if anything,'' Devils center John Madden said. ''It was not shakiness. We were doing things that were not characteristic of this team.''</p>
        <p>Much to the delight of the crowd of 15,512 -- well below the 19,040 capacity -- the Devils sliced a 4-0 deficit to 4-3 with goals by Travis Zajac, Brian Gionta and Andy Greene in a 5-minute-19-second stretch at the end of the first period and the beginning of the second.</p>
        <p>But with Devils center Erik Rasmussen serving a hooking penalty, Senators defenseman Wade Redden blasted a slap shot past Devils goaltender Martin Brodeur 43 seconds into the third period to make the score 5-3.</p>
        <p>Zach Parise scored with 30 seconds left, but the Devils failed to mount another attack. The Devils were pleased that they nearly hoisted themselves out of a cavern, but they were not so pleased that they fell into a cavern in the first place.</p>
        <p>''When they scored four goals, it was kind of hard to get into a rhythm,'' Brodeur said.</p>
        <p>Brodeur did not have a stellar game, stopping only 21 of 26 shots.</p>
        <p>Ottawa scored 90 seconds into the game, when Jason Spezza tipped in a shot by defenseman Tom Preissing, then another at 6:49, when Joseph Corvo scored an unassisted power-play goal.</p>
        <p>Usually, the Devils are good at buckling down when they fall behind. But they disintegrated, allowing two more goals in less than two minutes later in the period.</p>
        <p>The third Ottawa goal followed a giveaway by Devils defenseman Brian Rafalski.With Ottawa's Mike Comrie serving a hooking penalty, Rafalski shoveled a backhand pass in the Devils' zone. Ottawa left wing Dean McAmmond intercepted the pass, skated past Rafalski and put a wrist shot over Brodeur's left shoulder at 14:43.</p>
        <p>''We just didn't match their intensity,'' Gionta said. ''We didn't play a smart first period.''</p>
        <p>Ottawa right wing Dany Heatley blocked a shot inside the blue line and chased it down near center ice. Spezza joined him for a two on one.</p>
        <p>With Devils defenseman Richard Matvichuk playing both onrushing forwards, Heatley whisked a shot past Brodeur at 16:49.</p>
        <p>Zajac scored his first goal of the playoffs 59 seconds later, but the Devils were booed at the end of the period.</p>
        <p>''It's pretty tough to come back against Ottawa, but we gave it our best,'' Devils center Scott Gomez said.</p>
        <p>Asked if he considered pulling Brodeur after the first period, Lamoriello replied, ''Never even gave it a thought.''</p>
        <p>Later Lamoriello said: ''Even though we were down three goals, it wasn't a lopsided territorial situation. It was just bang-bang.''</p>
        <p>And, bang-bang, the Devils were back in it. Gionta, rolling down the right wing, beat goalie Ray Emery with a slap shot at 2:20 of the second period.</p>
        <p>Two minutes later, Parise intercepted a pass at the Ottawa blue line and raced into the Senators' zone. He passed to Jamie Langenbrunner, who could not get his stick on the puck before it was slapped out. Andy Greene, the rookie defenseman, stopped it and fired a long slapshot at Emery. It sped through traffic and scooted past Emery at 4:57.</p>
        <p>But the Devils did not score again until it was too late.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
