<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Family's Beloved Home, Now a Page in a Crime Story</title>
    <meta content="27house" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/nyregion/27house.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843233"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Catskills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Catskills (NYS Area)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E4DE123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="757" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Family's Beloved Home, Now a Page in a Crime Story</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Family’s Beloved Home, Now a Page in a Crime Story</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA W. FODERARO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Foderaro, Lisa W</byline>
      <dateline>MARGARETVILLE, N.Y., April 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Robert A. Chamberlain stood in a cold drizzle some 200 yards from his family's weekend house in the shadow of the Catskill Mountains as members of an elite state police unit were preparing to storm it.</p>
        <p>They were looking Wednesday afternoon for Travis D. Trim, a fugitive and petty criminal who they believed had shot three state troopers over the previous 24 hours, killing one, and who they suspected was holed up inside. But moments before the siege was to begin, a final round of tear gas was hurled into the cream-colored farmhouse, which suddenly caught fire.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>MARGARETVILLE, N.Y., April 26  Robert A. Chamberlain stood in a cold drizzle some 200 yards from his family’s weekend house in the shadow of the Catskill Mountains as members of an elite state police unit were preparing to storm it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Robert A. Chamberlain stood in a cold drizzle some 200 yards from his family's weekend house in the shadow of the Catskill Mountains as members of an elite state police unit were preparing to storm it.</p>
        <p>They were looking Wednesday afternoon for Travis D. Trim, a fugitive and petty criminal who they believed had shot three state troopers over the previous 24 hours, killing one, and who they suspected was holed up inside. But moments before the siege was to begin, a final round of tear gas was hurled into the cream-colored farmhouse, which suddenly caught fire.</p>
        <p>''Sheer horror,'' was how Mr. Chamberlain, 36, a police sergeant in Tenafly, N.J., described watching the house go up in flames. ''It was surreal,'' he said Thursday in a telephone interview. ''You can't put it into words.''</p>
        <p>The rambling house, which has been in Mr. Chamberlain's family for 25 years, sits on 38 acres at the corner of Cemetery Road and Route 30 in the town of Middletown, just outside the village of Margaretville. A stream tumbles over rocks along one side of the property, and there are expansive views of the Catskills, whose forested slopes are just showing a hint of spring green.</p>
        <p>When the fire had engulfed about two-thirds of the house, sending up a towering column of smoke visible for miles around, Mr. Chamberlain said he could no longer stand to watch. ''We decided we couldn't take it anymore,'' he said, ''and we went to the Margaretville Fire Department, and they fed us.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Chamberlain's mother, Carole Chamberlain-Berman of Bergenfield, N.J., owns the house along with her brother, Robert Ackerman. Ms. Chamberlain-Berman, who bought the house with her husband in 1982, was too distraught on Thursday to talk about the fire.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chamberlain, who lives in Cresskill, N.J., had driven up earlier on Wednesday, accompanied by two relatives, to provide the New York State Police with a detailed diagram of the house. The authorities had surrounded the house for hours after a morning shootout there between Mr. Trim, 23, and two state troopers, one of whom, David C. Brinkerhoff, was shot in the head and died shortly after. A second, Richard G. Mattson, was shot in the arm.</p>
        <p>The police said that Mr. Trim fired at another trooper on Tuesday afternoon in Margaretville after being pulled over for a missing license plate. The van he was driving turned out to be stolen, but the trooper, who was saved by a bulletproof vest, did not know that.</p>
        <p>After shooting the officer, the police said, Mr. Trim drove off, crashing the van not far from the farmhouse. He apparently sneaked into the empty house, at 1245 Cemetery Road, as a manhunt got under way, the police said. A tripped burglar alarm drew troopers to the house on Wednesday morning.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Chamberlain, the events elicited conflicting emotions.</p>
        <p>''It really came down to officer safety,'' he said. ''I don't fault the New York State Police. They used tear gas to protect everyone involved and to gain a tactical advantage. We're more saddened by the loss of the state trooper and the trooper who was injured than we are by the loss of the house, which is just material.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Chamberlain also said that his family was ''traumatized'' by the loss of the eight-bedroom clapboard house, which dated to World War I and was used as a year-round base camp for skiing, hunting and fishing by three generations. ''We just love the outdoors,'' he said.</p>
        <p>His stepfather, Carl Berman, who traveled with him from New Jersey on Wednesday, said, ''We definitely want to rebuild.'' The family planned to meet with their insurer on Friday, he said.</p>
        <p>The police are still investigating the cause of the fire. Preston L. Felton, the acting superintendent of the state police, said it would be days before investigators could determine whether the last canister of tear gas had somehow set off the blaze or whether Mr. Trim might have started it. (Mr. Trim's charred body was found crouched in a doorway on the second floor Thursday night, a rifle in his arms.)</p>
        <p>On Thursday, investigators inspected the house's blackened shell, where, absent a roof, two chimneys poked precariously into the sky. Yellow police tape stretched across the driveway, and passing drivers slowed for a closer look.</p>
        <p>''We put our blood, sweat and tears into that place,'' said Mr. Chamberlain, recalling a series of home improvement projects. ''We had a lot of nice pictures that were irreplaceable. Just a lot of memories.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
