<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bryant's 45 Help Lakers Cut Into Suns' Lead</title>
    <meta content="27nba" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843313"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL: ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Lakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Phoenix Suns</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E1DD123EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="884" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bryant's 45 Help Lakers Cut Into Suns' Lead</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, April 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kobe Bryant was serenaded with chants of ''M.V.P.,'' a sea of gold shirts bounced late into the evening Thursday at Staples Center, and the Los Angeles Lakers looked very much alive.</p>
        <p>Bryant scored 45 points in 45 minutes, and the Lakers restored a measure of belief in their anxious fan base with a 95-89 victory over the Phoenix Suns. The Suns lead the best-of-seven series, 2-1, with Game 4 here Sunday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Kobe Bryant was serenaded with chants of ''M.V.P.,'' a sea of gold shirts bounced late into the evening Thursday at Staples Center, and the Los Angeles Lakers looked very much alive.</p>
        <p>Bryant scored 45 points in 45 minutes, and the Lakers restored a measure of belief in their anxious fan base with a 95-89 victory over the Phoenix Suns. The Suns lead the best-of-seven series, 2-1, with Game 4 here Sunday.</p>
        <p>Phoenix led by as many as 17 points in the first half, but the Lakers dominated the second half and never trailed in the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>Amare Stoudemire led the Suns with 24 points and 10 rebounds. Leandro Barbosa, whose scoring bursts anchored the Suns' two victories, had a quiet 20 points off the bench.</p>
        <p>Kwame Brown scored a career playoff-high 19 points for the Lakers. Lamar Odom added 18 points as the Lakers used their size advantage for the first time in this first-round series.</p>
        <p>The stakes for the Lakers were obvious, and daunting. No N.B.A. team has come back to win a series after trailing by 3-0. Only 11 teams, out of 193, have come back from a 2-0 deficit to win a seven-game series.</p>
        <p>For the Suns, who have their eyes on June, the mission was simple: get the series over with as quickly as possible.</p>
        <p>''Our goals are pretty lofty this year,'' Phoenix Coach Mike D'Antoni said before the game, ''so when you have an opportunity to take an advantage like we have, you just can't squander it.''</p>
        <p>In the wake of a 28-point rout in Game 2, Lakers Coach Phil Jackson called his team depressed and humiliated. Odom openly questioned the Lakers' camaraderie, and Bryant questioned just about everything else.</p>
        <p>Addressing his team's potentially fragile psyche before tip-off, Jackson said: ''We basically had an A.A. meeting yesterday. We did some crying, we did some whining, and then we did some recognition of our own responsibilities.''</p>
        <p>Jackson said his players' mood was much better Thursday, but the Lakers opened the game still looking depressed. The Suns raced to an 11-0 lead in the first two and a half minutes, and an antsy crowd booed during the first timeout. The mood, and the Lakers' play, improved from there.</p>
        <p>The Laker Girls gave Jack Nicholson a birthday cake, and the Lakers gave him a spirit-lifting rally. Bryant scored 11 points in the second quarter, the Suns sputtered and the Lakers pulled within 3 points by halftime.</p>
        <p>The Lakers tied the score for the first time, at 53-53, on Luke Walton's 3-pointer early in the third quarter. Bryant gave them their first lead, 56-55, with 7 minutes 18 seconds left in the period, and the Lakers kept the momentum, taking an 83-75 lead early in the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>PISTONS 93, MAGIC 77 -- Tayshaun Prince scored 23 points, Chauncey Billups added 21 and visiting Detroit took a 3-0 lead in the first-round Eastern Conference playoff series.</p>
        <p>The victory ended a postseason trend for the Pistons -- they had lost their previous six Game 3s when leading by 2-0 -- and left them one win from advancing to the second round.</p>
        <p>Game 4 is Saturday in Orlando, Fla.</p>
        <p>Detroit gave the Magic plenty of chances. The Pistons trailed early, let Orlando be physical and looked flustered as they were whistled for three technical fouls. Richard Hamilton, Detroit's leading scorer, even had an off night, scoring 10 points on 2-for-11 shooting.</p>
        <p>But the Pistons made up for it with solid outside shooting from Prince, Billups and Rasheed Wallace. (AP)</p>
        <p>JAZZ 81, ROCKETS 67 -- Carlos Boozer had 22 points and 12 rebounds, and host Utah held Houston without a field goal for 10 minutes in the second half in Game 3 of their playoff series. Houston leads the series, 2-1, with Game 4 Saturday night.</p>
        <p>Yao Ming had 26 points and 14 rebounds and Tracy McGrady scored 24 points for Houston. The Rockets won the first two games of the series at home but were sloppy on the road during the first playoff game in Utah since 2003. Houston had 19 turnovers to Utah's 11 and was just 21 for 64 from the floor (32.8 percent). (AP)</p>
        <p>WARRIORS COACH FINES PLAYERS -- Warriors Coach Don Nelson said yesterday that he would fine Baron Davis and Stephen Jackson for being ejected from Golden State's 112-99 loss in Game 2 of the team's first-round playoff series against the Dallas Mavericks.</p>
        <p>Davis and Jackson put on a taunting, preening display that dampened an otherwise successful trip for the eighth-seeded Warriors, who stole Game 1 from the heavily favored Mavericks and headed back to the West Coast with home-court advantage in the series, starting with Game 3 Saturday.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't make any sense to me, as hard as we worked to get to the playoffs, to all of a sudden get there and not be able to play because of ejections and not controlling our emotions,'' Nelson said before a brief workout at the Warriors' training complex.</p>
        <p>The N.B.A. has not announced any potential discipline against Davis, who apparently was thrown out for sarcastically applauding the officials late in the third quarter, or Jackson, who left the court in a contentious, roundabout manner after getting his second technical foul in the final minutes. (AP)</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL: ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
