<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Corp. And Partners Take MySpace To the Chinese</title>
    <meta content="27myspace" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/business/worldbusiness/27myspace.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843190"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
        <org class="online_producer">MySpace.com</org>
        <org class="online_producer">News Corporation Limited</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEFD6153EF934A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="700" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Corp. And Partners Take MySpace To the Chinese</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Murdoch Is Taking MySpace to China</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BARBOZA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barboza, David</byline>
      <dateline>SHANGHAI, April 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rupert Murdoch's News Corporation is bringing MySpace.com to China, a latecomer that is betting it can overcome that handicap by competing unconventionally as a start-up.</p>
        <p>The News Corporation signed a deal to license the brand for its popular online social networking site and allow local Chinese entrepreneurs who understand their market to pick and choose to build an indigenous business. Using this approach, the News Corporation hopes to succeed where other Western Internet ventures have failed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The News Corporation signed a deal to license the brand in the world’s fastest-growing Internet market.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rupert Murdoch's News Corporation is bringing MySpace.com to China, a latecomer that is betting it can overcome that handicap by competing unconventionally as a start-up.</p>
        <p>The News Corporation signed a deal to license the brand for its popular online social networking site and allow local Chinese entrepreneurs who understand their market to pick and choose to build an indigenous business. Using this approach, the News Corporation hopes to succeed where other Western Internet ventures have failed.</p>
        <p>The company and two venture capital firms agreed this month to hire a former Microsoft executive to license the MySpace.com brand and technology in China in an attempt to capture some of the business in the world's fastest-growing Internet market.</p>
        <p>MySpace.com is entering China at a time when social networking sites, online games and entertainment sites are already wildly popular.</p>
        <p>''They want to avoid some of the mistakes made by the first and second waves of international Internet companies that came to China,'' said William Bao Bean, a partner at Softbank China &amp; India, a venture capital firm. ''By putting a local manager in, they give the company a fighting chance. This is a very crowded area, with at least 100 companies competing in the same space that MySpace has entered.''</p>
        <p>American Internet companies have scrambled to set up operations in China's booming online marketplace, which already has more than 137 million Internet users, second only to the United States.</p>
        <p>But the China operations of Amazon.com, eBay, Yahoo and even Google have all either lost ground or ceded the role of market leader to local rivals despite sometimes spending hundreds of millions of dollars to acquire established Chinese competitors.</p>
        <p>The new company, called MySpace China, will tailor the site to the Chinese market. For instance, while MySpace.com invites newcomers to meet their first friend, Tom Anderson, who is a company founder, MySpace China introduces new visitors to a Chinese friend.</p>
        <p>Still, it faces stiff competition from China's home-grown Internet companies, including Baidu, Tencent, Sina and 51.com, as well as dozens of other MySpace.com-like Internet start-ups.</p>
        <p>Analysts say that Chinese Internet entrepreneurs like Robin Li of Baidu, Ma Huateng of Tencent and Jack Ma of Alibaba.com, have managed to outmaneuver their Western counterparts, partly because they have a better sense of the needs of Chinese Internet users.</p>
        <p>Foreign Internet companies have also struggled to find the right balance of complying with China's stringent censorship -- their sites are sometimes blocked in China -- yet providing enough interesting content to attract users.</p>
        <p>Mr. Murdoch has tried to gain access to the Chinese market for some of his media properties, but has faced difficulties because of tight controls. Now the News Corporation, which acquired MySpace in 2005 for about $580 million, has teamed up with IDG VC, a unit of the Boston-based International Data Group, and China Broadband Capital Partners. In effect, they are financing a Chinese start-up.</p>
        <p>Richard Ji, an Internet analyst at Morgan Stanley, said MySpace China might use the News Corporation's content. ''They have a competitive advantage in sports content,'' Mr. Ji said. ''The Chinese government likes sports content, and so do advertisers'' in China.</p>
        <p>The group, headed by the News Corporation, did not say how much it has committed to invest in MySpace China, but people close to the talks say that the financing is substantial. The strategy and partnership were partly devised with the help of Wendi Deng, Mr. Murdoch's Chinese-born wife, according to people involved in the deal. Ms. Deng is not an officer of the News Corporation, but she has been named to the board of MySpace China, according to people involved in the talks.</p>
        <p>According to the deal, the News Corporation, IDG and China Broadband Capital will largely finance the operations. IDG, which is headed in China by Hugo Shong, has more than $800 million under management and has invested in some of China's biggest Internet start-ups, including Baidu, Tencent, 3721.com and Eachnet.</p>
        <p>Luo Chuan, 38, who used to run Microsoft's MSN portal in China, will be the company's chief executive. ''We want to create a site that allows people to find serious relationships and to share something with new friends,'' he said, ''to share pain and loneliness.''</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
