<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Into the Shadowy World Of Sex With Animals</title>
    <meta content="25zoo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/movies/25zoo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842736"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dargis, Manohla</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Devor, Robinson</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Zoo (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sundance Film Festival (Park City, Utah)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sundance Film Festival (Park City, Utah)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sundance Film Festival (Park City, Utah)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Devor, Robinson</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Zoo (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E7DB143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1171" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Into the Shadowy World Of Sex With Animals</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Into the Shadowy World of Sex With Animals</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MANOHLA DARGIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dargis, Manohla</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Manohla Dargis reviews Robinson Devor documentary film Zoo; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The director Robinson Devor apparently would like viewers who watch his heavily reconstructed documentary, ''Zoo,'' to see it as a story of ineluctable desire and human dignity. Shot on Super 16-millimeter film, with many scenes steeped in a blue that would have made Yves Klein envious, ''Zoo'' is, to a large extent, about the rhetorical uses of beauty and metaphor and of certain filmmaking techniques like slow-motion photography. It is, rather more coyly, also about a man who died from a perforated colon after he arranged to have sex with a stallion.</p>
        <p>Mercifully, you don't see this death on camera, though if you sit close enough to the screen, you will see a few fairly brief images of one sexual event, accompanied by graphic sounds. It isn't pretty, which is why the images appear only on a small television monitor. Art-house devotees may be a tolerant lot, but it's doubtful they want to look at a stallion's erect penis stretched across the big screen like a sailboat boom, at least in public. Certainly such an image would work directly counter to the self-conscious poeticism of Mr. Devor's film, to its carefully confected narrative of misunderstood barnyard love and baleful testimonial. It is, after all, difficult to sing of the bodies electric and equine amid a chorus of ''yucks.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“Zoo” is, to a large extent, about the rhetorical uses of beauty. It is, rather more coyly, also about a man who died after having sex with a stallion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The director Robinson Devor apparently would like viewers who watch his heavily reconstructed documentary, ''Zoo,'' to see it as a story of ineluctable desire and human dignity. Shot on Super 16-millimeter film, with many scenes steeped in a blue that would have made Yves Klein envious, ''Zoo'' is, to a large extent, about the rhetorical uses of beauty and metaphor and of certain filmmaking techniques like slow-motion photography. It is, rather more coyly, also about a man who died from a perforated colon after he arranged to have sex with a stallion.</p>
        <p>Mercifully, you don't see this death on camera, though if you sit close enough to the screen, you will see a few fairly brief images of one sexual event, accompanied by graphic sounds. It isn't pretty, which is why the images appear only on a small television monitor. Art-house devotees may be a tolerant lot, but it's doubtful they want to look at a stallion's erect penis stretched across the big screen like a sailboat boom, at least in public. Certainly such an image would work directly counter to the self-conscious poeticism of Mr. Devor's film, to its carefully confected narrative of misunderstood barnyard love and baleful testimonial. It is, after all, difficult to sing of the bodies electric and equine amid a chorus of ''yucks.''</p>
        <p>It is, however, very easy to hide behind aestheticized imagery, as ''Zoo'' soon proves. Much has been made of the film's look, and it's easy to see why. The cinematographer, Sean Kirby, who also shot Mr. Devor's ''Police Beat,'' a fiction film about a lovelorn Seattle bicycle cop, has done some striking work here. The prowling camera and dusky colors give much of ''Zoo,'' which opens with the portentous image of what appear to be miners emerging from a tunnel, a sumptuous, almost velvety look and vibe, an effect enhanced by the repeated use of slow-motion photography. Characters don't just walk in this film; they float across the frame, pouring like liquid toward their inexorable destinies.</p>
        <p>Written by Mr. Devor and Charles Mudede, ''Zoo'' is nothing if not artful. Even before its premiere at the Sundance Film Festival in January, it had attracted a fair amount of attention that quickly morphed into a reassuringly familiar drone. Documentaries, particularly the kind shown at festivals like Sundance, tend to reaffirm the audience's worldview, partly by appealing to its presumptive tolerance and partly by underscoring the artistry of the endeavor (the vision thing). Like many such documentaries, ''Zoo'' wraps its sensationalistic core in a seductive mantle, an approach that appeals to viewers already predisposed to art and the Enlightenment, ''Sesame Street'' and all things not Rush Limbaugh. These are films as documents of reason (yours, mine, the creators'), the cinema of indoor voices.</p>
        <p>In ''Zoo,'' three of those voices belong to men who, along with a group of unnamed, unnumbered other men, regularly met at a farm near the small city of Enumclaw, about 45 minutes southeast of Seattle, to party with one another and animals, occasionally recording their activities on video. Some of the men are identified only by their Internet handles (they met online), like the dead man, ''Mr. Hands.'' What Mr. Devor doesn't explain until right before the end credits is that almost everyone who appears in his film, including most of the men who call themselves ''zoos'' -- for zoophile or lover of animals -- are played by actors. Structured like a mystery that taps many of the usual suspense beats, the story unwinds through dramatic reconstructions that show what happened, if not really why.</p>
        <p>Reconstructions are old hat in documentary, employed by reality-minded, dramatically inclined filmmakers from Robert J. Flaherty to Errol Morris and of little aesthetic note or interest here. Far more interesting is Mr. Devor's decision not to name the dead man, identified in news reports and even the film's production material as Kenneth Pinyan, a divorced Boeing employee. This refusal to give the dead man a name, as well as the penumbral lighting, go a long way toward keeping Mr. Pinyan and the rest of his adopted community in the shadows from which Mr. Devor otherwise seems eager to retrieve them. Given that Mr. Mudede identified Mr. Pinyan in a February 2006 column he wrote for the Seattle newsweekly The Stranger, this silence seems, at best, poorly considered.</p>
        <p>It's hard to know what Mr. Devor is after, though a clue materializes during the only on-camera interview. Late in ''Zoo,'' the actor Michael Minard suddenly pops up on a blindingly white set, talking about how he was hired to play a cop in the film. On a banal level, his recollection about landing the role underscores that each of us -- actor and zoophile and doubtless filmmaker alike -- plays a role. But his performance here also appears to be a veiled statement of purpose. ''A man bled to death,'' Mr. Minard reminds us between clichés (''it hits close to home'') and memories of a young boy who died in his arms after a drowning accident. Looking into the dying child's eyes, the actor says, he saw his own reflection.</p>
        <p>Reality is in the eye of the beholder, and so too, Mr. Devor would seem to have us believe, are death and deviance. Not that he labels man-horse sex deviant or comic or icky or anything much at all. Instead of taking on the serious moral and political objections to bestiality, including those in Leviticus (thou shalt so not) and by animal-rights proponents who reject the instrumental use of animals, he offers haters shrieking on the radio and other opportunists. Yet, paradoxically, it is precisely because Mr. Devor refuses to acknowledge the murkiness that clings to every frame in his film, because he refuses to engage with the world beyond that of the zoophiles, that they seem like creatures from some never-ending night.</p>
        <p>That's too bad. After all, Bible-believers notwithstanding, if you eat and wear animals and agree that it's O.K. to torture them in the name of science and beauty, what's the big deal? Human beings subject animals penned in factory farms to far more grievous abuse than anything apparently done to the horses in ''Zoo,'' and on a daily basis human beings also subject themselves to greater risk. One zoophile's fond memories of cooking up ham for his brethren indicate that theirs was not a PETA-approved animal love, true. But, as Mr. Devor makes clear, again and again, these were men who truly loved their animals in sickness and in health and, at least in the case of one unfortunate soul, till death finally did part them.</p>
        <p>Zoo  Opens today in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Directed by Robinson Devor; written by Charles Mudede and Mr. Devor; director of photography, Sean Kirby; edited by Joe Shapiro; music by Paul Matthew Moore; production designer, Jeanne Cavenaugh; produced by Peggy Case and Alexis Ferris; released by ThinkFilm. At the IFC Center, 323 Avenue of the Americas, at Third Street, Greenwich Village. Running time: 76 minutes. This film is not rated.</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
