<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Police Chief and Wife Accused Of Bilking a Volunteer Group</title>
    <meta content="25madd" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/nyregion/25madd.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842756"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embezzlement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Mothers Against Drunk Driving</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6DA143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="492" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Police Chief and Wife Accused Of Bilking a Volunteer Group</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Police Chief and Wife Accused of Bilking a Volunteer Group</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS; Nate Schweber contributed reporting from Clayton, N.J.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smothers, Ronald; Schweber, Nate</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, April 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With 24 years on the job as chief of police in Clayton, N.J., Norman Frank Winters was already the stuff of local legend with his work promoting drug education and planning alcohol-free after-prom and after-graduation events for schools.</p>
        <p>Mr. Winters further burnished his image last year when he ordered police cars onto the train tracks near a local elementary school in a daring bid to force the freight line to reschedule trains so they were not passing when school let out.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>TRENTON, April 24  With 24 years on the job as chief of police in Clayton, N.J., Norman Frank Winters was already the stuff of local legend with his work promoting drug education and planning alcohol-free after-prom and after-graduation events for schools.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With 24 years on the job as chief of police in Clayton, N.J., Norman Frank Winters was already the stuff of local legend with his work promoting drug education and planning alcohol-free after-prom and after-graduation events for schools.</p>
        <p>Mr. Winters further burnished his image last year when he ordered police cars onto the train tracks near a local elementary school in a daring bid to force the freight line to reschedule trains so they were not passing when school let out.</p>
        <p>But on Tuesday that image may have been tarnished, as Mr. Winters and his wife, Bernice, were accused of bilking Mothers Against Drunk Driving of $150,000 in the three years when one or the other headed the state's volunteer chapter.</p>
        <p>The state attorney general, Stuart Rabner, said the Winterses had directed MADD to contract to purchase promotional items like key chains, pens and mugs from two companies they owned, Holiday House and Lasting Impact, in a scheme he called ''shocking on a number of levels.''</p>
        <p>The trinkets were never delivered, but the payments for them were authorized by the Winterses and mailed out, according to a criminal complaint filed against the couple after a yearlong investigation.</p>
        <p>While the charges are pending, the Gloucester County prosecutor will lead the 15-officer Police Department in Clayton, population 7,100.</p>
        <p>In a special meeting on Tuesday evening, the Borough Council of Clayton voted to suspend Chief Winters without pay indefinitely.</p>
        <p>The couple, who remain free, are to appear in municipal court May 1 on charges of conspiracy and theft by deception, which carry a maximum penalty of 10 years in prison.</p>
        <p>Clayton's police chief since 1983, Mr. Winters, 60, was recently elected to the Town Council in nearby Newfield, where the couple live. In 2005 he ran as a Republican for the State Assembly, but he lost.</p>
        <p>It was during that campaign that some in Clayton first learned of Mr. Winters's operation of Holiday House, the promotional trinket wholesaler, out of his home. The local newspaper reported that the company had sold items to the borough and to the Police Department and that Mr. Winters had not disclosed his ownership to the town or on campaign reporting forms.</p>
        <p>John Mitchell, a former mayor and a longtime friend of Mr. Winters, was shocked when told about the charges. ''He is highly thought of here,'' he said. ''Maybe not as a god, because politics is no lovefest here. But he was the right fit for this community.''</p>
        <p>Teresa Stevens, the executive director of the New Jersey chapter of MADD, said the Winterses became involved in the group 20 years ago after Bernice Winters was seriously injured in an accident with a drunken driver.</p>
        <p>''She became a victim advocate for us,'' Ms. Stevens said, adding that because of the trauma of the accident, she had not driven a car since. ''They were well regarded and respected in the organization.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
