<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judge in Sex Attack Trial Excludes Writer's Statements to Detective</title>
    <meta content="25fake" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/nyregion/25fake.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842753"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Braunstein, Peter</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E6DA143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="687" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judge in Sex Attack Trial Excludes Writer's Statements to Detective</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Judge in Sex Attack Trial Excludes Writer’s Statements to Detective</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANEMONA HARTOCOLLIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hartocollis, Anemona</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Manhattan judge ruled yesterday that three days of statements made by Peter Braunstein, a fashion writer accused of sexually molesting a former colleague at a fashion publication, should be excluded from his criminal trial.</p>
        <p>In those statements, made to a New York City police detective, Mr. Braunstein detailed how he had survived on the run, called his estranged father a ''media whore'' for talking to reporters, asked if the victim had a book contract and made other provocative comments.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Manhattan judge ruled yesterday that three days of statements made by Peter Braunstein, a fashion writer accused of sexually molesting a former colleague at a fashion publication, should be excluded from his criminal trial.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Manhattan judge ruled yesterday that three days of statements made by Peter Braunstein, a fashion writer accused of sexually molesting a former colleague at a fashion publication, should be excluded from his criminal trial.</p>
        <p>In those statements, made to a New York City police detective, Mr. Braunstein detailed how he had survived on the run, called his estranged father a ''media whore'' for talking to reporters, asked if the victim had a book contract and made other provocative comments.</p>
        <p>The statements became the basis for much of what the public knew about Mr. Braunstein in the days after his arrest in Memphis in December 2005. They became the grist for days of headlines in the tabloid papers, which branded Mr. Braunstein as ''Pervy Pete,'' and ''Halloween Sicko,'' because the attack on the former fashion editor occurred on Halloween in 2005.</p>
        <p>The statements also led Mr. Braunstein's lawyer, Robert Gottlieb, to ask a previous judge in January 2006 to prohibit the Manhattan district attorney's office and law enforcement officials from speaking to the news media.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's decision from Justice Thomas Farber came shortly before jury selection got under way in Mr. Braunstein's trial in State Supreme Court in Manhattan. The justice ruled that the detective, Josh Ulan, had cajoled the statements out of Mr. Braunstein over three days, even while on an airplane traveling from Memphis to New York, in violation of Mr. Braunstein's constitutional Miranda rights to have a lawyer present during police questioning.</p>
        <p>Justice Farber observed wryly that Mr. Braunstein's rambling, disjointed narrative -- as transcribed later from memory by Detective Ulan -- appeared to be ''the longest non-Mirandized statement in the history of criminal law.''</p>
        <p>But, in a blow to the defense, the judge declined to suppress Mr. Braunstein's diaries, which he was carrying in a backpack when he was arrested. The judge said that the police search of the backpack was legal and that the diaries might shed light on Mr. Braunstein's mental condition.</p>
        <p>Evidence about his mental condition is important, because the defense concedes that Mr. Braunstein is the person who carried out the attacks, in which prosecutors say he disguised himself as a firefighter to gain access to the former editor's Chelsea apartment, then sexually abused her for 13 hours.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gottlieb says that Mr. Braunstein has an organic brain disorder, visible on brain scans, that affected his behavior. The defense says that in legal terms this disorder prevented him from forming the intent necessary to commit a crime.</p>
        <p>The prosecution is arguing that the diaries show that Mr. Braunstein was able to rationally plan and carry out his acts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Braunstein is charged with kidnapping, arson, robbery, burglary, sexual abuse and assault charges. In an indication of how widely the case has been reported in the news media, only 30 jurors remained seated after the judge told the first 100 prospective jurors that they could leave if they had read about the case and believed that they could not be fair.</p>
        <p>In a detail that has amused lawyers in the case, Justice Farber has a connection to the fashion industry through his wife, Dana Buchman, a fashion designer. Not surprisingly, Justice Farber is one of the snappier dressers on the bench, and attracted admiring comments from spectators for a lime-green tie he wore under his robes this week.</p>
        <p>Still, Justice Farber seemed more articulate on the subject of Miranda rights than fashion trends, as he stumbled over the phrase ''Manolo Blahniks'' yesterday while alluding to the contents of Mr. Braunstein's diaries.</p>
        <p>Justice Farber ruled after listening to Detective Ulan testify during pretrial hearings that he thought he was simply making ''idle conversation'' with Mr. Braunstein, not conducting a police interrogation.</p>
        <p>The judge noted that Mr. Braunstein began by saying, ''I really don't think I should talk to you. I want to do the whole lawyer thing,'' which the detective duly noted.</p>
        <p>That sounded a lot like a request for a lawyer, the judge said, adding that since the detective did not proceed to read Mr. Braunstein his Miranda rights, it might never be possible to know for sure.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
