<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Staten Island Considers New Plans To Keep Its Youth From Leaving</title>
    <meta content="25staten" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/nyregion/25staten.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842830"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Staten Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ferries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ferries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Staten Island (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED9143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="734" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Staten Island Considers New Plans To Keep Its Youth From Leaving</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Staten Island Considers New Plans to Keep Its Youth From Leaving</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK McGEEHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgeehan, Patrick</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To reverse the flow of younger people leaving Staten Island, the borough should entice developers to build more affordable apartments close to the ferry, according to a study released yesterday.</p>
        <p>The St. George neighborhood near the ferry to Manhattan is the closest thing to a downtown district in the borough, but it lacks the vibrancy of other sections of New York City that have become havens for young professionals and artists, said Jonathan Bowles, who wrote the study for the Center for an Urban Future, a public policy group.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A study suggests that in order to reverse the flow of younger people leaving Staten Island, the borough should entice developers to build more affordable apartments close to the ferry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To reverse the flow of younger people leaving Staten Island, the borough should entice developers to build more affordable apartments close to the ferry, according to a study released yesterday.</p>
        <p>The St. George neighborhood near the ferry to Manhattan is the closest thing to a downtown district in the borough, but it lacks the vibrancy of other sections of New York City that have become havens for young professionals and artists, said Jonathan Bowles, who wrote the study for the Center for an Urban Future, a public policy group.</p>
        <p>What is needed, the study said, is an immediate change in zoning rules, which have prevented more dense developments near the waterfront.</p>
        <p>''If Staten Island is going to hang on to its young people and attract young professionals from elsewhere, it's going to have to have a dynamic neighborhood with new amenities,'' said Mr. Bowles, who presented the center's findings at a conference of the Staten Island Economic Development Corporation, which commissioned the study. ''In a lot of ways, Staten Island is doing very well right now, but under the hood there are a number of mounting problems.''</p>
        <p>Staten Island is the city's fastest-growing borough. That growth has produced new woes, Mr. Bowles said, like rapidly rising housing prices, congested roads and a shortage of high-paying jobs. The lack of a comprehensive plan to solve those problems is very likely to continue driving younger people away, he said.</p>
        <p>In the 1990s, the borough's population increased by 17 percent to about 450,000, but the number of residents ages 18 to 34 decreased by 5 percent, according to the study. That shift reduced the share of residents ages 18 to 34 to fewer than 23 percent from about 28 percent. Many of those who left moved to New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Even opponents of rapid development of the borough support revitalizing the St. George area. John V. Luisi, a lawyer who lives in the neighborhood and waged an unsuccessful campaign for borough president in 2005, said developers should be encouraged to build more apartments and stores within a short walk of the ferry terminal, the island's transit hub.</p>
        <p>''There's a general consensus that we'd like to achieve a critical mass of people in the area and attract appropriate retailing, such as a supermarket,'' Mr. Luisi said, citing the Red Hook section of Brooklyn, with its large Fairway store, as a model.</p>
        <p>But developers have been stymied by recent zoning changes that were aimed at curbing sprawl in other parts of Staten Island, which have been filled with tightly packed complexes of town houses, business leaders said.</p>
        <p>''The borough's basically been turned into a borough for more expensive one- and two-family detached homes,'' said R. Randy Lee, a builder and the chairman of the economic development corporation.</p>
        <p>From 2000 to 2006, the median price of a single-family home on the island doubled to $425,000, according to the study.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lee is leading the push for the borough to draft a comprehensive master plan that would direct future growth to appropriate areas. A master plan is one of the recommendations in the center's study and Staten Island's members of the City Council plan to call for each borough to have its own master plan.</p>
        <p>But that idea does not have the support of Daniel L. Doctoroff, a deputy mayor, who appeared at the conference to promote Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg's broad vision for the city.</p>
        <p>''We've done a lot of the master-planning for Staten Island,'' Mr. Doctoroff said. ''We're doing it in chunks. We don't think we need one comprehensive plan. What we have found is the one big plan typically will die of its own weight.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Doctoroff said that City Hall would help in looking for ways to solve Staten Island's traffic and transit problems. The borough has the longest average commuting times in the metropolitan region, with some residents -- many of whom work in Manhattan -- spending three hours a day getting to and from their jobs.</p>
        <p>Earlier in the day, Christine C. Quinn, the Council speaker, announced at the conference that the city would pay $350,000 for the study of a light-rail system that would run along the island's West Shore and across the Bayonne Bridge to connect to New Jersey Transit's tracks in Hudson County.</p>
        <p>''It's definitely feasible,'' Mr. Doctoroff said. ''It's definitely something worth looking into, which is why we're looking at it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
