<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Art Returning to SoHo Wall, With Room for Commerce</title>
    <meta content="25wall" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/nyregion/25wall.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842802"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sculpture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Speech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sculpture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E4D9143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Art Returning to SoHo Wall, With Room for Commerce</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Art Returning to SoHo Wall, With Room for Commerce</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY RAMIREZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ramirez, Anthony</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It has nothing to do with Berlin during the Cold War, but the story of ''The Wall,'' an enormous artwork in Lower Manhattan, is, in its own way, an epic conflict.</p>
        <p>The tale of ''The Wall'' spans more than a third of a century, 10 years of it in litigation, in which the outdoor art installation went up in SoHo, came down in SoHo -- and stayed down. But its reputation only grew as the artist, the artwork's landlords, neighborhood activists and, of course, lawyers, clashed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The tale of the outdoor art installation “The Wall” spans more than a third of a century, 10 years of it in litigation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It has nothing to do with Berlin during the Cold War, but the story of ''The Wall,'' an enormous artwork in Lower Manhattan, is, in its own way, an epic conflict.</p>
        <p>The tale of ''The Wall'' spans more than a third of a century, 10 years of it in litigation, in which the outdoor art installation went up in SoHo, came down in SoHo -- and stayed down. But its reputation only grew as the artist, the artwork's landlords, neighborhood activists and, of course, lawyers, clashed.</p>
        <p>''The Wall,'' commissioned in 1973, covered about one-sixth of an acre on the side of the building at 599 Broadway, just south of Houston Street. It was essentially a kind of dimpled field -- 42 protruding aluminum beams evenly spaced.</p>
        <p>Its parts have been in storage since 2002, perhaps never to be on display again. The building's owners wanted to put advertising billboards in its place.</p>
        <p>But yesterday, the conflict seemed about to end, not with a bang, but with applause.</p>
        <p>The city's Landmarks Preservation Commission unanimously approved, with little or no community opposition, a compromise reached by the creator of ''The Wall'' and the owners of 599 Broadway. It calls for advertising to go up on some of the space where ''The Wall'' once stood, satisfying the owners. But one floor above that, and illuminated at night, ''The Wall'' can return, satisfying the artist, Forrest Myers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Myers, 65, addressing the commission and noting the years it took to reach the compromise, said, ''I believe we're growing old together.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Myers, whose push-broom mustache and luxuriant eyebrows make him look like Mark Twain, added, ''If there is a movie made, I hope Brad Pitt plays me.''</p>
        <p>Still, there is much to do. Under the 20-page compromise, the owners will seek permits from the Department of Buildings to perform ''substantial work to the facade.'' The art and advertising will go up at the same time.</p>
        <p>But the original ''Wall,'' whose pieces were showing signs of deterioration, will not be used. Similar components will be installed under Mr. Myers's supervision. Michael Sillerman, the lawyer who represents the building's owners, estimated the work would take three to five months.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sillerman represents the SoHo Arts Condominium, the building's owners. David Topping, a partner in ABC Realty, owns most of the units in the building and rents them to other businesses, including the Blue Man Group.</p>
        <p>The original owner of 599 Broadway, Charles Tannenbaum, commissioned Mr. Myers's work as a way of disguising an eyesore -- naked joists that once were attached to a neighboring building that had been torn down. As its reputation grew, it became known as ''The Gateway to SoHo.''</p>
        <p>Successive building owners wanted to change the sculpture or replace it with advertising. ''The Wall'' became a local cause célèbre among artists and preservationists. It came down in 2002 when major repairs were made to the building.</p>
        <p>The owners, however, refused to put it back up when the repairs were finished. Since 599 Broadway is in a district that confers landmark status to everything within it, the sculpture became the subject of a federal lawsuit that Mr. Myers filed in 1997.</p>
        <p>Mr. Myers lost that suit in 2005. By that time, Mr. Topping and the other owners were weary of litigation and entered into negotiations with the artist. The settlement took more than 16 months to negotiate, and both sides came to an agreement in principle in early 2006, said Mr. Myers's lawyer, Sherman Kahn.</p>
        <p>''But every time we were close to done,'' Mr. Kahn said, ''there was another technical problem, like the Department of Buildings wouldn't approve the length of light poles for the advertising.''</p>
        <p>Although both sides agreed to let art and commerce coexist, Mr. Topping's lawyers wanted advertising to be placed both above ''The Wall'' and below it. ''That would have proved too distracting,'' Mr. Kahn said.</p>
        <p>The final compromise -- which won the endorsement of Community Board 2, the Municipal Art Society and the New York Landmarks Conservancy -- calls for ''The Wall'' to be raised 18 feet above its previous position, with four small panels of advertising at street level. The panels would measure 18 feet by 4 feet.</p>
        <p>What caught the imagination of Mr. Myers is that, under the agreement, his sculpture would be raised and illuminated by a lighting designer, Leni Schwendinger, who has won acclaim from architects for her work on the Parachute Jump in Coney Island.</p>
        <p>''It's so exciting to me I can't tell you,'' Mr. Myers told the Landmarks Preservation Commission yesterday. ''It'll be like illuminating the Empire State Building or the Statue of Liberty.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
