<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Virginia Tech Sets Out to Preserve Objects of Grief, Love and Forgiveness</title>
    <meta content="25virginia" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/us/25virginia.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842895"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cho, Seung-Hui</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E5D7143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="903" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Virginia Tech Sets Out to Preserve Objects of Grief, Love and Forgiveness</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Virginia Tech Sets Out to Preserve Objects of Grief, Love and Forgiveness</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTINE HAUSER</byline>
      <dateline>BLACKSBURG, Va., April 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The shrines arose spontaneously in the past few days on the Virginia Tech campus, makeshift memorials of letters and flowers to those who died in the shooting rampage on April 16. And, remarkably, there were 33 of them.</p>
        <p>One was a memorial to Seung-Hui Cho, the gunman who killed himself after shooting 32 students and teachers to death. At least a few people, as his site made clear, have prayed for and forgiven him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Among the shrines that have arisen spontaneously on the Virginia Tech campus is one for the gunmen, Seung-Hui Cho.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The shrines arose spontaneously in the past few days on the Virginia Tech campus, makeshift memorials of letters and flowers to those who died in the shooting rampage on April 16. And, remarkably, there were 33 of them.</p>
        <p>One was a memorial to Seung-Hui Cho, the gunman who killed himself after shooting 32 students and teachers to death. At least a few people, as his site made clear, have prayed for and forgiven him.</p>
        <p>Candles at Mr. Cho's memorial have burned to the wick. A plastic bottle holding flowers stands next to letters to him and his family, as well as cards and an American flag.</p>
        <p>''Dear Cho,'' a handwritten note says. ''You are not excluded from our sorrow in death although you thought you were excluded from our love in life.'' It continues: ''I wish you had given us all a chance. Your choice was so final.''</p>
        <p>Another letter, handwritten and covered in plastic, addresses him.</p>
        <p>''I hope that if I ever met anyone like you I would have the courage and strength to reach out and change his or her life for the better.''</p>
        <p>Another note says only three words: ''I forgive you.''</p>
        <p>But the little memorial, exposed like the others to the wind and the elements, is a fragile piece of testimony. With the prospect of rain washing away handwriting from letters and warping photographs, officials from Virginia Tech started the process on Tuesday of preserving these objects of grief, love and forgiveness.</p>
        <p>The task has several grim precedents in recent American history. University officials are consulting with experts from the Library of Congress, which compiled materials from the Sept. 11 terrorist attacks, and from Syracuse University, where tens of thousands of letters, artworks, newspaper clippings and other original documents form an archive of the Pan Am 103 bombing over Lockerbie, Scotland.</p>
        <p>''We are calling them in because it is new to us,'' said Eileen E. Hitchingham, dean of libraries at Virginia Tech. As she spoke, a photographer from the university took pictures of each small memorial while storm clouds gathered.</p>
        <p>''The idea is,'' Ms. Hitchingham said, ''what will we want to be looking at 10 years from now that we can do today?''</p>
        <p>Soon after the killings on April 16, the memorials started to take shape in a semicircle across from the campus's administration building on an expanse of lawn known as the Drillfield that has become a focal point for the grieving.</p>
        <p>The piles of flowers, pictures, handwritten cards and mementos express to the victims what can no longer be said in words, that they will be loved and missed, that they have inspired and amused.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hitchingham said every effort would be made to preserve all the objects, including pressing one flower from each shrine bouquet. The mementos and original documents will temporarily be held for safekeeping at a student center until a permanent home is found.</p>
        <p>''In some way, we will probably have for each person the recognition of the fact that they existed,'' Ms. Hitchingham said.</p>
        <p>Pieces of limestone had been placed as markers on each memorial, although at one point there was none at Mr. Cho's, without explanation. But his site, which is marked by piles of flowers and notes like the others, has allowed people to address the killer, giving them an opportunity to question a crime they know will never be explained.</p>
        <p>''The fact that he took his own life at the end deprived people of this opportunity,'' said Michael Bush, a volunteer mental health worker walking among the students on the field.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, a woman made her way around the semicircle, placing a fresh red rose on each memorial. She did so at Mr. Cho's, as well, after a brief hesitation.</p>
        <p>The archive at Virginia Tech will include the original documents left at the memorials, as well as electronic material, taking into account Internet messages and cellphone images.</p>
        <p>''The electronic component has become so large,'' Ms. Hitchingham said. ''We live in both the tangible record of the written word and the electronic.''</p>
        <p>The process could unfold over years. The university consulted with Edward L. Galvin, the director of archives and records management at Syracuse, who estimated that tens of thousands of items related to Pan Am 103 had been collected, and more keep coming in.</p>
        <p>''Who knew at the time the families of the victims of Pan Am 103 would become such a political group and work to get Libya to say that they actually did the bombing?'' Mr. Galvin said.</p>
        <p>The collections specialists at the Library of Congress have been asked to help Virginia Tech archive its digital material, said Jeremy E. Adamson, the library's director of collections and services. The library's American Folklife Center is interested in setting up a recording booth on campus, like one used after Sept. 11 at ground zero, to collect oral history.</p>
        <p>Peggy A. Bulger, director of the folklife center, said items left at spontaneous shrines like the ones at Virginia Tech were a form of folklife art because they were an aesthetic way that people express themselves.</p>
        <p>''This is going to be very important for people who will be studying later about what happened and what people's reactions were,'' Ms. Bulger said, referring to the archival process. ''It's absolutely a critical part of filling in the gaps of history. This is the emotional glue that really fills in everything.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
