<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Test for the Roberts Court</title>
    <meta content="25weds1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/opinion/25weds1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070430T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842774"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Editorial"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Supreme Court</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Feingold, Russell D</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kohl, Herb</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Roberts, John G Jr</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Alito, Samuel A Jr</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E2DA143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="448" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Test for the Roberts Court</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Test for the Roberts Court</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The campaign finance system is like an overburdened dam: it holds back a flood of special-interest money, but there is a constant struggle to keep it from springing leaks. The Supreme Court hears arguments today in a case that could determine whether a major new leak opens up, one that would allow corporations and unions to pour unprecedented amounts of money into political campaigns. It is important that the court continue to keep this money out.</p>
        <p>Corporations have been prohibited since the early 1900's from contributing to political campaigns. This ban and a similar one imposed later on unions prevents these wealthy entities from buying elections and elected officials. The Supreme Court, in upholding these bans, has recognized that Congress has a compelling interest in preventing the ''corrosive and distorting effects'' of corporate and union contributions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Supreme Court hears arguments Wednesday in a case that could determine whether a major new leak opens up in the campaign finance system.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The campaign finance system is like an overburdened dam: it holds back a flood of special-interest money, but there is a constant struggle to keep it from springing leaks. The Supreme Court hears arguments today in a case that could determine whether a major new leak opens up, one that would allow corporations and unions to pour unprecedented amounts of money into political campaigns. It is important that the court continue to keep this money out.</p>
        <p>Corporations have been prohibited since the early 1900's from contributing to political campaigns. This ban and a similar one imposed later on unions prevents these wealthy entities from buying elections and elected officials. The Supreme Court, in upholding these bans, has recognized that Congress has a compelling interest in preventing the ''corrosive and distorting effects'' of corporate and union contributions.</p>
        <p>Corporations and unions have, not surprisingly, tried to get around the ban. One tactic they have used is bankrolling phony ''issue ads'': commercials that purport to educate the public about a policy issue, but are actually intended to elect or defeat a particular candidate. Today's case involves phony issue ads run on radio and television by a group called Wisconsin Right to Life, which accepted major contributions from corporations against Senator Russell Feingold, Democrat of Wisconsin.</p>
        <p>The ads attacked Mr. Feingold and Wisconsin's other senator, Herb Kohl, for blocking President Bush's judicial nominees, and urged the public to contact the two men to complain. Clearly the ads' purpose was to try to prevent Mr. Feingold's re-election. Wisconsin Right to Life had made it clear that it was targeting him for defeat. Mr. Feingold's opponents were using the issue of judicial nominees against him. The ads ran shortly before the election, while the Senate was in recess and no votes on judges were being held. And they did not provide contact information for Mr. Feingold and Mr. Kohl.</p>
        <p>The court ruled in 2003 that bogus issue ads like these were the ''functional equivalent'' of campaign ads, and upheld Congress's ban on the use of corporate and union money to pay for them. That case should be controlling, but since 2003, two new members -- Chief Justice John Roberts and Justice Samuel Alito -- have joined the court. Today's case will be a test of their respect for Congress's authority to regulate campaign finance practices, and for the court's recent precedents.</p>
        <p>In last year's election, the voters clearly showed they are unhappy with the role special interests play in Washington. That frustration has grown with each new scandal involving Congress or the Bush administration. It would be disturbing if the court now changed the rules to make it easier for special interests to corrupt American democracy.</p>
        <p>Editorial</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 30, 2007, Monday  An Op-Ed article on Wednesday, about the Supreme Court abortion ruling, misidentified the state involved in a similar abortion case in 2000. It was Nebraska, not Kansas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 30, 2007, Monday</p>
        <p>An Op-Ed article on Wednesday, about the Supreme Court abortion ruling, misidentified the state involved in a similar abortion case in 2000. It was Nebraska, not Kansas.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
