<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Outside the Box: Rethinking All Geometric Limits of Form and Frame, Floor and Ceiling</title>
    <meta content="25grey" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/arts/design/25grey.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Grey Art Gallery</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ireland, Patrick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E7DB143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="821" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Outside the Box: Rethinking All Geometric Limits of Form and Frame, Floor and Ceiling</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Outside the Box: Rethinking All Geometric Limits of Form and Frame, Floor and Ceiling</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRIDGET L. GOODBODY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The provocative Brian O'Doherty/Patrick Ireland retrospective at New York University's Grey Art Gallery highlights the decade when Minimalism morphed into Conceptualism. What you'll discover here is a manifesto, albeit a high-minded one, that represents the decade (1966-1976) when artists thought they could change the world not by filling it with new stories, but by emptying it of them.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Doherty -- Patrick Ireland is the politically influenced name he signs on some works -- has spent his life promoting the arts, though he was trained as a doctor, not as an artist, in his native Ireland. He has worked as an editor and a critic but in contemporary art circles he's best known for his 1976 essays ''Inside the White Cube.'' These review the history behind postmodernism's break from Modernism, when art became part of the gallery because artists started using the space around the work -- literally, the wall, floor and ceiling -- as part of their art.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The provocative Brian O’Doherty/Patrick Ireland retrospective at New York University’s Grey Art Gallery highlights the decade when Minimalism morphed into Conceptualism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The provocative Brian O'Doherty/Patrick Ireland retrospective at New York University's Grey Art Gallery highlights the decade when Minimalism morphed into Conceptualism. What you'll discover here is a manifesto, albeit a high-minded one, that represents the decade (1966-1976) when artists thought they could change the world not by filling it with new stories, but by emptying it of them.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Doherty -- Patrick Ireland is the politically influenced name he signs on some works -- has spent his life promoting the arts, though he was trained as a doctor, not as an artist, in his native Ireland. He has worked as an editor and a critic but in contemporary art circles he's best known for his 1976 essays ''Inside the White Cube.'' These review the history behind postmodernism's break from Modernism, when art became part of the gallery because artists started using the space around the work -- literally, the wall, floor and ceiling -- as part of their art.</p>
        <p>As Mr. O'Doherty saw it, art's biggest stride forward at this time was the recognition (perhaps taken for granted now, but revolutionary then) that the social systems behind the exhibition and selling of art were part of, not separate from, the work itself.</p>
        <p>Much of Mr. O'Doherty's early work shows a clear debt to Marcel Duchamp, whose art often exposed the art world's underpinnings and prejudices. In 1966 he invited Mr. Duchamp to dinner and persuaded him to let him administer an electrocardiogram and make a portrait from it. Two light boxes here depict Mr. Duchamp's heartbeat: one is literal, showing it at a state of rest; the other, an artistic representation, shows it at an even slower rate. In other words, one is a stand-in for Mr. Duchamp, while the other is more a reference to the Duchampian idea.</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Duchamp (and John Cage, Max Ernst and Man Ray, among others), Mr. O'Doherty found inspiration in chess. Unlike him, Mr. O'Doherty used it to explore Minimalism's grid. He started by making drawings, some on view here, that turned the grammar of the chess pieces' moves into linear fretworks.</p>
        <p>Because he saw the movement of the pieces as labyrinthine, he started to make actual, human-size labyrinths, a form also cherished by his contemporaries Alice Aycock, Robert Morris, Tony Smith and Robert Smithson, among others.</p>
        <p>Conceptually, it's not a big leap from the chessboards and labyrinths (some took the form of a St. Brigid's Cross) to Mr. O'Doherty's sculptural series based on the Ogham script, an ancient Celtic notational language system. Made from reflecting metal or plexiglass and inscribed with the script, these sculptures marry Minimalism's reductivism to ancient architectural forms like the obelisk, ziggurat and pyramid.</p>
        <p>This was a way for Mr. O'Doherty to make forms that symbolized art's underlying grammar. His interest in linguistics inspired him to invite the semiotician Roland Barthes to contribute to the 1967 issue he edited of Aspen, a short-lived but still influential avant-garde magazine. (Copies in the show provide a fantastic window into the ideas of the period's movers and shakers.) Mr. Barthes contributed his now-famous essay ''The Death of the Author.''</p>
        <p>The pieces that best exemplify the ideas Mr. O'Doherty puts forth in ''Inside the White Cube'' are his rope drawings, which engage the ''white cube'' aspect of the gallery while being anything but a white cube.</p>
        <p>''Talking With Bramante, Rope Drawing No. 111,'' which he made for this show, could be called an allover sculpture. Its geometric patterns, covering the wall from floor to ceiling, are painted in a Fra Angelico-like palette. Not only do the ropes that are strung diagonally across the room transform the piece into a labyrinth, but they also turn the viewer into an active spectator -- to see the piece in its entirety, you have to step over or duck under the ropes.</p>
        <p>The piece also turns the Renaissance concept of compositional order on its head. There is no simple ''railroad track receding into the distance'' version of perspective here. The ropes lead into and out of the space as they simultaneously move the eye in myriad other directions.</p>
        <p>Successful as these works are, Mr. O'Doherty's most celebrated artistic performance began in 1972. To protest the Bloody Sunday Massacre in which British troops killed 13 civil rights marchers in Londonderry, he pledged to sign his artwork Patrick Ireland ''until such time as British military presence is removed from Northern Ireland and all citizens are granted their civil rights.''</p>
        <p>By taking this alias -- it is one of five Mr. O'Doherty uses; each can be further explored at the exhibition -- he makes the issue fresh each time his art is shown under it. Now British troops are scheduled to withdraw from Ireland this August. As Mr. O'Doherty once wrote: ''Life, not art, is the prime value.''</p>
        <p>''Beyond the White Cube'' is on view through July 14 at Grey Art Gallery, 100 Washington Square East, Greenwich Village; (212) 998-6780 or nyu.edu/greyart.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
