<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Second Thoughts About Veal</title>
    <meta content="25lett" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842725"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cruelty to Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E4DC143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="486" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Second Thoughts About Veal</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Veal to Love, Without the Guilt'' (April 18):</p>
        <p>This article's claims of livestock reform are admirable, but I think we could be missing the point here. Even the headline suggests that we feel guilty only about the way these animals are raised, turning a blind eye to another very real horror: the killing and processing that follows.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Veal to Love, Without the Guilt'' (April 18):</p>
        <p>This article's claims of livestock reform are admirable, but I think we could be missing the point here. Even the headline suggests that we feel guilty only about the way these animals are raised, turning a blind eye to another very real horror: the killing and processing that follows.</p>
        <p>Why did those images of ''formula-fed veal calves tethered in crates'' affect us so much? They took away the abstraction that is inherent in our consumption practices. We no longer saw these abstract gray slabs at the meat counter; we saw the animals from which this material came, and that made a world of difference.</p>
        <p>The article's rather pastoral images of calves grazing, ''mingling'' with other calves or with their mothers, are all well and good, but this isn't a Bambi story.</p>
        <p>If the article went on to describe the slaughter and processing of these animals, the techniques used and the volumes at which they are processed, that old guilt would come pouring back.</p>
        <p>If it's being completely ''guilt-free'' we're after, there's really only one solution: to stop eating meat altogether.</p>
        <p>RICHARD DI SANTO  Toronto</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I was raised on a farm and yes, veal is divine. But it still involves the killing of an innocent and emotional animal. Anyone working with animals, even young ones, soon discovers they have emotions as humans do. We would take young calves away from their mothers after three days. It was sad to see the mother cow be by herself for days afterward, not eating much, and staying near the last place she was with her baby. This is just one of many incidents about animals and their feelings. If human meat-eaters would see this side of animals, they would give up meat.</p>
        <p>DEBBIE COOPHAM  Portland, Ore.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I would like to thank you for writing the article called ''Veal to Love, Without the Guilt.'' It is encouraging to be reminded that people really do care about how animals are treated, as was mentioned in the article about the decline in popularity of veal after people learned how the calves were treated. I hope this article raised questions in people's minds about how we arrive at other animal products that we consume/use (besides veal).</p>
        <p>AMY STRIBULA  Rocky River, Ohio</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>There is no such thing as guilt-free veal. Cows give milk to feed calves, not humans. They are artificially impregnated so that they will produce a constant supply of milk. Their babies are taken away and killed for veal, and their milk is sold in supermarkets. When cows are no longer able to produce much milk, they are slaughtered -- just like their babies.</p>
        <p>The whole process is cruel and traumatic for the cows and the calves.</p>
        <p>ELAINE SLOAN  New York</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
