<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spitzer Visits Bruno Turf To Push Campaign Reform</title>
    <meta content="25spitzer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/nyregion/25spitzer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842829"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Spitzer, Eliot L</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bruno, Joseph L</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DEED9143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="755" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spitzer Visits Bruno Turf To Push Campaign Reform</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Spitzer Visits Bruno Turf to Push Campaign Reform</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM and MICHAEL COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny; Cooper, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>TROY, N.Y., April 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer traveled Tuesday to the district of the Senate majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, on the first stop of a statewide tour to blast Senate Republicans for scuttling his plan to overhaul campaign finance regulations.</p>
        <p>''It was close to my office and just happened to be a Senate district where the senator has not been in favor of the bill,'' the governor said, tongue in cheek, after meeting with the editorial board of The Troy Record here, in the heart of Mr. Bruno's district.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>TROY, N.Y., April 24  Gov. Eliot Spitzer traveled Tuesday to the district of the Senate majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, on the first stop of a statewide tour to blast Senate Republicans for scuttling his plan to overhaul campaign finance regulations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer traveled Tuesday to the district of the Senate majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, on the first stop of a statewide tour to blast Senate Republicans for scuttling his plan to overhaul campaign finance regulations.</p>
        <p>''It was close to my office and just happened to be a Senate district where the senator has not been in favor of the bill,'' the governor said, tongue in cheek, after meeting with the editorial board of The Troy Record here, in the heart of Mr. Bruno's district.</p>
        <p>Later in the morning, Mr. Bruno came out swinging at a press conference in the capital, portraying the governor as an out-of-touch rich guy, a hypocrite who raises big bucks while trying to limit contributions, the head of an administration beset by ''alleged corruption'' and someone who is failing to bring jobs to upstate New York.</p>
        <p>And that was in a news conference that lasted less than 15 minutes.</p>
        <p>''Does this governor think he's going to get a result on campaign finance reform by -- what, by doing what -- by having a tantrum?'' Mr. Bruno asked.</p>
        <p>The governor, speaking at another press conference in Schenectady shortly after noon, turned icy when told of Mr. Bruno's comments.</p>
        <p>''Once again, Joe Bruno's arguments are right on point,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''There is haze and smog surrounding the capital today, and that smog could have been lifted had the members of the Republican majority in the State Senate opted to embrace campaign finance reform,'' he said, adding, ''I am embarking today on an effort to go to the public across the state to say we can do better.''</p>
        <p>The day reinforced that the volatile relationship between the governor and Mr. Bruno, the state's top Republican, is on the rocks again, with the governor openly agitating to upend the Republicans' two-seat majority in the 62-member Senate.</p>
        <p>The governor appeared at the news conference with Assemblyman Paul D. Tonko, a Democrat now favored by party officials to run against Senator Hugh T. Farley, a Schenectady Republican, in 2008. Mr. Tonko was noncommittal when asked if he was considering a run for Senate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer called Mr. Farley ''a nice gentleman, a good man, but somebody who is fundamentally wrong on this issue.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Farley, in a written statement, said ''the Governor's 'campaign financing reform' will ensure that only people with great personal wealth -- such as Governor Spitzer and Mayor Bloomberg -- can afford to run for public office.''</p>
        <p>He and other Republicans continued to try to use the governor's family fortune against him, accusing him of trying to create a system that would favor rich candidates. The governor and his aides countered that their proposal included a special amendment that would allow candidates to exceed the regular contribution limits if they are running against a self-financed opponent.</p>
        <p>Republicans also accused the governor of trying to trade a legislative pay raise for campaign finance reform. The governor's aides denied that, though the governor himself has said for some time that he would reward lawmakers with a pay raise only if they agreed to make many of the changes he has proposed on a number of fronts.</p>
        <p>On campaign finance, the governor had proposed lowering contribution limits from $55,800 for statewide candidates to no more than $15,000, which is still much more than is allowed in federal or New York City elections, and also reducing limits for legislative candidates. He would have put the first limits on total contributions that political action committees could make, holding them to the still lofty sum of $350,000 a year.</p>
        <p>The governor and his aides said the sticking point was over banning donations by limited liability companies and corporate subsidiaries, which wealthy donors and corporations routinely use to circumvent contribution limits.</p>
        <p>''I would say it's time for Joe Bruno to answer a simple question,'' the governor said today. ''Mr. Bruno, why did you say directly to me, we cannot survive without L.L.C. money? Answer that question, Senator.''</p>
        <p>(Asked why he does not support banning contributions from such companies, Mr. Bruno answered, ''Life, liberty and the pursuit of happiness.'')</p>
        <p>Republicans have chafed at the comments because the governor used L.L.C.'s to raise substantial amounts of money, more than $3 million over four years, according to analysis by Common Cause New York, a group that supports the governor's proposal to ban such donations. In the Legislature, Senate Republicans have led the way in accepting such donations; the Senate Republican Campaign Committee raised nearly $580,000 last year from such companies.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
