<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AT&amp;T Earnings Beat Forecasts Despite Slow Market for Mobile Phones</title>
    <meta content="25phone" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/technology/25phone.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842808"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">AT&amp;T Corp</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E2D9143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="764" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AT&amp;T Earnings Beat Forecasts Despite Slow Market for Mobile Phones</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">AT&amp;T Earnings Beat Forecasts Despite Slow Market for Mobile Phones</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT RICHTEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Richtel, Matt</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, April 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT&amp;T, the world's largest telephone company, reported first-quarter earnings on Tuesday that handily beat Wall Street expectations. But some investors and telecommunications industry analysts said they were not sure that AT&amp;T could continue its pace, particularly as growth is slowing in the mobile phone business.</p>
        <p>The earnings show the potential for growth but also the steep challenges facing AT&amp;T and other telephone companies that are turning into multifaceted telecommunications providers offering landline, mobile, Internet and television services.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The earnings show the potential for growth but also the steep challenges facing AT&amp;T and other telephone companies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT&amp;T, the world's largest telephone company, reported first-quarter earnings on Tuesday that handily beat Wall Street expectations. But some investors and telecommunications industry analysts said they were not sure that AT&amp;T could continue its pace, particularly as growth is slowing in the mobile phone business.</p>
        <p>The earnings show the potential for growth but also the steep challenges facing AT&amp;T and other telephone companies that are turning into multifaceted telecommunications providers offering landline, mobile, Internet and television services.</p>
        <p>For the first quarter, which ended March 31, AT&amp;T reported net income of $4.1 billion, or 65 cents a share. That was 4 cents higher than the consensus estimate of Wall Street analysts who cover the company.</p>
        <p>The earnings were the first since AT&amp;T closed its $86 billion acquisition of BellSouth in December. The effects of that merger muddied the first-quarter results, making them hard to compare with the numbers for the same quarter a year ago.</p>
        <p>In the first quarter of 2006, before AT&amp;T absorbed BellSouth, the company's earnings were 52 cents a share.</p>
        <p>Costs associated with that deal and with AT&amp;T's previous acquisitions of the long-distance provider AT&amp;T Corporation and of AT&amp;T Wireless also added around $2 billion to expenses. When those and other one-time charges and gains are included, AT&amp;T's earnings drop to 45 cents a share, on roughly $2.8 billion in net income. Sales for the quarter were $29 billion.</p>
        <p>Shares of AT&amp;T fell slightly after the earnings announcement, closing the day at $39.10, down 67 cents from Monday's close. The company's shares have been on a steady two-year rise from the low $20s.</p>
        <p>Industry analysts said that a crucial question facing AT&amp;T was whether the company, now that it has wrapped up a series of major acquisitions, can find growth by expanding its underlying businesses.</p>
        <p>''They are executing for the most part,'' said Qaisar Hasan, an analyst with Buckingham Research, who has the equivalent of a hold rating on the company's stock. ''The issue for me is that people have unduly upbeat expectations about this company.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hasan said that while AT&amp;T beat analysts' expectations, the particulars of its performance left continuing questions, including the issue of competition from cable and Internet competitors. Analysts and AT&amp;T executives said that there were areas of good news coming from the mobile phone business, Cingular Wireless. Revenues from that business were $10 billion, up 11.2 percent from the same quarter a year ago, in part reflecting the growing use of mobile data services.</p>
        <p>Cingular's service margins, a measure of wireless profits, were 38.9 percent, up from 31.9 percent a year earlier. Analysts said that the margin improvement was a big contributor to the overall profit increase.</p>
        <p>Richard G. Lindner, AT&amp;T's chief financial officer, attributed the improved margins to refining and consolidation of the networks that carry its mobile phone traffic, particularly as Cingular merged operations with the former AT&amp;T Wireless.</p>
        <p>''Our expectations are that the margin levels will improve further,'' Mr. Lindner said.</p>
        <p>But the wireless business left some nagging questions, too. Cingular added 1.2 million subscribers, less than the 1.4 million projected by a consensus of Wall Street analysts, Christopher C. King, an analyst with Stifel Nicolaus Telecom Equity Research, wrote in a note to investors.</p>
        <p>''The quarter appears to be generally in line with the one exception of wireless net adds,'' Mr. King wrote.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lindner said that the subscriber problem was caused by an industrywide slowing in the number of new wireless subscribers as the market becomes saturated.</p>
        <p>''It's a natural evolution in the business,'' he said, adding, ''The thing you will increasingly see in the wireless business is some slowing of customer growth.''</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T, like other major telecommunications companies, continued to see a decline in its traditional telephone business. In the first quarter, it lost 285,000 primary consumer lines, compared with declines of 251,000 in the first quarter of last year and 331,000 in the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>The company said that it also lost 130,000 secondary phone lines in the latest quarter.</p>
        <p>But it continued to see gains in its high-speed Internet business, adding 691,000 subscribers to reach 12.9 million over all.</p>
        <p>The company is still in the early stages of introducing its television service, called U-verse. The company said it added around 10,000 subscribers in the quarter, bringing its total to 13,000. But it said that as of Tuesday that number had already climbed to 20,000, and that it was adding about 2,000 subscribers a week.</p>
        <p>However, AT&amp;T said that it still took about seven hours to install the service, because of the complexity of the job.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
