<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Questions on Officials' Ties to Lenders</title>
    <meta content="25loans" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/education/25loans.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842785"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Education Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sallie Mae</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, George (Rep)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glater, Jonathan D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arenson, Karen W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Education Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE1DA143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1018" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Questions on Officials' Ties to Lenders</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Questions on Officials’ Ties to Lenders</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN D. GLATER and KAREN W. ARENSON; Sam Dillon contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arenson, Karen W; Glater, Jonathan D</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rep George Miller, chairman of House Education Committee, says links between Education Dept and student loan industry are concern; committee is holding hearing on student loan problems; government investigators say at least 20 former Sallie Mae employees moved into department under Bush administration (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sara Martinez Tucker, the under secretary of education, was relatively new to her job when she announced in January that the Department of Education would allow Nelnet, a student loan company accused of overbilling the government, to keep $278 million in payments that auditors had declared improper.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tucker was not a stranger to the loan industry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sara Martinez Tucker, the under secretary of education, worked for student lenders before she worked for the department of education.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sara Martinez Tucker, the under secretary of education, was relatively new to her job when she announced in January that the Department of Education would allow Nelnet, a student loan company accused of overbilling the government, to keep $278 million in payments that auditors had declared improper.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tucker was not a stranger to the loan industry.</p>
        <p>Under her leadership, the Hispanic Scholarship Fund, a philanthropy she turned into a fund-raising powerhouse, harvested numerous donations from banks and loan companies, along with scores of other corporations.</p>
        <p>During her 10-year tenure, Sallie Mae donated at least $420,000. Bank of America gave at least $1 million. Citigroup donated at least $315,000. JPMorgan Chase gave at least $280,000.</p>
        <p>''We are grateful to Nelnet for supporting Hispanics in higher education,'' Ms. Tucker said last September, according to a scholarship fund press release, when the company made a $50,000 contribution.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tucker also served for nearly four years on the board of a subsidiary of Sallie Mae, the nation's largest student loan company. Appointed by President Bush when Sallie Mae was taking its final steps from a government-sponsored entity into a completely private company, she helped oversee the change.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tucker, who as under secretary is responsible for higher education and student aid, is not the only department official with previous ties to lenders. Representative George Miller, Democrat of California and chairman of the House Education Committee, said that links between the department and the student loan industry were a concern. His committee is holding a hearing today on student loan problems.</p>
        <p>''It is becoming increasingly clear that the conflicts of interest undermining the federal student loan programs may extend to the federal officials tasked with running them,'' Mr. Miller said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Luke Swarthout, higher education advocate for the U.S. Public Interest Research Group in Washington, called the situation a ''classic'' case ''of foxes guarding the henhouse.''</p>
        <p>Some officials came directly from lenders. Theresa S. Shaw, head of the department's Federal Student Aid office, worked at Sallie Mae for nearly two decades. Matteo Fontana, a former director of systems development at Sallie Mae, became general manager of the office that oversees a database with financial information on student borrowers. Mr. Fontana was put on leave by the department after his ownership of stock in a student lender was disclosed.</p>
        <p>Government investigators looking into the industry say that in all at least 20 former Sallie Mae employees had moved into the department under the Bush administration.</p>
        <p>A former Sallie Mae employee, Stanley Dore, who had been assistant vice president for corporate risk management at Sallie Mae, works in the office of Federal Student Aid. Mariana O'Brien, a vice president of public relations at Sallie Mae, also works there.</p>
        <p>Michael Sutphin, director of financial industry alliances at Sallie Mae until 2002, is state agency liaison officer at the department, according to his disclosure forms. When Mr. Sutphin joined the department he had $50,001 to $100,000 in Sallie Mae stock, which he reported in 2005 that he had sold the preceding year, before his promotion to his latest job, which requires him to work closely with lenders.</p>
        <p>Defenders of the department say that it has 4,000 employees and that it is not unreasonable for technical jobs to be filled by people with particular skills honed in industry. Katherine McLane, a department spokeswoman, said the ability to ''attract experienced professionals'' was essential to the agency's ''vital mission of helping more students afford college.''</p>
        <p>But the department's own inspector general's office, in a scathing report last September, said some staff members had favored ''partnership over compliance in dealing with guaranty agencies, lenders and servicers'' and failed to provide adequate oversight. The report looked only at the small division overseeing the department's financial partners; it did not cite individuals.</p>
        <p>At least a handful of others associated with the lending industry have moved into the department. Kristie Hansen and Tim Cameron, for example, both came to the department from the National Council of Higher Education Loan Programs, a loan industry trade group.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hansen declined to comment on her move, referring questions to Ms. McLane. Mr. Cameron, who is no longer at the department, could not be located for comment.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tucker, who had been an executive at AT&amp;T before joining the Hispanic fund, also served on Education Secretary Margaret Spellings's commission on higher education. Ms. Tucker joined the department months after the inspector general's report, and she has many ardent supporters who say she was devoted to giving out scholarships in her 10 years at the helm of the Hispanic Scholarship Fund. Roger Benjamin, the fund's chairman, said in an interview that asking about possible conflicts in Ms. Tucker's situation, growing out of her previous post, was ''fair,'' but that he could not imagine her stepping over any ethical line.</p>
        <p>''She certainly was the rainmaker for the Hispanic Scholarship Fund,'' Mr. Benjamin said. ''But there were so many contributors that I don't know that she had any particular relationships with the corporations and foundations in the banking and student loan area.''</p>
        <p>Ms. McLane declined to say whether Ms. Tucker was involved in making the decision to let Nelnet keep nearly $300 million, or whether there was any discussion about recusing her from certain decisions. The department said at the time that trying to recover the money from Nelnet might require it to pursue other lenders and could reduce students' borrowing options.</p>
        <p>Ms. McLane said that Ms. Tucker was not available for comment but added that she was ''a public servant of the highest integrity'' and was confirmed by the Senate, which did ''not think she had a conflict of interest.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Benjamin said he had faith she would be an impartial and creative force in cleaning up any problems with the student loan industry.</p>
        <p>''If anybody can get to the heart of what seems to be a mess, and it definitely needs to be cleaned up, she's just the person who can do it,'' Mr. Benjamin said. ''She has formidable organizational skills, and she is very sharp.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
