<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>China Sets Out To Cut Secrecy, But Laws Leave Big Loopholes</title>
    <meta content="25china" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/world/asia/25china.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842768"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yardley, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classification of Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classification of Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E2DA143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="441" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>China Sets Out To Cut Secrecy, But Laws Leave Big Loopholes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">China Sets Out to Cut Secrecy, but Laws Leave Big Loopholes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM YARDLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yardley, Jim</byline>
      <dateline>BEIJING, April 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>China announces new regulations to reduce government secrecy and grant citizens greater access to official information, but regulations include broad exceptions that raise questions about how much openness will actually be tolerated; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>China announced new regulations on Tuesday to reduce government secrecy and grant citizens greater access to official information, but the regulations include broad exceptions that raise questions about how much new openness will be tolerated.</p>
        <p>The regulations, approved in a decree signed by Prime Minister Wen Jiabao, were announced with fanfare on Tuesday but will not become effective until May 1, 2008. And the caveats suggest that the new regulations may represent only measured steps in fulfilling promises by top leaders to create a more transparent and accountable government.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>China announced new regulations to grant citizens greater access to official information, but questions about government openness remain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>China announced new regulations on Tuesday to reduce government secrecy and grant citizens greater access to official information, but the regulations include broad exceptions that raise questions about how much new openness will be tolerated.</p>
        <p>The regulations, approved in a decree signed by Prime Minister Wen Jiabao, were announced with fanfare on Tuesday but will not become effective until May 1, 2008. And the caveats suggest that the new regulations may represent only measured steps in fulfilling promises by top leaders to create a more transparent and accountable government.</p>
        <p>President Hu Jintao and Mr. Wen have declared corruption a major crisis within the Communist Party and have made improving governance a priority in their efforts to clean things up.</p>
        <p>Reformers have pushed for more openness and public oversight through access to official information. But conservatives have resisted loosening the grip of party control, including on official data.</p>
        <p>The new rules, as decided by China's cabinet, include a list of ''priorities'' detailing what information should be eligible for public release: government responses to emergencies; government spending and fees; and official investigations into environmental problems and public health concerns, as well as food and drug safety.</p>
        <p>In addition, the new rules would require local governments to publicize information about land acquisitions from farmers, as well as details on where those farmers would be relocated and how much compensation they would receive.</p>
        <p>At face value, these new rules would seem to create broad new public rights to once secret information. Farmers, for example, have routinely been denied access to official records in their efforts to fight illegal land seizures.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, officials have regularly withheld vital information during crises like the outbreak of severe acute respiratory syndrome, or SARS, in 2003, as well as during the 2005 chemical spill that poisoned the Songhua River and forced the shutdown of public drinking water in the city of Harbin.</p>
        <p>Zhang Qiong, deputy director of the cabinet's Legislative Office, praised the new rules as a breakthrough for China in preventing abuses of power.</p>
        <p>''It will also safeguard the public's right to know, the right to participate and the right to supervise,'' Mr. Zhang said at a news conference on Tuesday, according to Xinhua, China's official news agency. ''The regulation will help curb corruption at its source, largely reducing its occurrence.''</p>
        <p>But, in fact, the new rules include exclusions that could allow officials substantial latitude in deciding what they choose to make public.</p>
        <p>The regulations said that local governments must ''steer clear'' of releasing any information defined as a ''state secret,'' a major exception given that China designates a wide range of information as state secrets.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
