<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mommy Books: More Buzz Than Buyers</title>
    <meta content="25momm" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/books/25momm.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842739"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Feminist Movement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Blogs and Blogging (Internet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Feminist Movement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blogs and Blogging (Internet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Friedan, Betty</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E6DB143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1431" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mommy Books: More Buzz Than Buyers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mommy Books: More Buzz Than Buyers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MOTOKO RICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rich, Motoko</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the last few months, Monique Moen, a former actress and now a stay-at-home mother in Los Angeles, has bought several books: ''Slaughterhouse-Five'' by Kurt Vonnegut; ''A Room of One's Own'' by Virginia Woolf; ''Mistress of the Art of Death,'' a historical thriller by Ariana Franklin; and the latest James Patterson novel.</p>
        <p>But the book that prompted her to write a 1,200-word post on her blog, www.mommiesparadise.com, was ''The Feminine Mistake'' by Leslie Bennetts, which Ms. Moen has not read and has no intention of reading.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The perennial dilemma of whether to return to work or stay at home with the kids appears to be a better conversation starter than a page turner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the last few months, Monique Moen, a former actress and now a stay-at-home mother in Los Angeles, has bought several books: ''Slaughterhouse-Five'' by Kurt Vonnegut; ''A Room of One's Own'' by Virginia Woolf; ''Mistress of the Art of Death,'' a historical thriller by Ariana Franklin; and the latest James Patterson novel.</p>
        <p>But the book that prompted her to write a 1,200-word post on her blog, www.mommiesparadise.com, was ''The Feminine Mistake'' by Leslie Bennetts, which Ms. Moen has not read and has no intention of reading.</p>
        <p>Having seen an article from HuffingtonPost.com by Ms. Bennetts and a review of the book, which argues that mothers who stay at home with their children are financially, emotionally and medically at risk, Ms. Moen believes that she knows enough about it to debate its premise.</p>
        <p>''I really think she laid out what she wrote about in the book in the article,'' Ms. Moen said. ''The whole article rubbed me the wrong way, so I'm not inclined to read the book.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Moen is one of dozens of women online who have tangled with what they perceive as Ms. Bennetts's message. Fueled by the author's appearance on the ''Today'' show, an excerpt in Glamour magazine, and reviews or interviews in Parade and People, these women are giving Ms. Bennetts the kind of cocktail-party stature (if these women, mostly mothers, had time for cocktail parties) to which many writers aspire.</p>
        <p>The explosion of commentary on blogs and elsewhere about ''The Feminine Mistake'' joins a growing list of similar fracases stirred up by books that touch on the perennial dilemma of mostly upper-middle-class women: return to work or stay at home with the kids. But the truth is that, with rare exceptions (and it's too early to say whether Ms. Bennetts's book may be one of them), these so-called mommy books fail to transform their talk-show and blogosphere buzz into book sales. Talk, it turns out, is much cheaper than the $24.95 cover price.</p>
        <p>''There is a lot of discussion out there about this issue and that's why we're having these books,'' said Nancy Sheppard, vice president of marketing at Viking, which last year published ''Get to Work: A Manifesto for Women of the World'' by Linda R. Hirshman. ''But it's mostly just a discussion.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hirshman, who also argued that women should work outside the home to fulfill their human capacities and avoid economic dependency, appeared on ''Good Morning America'' and ''The Colbert Report'' after the book's release in June, and the blogosphere went wild. But her book sold only 4,000 copies, according to Nielsen BookScan, which accounts for about 70 percent of sales in stores and online.</p>
        <p>Nobody has matched the success of ''The Feminine Mystique,'' Betty Friedan's bombshell that exposed the dreariness of women's domestic lives and has sold about three million copies since it first appeared in 1963. Judith Warner's ''Perfect Madness: Motherhood in the Age of Anxiety'' has been described as a recent success because it sold 37,000 copies in hardcover and hit the New York Times hardcover nonfiction best-seller list for three weeks. (After publication, Ms. Warner became a columnist for TimesSelect, the paid Web site of The New York Times, and a contributor to the Op-Ed page.)</p>
        <p>Recent mommy books that have not lived up to the promise of their publicity include Sylvia Ann Hewlett's ''Creating a Life: Professional Women and the Quest for Children,'' which sold only 11,000 copies in hardcover and 2,000 in paperback, according to BookScan, despite the book's appearance on ''60 Minutes,'' ''The Oprah Winfrey Show'' and the covers of Time and New York magazines.</p>
        <p>And last year Caitlin Flanagan's ''To Hell With All That: Loving and Loathing Our Inner Housewife,'' a collection of essays that said, among other things, that when a woman works, something is lost, generated a media and Internet frenzy, but sold only 9,000 copies in hardcover, according to BookScan.</p>
        <p>What is striking about these limp sales figures is that these books cover a topic that raises fierce passions, as anyone who has spent time on a playground or near an office water cooler knows. But that may get at the heart of why women are not buying books about these subjects.</p>
        <p>''I always felt it was something that women didn't want to look at too closely,'' said Jonathan Burnham, publisher of HarperCollins, who was editor in chief at Talk Miramax Books when Ms. Hewlett's book, which suggested that women who pursued high-powered careers could end up childless, was published five years ago. ''It was a problem that touched very complicated feelings, so while they read a magazine article or watched a segment on 'Oprah,' they didn't want to read a whole book about it because it was such a difficult subject.''</p>
        <p>It also may be that in the absence of any policy changes making the lives of mothers easier, people are more interested in venting their frustrations than in reading another book. Because it's such an unresolved issue, women have a ''desperate need to express their feelings and have a discussion,'' Naomi Wolf, the feminist writer, said. ''You don't really need to buy a book to do that.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Bennetts, who interviewed hundreds of people, including mothers, economists and sociologists, and marshaled a broad array of statistics for ''The Feminine Mistake,'' said she didn't understand why the people who have posted inflammatory comments about the book weren't willing to buy it and find out what she has to say. Some have even taken to personal attacks, with one blogger discrediting Ms. Bennetts because of her weight.</p>
        <p>''Among full-time homemakers, this overdeveloped capacity for denial is often accompanied by a highly combative sense of indignation about views that challenge their own,'' Ms. Bennetts wrote in a HuffingtonPost.com article.</p>
        <p>In an interview Ms. Bennetts, who worked at The New York Times for 10 years before moving to Vanity Fair, where she is now a contributing editor, added that the negative blog posts do not reflect the many positive responses she has personally received. ''We've got this incredible response from working women who are just about euphoric about the fact that somebody has finally written that not only are you not a bad mother, but you are providing for your kids in really crucial ways,'' Ms. Bennetts said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bennetts said she even received a call early one Saturday morning from a stay-at-home mother who told her: '' 'I didn't realize how depressed and unhappy I've been until I read your book.' She said, 'I swear to God, I think you've saved my life.' ''</p>
        <p>At Barnes &amp; Noble, Mike Ferrari, a director of merchandising, said the book is ''selling extremely well.''</p>
        <p>Still, some booksellers say sales have not taken off. ''I really expected more than what we're seeing,'' given the publicity, said Cathy Langer, lead book buyer for the Tattered Cover bookstores in Denver. ''We bought, thinking it would move a little faster, a little bigger.'' So far, according to BookScan, ''The Feminine Mistake,'' which went on sale on April 3, has sold 5,000 copies.</p>
        <p>Ellen Archer, publisher of Voice, a new imprint of Hyperion directed at women that published ''The Feminine Mistake,'' said the book is already in its fourth printing, with 42,000 copies. ''This is a book that's going to build over time through word of mouth,'' Ms. Archer said. ''There are many business books that sell hundreds of thousands of copies that never hit any best-seller lists, but they endure over time and become classics in their category.''</p>
        <p>Some authors say that book sales are not the only goal. Ms. Hirshman, who wrote a shortened version of her book for the online site of American Prospect magazine six months before the book's release, said the book was just a platform for getting her ideas into the ether.</p>
        <p>''I guess the media world has changed in such a way that a book is just a pretext for television appearances and blogging and writing for The New Republic,'' Ms. Hirshman said. ''If the world is divided into people who don't need my message and women who don't want to hear it, it's a miracle I sold any books.''</p>
        <p>But for many busy mothers, it is simply the only-so-many-hours-in-the-day factor. ''I'm home-schooling, I have three children, and my reading time is limited,'' said Heather Cushman-Dowdee of Los Angeles. With many of the mommy books, she said, ''I think I get their points through the articles that they're writing without needing to delve in.'' Declining to buy the books, she said, is a way to ''protect your sanity a little bit.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
