<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Youthful Exuberance Carries Day For Raptors</title>
    <meta content="25nets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/sports/basketball/25nets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070426T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842887"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Toronto Raptors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Toronto Raptors</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bosh, Chris</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jefferson, Richard</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03EED8143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="808" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Youthful Exuberance Carries Day For Raptors</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Youthful Exuberance Carries Day for Raptors</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eligon, John</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO, April 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shortly before 9:25 p.m. Tuesday, red confetti fell from the rafters at the Air Canada Center. An old-school hip-hop tune blared from the loudspeakers, fans waved red flags, and the Toronto Raptors' dancers performed on the court.</p>
        <p>For a team as young as the Raptors, playoff success is measured in increments. So Tuesday night's celebration was as much about the franchise's first playoff victory in five years as it was about the confidence the Raptors could be gaining.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In front of a raucous home crowd, the third-seeded Raptors showed more poise than the veteran-laden Nets when the game was on the line.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shortly before 9:25 p.m. Tuesday, red confetti fell from the rafters at the Air Canada Center. An old-school hip-hop tune blared from the loudspeakers, fans waved red flags, and the Toronto Raptors' dancers performed on the court.</p>
        <p>For a team as young as the Raptors, playoff success is measured in increments. So Tuesday night's celebration was as much about the franchise's first playoff victory in five years as it was about the confidence the Raptors could be gaining.</p>
        <p>With their 89-83 victory against the Nets, the Raptors evened this best-of-seven N.B.A. playoff series at 1-1. Game 3 will be Friday at Continental Arena, with the sixth-seeded Nets still in control of the home-court advantage.</p>
        <p>''I think we definitely turned the corner as a team tonight,'' said Anthony Parker, the Raptors' unheralded swingman, who led all scorers with 26 points and played excellent defense on Vince Carter. ''We gutted it out.''</p>
        <p>The biggest strides made by the precocious Raptors could be seen in the final minutes. Backed by a raucous crowd of more than 20,000, they showed more poise than the veteran-laden Nets when the game was on the line.</p>
        <p>The Raptors' closing kick included scores on 10 of their final 12 possessions. The Nets, meanwhile, came up empty on seven of their final nine possessions.</p>
        <p>Richard Jefferson made a 3-pointer from the top of the key with 46.6 seconds to play, giving the Nets an 83-82 lead. But Raptors guard T. J. Ford, who had 13 points and 6 assists, made two free throws to give his team the lead. On the Nets' next possession, Jefferson missed a shot from the wing. Ford made two more free throws to extend the Raptors' lead to 86-83 with 15.2 seconds left.</p>
        <p>Nets forward Bostjan Nachbar, who scored 17 points, missed an open 3-pointer from the corner with 9.9 seconds left, and the Raptors sealed the outcome with free throws.</p>
        <p>''We weren't too excited over the last game, we're not too down over this one,'' said Jefferson, who scored 13 points and shot 4 of 16 from the field after scoring 28 points in Game 1. ''It's one game. Move on. No need to overanalyze this and that. We've been leading for a majority of this series, just at the end of the game they made the plays.''</p>
        <p>Although he has maintained that the heckling by Toronto fans does not affect him, Carter struggled here for the fourth time this season. In two regular-season games at the Air Canada Center, he averaged 14.5 points and shot 28.1 percent. In the first two games of this series, he averaged 17.5 points and shot 30.2 percent.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday night, Carter, who shot 8 of 24 and scored 19 points, was slow to get back on defense several times and looked out of sorts on offense. With about two and a half minutes to play, Parker stole the ball from Carter at midcourt, and Carter responded by fouling Parker. It was his third foul, and his shoulders were slumped.</p>
        <p>''I'm still aggressive, still confident, still going to play my same game until the end,'' Carter said. ''If I remain aggressive, I'll play my way out of it.''</p>
        <p>Carter, and the rest of the Nets, could be comforted by their home crowd this weekend. The Raptors fans were thunderous and hostile.</p>
        <p>''I don't think I've ever heard a building so excited than what I heard the other day,'' Bryan Colangelo, the Raptors' president, said, referring to Game 1 on Saturday.</p>
        <p>The fans were at their loudest when the Raptors scored the first 10 points of the fourth quarter. The run was capped when power forward Chris Bosh, who scored 25 points, sent Jefferson to the floor with a block. On the other end, Parker made a 3-pointer that gave the Raptors a 68-63 lead with 9 minutes 55 seconds to play.</p>
        <p>Only five Raptors entered the playoffs with postseason experience. Coach Sam Mitchell and his players chalked up their mistakes in Game 1 to jitters.</p>
        <p>Now, they seem to be getting the hang of the postseason.</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>Sam Mitchell, the Raptors' third-year coach, was named coach of the year Tuesday. The award came a little over a year after Mitchell was voted the worst coach in the N.B.A. in a Sports Illustrated survey of 248 players. Mitchell led the Raptors to 47 victories this season, 20 more than they had last season. ''Sam has handled every situation we've come across this season,'' Bryan Colangelo said. ''There was always an approach that got us over the hump.''  Vince Carter, perhaps trying to make amends with the fans in his former city, made several positive comments about Toronto on Tuesday. ''I'm just surprised about how the city looks now,'' he said. ''It's just built up -- hotels, apartments. It's definitely an up-and-coming city.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 26, 2007, Thursday  A sports picture caption yesterday about Toronto's 89-83 playoff victory against the Nets referred imprecisely in some copies to the Raptors' postseason history. It was the team's first playoff victory in five years -- not the first ever. (The first was in 2001, against the Knicks.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 26, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>A sports picture caption yesterday about Toronto's 89-83 playoff victory against the Nets referred imprecisely in some copies to the Raptors' postseason history. It was the team's first playoff victory in five years -- not the first ever. (The first was in 2001, against the Knicks.)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
