<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Connected, And Willing To Tell All</title>
    <meta content="25biog" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/theater/reviews/25biog.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842731"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bellafante, Ginia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Behrman, S N</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccormick, Carolyn</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Biography (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Pearl Theater Co</org>
        <person class="online_producer">McCormick, Carolyn</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Biography (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807EEDC143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="435" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Connected, And Willing To Tell All</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Connected, and Willing to Tell All</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINIA BELLAFANTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bellafante, Ginia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ginia Bellafante reviews revival of S N Behrman play Biography, starring Carolyn McCormick; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>S. N. Behrman came to the attention of theatergoers in the late 1920s and '30s as a writer of high comedies about good people from great stock. Behrman tended to view fortune not as a barrier to tolerance or vulnerability but as an impetus to higher moral calling. He was a conscientious objector in Depression-era class wars. As plays like ''Dinner at Eight'' cast an eye at the snobbish and trifling habits of the well-to-do, Behrman functioned almost as a press agent for the upper classes.</p>
        <p>That satire was not his métier goes a long way in explaining why something like ''Biography,'' his 1932 Broadway hit, currently in revival at the Pearl Theater, simply doesn't hold up, if indeed it ever did.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>S. N. Behrman’s 1932 Broadway hit, currently in revival at the Pearl Theater, simply doesn’t hold up, if indeed it ever did.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>S. N. Behrman came to the attention of theatergoers in the late 1920s and '30s as a writer of high comedies about good people from great stock. Behrman tended to view fortune not as a barrier to tolerance or vulnerability but as an impetus to higher moral calling. He was a conscientious objector in Depression-era class wars. As plays like ''Dinner at Eight'' cast an eye at the snobbish and trifling habits of the well-to-do, Behrman functioned almost as a press agent for the upper classes.</p>
        <p>That satire was not his métier goes a long way in explaining why something like ''Biography,'' his 1932 Broadway hit, currently in revival at the Pearl Theater, simply doesn't hold up, if indeed it ever did.</p>
        <p>The play exists as a two-and-a-half-hour solicitation to fall at the feet of its heroine, Marion Froude (Carolyn McCormick), a Manhattan society painter with Southern belle roots who has orbited every social whirl from Nashville to Minsk. She relishes life, sex, culture. We are to admire her because she is so open, so removed from judgment, so European in her views.</p>
        <p>What Marion embraces most is her own right to free expression. You have met women like her and recoiled -- women who imagine that their very willingness to buck sexual convention and talk and talk gives them an aura of intellectual interest. Marion has 106 opinions, and she is in possession of not a single interesting one.</p>
        <p>But Behrman refuses to see her as a cipher. He wants us to believe instead that men keep falling in love with Marion for the expansive quality of her mind and spirit. The plot revolves around the conflicting ambitions of two suitors: one is a hungry editor who gets her to start writing a memoir, and another, a candidate for the Senate and a former lover, wishes she would stop. What makes ''Biography'' so hoary is that it asks its audience to take seriously the idea of the tell-all -- Marion is basically writing ''I'm With the Band'' -- as a justifiable feminist ambition.</p>
        <p>Ms. McCormick doesn't let the current carry her; she imposes her own electric charge. She has found something to like in Marion, but whatever it is, she refuses to let us know. Her patrician carriage and the stylized formality she brings to her character's dim philosophies only serve to make Marion more insufferable, not less, as if she were a needlepoint pillow that read ''Home, James, and Don't Forget My Pimm's Cup.''</p>
        <p>''Biography'' continues through May 20 at the Pearl Theater, 80 St. Marks Place, East Village; (212) 598-9802, pearltheatre.org.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
