<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Recalling Kirstein, Endearing Monster</title>
    <meta content="25linc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/arts/dance/25linc.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842738"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York City Ballet</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Kirstein, Lincoln</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Balanchine, George</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Evans, Walker</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Nadelman, Elie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E6DB143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1287" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Recalling Kirstein, Endearing Monster</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Recalling Kirstein, Endearing Monster</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunning, Jennifer</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Everyone was Lincoln Kirstein's friend. Or so it has seemed to Nancy Lassalle, a longtime ballet patron and associate of Mr. Kirstein's who has coordinated activities for a wide-ranging centennial celebration that begins tonight with a tribute by the New York City Ballet at the New York State Theater.</p>
        <p>I cannot say I was one. But I came to love this complicated and brilliant ''horrid character,'' as he once called himself, over several years of interviews and time spent together while I was working on ''But First a School,'' a 1985 book on the School of American Ballet, affiliated with City Ballet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York’s dance world celebrates Lincoln Kirstein, a mercurial builder of the School of American Ballet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Everyone was Lincoln Kirstein's friend. Or so it has seemed to Nancy Lassalle, a longtime ballet patron and associate of Mr. Kirstein's who has coordinated activities for a wide-ranging centennial celebration that begins tonight with a tribute by the New York City Ballet at the New York State Theater.</p>
        <p>I cannot say I was one. But I came to love this complicated and brilliant ''horrid character,'' as he once called himself, over several years of interviews and time spent together while I was working on ''But First a School,'' a 1985 book on the School of American Ballet, affiliated with City Ballet.</p>
        <p>Establishing the school was one of Mr. Kirstein's proudest accomplishments. He was formidable yet oddly shy, a manipulator whose scheming was almost always discernible and almost always in the service of his beloved dance. He is probably best known for having founded, with George Balanchine, the City Ballet and its school. But he was a Renaissance man of the arts, though that title sat uneasily on his massive, ungainly shoulders.</p>
        <p>The planned centennial books, seminars and exhibitions reflect that breadth of interest. They range from dance publications and programs to ''Whitney Presents Lincoln Kirstein,'' which opens today at the Whitney Museum of American Art and focuses on the work of Walker Evans, Elie Nadelman and Pavel Tchelitchew, artists Mr. Kirstein championed early on.</p>
        <p>A just-published biography by Martin Duberman, ''The Worlds of Lincoln Kirstein'' (Alfred A. Knopf), chronicles his lesser-known pursuits, like hunting down and rescuing a trove of priceless art hidden by the Nazis in an Austrian mine during World War II. A poet, novelist and playwright of sorts, Mr. Kirstein was also an essayist who wrote about everyone from James Cagney, Marilyn Monroe and Ernest Hemingway to Robert Gould Shaw, the Boston blueblood who commanded a regiment of black soldiers in the Civil War.</p>
        <p>The child of a difficult but privileged background, Mr. Kirstein was born to wealth that was earned by his merchant father, not inherited. A Jew in the Harvard of the late 1920's, he helped found the university's literary magazine and a college art society that inspired the Museum of Modern Art. In love with ballet from the time he saw Anna Pavlova dance when he was 12, Mr. Kirstein became entranced with Balanchine and his work during a youthful visit to Europe in the 1930s. After considerable prodding, well-heeled friends from Harvard agreed to sponsor Balanchine's immigration to America in 1933.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kirstein's accounts of those days are notoriously unreliable. Balanchine's supposed utterance ''but first a school'' was Mr. Kirstein's neatening-up of history, a fabrication he tried to pin on Ms. Lassalle. But it was also Mr. Kirstein who cleaned and polished the studio mirrors in the new school and hovered anxiously on the first day, feeling, he later said, like a child hoping someone would turn up for his party. Years later, he would try to drag the reluctant ''mice,'' as he called the students, to mind-enlarging events like museum visits. And he was one of the first to push for dancers to train for after-career jobs.</p>
        <p>He could be terrifying, then and in later years, partly, perhaps, because of his late-diagnosed bipolar disorder. Friends warned me that he tended to drop people suddenly and without apparent reason. He was the man who, rising in a glittery-eyed rage from his desk at the school one day, so frightened an unexpected newspaper photographer that the man refused to go back, saying it was worse than Vietnam. Mr. Kirstein's books may fill more than one shelf beside my desk, brimming with lessons about dance and writing. But he was also the man whose idea of a dinner party was Chinese takeout dishes all poured into a single tureen.</p>
        <p>Light filtered from a nondescript garden into a ground-floor living room in his house on East 19th Street, where no hour seemed too early to offer large amounts of Scotch on the rocks to wash down ballet gossip and talk about choreography. But the house was otherwise dark. On a tour through a roomful of his collection of cat artifacts, he carefully put in and pulled out the electrical plug of a single lamp, plunging the room into sallow light and then darkness when we left.</p>
        <p>One less pleasant summoning occurred during a nasty battle for control of the school, in 1985. Mr. Kirstein's voice, cracking and agitated on the telephone, asked for an immediate visit. ''Poor man,'' I thought nervously, ''he's losing it.'' Downtown I went, handing him my coat at the door and then walking in on a room of potential foundation supporters for his cause. Far from losing his grip, he was marshalling them to his side, and what better plum to produce than a writer for a major newspaper? Unwilling to participate in that command performance, I was left to grope my way alone and blindly through the impenetrable darkness in search of my coat. Still, how could one not be amused and touched by such a sacred monster?</p>
        <p>Mr. Kirstein, who died in 1996, loved American arts in all their plainness but sensed that it was Balanchine, a fashionable, stateless Russian, whom American ballet needed. And his plans were as revolutionary in some aspects as they were idealistic. In one of his feverish letters written in 1933 to friends who might help sponsor the school -- his pen burning his hand, he wrote -- Mr. Kirstein envisioned a free school with 16 students, 8 black and 8 white.</p>
        <p>There is a charming photograph of him on a 1965 civil rights march in Montgomery, Ala., with a young black boy perched on his shoulders. And it must have been Mr. Kirstein who made sure to include a photograph of a black male student partnering a white woman in the 1954 school catalog, hardly a sure way of increasing enrollment in those days. Mr. Kirstein cautioned Arthur Mitchell, the dancer in that photo, who later became the City Ballet's first and last black star, that he must dance like a soloist to be chosen for the company's corps de ballet. I wonder if the white look of ballet today might have been different if Mr. Kirstein had had his way.</p>
        <p>Lovable and loving, as kind as he could be abruptly and woundingly cruel, possessed of a wicked and sometimes raunchy sense of humor, Mr. Kirstein is as alive for me in his gnarled, fierce imperfection as in any of his extraordinary accomplishments. He is most alive in a brief anecdote in the 1930s diaries he gave me for ''But First a School.''</p>
        <p>He seemed to know everyone -- or everyone who knew anyone -- in Paris and London in those days. A friend invited Mr. Kirstein to accompany him to a garden party at the home of Lady Ottoline Morrell, the famous Bloomsbury hostess, whom Mr. Kirstein describes as ''heavily powdered down to the cleft of her breasts'' and ''a ghoul of a Gainsborough.''</p>
        <p>There, as he wandered presumably among the greats of the day in literature and the arts, glass or cup in hand, Mr. Kirstein recalls, ''caterpillars fell from the trees in clusters and badly bit my neck.'' That was he. Somehow I know that no caterpillars fell into any other collar at that stylish gathering. And no other guest could have been so filled with single-minded, impractical visions as that raw young American, bursting with ideas that would change a world.</p>
        <p>New York City Ballet opens its spring season with ''For Lincoln: Program 1'' tonight at the New York State Theater, Lincoln Center; (212) 870-5570 or nycballet.org. ''Lincoln Kirstein'' opens today at the Whitney Museum of American Art, Madison Avenue at 75th Street, (800) 944-8639.</p>
        <p>DANCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
