<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Appeals Court Allows Net Phone Company to Continue Signing Up New Customers</title>
    <meta content="25vonage" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/technology/25vonage.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842809"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Vonage Holdings Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Verizon Communications</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E2D9143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="574" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Appeals Court Allows Net Phone Company to Continue Signing Up New Customers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Appeals Court Allows Net Phone Company to Continue Signing Up New Customers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURIE J. FLYNN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Flynn, Laurie J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vonage, the Internet phone company embroiled in a bitter patent suit with Verizon, is still in business, at least for now.</p>
        <p>A federal appeals court in Washington extended its stay yesterday of a lower court's injunction that would have barred Vonage from signing up new customers, a move that could have had dire consequences for the ailing company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vonage can sign up new customers as it pursues its appeal of an earlier ruling that it infringed three Verizon patents.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vonage, the Internet phone company embroiled in a bitter patent suit with Verizon, is still in business, at least for now.</p>
        <p>A federal appeals court in Washington extended its stay yesterday of a lower court's injunction that would have barred Vonage from signing up new customers, a move that could have had dire consequences for the ailing company.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the three-judge appeals panel set a June court date to hear the appeal, several months sooner than expected.</p>
        <p>The stay means that Vonage can sign up new customers as well as maintain service to existing ones as it pursues its appeal of a district court's April 6 ruling that it infringed three Verizon patents.</p>
        <p>''We thank the appellate court for its thoughtful consideration of the merits of our case,'' Jeffrey A. Citron, Vonage's chairman and interim chief executive, said in a statement. ''It's business as usual for us.''</p>
        <p>Vonage shares rose 83 cents, nearly 29 percent, to close at $3.72 on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>In the courtroom yesterday, Vonage lawyers argued that the company could face a ''real risk of insolvency'' if the injunction took effect. In a regulatory filing last week, Vonage said that a Verizon victory could cause a decline in its stock price that could lead to the delisting of its stock or possibly even bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>Oral arguments before the appeals court will be June 25, and legal experts say they expect the appeals court to issue a ruling quickly, possibly as early as July.</p>
        <p>''They clearly want to shorten the period the companies are in limbo,'' said Rebecca Arbogast, a lawyer and analyst with Stifel Nicolaus, who attended the hearing.</p>
        <p>While its appeal is pending, Vonage is paying a quarterly royalty of 5.5 percent to Verizon and has posted a $66 million bond. Vonage officials said the company had enough cash to pay the fees and still develop a ''workaround'' that skirts the patented technology in the event it loses its appeal.</p>
        <p>Verizon's deputy general counsel, John Thorne, also applauded the prospect of a quick ruling on the appeal, saying that it would ''accomplish the same thing that a partial stay of the injunction pending a longer appeal would have accomplished, limiting Vonage's infringement during the appeal.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Thorne said the appeal could have taken a year or longer.</p>
        <p>Sharon A. O'Leary, Vonage's chief legal officer, said that the lower court mistakenly defined Verizon's patents too broadly, and predicted that the appeals court's exclusive focus on intellectual property cases would help Vonage. ''We are confident this error will be rectified by the appeals court,'' Ms. O'Leary said.</p>
        <p>Vonage was one of the first entries into the market for low-cost phone service that transmits calls over the Internet rather than over standard phone and wireless networks. Competition has intensified in recent years as cable and telephone companies, including Verizon, have begun offering low-cost service bundles, some including Internet phone service. Last month, Vonage announced that it lost $286 million for the year on revenue of $607 million.</p>
        <p>Vonage, which has 2.3 million customers, went public last spring. But the shares fell nearly 13 percent on the first day of trading, closing at $14.85, and have since lost more than 75 percent of their value.</p>
        <p>Mr. Citron, who founded Vonage seven years ago, returned as chief executive earlier this month after the resignation of Michael A. Snyder, Vonage's chief executive since early last year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
