<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yankees Find Themselves In Last Place They Expected</title>
    <meta content="25yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/sports/baseball/25yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842885"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Devil Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Tampa Bay Devil Rays</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wang, Chien-Ming</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jeter, Derek</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rodriguez, Alex</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EED8143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="902" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yankees Find Themselves In Last Place They Expected</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Yankees Find Themselves in Last Place They Expected</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>ST. PETERSBURG, Fla., April 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mike Myers stood on the pitcher's rubber, aimlessly kicking the dirt with his right foot, over and over. His eyes darted away from the fielders converging on him, away from the manager coming to take the ball. Myers was a portrait of isolation.</p>
        <p>He is on the Yankees' roster to retire left-handed hitters in crucial spots. He was called on to do that with the bases loaded and two outs in the seventh inning Tuesday night, and he failed in spectacular fashion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chien-Ming Wang pitched well in his return, but Alex Rodriguez ended his hitting streak and Derek Jeter left the game after being hit with a pitch as the Yankees fell to last place in the division.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mike Myers stood on the pitcher's rubber, aimlessly kicking the dirt with his right foot, over and over. His eyes darted away from the fielders converging on him, away from the manager coming to take the ball. Myers was a portrait of isolation.</p>
        <p>He is on the Yankees' roster to retire left-handed hitters in crucial spots. He was called on to do that with the bases loaded and two outs in the seventh inning Tuesday night, and he failed in spectacular fashion.</p>
        <p>Myers threw a slider that swept into the bat path of the Tampa Bay Devil Rays' Carl Crawford, who slashed it into the right-field seats for his first career grand slam. The Yankees' lead went with it, and they lost, 6-4, at Tropicana Field. They were swept on a five-game trip.</p>
        <p>''This is where you really test your mettle,'' Manager Joe Torre said. ''This is the tough part of playing our game. This is where you earn your money. We have to turn this thing around and not get wallowed up in self-pity. That's something that's not acceptable. It won't happen, and it hasn't happened.''</p>
        <p>After losing three in a row in Boston, the Yankees dropped two here. It was the first time they had been swept on a trip of at least five games since they lost six in a row to end the 2000 season.</p>
        <p>''It's the absolute worst road trip we could imagine,'' Johnny Damon said. ''No one could imagine being 0-5. We're 0-5 without being outplayed.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees led in every game, but the bullpen, which leads the majors in appearances, had a 7.02 earned run average. The team had looked forward to the return of Chien-Ming Wang, but by the time he took the mound, another injury had dampened the mood.</p>
        <p>Derek Jeter was hit on the left thigh by a pitch from Scott Kazmir in the top of the first. He stayed down for a while, and Torre said he knew that was a bad sign. After staying in to run the bases, Jeter left the game with a bruise.</p>
        <p>Although he said he would play Wednesday, Jeter said there was no way he could have continued on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>''I couldn't move,'' he said. ''It probably wouldn't be a good idea. It wasn't in a good place, but it really is not that big a deal.''</p>
        <p>Alex Rodriguez went 0 for 3 to end his hitting streak at 23 games, dating from last season. He walked in the first inning, then grounded out twice and struck out on three pitches against Shawn Camp.</p>
        <p>''Those pitches were unbelievable,'' Rodriguez said. ''Those balls were dropping about two feet.''</p>
        <p>Hideki Matsui, in his second game off the disabled list, hit a 438-foot homer off Kazmir in the second inning and later drove in a run with a single. His home run gave Wang a lead, and the Yankees liked their chances.</p>
        <p>In half their games before Tuesday, the Yankees' starter had failed to last five innings. Torre did not want to extend Wang much past 80 pitches, but 81 was enough to get him through six and a third innings.</p>
        <p>That stretch included a line drive off Wang's left thigh by Ty Wigginton in the sixth. A trainer rushed to the mound, but Wang threw two warm-up pitches and stayed in.</p>
        <p>Wang strained his right hamstring late in spring training, but he said he felt normal Tuesday. He gave up four runs, nine hits and no walks. Only two runs scored while he was pitching.</p>
        <p>The Yankees led, 3-2, in the seventh, and Wang was still throwing hard, striking out Jonny Gomes with a 93-mile-an-hour pitch to start the bottom of the inning. But a single and a double chased Wang.</p>
        <p>Luis Vizcaíno entered and walked Rocco Baldelli intentionally to load the bases for Brendan Harris, who lined out. Torre then summoned Myers, who had induced a popout from Crawford on Monday and had held him to a .190 career average (4 for 21) with no home runs.</p>
        <p>That changed with one swing at a 2-2 slider. Myers had just thrown the same pitch for a called strike, and he wanted to get Crawford to chase another on the outside edge of the plate. Instead, the ball was over the middle, and then it was over the fence.</p>
        <p>''I go out there expecting to get outs,'' Myers said. ''When it doesn't happen, especially after what we've gone through on this road trip and having Wang come off the D.L. and getting out of our starter exactly what we wanted to get, it's very disappointing.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees scored once in the eighth, but they fell flat against closer Al Reyes in the ninth. The loss dropped their record to 8-11, a half-game behind the Devil Rays. They are in last place in the American League East.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Humberto Sánchez, the pitching prospect acquired for Gary Sheffield who had reconstructive elbow surgery last week, visited the Yankees during batting practice. Sánchez, 23, said he hoped the surgery would end his long struggle with injuries. ''I'm really excited to come back next year with no pain,'' he said.  The Yankees optioned outfielder Kevin Thompson to Class AAA Scranton/Wilkes-Barre to make room for Chien-Ming Wang. Manager Joe Torre said he did not consider sending down Melky Cabrera, who is batting .197 with no extra-base hits.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
