<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Says Fire Dept.'s Exam Is Biased, Opening Way to Suit</title>
    <meta content="25fire" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/nyregion/25fire.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842788"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Civil Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Justice Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E0DA143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="696" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Says Fire Dept.'s Exam Is Biased, Opening Way to Suit</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Says Fire Dept.’s Exam Is Biased, Opening Way to Suit</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN FEUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Feuer, Alan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A federal civil rights investigation has determined that the written entrance exam for the New York City Fire Department discriminates against black and Hispanic applicants, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>As a result, the Department of Justice, which conducted the inquiry, can file a lawsuit against the city over the exam, a possibility that city lawyers have said would be unnecessary and wasteful.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The conclusions by the Justice Department are the latest round of criticism about diversity issues in the New York City Fire Department, which is about 90 percent white and 99 percent male.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A federal civil rights investigation has determined that the written entrance exam for the New York City Fire Department discriminates against black and Hispanic applicants, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>As a result, the Department of Justice, which conducted the inquiry, can file a lawsuit against the city over the exam, a possibility that city lawyers have said would be unnecessary and wasteful.</p>
        <p>While no suit has yet been filed, the conclusions by the Justice Department are the latest round of criticism about diversity issues in the Fire Department, which is about 90 percent white and 99 percent male. In recent years, the department's record has spurred a scathing report by a city civil rights panel and a federal complaint by the Vulcan Society, a group of black firefighters, which prompted the investigation.</p>
        <p>Little was known about the details of the two-year investigation beyond the fact that it focused on entrance exams in 1999 and 2002; the exams are given every three to four years.</p>
        <p>Cynthia Magnuson, a spokeswoman for the Justice Department's civil rights division in Washington, would say only that city officials were notified of the findings on Friday and that the department has 30 days from that date to file a suit.</p>
        <p>In a letter to the civil rights division as well as to federal prosecutors in Brooklyn, Michael A. Cardozo, the city's corporation counsel, said he was deeply disappointed by the findings, especially since the Fire Department had undertaken a $1.4 million recruitment campaign to diversify its ranks, including a revision of the very entrance exam that federal officials found discriminatory.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cardozo, writing of the Justice Department's decision to authorize a suit, said, ''It is simply a waste of federal and local resources and creates the totally unfair perception that the City of New York has failed to take steps to promote diversity in its fire department.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cardozo seemed somewhat shocked in his letter that federal officials would pursue a lawsuit over what he called ''old and no longer applicable tests.'' On Jan. 20, the Fire Department introduced a new written entrance exam, and 40 percent of those who applied to take it were minority candidates, he wrote.</p>
        <p>Since the department started seeking a more diverse applicant pool, there has been an increase in minority candidates. In all, 3,810 black candidates took the test in January, three times the number of blacks who took it in 2002, Mr. Cardozo wrote. He added that 4,041 Hispanics took the test in January, two times the number who took it in 2002.</p>
        <p>''Given that the City of New York has voluntarily, and at substantial expense, undertaken these measures,'' Mr. Cardozo wrote the Justice Department, ''authorization of a lawsuit by your office is clearly ill advised at this time.''</p>
        <p>He concluded, ''I ask that you reconsider the proposed lawsuit and agree to meet privately with representatives of my office to see if this matter can be resolved.''</p>
        <p>Fire Department officials said they had made great strides to diversify in the past few years, particularly during the tenure of the current fire commissioner, Nicholas Scoppetta. Since Mr. Scoppetta took over in 2002, the hiring of minority applicants has tripled, officials said.</p>
        <p>Last year, they said, the department began an advertising campaign to seek a more diverse crop of applicants. It also relaxed its qualifications for taking the entrance exam, deciding that applicants no longer needed 30 college credits to apply. (Either 15 college credits or a high school diploma with six months of work or military experience can now qualify an applicant for the test.)</p>
        <p>John Coombs, president of the Vulcan Society, said that little had changed in the department even under Mr. Scoppetta. He added that the entrance exam was still ''slanted'' against blacks and Hispanics, though he refused to explain precisely why.</p>
        <p>''The test is no true indicator of who will make a good firefighter,'' Mr. Coombs said. ''We shouldn't be testing for anything more than one's ability to be trained.''</p>
        <p>Still, he was hopeful that with federal intervention the department would change.</p>
        <p>''This is an opportunity for the Fire Department to grow and advance like the glorious city of New York.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
