<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trying to Break the Jinx of Chicago's Block 37</title>
    <meta content="25Real" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/realestate/commercial/25Real.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842792"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Square Feet"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Construction and Maintenance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois/Chicago</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Chicago (Ill)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07EEDA143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1318" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trying to Break the Jinx of Chicago's Block 37</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Trying to Break the Jinx of Chicago’s Block 37</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT SHAROFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sharoff, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Joe Mansueto was pondering whether to relocate the main offices of his financial services company to a new office tower under construction in the Loop, the history of the site gave him second thoughts. But Mr. Mansueto, chief executive of Morningstar Inc., which is now several blocks west, finally decided to make the move.</p>
        <p>''I think it's going to be a terrific development when it's done,'' he said. ''But you do wonder if this site is jinxed in some way.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After 20 years of failed development efforts, buildings are finally going up on Chicago’s long-vacant Block 37.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Joe Mansueto was pondering whether to relocate the main offices of his financial services company to a new office tower under construction in the Loop, the history of the site gave him second thoughts. But Mr. Mansueto, chief executive of Morningstar Inc., which is now several blocks west, finally decided to make the move.</p>
        <p>''I think it's going to be a terrific development when it's done,'' he said. ''But you do wonder if this site is jinxed in some way.''</p>
        <p>''This site'' is Block 37, a square block on State Street opposite the large Macy's downtown store that was the most prominent vacant lot in Chicago, if not the country. Over the last 20 years, the failure of the city, as well as of succeeding teams of developers, to build something on the site inspired both a book -- ''Here's the Deal: The Making and Breaking of a Great American City'' by Ross Miller -- and a BBC-produced documentary film.</p>
        <p>One project after another fell through as some of the most high-profile developers in the city tried and failed to line up tenants and financing for a series of mixed-use projects, all of which were announced with great fanfare and then never heard from again.</p>
        <p>Indeed, it is estimated that about $300 million in public and private funds was spent on failed development projects for the site over the years.</p>
        <p>In recent years, the site -- which had been vacant except for a small utility substation since the early 1990s -- was used primarily as a student art gallery and winter skating rink.</p>
        <p>But now two local developers -- Golub &amp; Company and Joseph Freed &amp; Associates -- actually have projects under way there.</p>
        <p>Golub's is a 16-story, 440,000-square-foot office tower that is 80 percent leased to two tenants, Morningstar -- with 236,000 square feet -- and WBBM-TV, the local CBS affiliate. The architect is Ralph Johnson of the locally based Perkins &amp; Will.</p>
        <p>Freed's is a 400,000-square-foot retail mall that is also to include an elaborate new subway station for the Chicago Transit Authority. The designer is Grant Uhlir of Gensler. Freed also has the rights to develop a second phase of the project consisting of 800 residential or hotel units.</p>
        <p>Both projects broke ground in late 2005 and are scheduled to be finished next year. The combined cost is about $750 million. The city has assisted the developments by selling the land for $12.2 million, which is about a third of its market price.</p>
        <p>So what are these developers finally doing right that their many predecessors did not? They are not sure.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, timing is some of it,'' said Lee Golub, executive vice president of Golub. ''The timing was finally right for something to happen here.''</p>
        <p>More important, the city, in the early 2000s, changed its expectations for the site. Instead of holding out for an all-at-once megaproject by a single developer, it decided to take a more ad-hoc approach by appointing a master developer, which was then free to sell off the development rights to different components of the project.</p>
        <p>A key advantage to this approach was that it allowed the different components to be built over time as financing became available.</p>
        <p>''We've gotten more sophisticated about how we structure deals,'' said Lori T. Healey, the city's planning commissioner. ''We gave the master developer the flexibility to structure its own transaction rather than us trying to force a single transaction.''</p>
        <p>But even that strategy has had some problems. The master developer the city selected was the Mills Corporation, the embattled mall developer that was recently sold to the Simon Property Group. Mills broke ground on the project but wound up selling its interests in Block 37 to Freed and Golub after running into financial problems last year.</p>
        <p>''We're kind of taking the baton in the middle of the race and continuing the programs that have been developed over the last two and a half years,'' said Paul Fitzpatrick, managing director of Freed.</p>
        <p>The two developers have managed -- just barely -- to avoid the rancor and strife that have plagued the site. Both recently tussled in court over the rights to develop the residential portion of the project, with Freed emerging as the victor.</p>
        <p>''We were under contract for the residential but things changed,'' said Michael Newman, chief executive of Golub. ''That's O.K. with us. And we're still there. And we all have to support each other.''</p>
        <p>The project -- one of several major projects under way on State Street -- promises to continue the revitalization of the East Loop that began several years ago with the completion of the nearby Millennium Park.</p>
        <p>Mayor Richard M. Daley, in an e-mail message, said that the development ''helps strengthen downtown Chicago. And a strong downtown is what holds a city together; it's the focal point, and it gives the city its identity.''</p>
        <p>The development also promises to consolidate State Street's position as the city's second-largest retail district after North Michigan Avenue.</p>
        <p>''I think Block 37 will be the epicenter of State Street,'' said Bruce Kaplan, president of Northern Realty Group, a major downtown retail leasing firm whose offices overlook the site. ''In the not too distant past, State Street was pretty downmarket. But now you're seeing better merchants like Borders and Urban Outfitters take space there. I think State will continue to notch up.''</p>
        <p>Some see a parallel between Chicago and New York in this regard. ''In New York, you have 57th and Fifth and 34th and Fifth, and both are thriving retail environments,'' said Bill Smith, a developer who is currently finishing a 33-story mixed-use building diagonally across State Street from Block 37 at the corner of Randolph Street. ''Michigan Avenue is our 57th and Fifth. State is more akin to 34th and Fifth. It's going to be nonluxury goods.''</p>
        <p>Block 37 promises to add about 270,000 square feet of new retail space to the street's existing base of about three million square feet.</p>
        <p>The leasing effort for the retail portion of Block 37 is still in its early stages, with only one large tenant -- David Barton Gym -- in place. The gym is to occupy about 40,000 square feet on the top floor of the four-story retail mall.</p>
        <p>''I was attracted to both the project and the location,'' Mr. Barton, the gym owner, said. ''There's a lot of residential development going on downtown as well as an existing market of people who work and shop in the area. This project will provide a critical mass of retail, entertainment and services and will also be a transportation hub.''</p>
        <p>The transportation center is one of the more intriguing aspects of the project. The mall is to be built around a five-story atrium, at the bottom of which will be the new subway station.</p>
        <p>The aim is to connect the two subway lines that currently converge downtown -- the Red Line along State Street and the Blue Line a block to the west along Dearborn Street -- and also provide a central departure point for passengers heading for either of the city's two airports.</p>
        <p>The eventual goal is for passengers to be able to check their baggage downtown and then board an express train that would whisk them to either O'Hare International or Midway Airport in about 20 minutes. Currently, the trip can take up to an hour. That level of service, however, depends on the construction of an extensive -- and as yet unfinanced -- program of track improvements.</p>
        <p>''The ability to connect the airports to the city center in a way that's speedy and reliable is very important,'' said Frank Kruesi, president of the Chicago Transit Authority, who announced last week that he is resigning. ''To have an entire city block available to make that happen is something that happens once in a generation. We have an opportunity to make the connection and to have the basic infrastructure in place to allow it over time to be phased in.''</p>
        <p>Square Feet</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
