<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Auto Rivalries Make Madison Avenue a Frantic Street</title>
    <meta content="25adco" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/business/media/25adco.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842817"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E0D9143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="996" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Auto Rivalries Make Madison Avenue a Frantic Street</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Auto Rivalries Make Madison Avenue a Frantic Street</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STUART ELLIOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE frenetic competition in the automotive industry is taking its toll on the advertising industry.</p>
        <p>In the last six months, the makers of six auto brands decided to re-evaluate the relationships with the agencies that worked for them. Five placed accounts in review, while the sixth changed agencies without any formal reassessment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The frenetic competition in the automotive industry is taking its toll on the advertising industry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE frenetic competition in the automotive industry is taking its toll on the advertising industry.</p>
        <p>In the last six months, the makers of six auto brands decided to re-evaluate the relationships with the agencies that worked for them. Five placed accounts in review, while the sixth changed agencies without any formal reassessment.</p>
        <p>Together, the brands -- Audi, Hyundai, Jeep, Porsche, Saturn and Volvo -- account for $1.25 billion to $1.3 billion in ad spending each year. In 2006, domestic and foreign automakers spent $16.3 billion to advertise in major media, according to TNS Media Intelligence, a division of Taylor Nelson Sofres that tracks ad spending.</p>
        <p>Those huge outlays put auto marketers first among all those tracked by TNS; by comparison, the next largest category, telecommunications, accounted for $9.4 billion in ad spending last year.</p>
        <p>''It's not only the biggest category, but also the most visible and prestigious,'' said Fran Kelly, chief executive at Arnold Worldwide in Boston, part of the Arnold Worldwide Partners division of Havas.</p>
        <p>''Almost everybody is interested in cars,'' said Mr. Kelly, who got back into the category on Monday when Volvo, part of Ford Motor, chose Arnold and the London office of Nitro as its new worldwide creative team. The two agencies will oversee work with spending estimated at $150 million to $200 million a year.</p>
        <p>Even so, to paraphrase the familiar expression from ''Spider-Man,'' with great assignments come great responsibilities.</p>
        <p>''Every one of us is looking for an edge, looking to tell our client's story in a better way, because every automotive client is under pressure to deliver,'' Mr. Kelly said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kelly and his agency are all too familiar with those pressures. In 2005, after a decade of creating campaigns for Volkswagen of America, Arnold lost the account, without a review, to Crispin Porter &amp; Bogusky in Miami, part of MDC Partners.</p>
        <p>The primary reason for the restlessness among auto marketers is the intensifying competition in the selling of cars, sport utilities, minivans and other vehicles.</p>
        <p>If anyone needed another reminder of the relentless rivalries, one came yesterday when data showed that Toyota Motor had passed General Motors in worldwide sales for the first three months of the year. It was the first time that G.M. had fallen behind Toyota in a quarterly global sales tally.</p>
        <p>Every so often, auto account changes come in bursts, like the current one. For example, from February 1991 to March 1993, the relationships of 14 auto brands and their agencies were re-examined, and only one incumbent agency survived a review.</p>
        <p>That exception was Leo Burnett, whose relationship with Oldsmobile was later severed anyway when General Motors phased out the brand in 2004.</p>
        <p>This time, of the five auto assignments placed in review, four have been decided and assignments have changed hands in each case. (Porsche Cars North America is still reviewing its creative and media accounts.)</p>
        <p>''You always want to see the possibilities of what can be,'' said Scott Keogh, chief marketing officer at Audi of America in Auburn Hills, Mich., part of Volkswagen. In December, Audi shifted its creative account, with spending estimated at $100 million a year, to Venables Bell &amp; Partners in San Francisco from McKinney &amp; Silver in Durham, N.C., a Havas agency that had produced Audi campaigns since 1993.</p>
        <p>''We saw a brand that will have significant new products in the market place, a brand ready for takeoff here in America,'' Mr. Keogh said of Audi, adding: ''We just had a record sales year in 2006, breaking over 90,000. But we think absolutely there's more opportunity to grow even more.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Keogh acknowledged the risk of leaving an agency that created Audi's ads for so long and helped sales increase to 90,116 last year, from 77,917 in 2004.</p>
        <p>''From our point of view, we saw the upside,'' Mr. Keogh said, ''and the upside outweighed the risk.'' The first work from Venables Bell for Audi is due soon.</p>
        <p>Another review that ended with a decision to change agencies involved Hyundai Motor America, part of Hyundai Motor of South Korea, which spends about $600 million a year on ads in major media. Last week, Hyundai left the Richards Group in Dallas for Goodby, Silverstein &amp; Partners in San Francisco, part of the Omnicom Group.</p>
        <p>''We do not have a product problem,'' said Joel Ewanick, vice president for marketing at Hyundai Motor America in Fountain Valley, Calif. ''We have a brand problem.''</p>
        <p>''And Goodby gave us an idea that could really take the brand to the next level,'' he added. Mr. Ewanick declined to reveal details of the new approach until the work from Goodby, Silverstein begins to run.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ewanick described a change in consumer habits that is contributing to the turnover in auto accounts.</p>
        <p>''Last year, over 80 percent of people who bought cars in America said they did some kind of online research,'' he said, adding that while Hyundai ''jumped in early'' into Internet marketing, ''we kind of reached a plateau and stayed where we were, frankly not using it to its full potential.''</p>
        <p>So an important element of the creative review involved seeking an agency with digital expertise. Goodby, Silverstein is among agencies steeped in traditional forms of marketing that are striving to bolster their abilities to handle tasks like search marketing, mobile marketing and online advertising.</p>
        <p>Goodby, Silverstein is also an example of how the traffic in auto accounts can sometimes resemble the congestion on a California freeway.</p>
        <p>Goodby, Silverstein was the creative agency for the Saturn division of General Motors until late January, when the assignment left without a review for the Los Angeles office of Deutsch, part of the Interpublic Group of Companies.</p>
        <p>After losing Saturn, Goodby, Silverstein joined the review for the Volvo creative assignment, teaming up with 180, an agency that is majority-owned by Omnicom.</p>
        <p>But when Hyundai started its creative review, Goodby, Silverstein decided to withdraw from pursuing Volvo to go after the South Korean brand -- a smart move, in retrospect.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
