<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Smoothing the Rough Edges, Renney Is Rangers' Cool Hand</title>
    <meta content="25rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/sports/hockey/25rangers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842879"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Buffalo Sabres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Renney, Tom</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00EFD8143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1163" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Smoothing the Rough Edges, Renney Is Rangers' Cool Hand</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Renney, Rangers’ Cool Hand, Is Smoothing the Rough Edges</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinser, Lynn</byline>
      <dateline>GREENBURGH, N.Y., April 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tom Renney's steady, silver-eyed gaze is now matched with a head of silver hair and neither ever seems to be in disarray. Renney also wears perfectly pressed shirts and crisp ties, and they, too, look just as pressed and crisp after a Rangers game as they did before the contest began.</p>
        <p>For the past two seasons, the 52-year-old Renney has tackled the job of coaching the Rangers with earnestness, dogged preparation and a great deal of composure. Wednesday night, when he leads the Rangers into Game 1 of the second round of the playoffs against Buffalo, he will, by all outward appearances, look like a man about to coach a regular-season game in November.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the past two seasons, Tom Renney has tackled the job of coaching the Rangers with earnestness, dogged preparation and a great deal of composure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tom Renney's steady, silver-eyed gaze is now matched with a head of silver hair and neither ever seems to be in disarray. Renney also wears perfectly pressed shirts and crisp ties, and they, too, look just as pressed and crisp after a Rangers game as they did before the contest began.</p>
        <p>For the past two seasons, the 52-year-old Renney has tackled the job of coaching the Rangers with earnestness, dogged preparation and a great deal of composure. Wednesday night, when he leads the Rangers into Game 1 of the second round of the playoffs against Buffalo, he will, by all outward appearances, look like a man about to coach a regular-season game in November.</p>
        <p>''It's just the kind of guy he is,'' said Rangers center Blair Betts. ''He's a fairly composed person. He doesn't let emotion get the better of him. When things weren't going well, he didn't panic. He didn't start getting down on us. He just stayed positive. He's just a good guy.''</p>
        <p>With a metaphor for every occasion and a disarming sense of honesty, Renney has been the Rangers' steadying influence through two full seasons as head coach, a span that has had enough ups and downs to qualify as an amusement-park ride. In recent months, the Rangers got off the ground and steamrolled into the playoffs. But when given the chance to take credit for the comeback, Renney credited his players. ''It really is the players' show,'' he said. ''It's all about them.''</p>
        <p>For Renney to make the Rangers all about the players, he has had to step back from a set of players with strong personalities, including his two star veterans, Jaromir Jagr and Brendan Shanahan.</p>
        <p>''What we've really achieved here is work on the culture of our group, that it's a team game and it doesn't fall on the shoulders of one guy,'' Renney said. ''We are in this together and it is about supporting each other and defending each other and showing a common front when things are bad.''</p>
        <p>Shanahan said: ''He coaches when you need to coach, but he's got a great knack for knowing when to back off and let the players be players. There are a lot of guys that want to claim that they've reinvented the wheel. He's the opposite. He actually doesn't take credit when he deserves it.''</p>
        <p>When Renney took over the Rangers, the job came with built-in challenges. Foremost among them was the team's futility over much of the previous decade.</p>
        <p>For Renney, it was a second chance to be an N.H.L. coach. His first stint ended badly in Vancouver, where he was fired in 1997 after the Canucks started the season 3-13-2.</p>
        <p>Even worse for Renney was the fact that it was Vancouver's star players -- in particular, Mark Messier and Pavel Bure -- who turned on him, complaining that his rules were too strict and his manner too overbearing. The Canucks railed against Renney when he banned beer on postgame flights.</p>
        <p>In retrospect, it seems clear that Renney's background in coaching young players, particularly in the Western Hockey League and with Team Canada, had not translated well in Vancouver. While Renney said he had learned a lot from his struggles in Vancouver, his approach to coaching essentially remains the same. With the Rangers, it has paid dividends.</p>
        <p>''The whole thing is, you have to respect the players,'' Jagr said. ''If you want to get respect, you have to give respect and that's what he does. He respects the players who are playing for him and they respect him. That's the bottom line. That's the starting point.</p>
        <p>''Even if you lose, he's never going to turn against you,'' Jagr added. ''That's the way he is. He's a nice guy.''</p>
        <p>Renney has navigated what could have been a complicated relationship with Jagr, which has included ironing out the identity of Jagr's linemates and resolving the issue of Jagr's participation in shootouts. (Jagr avoided them for much of this season.) For the most part, Renney has used gentle persuasion with Jagr, pushing him privately while never criticizing him publicly -- and eventually getting him back into the shootout lineup.</p>
        <p>''As a coach, if you have a big ego, you're going to find yourself in trouble sooner or later because you're going to wind up clashing with your best players,'' the Rangers assistant Perry Pearn said. ''I think again one of Tom's great strengths is that it's never an issue with how he deals with things.''</p>
        <p>When the Rangers signed Shanahan before this season, they added a player with strong opinions and a Hall of Fame résumé spanning 19 seasons. Renney made sure Shanahan fit right in, and said he takes time to confer with Shanahan and Jagr on many major decisions.</p>
        <p>''They made it easy,'' Renney said of the two players, who have five Stanley Cups between them to Renney's none. ''They're two good men who are very proud about where they're playing and with whom.</p>
        <p>''I respect each of their opinions,'' he added. ''I think they have that feeling for me.''</p>
        <p>Still, it is the development of the Rangers' younger players that probably gives Renney the most job satisfaction. He is, at heart, a developmental coach. He weaved the rookies Ryan Callahan and Dan Girardi into the lineup, and he stuck with his belief in players like Marcel Hossa, Thomas Pock and Colton Orr, a stubbornness that paid off when they began to fill major roles.</p>
        <p>His pushing was all behind the scenes, often in small gestures like quickly putting a young player back out on the ice after he has made a mistake.</p>
        <p>''Tom and his people skills become so important because if you look at our team, a guy like Brendan Shanahan and a guy like Jaromir Jagr, they're not interested in whether Dan Girardi is going to develop,'' Pearn said. ''They want to win now. They're older, experienced players. They'd like a crack at the Stanley Cup one more time.''</p>
        <p>There was a time this season when that seemed far-fetched. The Rangers had sunk as low as 12th place in the Eastern Conference as recently as February. Injuries were piling up. The Rangers were losing home games to teams going nowhere. It was the testing ground for Renney's resolve.</p>
        <p>''Some coaches would go nuts,'' forward Martin Straka said. ''I was on teams when you are losing and you think: 'Oh my God, what are we going to do today? It's going to be 50 meetings and the coach is going to go crazy and the guys don't want to even come to the rink.' It never happened to me here.</p>
        <p>''That's Tom. He's done an unbelievable job. That's the biggest reason, too, that we have gone so far. We want to play. We want to be together.''</p>
        <p>The man standing behind them, with the unwavering silver-eyed gaze, would like to keep them together a bit longer as the playoffs continue and the Stanley Cup draws closer.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
