<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Must Be Italy, There's Straw on the Bottles</title>
    <meta content="25rest" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/dining/reviews/25rest.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842737"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E6DB143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1279" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Must Be Italy, There's Straw on the Bottles</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Must Be Italy, There’s Straw on the Bottles</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank Bruni</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT this point in his justly storied career, Keith McNally could probably open a lemonade stand on a runway at La Guardia and have normally proud New Yorkers groveling for tarmac. So the crowds at his new restaurant, Morandi, didn't throw me.</p>
        <p>The chaos did, and it was underscored by the desperate way a host implored two companions and me to squeeze even tighter against the mass of bodies at the bar so that servers hustling from the kitchen could get by. We were blocking the ''food highway,'' he told us, and as we subsequently watched the couriers of tagliatelle alla bolognese barrel down it, we realized that we had nearly become roadkill.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Having played with French conceits at Balthazar and Pastis, the restaurateur Keith McNally turns to Italian ones at Morandi, his new restaurant in the West Village.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT this point in his justly storied career, Keith McNally could probably open a lemonade stand on a runway at La Guardia and have normally proud New Yorkers groveling for tarmac. So the crowds at his new restaurant, Morandi, didn't throw me.</p>
        <p>The chaos did, and it was underscored by the desperate way a host implored two companions and me to squeeze even tighter against the mass of bodies at the bar so that servers hustling from the kitchen could get by. We were blocking the ''food highway,'' he told us, and as we subsequently watched the couriers of tagliatelle alla bolognese barrel down it, we realized that we had nearly become roadkill.</p>
        <p>I suppose that's a danger at many of Mr. McNally's breathlessly thronged productions: Balthazar, Pastis, Schiller's Liquor Bar. But those restaurants present clever, dashing stage sets that find some poetry in the commotion.</p>
        <p>Morandi -- with its low ceiling, inconveniently situated columns and hokey visual motifs -- presents a riddle: how did Mr. McNally and his collaborators come to deem this an alluring destination? He's miscalculated with this restaurant, which doesn't have enough atmospheric magic to distract you from the insane decibel level, absence of elbowroom and uncomfortable chairs.</p>
        <p>Teaming up with the chef Jody Williams, who cooked at Il Buco, Giorgione and Gusto, Mr. McNally is making his first foray into Italian cuisine, and he plays with Italian conceits the way he did with French ones at Balthazar.</p>
        <p>But while Balthazar's evocation of a brasserie bespoke an adoration of France, Morandi's incarnation of a trattoria suggests something more like amusement with Italy. The restaurant strikes an odd tone, starting with the recorded voice on the phone line, as broadly accented as that of Father Guido Sarducci on an old episode of ''Saturday Night Live,'' and extending to row upon row of straw-bottomed Chianti bottles lining the walls. Is this tribute or burlesque?</p>
        <p>Against the hackneyed backdrop Ms. Williams's menu -- including fritto misto, vitello tonnato, bucatini cacio e pepe and a gargantuan veal chop smothered in prosciutto and fontina -- sometimes plays less like a loving repertory of classics than a failure of imagination and nerve. Most food-savvy New Yorkers have repeatedly encountered dishes like these in a setting of cheeky rusticity like this, and that compels the Morandi kitchen to perform at a higher, more consistent level than it does.</p>
        <p>Even so, the food has been getting a worse rap than it deserves. Ms. Williams is an earnest, talented chef, and there's sufficient evidence of that across the menu's discrete categories for fried versus other starters; for fresh versus dried pasta; for meat versus fish.</p>
        <p>Begin with the fried stuffed green olives, which pack in pork sausage, ground pork, pecorino and egg. I could nibble on these all night long. But then I'd miss the grilled octopus, and I wouldn't want to.</p>
        <p>New York has turned some sort of octopus corner. Not only is octopus challenging squid as the multi-tentacled cephalopod of choice, it's being cooked more expertly than it once was. At Morandi it's crisped on a gas grill and paired with black olives and -- the inspired, just-right touch -- celery.</p>
        <p>Ms. Williams did this dish or versions of it before Morandi, and the same goes for another great appetizer, a bright-tasting salad of fava beans, escarole and pecorino that's given a lively dose of mint.</p>
        <p>My favorite dishes among pasta and its kin were the troffiete al pesto -- nicely doughy squiggles entwined with crunchy green beans -- and risotto sotto bosco, whose name translates literally as ''under forest'' and flags the presence of porcini, blueberries and blackberries in a blend of rice, butter, Parmesan and herbs. The interplay of earthy, fruity and salty effects was fantastic.</p>
        <p>The sage butter on top of spinach and ricotta ravioli and the thyme butter on top of porcini ravioli had been applied with a generous hand, making each dish feel like a bit of a cheat -- but a happy cheat.</p>
        <p>Morandi doesn't take many chances with entrees, either. There's grilled chicken, grilled hanger steak and grilled branzino, none seasoned in a revelatory way. The roasted veal chop stands out, courtesy of that decadent hood and a juicy core. Then again, it should. At $45, it's far and away the most expensive item on a menu that, like those at Mr. McNally's other restaurants, admirably gives diners strategies for keeping the check under control.</p>
        <p>But the most impressive entree also reveals how erratic Morandi can be. It's salt cod cooked in milk, festooned with raisins and placed on polenta. The notes of saltiness and sweetness integrate beautifully, but while the cod was moist and flaky when I first tried the dish, it was repulsively tough the second time around. The polenta had taken its own nose dive, plummeting from creamy to runny.</p>
        <p>The kitchen's miscues and misjudgments are frequent: a little too much lemon on the grilled chicken; a lot too much lemon in an egg and cheese sauce over lackluster lamb chops; a deficit of pepper in the cacio e pepe (pecorino and black pepper). Many savory dishes, like the décor, are disconcertingly off key.</p>
        <p>Morandi does a steadier job with desserts, most of them likable but none really lovable. Once again a greatest-hits approach prevails: tartufo, zuppa inglese, gelato, granita. I had particular luck with tarts, including one with lemon, almond and ricotta.</p>
        <p>The kindly priced wine list explores all of Italy, not only in the selection of bottles but also in the wines available by the glass, half carafe and carafe. There are exactly 20 of these, one from each region of Italy.</p>
        <p>A catchy approach? Sure. But a gimmicky one, too, reflecting this restaurant's treatment of Italy as theme park -- as what the British writer John Mortimer once called Chiantishire.</p>
        <p>Morandi's overworked Chianti bottles and its canopy of brick arches -- no matter how old the brick -- aren't whimsical; they're just clichéd. Unlike Balthazar and Pastis, which Mr. McNally cunningly sculptured to look old before their time, Morandi can simply feel tired before its time, and not quite worth the struggle to get in and stay upright in the scrum.</p>
        <p>Morandi  * [Rating: One Star]  211 Waverly Place (Seventh Avenue South), Greenwich Village; (212) 627-7575.</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Brick arches and straw-bottomed Chianti bottles strive to evoke a rustic trattoria, named after an Italian painter.  SOUND LEVEL -- A McNally-esque roar.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Fried stuffed olives; fava bean salad; bruschetta with ricotta; grilled octopus; troffiete al pesto; porcini ravioli; risotto sotto bosco; veal chop; calf's liver; cuttlefish stew; budino; ricotta tart.  WINE LIST -- Representative of all 20 regions of Italy, with many bottles under $50 and many wines by the glass, half carafe and carafe.  PRICE RANGE -- Dinner appetizers, $7 to $18. Pasta dishes and entrees, $15 to $45. Desserts, $6 to $9. Lunch appetizers, salads and sandwiches, $7 to $16. Pasta dishes and entrees, $14 to $26. Brunch dishes, $5 to $24.  HOURS -- Lunch noon to 3 p.m. Monday through Friday, and brunch 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Saturday and Sunday. Dinner 5:30 p.m. to midnight seven days a week. Breakfast to be added in May.  RESERVATIONS -- Accepted up to two weeks in advance, increasing to a month in May.  CREDIT CARDS -- All major cards.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Entrance and entire restaurant on street level; accessible restroom.  WHAT THE STARS MEAN -- Ratings range from zero to four stars and reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.  PAST REVIEWS from The Times, with additional capsule reviews by Times critics: nytimes.com/dining</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
