<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Room to Grow, or to Sublet, in Manhattan</title>
    <meta content="25space" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/realestate/commercial/25space.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842794"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SQUARE FEET"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7D9143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1063" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Room to Grow, or to Sublet, in Manhattan</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Room to Grow, or to Sublet, in Manhattan</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By J. ALEX TARQUINIO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tarquinio, J Alex</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An unusual land rush is stirring in Midtown Manhattan: many companies are signing long-term leases for much more office space than they need.</p>
        <p>Brokers refer to this as ''land banking'' space. It is a term that has not been heard much around Midtown in years. But land banking has come back into vogue in the last six months, said Mitchell Konsker, an executive vice president at Cushman &amp; Wakefield. Mr. Konsker said this made him a bit nervous, because ''after the last time I saw this, in 2000 and 2001, there was a bust in the market.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An unusual land rush is stirring in Midtown Manhattan as companies sign long-term leases for much more office space than they need.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An unusual land rush is stirring in Midtown Manhattan: many companies are signing long-term leases for much more office space than they need.</p>
        <p>Brokers refer to this as ''land banking'' space. It is a term that has not been heard much around Midtown in years. But land banking has come back into vogue in the last six months, said Mitchell Konsker, an executive vice president at Cushman &amp; Wakefield. Mr. Konsker said this made him a bit nervous, because ''after the last time I saw this, in 2000 and 2001, there was a bust in the market.''</p>
        <p>Back then, Internet start-ups and investment banks did most of the land banking in a narrow swath of Lower Manhattan. Now the trend has hit Midtown, where the office market is stretched especially thin. Mr. Konsker said this was one reason that the trend might have more staying power.</p>
        <p>The vacancy rate in Midtown fell to 5.3 percent in the first quarter of 2007, from 7.8 percent a year earlier, according to Cushman &amp; Wakefield. What's more, few new office buildings are planned for Midtown in the next five years, so some executives are worried about becoming ''landlocked'' in their buildings.</p>
        <p>They are also scrambling to lock in rents at today's prices. Average rents for Class A offices, the highest quality space, in Midtown Manhattan hit $70 a square foot in the first quarter, but Cushman &amp; Wakefield forecasts that rents could rise to $75 or $80 a square foot by the end of the year.</p>
        <p>Joyce Geiger, the senior managing director in charge of client consulting services at GVA Williams, said she thought that companies were being much smarter than during the dot-com boom, when workers at some Internet companies were rattling around huge empty offices. ''They were so cocky,'' Ms. Geiger said. ''They had so much money, and they thought they would grow so fast.''</p>
        <p>Today, many companies are planning to sublet space that they do not need right away. That should not be difficult to do, since there is a razor-thin 1.1 percent vacancy rate in the Midtown sublet market, according to Cushman. By comparison, five years ago the sublease vacancy rate was 3.2 percent and the overall vacancy rate in the area was 9.3 percent.</p>
        <p>Indeed, a growing number of sublets are being offered when the ink is barely dry on the original lease. For example, D. E. Shaw, a hedge fund, leased 112,000 square feet at 1166 Avenue of the Americas, between 45th and 46th Streets, in September. It is now offering more than 37,000 square feet for sublet.</p>
        <p>Legg Mason, a mutual fund company based in Baltimore, signed a lease in August for 193,000 square feet in The New York Times Building, which is nearing completion at 620 Eighth Avenue, between 40th and 41st Streets. Legg Mason is marketing 63,000 square feet of its space on two floors to potential subtenants.</p>
        <p>And American Capital Strategies, a private equity firm based in Bethesda, Md., signed a lease this winter for the 17th, 18th and 19th floors of 505 Fifth Avenue, at 42nd Street. American Capital already had the top five floors of this new 28-story building, which is diagonally opposite the New York Public Library. The company plans to sublet all of the space on the 28th floor and the 17th floor, totaling about 18,000 square feet.</p>
        <p>Smaller financial firms like hedge funds and venture capitalists have been some of the biggest winners as the stock market has recently risen to new highs. Some of these firms are applying their riches to office space.</p>
        <p>For example, Cyrus Capital Partners, a hedge fund, leased 23,000 square feet in the top two floors of 399 Park Avenue, at 54th Street, in 2006. Initially, the partners had planned to take only 13,000 square feet on the 39th floor, but then their broker told them about 10,000 square feet available on the floor directly beneath.</p>
        <p>Robert A. Nisi, the chief operating officer of Cyrus Capital Partners, said the firm took the extra space because it would be easy to install a staircase to connect the two floors if it ever needed more space. The partners also locked in rents that are already below today's market rates.</p>
        <p>Although the firm has been approached many times about subletting its space on the 38th floor, Mr. Nisi said it would not be worth the distraction of being a landlord.</p>
        <p>Of course, some hedge funds choose not to leave office space vacant, according to Benjamin L. Friedland, a senior vice president at CB Richard Ellis, who represented Cyrus Capital Partners on its lease. Mr. Friedland said some of his other hedge fund clients were using space they were warehousing to create start-up hedge funds, in which they may also take a financial interest.</p>
        <p>New York City's law firms have traditionally tended to keep all of their lawyers in one office, rather than scattered throughout a building. Now, with their practices booming, many of them are land banking, too.</p>
        <p>Donald C. Ross, the managing partner of the New York law offices of Osler, Hoskin &amp; Harcourt, a large Toronto law firm, said he expected the firm's relatively new American practice to grow rapidly. So Mr. Ross signed a 15-year lease last year for 66,000 square feet on the 36th and 37th floors of The New York Times Building.</p>
        <p>But when Osler moves in this June, it will occupy only about half of that space. Ideally, Mr. Ross said, he would like to break the rest of it up into three offices and sublet them to smaller law firms, with subleases expiring sequentially in two to five years.</p>
        <p>Even some real estate brokerage firms are getting into the act. PBS Real Estate signed a five-year lease this month for the office next to its own on the 18th floor of the Helmsley Building at 230 Park Avenue, at 45th Street, right above Grand Central Terminal. When the company knocks down the walls between the two offices, it will add 3,000 square feet to the existing 6,500-square-foot office.</p>
        <p>But Robert B. Emden, a principal at PBS Real Estate, said the firm would need only a small piece of that right away. ''We are warehousing the rest for future growth,'' said Mr. Emden, who added that he often recommended this to his clients. ''We are practicing what we preach.''</p>
        <p>SQUARE FEET</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
