<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sales of Previously Owned Homes Plunge to 1989 Level</title>
    <meta content="25econ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/business/25econ.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070427T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842814"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Subprime Lending</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE1D9143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="709" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sales of Previously Owned Homes Plunge to 1989 Level</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Drop in Sales of Previously Owned Homes Is Steepest Since 1989</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEREMY W. PETERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Peters, Jeremy W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A rebound in residential real estate remains elusive.</p>
        <p>After two months of stronger sales and some tentative suggestions that the housing market was stabilizing, sales last month of previously owned homes took their biggest tumble in nearly two decades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Winter weather and newly tightened lending standards probably sped the 8.4 percent drop in March, economists said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A rebound in residential real estate remains elusive.</p>
        <p>After two months of stronger sales and some tentative suggestions that the housing market was stabilizing, sales last month of previously owned homes took their biggest tumble in nearly two decades.</p>
        <p>The National Association of Realtors said yesterday that sales of existing homes, which account for the vast majority of all home sales, fell 8.4 percent in March. That was the steepest monthly decline since January 1989.</p>
        <p>The combination of winter weather and newly tightened lending standards for people with weak credit probably sped the drop, economists said.</p>
        <p>The fresh data on home sales came as two other economic reports showed further deterioration in home prices in major metropolitan areas and a growing sense of consumer unease.</p>
        <p>At first, the news deflated stock prices on Wall Street. Investors quickly shook off their worries and pushed the Dow Jones industrial average high enough to come within 11 points of 13,000 -- a high point it has never crossed. But at the close of the trading day stocks finished mixed, with the Dow closing up 34.54 points, to 12,953.94.</p>
        <p>The Realtors association's report reflected a housing market that became increasingly unfriendly to those looking to sell their homes last month. While the number of unsold existing homes for sale fell 1.6 percent in March, to 3,745,000, it took longer to sell a home. There was a 7.3-month supply of unsold properties last month, up from a 6.8-month supply in February.</p>
        <p>The backlog grew even as prices dropped. The median price of an existing single-family home decreased 0.9 percent last month, to $215,300, compared with a year earlier. Total sales compared with a year earlier were off 11.3 percent.</p>
        <p>''Because demand is weak, and because inventories remain high, there's little ability for prices to rise,'' said Celia Chen, director of housing economics at Moody's economy.com. Ms. Chen speculated that the overall inventory number may have declined last month because sellers were pulling their homes off the market in frustration.</p>
        <p>''The overall trend in housing is still weak,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The sharp fall in existing home sales last month was a sign that the increases earlier this year were not in line with the market's underlying path.</p>
        <p>''The January, February figures were certainly higher than many analysts had anticipated, and that was due to the sort of artificial elevation from the warm weather,'' said Lawrence Yun, senior economist with the Realtors association. ''Now it's payback time in March.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Yun said that as the weather becomes warmer and seasonal distortions become less of a factor, it will be easier to determine where the market is headed. ''That's when we have the weather influences out of the way, and we'll see the market stabilize, recover or continue to slump,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Regionally, housing market conditions were most depressed in the Midwest, where sales fell 10.9 percent in March. Sales in the South declined 6.2 percent, while they fell 8.2 percent in the Northeast and 9.1 percent in the West.</p>
        <p>Such widespread sales declines suggested that the problems plaguing subprime mortgage lenders -- those who loan to people with weak credit -- are playing a role, said Patrick Newport, an economist with Global Insight. ''The weather really doesn't usually affect existing home sales that much.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Yun said that some would-be buyers with borderline credit are having difficulty obtaining loans. At the same time, mortgage lenders have faced a tight squeeze as more and more subprime borrowers have defaulted on their loans.</p>
        <p>One bright spot in the housing data was sales of condominiums. In contrast to overall home prices and sales -- which both declined -- sales of condos and co-op apartments were unchanged last month as prices rose 3.2 percent, to $228,200, compared with a year earlier.</p>
        <p>But prices on average remained in a slump. The Realtors association report showed the eighth straight monthly price decline. A separate report from Standard and Poor's, which surveyed home prices in 20 major metropolitan areas, found that prices fell in 17 of those cities in February.</p>
        <p>The only cities where prices rose last month were Dallas, Portland, Ore., and Seattle.</p>
        <p>And the Conference Board said yesterday that its measure of consumer confidence for April fell for the second straight month.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 27, 2007, Friday  A headline in Business Day on Wednesday about the drop in sales of existing homes in March to 6.12 million units, on a seasonally adjusted annual basis, misstated the historical context of those sales. While the drop of 8.4 percent was indeed the steepest monthly decline since January 1989, when sales fell by 12.6 percent; the sales did not fall to the 1989 level. (The sales rate for 1989 was 3.29 million units.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 27, 2007, Friday</p>
        <p>A headline in Business Day on Wednesday about the drop in sales of existing homes in March to 6.12 million units, on a seasonally adjusted annual basis, misstated the historical context of those sales. While the drop of 8.4 percent was indeed the steepest monthly decline since January 1989, when sales fell by 12.6 percent; the sales did not fall to the 1989 level. (The sales rate for 1989 was 3.29 million units.)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
