<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Philharmonic To Add A Position At the Top</title>
    <meta content="25phil" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/arts/music/25phil.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842740"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Music"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Philharmonic</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Maazel, Lorin</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E6DB143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="995" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Philharmonic To Add A Position At the Top</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Philharmonic to Add a Position at the Top</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL J. WAKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wakin, Daniel J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York Philharmonic, hunting for a successor to its music director, Lorin Maazel, has decided to divide up its leadership by adding the new position of principal conductor, orchestra officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>In a meeting with the musicians, the Philharmonic's president, Zarin Mehta, said the orchestra would create other new positions, including composer in residence; director for a mini-festival; and artist in residence, probably a soloist.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York Philharmonic, hunting for a successor to its music director, Lorin Maazel, has decided to divide up its leadership by adding the new position of principal conductor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New York Philharmonic, hunting for a successor to its music director, Lorin Maazel, has decided to divide up its leadership by adding the new position of principal conductor, orchestra officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>In a meeting with the musicians, the Philharmonic's president, Zarin Mehta, said the orchestra would create other new positions, including composer in residence; director for a mini-festival; and artist in residence, probably a soloist.</p>
        <p>''An organization like ours needs somebody who's there more than a regular musical director,'' Mr. Mehta said in an interview later. ''We just thought that more than one person would be a better idea from the musical standpoint.''</p>
        <p>Most American orchestras have music directors, a sole authority who controls hiring and firing, helps with fund-raising, programs concerts, oversees the hiring of guest conductors and soloists and serves as the public face of the institution. The Philharmonic has generally operated that way for its 165 years.</p>
        <p>Under Mr. Mehta's plan, a music director would serve the usual 12 to 14 weeks on the podium out of a 44-week season, but the principal conductor would come in for another 8 to 10 weeks to increase the presence of an artistic leader, adding a collaborative voice and, potentially, excitement. Mr. Mehta said he knew of no parallel setups, although principal guest conductors are common.</p>
        <p>The music director would control hiring and have ultimate say over musical matters, with input from the principal conductor, who would also help out with fund-raising and community involvement and lead tours: a much greater role than that of a principal guest. The music director would be hired first, Mr. Mehta said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mehta said no conductors had been approached about the jobs, although several had been consulted for opinions on the system. He ruled out Daniel Barenboim and Riccardo Muti for either job, saying neither were interested. Mr. Muti, who turned down the music director's post in 2000, has been a particular favorite of the musicians, who have also expressed support for Mr. Barenboim.</p>
        <p>Robert Rinehart, a violist and chairman of the musicians' artistic committee, called the new model ''an exciting prospect.''</p>
        <p>A composer in residence would effectively serve as the contemporary-music guru, a potential answer to music critics who chide the Philharmonic for being hidebound in programming. The composer in residence would help run a proposed new-music ensemble within the orchestra; the last composer in residence was David Del Tredici, in 1990.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mehta also said it was no longer taking into account the closing of its home, Avery Fisher Hall, for renovations in the music director search. Money must still be raised, and no new concert hall has presented itself, with the Seventh Regiment Armory now out of contention because of size limitations, he said.</p>
        <p>With Mr. Maazel's time as music director trickling away -- his term ends after two more seasons, the day after tomorrow in the orchestra world -- the Philharmonic has been under pressure to figure out a succession. It is competing with the Chicago Symphony and the Philadelphia orchestra, also looking for music directors.</p>
        <p>Finding the ideal candidate in the traditional mold is becoming more and more like seeking the holy grail. He or she should be a talented, highly knowledgeable musician who can earn the respect of musicians, draw audiences through charisma, help raise money, foster young soloists and composers, keep the orchestra musically healthy, connect with the community and come up with imaginative, interesting programs.</p>
        <p>Each constituency has its own priorities: management wants to fill seats, the fund-raisers want handshake charm, and the critics want innovation and freshness. The players, who have a strong say in the choice, above all want musical depth -- knowledge, interpretive skills, insight into the composer, good ears -- and conducting technique to convey ideas and a clear beat.</p>
        <p>''You have to have a conductor who is at least as good as the members of the orchestra,'' said Evangeline Benedetti, a veteran cellist, ''people like Erich Leinsdorf, who knew by memory every note of the 'Ring' when he was 25.''</p>
        <p>Many of the players have a sense that they deserve a conductor with stature commensurate to the orchestra's, but some are also open to the untested, provided he or she has the musical goods. ''I think I might take a chance on someone young and vital,'' said Thomas Stacy, the English horn player. ''The problem is, I don't know who that is.''</p>
        <p>Whether the new system would please everyone remains to be seen. The clash of two conductorly egos is another question mark, one Mr. Mehta played down, saying ''I think the ego part is overdrawn.''</p>
        <p>As signs of the difficulty in finding the right person, Chicago and Philadelphia essentially put off the decision by hiring interim figures. In the fall of 2008, Charles Dutoit is to start a four-year term as chief conductor in Philadelphia; Bernard Haitink is serving a three-year term as principal conductor in Chicago.</p>
        <p>A handful of orchestras have tried out hydra-headed leadership, most notably the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra, which announced in September 2004 that three conductors would share the podium, partly because it could not find a lone candidate willing to take the music director's job. The orchestra is putting an end to that experiment.</p>
        <p>The Philharmonic declined to release Mr. Maazel's salary, but the most recent available tax filing by the orchestra listed his pay as $2.6 million in 2004. He joined the orchestra in the fall of 2002 on a four-year contract and extended it for three more years, through the 2008-9 season. This season, he is conducting 13 subscription weeks and leading the orchestra on two foreign tours.</p>
        <p>Over the last four seasons, the orchestra has recorded a steady increase in ticket sales, raising the percentage of tickets sold to a projected 86 this year, from 73. But it has been recording large deficits over the last four years, with $2.8 million expected this year. It has been using the endowment to make up deficits.</p>
        <p>Music</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
