<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wall St. Firm Will Settle Sex Bias Suit</title>
    <meta content="25bias" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/business/25bias.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842840"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Diversity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Morgan Stanley</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E5D8143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="714" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wall St. Firm Will Settle Sex Bias Suit</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Wall St. Firm Will Settle Sex Bias Suit</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNY ANDERSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For years, sex discrimination lawsuits against Wall Street firms were almost guaranteed to include details of crude antics, pornography and strip clubs.</p>
        <p>A bias settlement announced yesterday had no such lurid accusations, but sought to tackle a subtler, if arguably systemic, form of discrimination that has long troubled Wall Street.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Morgan Stanley agreed to pay $46 million to settle a suit by female brokers who said they were discriminated against in how they were trained, promoted and paid.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For years, sex discrimination lawsuits against Wall Street firms were almost guaranteed to include details of crude antics, pornography and strip clubs.</p>
        <p>A bias settlement announced yesterday had no such lurid accusations, but sought to tackle a subtler, if arguably systemic, form of discrimination that has long troubled Wall Street.</p>
        <p>Morgan Stanley agreed to pay at least $46 million to settle a class-action suit filed by eight current and former female brokers who contended that they were discriminated against in how they were trained, promoted and paid.</p>
        <p>The settlement is intended to overhaul the way accounts are distributed in the firm's retail branches -- a practice that determined, the women said, their opportunities for pay and advancement. The distribution system, they argued, favored the men who had long dominated the brokerage business.</p>
        <p>''It kind of institutionalizes historical bias from the freewheeling wild west days,'' said Cyrus Mehri, one of the lawyers who represented the eight plaintiffs named in the suit and the class of 2,700 women.</p>
        <p>Under the settlement, Morgan Stanley agreed to make changes in the way new accounts are distributed among brokers. As a result, pay for its 2,700 female brokers will increase at least $16 million, according to an estimate in the settlement.</p>
        <p>The case is Morgan Stanley's second major sex discrimination lawsuit in the last three years. On the eve of trial in 2004, Morgan Stanley agreed to pay $54 million to settle accusations that it denied women equal pay and promotions in its investment bank. That case was brought by Allison K. Schieffelin, a former bond saleswoman.</p>
        <p>Wall Street has struggled in recent years to overcome its reputation for workplaces dominated by white males. This case underlined in particular a ''power ranking'' system that dictated how the accounts of retiring and departing brokers were distributed, as well as new accounts generated from cold calls or walk-ins. The system measures the revenue that brokers produce and rewards those with the highest figures.</p>
        <p>But such a system favored those who reaped the benefits from branch managers' handing out new accounts to friends and golf buddies. By gaining the largest accounts, they generated the most revenue and won the majority of new ones.</p>
        <p>The new system will automate the distribution of accounts, and the methodology for distributing accounts will be explained to the brokers in writing, according to the settlement. The data will be made available to those who believe that they are being discriminated against.</p>
        <p>The settlement, Mr. Mehri said, ''is a tremendous first step in terms of changing the practice on Wall Street with regard to how female financial brokers are treated.''</p>
        <p>It followed two years of negotiations.</p>
        <p>Caroline Gundeck, head of Morgan Stanley's global wealth management office of diversity, said: ''We are firmly committed to the initiatives we will be undertaking to attract and retain women financial advisers and help them be as successful as possible, and pleased to resolve a legal matter stemming from the past. Our goal -- across the organization -- is to be the employer of choice for talented women.''</p>
        <p>The settlement estimates that Morgan Stanley will pay about $7.5 million to put into effect a number of changes, including the hiring of two industrial psychologists and an independent monitor to evaluate how the settlement is applied. The psychologists are charged with the task of understanding complex issues, like how partnerships are formed among brokers and how women can secure more accounts from departing brokers.</p>
        <p>The plaintiffs named in the suit were Joanne Augst-Johnson, Nancy Reeves, Debra K. Shaw, Jan Tyler, Cheryl Giustiniano, Laurie Blackburn, Erna Tarantino and Elizabeth Reinke. Mr. Mehri said that none of the women would be available for comment.</p>
        <p>The settlement applies to all women who were employed as financial advisers or registered financial adviser trainees in Morgan Stanley's wealth management division at any time from Aug. 5, 2003, to the day it is approved. Mr. Mehri estimated the class at 2,700.</p>
        <p>Morgan Stanley employs 8,000 brokers in 400 branches in the United States. The settlement is subject to the approval of the United States District Court for the District of Columbia.</p>
        <p>Discrimination issues continue to dog Wall Street. Merrill Lynch, after paying more than $200 million to settle a class-action suit brought in 1997, faces another suit by black brokers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
