<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chase Says It Will Move To Stamford If City Balks</title>
    <meta content="25chase" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/nyregion/25chase.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842836"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Morgan, J P, Chase &amp; Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E6D8143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="761" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chase Says It Will Move To Stamford If City Balks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Chase Says It Will Move if City Balks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES V. BAGLI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bagli, Charles V</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JPMorgan Chase is threatening to move thousands of employees from Midtown to Stamford, Conn., if New York officials do not give it a larger subsidy package to build a 50-story skyscraper near ground zero, according to real estate executives and government officials involved in the talks.</p>
        <p>Officials view the bank's threat to relocate outside Manhattan as the latest move in what has become a routine game of corporate poker in which companies try to extract special benefits. But Chase has gotten in touch with at least one large property owner in downtown Stamford, although it remains unclear whether the bank is serious or bluffing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>JPMorgan Chase is threatening to move thousands of employees from Midtown to Connecticut if New York officials do not give it a larger subsidy package to build near ground zero.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JPMorgan Chase is threatening to move thousands of employees from Midtown to Stamford, Conn., if New York officials do not give it a larger subsidy package to build a 50-story skyscraper near ground zero, according to real estate executives and government officials involved in the talks.</p>
        <p>Officials view the bank's threat to relocate outside Manhattan as the latest move in what has become a routine game of corporate poker in which companies try to extract special benefits. But Chase has gotten in touch with at least one large property owner in downtown Stamford, although it remains unclear whether the bank is serious or bluffing.</p>
        <p>Chase struck a tentative deal with the Port Authority in late March to pay about $300 million for the development rights at the site of the soon-to-be-demolished Deutsche Bank building, at Greenwich and Cedar Streets. Chase planned to build a 1.3-million-square-foot tower there and move thousands of employees from Park Avenue to Lower Manhattan, in what was widely regarded as a boon for the beleaguered district.</p>
        <p>Officials expected that the move would solidify Lower Manhattan's place as a world financial center and validate the redevelopment of the World Trade Center site as a commercial complex.</p>
        <p>In subsequent negotiations, state and city officials offered the bank the kind of benefit package available to any company moving to ground zero: a combination of tax breaks, cash payments and subsidized electricity benefits worth more than $100 million. But Chase has continually pushed city and state officials for a batch of subsidies akin to what Goldman Sachs got in 2005 to build a headquarters in Battery Park City. Critics described that deal as an egregious example of corporate welfare.</p>
        <p>State and city officials have resisted the bank's demands. They regard the Goldman deal as an aberration. And Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg has said that the city will not grant any special benefits beyond what any other company would get.</p>
        <p>''We would hope that Chase recognizes that Lower Manhattan is the financial capital of the world and that they would want to be located here,'' said John Gallagher, a spokesman for Mayor Bloomberg. ''Because the market in Lower Manhattan is strong and because Chase will realize more than $100 million with the incentives in place for Lower Manhattan, giving them an additional incentive package at this point would be difficult to justify.''</p>
        <p>Joseph Evangelisti, a spokesman for Chase, declined to comment. Last week, Chase reported a 55 percent rise in first-quarter profits.</p>
        <p>Stamford has been a relatively sleepy rival for Manhattan corporations compared with Jersey City, where U.S. Trust, Goldman Sachs, Chase, UBS and other financial institutions have moved at least part of their operations. Until recently, only UBS and some hedge funds had major operations in Stamford. But now the Royal Bank of Scotland is building a $400 million office complex there for what will be its North American headquarters. The complex includes a 95,000-square-foot trading floor and room for up to 1,400 traders.</p>
        <p>State and city officials in New York continue to express optimism that a deal can be struck downtown for Chase. One official, who insisted on anonymity because he was not authorized to talk about Chase, said that the snag centered on sales-tax breaks on building materials for the tower, while another said it had to do with payments the bank would be required to make in lieu of taxes.</p>
        <p>Office rents are considerably cheaper downtown than uptown, but holding the line on subsidies has still been difficult since the 2005 Goldman Sachs deal. Goldman negotiated with state and city officials to build a headquarters in Battery Park City, a significant financial investment and the first dramatic boost for Lower Manhattan after the terrorist attack on the World Trade Center.</p>
        <p>But after a series of missteps by aides to Gov. George E. Pataki, the state was forced to grant an unusually large subsidy package to ensure that Goldman would build the tower.</p>
        <p>Goldman Sachs got incentives worth an estimated $650 million in cash grants, tax-exempt bonds, sales and utility tax breaks and discounts on required payments in lieu of taxes. Since then, Chase, Lehman Brothers and Merrill Lynch have sought similar packages. City and state officials have rebuffed them.</p>
        <p>''The atmosphere in the city and downtown has changed dramatically since Sept. 11,'' said Patrick J. Foye, co-chairman of the Empire State Development Corporation, who is talking with Chase executives. ''Rents downtown are very strong and demand continues to grow. The state would welcome JPMorgan moving part of its operations to the city's vibrant downtown.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
