<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Brother's Death, a Crusade</title>
    <meta content="25face" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/education/25face.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Education Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842747"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FACE BOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E7DA143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="953" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Brother's Death, a Crusade</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From Brother’s Death, a Crusade</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TAMAR LEWIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewin, Tamar</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One Friday afternoon in March 2000, Alison Malmon, a freshman at the University of Pennsylvania, got word that her brother, Brian, a 22-year-old on leave from Columbia, had committed suicide.</p>
        <p>Brian had been a kind of star on campus, with a 3.7 grade-point average, and a lively wit that shone through his roles as sports editor of the newspaper, president of an a cappella group and actor in the annual student-written musical.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A brother’s suicide led his sister to organize a student group that evolved into a nonprofit organization devoted to awareness of mental illness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One Friday afternoon in March 2000, Alison Malmon, a freshman at the University of Pennsylvania, got word that her brother, Brian, a 22-year-old on leave from Columbia, had committed suicide.</p>
        <p>Brian had been a kind of star on campus, with a 3.7 grade-point average, and a lively wit that shone through his roles as sports editor of the newspaper, president of an a cappella group and actor in the annual student-written musical.</p>
        <p>The death of her only brother, and the discovery that he had hidden his struggles with mental illness from his friends and family for years after he began hearing voices, rocked Ms. Malmon's world, and by her junior year led her to start the student group that evolved into Active Minds Inc., a nonprofit organization with student-run chapters on 65 campuses, devoted to increasing awareness of mental illness.</p>
        <p>She started small. Very small. Only three people showed up for the first meeting at Penn of what she initially called Open Minds.</p>
        <p>''I asked them to help me figure out what we should do, '' said Ms. Malmon, now 25. ''There's so much talk about sexual identity and racial relations on college campuses. It was ridiculous in my mind that mental health wasn't right up there with them, since it's an issue that touches so many people.''</p>
        <p>The prevalence of mental illness on campus is stunning, she found when she began researching the topic: Suicide is the second leading cause of death for college students. Almost one in 10 college students has made a suicide plan. Nearly half of all students report having felt so depressed that they could not function in the previous year. Most people with schizophrenia develop the disease before they are 25.</p>
        <p>And yet, Ms. Malmon said, mental illness like her brother's is so stigmatized that it is often kept secret.</p>
        <p>''Mental illness is such an isolating thing,'' she said. ''It's not something that's easy to tell your family and friends about. That is the impetus for this. I firmly believe that Brian took his life because he didn't know how to live with mental illness. It's terrifying, because there aren't positive role models, there's just the people you see on the streets.''</p>
        <p>Now, with the Virginia Tech shootings, Ms. Malmon is concerned about a resurgence of the stigma against mental illness. ''I worry that as a society we're going to look toward everybody with mental illness as being violent, and that stigma will build right back up,'' she said. ''We want to emphasize the need for students to talk about what they're going through, and share their experiences. ''</p>
        <p>Active Minds is one place where students can do that. While each chapter is different, the membership blurs the lines between students with mental illness, students with friends or family members living with mental illness, and a smattering of psychology students, social workers and nurses.</p>
        <p>''When we have panel discussions, some are about what you can do to help a friend you're concerned about, that you should go and say, 'I'm worried about you, is everything O.K.?' and walk them over to the counseling center,'' Ms. Malmon said. ''Others are about how to live with mental illness, where people discuss their own experiences with anxiety disorder or depression. It may sound a little mushy, but all these things help get the word out,'' whether it is showing ''A Beautiful Mind,'' sponsoring a Stamp Out Stigma run or having a speaker.</p>
        <p>When a college student develops a mental illness, she said, friends are often the only ones who notice. Active Minds seeks to ensure that everyone on campus knows what mental health services are available and when to use them. On each campus, Active Minds has tables offering materials on mental health -- often the same materials available at the counseling center, Ms. Malmon said, but more visible. In some cases, a chapter has worked even more closely with the counseling center, providing student interviewers to sit in when candidates are interviewed for counseling jobs.</p>
        <p>Ms. Malmon, a sunny and impressively composed young woman who was a gymnast as a child and a varsity cheerleader at Penn, grew up in Potomac, Md., with her mother, Joanne, a social worker, and her father, Stuart, a lawyer. They separated when she was 8 and divorced when she was 12. ''That's really when Brian and I bonded, traveling back and forth from one to the other,'' she said. ''It was very important having a brother with me.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Malmon was always interested in psychology. As a freshman, she studied historical perspectives on mental illness, and abnormal psychology. Brian's death focused her interests further. Her senior thesis was ''Attitudes Toward Mental Illness Among Ivy League Undergraduates.''</p>
        <p>In 2003, Ms. Malmon graduated Phi Beta Kappa from Penn, incorporated Active Minds, and became the youngest recipient of the Tipper Gore Remember the Children Award from the National Mental Health Association.</p>
        <p>Now, financed by a combination of individual donations and foundation grants, Active Minds is her full-time job. She shares the headquarters, a crammed one-room office in Washington, with two other women who coordinate the campus chapters. And soon, she expects, they will need more space. Every week brings inquiries about starting chapters, most recently from students or staff members at Arizona State University, Luzerne County Community College in Pennsylvania, the University of Central Florida and Humboldt State University in California.</p>
        <p>''We just got a $100,000 three-year grant to do outreach,'' Ms. Malmon said. ''The goal is a chapter on every campus, but more realistic is that we'll have about 300 chapters in the next three years. Mental illness is such an important issue. I expect to grow, not stay a little nothing nonprofit.''</p>
        <p>FACE BOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
