<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Hamptons to Royals, On the Road Less Traveled</title>
    <meta content="25royals" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/sports/baseball/25royals.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842847"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago White Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Kansas City Royals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Kansas City Royals</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE4D8143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="834" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Hamptons to Royals, On the Road Less Traveled</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Long Islander’s Long Road to the Major Leagues</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAINER SABIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sabin, Rainer</byline>
      <dateline>KANSAS CITY, Mo., April 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It did not matter that Kauffman Stadium was half-empty Sunday, or that the wind was whipping around the field. Ross Gload said he was simply happy to be there, wearing what he called a kid's uniform and playing the game he loves.</p>
        <p>''I'm just enjoying my time,'' he said. ''They're going to have to go into my locker and pry the uniform out of there to make me go home.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was in East Hampton, N.Y., on the south fork of Long Island, that Royals outfielder Ross Gload picked up lessons about patience, perseverance and fate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It did not matter that Kauffman Stadium was half-empty Sunday, or that the wind was whipping around the field. Ross Gload said he was simply happy to be there, wearing what he called a kid's uniform and playing the game he loves.</p>
        <p>''I'm just enjoying my time,'' he said. ''They're going to have to go into my locker and pry the uniform out of there to make me go home.''</p>
        <p>That Gload was roaming left field for the Royals was somewhat remarkable. After all, he did not earn an established spot on a major league roster until last year. And by then, he was a 30-year-old first baseman who could not hit for much power. A long career in the majors did not seem likely.</p>
        <p>Then again, Gload said, neither did his chances of playing baseball beyond high school.</p>
        <p>It was in East Hampton, N.Y., on the South Fork of Long Island, that Gload picked up lessons about patience, perseverance and fate. There -- in a town with quiet beaches, woody enclaves, vast swaths of farmland and shingled mansions -- he discovered the funny way the world can work.</p>
        <p>In 1994, Gload was playing in obscurity, ignored by college coaches and major league scouts. He was having an outstanding senior season for the Bonackers. He hit 20 home runs, a New York state record that still stands, and fielded his position with the precision of a pro.</p>
        <p>Jim Nicoletti, East Hampton's coach at the time, said it seemed unfair that his prized player was being overlooked. Nicoletti said Gload was a bona fide college prospect.</p>
        <p>But there was a problem: he lived in East Hampton. Although the Hall of Famer Carl Yastrzemski grew up in nearby Bridgehampton, East Hampton is hardly known as a thriving recruiting ground for baseball talent.</p>
        <p>''I made tons of phone calls to colleges that year,'' Nicoletti said. ''But nobody was really interested. The standard response was, 'We don't recruit first basemen, let alone are going to come out to East Hampton, Long Island, to see one.' ''</p>
        <p>For as much as he accomplished on the field, Gload seemed destined to remain undiscovered. But then somebody he barely knew -- Ed Bahns -- called an old college buddy.</p>
        <p>Bahns, who grew up in East Hampton, had also been a promising first baseman who went virtually unrecruited. He was a walk-on at Florida Southern before earning a scholarship his sophomore year. Bahns proved himself and was later selected in the 21st round by the Chicago White Sox in the 1977 draft. He reached the White Sox' Class AA affiliate before his career flatlined. By 1980, he was out of baseball.</p>
        <p>Over the next 14 years, Bahns would hear about decent players from his hometown, but never one as good as Gload. Bahns was aware that Gload was not receiving much attention, so he called Eddie Cardieri, a former teammate from Florida Southern and the coach of South Florida.</p>
        <p>''He was like: 'Why would I even come up to New York? I can go anywhere in Florida and get a player I want,' '' Bahns, 51, recalled. ''I said Eddie, 'I just think he's good.' ''</p>
        <p>The endorsement was enough to persuade Cardieri to make a last-minute trip to St. Joseph's College in Patchogue, N.Y., where Gload was playing in the Suffolk County Small Schools Championship game.</p>
        <p>Cardieri was skeptical that Gload could be a Division I first baseman until he settled into the stands that afternoon in 1994. What he saw convinced him to offer Gload one of his last available scholarships. Gload hit three home runs and led East Hampton to a victory over Kings Park.</p>
        <p>''I'll never forget it,'' Cardieri said.</p>
        <p>Asked what would have happened had Cardieri missed his flight or decided not to go that day, Gload shrugged.</p>
        <p>''What I was supposed to do actually happened,'' Gload said.</p>
        <p>Even after leaving East Hampton, however, he did not immediately realize his dream. He would produce, then be ignored. After having an outstanding career at South Florida, he was selected by the Florida Marlins in the late rounds of the 1997 draft.</p>
        <p>For the next seven years, he played for four organizations, occasionally seeing action in the majors. It was not until 2006 that he felt that he would not have to prove himself anymore. Last season, with the White Sox, he hit .327 in 77 games before he was traded in the off-season.</p>
        <p>''In Ross's case, I don't think anything set him back,'' Royals Manager Buddy Bell said. ''I think it just made him more determined.''</p>
        <p>On Sunday, after Kansas City defeated Minnesota, 3-1, Gload stood in the clubhouse in front of his locker. The uniform was not in it. That was because he was still wearing it as reporters peppered him with questions about his two-run homer. One of the reporters asked Gload what it felt like to contribute such a big hit. He smiled.</p>
        <p>''If I don't do my job, then they'll get somebody else,'' he said.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
