<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Board Wavers on Contract for Siemens Chief</title>
    <meta content="25siemens" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/business/worldbusiness/25siemens.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842825"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Siemens AG</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Kleinfeld, Klaus</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06EED9143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="625" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Board Wavers on Contract for Siemens Chief</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Board Divided on Renewing Contract for Siemens Chief</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By G. THOMAS SIMS and MARK LANDLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Landler, Mark; Sims, G Thomas</byline>
      <dateline>FRANKFURT, April 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Klaus Kleinfeld's future as the chief executive of Siemens, the scandal-ridden engineering giant, was left hanging Tuesday as the company's supervisory board wavered over the extension of his contract.</p>
        <p>The board had long planned to renew Mr. Kleinfeld's contract, which expires on Sept. 30, at a meeting Wednesday. But as a series of corruption scandals ensnare more and more executives at the German engineering giant, some board members are arguing that they should await the outcome of an internal investigation before agreeing to offer Mr. Kleinfeld an extension.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Klaus Kleinfeld’s future was left hanging as the company’s supervisory board wavered over the extension of his contract.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Klaus Kleinfeld's future as the chief executive of Siemens, the scandal-ridden engineering giant, was left hanging Tuesday as the company's supervisory board wavered over the extension of his contract.</p>
        <p>The board had long planned to renew Mr. Kleinfeld's contract, which expires on Sept. 30, at a meeting Wednesday. But as a series of corruption scandals ensnare more and more executives at the German engineering giant, some board members are arguing that they should await the outcome of an internal investigation before agreeing to offer Mr. Kleinfeld an extension.</p>
        <p>Last week, Heinrich von Pierer, the former Siemens chief and one of Germany's most prominent industrialists, said that he would resign as chairman of the supervisory board to help bring the company into ''calmer waters,'' although he admitted no wrongdoing.</p>
        <p>Pressure has been growing on Mr. Kleinfeld ever since.</p>
        <p>Investors were surprised by his tenuous position, reported in the German media on Tuesday, and the share price fell 2.67 euros, or 2.9 percent, to 89.20 euros ($121.63).</p>
        <p>''A group of supervisory board members are questioning whether now is the right time to do renew the contract,'' said a person with direct knowledge of the thinking of shareholder representatives on the board.</p>
        <p>Among board members reportedly playing an important role is Josef Ackermann, the chief executive of Deutsche Bank. Mr. Ackermann survived a long period of uncertainty about his status at the bank, stemming from a case involving the telecommunications giant Mannesmann. The supervisory board of Deutsche Bank steadfastly supported him during his trial on corruption charges from actions he took as a Mannesmann board member. The charges were dropped last year as part of a settlement.</p>
        <p>But as a supervisory board member of Siemens, Mr. Ackermann is said to be determined to avoid fresh legal trouble.</p>
        <p>The person with knowledge of the thinking of the supervisory board said it would be contrary to good corporate governance practices if the contract were renewed before Mr. Kleinfeld was cleared, even though there was no indication yet of any wrongdoing. The person spoke on condition of anonymity because he was not authorized to speak for the board.</p>
        <p>Union representatives, which hold half the seats on the board, were also debating at meetings Tuesday on whether or not to extend, said Ingrid Gier, a spokeswoman for the IG Metall union.</p>
        <p>IG Metall has been angered by one corruption charge in particular -- that Siemens funneled 34 million euros ($46 million) to finance a competing union to act as a counterweight.</p>
        <p>The supervisory board, which is similar to an American board of directors, would have another opportunity to renew Mr. Kleinfeld's contract before its expiration, but a delay would show a growing lack of confidence in Mr. Kleinfeld.</p>
        <p>Jessika Gallitz, a spokeswoman for Siemens, declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Investors admire Mr. Kleinfeld, 49, the former head of United States operations, because the company's share price has risen 50 percent since he took the job in early 2005.</p>
        <p>Daniela Bergdolt, head of the Bavarian division of the DSW association for private investors, said she would like to see Mr. Kleinfeld's contract renewed to ensure a ''phase of calm and stability'' after the departure of Mr. von Pierer. ''What he's delivered so far in terms of strategy and results is no reason to replace him,'' Ms. Bergdolt said.</p>
        <p>In addition to the charges of bribing union officials, Siemens is also accused of bribing an Italian energy company. In a third case, prosecutors in Munich are investigating reports that more than $500 million in bribes was paid to foreign officials during the last seven years by the communications unit of Siemens to win contracts.</p>
        <p>The accusations have raised concerns that corruption is more widespread in German business than previously thought.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
