<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Building Owners' Costs Rose in Last Year, but So Did Revenues</title>
    <meta content="25rent" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/nyregion/25rent.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070512T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842800"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Rent Control and Stabilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rent Control and Stabilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E4D9143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="608" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Building Owners' Costs Rose in Last Year, but So Did Revenues</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Building Owners’ Costs Rose in Last Year, but So Did Revenues</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANNY SCOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scott, Janny</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The cost of operating the apartment houses that hold the city's more than one million rent-stabilized apartments rose by 5.1 percent in the last year -- less than in the previous year, the Rent Guidelines Board reported yesterday. And while building owners' costs grew at a faster rate than their income, their revenue after operating expenses were paid still increased.</p>
        <p>Those findings, in two reports by the rent board's staff, will be used by the board in setting allowable rent increases for rent-stabilized apartments for the coming year. The board, made up of nine members appointed by the mayor, is scheduled to hold a preliminary vote on May 7, three public hearings, then a final vote on June 22.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The cost of operating the apartment houses that hold the city’s more than one million rent-stabilized apartments rose by 5.1 percent in the last year  less than in the previous year, the Rent Guidelines Board reported yesterday. And while building owners’ costs grew at a faster rate than their income, their revenue after operating expenses were paid still increased.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The cost of operating the apartment houses that hold the city's more than one million rent-stabilized apartments rose by 5.1 percent in the last year -- less than in the previous year, the Rent Guidelines Board reported yesterday. And while building owners' costs grew at a faster rate than their income, their revenue after operating expenses were paid still increased.</p>
        <p>Those findings, in two reports by the rent board's staff, will be used by the board in setting allowable rent increases for rent-stabilized apartments for the coming year. The board, made up of nine members appointed by the mayor, is scheduled to hold a preliminary vote on May 7, three public hearings, then a final vote on June 22.</p>
        <p>Last year, when owners' costs had risen by 7.8 percent, the board approved rent increases of 7.25 percent on two-year leases and 4.25 percent on one-year leases.</p>
        <p>The first of the reports, the price index of operating costs, measures changes in the cost of certain goods and services. It found that labor costs for landlords rose 8.1 percent, administrative costs 6.9 percent and utility costs 6.3 percent. Real estate taxes grew 5.8 percent, while insurance costs grew by just 1.9 percent and fuel costs by only 0.5 percent.</p>
        <p>The increase in taxes, based on city Department of Finance data, was smaller than the 7.8 percent rise a year earlier. So was the rise in fuel costs, which had gone up 20 percent in each of the two previous years. On the other hand, the rise in administrative costs -- fees paid to management companies, accountants and lawyers -- was the biggest since 1986.</p>
        <p>The second report released yesterday, the income and expense study, was based on statements filed annually with the city by building owners themselves. The filings from more than 11,500 buildings with rent-stabilized apartments showed that owners' income rose by 4.7 percent and their costs by 6 percent.</p>
        <p>Even so, their ''net operating income'' -- the earnings that remain after operating and maintenance expenses are covered but before income tax and debt service are paid -- grew by 1.6 percent. (Because income exceeds expenses, a smaller percentage increase in income can outweigh a larger percentage increase in expenses.)</p>
        <p>At a board meeting in Lower Manhattan, Steven J. Schleider, a member appointed to represent the interests of owners, said the fact that net operating income was not larger showed that rent-stabilized buildings ''are not the investment panacea'' that, he said, some suggest. ''There are alternative investments that surely could generate a higher income than these properties,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Adriene L. Holder, a rent board member appointed to represent tenants, said business writers had stated recently that rent-regulated properties continued to be a good investment. She said, ''No one else is guaranteed that kind of return on investment, and it's guaranteed because this board exists.''</p>
        <p>Noting that net operating income rose only in Manhattan but decreased elsewhere, Mr. Schleider retorted, ''I fail to see the guarantee.''</p>
        <p>The Rent Guidelines Board, which sets guidelines for the 1.043 million rent-stabilized apartments but not for the 43,000 apartments under rent control, uses the staff reports as the basis for a discussion of rent increases for the coming year. It also takes into consideration a study on income and affordability intended to shed light on how much rent New Yorkers can afford to pay.</p>
        <p>That report, released on April 12, found unemployment down, wages up and gross city product growing, but the household income of tenants in rent-stabilized apartments shrinking. Evictions were up, the number of homeless families moving into permanent housing was down, and fewer people on public assistance were being placed in jobs.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 12, 2007, Saturday  An article in some copies on Tuesday about proposed tentative rent increases for New York City's one million rent-stabilized apartments included an outdated schedule for the board's final vote. It is now expected June 26, not June 22. The article also misstated the number of public hearings to be held on the increases. (The same error appeared in an article on April 25 about reports that building owners' costs and revenues rose in the last year.) There will be two hearings, not three.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 12, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article in some copies on Tuesday about proposed tentative rent increases for New York City's one million rent-stabilized apartments included an outdated schedule for the board's final vote. It is now expected June 26, not June 22. The article also misstated the number of public hearings to be held on the increases. (The same error appeared in an article on April 25 about reports that building owners' costs and revenues rose in the last year.) There will be two hearings, not three.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
