<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Paul Erdman, 74, Author Of Finance-Based Novels</title>
    <meta content="25erdman" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Obituaries" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/obituaries/25erdman.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842760"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Books And Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Paul E. Erdman</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erdman, Paul E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fox, Margalit</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Obituary (Obit)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Obituaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E5DA143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="662" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Paul Erdman, 74, Author Of Finance-Based Novels</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Paul Erdman, 74, Author of Finance-Based Novels, Dies</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARGALIT FOX</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fox, Margalit</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Paul E Erdman, writer of best-selling novels of financial intrigue, dies at age 74 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Paul E. Erdman, a writer of best-selling novels of financial intrigue who began his literary career in the comfort of a Swiss jail, where he was being held in connection with the collapse of the Swiss bank he ran, died on Monday at his ranch in Healdsburg, Calif. He was 74.</p>
        <p>The cause was cancer, his family said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Paul E. Erdman was a writer of best-selling novels of financial intrigue who began his literary career in the comfort of a Swiss jail, where he was being held in connection with the collapse of the Swiss bank he ran.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Paul E. Erdman, a writer of best-selling novels of financial intrigue who began his literary career in the comfort of a Swiss jail, where he was being held in connection with the collapse of the Swiss bank he ran, died on Monday at his ranch in Healdsburg, Calif. He was 74.</p>
        <p>The cause was cancer, his family said.</p>
        <p>An economist and former Lutheran seminarian, Mr. Erdman was widely regarded as having popularized financial fiction, a genre he affectionately called fi-fi. Among his best-known novels are ''The Billion Dollar Sure Thing,'' ''The Crash of '79'' and ''The Panic of '89.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Erdman was in all likelihood one of the few novelists whose books were routinely reviewed -- often glowingly -- in Business Week and The American Banker as well as in mainstream publications. His novels featured exotic locales, shadowy cartels and lots and lots of money.</p>
        <p>Paul Emil Erdman was born on May 19, 1932, in Stratford, Ontario, to parents who had moved there from the United States. (Mr. Erdman's father, a Lutheran pastor, had a pulpit in Stratford.)</p>
        <p>In 1954, Paul Erdman earned a bachelor of divinity degree from Concordia Seminary in St. Louis, followed the next year by a second bachelor's, from the Georgetown University School of Foreign Service. After a stint at The Washington Post, he earned a doctorate in economics, European history and theology from the University of Basel, in Switzerland, in 1958.</p>
        <p>Remaining in Europe, Mr. Erdman worked as an economist for the European Coal and Steel Community. In 1965, he established a private bank in Switzerland, the first American to do so. Originally called the Salik Bank, it later became the United California Bank in Basel.</p>
        <p>In 1970, Mr. Erdman's bank collapsed because of unauthorized speculation in cocoa and silver futures. Losses were reported in the tens of millions of dollars. Mr. Erdman, the bank's president, was dispatched to a Swiss jail -- a 17th-century dungeon in Basel -- to await charges.</p>
        <p>It was by all accounts a very nice dungeon. Room service, complete with fine wines, was provided (at Mr. Erdman's expense) by the best local restaurants. The wine would come in handy later, as he discovered.</p>
        <p>Mr. Erdman also had a portable Olivetti, and to pass the time, he decided to write a nonfiction book about economics. But the one thing the dungeon lacked was a research library, so he turned the book into a novel.</p>
        <p>Writing was a struggle at first. But help arrived in the form of a new inmate, a Frenchman reputed to be the finest safecracker in Europe.</p>
        <p>''I sent him over a couple of bottles of wine, and in exchange he told me a way for an amateur to crack a safe rather easily with ordinary equipment,'' Mr. Erdman told The New York Times in 1981. ''That became the first scene in the first chapter in my first novel.''</p>
        <p>The novel, ''The Billion Dollar Sure Thing,'' won an Edgar Award from the Mystery Writers of America in 1974.</p>
        <p>After about eight months in jail, Mr. Erdman posted $133,000 bail and moved back to the United States. In 1973, a Swiss court convicted him in absentia of fraud and sentenced him to nine years' imprisonment. He declined to return to Switzerland.</p>
        <p>Mr. Erdman's novel ''The Silver Bears'' became a Hollywood movie in 1978, starring Michael Caine, Cybill Shepherd, Martin Balsam and Jay Leno.</p>
        <p>He also wrote several nonfiction books on financial topics.</p>
        <p>Mr. Erdman is survived by his wife, the former Helly Boeglin, whom he married in 1954; two daughters, Jennifer Erdman of Healdsburg and Constance Erdman Narea of Greenwich, Conn.; a brother, Donald, of Waterloo, Ontario; a sister, Lois Erdman Kress of South Bend, Ind., and Fort Myers, Fla.; and two grandchildren.</p>
        <p>Reflecting on his time in jail, Mr. Erdman concluded that from a business standpoint, at least, it had been of considerable benefit. As he told The American Banker in 1996, ''It was what you call a successful career change.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
