<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Heat Loses Game, Not Confidence</title>
    <meta content="25bulls" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/sports/basketball/25bulls.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842886"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Chicago Bulls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Miami Heat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Chicago Bulls</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Miami Heat</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wade, Dwyane</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Deng, Luol</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01EED8143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="834" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Heat Loses Game, Not Confidence</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bulls’ Energy Overwhelms the Heat</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, April 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The deficit looks eerily familiar to the Miami Heat. Even the words coming out of a losing locker room sound the same.</p>
        <p>The last time the Heat trailed by 0-2 in the playoffs, they responded by winning four straight games against the Dallas Mavericks and capturing an N.B.A. title.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Luol Deng scored 14 of his 26 points in the final quarter, lifting Chicago to a thunderous victory to seize a 2-0 lead in the best-of-seven games series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The deficit looks eerily familiar to the Miami Heat. Even the words coming out of a losing locker room sound the same.</p>
        <p>The last time the Heat trailed by 0-2 in the playoffs, they responded by winning four straight games against the Dallas Mavericks and capturing an N.B.A. title.</p>
        <p>Much is different now. It is April and Dwyane Wade's left shoulder is ailing.</p>
        <p>For the second straight game at the United Center, the Chicago Bulls spun the Heat players on their heels, rotating with precision to the open man, and whenever that man was Luol Deng or Ben Gordon, the shot almost always found the net.</p>
        <p>Deng scored 14 of his 26 points in the fourth quarter when he shot down a Wade-led rally that brought Miami within 7 points. With boundless energy, the Bulls ran to a 107-89 victory and seized an early 2-0 lead in the best-of-seven series that shifts to Miami.</p>
        <p>Just where the Heat want the Bulls.</p>
        <p>''We've been here before, you know?'' Miami's Alonzo Mourning said with a grin in the locker room. ''And I've got the utmost confidence in this team that we can pick ourselves back up and get back on track. I'm very confident. Regardless of the scenario there.''</p>
        <p>The Bulls, in their third straight playoff appearance, are trying to win their first first-round series since the Michael Jordan era, trying to separate once and for all from the past. The Heat is clinging to it.</p>
        <p>''The bottom line is, we're the world champions and the first team to win four games moves on and that has not happened yet,'' Mourning said. ''Until we lose at home, I like our chances.''</p>
        <p>Heat Coach Pat Riley had the same sentiment. ''The game can change quickly,'' he said. ''We learned that last year in the playoffs. When everything seems the worst, it's just beginning. They deserved to win both of these games.''</p>
        <p>Riley did allow for improvement, however, especially with his team's perimeter defense. ''We have to do to a better job of containing them. If we don't correct some things, it will be difficult for us to win at home.''</p>
        <p>The Bulls shot 55.1 percent and forced the Heat into 21 turnovers, scoring 23 points off of those miscues. And while the Heat stayed within reach early -- trailing by 3 points at halftime -- the Bulls did not allow Miami to get any closer.</p>
        <p>Deng, once again, was a major reason for Chicago's domination. He began the game shooting 1 of 6, but caught fire in the fourth quarter, shooting 6 of 7 from the field. Deng has scored 59 points in two games.</p>
        <p>When Wade scored the first three baskets of the fourth quarter to cut the deficit to 89-82 with 8 minutes 48 seconds to play, Deng responded with back-to-back midrange jumpers. Thabo Sefolosha, the rookie from Switzerland playing for the foul-plagued Kirk Hinrich, added another jump shot and the Bulls' lead was back to 13 points.</p>
        <p>''We didn't want them to close the gap,'' Deng said. ''I felt good shooting the ball. I didn't really hesitate or think about it twice when I caught.''</p>
        <p>The Bulls are playing on instinct and a rhythm finely tuned during the regular season. Gordon had it through three quarters, when he shot 11 of 17 from the field, scoring 27 points on driving layups and 3-point daggers.</p>
        <p>''We're not overconfident,'' Gordon said. Why? He said he remembers precisely how, with the Heat trailing by an 0-2 deficit, Wade took over the N.B.A. finals last season</p>
        <p>But in this series, Wade is clearly different. His mobility and driving ability are restricted by his dislocated left shoulder that is rehabilitated, but not healed. For the second straight game, he finished with 21 points. Shaquille O'Neal finished with 17 and said that the referees were not a factor in keeping him subdued.</p>
        <p>''Right now they're playing with a lot of energy, they're getting a lot of the loose balls,'' O'Neal said. ''No excuses for tonight's loss, none whatsoever.''</p>
        <p>The Bulls continued to overwhelm their older opponents with energy on second-chance points, drawing from depth that ranged from 37-year-old power forward P. J. Brown to 27-year-old forward Andres Nocioni to 32-year-old center Ben Wallace.</p>
        <p>Nocioni provided the telling moment of the game in the first half. After scoring 7 consecutive points in the final 11.6 seconds of the second quarter with two 3-pointers and a foul, he threw his head back and unleashed a primal scream, punching his arms into the air.</p>
        <p>The Bulls were quick to temper themselves, though. The last time they were up 2-0 in a series? It was two seasons ago against Washington. ''We lost four straight,'' Bulls Coach Scott Skiles said. ''I know overconfidence won't be a problem.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>Shaquille O'Neal was not fined for complaining about the referees, calling out Eddie F. Rush by name after Game 1. The Bulls' Kirk Hinrich was fined $25,000 Monday for flinging his mouthpiece into the stands.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
