<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Another Go At a Women's League, But Not Going It Alone</title>
    <meta content="25soccer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/sports/soccer/25soccer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842880"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER: EXTRA TIME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Women's United Soccer Assn</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903EFD8143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1156" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Another Go At a Women's League, But Not Going It Alone</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Another Go at a Women’s League, but Not Going It Alone</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK BELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bell, Jack</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It has been nearly four years since players have kicked a ball in anger in a top-tier women's professional league in the United States. The Women's United Soccer Association ceased operations after the 2003 season, having raced through $40 million in seed money -- which was supposed to last for five years -- in only one season.</p>
        <p>Since then, Tonya Antonucci, an executive at Yahoo, has worked, with financial support from U.S. Soccer and the United States Soccer Foundation, to start another league. Last week Antonucci, the chief executive of the Women's Soccer Initiative Inc., announced ownership groups in Boston and the New York area for an eight-team circuit that plans to begin anew next April.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tonya Antonucci, an executive at Yahoo, has worked, with financial support from U.S. Soccer and the United States Soccer Foundation, to start a women’s professional league.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It has been nearly four years since players have kicked a ball in anger in a top-tier women's professional league in the United States. The Women's United Soccer Association ceased operations after the 2003 season, having raced through $40 million in seed money -- which was supposed to last for five years -- in only one season.</p>
        <p>Since then, Tonya Antonucci, an executive at Yahoo, has worked, with financial support from U.S. Soccer and the United States Soccer Foundation, to start another league. Last week Antonucci, the chief executive of the Women's Soccer Initiative Inc., announced ownership groups in Boston and the New York area for an eight-team circuit that plans to begin anew next April.</p>
        <p>In a departure from the W.U.S.A.'s start-up, when women's soccer and a group of elite players were intoxicated after the success of the 1999 Women's World Cup in the United States, many if not all teams will have some kind of working relationship with Major League Soccer. For example, some will play in M.L.S. stadiums (like Home Depot Center outside Los Angeles), and the league will work with M.L.S.'s marketing company, Soccer United Marketing. The new league does not have a name yet, but Antonucci said it was likely that a single sponsor could affix its name, along the lines of the Barclaycard English Premier League.</p>
        <p>''We need to get a few things right and give women's professional soccer another chance in this country,'' Antonucci said Saturday in a telephone interview. ''We have a more conservative business plan, with an average budget of between $1.5-$2.5 million a team, including salaries.</p>
        <p>''Before, the organizers viewed it as a major league that was in a position to go it alone. We're taking a different approach: We are independent but want to align with M.L.S. and work within the soccer infrastructure.''</p>
        <p>The league lineup includes teams in Boston, New York/New Jersey, Washington, St. Louis, Dallas, Los Angeles, Chicago and a city to be determined.</p>
        <p>''This is a unique product that has been absent from the marketplace,'' Antonucci said. ''To fans, our key message is that you've seen us fail once before, and it's not enough to wish for us to succeed. We need fans to support us.''</p>
        <p>Red Bulls</p>
        <p>The club's new addition, the Colombian striker Juan Pablo Ángel, was introduced by the Red Bulls after the team's training session yesterday at Montclair State College in New Jersey. Ángel, acquired from Aston Villa of the English Premier League, arrived in New York on Sunday night. He is here on a tourist visa, which means he is forbidden to train or play with the club. He is awaiting a work visa and will probably not be available to play until the Red Bulls' game at Real Salt Lake on May 5.</p>
        <p>Red Bulls defender Jeff Parke is wearing uniform No. 60 (more appropriate for an offensive lineman) this season, his fourth jersey number since he was taken 60th, and last, out of Drexel in the 2004 M.L.S. draft (the same draft in which Freddy Adu was picked No. 1 by D.C. United). In his first season, Parke wore No. 12. That number went to Jeff Agoos when he joined the team for the 2005 season; Parke switched to No. 5. In 2006, Parke yielded his number to the veteran Steve Jolley, and wore No. 23. This season, the Dutch goalkeeper Ronald Waterreus has asked for and received No. 23.</p>
        <p>''I figure that this time no one is going to want No. 60,'' Parke said. ''So I'm safe.''</p>
        <p>Arsenal</p>
        <p>The support of the 81-year-old Queen Elizabeth II, who said she had been a fan for more than 50 years, may not be enough to save Arsenal from a hostile takeover bid by Stan Kroenke and his company, Kroenke Sports Enterprises.</p>
        <p>Also in the balance is the strategic partnership announced in February between Kroenke's M.L.S. team, the Colorado Rapids, and Arsenal. Since the announcement, Kroenke has bought a 12.2 percent stake in the North London club. Last week, David Dein, Arsenal's vice chairman, resigned. He owns a 14.5 percent stake in Arsenal. If Dein and Kroenke work together and acquire 30 percent of the shares in the club, British law requires they make a formal bid for the team.</p>
        <p>Arsène Wenger, the Frenchman who was hired by Dein in 1996 to coach Arsenal, said he would not discuss his future with the club; his contract expires at the end of next season. The club's remaining board members control 45.5 percent of the shares. Arsenal, one of the most popular teams in England, moved into its new Emirates Stadium at the start of the season.</p>
        <p>Three clubs in the English Premier League -- Manchester United, Liverpool and Aston Villa -- are controlled by Americans, while two other teams -- Chelsea and West Ham United -- have non-English owners. In addition, Manchester City officials have been considering a takeover by a group of American investors and a former prime minister of Thailand, Thaksin Shinawatra.</p>
        <p>Notes</p>
        <p>Mexico defender Rafael Márquez will miss the Concacaf Gold Cup in June because of club commitments to Barcelona, said the Mexican national team coach, Hugo Sánchez. The Gold Cup will be played in the United States June 6-24; Barcelona is likely to be in the Spanish Cup final after beating Getafe, 5-2, in the first leg. That final will be June 23.</p>
        <p>The Dutch legend Johan Cruyff celebrates his 60th birthday today.</p>
        <p>The United States men's under-20 national team will face the defending world champion Argentina on May 15 in Rochester as it continues to prepare for the under-20 world championship in Canada from June 30 to July 22.</p>
        <p>Negotiations between Lew Wolff and officials at San Jose State have broken down, which means a new stadium will not be built on campus for an M.L.S. team. Wolff, who owns the Oakland Athletics, has an exclusive option to put an M.L.S. team in the Bay Area. The option expires in 2009 and is contingent upon the team having a new stadium to play in. The Earthquakes left for Houston before last season.</p>
        <p>Iraq has dropped its national team coach, Akram Ahmed Salman, only three months before the start of the Asian Cup.</p>
        <p>If you have not seen a clip of Lionel Messi's incredible goal on April 18, when Barcelona beat Getafe in the Spanish Cup, go to YouTube. It is certainly among the best goals of this or any year.</p>
        <p>WEEK'S NOTABLES</p>
        <p>CLUBS -- In Europe, four teams clinched first place last weekend: Inter Milan in Italy's Serie A; Olympique Lyon in France's Ligue 1; Glasgow Celtic in the Scottish Premier League; and Olympiakos Piraeus in Greece.</p>
        <p>PLAYER -- According to a report in the Spanish sports daily Marca, Real Madrid is interested in acquiring the 22-year-old Brazilian midfielder Diego from Werder Bremen. Diego left Porto after last season and has Werder in contention for the title in Germany's Bundesliga.</p>
        <p>SOCCER: EXTRA TIME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
