<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Corzine Leaves Hospital Bed For First Time Since Crash</title>
    <meta content="25corzine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/nyregion/25corzine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842754"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E6DA143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="477" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Corzine Leaves Hospital Bed For First Time Since Crash</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Corzine Leaves Hospital Bed for First Time Since Crash</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN; Nate Schweber contributed reporting from Camden, N.J.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schweber, Nate; Chen, David W</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, April 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Jon S. Corzine, freed from a catheter tube in his back, was able to sit upright in a chair on Tuesday for the first time since his car accident nearly two weeks ago, according to a statement released by a spokesman.</p>
        <p>In his 13th day at Cooper University Hospital in Camden, Mr. Corzine ate pancakes and sausage, an apple and a protein shake, according to Anthony Coley, his communications director. Mr. Corzine also underwent physical therapy and sat in a chair, a development that doctors said on Monday would be a significant milestone in his recovery.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Jon S. Corzine of New Jersey, freed from a catheter tube in his back, was able to sit upright in a chair on Tuesday for the first time since his car accident.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Jon S. Corzine, freed from a catheter tube in his back, was able to sit upright in a chair on Tuesday for the first time since his car accident nearly two weeks ago, according to a statement released by a spokesman.</p>
        <p>In his 13th day at Cooper University Hospital in Camden, Mr. Corzine ate pancakes and sausage, an apple and a protein shake, according to Anthony Coley, his communications director. Mr. Corzine also underwent physical therapy and sat in a chair, a development that doctors said on Monday would be a significant milestone in his recovery.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine continues to receive antibiotics for a possible infection of his trachea, but ''is showing no other sign of infection or complication at this time,'' Mr. Coley said. The governor, who suffered more than a dozen broken bones on April 12 when the car in which he was riding crashed on the Garden State Parkway, remained in stable condition, one day after he was moved out of intensive care.</p>
        <p>Richard J. Codey, a fellow Democrat who is president of the State Senate, is serving as acting governor at least until Mr. Corzine's release from the hospital, which doctors say could be within a week.</p>
        <p>It is not known when Mr. Corzine will make his first public appearance, or greet visitors beyond the small circle of family, friends and aides who have been allowed to see him so far. Mr. Codey, for one, has asked when he and his wife can visit but has yet been given no date.</p>
        <p>Nor is it clear where the governor will undergo the rehabilitation that his doctors and aides have said will be arduous and likely to last for several months. But legislators, lobbyists and administration officials say that it would be preferable for Mr. Corzine to be closer to Trenton than his apartment in Hoboken.</p>
        <p>Still, with Mr. Corzine's condition improving, his administration on Tuesday released a small sampling of the more than 1,300 e-mail messages his office has received from state residents since his accident. By the administration's own count, about 90 percent have been positive, with many offering generic salutations like, ''Wishing you a speedy recovery.''</p>
        <p>A message signed ''Robyn'' said: ''You certainly gave us a huge scare! It is heartening to hear that your recovery is going better than expected. That must be a testament to your strong will and determination. Continue to focus your energy on healing. The rest of us will muddle through until you can return to your office!''</p>
        <p>But a handful also criticized Mr. Corzine, like ''Marissa, a concerned N.J. taxpayer,'' who followed her ''Get well soon!'' wish with the admonition: ''Is it true you weren't wearing a seat belt? Are you going to get a ticket? Please wear a seat belt; they save lives.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
