<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pentagon Intelligence Chief Proposes Ending a Database</title>
    <meta content="25intel" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/washington/25intel.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842759"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveillance of Citizens by Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mazzetti, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clapper, James R Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Surveillance of Citizens by Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveillance of Citizens by Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Defense Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5DA143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="680" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pentagon Intelligence Chief Proposes Ending a Database</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pentagon Intelligence Chief Proposes Ending a Database</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK MAZZETTI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mazzetti, Mark</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Defense Dept says new Pentagon intelligence chief James R Clapper intends to dismantle antiterrorism database that civil liberties groups have criticized for gathering information about antiwar groups, churches and student activists; database was begun in 2003 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Pentagon's new intelligence chief intends to dismantle an antiterrorism database that civil liberties groups have criticized for gathering information about antiwar groups, churches and student activists, Defense Department officials said Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The database was begun in 2003 to house intelligence reports about possible threats to military bases within the United States, but it was expanded to include reports by local law enforcement agencies and military security personnel about nonviolent demonstrations and rallies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The antiterrorism database was criticized by civil liberties groups for gathering information about antiwar groups, churches and student activists.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Pentagon's new intelligence chief intends to dismantle an antiterrorism database that civil liberties groups have criticized for gathering information about antiwar groups, churches and student activists, Defense Department officials said Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The database was begun in 2003 to house intelligence reports about possible threats to military bases within the United States, but it was expanded to include reports by local law enforcement agencies and military security personnel about nonviolent demonstrations and rallies.</p>
        <p>The decision is one of the first moves by James R. Clapper since he took over as the Pentagon's top intelligence official earlier this month. Department officials said Mr. Clapper had recommended to Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates that the database, called Talon, be dismantled.</p>
        <p>A Pentagon spokesman, Bryan Whitman, said Mr. Gates would make the ultimate decision about Talon and called the program ''controversial and often misunderstood.''</p>
        <p>The decision to scuttle the database could be the first step in a broad overhaul of Pentagon intelligence activities under Mr. Gates, who has made public his distaste for some intelligence initiatives begun by his predecessor, Donald H. Rumsfeld.</p>
        <p>A senior department official, speaking on condition of anonymity because Mr. Gates has not made any final decisions, said Mr. Clapper was concerned about the negative publicity surrounding the Talon database and told Mr. Gates that the Pentagon could find other ways to assess threats to military installations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clapper's recommendation was first reported by Reuters on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Civil liberties groups and some members of Congress criticized the database, which was run by the Pentagon's Counterintelligence Field Activity office, suggesting it was an effort by the military to expand its domestic spying operations under the guise of combating terrorism.</p>
        <p>The Pentagon has long been restricted in conducting domestic intelligence operations and is barred from traditional law enforcement work.</p>
        <p>A lawyer with the American Civil Liberties Union, Ben Wizner, called Mr. Clapper's decision a ''positive step'' but said he was concerned that the Pentagon could carry out similar activity in the future under different names.</p>
        <p>''What we don't know about Pentagon surveillance within the United States far exceeds what we do know,'' Mr. Wizner said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rumsfeld had long criticized the capabilities of American intelligence agencies and had moved during his tenure to improve and expand military intelligence collection worldwide. Both Mr. Rumsfeld and his intelligence chief, Stephen A. Cambone, were viewed with suspicion by many in the intelligence community who believed the Pentagon was trying a power grab from other spy agencies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rumsfeld created the Counterintelligence Field Activity office, or CIFA, in 2002 to improve coordination of the military's efforts to combat foreign intelligence services and terrorism groups inside the United States. Some civil liberties groups have criticized the office for its efforts to gather information inside the United States, but Pentagon officials have said that CIFA never violated department regulations prohibiting domestic spying.</p>
        <p>Most of what is publicly known about the Talon database came in documents released last year by the Pentagon in response to a request from the American Civil Liberties Union under the Freedom of Information Act.</p>
        <p>Among the database entries were one from February 2005 that noted that a ''church service for peace'' would be held in the New York City area and another revealing that military officials had labeled a March 2005 ''Stop the War Now'' rally in Akron, Ohio, a ''potential terrorist activity.''</p>
        <p>Pentagon officials said last year that some of the controversial Talon reports had made it into the database by accident and that some had been kept in Talon past the 90 days that department guidelines allowed.</p>
        <p>The Pentagon purged more than 250 incident reports from Talon last year and tightened procedures to ensure that only actual terror threats were entered in the database.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gates, who once served as director of central intelligence, took office pledging to smooth over the Pentagon's relations with the intelligence community. Early in his tenure he met with the directors of the other intelligence agencies and asked them to produce an assessment of programs that were working and those that were not.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
