<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jordan Palmer Looks to Make A Name For Himself</title>
    <meta content="25palmer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/sports/football/25palmer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842883"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Cincinnati Bengals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Football League</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Cincinnati Bengals</org>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Texas-El Paso</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Palmer, Carson</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Quinn, Brady</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mayock, Mike</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD8143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1058" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jordan Palmer Looks to Make A Name For Himself</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Jordan Palmer Looks to Make a Name for Himself</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crouse, Karen</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jordan Palmer shops for his clothing at Goodwill stores, which seems a fitting way to introduce a quarterback prospect for whom the N.F.L. draft is a hand-me-down experience.</p>
        <p>In 2003, the Cincinnati Bengals made Palmer's brother, Carson, a quarterback out of Southern California, the No. 1 pick in the draft. Four years later, the younger Palmer, a four-year starter at Texas-El Paso, is considered a probable second-day pick.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The younger brother of the former No. 1 draft pick and Bengals’ starting quarterback Carson Palmer has used humor and some good performances to distinguish himself before the N.F.L. draft.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jordan Palmer shops for his clothing at Goodwill stores, which seems a fitting way to introduce a quarterback prospect for whom the N.F.L. draft is a hand-me-down experience.</p>
        <p>In 2003, the Cincinnati Bengals made Palmer's brother, Carson, a quarterback out of Southern California, the No. 1 pick in the draft. Four years later, the younger Palmer, a four-year starter at Texas-El Paso, is considered a probable second-day pick.</p>
        <p>Carson Palmer entered the 2003 draft weekend having already agreed to a contract with the Bengals that guaranteed him a $10 million signing bonus. Jordan Palmer heads into this weekend's draft with a guaranteed tee time for 36 holes with Carson on a golf course in Colorado, where their parents, Bill and Dana, own a home.</p>
        <p>If Palmer is at all burdened that his football career has not measured up to his brother's, he did not show it at the N.F.L. scouting combine in February. ''I don't think there is a huge difference,'' he said when asked about the inevitable comparisons. ''Besides that he's won a bunch of awards, he's really famous and he's really rich.''</p>
        <p>In the yearly shopping expedition that is the N.F.L. draft, Palmer described himself as a steal for a team that is not stuck on labels and recognizes, as he does, that some of the best picks can often be found off the gilded path.</p>
        <p>''I can't compete with Carson in a lot of areas,'' Palmer said recently over lunch at a sports bar not far from where he grew up in Mission Viejo, Calif. ''But I can compete with him for Super Bowls, because he hasn't won one of those yet. In the N.F.L., I want to be that guy who leads my team to a championship. That's my goal.''</p>
        <p>Palmer's dream is to be drafted by a team in the Bengals' division, the American Football Conference North, so he and his brother can oppose each other twice a year into the next decade.</p>
        <p>''If I could go anywhere, it'd be somewhere like Baltimore so I could play against Carson,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Jordan Palmer is 6 feet 6 inches and 230 pounds, with broad shoulders and close-cropped, dirty blond hair that he usually keeps tucked underneath a baseball cap. He is the spitting image of Carson.</p>
        <p>Not long ago, he was taking his girlfriend, Dottie O'Dell, to dinner when a stranger ran up to him, grabbed him by the arm, thrust a piece of paper in front of him and said, ''Carson, will you sign this for me?''</p>
        <p>Palmer politely shrugged off the autograph seeker, and according to O'Dell, said, ''No, no, I'm not him, but I get that a lot.'' He has been heard telling others who confuse him for his brother: ''I'm not an N.F.L. player. I'm unemployed and live with my parents.''</p>
        <p>It is the pared-down truth, but after this weekend he hopes his story changes. Palmer, 22, completed 65.7 percent of his passes last season for 3,595 yards and 26 touchdowns for the Miners (5-7), a Conference USA team.</p>
        <p>Although his mechanics are exceptional, the same cannot be said of his accuracy; as a senior he was intercepted 14 times, the same number Brady Quinn had during his final two seasons at Notre Dame.</p>
        <p>Mike Mayock, an NFL Network draft expert, said Palmer could be selected late in the fourth round, but more likely in the fifth or sixth. ''He's a bit of a project,'' Mayock said. ''In my opinion the whole interception-to-touchdown ratio has gotten blown out of proportion a little. If you watch tape a lot of the interceptions were not his fault.''</p>
        <p>Palmer, who conceded that he has a gambler's streak that he is working to tone down, does not dwell on things he cannot control. His focus, he said, was on being coachable, being a hard worker and being tough. ''I don't want people to think I'm content with my last name and being tall,'' he said. ''I love to compete and I want to be successful, and to do that I know I need to work hard every day to get better.''</p>
        <p>Ron Hudson, who recruited Palmer to play at Texas-El Paso before leaving to become the offensive line coach at Louisiana-Lafayette, called Palmer a one-of-a-kind person and a leader.</p>
        <p>''He's not ashamed to be a little different,'' Hudson said in a telephone interview. ''He has a swagger that comes not from arrogance, but from a leadership standpoint.''</p>
        <p>Hudson remembered how Palmer reached out to teammates who came from different backgrounds and was not afraid to confront players about behavior that could be considered detrimental to the team. ''He's the best leader I've seen bar none,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As the draft nears, Hudson listens to those who question Palmer's decision-making and his reads. ''Will he make it in the N.F.L.?'' Hudson said. ''I don't know, but I've told people this: he will never embarrass anybody who brings him in.''</p>
        <p>Palmer acknowledged his second-hand sartorial style probably raises a few eyebrows in certain places he goes with O'Dell in Orange County, like the glitzy outdoor malls where consumers seem to spend a lot of time shopping for status. The dark, three-piece polyester suit that he considers one of his best Goodwill finds might not go over too well with the Hugo Boss crowd.</p>
        <p>During one of Carson's recent trips to Southern California, he and his brother played Torrey Pines, the public golf course outside San Diego. They were paired with two strangers from West Virginia, who happened to be wide-eyed Bengals fans. After trading stories and shots for 18 holes, the men told the Palmers they were surprised at how normal they were.</p>
        <p>''That's a bigger compliment than someone saying you're cool,'' said Jordan Palmer, who has no use for people who judge others by the clothes on their backs, the car in their garage or their family name.</p>
        <p>''I take what I do very seriously, but I don't take myself seriously,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Palmer played second violin in the high school band and college football in West Texas as a way to forge an identity separate from his brother's. As he prepares to follow Carson into the N.F.L., Jordan's sense of self is stronger than his throwing arm.</p>
        <p>''He doesn't care what other people think,'' O'Dell, said. ''He is his own person.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
