<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Veteran Actor Who Defies Pigeonholing</title>
    <meta content="25farl" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/movies/25farl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842742"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E6DB143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="774" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Veteran Actor Who Defies Pigeonholing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Veteran Actor Who Defies Pigeonholing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL GENZLINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genzlinger, Neil</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Put Farley Granger in a grocery checkout line, and when the time comes to select paper or plastic, he might well choose both. Mr. Granger, in his star-studded personal life and in his nearly 60 years as an actor, has made an art form of keeping one foot in each of two worlds. Film and theater. American and Italian. Gay and straight.</p>
        <p>Mr. Granger, 81, has crammed a lot of his tales into ''Include Me Out: My Life From Goldwyn to Broadway'' (St. Martin's Press), a genteel new tell-almost-all written with his longtime partner, Robert Calhoun. And he told some of them on Monday night at Film Forum in the South Village during a discussion peppered with clips of his work.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Actor Farley Granger has made an art form of keeping one foot in each of two worlds. Film and theater. American and Italian. Gay and straight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Put Farley Granger in a grocery checkout line, and when the time comes to select paper or plastic, he might well choose both. Mr. Granger, in his star-studded personal life and in his nearly 60 years as an actor, has made an art form of keeping one foot in each of two worlds. Film and theater. American and Italian. Gay and straight.</p>
        <p>Mr. Granger, 81, has crammed a lot of his tales into ''Include Me Out: My Life From Goldwyn to Broadway'' (St. Martin's Press), a genteel new tell-almost-all written with his longtime partner, Robert Calhoun. And he told some of them on Monday night at Film Forum in the South Village during a discussion peppered with clips of his work.</p>
        <p>Mr. Granger may not have achieved the film idol fame of contemporaries like James Stewart and Marlon Brando, but you'd never have known it from his Film Forum appearance: the place was packed, and a standby line stretched down the block. ''Absolute Farleymania,'' Bruce Goldstein, Film Forum's director of repertory programming, called it in introducing the evening.</p>
        <p>If the theater was packed, so is Mr. Granger's book. Seemingly everyone who was anyone in postwar Hollywood or East Coast theater turns up in it. Some of them also turn up in his bed: Ava Gardner, Leonard Bernstein, Shelley Winters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Granger was a good-looking teenager when he was spotted in a play by a casting director for Samuel Goldwyn and, with Hollywood short on men during World War II, quickly thrust into the movies: ''The North Star'' in 1943, ''The Purple Heart'' the next year.</p>
        <p>''I was blinded in the film about Russia, and in the one about Japan, I had my tongue cut out,'' he said of those two movies in an interview last week. But soon roles with more dialogue and less disfigurement came, most famously his two films for Alfred Hitchcock: he was a preppy who kills in ''Rope'' (1948) and a tennis player implicated in murder in ''Strangers on a Train'' (1951).</p>
        <p>Mr. Granger, though, said he was most proud of his work in Luchino Visconti's ''Senso'' (1954), one of a number of Italian films on his résumé. And while clips from his American films drew the applause of familiarity on Monday, a scalding scene from the less familiar ''Senso'' drew both applause and a murmur of admiration, as if his casual fans were not aware of the depth of his acting skill.</p>
        <p>Though the movies brought him quick fame, Mr. Granger had another aspiration almost from the beginning: the stage. Early on he was befriended by musicians and theater types like Bernstein and Betty Comden.</p>
        <p>''That was a crowd that didn't care whether you were gay, straight, anywhere on a sliding scale,'' he said in the interview. And it was a crowd that gave him the theater bug. Goldwyn was not taking Mr. Granger's film career where he wanted it to go. ''I played the same part over and over again,'' he told Monday's audience, and when ''Edge of Doom'' (1950), in which he kills a priest, came up, he muttered, ''I should have killed Sam Goldwyn.''</p>
        <p>So in 1953 he took the unusual step of buying his way out of his Goldwyn contract so he could be freer to work on the stage. His theatrical years, he said in the interview, never measured up to his hopes, despite his half-dozen Broadway credits. But he did find plenty of work in its close cousin, live television, during that medium's early years.</p>
        <p>Despite his wide-ranging career and personal choices, when pressed by an interviewer to make paper-or-plastic-type decisions, Mr. Granger, it turns out, does have preferences in the various touchstones of his life.</p>
        <p>''Rope'' or ''Strangers on a Train''?</p>
        <p>'' 'Strangers,' '' he said without hesitation. ''I think it was a more complete film. I think 'Rope' was more an experiment for Hitchcock.''</p>
        <p>American or Italian?</p>
        <p>''Oh, the American films,'' he said, but then backed up. ''With the exception of the Visconti. That lives on a level all by itself. The other foreign films, I could care less about.''</p>
        <p>Film or theater?</p>
        <p>Theater by a landslide, because of the visceral thrill of hearing a live audience react. ''I think that film is legitimate, and I have great respect for it,'' Mr. Granger said, ''but it can't compare.''</p>
        <p>Men or women?</p>
        <p>''That really depends on the person,'' he said impishly. But his follow-up comment left little doubt: ''I've lived the greater part of my life with a man'' -- he has been with Mr. Calhoun in New York since the 1960s -- ''so obviously that's the most satisfying to me.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
