<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Leads to a Game of Wits In a Sinister Underworld</title>
    <meta content="25tria" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/movies/25tria.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842745"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dargis, Manohla</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">To, Johnnie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koo, Louis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yam, Simon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheung, Nick</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Triad Election (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Triad Election (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DB143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="843" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Leads to a Game of Wits In a Sinister Underworld</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">... Leads to a Game of Wits in a Sinister Underworld</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MANOHLA DARGIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dargis, Manohla</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Manohla Dargis reviews film Triad Election, directed by Johnnie To; Louis Koo, Simon Yam and Nick Cheung star; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The surfaces gleam as luxuriously in Johnnie To's exemplary gangster thriller ''Triad Election'' as those in a similarly slicked-up Hollywood film, but the blood on the floor here seems stickier, more liable to seep and to stain. A dark, brutal look at the shadows darkening the Hong Kong triads, the film picks up the narrative line expertly coiled and kinked in Mr. To's companion piece made the year before, ''Election.'' As in the earlier film (released in Hong Kong in 2005), this new work (2006) involves a Machiavellian game of chess between rivals, each of whom would be king, each of whom sacrifices legions of pawns.</p>
        <p>One of the greatest action directors working in the world and one of the most excitingly prolific, Mr. To amassed a notable list of credits in the 1980s and 1990s before his films started showing up on the festival circuit. In its size and uneven quality, his recent output can bring to mind those golden-age Hollywood professionals who, come hell, high water or inferior script, would reliably do their part to meet the studio's sausage quota. Some films disintegrate on impact, like Mr. To's witless shoot'em-up ''Fulltime Killer'' (directed with Wai Ka-fai); some are little more than excuses for their maker's dazzling technique, like Mr. To's three-ring genre workout, ''Breaking News.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The surfaces gleam as luxuriously in Johnnie To’s exemplary gangster thriller “Triad Election” as those in a similarly slicked-up Hollywood film, but the blood on the floor here seems stickier.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The surfaces gleam as luxuriously in Johnnie To's exemplary gangster thriller ''Triad Election'' as those in a similarly slicked-up Hollywood film, but the blood on the floor here seems stickier, more liable to seep and to stain. A dark, brutal look at the shadows darkening the Hong Kong triads, the film picks up the narrative line expertly coiled and kinked in Mr. To's companion piece made the year before, ''Election.'' As in the earlier film (released in Hong Kong in 2005), this new work (2006) involves a Machiavellian game of chess between rivals, each of whom would be king, each of whom sacrifices legions of pawns.</p>
        <p>One of the greatest action directors working in the world and one of the most excitingly prolific, Mr. To amassed a notable list of credits in the 1980s and 1990s before his films started showing up on the festival circuit. In its size and uneven quality, his recent output can bring to mind those golden-age Hollywood professionals who, come hell, high water or inferior script, would reliably do their part to meet the studio's sausage quota. Some films disintegrate on impact, like Mr. To's witless shoot'em-up ''Fulltime Killer'' (directed with Wai Ka-fai); some are little more than excuses for their maker's dazzling technique, like Mr. To's three-ring genre workout, ''Breaking News.''</p>
        <p>His mastery of genre, both its conventions and possible variations, is generously in evidence in another of his films scheduled for release later this year, ''Exiled.'' Like others of his films, it is a gangster exercise in which story scarcely matters compared with the sounds of ricocheting bullets, nods to Sergio Leone and the geometric patterns of human arms creating right angles across the screen, a gripped gun indicating the exact point at which each lower straight line comes to a dangerous end.</p>
        <p>Taken together, ''Election'' and ''Triad Election'' -- which, for their full-on, cumulative power, should be seen back to back -- are better yet and show Mr. To at his most openly ambitious. (They were presented at consecutive editions of the Cannes Film Festival; the first in competition, the second not.) In their epic scope, bountiful casts, multiple story lines and political shadings, these two films suggest that Mr. To and his screenwriters, Yau Nai-hoi and Yip Tin-shing, have nothing less in mind than a Hong Kong analogue to the first two chapters in Francis Ford Coppola's ''Godfather'' cycle.</p>
        <p>The first ''Election'' involves the violent transfer of triad leadership to a middle-aged gangster, Lok (the great Simon Yam), a smoothie who hides his killer hunger with a soft smile and a businessman's immaculately tailored suit. Two years later, in ''Triad Election,'' Lok is being backed up against the wall by one of his younger subordinates, Jimmy (Louis Koo), who nonetheless insists he would prefer to diversify his portfolio through legitimate means rather than the bloody business of Murder Inc.</p>
        <p>Yet while Jimmy voices reservations as volubly as Michael Corleone, insisting that he wants to go legitimate, Mr. To knows better. More elegantly plotted and streamlined than the first film, ''Triad Election'' largely involves Jimmy's simultaneous attempts to insinuate himself into seemingly legitimate business dealings in mainland China and, at least initially, to extricate himself from the complex, deadly machinations of Hong Kong's underworld.</p>
        <p>Standing on a grassy slab of mountain in China, where he hopes to build a real estate kingdom and a castle teeming with heirs, Jimmy casts a gaze across a horizon that appears as limitless as his immediate future. Listen closely and you just might hear him say, echoing the famous first line in the ''Godfather'' saga, ''I believe in China.''</p>
        <p>Like Michael Corleone, Jimmy keeps getting pulled back in again and again, though Mr. To and his screenwriters make sure that this is one gangster, at least, who can be neither sentimentalized nor romanticized, as is usually the case with big-screen and small-time American gangsters. Any idea that Jimmy has been conceived as a variation on the Michael Corleone/Tony Soprano brand of thoughtfully troubled murderers is firmly laid to rest in a gruesome scene that is as nauseating to watch as it is effectively blunt and intellectually pointed. (Hint: skip the burger before showtime.) Mr. To has built a dazzling brilliant career out of cinematic mayhem; here he rises to the challenge of that legacy with a metaphor about capitalism, men and meat that is perfect in its simplicity and barbarism.</p>
        <p>Triad Election  Opens today in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Directed by Johnnie To; written (in Cantonese, with English subtitles) by Yau Nai-hoi and Yip Tin-shing; director of photography, Cheng Siu-keung; edited by Law Wing-cheong and Jeff Cheung; music by Robert Ellis-Geiger; art director, Tony Yu; produced by Dennis Law and Mr. To; released by Tartan Films. At the Film Forum, 209 West Houston Street, west of Avenue of the Americas, South Village. Running time: 93 minutes. This film is not rated.</p>
        <p>WITH: Louis Koo (Jimmy), Simon Yam (Lok), Nick Cheung (Jet), Cheung Siu-fai (Mr. So), Lam Ka-tung (Kun), Nick Cheung (Jet) and Lam Suet (Big Head).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
