<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Attack by Hamas Casts Doubt On Future of Cease-Fire in Gaza</title>
    <meta content="25mideast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/world/middleeast/25mideast.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842769"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Gaza Strip</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hamas</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kershner, Isabel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">khodary, taghreed el-</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Gaza Strip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Gaza Strip</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Israel</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Hamas</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2DA143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="615" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Attack by Hamas Casts Doubt On Future of Cease-Fire in Gaza</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Attack by Hamas Casts Doubt on Future of Cease-Fire in Gaza</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ISABEL KERSHNER; Taghreed El-Khodary contributed reporting from Gaza.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kershner, Isabel; khodary, taghreed el-</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, April 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Military wing of Hamas fires barrage of rockets and mortar shells from Gaza Strip into Israel for first time since Hamas committed to cease-fire in Nov 2006 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The military wing of Hamas fired a barrage of rockets and mortar shells from the Gaza Strip into Israel on Tuesday for the first time since Hamas committed to a cease-fire in November.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the Hamas military wing in Gaza declared the truce there over. But more moderate members of Hamas in the Palestinian unity government, including Prime Minister Ismail Haniya, said they were making efforts to preserve the cease-fire. And a Hamas spokesman in Gaza, Ismail Radwan, stopped short of calling off the cease-fire, saying the actions on Tuesday were ''a natural response to Israeli aggression and violations of the truce.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A spokesman for the Hamas military wing declared the truce over, but members of the Palestinian government said they want to preserve the cease-fire.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The military wing of Hamas fired a barrage of rockets and mortar shells from the Gaza Strip into Israel on Tuesday for the first time since Hamas committed to a cease-fire in November.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the Hamas military wing in Gaza declared the truce there over. But more moderate members of Hamas in the Palestinian unity government, including Prime Minister Ismail Haniya, said they were making efforts to preserve the cease-fire. And a Hamas spokesman in Gaza, Ismail Radwan, stopped short of calling off the cease-fire, saying the actions on Tuesday were ''a natural response to Israeli aggression and violations of the truce.''</p>
        <p>Over the weekend, Israeli forces killed up to nine Palestinians, mostly militants in the West Bank, during military operations and confrontations. One of the dead was a Palestinian in Gaza, killed in an airstrike that Israel said had been aimed at militants traveling in a car after they had launched rockets into Israel.</p>
        <p>The November cease-fire agreement pertained only to Gaza. Palestinian leaders have asked to extend it to the West Bank, but Israeli officials have said it must be carried out properly in Gaza first. Smaller Palestinian factions that rejected the cease-fire, including Islamic Jihad, have continued firing rockets at Israel almost daily.</p>
        <p>The rocket and mortar attacks on Tuesday, which caused no injuries, occurred as Israelis woke up to celebrate the country's 59th Independence Day.</p>
        <p>Miri Eisin, a spokeswoman for the Israeli prime minister, Ehud Olmert, said, ''We reserve our right to respond and to defend our citizens at any time.'' But Israeli officials speaking on condition of anonymity suggested that any response would be limited, and that Israel would continue with its five-month-old policy of restraint in Gaza until the position of Hamas as a whole became clearer.</p>
        <p>Hamas's military wing said it fired 30 rockets and 70 mortar shells at Israel on Tuesday. An Israeli Army spokesman said six rockets and eight mortars were launched over a period of about three hours in the early morning.</p>
        <p>The army spokesman said that according to security assessments, Hamas had intended to carry out what he termed ''a much larger terrorist attack'' under the cover of the rocket fire, but was thwarted by the army's quick response. The Israeli Air Force fired into open areas where the rockets had been launched, the spokesman said.</p>
        <p>The Israeli news media reported that the plan had been to kidnap another Israeli soldier. Cpl. Gilad Shalit, who was abducted by Palestinian militants from Gaza in a cross-border raid in June, is still believed to be held in Gaza. Hamas and two other organizations claimed responsibility for that operation.</p>
        <p>The army spokesman would not confirm or deny the reports of a new kidnapping attempt. But he pointed to a statement made in the morning by the Hamas military spokesman, Abu Obeideh, who said on Voice of Palestine radio: ''The cease-fire has been over for a long time, and Israel is responsible for that. We are ready to kidnap more and more, and kill more and more of your soldiers.''</p>
        <p>Hamas has demanded the release of hundreds of Palestinians in Israeli jails in return for Corporal Shalit.</p>
        <p>In recent months, informed observers have pointed to differences between the Hamas armed underground and some of the more moderate political leaders, who support the cease-fire, in part, because they are trying to win international support for the unity government. Although Mr. Radwan, the Hamas spokesman, said Tuesday that there were ''no disputes between the military and political wings,'' he made a distinction between the ''Hamas movement'' and members in the unity government, which has ''its own program and positions.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
