<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sabres Choose to Let Skates Do Their Talking</title>
    <meta content="25sabres" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/sports/hockey/25sabres.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842763"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Buffalo Sabres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Buffalo Sabres</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Avery, Sean</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E4DA143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sabres Choose to Let Skates Do Their Talking</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sabres Choose to Let Skates Do Their Talking</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT HIGGINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Higgins, Matt</byline>
      <dateline>BUFFALO, April 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Known for their speed on the ice, the Buffalo Sabres have chosen to take a more cautious approach off it in a budding war of words with the Rangers.</p>
        <p>The Sabres and the Rangers will play Game 1 of their Eastern Conference semifinal series here Wednesday night. After practice Tuesday at HSBC Arena, the Sabres were asked repeatedly about negative remarks made Monday by Rangers Coach Tom Renney and forward Sean Avery.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Known for their speed on the ice, the Buffalo Sabres have chosen to take a more cautious approach off it in a budding war of words with the Rangers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Known for their speed on the ice, the Buffalo Sabres have chosen to take a more cautious approach off it in a budding war of words with the Rangers.</p>
        <p>The Sabres and the Rangers will play Game 1 of their Eastern Conference semifinal series here Wednesday night. After practice Tuesday at HSBC Arena, the Sabres were asked repeatedly about negative remarks made Monday by Rangers Coach Tom Renney and forward Sean Avery.</p>
        <p>Renney expressed doubts that the Sabres, who finished with the league's best record during the regular season, were the ''cream of the crop.'' And the voluble Avery said he would be out to ''hurt'' the Sabres.</p>
        <p>''It's psychological warfare,'' Buffalo goaltender Ryan Miller said. ''I don't think anybody in here is going to play that game.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''We're just going to worry about hockey. We're not going to worry about the off-ice, in-between-whistles stuff, which is apparently what they've already started.''</p>
        <p>Several Sabres echoed Miller's statements, demonstrating an emotional reservoir to complement the depth of their roster, which Buffalo relied on during the regular season and in its opening-round playoff series against the Islanders. But such measured responses were also a notable contrast to the swarming style the Sabres have used on the ice with such success this season.</p>
        <p>On Friday, after his team was eliminated by Buffalo in five games, Islanders Coach Ted Nolan was asked if the Sabres' speed was the difference. ''I don't know,'' he said. ''We meet all kinds of fast teams, and on the attack they send four guys. You're on your toes all the time. Definitely their speed was a factor.''</p>
        <p>If Nolan seemed at a loss to explain what happened to his team, he was not alone.</p>
        <p>Buffalo has baffled opponents all season. The Sabres won their first 10 games and jumped to the top of the standings. They occupied that perch virtually the entire season and ended up winning the Presidents' Trophy for finishing with the league's best record (53-22-7).</p>
        <p>What has made the Sabres so hard for opponents is their ability to use four forward lines and three defensive pairings, each capable of scoring and playing competent defense.</p>
        <p>Because of his team's depth, Sabres Coach Lindy Ruff has often taken the unusual approach of not matching his players to counter the opposition's top line. Instead, teams are forced to try to match the Sabres, which is a difficult task because they do not have a true No. 1 line.</p>
        <p>During the regular season, Buffalo led the N.H.L. with 308 goals by using a balanced attack. A league-leading four players, spread over three lines, scored 30 goals or more.</p>
        <p>Daniel Brière, who scored 32 and led the team with 95 points, centers a line with wing Jason Pominville, who had 34 goals. Wing Thomas Vanek, who led Buffalo with 43 goals, plays on another line. Chris Drury, who had 37 goals during the regular season and a team-leading 4 in the series against the Islanders, is on yet another line.</p>
        <p>Forwards Maxim Afinogenov and Tim Connolly, who missed significant time because of injuries, are also capable of scoring. Afinogenov had a goal and three assists against the Islanders. Connolly returned this month from a concussion sustained in last year's playoffs.</p>
        <p>Dainius Zubrus, acquired from the Washington Capitals at the trade deadline in February, had five assists against the Islanders.</p>
        <p>Buffalo won all four regular-season games against the Rangers, by a combined score of 18-12. Two of the victories came in overtime and one in a shootout. They last met Dec. 1.</p>
        <p>To prevent a repeat in the playoffs, Renney said Tuesday, the Rangers will need to match the Sabres' speed on offense and have all five skaters help on defense.</p>
        <p>Renney suggested that he would match Buffalo's four-line rotation with four Rangers lines. And above all, he stressed aggressive play.</p>
        <p>''We want to be proactive,'' he said. ''To sit back and watch them is fatal.''</p>
        <p>If Buffalo has a weakness, it is its power play. The Sabres ranked 17th in the league during the regular season, converting 17.4 percent of its chances.</p>
        <p>The Sabres are at their best on rushes at even strength. They quickly make the transition from defense to offense, with the defensemen often joining the rush.</p>
        <p>The Sabres are able to take such risks because of their speed in getting back on defense -- and their confidence in Miller, who set a franchise record with 40 victories this season.</p>
        <p>In their series against the Islanders, the Sabres appeared to sleepwalk through long stretches. That could change against the Rangers, who played an agitating, physical style in sweeping the Atlanta Thrashers, 4-0, in their first-round series.</p>
        <p>''You've got to tend to hate your opposition,'' Ruff said Tuesday. ''Get in and start hating them.''</p>
        <p>Asked if he hated the Rangers, Ruff said: ''I'm starting to. It is a good thing to develop a little bit of emotion and passion for your opposition, and things that they've said already about us, that's good. I like that.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
