<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Alcatel-Lucent Warns of Continued Losses</title>
    <meta content="25alcatel" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/technology/25alcatel.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842816"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Alcatel SA</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E0D9143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="514" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Alcatel-Lucent Warns of Continued Losses</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Alcatel-Lucent Warns of Continued Losses</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES KANTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kanter, James</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, April 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alcatel-Lucent, the telecommunications equipment giant, warned investors Tuesday of continued losses and weak sales, casting doubt about the long-term outlook for the company four months after completing a trans-Atlantic merger.</p>
        <p>In the unexpected announcement, Alcatel-Lucent said first-quarter operating losses would be about 260 million euros ($353 million) and that sales would drop about 12 percent, to 3.9 billion euros -- the second consecutive quarterly decline -- prompting a drop in share prices.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The warning cast doubt about the long-term outlook for the company four months after completing a trans-Atlantic merger.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Alcatel-Lucent, the telecommunications equipment giant, warned investors Tuesday of continued losses and weak sales, casting doubt about the long-term outlook for the company four months after completing a trans-Atlantic merger.</p>
        <p>In the unexpected announcement, Alcatel-Lucent said first-quarter operating losses would be about 260 million euros ($353 million) and that sales would drop about 12 percent, to 3.9 billion euros -- the second consecutive quarterly decline -- prompting a drop in share prices.</p>
        <p>But shares later made a strong recovery, closing up 3.4 percent, reflecting upbeat sentiment among some analysts about the company's orders and growth.</p>
        <p>Even so, analysts said the results showed that the combination of Alcatel of Paris and Lucent of Murray Hill, N.J., was being dogged by overlapping product lines and weak demand for wireless telecommunications equipment in a fast-changing market.</p>
        <p>''It's still a pretty poor result,'' said Thomas Langer, an analyst with West LB in Düsseldorf, Germany, who had predicted an operating loss of about 9 million euros this quarter, far less than the forecast issued Tuesday.</p>
        <p>''A few people have a doomsday scenario, but I think we need another four quarters before we can give a sensible judgment,'' Mr. Langer said.</p>
        <p>Others attributed the losses directly to the merger, saying the alliance had done little to refresh an inadequate range of products developed by Alcatel and Lucent to run high-speed mobile networks.</p>
        <p>''The merger has all the ingredients of being a disaster,'' said Per Lindberg, an analyst with Dresdner Kleinwort in London. Alcatel-Lucent was ''the combination of second-tier offerings, none of which are competitively placed, or strong enough to compete against Ericsson and Nokia.''</p>
        <p>Efforts to develop new products would be expensive and probably interrupted by clashes between French and American managers, Mr. Lindberg warned.</p>
        <p>The chief executive, Patricia F. Russo, said in a statement that she would present more details when official results were released May 11, including an outlook for 2007.</p>
        <p>''We are making good progress in terms of our integration,'' Ms. Russo said.</p>
        <p>Savings from combining businesses belonging to Alcatel, Lucent and Nortel ''have not yet been fully realized,'' but she said that she was ''confident in our ability to resume growth as the year progresses.''</p>
        <p>Half of the 260 million euro operating loss was the result of ''unusual significant items,'' the company said, without giving further details.</p>
        <p>Phil Kendall, the director of global wireless practice for Strategy Analytics, said Alcatel-Lucent was right to be cautious about which product lines to discard before jeopardizing important relationships with major clients in its established markets, like Cingular, Verizon and France Télécom.</p>
        <p>''It's not an easy process,'' Mr. Kendall said, adding that he was confident of better results by the end of 2007. Executives had to make choices about ''who they can afford to annoy,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Alcatel chief executive, Serge Tchuruk, agreed in April to acquire Lucent in a deal valued at around $11 billion to create the world's biggest telephone equipment maker.</p>
        <p>At a shareholders' meeting in September, Mr. Tchuruk said that the two companies were largely complementary, but he acknowledged that cultural issues could arise.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
