<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Host Dials Down, and Bush Speaks Up</title>
    <meta content="25teevee" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/25/arts/25teevee.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842866"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE TV WATCH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stanley, Alessandra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rose, Charlie</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Charlie Rose Show (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rose, Charlie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E0D8143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="703" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Host Dials Down, and Bush Speaks Up</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Host Dials Down, and Bush Speaks Up</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALESSANDRA STANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stanley, Alessandra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alessandra Stanley The TV Watch column says Pres Bush looked more at ease in appearance on Charlie Rose talk show than he usually does in interviews, but says he did not offer any revelations about his showdown with Congress over financing for more troops in Iraq; says Rose created confortable ambience in which Bush spoke forcefully and at length about Iraq (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Charlie Rose is a talk show host known for long and rambling questions. President Bush is famous for his short, Texas-terse answers.</p>
        <p>On last night's show, the two men reversed roles. Mr. Bush spoke forcefully and at length about Iraq. Mr. Rose was succinct.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Tuesday night’s Charlie Rose show, President Bush spoke forcefully and at length about Iraq.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Charlie Rose is a talk show host known for long and rambling questions. President Bush is famous for his short, Texas-terse answers.</p>
        <p>On last night's show, the two men reversed roles. Mr. Bush spoke forcefully and at length about Iraq. Mr. Rose was succinct.</p>
        <p>It was the closest Mr. Bush has come to the kind of winding declamations that Richard M. Nixon delivered to the British interviewer David Frost in 1977 and that are now resurrected on Broadway in ''Frost/Nixon,'' a play by Peter Morgan. Mr. Morgan, who was one of Mr. Rose's guests on Monday, told the host that American audiences would see parallels ''between presidents facing the wrath of a country that feels that in their name, bad decisions were made.''</p>
        <p>Actually, Mr. Bush looked more at ease than he usually does in interviews, but he did not offer any revelations about his showdown with Congress over financing for additional troops or his support for his embattled attorney general, Alberto R. Gonzales. He mostly expanded on positions he had staked out in the past. It was his wordiness that spoke volumes.</p>
        <p>The administration is under attack by Democrats and some Republicans, and Mr. Bush is increasingly described by his critics as isolated and out of touch. To counter that image, Mr. Bush turned to one of his least favorite pastimes: explaining himself to a reporter in front of a camera. Mr. Bush was fairly candid about why he decided to spend almost an hour defending his policies on public television, a venue that many conservatives mistrust as too liberal.</p>
        <p>''I do think it's important for me to explain to your listeners one more time, if I might, why I made the decision I made,'' Mr. Bush said. ''I believe that if Iraq were to fall apart, and there were to be a vacuum, into that vacuum would come extremist elements.'' He continued from there, explaining his concerns about a regional conflagration with less restraint and more dependent clauses than usual.</p>
        <p>It was Mr. Bush's first in-depth interview since a round of television appearances he made after announcing in January that he would send more troops to Iraq. As the two men sat face to face in a room in the Waldorf-Astoria, Mr. Rose raised the issue of military buildup almost casually, saying, ''How is what's sometimes called 'the surge' going?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's answer was mixed. ''The good news is that sectarian death is down in Baghdad,'' he replied. ''The bad news is that spectacular car bombs still go off, in a way that tends to shake the confidence of the Iraqi people that their government can protect them.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rose asked his guest about Senator John McCain's admission that he had no ''Plan B'' if the administration's current strategy failed. Mr. Bush replied, somewhat grimly, ''The Plan B is to make Plan A work.'' But he went on to assure Mr. Rose that his administration constantly reassessed its plans and decision-making.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush chose Mr. Rose over other interviewers for the obvious reason: the courtly host does not traffic in hectoring, Mike Wallace-style interrogations, instead giving his guests room to free-associate and set their own agenda. And sometimes, that is more effective than cross-examination. Mr. Rose did not wring any secrets or expressions of regret from Mr. Bush, but he gave viewers a glimpse of what this president sounds like when he talks to a visitor behind closed doors, when the cameras are off.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rose is a Larry King for Mensa members; he is more genteel and cultivated than his brash CNN rival, but he, too, conducts a conversation, not an interview. His drawn-out questions come out pell-mell -- sometimes bland, sometimes probing and sometimes even highly personal, but in no particular order.</p>
        <p>Mostly, Mr. Rose is a facilitator, creating a comfortable ambience where important people and opinion-makers can speak at length and make more than one point. Dick Cavett in his heyday was wittier and more penetrating, but for viewers interested in thoughtful talk, Mr. Rose's stark studio is the best place in town.</p>
        <p>For presidents who want to reassure viewers that they think long and hard before they act, it is the only game in town.</p>
        <p>THE TV WATCH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
