<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hughes Did Not Hear First Call to the Mound</title>
    <meta content="25pins" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842846"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E4D8143EF936A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="742" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hughes Did Not Hear First Call to the Mound</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>ST. PETERSBURG, Fla., April 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Yankees called Phil Hughes on Monday to tell him he was going to the major leagues, Hughes was in a mall eating lunch with his teammates. He did not feel his cellphone vibrate.</p>
        <p>So Dave Eiland, the pitching coach for Class AAA Scranton-Wilkes-Barre, called Hughes's friend Tyler Clippard, a pitcher who was eating with Hughes, and Clippard handed him the phone. That was how Hughes got the only call to the big leagues he expects to receive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Yankees called Phil Hughes on Monday to tell him he was going to the major leagues, Hughes was in a mall eating lunch with his teammates. He did not feel his cellphone vibrate.</p>
        <p>So Dave Eiland, the pitching coach for Class AAA Scranton-Wilkes-Barre, called Hughes's friend Tyler Clippard, a pitcher who was eating with Hughes, and Clippard handed him the phone. That was how Hughes got the only call to the big leagues he expects to receive.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to go up there and pitch to the best of my ability,'' Hughes told reporters in Scranton on Tuesday. ''And, no, I don't have any intention of coming back.''</p>
        <p>Hughes, 20, said he would probably leave 30 to 50 tickets for friends and family flying in from California for his start Thursday night. Two of his coaches from Foothill High School will be there, but the head coach, Gary Fishel, has to stay behind in Santa Ana to run practice.</p>
        <p>''We're going to get done early for sure,'' Fishel said in a telephone interview. ''I'm going to find a way to end practice at 4 and find somewhere to watch the game. A lot of the guys are excited. They were freshmen when he was a senior here.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees drafted Hughes in the first round in 2004, and Fishel said he was not surprised to see him advance to the majors so quickly.</p>
        <p>''He's got great ability, but a lot of people do,'' Fishel said. ''But his mental makeup was way beyond a high school kid. He was coming out like a college pitcher. I don't know if I could have predicted three years, but I thought it could happen.''</p>
        <p>Fishel described Hughes as no-nonsense in everything from the classroom to the practice field. He said Hughes was the same way when they spoke this week after his promotion to the Yankees. Hughes described his schedule as if it were nothing special.</p>
        <p>''It's funny,'' Fishel said. ''He was the same Phil.''</p>
        <p>Jason Giambi, who compared Hughes to a young Roger Clemens during spring training, said Hughes could have the kind of immediate impact that Tim Hudson, Mark Mulder and Barry Zito had with the Oakland Athletics. All three of them were Giambi's teammates when he played for the A's.</p>
        <p>''The kid's got great makeup to be up here, and, definitely, he can help us win,'' Giambi said. ''I know he's young, and you've got to be careful with him, but he can make a difference -- fast. He's got one of those arms like you saw when Hudson, Mulder and Zito came up. He's definitely a difference-maker already.''</p>
        <p>The Toronto Blue Jays lineup that Hughes will face will probably include Frank Thomas, who was in the Chicago White Sox lineup when Mike Mussina made his major league debut for the Orioles on Aug. 4, 1991. Thomas homered against Mussina for the only run of the game.</p>
        <p>''Hopefully, he'll do better,'' Mussina said. ''Hopefully, we'll score.''</p>
        <p>Mussina will start for Class AA Trenton on Friday, when he will test his strained left hamstring. After that, his next start would be for the Yankees, and he could take Hughes's spot.</p>
        <p>Of course, by midseason, the Yankees hope to have Roger Clemens in their rotation, too. But Clemens is still at least a month from deciding whether to pitch this season.</p>
        <p>''I expect him to make a decision by the end of May,'' Clemens' agent, Randy Hendricks, said in an e-mail message. ''We aren't close to a decision.''</p>
        <p>RODRIGUEZ WANTS TO STAY -- Alex Rodriguez could always change his mind. But for now, he continues to say he will remain with the Yankees and not opt out of his contract for the possibility of a longer deal with another team.</p>
        <p>Rodriguez is owed $81 million for the next three seasons but can choose to become a free agent this winter. Meeting with reporters before batting practice Tuesday, Rodriguez was asked if he would still want to return, even if other teams were willing to make him a longer-term offer in free agency.</p>
        <p>''I want to stay in New York, no matter what,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As for the idea of challenging Barry Bonds's single-season home run record of 73, set in 2001, Rodriguez said it was too early to consider. Rodriguez had 14 homers through the Yankees' first 18 games. Bonds had 8 through the first 18 games in 2001.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
