<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Consortium Buys Control Of Italy's Phone Giant</title>
    <meta content="30telecom" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/business/worldbusiness/30telecom.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844023"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Telefonica SA</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Telecom Italia Spa</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E2DC133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1139" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Consortium Buys Control Of Italy's Phone Giant</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Consortium Buys Control of Italy’s Phone Giant</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VICTORIA BURNETT and PETER KIEFER; Victoria Burnett reported from Madrid and Peter Kiefer from Rome. Michael J. de la Merced contributed reporting from New York.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burnett, Victoria; Kiefer, Peter</byline>
      <dateline>MADRID, April 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Telefónica of Spain and a group of Italian investors agreed on Saturday to pay 4.1 billion euros ($5.6 billion) for a controlling 18 percent stake in Telecom Italia, allowing the Spanish telecommunications giant to expand into the Italian market and extend its presence in Latin America.</p>
        <p>The deal ends months of speculation about the future of Telecom Italia, whose suitors had included AT&amp;T, and it represents a setback for Telefónica's arch rival América Móvil, owned by the Mexican tycoon Carlos Slim Helú.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A deal may ensure an Italian face remains on Telecom Italia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Telefónica of Spain and a group of Italian investors agreed on Saturday to pay 4.1 billion euros ($5.6 billion) for a controlling 18 percent stake in Telecom Italia, allowing the Spanish telecommunications giant to expand into the Italian market and extend its presence in Latin America.</p>
        <p>The deal ends months of speculation about the future of Telecom Italia, whose suitors had included AT&amp;T, and it represents a setback for Telefónica's arch rival América Móvil, owned by the Mexican tycoon Carlos Slim Helú.</p>
        <p>Despite the involvement of Telefónica, the deal also appears to maintain the Italian-majority ownership of the country's former monopoly phone company.</p>
        <p>The deal is the latest in a series of cross-border sales in Europe. Barclays of Britain is battling a rival group of Scottish, Spanish and Belgian banks for control of ABN Amro, the Dutch banking giant, in what would be one of the biggest deals ever. And this month, PPR, the French luxury goods conglomerate, began a friendly $7 billion offer for Puma, the German sportswear maker.</p>
        <p>But European protectionism has not died out completely: a $57 billion bid by E.On, a major German energy company, for its Spanish rival Endesa was blocked by Spanish regulators. (A competing bid by the Spanish construction giant Acciona and the Italian energy company Enel has been approved by the regulators.)</p>
        <p>Telefónica will team up with the Italian insurer Generali, the Italian banks Intesa Sanpaolo and Mediobanca, and the Benetton family to buy Olimpia, an investment vehicle that holds 18 percent of Telecom Italia's stock, from Pirelli, the Italian tire maker, the companies said. Olimpia has the right to nominate 80 percent of Telecom Italia's board.</p>
        <p>Telefónica will pay 2.3 billion euros ($3.14 billion) for a 42 percent stake in a new investment vehicle, referred to as Telco, which will combine the Olimpia holding with another 5.6 percent of Telecom Italia's shares, already owned by the Italian partners.</p>
        <p>The agreement allows Telefónica to enter Telecom Italia's capital while limiting its power and keeping an Italian face on the company -- a formula designed to win approval from Rome, whose efforts to keep Telecom Italia in Italian hands have drawn ire from foreign capitals.</p>
        <p>''It's good to see that Italian financial institutions have shown a willingness to make a commitment,'' Romano Prodi, the Italian prime minister, said on the Italian news channel Sky Tg24 before the agreement became official.</p>
        <p>Mr. Prodi had called for Italian banks to bid for the Telecom Italia stake as part of a strategy to retain Italian control, but he told the Agence France-Presse on Sunday that he had not intervened in the deal reached on Saturday.</p>
        <p>Intesa Sanpaolo said in a statement that the partners would be bound by a shareholders' pact aimed at ensuring a balance between the Italians and the Spanish investor. For example, Telefónica will have the right to nominate only two members of the Telecom Italia board of 21, and its Italian investors must approve the appointment of the chairman.</p>
        <p>Telefónica, which is paying 25 percent over the market price for the Telecom Italia shares, said the agreement would give it a foothold in Italy and strengthen its presence in Latin America. Telecom Italia's mobile division, TIM, has 26 percent of the Brazilian mobile market.</p>
        <p>Telefónica also has a 50 percent stake in the Brazilian mobile operator Vivo, which is half-owned by Portugal Telecom and has 28 percent of the domestic market. Management of Vivo and TIM in Brazil would remain independent of one another.</p>
        <p>Telefónica and Telecom Italia will have an exclusive industrial and strategic alliance, according to people familiar with the details of the deal, which will seek cost savings by pooling resources on research and development, sharing communications networks and buying assets jointly.</p>
        <p>''This could be a very good investment, if Telefónica is allowed to exercise significant influence at Telecom Italia,'' Glen Spencer-Chapman, an analyst at Ibersecurities in Madrid, told Bloomberg News.</p>
        <p>The Italian government's preference for an Italian solution for Telecom Italia angered American officials and has drawn scrutiny from Brussels. AT&amp;T withdrew its bid of 2.7 billion euros ($3.68 billion) this month for the Pirelli stake -- for which it had joined forces with Mr. Slim -- citing ''regulatory uncertainties.''</p>
        <p>In a letter to an Italian newspaper following AT&amp;T's decision, Ronald Spogli, the United States ambassador to Rome, accused the government of erecting barriers to foreign investors and suggested that the country's poor economic growth was linked to protectionism.</p>
        <p>''It would be best to focus less on who wants to invest and more on the fact that Italy is in last position among European countries in terms of growth of G.D.P., salaries and productivity,'' Spogli wrote in Corriere della Sera, an Italian newspaper.</p>
        <p>Paolo Gentiloni, Italy's minister of communications, denied ''any form of intervention'' in the deal by the Italian government, saying Rome had simply ''tried to indicate the general interest of the country'' in Telecom Italia's future. Maurizio Gasparri, an opposition senator and a former minister of communications, said the government's ''grave and incorrect interference'' in the bid had been ''greatly damaging.''</p>
        <p>Linda Lanzillotta, an economist at the Roma Tre university, said the deal was ''good in terms of the perceptions of the European Union, and it's certainly a step forward for Italy.''</p>
        <p>She dismissed the notion that there was general protectionism in the Italian telecommunications sector, pointing out that several foreign providers are already present in the country.</p>
        <p>The deal marks a change in the fortunes of Spanish companies trying to get a foothold in Italy.</p>
        <p>Some had previously complained of protectionism and prejudice on corporate boards. The Spanish infrastructure company Abertis and the Italian highways operator Autostrade blamed government opposition for the collapse last year of their planned merger, and the Spanish banking groups Santander and BBVA were thwarted in efforts to buy into the Italian banking sector.</p>
        <p>Some commentators viewed the Telecom Italia agreement as a payback for Spain's decision last month to let the Italian energy company Enel a controversial, last-minute takeover bid for Endesa, the Spanish energy giant. The deal effectively spoiled an existing bid by E.On of Germany.</p>
        <p>''One should wonder if there's a relationship between the premium Telefónica pays to enter Italy and the one that Enel paid in Spain,'' the Italian newspaper Il Sole 24 Ore said in an editorial published Sunday.</p>
        <p>To finance the deal, Telefónica will be able to use proceeds from the 2.8-billion-euro sale of Airwave O2, the British radio network, and it hopes to raise as much as 3 billion euros more from the sale of a stake in Endemol, the Dutch television producer behind the ''Big Brother'' show. Telefónica has said it hopes to sell the stake by the summer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
