<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Boss May Need Time to Regain Firing Form</title>
    <meta content="30chass" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/sports/baseball/30chass.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844075"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Steinbrenner, George M 3d</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Torre, Joe</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E7DA133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="902" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Boss May Need Time to Regain Firing Form</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Steinbrenner May Need Time to Regain Firing Form</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>George Steinbrenner's April managerial scorecard:</p>
        <p>1982 -- Bob Lemon, 14 games.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>You have to go all the way back to 1991 to find a clearly fired Yankees manager, so George Steinbrenner may be out of shape with the procedure if he decides to jettison Joe Torre.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>George Steinbrenner's April managerial scorecard:</p>
        <p>1982 -- Bob Lemon, 14 games.</p>
        <p>1985 -- Yogi Berra, 16 games.</p>
        <p>2007 -- Joe Torre, 23 games?</p>
        <p>Today is the last day of April, and Steinbrenner has a few hours left in which to jettison Torre as the Yankees' manager and put him in the class with Lemon and Berra. He fired them despite having said that they would keep their jobs the entire season no matter what.</p>
        <p>Steinbrenner made no such pronouncement about Torre before this season, but that won't stop him from making a change if he feels one is warranted.</p>
        <p>No signs have emerged from Tampa, Fla., that Steinbrenner will change managers. But the talk intensified yesterday after the Yankees lost another game to Boston, their fifth loss in six games and two weekends with the Red Sox. Steinbrenner was unhappy with the sweep in Boston last weekend, and he was unhappy with the results of the series at Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>In Game 6 yesterday, the Yankees started their No. 1 pitcher, Chien-Ming Wang, against Boston's No. 5 starter, Julián Tavárez, and they still lost. That's enough to curdle the milk in anyone's oatmeal.</p>
        <p>Steinbrenner did not react reflexively yesterday, but he didn't have to. Today is a day off for the Yankees, and Steinbrenner has fired managers on days off before.</p>
        <p>He hasn't fired a manager since 1995, and even that act was not a clear-cut dismissal. There was some suspicion then that Buck Showalter wanted to be fired and induced that change.</p>
        <p>You have to go all the way back to Stump Merrill in 1991 to find a clearly fired Yankees manager, so Steinbrenner may be out of shape with the procedure. He may need time to work up to it. Add, too, the fact that Steinbrenner is more than 15 years older than he was then. In his condition today, he may need time to generate the psychic energy needed for a change.</p>
        <p>Until he makes a change or the Yankees emerge from their awful start, people will talk.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to say it's distracting, because when the game starts, that's all I'm concerned with,'' Torre said yesterday after the team's eighth loss in nine games. ''But it's something else you have to deal with. I'm not happy about it. It's uncomfortable when people ask me if I think I'm going to be fired.''</p>
        <p>It's ludicrous that Torre's job status is in doubt. This is his 12th season as the Yankees' manager, and the team has won 10 division titles, including a league-record nine in a row.</p>
        <p>For Steinbrenner, though, 10 is not enough if his team starts the next season by losing 14 of the first 23 games, especially if the team hasn't won the World Series for six years.</p>
        <p>''The question I find comical is you haven't won a World Series since 2000,'' said Torre, who is in the last year of a three-year, $19.2 million contract. ''When I got here, we hadn't won a World Series since '78. Everybody's gotten spoiled, including us. But you know what happens when you work for George. He wants instant results, and sometimes when it doesn't happen, he has a tendency to do that.''</p>
        <p>The old Steinbrenner might have fired Torre after last weekend. But the Yankees are dealing with a different, less volatile owner, which is good for their psyches and their status.</p>
        <p>Torre says that he calls Steinbrenner every 10 days, give or take a day, and did so most recently after the Fenway fiasco.</p>
        <p>Saying he wasn't concerned about Steinbrenner's reaction to the slow start, Torre said: ''I called him on the heels of the sweep and he wasn't too happy. I didn't expect him to be, but I wasn't going to say, We lost; I'm afraid to call him.''</p>
        <p>General Manager Brian Cashman's job would also seem to be in jeopardy. He asked for and was given full authority over the baseball operation, and the 9-14 team is his.</p>
        <p>Has Cashman found any reason to fault Torre or himself for the awful April?</p>
        <p>''As far as I'm concerned,'' he said, ''I take full responsibility for this start because that's my job. This is the team I put together. If people are looking for blame, I say blame me.''</p>
        <p>If Steinbrenner decides to change managers, Cashman is believed to favor Joe Girardi as Torre's replacement. Steinbrenner, however, may favor Don Mattingly, the team's bench coach and former star player. Mattingly, though, doesn't see a reason or a need to change.</p>
        <p>''Joe deserves to manage,'' Mattingly said before the game. ''The way we're playing has nothing to do with the manager. Changing managers isn't going to change one thing. Joe has respect in the clubhouse. Joe has guys believing in him. If you have a manager you don't believe in, that's one thing. They believe in this guy and they should. He deserves all that respect. He gives it and he deserves to get it back.''</p>
        <p>Mattingly never played for Torre, having retired before Torre's first season. But he played for plenty of other managers in his 14-year career.</p>
        <p>''I played for Billy three times, I played for Lou twice, I played for Stump, Yogi, Dallas Green, Bucky, Buck,'' Mattingly said. ''There was somebody in September '82, when I was a September call-up, maybe Clyde King.''</p>
        <p>Torre followed Mattingly's last manager, Showalter, and now Mattingly could follow Torre.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
