<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>French Presidential Candidates Make Bids for Centrist's Support</title>
    <meta content="30france" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/world/europe/30france.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844071"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bennhold, Katrin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sarkozy, Nicolas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bayrou, Francois</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Royal, Segolene</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">France</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bayrou, Francois</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Sarkozy, Nicolas</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Royal, Segolene</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00EEDB133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="400" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>French Presidential Candidates Make Bids for Centrist's Support</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">French Presidential Candidates Make Bids for Centrist’s Support</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATRIN BENNHOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bennhold, Katrin</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, April 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Defeated centrist candidate Francois Bayrou and his supporters are being courted by two frontrunners in French presidential election; Nicolas Sarkozy, conservative, offers ministerial posts in his future administration to members of Bayrou's party; Socialist candidate Segolene Royal hints that she might ask Bayrou to be her prime minister; latest opinion polls give Sarkozy lead over Royal, but gap appears to be shrinking; Bayrou's nearly seven million centrist voters could swing election; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the French presidential race tightening a week before the runoff vote, Nicolas Sarkozy, the conservative front-runner, on Sunday stepped up his efforts to court supporters of a defeated centrist candidate by offering ministerial posts in his future administration to members of that centrist party.</p>
        <p>Not to be outdone, Ségolène Royal, the Socialist candidate, hinted that she might even ask François Bayrou, the centrist leader, to be her prime minister.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Both finalists have been aggressively courting supporters of François Bayrou’s centrist party, aware that they are decisive to the outcome of the runoff on Sunday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the French presidential race tightening a week before the runoff vote, Nicolas Sarkozy, the conservative front-runner, on Sunday stepped up his efforts to court supporters of a defeated centrist candidate by offering ministerial posts in his future administration to members of that centrist party.</p>
        <p>Not to be outdone, Ségolène Royal, the Socialist candidate, hinted that she might even ask François Bayrou, the centrist leader, to be her prime minister.</p>
        <p>''I'm not ruling anything out,'' Ms. Royal told Canal Plus, a major television channel, in an interview. She added that once elected, she would be prepared to amend her presidential platform with some centrist ideas.</p>
        <p>In an interview on the same channel, Mr. Sarkozy emphasized the similarities between his economic platform and that of Mr. Bayrou.</p>
        <p>''We could work perfectly together,'' said Mr. Sarkozy, a former interior minister. ''We can perfectly govern together. François Bayrou cannot drive his political family into an alliance with the far left.''</p>
        <p>A week after he was defeated in the first round of the election, Mr. Bayrou remained in the spotlight of the election campaign as no other ''third man'' in a French election has ever managed. Both finalists have been aggressively courting Mr. Bayrou's nearly seven million centrist voters, aware that they are decisive to the outcome of the election next Sunday.</p>
        <p>The latest opinion polls gave Mr. Sarkozy a lead over Ms. Royal, but the gap appeared to be shrinking. According to a poll by the IFOP institute, published Sunday in Le Journal du Dimanche, a weekly newspaper, 52.5 percent of voting-age adults support Mr. Sarkozy, compared with 47.5 percent for Ms. Royal. A week earlier, Mr. Sarkozy was eight percentage points ahead in an IFOP poll.</p>
        <p>The most recent poll, which was conducted Thursday and Friday, was based on telephone interviews with 886 people. Because public opinion polls in France use quota samples instead of probability samples, a margin of error cannot be calculated.</p>
        <p>One day after Ms. Royal engaged in a 100-minute televised debate with Mr. Bayrou, Mr. Sarkozy tried to move the attention to the official debate between him and Ms. Royal that will be broadcast live on national television on Wednesday. Ms. Royal told Canal Plus that she had been preparing by studying past presidential debates. Mr. Sarkozy likened it to riding a bicycle up the Alps in the toughest leg of the Tour de France.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
