<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Despite Options, Giants Turn to Kiwanuka to Address a Need</title>
    <meta content="30giants" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/sports/football/30giants.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844084"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Football League</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Kiwanuka, Mathias</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Reese, Jerry</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE6DA133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="810" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Despite Options, Giants Turn to Kiwanuka to Address a Need</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Despite Options, Giants Turn to Kiwanuka to Address a Need</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN BRANCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Branch, John</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., April 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Brown linebacker Zak DeOssie visited the Giants last week, he was given a tour of the locker room at Giants Stadium.</p>
        <p>He called his father, Steve, who served the team as a scrappy run-plugging linebacker and a long snapper from 1989 to 1993, and asked which locker was once his.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>None of the additions will arrive at training camp as projected starters, but the Giants hope several of their choices will eventually find the top of the depth chart.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Brown linebacker Zak DeOssie visited the Giants last week, he was given a tour of the locker room at Giants Stadium.</p>
        <p>He called his father, Steve, who served the team as a scrappy run-plugging linebacker and a long snapper from 1989 to 1993, and asked which locker was once his.</p>
        <p>''He directed me toward the locker, and I was looking inside of it,'' Zak DeOssie said. ''And he asked me over the phone if I could feel the greatness coming out of it.''</p>
        <p>The Giants waited until the fourth round of the N.F.L. draft to address what seemed to be the thinnest position on the roster. Then they took DeOssie, and praised him as a player not unlike his father, a viable backup and strong special-teams player with a possible long-range future as a starter.</p>
        <p>There was a reason the Giants did not view the need to draft an outside linebacker with much urgency, the way most onlookers outside Giants Stadium did. The Giants realized that they found a starting outside linebacker in last year's draft.</p>
        <p>They plan to move defensive end Mathias Kiwanuka, last year's first-round draft choice, to strongside linebacker, which is known as Sam in football parlance.</p>
        <p>''We already have him penciled in as our Sam linebacker, so linebacker wasn't a pressing need for us,'' General Manager Jerry Reese said.</p>
        <p>The Giants say Kiwanuka has the versatility to move up to stop the run and drop back to protect against the pass, and the burst to rush the passer. Mainly, they see the plan as a way to keep him on the field, rather than have him rotate with the starting ends, Michael Strahan and Osi Umenyiora.</p>
        <p>Kiwanuka, 6 feet 5 inches and 265 pounds, started nine games last season because of injuries at defensive end. He had 55 tackles, 4 sacks, 23 quarterback hurries, 2 interceptions and 2 forced fumbles.</p>
        <p>''There's no question he can make the transition to outside linebacker,'' Reese said.</p>
        <p>When the two-day N.F.L. draft ended Sunday afternoon, the Giants had eight new players, including tight end Kevin Boss from Western Oregon (fifth round), Oregon State offensive tackle Adam Koets (sixth), Arizona safety Michael Johnson and Marshall running back Ahmad Bradshaw (both in the seventh).</p>
        <p>The choice of DeOssie followed the central theme of Reese's first draft as general manager, taking over for the retired Ernie Accorsi. The Giants upgraded several shaky positions with players who piled up impressive statistics in college, predicting future potential with past production.</p>
        <p>''I think we got better at a lot of need positions,'' Reese said.</p>
        <p>None of the additions will arrive at training camp in July as projected starters, but the Giants hope several of the early choices work their way to the top of the depth chart by September.</p>
        <p>''They certainly are going to make a strong contribution, whether or not they are starters or however they fit,'' Coach Tom Coughlin said.</p>
        <p>On Saturday, the Giants held the 20th pick and selected Texas cornerback Aaron Ross, and they chose Southern California receiver Steve Smith in the second round. Their last move Saturday was selecting Penn State defensive tackle Jay Alford.</p>
        <p>The biggest hole remaining for the Giants is at left tackle, which has been vacant since February, when Reese cut the starter, Luke Petitgout, because of his big salary and growing injury problems.</p>
        <p>Koets is a long-range project, so the Giants, for now, have two options on the roster -- slide guard David Diehl to tackle and insert Rich Seubert at guard, or start Guy Whimper, a fourth-round draft choice last year who has not taken an offensive snap.</p>
        <p>The Giants are busy scanning the trade and free-agent markets.</p>
        <p>''There's some things that we can do to see if there's a left tackle available,'' Reese said. ''We'll keep looking for a left tackle.''</p>
        <p>DeOssie, 6-4 1/2 and 250 pounds, is initially set to be a backup for Kiwanuka. His father was part of the Giants' 1990 championship team, one with Coughlin and Patriots Coach Bill Belichick as assistant coaches. Steve DeOssie later played for New England, and Zak DeOssie was a Patriots ball boy.</p>
        <p>When the Patriots gave Oakland a fourth-round choice for receiver Randy Moss, the DeOssie family wondered if the Giants would call a few picks later. The phone did not ring, but word came through the television broadcast of the draft.</p>
        <p>''I broke down right when it happened,'' Zak DeOssie said. ''My old man was right next to me.''</p>
        <p>Steve DeOssie said that his son was roughly the same size that he was as a player, but far more athletic.</p>
        <p>''He loves the violence, loves the action, and loves the challenge,'' Steve DeOssie said. ''All those things we have in common. In terms of sheer athletic ability, there is very little similarity.</p>
        <p>''He is a thoroughbred, and I was a Clydesdale.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
