<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Maine Quietly Completes a Dominating Month</title>
    <meta content="30mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/sports/baseball/30mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844083"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Washington Nationals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Washington Nationals</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Maine, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E6DA133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="917" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Maine Quietly Completes a Dominating Month</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Maine Quietly Completes a Dominating Month for Mets</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shpigel, Ben</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Maybe John Maine is right when he swears that he has plenty of room for improvement. He does, after all, have only the second-lowest earned run average among major league starters. Time to get to work, John.</p>
        <p>''I'll see what I can do,'' Maine said with a wry smile.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pitcher John Maine punctuated his exceptional month Sunday by shutting out the Washington Nationals through seven innings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Maybe John Maine is right when he swears that he has plenty of room for improvement. He does, after all, have only the second-lowest earned run average among major league starters. Time to get to work, John.</p>
        <p>''I'll see what I can do,'' Maine said with a wry smile.</p>
        <p>For the moment, he'll have to settle for owning one of the most dominating Aprils by a pitcher in franchise history. He punctuated his exceptional month Sunday by shutting out the Washington Nationals through seven innings, making Carlos Beltrán's sixth-inning home run hold up in the Mets' 1-0 victory at R.F.K. Stadium.</p>
        <p>The Mets managed only three hits, and with runs at a premium all weekend, they called on Billy Wagner to finish off Maine's performance. He recorded his first save since April 13.</p>
        <p>''I forgot what those felt like,'' Wagner said.</p>
        <p>Like Wagner, a proud native of nearby Virginia, Maine limited the Nationals to three hits and struck out a career-high eight to raise his record to 4-0.</p>
        <p>Aside from his meager outing April 9 in the home opener, Maine has pitched at least seven innings in every start and has yet to allow more than two runs. Opponents are batting .159 against him, and his E.R.A. dropped to 1.35, a smidgen behind Atlanta's Tim Hudson (1.22).</p>
        <p>''He showed me again that he's getting better and better,'' Mets Manager Willie Randolph said. ''Each time out, he's getting stronger and stronger.''</p>
        <p>According to Stats LLC, only three Mets have entered May unbeaten with four or more victories and a lower E.R.A. than Maine: Frank Viola (1.32) in 1990, Jerry Koosman in 1968 (1.04) and 1973 (1.06) and Dwight Gooden (1.26) in the World Series championship season of 1986. That's it. No Tom Terrific or David Cone, no Tom Glavine or Al Leiter on that list.</p>
        <p>Julio Franco is perhaps one of the only players to have batted against all of the above pitchers (except Maine), and he passed on some much-welcomed advice during the seventh inning, the only time all game that Maine ran into trouble.</p>
        <p>After Austin Kearns banged a leadoff double, Maine walked Ryan Church, which brought out the pitching coach Rick Peterson. Then Franco, starting at first base for Carlos Delgado, came over, and he told Maine that he expected the next hitter, Jesús Flores, to bunt. And if Flores did, Franco told him, don't worry -- he'd throw out the runner at third.</p>
        <p>Sure enough, with Franco charging toward the plate, Flores bunted the first pitch toward him. Franco fielded it, whirled and, summoning the grace of his middle-infield days, nabbed Kearns at third by a step.</p>
        <p>''I told him,'' Franco said, recalling his conversation with Maine.</p>
        <p>With that out of the way, Maine fell behind, 2-0, on Chris Snelling but recovered to strike him out. Then he fell behind, 3-0, to Robert Fick. His next pitch, a fastball, seemed to miss the outside corner, but the home-plate umpire, Tony Randazzo, called it a strike, and a howl erupted from the fans in the lower bowl.</p>
        <p>Maine proceeded to blow a 93-mile-an-hour fastball by Fick for strike two, then a foul ball, then another 93-m.p.h. heater for strike three, setting off a burst of applause and hand-slapping in the Mets' dugout.</p>
        <p>The Mets avoided further trouble in the eighth when Aaron Heilman, who allowed a go-ahead run in the Mets' victory Saturday night, yielded consecutive singles to begin the inning. He retired the next two hitters before walking Kearns to load the bases. Out went Heilman, in came the left-hander Scott Schoeneweis, who got Church to ground out sharply to Franco and keep alive Maine's hopes of remaining unbeaten.</p>
        <p>In conversations about the game's best 25-and-younger pitchers, Maine's name rarely pops up at the beginning. This despite his excellent performance during the postseason last year when, among other things, he defeated the Cardinals to force a seventh game in the National League Championship Series.</p>
        <p>Maybe it is because of his low-key nature or how quickly success has come; last year at this time, Maine had not thrown his first pitch as a Met. But Peterson says Maine is on the cusp. As does Randolph, who said: ''If he keeps going, he's going to be up there soon. He's got a long way to go, but I like what I'm seeing.''</p>
        <p>Not Maine, though. He still has a lot more work to do. Always will, too.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Orlando Hernández flew to New York to have his right shoulder examined by team doctors after complaining of tightness before Sunday's game. General Manager Omar Minaya said that Hernández was still on track to make his scheduled start Monday against the Florida Marlins. If he cannot, the long reliever Aaron Sele, who threw 21 pitches Saturday night, is the probable in-house option. Chan Ho Park would be on turn to pitch for Class AAA New Orleans, but he is 3-1 with a 7.29 earned run average.  Second baseman José Valentín is scheduled for further testing in New York on his right knee Monday, perhaps indicating that the injury he sustained Saturday may be more serious than expected. ''It's too early to comment,'' Minaya said. ''When we get a final report, we'll be ready to announce something.'' If Valentín requires a stay on the disabled list, the Mets will probably recall Anderson Hernández, the New Orleans shortstop who, unlike the second baseman Rubén Gotay, is on their 40-man roster. Hernández has eight errors.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
