<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Who's Watching Your Money?</title>
    <meta content="30morgenthau" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/opinion/30morgenthau.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844066"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Comptroller of the Currency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morgenthau, Robert M (Dist Atty)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Subprime Lending</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Personal Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Personal Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E1DB133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="854" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Who's Watching Your Money?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Who’s Watching Your Money?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robert M. Morgenthau</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Morgenthau, Robert M (Dist Atty)</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by Manhattan Dist Atty Robert M Morgenthau disagrees with Supreme Court's recent ruling upholding regulation issued by Office of Comptroller of Currency that exempts subsidiaries of national banks from regulation by state banking authorities; says this ill-advised regulation makes comptroller exclusive regulator of these banks, even though office is financed almost entirely by banks it oversees; notes court ruling rejects arguments of attorneys general and bank regulators in all 50 states; says ruling will deal heavy blow to system of dual federal and state authority over national banks that has served country well for nearly 150 years; calls on Congress to amend National Bank Act to give proper regulatory role back to state banking authorities; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN a ruling this month, the United States Supreme Court upheld an ill-advised regulation issued by the Office of the Comptroller of the Currency that exempted subsidiaries of national banks from regulation by state banking authorities. This regulation makes the comptroller the exclusive regulator of these banks, even though the office is financed almost entirely by the banks it oversees.</p>
        <p>In the case, Watters v. Wachovia Bank, the court held that the National Bank Act barred Michigan's bank regulator from overseeing the activities of the mortgage-lending subsidiary of Wachovia, a national bank, even though the subsidiary itself was a state-chartered institution. The court thus rejected the arguments of the attorneys general and bank regulators in all 50 states.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The hands of state banking regulators have been tied when it comes to predatory mortgage lending by national banks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN a ruling this month, the United States Supreme Court upheld an ill-advised regulation issued by the Office of the Comptroller of the Currency that exempted subsidiaries of national banks from regulation by state banking authorities. This regulation makes the comptroller the exclusive regulator of these banks, even though the office is financed almost entirely by the banks it oversees.</p>
        <p>In the case, Watters v. Wachovia Bank, the court held that the National Bank Act barred Michigan's bank regulator from overseeing the activities of the mortgage-lending subsidiary of Wachovia, a national bank, even though the subsidiary itself was a state-chartered institution. The court thus rejected the arguments of the attorneys general and bank regulators in all 50 states.</p>
        <p>With the collapse of the subprime mortgage business front-page news, one might have hoped for more effective bank regulation. Instead, the hands of state banking regulators have been tied when it comes to predatory mortgage lending by national banks.</p>
        <p>This ruling, which will no doubt have implications for state regulation of car loans and other areas of consumer finance, dealt a heavy blow to the system of dual federal and state authority over national banks that has served this country well for nearly 150 years. Banks now have an added incentive to opt out of state systems and put themselves under the protection of the comptroller.</p>
        <p>I say ''protection'' because the comptroller has shown itself to be a timid regulator, even in the face of flagrant wrongdoing. After all, you can't bite the hand that feeds you.</p>
        <p>In 2004, the Permanent Subcommittee on Investigations of the United States Senate criticized the comptroller for doing a ''poor job'' of compelling Riggs Bank to comply with laws against money laundering. The comptroller failed to take enforcement action against Riggs -- which had helped Augusto Pinochet launder millions of dollars through secret offshore accounts -- even after learning that the bank had hid the Pinochet accounts from the comptroller itself for two years.</p>
        <p>Last year, the inspector general of the Treasury Department found that the comptroller had ''sent the wrong message to the banking industry'' by failing to take formal, public enforcement action against Wells Fargo Bank for deficiencies in its money laundering program over several years.</p>
        <p>And, last September, the Bank of America, a national bank, paid $7.5 million in penalties and costs in a settlement with the Manhattan District Attorney's Office; this followed an investigation that showed that the bank had ignored safeguards against money laundering in connection with the illegal transfer of $3 billion over two years through the account of a Uruguayan money transmitter at a Manhattan branch of the bank. The comptroller took no formal enforcement action against the bank.</p>
        <p>The comptroller's actions must not only be fair, they must be seen to be fair. Under the present system of financing, that is not possible. The comptroller gets no Congressional money. Ninety-six percent of the agency's revenues comes from assessments on the banks it regulates, 70 percent from the large banks. In 2001, Bank of America alone paid the comptroller more than $40 million a year in assessments, then 10 percent of the agency's annual budget.</p>
        <p>It is no wonder that the comptroller has not only failed to come down hard on its paymasters when they have misbehaved, but has also actively supported them, even at the expense of the banks' customers. The comptroller supported a suit by Bank of America and Wells Fargo to overturn a law passed by San Francisco and Santa Monica, Calif., banning certain A.T.M. fees; it sided with the same banks in their efforts to defeat a proposed ban on check-cashing fees in Texas; and it issued a ruling exempting car dealers that marketed car loans made by national banks from state motor vehicle finance laws.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, two of the nation's biggest banks, JPMorgan Chase and HSBC (an affiliate, incidentally, of HSBC Finance Corporation, one of the largest lenders in the subprime mortgage market) swapped their state charters for federal charters in 2004. The comptroller now supervises 14 of the nation's top 20 banks in asset size.</p>
        <p>There has to be a role for state regulators, who are independent of the comptroller, in overseeing the activities of the national banks conducted through subsidiaries. As history shows, regulators often become captives of the industry they are supposed to regulate -- even when they are not dependent on the industry for financial support. The Interstate Commerce Commission, which became the tool of the railroads and was abolished in 1995, is a case in point. We cannot afford to have a banking system that has one all-powerful federal regulator for the major banks and relegates the states to monitoring only the smaller institutions.</p>
        <p>Congress should amend the National Bank Act to give a proper regulatory role back to state banking authorities. With the public's confidence in the national government at a low ebb, this is not the time for the comptroller to pre-empt state bank regulation further. Perhaps more important, Congress should appropriate funds for the comptroller and free the office from its unseemly financial dependence on the major banks.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor Robert M. Morgenthau is the Manhattan district attorney.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Robert M. Morgenthau is the Manhattan district attorney.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
