<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Corzine to Leave Hospital Today, Earlier Than Expected</title>
    <meta content="30corzine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/nyregion/30corzine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844088"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seat Belts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seat Belts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E5DA133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="557" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Corzine to Leave Hospital Today, Earlier Than Expected</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Corzine to Make Early Exit From Hospital Monday</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chen, David</byline>
      <dateline>HOBOKEN, N.J., April 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Jon. S. Corzine will be released from a Camden hospital on Monday afternoon, 18 days after he was critically injured in a traffic accident, his office announced Sunday night.</p>
        <p>The release would come a day earlier than even Mr. Corzine had predicted late last week. On Friday, the governor told the Senate president, Richard J. Codey, who also is the acting governor, and Assembly Speaker Joseph J. Roberts Jr. that he expected to leave Cooper University Hospital on Tuesday or Wednesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Jon. S. Corzine will be released from a Camden hospital 18 days after he was critically injured in a traffic accident, his office announced.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Jon. S. Corzine will be released from a Camden hospital on Monday afternoon, 18 days after he was critically injured in a traffic accident, his office announced Sunday night.</p>
        <p>The release would come a day earlier than even Mr. Corzine had predicted late last week. On Friday, the governor told the Senate president, Richard J. Codey, who also is the acting governor, and Assembly Speaker Joseph J. Roberts Jr. that he expected to leave Cooper University Hospital on Tuesday or Wednesday.</p>
        <p>''He's ahead of the curve right now,'' Anthony Coley, Mr. Corzine's communications director, said Sunday night. ''Like most other patients who have been in the hospital for a while, he's ready to go home.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine lost half of the blood in his body and broke 11 ribs, his left femur, a clavicle, his sternum and a lower vertebra in the accident on April 12.</p>
        <p>It is unclear when Mr. Corzine will resume his duties as governor. He told Mr. Codey and Mr. Roberts that he would need a week to decide.</p>
        <p>Mr. Coley said it was possible that Mr. Corzine would speak to reporters briefly upon leaving the hospital. He has not spoken publicly since the accident, although during a five-minute photo shoot on Thursday, he told an Associated Press photographer, ''I'm the most blessed person who ever lived.''</p>
        <p>Home, for the foreseeable future, means Drumthwacket, the governor's official residence in Princeton, and not Mr. Corzine's home in a luxury apartment building here.</p>
        <p>State officials have been working to modify Drumthwacket, an 1835 Greek Revival mansion, to suit Mr. Corzine's needs while he embarks on a rehabilitation process that is expected to be long and painful, according to his doctors and aides.</p>
        <p>As part of his rehabilitation, a portable chairlift will be installed on Drumthwacket's center staircase from the ground floor to the private residence on the second floor. An exercise room on the second floor will be renovated to accommodate rehabilitation equipment, including a stationary bicycle. And the mansion's outdoor pool will be converted into a heated one for his physical therapy.</p>
        <p>In addition, Mr. Corzine will have a hospital bed installed in the mansion, and he will be attended by nurses and physical therapists.</p>
        <p>The total cost to taxpayers: zero. Mr. Corzine, a multimillionaire and former co-chairman of Goldman Sachs, is paying his own medical bills, even though he is eligible for insurance under the state plan.</p>
        <p>On the road, Mr. Corzine will use a modified GMC Savana van that he bought a few days ago. One of the seats has been removed to make traveling easier, Mr. Coley said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine was injured when his state vehicle, traveling at 91 miles per hour, 26 m.p.h. above the limit, crashed on the Garden State Parkway, just outside of Atlantic City. At the time of the accident, he was not wearing a seat belt, as state law requires.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine is expected to use a wheelchair for much of the time during the next several weeks. But in a sign of his quick progress, he began using crutches on Saturday, well ahead of when doctors had been predicting.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine still tires easily, Mr. Coley said. But on Saturday, Mr. Corzine, a sports fan, had plenty of energy to talk about the National Football League draft, Mr. Coley said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
