<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Playoff Experience Is on Devils' Side</title>
    <meta content="30devils" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/sports/hockey/30devils.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844045"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Ottawa Senators</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Ottawa Senators</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Langenbrunner, Jamie</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gionta, Brian</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E6DB133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Playoff Experience Is on Devils' Side</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Playoff Experience Is on Devils’ Side</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., April 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Travis Zajac, a 21-year-old rookie center for the Devils, retreated with his teammates to the locker room after the third period Saturday night. He was not quite sure what to expect when the door was closed.</p>
        <p>The Devils had lost a lead to the Ottawa Senators with 27 seconds left in regulation, extending the game into overtime, and Devils right wing Brian Gionta had been called for a hooking penalty at the end of regulation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the series moves to Ottawa, it has become clear that the Senators have more speed and skill. But the Devils have been through this before.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Travis Zajac, a 21-year-old rookie center for the Devils, retreated with his teammates to the locker room after the third period Saturday night. He was not quite sure what to expect when the door was closed.</p>
        <p>The Devils had lost a lead to the Ottawa Senators with 27 seconds left in regulation, extending the game into overtime, and Devils right wing Brian Gionta had been called for a hooking penalty at the end of regulation.</p>
        <p>Zajac, who was playing for the University of North Dakota in the N.C.A.A. Frozen Four last April, said he was somewhat agitated, especially because his line had wasted so many chances. The interesting part, however, was that no one else was agitated.</p>
        <p>''It's experience,'' Zajac said. ''They know that something like that goal is not getting to us.''</p>
        <p>Early in the second overtime period, Zajac chipped the puck to Jamie Langenbrunner, the right wing on his line, and Langenbrunner beat Senators goaltender Ray Emery on a breakaway to lift the Devils to a 3-2 victory in Game 2 of their Eastern Conference semifinal series.</p>
        <p>Langenbrunner's goal helped the Devils tie the best-of-seven series at one victory apiece. It was his 12th game-winning playoff goal -- and fourth in overtime -- in 120 postseason games.</p>
        <p>But Langenbrunner, a 31-year-old veteran from Cloquet, Minn., is not the only Devils player with a lot of playoff seasoning. Ten Devils who played in Saturday's game have at least 90 games of playoff experience. No one on the Senators has that much.</p>
        <p>''There's no panic in this locker room,'' Langenbrunner said. ''We all trust in each other to get the job done.''</p>
        <p>As the series moves to Ottawa, where Games 3 and 4 are to be played Monday and Wednesday, it has become clear that the Senators have more speed and skill. What the Devils have on their side is that they have been through this before.</p>
        <p>Six Devils have played in more than 100 playoff games. Goaltender Martin Brodeur, who turns 35 on Sunday, has played in 161 playoff games (winning 94 of them, as well as three Stanley Cups).</p>
        <p>After he allowed five goals in the Devils' lackluster loss to Ottawa in Game 1, Brodeur decided to use a new set of pads. For most goaltenders, taking out a new set of pads for a playoff game may be like wearing no pads at all.</p>
        <p>''I just wanted to feel good -- feel different,'' Brodeur said.</p>
        <p>Brodeur stopped 43 of 45 shots Saturday, some spectacularly. He stopped all 14 shots he faced in the two overtime periods. He gave up the tying goal to Dany Heatley in the final minute, but that was because Heatley, uncovered, shot from 10 feet away.</p>
        <p>''We don't worry about him,'' Langenbrunner said of Brodeur.</p>
        <p>What the Devils talked about after regulation, and apparently calmly, was how they would kill the penalty on Gionta. They did, and without much trouble. They did not dwell on how Heatley, a 50-goal scorer in the regular season, could set up in the low slot.</p>
        <p>''You just have to stay positive and play the game, and that's what we did,'' said Sergei Brylin, who scored the Devils' second goal with two-tenths of a second left in the first period.</p>
        <p>Zajac, who had 17 goals and 25 assists in the regular season, gave Langenbrunner a chance early in the second overtime simply by winning a race to a loose puck and knocking it up the ice. Langenbrunner raked it in and sped away.</p>
        <p>''Probably the fastest I've skated in a while,'' Langenbrunner said, smirking.</p>
        <p>He appeared as if he would shift the puck from his forehand to his backhand, and Emery was fooled. Langenbrunner swept the puck past Emery and was soon mobbed by Zajac and the left wing on the line, Zach Parise, who is 22.</p>
        <p>''What can you say about the two kids?'' said Scott Gomez, the center on the Devils' top line. ''They were awesome all night.''</p>
        <p>In fact, Zajac was disappointed that his line had not scored a goal earlier Saturday, in his eighth playoff game.</p>
        <p>Langenbrunner joked after the game that he had missed scoring about eight goals before his winner. But they all pressed on.</p>
        <p>''We should have ended it in regulation, but those things happen,'' said center John Madden, who played in his 97th playoff game Saturday. ''We just turned the page and said: 'It's over with. We can't change it now. Let's kill the penalty and look for the game winner.' ''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
