<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rozsival Saves Rangers With His Eyes Closed</title>
    <meta content="30rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/sports/hockey/30rangers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844095"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Buffalo Sabres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Buffalo Sabres</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Rozsival, Michal</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3DA133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="868" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rozsival Saves Rangers With His Eyes Closed</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rozsival Saves Rangers With His Eyes Closed</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinser, Lynn</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After nearly 97 minutes of hockey yesterday, the Rangers player who should have been feeling the worst stared at the puck bouncing in front of him as he wound up for the game's most important shot. Defenseman Michal Rozsival, playing deep into the second overtime on a left leg that had been injured twice in the two previous playoff games against Buffalo, said all he could do was focus on the puck.</p>
        <p>He did not look up. He did not see where it went. The roar that the Madison Square Garden crowd unleashed and the teammates who mobbed him told him what he needed to know. Rozsival's slap shot rifled past a group of players in front of the Buffalo net and went inside the left post, salvaging his team's playoff hopes as the Rangers beat the Sabres, 2-1, in Game 3 of their Eastern Conference semifinal series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Playing at home after losing two games in Buffalo, the Rangers take this jolt of momentum into Tuesday’s Game 4 at the Garden.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After nearly 97 minutes of hockey yesterday, the Rangers player who should have been feeling the worst stared at the puck bouncing in front of him as he wound up for the game's most important shot. Defenseman Michal Rozsival, playing deep into the second overtime on a left leg that had been injured twice in the two previous playoff games against Buffalo, said all he could do was focus on the puck.</p>
        <p>He did not look up. He did not see where it went. The roar that the Madison Square Garden crowd unleashed and the teammates who mobbed him told him what he needed to know. Rozsival's slap shot rifled past a group of players in front of the Buffalo net and went inside the left post, salvaging his team's playoff hopes as the Rangers beat the Sabres, 2-1, in Game 3 of their Eastern Conference semifinal series.</p>
        <p>''I had my eyes closed, actually,'' Rozsival said. ''It was a lucky shot. I was just trying to get it on the net and hopefully somebody's going to tip it. Anything can happen when you put it on the net.''</p>
        <p>The victory staved off what could have been disaster. Playing at home after losing two games in Buffalo, the Rangers take this jolt of momentum into tomorrow's Game 4 at the Garden down by 2-1 in the best-of-seven series.</p>
        <p>''It's a start,'' Rangers forward Brendan Shanahan said. ''It could have been devastating to lose this game, having played so well, having controlled a lot of the play for most of the game.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers largely dominated this game, despite being called for nine penalties to Buffalo's five. Before Rozsival's blast, the Rangers fired 45 shots at Sabres goalie Ryan Miller and he saved all but one. Nineteen attempted shots missed the net. Buffalo blocked 36 more.</p>
        <p>''You have to expect that in their building, with their backs up against a wall,'' Miller said. ''It was a hard-fought game, but we expected that from this series.''</p>
        <p>Despite everything the Rangers threw at Miller, they could get nothing more than Jaromir Jagr's goal 33 seconds into the second period, scored off a rebound. They had another goal disallowed a few minutes later, when replay referees ruled that Rangers defenseman Karel Rachunek had kicked the puck into the net, even though Rachunek was sliding to a stop in front of Miller when the puck bounced off his skate.</p>
        <p>One of the penalties called on the Rangers -- a crosschecking call on Shanahan -- helped the Sabres tie the score. On the power play, a shot by center Daniel Brière bounced through traffic and past Rangers goalie Henrik Lundqvist with 7 minutes 46 seconds left in the third.</p>
        <p>The Rangers had the best of the opportunities to win down the stretch, but the Sabres had a great chance at the end of the first overtime when a shot by Derek Roy beat Lundqvist but clanged off the right post behind him. It took a video review to confirm that the puck did not go in.</p>
        <p>Players said they stayed calm before each overtime, confident despite the huge stakes.</p>
        <p>''I don't think anybody was thinking about losing this game,'' Rozsival said.</p>
        <p>The Rangers, after all, are familiar with the feeling of having everything stacked against them. They have played their best since their playoff prospects looked bleakest late in the season. Jagr has played a giant role since then, and in this game he took 10 shots and played 30 minutes.</p>
        <p>''I want to help this team,'' Jagr said. ''I just love the playoffs. How many years have I got left? How many playoffs have I got left? How many games like that am I going to have? I just enjoy every moment. For as long as I can play, I am going to do my best.''</p>
        <p>From Jagr's point of view, it was fitting that Rozsival, one of his fellow Czechs, won this game. Rozsival is the team's top defenseman. He plays nearly every shift that Jagr's line is on the ice, quarterbacks the power play and kills penalties.</p>
        <p>But Rozsival was questionable for each of the past two games because of an injury to his left knee in Game 1, aggravated by another hit in Game 2. He wears metal braces on both knees (an injury to the right one cost him the entire 2003-4 season), but Rozsival said he never doubted he would play.</p>
        <p>''I'm healthy, 100 percent,'' Rozsival said, grinning.</p>
        <p>Shanahan said: ''It's a great example to our young players. These are the kind of guys you want in your organization. When you're trying to rewrite the type of players and people that this team wants to be and wants to attract, you can't have enough guys like Rozey.''</p>
        <p>In the end, Rozsival played more than 38 minutes. He blocked eight shots. He was crucial in turning defensive possessions into offensive rushes for the Rangers' forwards, who often tell him he should shoot more. This was his third goal of the playoffs.</p>
        <p>''This is the biggest goal of my career, definitely,'' he said. ''It can't get any better, scoring a game-winning goal in overtime.''</p>
        <p>Too bad he didn't see it.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
