<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Explosion of Tanker Truck Collapses Bay Area Overpass</title>
    <meta content="30collapse" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/us/30collapse.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844087"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Oakland (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckinley, Jesse</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marshall, Carolyn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mosqueda, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Michael (Comr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Oakland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Oakland (Calif)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E5DA133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="904" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Explosion of Tanker Truck Collapses Bay Area Overpass</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tanker Truck Fire Collapses Bay Area Overpass</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JESSE McKINLEY and CAROLYN MARSHALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marshall, Carolyn; Mckinley, Jesse</byline>
      <dateline>OAKLAND, Calif., April 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Heavily trafficked freeway overpass near downtown Oakland, Calif, collapses in fiery predawn crash of tanker truck carrying 8,600 gallons of gasoline; hundreds of feet of concrete are sent crashing onto highway below, hobbling vital Bay Area interchange; truck driver is hospitalized with second-degree burns; highway patrol believes driver, James Mosqueda, lost control in curve, hitting guardrail and flipping truck on its side; tanker exploded, sending flames hundreds of feet in air and quickly buckling three-lane section of Interstate 580; Michael Brown, commissioner of highway patrol, says there is no evidence of drug or alcohol impaiarment of driver; photo; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A fiery predawn tanker truck accident caused the collapse of a heavily trafficked freeway overpass near downtown on Sunday, sending hundreds of feet of concrete crashing onto a highway below and hobbling a vital Bay Area interchange.</p>
        <p>The driver of the truck, which was carrying 8,600 gallons of gasoline, was hospitalized with second-degree burns. No other injuries were reported from the accident, which occurred at 3:42 a.m.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A fiery predawn accident sent concrete crashing onto a highway below and hobbled a vital Bay Area interchange.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A fiery predawn tanker truck accident caused the collapse of a heavily trafficked freeway overpass near downtown on Sunday, sending hundreds of feet of concrete crashing onto a highway below and hobbling a vital Bay Area interchange.</p>
        <p>The driver of the truck, which was carrying 8,600 gallons of gasoline, was hospitalized with second-degree burns. No other injuries were reported from the accident, which occurred at 3:42 a.m.</p>
        <p>But even as the fire smoldered, transit officials said the accident could complicate the lives of commuters in both directions for months, raising the specter of circuitous detours to either the south or north.</p>
        <p>''It will make for a long trip,'' said Will Kempton, the director of Cal Trans, the state transportation agency.</p>
        <p>The accident occurred in the heart of an unruly tangle of freeways known as the MacArthur Maze, where several major arteries converge at the approach to the San Francisco-Oakland Bay Bridge, which connects San Francisco with the cities on the east side of San Francisco Bay.</p>
        <p>The California Highway Patrol identified the driver as James Mosqueda, 51, from Woodland, Calif., near Sacramento. Officer Trent Cross, a spokesman for the highway patrol, said Mr. Mosqueda had just picked up the gasoline from a refinery and was headed to a gas station near the Oakland airport.</p>
        <p>The highway patrol believes that Mr. Mosqueda was heading south on Interstate 80 into an interchange with Interstate 880 when he lost control in a curve, hit a guardrail and flipped the truck on its side. The tanker exploded, which sent flames hundreds of feet into the air, witnesses said. The fire quickly buckled a three-lane section of Interstate 580 and caused it to collapse onto some lanes of Interstate 880 about 30 feet below.</p>
        <p>Michael Brown, the commissioner of the highway patrol, said the driver had been able to escape the burning truck, and he apparently took a cab in order to go to the hospital.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown said there was ''no indication of impairment of the driver'' by drugs or alcohol, but that some legal issues are outstanding for both Mr. Mosqueda, and the truck's owner, Sabek Transportation, based in San Francisco. He did not elaborate.</p>
        <p>Last June, according to records of the California Office of Spill Prevention and Response, a Sabek tanker truck jackknifed on an Interstate near Vallejo, spilling 4,500 gallons of diesel fuel, which contaminated a creek and vegetation.</p>
        <p>For some Bay Area residents, the accident evoked memories of the 1989 Loma Prieta earthquake, which caused the collapse of a mile-long, double-decker section of I-880, near the site of Sunday's accident. That collapse, which occurred during the evening rush hour, resulted in 41 deaths and more than 100 injuries, as cars on the lower level were crushed.</p>
        <p>Mayor Gavin Newsom of San Francisco, who visited the site on Sunday, called the collapse ''a giant wake-up call to the region'' about what may happen in a major temblor.</p>
        <p>''It's a matter of when not if,'' Mr. Newsom said.</p>
        <p>This time around, the results were not deadly on I-880, but no less arresting to look at. Dozens of people converged near the collapse site to gawk, and rubbernecking drivers on remaining roadways slowed traffic.</p>
        <p>''I was on the road last night, so it's kind of scary for me,'' Anita Myles, 49, an Oakland resident, said as she peered at the damage through a chain link fence.</p>
        <p>Another onlooker, James Signore, a civil engineer from Oakland, said he had a professional interest in the damage. ''I have not seen this kind of wreckage before,'' Mr. Signore, 43, said. ''And I'm really curious how something this stout could be taken down.''</p>
        <p>He was not the only one wondering how the overpass, which dates to the 1950s, had failed. At a noontime press conference held at a toll plaza near the collapse, Mr. Kempton said the heat from the fireball had most likely melted the steel girders and bolts that supported the concrete roadway. ''If you have that kind of heat,'' he said, ''you're going to have this kind of reaction. We're not surprised by this result.''</p>
        <p>With a Monday morning rush hour looming, officials said they were trying to assess the damage as fast as possible. Even with fewer cars on a Sunday afternoon, traffic was slow coming off the Bay Bridge into the East Bay, a situation that will no doubt intensify as the workweek begins. On an average day, the two spans that were destroyed on Sunday morning carried 160,000 vehicles, Mr. Kempton said.</p>
        <p>Bay Area Rapid Transit, the train system connecting San Francisco and the East Bay, was not affected by the accident but said it would lengthen its trains to accommodate the rush on Monday.</p>
        <p>''We would encourage people to stay away from the maze,'' Mr. Kempton said. ''If experience tells us anything, it will take a day or two to get this sorted out.''</p>
        <p>Evaluating the damage will be the first step of a long process. Rebuilding the collapsed section of I-880 took nearly a decade, though Mr. Kempton called that situation ''a much larger issue'' involving neighborhood and environmental concerns.</p>
        <p>Gov. Arnold Schwarzenegger authorized money for ferries, buses and the rail system to carry commuters at no charge during Monday's commute, The Associated Press reported.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kempton pleaded for patience, saying with this kind of complex highway system, ''You're not going to have a picnic every day.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
