<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Line Up, Young Hopefuls (And Really, Be Young)</title>
    <meta content="30spri" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/theater/30spri.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844029"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E1DC133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="630" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Line Up, Young Hopefuls (And Really, Be Young)</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Line Up, Young Hopefuls (and Really, Be Young)</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAMPBELL ROBERTSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robertson, Campbell</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Michael Freeman came all the way from the University of Alabama to spend six chilly early-morning hours yesterday sitting on the sidewalk along 38th Street in Manhattan. Scott Johnston just came from Long Island, but he got to the sidewalk three hours earlier than Mr. Freeman. One a.m.: first in line.</p>
        <p>The producers of ''Spring Awakening,'' the rock-musical portrait of teenage discontent playing on Broadway, were looking for future replacements for their young cast (future being the crucial word, the casting notice said; nobody in the current cast is going anywhere soon).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>More than 1,000 hopefuls lined up at an open call for young performers to star as replacements in the Broadway musical “Spring Awakening.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Michael Freeman came all the way from the University of Alabama to spend six chilly early-morning hours yesterday sitting on the sidewalk along 38th Street in Manhattan. Scott Johnston just came from Long Island, but he got to the sidewalk three hours earlier than Mr. Freeman. One a.m.: first in line.</p>
        <p>The producers of ''Spring Awakening,'' the rock-musical portrait of teenage discontent playing on Broadway, were looking for future replacements for their young cast (future being the crucial word, the casting notice said; nobody in the current cast is going anywhere soon).</p>
        <p>They put out an open call for performers between the ages of 16 and 21 in all the usual places, adding the show's sites on MySpace and Facebook. Have a ''folk/alternative rock song'' prepared, the notice read. A Beatles songbook was on hand if necessary.</p>
        <p>At 10 o'clock yesterday morning the seekers had come, more than 1,000 of them, with their sheet music, saccharine smiles and terror-filled eyes, stretching down 38th Street, turning the corner onto Ninth Avenue, then turning the corner again onto 39th Street. Whether there were new Wendlas and Melchiors in that huge crowd remains to be seen, but the event did make pretty nice publicity for a show that has at times struggled to fill its theater and is being promoted for a Tony Award. The auditions began upstairs in the New Dance Group studios.</p>
        <p>Line up against the wall, have your head shots and résumés handy. O.K., here's the drill.</p>
        <p>The first room was the one of heartbreak. It's where people were accepted or rejected on sight; the rejects didn't even get to sing. They walked in and stood in a line, looking inexperienced, confident, flirtatious, petrified or some combination thereof.</p>
        <p>Stephen Kopel, who works for Jim Carnahan, the show's casting director, flipped through head shots and glanced at résumés: an endless stream of former von Trapp children, a Fantine or two, a Little Sally from ''Urinetown,'' a Tybalt, an Emily Webb, a great many portrayals of this particular character named Ensemble. These bona fides did not matter so much; Mr. Kopel was mainly there to cut out the ancient 22- and 23-year-olds who thought they could squeeze in.</p>
        <p>''Brittany, how old are you?'' Mr. Kopel asked a young woman clutching her sheet music to her chest.</p>
        <p>''I'm actually, well, I'm 15, but I'm a freshman,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''You in school, Lauren?'' Mr. Kopel asked.</p>
        <p>Pigtails fooled no one.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Kopel finished eyeballing a group, which usually took a minute at most, he handed the résumés in two stacks to another casting person. In the hall that person held out a few head shots: ''You guys -- sorry, too old.''</p>
        <p>The rest filed upstairs.</p>
        <p>Audition Room B. Carrie Gardner, a casting agent who works for Mr. Carnahan, sat at a table as one young woman came in after another, a numbered sticker slapped on her clothes. The women smiled, handed the sheet music to a piano player, stepped to the blue line and announced their selections.</p>
        <p>No. 82: ''Fiona Apple's 'Criminal.' ''</p>
        <p>No. 84: '' 'Over the Rainbow' by way of Eva Cassidy.''</p>
        <p>No. 87: '' 'Call Me When You're Sober' by Evanescence.''</p>
        <p>Thanks, that was great.</p>
        <p>''If we are interested in seeing you further, you will be contacted,'' read a short information sheet being handed out. ''Please DO NOT contact us.''</p>
        <p>And so, having waited and waited and waited and sung, they walked, a little dazed, back out to 38th Street.</p>
        <p>Mr. Freeman, 22, did not have such luck. Sorry, too old, the woman said. After a $230 plane ticket, six hours on the sidewalk and one minute in front of a casting agent: sorry, too old.</p>
        <p>''I guess it's the price you pay,'' Mr. Freeman said, and shrugged.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
