<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>War Report Could Decide Israeli Premier's Fate</title>
    <meta content="30mideast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/world/middleeast/30mideast.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070502T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844042"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lebanon</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hezbollah</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kershner, Isabel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olmert, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peretz, Amir (Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halutz, Dan (Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Israel</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Lebanon</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Hezbollah</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEEDC133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="968" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>War Report Could Decide Israeli Premier's Fate</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">War Report Could Decide Israeli Premier’s Fate</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ISABEL KERSHNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kershner, Isabel</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, April 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interim report on Israeli government's failings during last summer's war against Hezbollah in Lebanon is expected to contain harsh criticism of decision-making process leading up to war and performance of Prime Min Ehud Olmert, Defense Min Amir Peretz, and wartime army chief of staff Lt Gen Dan Halutz; Halutz resigned in Jan and Peretz says he will leave next month; Olmert's future is uncertain; he has been weakened, in part, because he is facing numerous corruption investigations (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the eve of the publication of an official report on the Israeli government's failings during last summer's war against Hezbollah in Lebanon, the main topic of public debate is whether Prime Minister Ehud Olmert will be able to hang on to power.</p>
        <p>Support for Mr. Olmert has been shaky since the war, which many Israelis consider to have been a failure. Current polls show his approval ratings hovering between 2 and 3 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A much anticipated report on the Israeli government’s failings during last summer’s war in Lebanon is to be made public on Monday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the eve of the publication of an official report on the Israeli government's failings during last summer's war against Hezbollah in Lebanon, the main topic of public debate is whether Prime Minister Ehud Olmert will be able to hang on to power.</p>
        <p>Support for Mr. Olmert has been shaky since the war, which many Israelis consider to have been a failure. Current polls show his approval ratings hovering between 2 and 3 percent.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, a well-informed senior official said Mr. Olmert did not intend to resign. But the official said that could change if the report stated that he bore ''personal responsibility'' for failures in the war.</p>
        <p>The much anticipated interim report, prepared by a government-appointed committee headed by Eliyahu Winograd, a retired judge, is to be made public on Monday afternoon. It is widely expected to contain harsh criticism of the decision-making process leading up to the war and the performance of the prime minister; the defense minister, Amir Peretz; and the wartime army chief of staff, Lt. Gen. Dan Halutz. General Halutz resigned in January, and Mr. Peretz has said he will leave the Defense Ministry in late May or soon after.</p>
        <p>Over the weekend, the Israeli news media reported on what they described as leaks from the report indicating that the three were considered to have failed in their duties.</p>
        <p>Opposition politicians from the left and right have already called for the prime minister to resign. A recently formed protest movement, led by a former national security official, is organizing a rally around the slogan ''You've failed; go home,'' to take place in Tel Aviv on Thursday.</p>
        <p>The war followed Hezbollah's seizure of two Israeli soldiers in a cross-border raid on June 12. The conflict lasted 34 days and claimed the lives of 160 Israelis -- 119 soldiers and 41 civilians, according to officials. About 1,000 Lebanese, mostly civilians, are believed to have died in the fighting. Israel was not able to secure the soldiers' release or to destroy Hezbollah.</p>
        <p>The interim report deals with the period leading up to the war and its early days, until July 17. That is when Mr. Olmert made a speech in Parliament declaring that Israel was at war. The Winograd Committee's full report, dealing with rest of the war, is due this summer.</p>
        <p>According to what were said to be leaks published in the Israeli news media, the interim report will accuse Mr. Olmert of acting hastily and injudiciously and serving in effect as a rubber stamp for the army. Mr. Peretz will supposedly be criticized for failing to understand the magnitude of the problem posed by his lack of experience in security matters and for failing to seek professional counsel. General Halutz will reportedly be taken to task for silencing dissenting views, for taking advantage of Mr. Peretz's lack of experience and for underestimating the strength of Hezbollah and the threat posed by its rockets.</p>
        <p>The spokesman for the Winograd Committee, Eli Shaked, would not confirm the veracity of the leaks, saying there was a ''strict policy of not responding to unofficial leaks.''</p>
        <p>The committee went to great lengths to keep its findings secret before publication, including printing the report at the headquarters of Israel's Shin Bet internal security agency.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, several politicians from the right-wing opposition parties called for the prime minister's immediate resignation. Yossi Beilin, a lawmaker and the leader of the leftist Meretz Party, said that Mr. Olmert should not stay in his post ''one more day'' and that his ''fate would be like that of Golda and her associates after the Yom Kippur war.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Beilin was referring to Golda Meir, the former prime minister, and her defense minister, Moshe Dayan, who were forced out of office because of public pressure in 1974, months after the end of the 1973 war. A state commission of inquiry, the Agranat Commission, headed by the president of the Supreme Court, had cleared both of any responsibility for the intelligence failure that led to the war, blaming the military instead.</p>
        <p>Another official state commission of inquiry, the Kahan Commission, examined the Sabra and Shatila massacres in Lebanon by a Christian militia in 1982. It determined that the defense minister at the time, Ariel Sharon, bore some responsibility for the events and recommended his dismissal. He was forced to resign as defense minister soon afterward.</p>
        <p>Because the Winograd Committee was appointed by the government rather than by the Supreme Court, some Israeli analysts have said it does not have the legal authority to make such decisive recommendations. The fate of the government will depend on the level of public protest and pressure after the report, the analysts said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Olmert has been weakened, in part, because he is facing numerous corruption investigations, including one involving his role in the sale of the government's controlling share in a bank when he was finance minister.</p>
        <p>The rally scheduled for Thursday is being organized by Uzi Dayan, a former national security adviser and a nephew of Moshe Dayan. Mr. Dayan has formed a protest group known as the Civil Coalition made up of reservists, bereaved parents of soldiers who died in the war, representatives of border communities in the north and the south and various movements for clean government -- including his own group, Tafnit, whose name means ''turning point'' in Hebrew.</p>
        <p>Speaking by telephone from his headquarters in Tel Aviv, Mr. Dayan said it was time ''to let the people have their say.'' Mr. Dayan said that there was no money for organized transportation to the rally, but he added that he was heartened by a call he said he received Saturday from Motti Ashkenazi, who wanted to join the struggle. In 1974, Mr. Ashkenazi, then a 33-year-old reservist, led the public protests against Mrs. Meir.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 2, 2007, Wednesday  An article on Monday about the public debate in Israel over whether Prime Minister Ehud Olmert could retain power despite a government report criticizing his leadership in the 34-day Lebanon war misstated the date the war began last year. It was July 12, not June 12.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 2, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article on Monday about the public debate in Israel over whether Prime Minister Ehud Olmert could retain power despite a government report criticizing his leadership in the 34-day Lebanon war misstated the date the war began last year. It was July 12, not June 12.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
