<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Push to Legalize Gay Marriage</title>
    <meta content="l30gay" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844058"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presbyterian Church</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2DB133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="602" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Push to Legalize Gay Marriage</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Mr. Spitzer and Gay Marriage'' (editorial, April 24):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Mr. Spitzer and Gay Marriage'' (editorial, April 24):</p>
        <p>Sincere thanks to Gov. Eliot Spitzer for wanting to help make marriage a reality for New York State's gay and lesbian couples.</p>
        <p>My partner, David, and I have been married in all but name for more than 13 years. We are often asked why we haven't had a commitment ceremony, or even been married in Canada.</p>
        <p>We will get married when it is legal in New York State. Until that time comes, something less than marriage doesn't seem, to us, a real reason to celebrate.</p>
        <p>Paul D. Poux  New York, April 24, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Thank you for the sensitive and sensible editorial supporting Gov. Eliot Spitzer's intentions for legislating gay marriage in New York.</p>
        <p>But where is the leadership on a national level? Perhaps it's too much to expect from a presidential candidate, but there must be some people ''brave'' enough to assert themselves for such a sensible cause -- Bill Clinton or Al Gore, perhaps?</p>
        <p>It is painful to realize that there are so many who chose to ignore the gays and lesbians left ''sitting at the back of the bus.''</p>
        <p>Tom Power  Venice, Calif., April 24, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I applaud your editorial backing Gov. Eliot Spitzer's intention to introduce a bill legalizing same-sex marriages. While Mr. Spitzer will certainly face ''outspoken opponents'' among religious organizations, not all faith groups oppose marriage equality.</p>
        <p>Unitarian Universalists have advocated for legal marriage rights for same-sex couples since 1996. And while we acknowledge the right of other religions to refuse to perform wedding ceremonies for any reason, Unitarian Universalist ministers have joyfully officiated at same-sex religious unions for several decades.</p>
        <p>In my home state, Massachusetts, marriage equality has been the law for nearly three years. We have seen how quickly the extraordinary becomes ordinary.</p>
        <p>The sun still rises and sets every day, but now it shines on several thousand more couples whose commitments to one another are legally recognized by the state.</p>
        <p>If the institution of marriage is good for couples, good for families, and good for society, then we all benefit when this institution is free from discrimination.</p>
        <p>Marriage is a civil right.</p>
        <p>(Rev.) William G. Sinkford  Boston, April 24, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is president, Unitarian Universalist Association of Congregations.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>You're worried that religious groups might ''dictate who can and who cannot be married by the state'' (editorial, April 24)?</p>
        <p>Consider this: my Christian faith profoundly informs the way I vote. If I believe that a legislative proposal threatens the common good, I will vote against it and encourage others to do the same.</p>
        <p>That's not dictatorial. That's democracy.</p>
        <p>(Rev.) James D. Miller  Tulsa, Okla., April 25, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is pastor of the First Presbyterian Church.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In response to your editorial, I would like to point out that not all religious groups will oppose a bill to legalize same-sex marriage.</p>
        <p>My congregation is the largest gay and lesbian synagogue in the world, and we wholeheartedly support Gov. Eliot Spitzer's move to embrace justice for all by legalizing same-sex marriage. As a rabbi who has officiated at dozens of same-sex marriages in New York City, I would like to see these unions recognized by the state.</p>
        <p>I look forward to a day when all religious groups recognize that whether gay, lesbian, transgender or straight, we are all created in God's image.</p>
        <p>Sharon Kleinbaum  New York, April 24, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is senior rabbi, Congregation Beth Simchat Torah.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
