<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inspired by the Spelling Bee Comes the 'Define-a-Thon'</title>
    <meta content="30define" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/business/30define.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844002"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dictionaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Houghton Mifflin Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E5DC133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1077" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inspired by the Spelling Bee Comes the 'Define-a-Thon'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Inspired by the Spelling Bee Comes the ‘Define-a-Thon’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ADAM NEWMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Newman, Andrew Adam</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Now that spelling bees have been turned into a hit Broadway show and crossword puzzles into a movie, the publishers of the American Heritage dictionary are hoping to create a cultural moment with a competitive game about word definitions.</p>
        <p>Dictionary publishers typically send out a press release highlighting new entries -- ''blogosphere,'' ''instant messaging'' and ''shout-out'' are recent examples --but struggle to find other ways to get attention.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Houghton Mifflin created the Define-a-Thon, which asks contestants to match words to definitions (and gives them a helpful list of words to choose from).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Now that spelling bees have been turned into a hit Broadway show and crossword puzzles into a movie, the publishers of the American Heritage dictionary are hoping to create a cultural moment with a competitive game about word definitions.</p>
        <p>Dictionary publishers typically send out a press release highlighting new entries -- ''blogosphere,'' ''instant messaging'' and ''shout-out'' are recent examples --but struggle to find other ways to get attention.</p>
        <p>''I think everyone publicizes new words, so I want to go beyond that,'' said Taryn Roeder, 32, who as Houghton Mifflin's assistant director of publicity promotes the American Heritage Dictionaries reference line.</p>
        <p>So this year Houghton Mifflin created -- and trademarked -- the Define-a-Thon, which is modeled after a spelling bee but instead asks contestants to match words to definitions (and gives them a helpful list of words to choose from). The publisher has dispatched Steve Kleinedler, supervising editor at American Heritage, to hold events across the country.</p>
        <p>On a recent Thursday night in Cambridge, Mass., about 225 people filed into the Brattle Theater in Harvard Square to watch a Define-a-Thon. After two heats of 20 contestants each, the finalists were Brandy Jones, a community design planner who picked the correct word for definitions like the ringing or sounding of bells (''tintinnabulation''), and Katherine Bryant, a science textbook editor, whose definitions included head-scratchers like the right to use and enjoy someone else's property without harming it (''usufruct'').</p>
        <p>In the final round, Ms. Bryant, a crossword enthusiast, was victorious. ''It was fun,'' she said by telephone from Boston. ''Kind of geeky, but fun.''</p>
        <p>For Mr. Kleinedler, who has a tattoo of the phonetic vowel chart on his back, it is not just about fun; it is about the business of making dictionaries seem sexy. Part of his job is to debunk the notion that lexicographers are ''gray-haired people hunched over a drafting table who never see the light of day,'' he said.</p>
        <p>To propagate the Define-a-Thon, Houghton Mifflin is circulating a 70-page event planning kit that includes questions, rules and a certificate that can be presented to winners. In the fall, the publisher will release two books, ''Define-a-Thon for the High School Graduate'' and ''Define-a-Thon for the High School Freshman,'' at $5.95 each.</p>
        <p>It will not be the first time that the company's promotion for one book has led to the creation of another. In 2002, when the American Heritage College Dictionary, Fourth Edition, was released, the publicity department asked editors for 100 words every adult should know, and printed the list -- which included words like ''inculcate'' and ''evanescent'' -- on posters that it distributed to book shows, stores and schools.</p>
        <p>The posters were so popular that they spawned a book, ''100 Words Every High School Student Should Know,'' which added definitions, word histories and quotations.</p>
        <p>First published in 2003, the original ''100 Words'' book has sold 94,000 copies, according to Nielsen BookScan. Houghton Mifflin has subsequently released five related titles, including ''100 Words Every Word Lover Should Know'' (like ''ephemeral,'' and ''fecundity'') and ''100 Words to Make You Sound Smart'' (like ''ennui'' and ''lurid''), which have collectively sold another 117,000 copies and have landed Mr. Kleinedler, the editor, on hundreds of radio broadcasts, he said.</p>
        <p>''Everyone in America loves a list,'' said Mr. Kleinedler. ''Doing publicity for those books has been like rolling off a log. Radio hosts love talking about them, and it's a really good hook, because it's easy to segue to talking about the dictionary.''</p>
        <p>While publishers traditionally promote books in advance of their publication dates and to a lesser degree when they are released in paperback, dictionary publishers face the quandary of releasing new editions as infrequently as once a decade. Although the fourth edition of the American Heritage dictionary was published five years ago, the Define-a-Thon promotion is linked to the release of a 2007 update, which features some new words.</p>
        <p>''There are long stretches of time when we don't have a new publication, so we have to find a way to keep our name and our brand out there,'' said Arthur Bicknell, publicist for Merriam-Webster, which publishes the country's best-selling dictionary, Merriam-Webster's Collegiate Dictionary.</p>
        <p>Merriam-Webster gets a yearly publicity jolt from the Scripps National Spelling Bee, which it has sponsored for 50 years, and whose popularity has surged thanks to recent films like ''Spellbound'' and stage productions like ''The 25th Annual Putnam County Spelling Bee.'' (The movie ''Wordplay,'' about crossword puzzle competitions, may also have helped send viewers to reference books.)</p>
        <p>Merriam-Webster's unabridged dictionary is the official arbiter for a word's inclusion in the Scripps bee, so many contestants purchase it as a study guide.</p>
        <p>A three-time finalist in the Scripps National Spelling Bee, Emily Stagg, was a featured competitor in the movie ''Spellbound,'' who inspired the Define-a-Thon, according to Ms. Roeder, the American Heritage publicist. In an opinion column in The New York Times last May, she wrote, ''Why don't we make the National Spelling Bee a 'definitions bee,' where competitors need to know primarily what words mean rather than simply how to spell them?''</p>
        <p>While American Heritage does not expect to rival the 79-year-old Scripps bee with its Define-a-Thon anytime soon, it is striking a chord with some language experts. Richard Gentry, who has written several books about spelling and literacy development, said that vocabulary aptitude is a stronger indicator of overall intelligence than spelling aptitude, which is one reason that many dyslexics become accomplished scholars. Mr. Gentry, who has dyslexia himself, said he was ''a horrible speller with a not-bad vocabulary.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Roeder said that she has had many opportunities to take stock of her own verbal proficiency. Shortly after taking her job as a publicist three years ago, for example, she had to write a press release for ''100 Words Almost Everyone Confuses and Misuses'' (think of ''lay'' and ''wreak''). She knew from the start that her work would be edited by the very lexicographers who had just written the book.</p>
        <p>''I was really intimidated,'' she said. ''When I tell people I'm passing my press releases along to people who write dictionaries and they're proofreading them, they think I have a very scary job.''</p>
        <p>Eventually Ms. Roeder got that first press release back. ''There was a lot of red on it,'' she said. ''And the materials that I send up to their department still come back with a lot of red on it. But that's fine by me. They're lexicographers, so I'm happy to have them wordsmith my writing.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
