<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jets Draft Two More Players, Then Say They're Looking for Others</title>
    <meta content="30jets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/sports/30jets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844085"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New England Patriots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New England Patriots</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Football League</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Moss, Randy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DA133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="753" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jets Draft Two More Players, Then Say They're Looking for Others</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Jets Draft Two More Players, Then Say They’re Looking for Others</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crouse, Karen</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., April 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the second day of the N.F.L. draft, the Jets acquired a wide receiver. So did their main American Football Conference East rival, the New England Patriots.</p>
        <p>The Jets used their seventh-round pick (No. 235 over all) to select Chansi Stuckey, who sustained four injuries in his last three seasons at Clemson.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Jets used their sixth and seventh-round picks to select offensive tackle Jacob Bender and wide receiver Chansi Stuckey, respectively.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the second day of the N.F.L. draft, the Jets acquired a wide receiver. So did their main American Football Conference East rival, the New England Patriots.</p>
        <p>The Jets used their seventh-round pick (No. 235 over all) to select Chansi Stuckey, who sustained four injuries in his last three seasons at Clemson.</p>
        <p>The Patriots traded for Oakland's Randy Moss, a five-time Pro Bowl selection. Moss will join his fellow newcomers Wes Welker, Donte' Stallworth and Kelley Washington in the renovated receiving corps of the Patriots' offense, which ranked 11th in the league last season.</p>
        <p>After its facelift, the New England roster that the Jets will face twice this season certainly looks more formidable than the one that defeated the Jets, 37-16, in the first round of last season's playoffs.</p>
        <p>The Jets have added the veteran running back Thomas Jones, whom they acquired from the Chicago Bears. And on the first day of the draft, they traded up to select two potential starters, cornerback Darrelle Revis and linebacker David Harris, for a defense that was 20th in the league last season.</p>
        <p>In doing so, they continued a defensive renovation that began with the signing of defensive end Kenyon Coleman and linebacker Andre Wadsworth in March.</p>
        <p>The Jets used their sixth-round pick Sunday to select Jacob Bender, an offensive tackle from Division I-AA Nicholls State, then selected Stuckey to complete their four-player draft. It is the smallest class in the franchise's draft history and it poses this question: Have the Jets done enough to keep pace with the Patriots?</p>
        <p>Asked his reaction to Moss joining the Patriots, Jets General Manager Mike Tannenbaum said: ''Obviously we were made aware of that. But we're just focused on the Jets this weekend, and that's where our focus has been all weekend long.''</p>
        <p>Coach Eric Mangini bristled at any mention of the Patriots, his employer for six seasons before he was hired by the Jets last year. He suggested that any moves the Jets made would be independent of anything being done anywhere else, including ''the other place,'' as he referred to New England for most of the 2006 season.</p>
        <p>''I think that the road anywhere starts with the next minicamp and then training camp,'' Mangini said. ''I think that this is a process, and we're starting on the process.''</p>
        <p>Asked if the Jets drafted a cornerback in the first round as a reaction to the Patriots' improved receiving corps, Mangini said: ''I wouldn't say it's reactionary. It's more a function of us trying to get our team better as opposed to reacting to what happens externally.''</p>
        <p>The Jets' offense ranked No. 25 in the league last year. While both picks Sunday were offensive players, it would appear, at first glance, that they were added for depth, not for immediate impact.</p>
        <p>Bender, who is 6 feet 6 inches and 316 pounds, acknowledged in a teleconference that he needed to gain weight, probably at least 15 pounds. He played left tackle at Nicholls State, where last season he played against Nebraska defensive end Adam Carriker, a first-round pick of the St. Louis Rams.</p>
        <p>Since the Jets seem set at left tackle for the next decade after drafting D'Brickashaw Ferguson No. 4 over all last year, Bender, 22, will probably be switched to right tackle. He has dabbled at that position but has never played a competitive down at guard.</p>
        <p>''Obviously I'll leave that that up to Coach Mangini and the O-line coaches and see where it goes from there,'' Bender said.</p>
        <p>Stuckey, 23, had 141 career receptions, including 50 as a senior. He missed two games with a sprained left ankle as a sophomore, sustained a concussion as a junior, missed spring practice his senior year with a thumb injury and was sidelined for three games with a broken right foot last October.</p>
        <p>His injured foot, which required surgery, was still not right at the N.F.L. combine when he was timed in 4.61 in the 40. He ran a 4.48 during a later workout.</p>
        <p>''Based on all the information we had, we were comfortable with the selection,'' Tannenbaum said.</p>
        <p>He added that the Jets felt comfortable with the weekend. ''We feel good about what we've accomplished,'' Tannenbaum said.</p>
        <p>Which is not to say there is no room for improvement. ''We do have some free agents we're trying to sign,'' Tannenbaum said.</p>
        <p>Borrowing a line used earlier in the day by Mangini, Tannenbaum said: ''We're the land of opportunity. If you weren't drafted, you'll be hearing from us.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
