<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cardinals Relief Pitcher Dies in a Car Accident</title>
    <meta content="30hancock" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844082"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Missouri</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Missouri/St. Louis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Missouri</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E6DA133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="823" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cardinals Relief Pitcher Dies in a Car Accident</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY; Jim Orso contributed reporting from St. Louis, Tyler Kepner from New York and Ben Shpigel from Washington.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the telephone rang in Bruce Evans's home in Vestavia Hills, Ala., at 6:30 a.m. yesterday, the sound jolted him. The news that Evans then received stunned him. He learned that Josh Hancock, a relief pitcher for the St. Louis Cardinals, had died in an automobile accident.</p>
        <p>Evans, the baseball coach at Vestavia Hills High School, coached the junior varsity team while Hancock was pitching the varsity to three consecutive state titles from 1994-96. Evans said Hancock was a free spirit whose days and nights revolved around baseball.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the telephone rang in Bruce Evans's home in Vestavia Hills, Ala., at 6:30 a.m. yesterday, the sound jolted him. The news that Evans then received stunned him. He learned that Josh Hancock, a relief pitcher for the St. Louis Cardinals, had died in an automobile accident.</p>
        <p>Evans, the baseball coach at Vestavia Hills High School, coached the junior varsity team while Hancock was pitching the varsity to three consecutive state titles from 1994-96. Evans said Hancock was a free spirit whose days and nights revolved around baseball.</p>
        <p>''He loved baseball and he was very dedicated to it,'' Evans said. ''The kids that played on the team with Josh, they loved him. It's all shocking.''</p>
        <p>Hancock, 29, was a useful reliever for St. Louis last year, going 3-3 with a 4.09 earned run average in 62 games. His death was being compared to the death of Cardinals starter Darryl Kile in June 2002.</p>
        <p>Kile died in a Chicago hotel room after a heart blockage. Both deaths occurred during a Cardinals-Cubs series, and both resulted in the next game between the teams being canceled. Last night's game was to be nationally televised.</p>
        <p>According to St. Louis Police Chief Joseph Mokwa, Hancock died on impact at about 12:30 a.m. yesterday when his 2007 Ford Explorer hit a tow truck that was parked in the far left westbound lane of Highway 40 in St. Louis.</p>
        <p>Mokwa said the 13-ton flatbed tow truck, with emergency lights flashing, was parked squarely in the left lane behind a disabled car. He said the tow truck operator, who saw Hancock's Explorer approaching in his rearview mirror and blew the truck's horns, was not injured. The occupants of the car in front of the tow truck were also not injured. Hancock was alone in his car.</p>
        <p>Mokwa said there was no visual evidence that alcohol was involved in the accident. An autopsy has been scheduled.</p>
        <p>''It appears that he just didn't see the tow truck,'' Mokwa said at a news conference at Busch Stadium.</p>
        <p>Manager Tony La Russa, who attended a news conference with the Cardinals' owner, Bill DeWitt, and General Manager Walt Jocketty, said the Cardinals planned to take a charter flight to Tupelo, Miss., on Thursday for Hancock's funeral. The Cardinals, who begin a series in Milwaukee today, will wear a patch with Hancock's No. 32 on their uniform sleeves for the rest of the season.</p>
        <p>Jocketty said the death of Hancock was ''very difficult for all of us, especially for those of us who were here five years ago when we lost Darryl Kile.''</p>
        <p>La Russa praised Hancock, who was 0-1 with a 3.55 E.R.A. this season, for handling mop-up situations, in which the Cardinals were trailing by several runs, without complaint. In fact, Hancock's final appearance was a three-inning stint in an 8-1 loss to the Cubs on Saturday.</p>
        <p>''You saw it yesterday,'' La Russa said.</p>
        <p>Yankees pitcher Colter Bean went to high school with Hancock for two years and played with him at Auburn for one year. Hancock was a year behind Bean, who said he drove Hancock to high school until Hancock got his driver's license.</p>
        <p>''Then he got some old, beat-up '77 Bronco and started driving it around,'' Bean said.</p>
        <p>Bean said a friend called him at 7 a.m. to tell him about Hancock's death. The friend had talked to Hancock's father, who asked the friend to alert people about Josh's death before it was disclosed to the news media.</p>
        <p>''When I heard the news, it just kind of stopped me in my tracks,'' Bean said. ''It's the last kind of news you expect to hear at any time.''</p>
        <p>Hancock played for four teams in parts of six seasons, so he had former teammates sprinkled throughout the major leagues. Those who talked about Hancock remembered him as quiet and dedicated.</p>
        <p>''Josh was just a super kid,'' said Mets closer Billy Wagner, who was a teammate of Hancock's in Philadelphia. ''He couldn't be happier about getting to the big leagues. He was such a humble, hard worker.''</p>
        <p>Ryan Wagner, a Nationals pitcher who played with Hancock on the Cincinnati Reds, recalled how excited Hancock was last season about pitching in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>''Your typical ballplayer,'' he said, describing Hancock. ''He kept to himself. He never complained about a thing, just an all-around great dude.''</p>
        <p>After being picked by the Boston Red Sox in the fifth round of the 1998 draft, Hancock briefly made it to the major leagues with them in 2002. Hancock pitched for the Phillies in 2003 and 2004 and for the Reds in 2004 and 2005. He had his most productive season with the Cardinals a year ago.</p>
        <p>''He had such a good year, won the World Series, and then this happens,'' Bean said. ''You never know when it's going to end.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
