<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Truth in Co-ops: Just Tell Me Why I'm Not In</title>
    <meta content="l30coops" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844057"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE2DB133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="443" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Truth in Co-ops: Just Tell Me Why I'm Not In</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Pushing Co-ops to Explain Why You Can't Buy'' (front page, April 21):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Pushing Co-ops to Explain Why You Can't Buy'' (front page, April 21):</p>
        <p>My own experience as a former co-op board president is in direct contrast to the rhetoric of the co-op industry representatives opposing a bill requiring co-op boards to explain why they have rejected an applicant.</p>
        <p>The board I served on tried hard to make decisions on the merits. It would have been easy for us to put in writing why we made decisions about sales, since we always knew what motivated our actions. That's undoubtedly the case at most co-ops.</p>
        <p>Would this bill discourage anyone from joining a co-op board, as industry spokesmen have argued? Don't believe it for a second. Instead, it will simply provide a strong incentive for co-ops to adopt a ''best practices'' standard toward purchases, with fair and open decision-making. Anyone who cannot abide by this simple goal should not be on a co-op board in the first place.</p>
        <p>Joseph G. Rappaport  New York, April 21, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As a board member and president of a large co-op for nine years, I must tell you that the city's proposed law is not just wrongheaded, but also goes against everything the state intended for co-ops.</p>
        <p>It was and is the intention of the State of New York to shield co-op directors from reporting and exposure. Under the proposed bill, volunteer shareholders, unpaid by state law, would become subject to lawsuits that would result in zero participation on boards, putting co-ops at total risk.</p>
        <p>For the city to intervene and interfere with existing structures is at least as immoral and unethical as the activity it is supposed to address -- discrimination.</p>
        <p>The way this law is worded, it might as well be titled ''The Full Employment Act for Co-op Lawyers.'' It will result not only in mass resignations, but also in higher insurance premiums, and therefore higher maintenance, all of which will go directly to lawyers.</p>
        <p>It is simply an unfair tax on co-op shareholders. Meanwhile, the problem of discrimination will not be altered in any way.</p>
        <p>David Wineberg  New York, April 22, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''Maybe someone has been turned down because he is a cheater at the golf club,'' says a lawyer who represents co-op boards.</p>
        <p>I don't play golf and I don't cheat at sports, but I certainly don't consider cheating at golf to be grounds for rejecting someone from a co-op.</p>
        <p>I find it interesting that New York City co-op boards seem so scared of bringing transparency and truthfulness to such a murky and clandestine operation.</p>
        <p>Douglas Binder  Albuquerque, April 21, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
