<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Doing Everything but Playing the Music</title>
    <meta content="30adam" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/arts/music/30adam.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844012"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">American Composers Orchestra</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Adams, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Beaser, Robert</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E3DC133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="514" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Doing Everything but Playing the Music</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Doing Everything but Playing the Music</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The composer John Adams is also a skilled and dynamic conductor. He showed his versatility on the podium in 2003 during one of the inaugural concerts for Zankel Hall, conducting demanding scores by Ives, Lou Harrison, Thomas Adès and Esa-Pekka Salonen.</p>
        <p>He certainly seemed in his element on Friday night at Carnegie Hall, when he conducted the American Composers Orchestra in an all-Adams program to commemorate his 60th birthday this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Adams conducted the orchestra in an all-Adams program to commemorate his 60th birthday this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The composer John Adams is also a skilled and dynamic conductor. He showed his versatility on the podium in 2003 during one of the inaugural concerts for Zankel Hall, conducting demanding scores by Ives, Lou Harrison, Thomas Adès and Esa-Pekka Salonen.</p>
        <p>He certainly seemed in his element on Friday night at Carnegie Hall, when he conducted the American Composers Orchestra in an all-Adams program to commemorate his 60th birthday this year.</p>
        <p>After receiving the orchestra's Distinguished Composer Award from its artistic director, Robert Beaser, Mr. Adams remarked on how rewarding it was to work with musicians who have ''such immediate intuition'' for the ''inner life of my music.''</p>
        <p>The performances could not have been more vibrant and authoritative, starting with ''My Father Knew Charles Ives'' (2003), a three-movement, 25-minute de facto symphony. Actually, as Mr. Adams wrote in the program notes, his father did not know Charles Ives, though he was a similar kind of Yankee character.</p>
        <p>The piece is like an hommage to Ives: atmospheric and thickly textured music with multiple elements happening at once.</p>
        <p>''Concord,'' the first movement, begins with misty and shimmering sustained harmonies packed with pitches, over which a solo trumpet melody meanders restlessly, a clear reference to Ives's ''Unanswered Question.'' Soon, though, quiet internal riffs and rhythmic figures break out. ''The Lake,'' the second movement, is like a collage of marches, dance tunes and breezy piano salon music, with passages to take time out and meditate on it all. ''The Mountain'' is contemplative only on its deceptive surface, for the music builds in intensity and urgency, if not in volume and rhythmic drive. Though at times the score seemed structurally amorphous, moment to moment the music was riveting.</p>
        <p>In contrast, Mr. Adams's Violin Concerto (1993), here offering the virtuosic Leila Josefowicz as soloist, is very formally structured. There is a neo-Baroque quality to the work, which begins with a searching and endless melody for the violin as the orchestra plays recurring patterns of ascending figures.</p>
        <p>The second movement is a modernistic take on the Baroque chaconne form, here turned mystical, transfigured and hauntingly ethereal. The finale, marked ''Toccare,'' is a metrically fractured but perpetual-motion tour de force. Ms. Josefowicz gave an incisive, tireless, bright-toned and breathtaking account of the formidable solo part.</p>
        <p>It was gratifying to hear Mr. Adams's extraordinary 1989 vocal work, ''The Wound-Dresser.'' The 20-minute piece is a setting of Walt Whitman's profound and revealing account of attending to wounded soldiers as a nurse during the Civil War.</p>
        <p>The gravely beautiful yet restless music ennobles the text, but it also captures Whitman's ambiguous feelings.</p>
        <p>There is tension between the poet's graphic descriptions of the injuries and his real sense of witnessing spiritual transcendence of the body. In their anguish and pain, their need and hurt, these brave soldiers seem to Whitman the essence of young beauty tragically cut down.</p>
        <p>The bass-baritone Eric Owens brought a burnished and powerful voice to his sensitive performance, though his diction sometimes lacked clarity. Hearing every word of this extraordinary text is essential to the impact of the piece.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
