<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Intermission for Renovation Begins at Alice Tully Hall</title>
    <meta content="30linc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844031"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE1DC133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="845" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Intermission for Renovation Begins at Alice Tully Hall</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN POGREBIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pogrebin, Robin</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tonight, when the strains of Juilliard Orchestra violins have died away and Audra McDonald's vibrato is a fading memory, Alice Tully Hall will bid New York a temporary adieu and go dark until late 2008.</p>
        <p>This evening's gala, ''Good Night Alice,'' signals the start of a major transformation of the stage and surrounding spaces as part of Lincoln Center's ambitious redevelopment plan. The work is expected to take 18 months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tonight, when the strains of Juilliard Orchestra violins have died away and Audra McDonald's vibrato is a fading memory, Alice Tully Hall will bid New York a temporary adieu and go dark until late 2008.</p>
        <p>This evening's gala, ''Good Night Alice,'' signals the start of a major transformation of the stage and surrounding spaces as part of Lincoln Center's ambitious redevelopment plan. The work is expected to take 18 months.</p>
        <p>The Alice Tully makeover, designed by Diller Scofidio &amp; Renfro in collaboration with FXFowle, is perhaps the largest piece of a project that many doubted would ever come to pass, partly because of the steep price. Yet today Lincoln Center officials are to announce that they have raised $482 million of its estimated $702 million share of the overall project.</p>
        <p>''We are not declaring victory,'' Frank A. Bennack Jr., Lincoln Center's chairman, said in an interview. ''We're just saying we're in good shape.''</p>
        <p>In addition to a new auditorium and a three-story glass lobby for Alice Tully Hall, the improvements to the West 65th Street area include new rehearsal studios for Juilliard, a new lobby and marquee for Lincoln Center Theater, and a new theater and screening room for the Film Society. There will be public spaces like bleachers outside Alice Tully on Broadway, interactive information kiosks and a grass roof (of a new restaurant) where visitors can lounge and chat.</p>
        <p>Improvements to the plaza area include a streamlining of the fountain and a broad new staircase entrance with a new underground roadway for car drop-offs. The goal is to make the campus more welcoming and accessible.</p>
        <p>The Lincoln Center development project has not been without complications. Last month, Jerry Hastings resigned as the project's executive director after less than a year in the job, saying he wanted to pursue other opportunities. On Wednesday Lincoln Center named Ron Austin, a construction management specialist, to succeed him.</p>
        <p>And during the last year, the project's total estimated cost has climbed to $900 million, including $650 million for the 65th Street sector, $190 million for the plaza area and $60 million in additional expenses.</p>
        <p>(Of that $900 million, individual constituent groups -- including the Juilliard School, Film Society and Lincoln Center Theater -- are responsible for raising about $200 million.)</p>
        <p>The increases bring the price closer to the $1.2 billion originally projected in 1999, a figure later disavowed by Lincoln Center officials as excessive.</p>
        <p>The cost has risen because of the addition of new public and performance spaces and because improvements to the Juilliard School and the updating of mechanical systems proved more extensive than expected, said Katherine G. Farley, chairwoman of the development project.</p>
        <p>Additions include a renovation of the Harmony Atrium, an indoor space that extends from Broadway to Columbus Avenue between 62nd and 63rd Streets, as a gathering spot before or after performances and a place to buy discount tickets. Lincoln Center Theater is considering a experimental stage that has also been factored into the budget.</p>
        <p>Many elements have yet to be resolved. Changes to the New York State Theater are back on the table now that the New York City Opera has decided to stay there at the urging of its new director, Gerard Mortier, rather than look for its own home. The opera has already opened discussions with the New York City Ballet, which shares the theater, about potential adjustments, said Reynold Levy, the president of Lincoln Center.</p>
        <p>A new stage for Avery Fisher Hall has been designed by Norman Foster, but is on hold until the 65th Street project is completed. Other unfinished designs include one for a garage on West 65th Street and another for a friendlier facade on the west side of Lincoln Center, long criticized for turning its back on Amsterdam Avenue.</p>
        <p>Lincoln Center is promoting several naming opportunities to help pay for the redevelopment. Already christened are the Starr auditorium and the Hauser patrons lounge. A new ''Please Take Your Seat'' campaign offers naming options for $5,000 to $10,000 a chair.</p>
        <p>The gala tonight, which also features Wynton Marsalis and Philip Glass, is to be broadcast on Thursday as part of PBS's ''Live From Lincoln Center'' series. The event has raised more than $5 million, a record for a single Lincoln Center event, most of which will go toward the redevelopment.</p>
        <p>In the months ahead, Alice Tully's regular performances will unfold on other stages. The Great Performers series, the Film Society's New York Film Festival screenings and some of Juilliard's concerts will be moved to Jazz at Lincoln Center's Frederick P. Rose Hall at Columbus Circle. The Chamber Music Society will move most performances to the Society for Ethical Culture on Central Park West at 64th Street.</p>
        <p>Given a history of infighting among Lincoln Center's various groups, which once threatened to jeopardize fund-raising prospects for the project, the mood seems relatively upbeat. ''The news is good,'' Mr. Bennack said. ''This city and the movers and shakers in it have more awareness of what's going on at Lincoln Center than at any time in my 30 years here.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
