<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Disease Drove Sex Attack, Defense Says</title>
    <meta content="30fake" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/nyregion/30fake.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844101"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Schizophrenia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Braunstein, Peter</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E3DA133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1277" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Disease Drove Sex Attack, Defense Says</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Disease Drove Sex Attack, Defense Says</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANEMONA HARTOCOLLIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hartocollis, Anemona</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He was a media columnist for Women's Wear Daily who built a reputation on his writing about the counterculture of the 1960s and '70s. He got attention for his odd dress, a self-consciously nerdy, retro look that reminded some people of Austin Powers. His prose was dense, sarcastic, with intellectual overtones.</p>
        <p>Now the writer, Peter Braunstein, 43, is about to go on trial, charged with a bizarre crime against a woman who worked in his own newsroom. Prosecutors say he dressed as a firefighter, staged a fire to get into her Chelsea apartment, tied her to a bed, drugged her with chloroform and sexually molested her for 13 hours.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The defense in a writer’s trial for a bizarre sexual assault will make use of the burgeoning field of “neurolaw,” which holds that there is a biological basis for behavior.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He was a media columnist for Women's Wear Daily who built a reputation on his writing about the counterculture of the 1960s and '70s. He got attention for his odd dress, a self-consciously nerdy, retro look that reminded some people of Austin Powers. His prose was dense, sarcastic, with intellectual overtones.</p>
        <p>Now the writer, Peter Braunstein, 43, is about to go on trial, charged with a bizarre crime against a woman who worked in his own newsroom. Prosecutors say he dressed as a firefighter, staged a fire to get into her Chelsea apartment, tied her to a bed, drugged her with chloroform and sexually molested her for 13 hours.</p>
        <p>As the trial opens today in State Supreme Court in Manhattan, jurors will be asked to decide whether he was a sadistic man preying on an unsuspecting woman or whether his actions were the result of mental illness.</p>
        <p>The defense has conceded that he committed the crime, and is working on a risky defense that will combine traditional psychiatric testimony with the burgeoning field of ''neurolaw,'' which holds that there is a biological basis for behavior. Prosecutors have said that steps Mr. Braunstein took before the attack show his intent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Braunstein's lawyer, Robert Gottlieb, has said he would show color images of his client's brain, called positron emission tomography, or PET, scans, that he said show that Mr. Braunstein had undiagnosed and, until his arrest, untreated paranoid schizophrenia that drove him to behave as he did.</p>
        <p>During jury selection last week, and in his court papers, Mr. Gottlieb said he planned to argue that Mr. Braunstein was so psychologically impaired that he could not form the intent to commit a crime. He has hinted that Mr. Braunstein's attack on the woman was part of an elaborate fantasy over which he had little conscious control.</p>
        <p>In similar cases, lawyers have argued that their clients were in a dissociated state, much like sleepwalking. A version of this defense, said Rachel Barkow, a law professor at New York University, would be: ''You know killing is wrong, but it turns out you think you're in the middle of a video game. Because of a paranoid delusional state, you thought it was all a fantasy.''</p>
        <p>A more classic lack of intention defense, said Stephen J. Morse, a professor of law and psychiatry at the University of Pennsylvania, would be that someone out hunting in the dark shot a person thinking he was shooting a tree.</p>
        <p>Dr. Morse compared Mr. Braunstein's argument to that in Clark v. Arizona, in which the defendant, a paranoid schizophrenic, was convicted of killing an Arizona police officer. There, too, intent was one of the issues, he said. The defendant claimed that he thought aliens -- some impersonating government agents -- were trying to kill him. ''If he really believed that this was a space alien, he did not intend to kill a human being knowing it was a police officer,'' Dr. Morse explained. (The United States Supreme Court affirmed the murder conviction in 2006.)</p>
        <p>But the challenge of mounting such a defense, Dr. Morse said, is that ''even abnormal brains produce intention.'' Dr. Morse said that for a defendant to claim he was in an automatic state like sleepwalking for 13 hours would be unusual. ''Virtually always, when people claim they committed a crime in an automatic state, that automatic state was relatively transient,'' he said.</p>
        <p>At first glance, Mr. Braunstein seems an unlikely candidate for a high profile trial. He had a fairly ordinary upbringing in Kew Gardens, Queens. The strangest part of his past, according to court papers, may be the family secret he unearthed when he was 27. He found out that his cousin was also his half-brother, the son of his father's previous marriage to his aunt.</p>
        <p>But because of his connection to New York's fashion and media worlds, his story has been picked up not only by the crime-hungry tabloids, but by Vanity Fair and New York magazine.</p>
        <p>As if working off a script, Mr. Braunstein staged the crime on Oct. 31, 2005, Halloween night, the prosecutors said. In an echo of a scene from his failed 2004 play, ''Andy and Edie,'' about Andy Warhol and Edie Sedgwick, it appeared he had videotaped his attack, although court papers say the tape was blank. He left a Manolo Blahnik shoe -- the ultimate symbol of the fashion industry that had cast him out a few years before -- on the bed, the police said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Braunstein spent six weeks as a fugitive before being captured at the University of Memphis, where an employee recognized him from the television program ''America's Most Wanted.''</p>
        <p>His downward spiral began in 2002, according to court papers filed by the defense, when he was fired from Women's Wear Daily, in a dispute over free tickets to a Vogue event, and accelerated after he broke up with his girlfriend, Jane Larkworthy, the beauty editor at W magazine. ''Without the stabilizing factor of a regular job, Mr. Braunstein rapidly began to unravel psychologically,'' Barbara R. Kirwin, a clinical psychologist hired by the defense, said in a written report. He became suicidal and felt like a ''person who exists with no social identity,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But the fashion press, Dr. Kirwin added, was the wrong job for Mr. Braunstein from the beginning.</p>
        <p>''Working in the highly competitive, glitzy and sexually charged atmosphere of a celebrity-driven fashion periodical was an extremely toxic and unsuitable environment for a socially compromised and marginally compensated schizotype like Mr. Braunstein,'' Dr. Kirwin wrote.</p>
        <p>''It was,'' she added, ''in fact the proverbial recipe for disaster.''</p>
        <p>The expert who conducted Mr. Braunstein's PET scans, Monte S. Buchsbaum, a professor of psychiatry at Mount Sinai School of Medicine, has worked with other high-profile defendants, including Vincent Gigante, the Mafia leader. Mr. Gigante was known for wandering Greenwich Village in a bathrobe and slippers, and prosecutors accused him of faking mental illness to avoid prosecution. Dr. Buchsbaum testified in 1997 that brain images showed Mr. Gigante suffered from dementia.</p>
        <p>In 2003, Mr. Gigante pleaded guilty to obstruction of justice, admitting he tried to outsmart the legal system by pretending he was mentally ill. Dr. Buchsbaum said in an interview last week that he stands by his diagnosis of Mr. Gigante, who died in 2005, and that he considered the guilty plea to be a legal maneuver.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Braunstein's case, while the defense is putting forward an insanity defense, prosecutors have a more prosaic theory of what happened. Maxine Rosenthal, the lead prosecutor, argued in pretrial hearings that Mr. Braunstein was bitter over his breakup with Ms. Larkworthy and enraged at the fashion world for rejecting him.</p>
        <p>He could not attack Ms. Larkworthy, the prosecutor said, because she had taken out an order of protection against him, after accusing him of harassing and stalking her. So he lashed out at his co-worker, the prosecutor said, because she was an unwary surrogate for those who had betrayed and humiliated him.</p>
        <p>The intentional element, the prosecutors said, can be seen in Mr. Braunstein's ordering of the firefighter's costume, chloroform and other supplies. He also called his probation officer in the stalking case to postpone an appointment scheduled for Oct. 31, the day of the attack.</p>
        <p>In the end, said Stephen Gillers, a law professor at New York University, Mr. Braunstein will have to show why he should not be held accountable by society. ''Gottlieb can point to his very pretty color photograph of Braunstein's brain,'' Mr. Gillers said. ''But that's not going to be enough. He's got to satisfy the moral conscience of the jury, which is going to take this very seriously.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
