<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Former Political Director at ABC Is Moving to Time Magazine</title>
    <meta content="30time" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/business/media/30time.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070502T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844010"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consultants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Time</org>
        <org class="online_producer">ABC Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Halperin, Mark</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E4DC133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="496" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Former Political Director at ABC Is Moving to Time Magazine</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Former Political Director at ABC Is Moving to Time Magazine</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARIA ASPAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Aspan, Maria</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mark Halperin, who stepped down last month as the political director of ABC News, is moving to Time magazine.</p>
        <p>Mr. Halperin, a pioneer of online reporting who founded ABCnews.com's political memo, The Note, will join Time as an editor-at-large and senior policy analyst effective next Monday, the magazine said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mark Halperin, a pioneer of online reporting who founded ABCnews.com’s political memo, The Note, will join Time as an editor-at-large and senior political analyst.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mark Halperin, who stepped down last month as the political director of ABC News, is moving to Time magazine.</p>
        <p>Mr. Halperin, a pioneer of online reporting who founded ABCnews.com's political memo, The Note, will join Time as an editor-at-large and senior policy analyst effective next Monday, the magazine said.</p>
        <p>ABC said that Mr. Halperin would continue to play a role at the network as a policy analyst and political consultant. David Chalian, a longtime political reporter at ABC, replaced him in late March as political director, while a senior political reporter, Rick Klein, will take over this week as the primary author of The Note.</p>
        <p>So why would an executive who had spent 10 years overseeing political coverage across all of ABC's news shows relinquish such a job right when a wide-open presidential campaign is starting to heat up?</p>
        <p>''After almost 20 years in one place and having decided I really liked to write, I wanted to figure out a way to keep doing TV with ABC but also keep writing,'' Mr. Halperin said in a telephone interview. He is an author, along with John F. Harris of The Washington Post, of a book published last fall about what it would take for a candidate to win the White House in 2008.</p>
        <p>At Time, Mr. Halperin will report to Richard Stengel and Josh Tyrangiel, the managing editors, respectively, of Time magazine and the Time.com Web site.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stengel said that he started talking to Mr. Halperin, a longtime acquaintance, after the ABC announcement last month, with an eye to preparing for Time's coverage of the 2008 elections.</p>
        <p>''We're a 24/7 news site now, and politics is the biggest game in town,'' said Mr. Stengel, who has overseen a redesign at the magazine and a major shift in resources from print to the Web site. ''Everybody wants to be ahead of the curve in this area, and Mark is the curve,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Halperin will write and produce a ''daily product'' about politics on Time.com, as well as contribute to the magazine and appear as a policy analyst for Time on network and cable television news shows.</p>
        <p>Both men declined to provide specific details about Mr. Halperin's online project, which they said was still evolving. But Mr. Halperin said that it would not be competing with The Note, which he started during the 2000 election cycle as an internal daily politics memo. It was introduced to the public in 2002, setting the standard for many political blogs and online news digests to come.</p>
        <p>ABC temporarily downgraded The Note to The Mini-Note last month but has since restored it as part of a redesigned ABCnews.com Web site, unveiled over the weekend. The new Note will officially be introduced on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stengel of Time acknowledged that there would be comparisons between Mr. Halperin's old and new online ventures, but the new one, he said, was ''going to be a fabulous successor to The Note.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 2, 2007, Wednesday  An article in Business Day on Monday about Mark Halperin, who stepped down as the political director of ABC News and will join Time magazine, misstated his role at both media outlets. He is a political -- not a policy -- analyst. Because of an editing error, the article referred incorrectly to John F. Harris who, with Mr. Halperin wrote a book about the 2008 presidential race. Mr. Harris, who was at The Washington Post when the book was published last fall, is now editor in chief of The Politico, which covers national politics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 2, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day on Monday about Mark Halperin, who stepped down as the political director of ABC News and will join Time magazine, misstated his role at both media outlets. He is a political -- not a policy -- analyst. Because of an editing error, the article referred incorrectly to John F. Harris who, with Mr. Halperin wrote a book about the 2008 presidential race. Mr. Harris, who was at The Washington Post when the book was published last fall, is now editor in chief of The Politico, which covers national politics.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
