<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rising to Challenges in the Familiar: Dreams, Ghosts, a Flapper and a Guy</title>
    <meta content="30tudo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/arts/dance/30tudo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844000"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">American Ballet Theater Studio Company</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Tudor, Antony</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E6DC133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="401" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rising to Challenges in the Familiar: Dreams, Ghosts, a Flapper and a Guy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rising to Challenges in the Familiar: Dreams, Ghosts, a Flapper and a Guy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunning, Jennifer</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The technique and performing were as impressive as ever by the American Ballet Theater Studio Company on Friday at the Skirball Center at New York University. Even more, the dancers met the stylistic challenges of the program's five very different pieces.</p>
        <p>Brian Reeder gave them an exercise in nostalgia in his new ''Ghost Light,'' set to a brassy, glinting score by Aaron Copland. The theme and the characters were familiar: a dreaming stagehand (Roddy Doble) with a broom and his fleeting encounters with seeming ghosts, who included two elegant swells (Devon Teuscher and Ty Gurfein), a flapper and her guy (Mary Mills Thomas and Yannick Bittencourt), and two urchins (Aria Alekzander and José Sebastian). With time and a little more living, the performers will doubtless invest it all with the kind of perfume more experienced dancers might bring to the ballet. But such a time was perfectly imaginable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The technique and performing were as impressive as ever, and the dancers met the stylistic challenges of the program’s five very different pieces.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The technique and performing were as impressive as ever by the American Ballet Theater Studio Company on Friday at the Skirball Center at New York University. Even more, the dancers met the stylistic challenges of the program's five very different pieces.</p>
        <p>Brian Reeder gave them an exercise in nostalgia in his new ''Ghost Light,'' set to a brassy, glinting score by Aaron Copland. The theme and the characters were familiar: a dreaming stagehand (Roddy Doble) with a broom and his fleeting encounters with seeming ghosts, who included two elegant swells (Devon Teuscher and Ty Gurfein), a flapper and her guy (Mary Mills Thomas and Yannick Bittencourt), and two urchins (Aria Alekzander and José Sebastian). With time and a little more living, the performers will doubtless invest it all with the kind of perfume more experienced dancers might bring to the ballet. But such a time was perfectly imaginable.</p>
        <p>Antony Tudor's ''Jardin aux Lilas'' (''Lilac Garden'') requires that perfume. But these young dancers made something of their own of that ballet classic, performed with care in a staging by Donald Mahler.</p>
        <p>Ms. Teuscher was a warm and womanly Caroline and Mr. Doble appropriately stolid as her chill fiancé. Mr. Bittencourt was a little bland as Caroline's lover, but Christine Shevchenko's strong performance as the fiancé's lover suggested, unusually, the fragility of the character. Katherine Williams nearly stole the show in the small but important role of the sad friend who tries to comfort Caroline, a performance full of pathos delivered by a dancer with the most eloquent of backs.</p>
        <p>It was Joseph Gorak's pliant feet -- oh, for a pair of toe shoes -- that drew the eyes first to him. But Mr. Gorak, the company's resident classicist, also stood out for the fine articulation of his dancing. He did that first in ''Nocturne,'' a new solo set to Chopin and choreographed by the company director, Kirk Peterson, and next in the pas de deux from Bournonville's ''Flower Festival in Genzano.'' His partner, Ms. Teuscher, moved with slightly too hard an attack, but proved already to be a trouper, blithely negotiating complex, finicky choreography evenwith a trailing shoe-ribbon underfoot.</p>
        <p>Adam Hougland gave the dancers a workout in his new ''Vanish.'' Ten performers sliced sharply through the stage to driving music by Peteris Vasks, bodies flying in high skewed lifts, as fresh as if this were the first dance of the evening.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
