<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Playoff Overtime: Its Drama Is Incomparable</title>
    <meta content="30anderson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/sports/hockey/30anderson.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844067"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Buffalo Sabres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Buffalo Sabres</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DB133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="823" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Playoff Overtime: Its Drama Is Incomparable</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Playoff Overtime: Its Drama Is Incomparable</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the Rangers, these were the desperate hours of why hockey people consider sudden-death Stanley Cup overtime to be sport's best theater.</p>
        <p>If the Rangers had lost yesterday's marathon matinee at Madison Square Garden, they would be down, three games to none, to the Buffalo Sabres and all but out of the Eastern Conference semifinals. If they won, they would pull to 2-1 with the opportunity to even the series tomorrow night at the Garden.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the Rangers, these were the desperate hours of why hockey people consider sudden-death Stanley Cup overtime to be sport’s best theater.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the Rangers, these were the desperate hours of why hockey people consider sudden-death Stanley Cup overtime to be sport's best theater.</p>
        <p>If the Rangers had lost yesterday's marathon matinee at Madison Square Garden, they would be down, three games to none, to the Buffalo Sabres and all but out of the Eastern Conference semifinals. If they won, they would pull to 2-1 with the opportunity to even the series tomorrow night at the Garden.</p>
        <p>And with 18,200 fans roaring ''Let's go, Rangers!'' they won when defenseman Michal Rozsival's bullet from the blue line zipped past Sabres goaltender Ryan Miller at 16 minutes 43 seconds of the second overtime.</p>
        <p>''Going into the fifth period, you know that if you relax for a second it could be over,'' goaltender Henrik Lundqvist, his long-sleeve navy blue undershirt soaked through with perspiration, said in his corner of the dressing room. ''It was a must-win for us, and it came out big. We dominated the game. We deserved to win.''</p>
        <p>Not since their joyous journey in 1994, when Mark Messier, Brian Leetch and Mike Richter hoisted Lord Stanley's silver chalice for the franchise's first Cup title since 1940, had the Rangers worked so hard and so long and so successfully to win a game that displayed all the determination and drama of classic playoff hockey: Two good teams of skaters with tireless energy; two outstanding goaltenders sprawling and squirming in the tension.</p>
        <p>No other event can match it. Not the Super Bowl, which has never had an overtime game. Not the World Series, where there is no time element. Not the N.B.A. playoffs, which has complete overtime periods. Not soccer's World Cup, which can dissolve into a penalty-kick shootout.</p>
        <p>But when the score of an N.H.L. playoff game is tied at the end of the regulation 60 minutes, the teams keep playing until somebody scores. It's always theater and it's often history.</p>
        <p>As yesterday's duel continued, many of those voices yelling ''Let's go, Rangers!'' remembered when Stéphane Matteau swatted the puck past Devils goaltender Martin Brodeur to snap a 1-1 tie after 4:24 of the second overtime in Game 7 of the 1994 Eastern Conference finals. Matteau was not a Ranger for long, but he is a legend.</p>
        <p>If the Devils had won that game, the Rangers would not have won the title that year. Judging by the quality of most Rangers teams since then, the franchise's Cup drought might well be 67 years and counting.</p>
        <p>Not that these Rangers are likely to win the Cup. The Sabres are a better team, maybe the best in the league. But yesterday, these Rangers provided their usually frustrated followers with a game to remember as well as a goaltender to remember.</p>
        <p>Every so often, the chant ''Hen-rik! Hen-rik!'' resounded through the Garden, even louder when he was announced as the game's first star and he waved his big goalie stick, skating the width of the ice.</p>
        <p>Minutes earlier, if the puck had slid across the goal line when the Sabres were swarming around him, Lundqvist might have been booed. But it didn't. The puck was cleared, the Rangers took off down the ice, and Rozsival, a Czech defenseman, fired a shot heard round the hockey world. ''I always tell him to shoot more,'' Lundqvist said. ''He always hits the net.''</p>
        <p>Lundqvist had toweled his bearded face and hair, but he was still sweating. His undershirt was still soaked. So were his red uniform pants and his red-white-and-blue stockings. On the floor nearby, his leather skates glistened.</p>
        <p>''You can't take your skates off between periods,'' he said. ''If you turned around the skates now, it would come out water.''</p>
        <p>Lundqvist deflected or smothered 38 of 39 shots, while Miller stopped 44 of 46 in their goaltender duel. Good, if not great, goaltending creates the tension of overtime hockey, the tension that sooner or later is always cut when a puck stretches the twine, as Rozsival's slap shot did, or slides across the goal line, as Chris Drury's shot nearly did moments earlier.</p>
        <p>''I didn't know where the puck was,'' Lundqvist said. ''I saw the puck under my pads. I think it hit my skate. I was slow coming across.''</p>
        <p>He wasn't slow very often. The Sabres' two most dangerous skaters, Daniel Brière and Drury, had a total of 11 shots on goal, but neither scored. And finally, when Lundqvist was pressed to rate his performance against others in his career, he remembered having ''a couple games like this in Sweden,'' and he remembered playing well in earning an Olympic gold medal for Sweden last year in Turin.</p>
        <p>''But it's more intense over here,'' he said. ''You know the feeling if you win and if you lose. That's hockey. That's why you love the sport.''</p>
        <p>And that's why everybody loves overtime hockey in the Stanley Cup playoffs -- the best theater in any sport. Especially when your team wins.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
