<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nets Get Healthy Boost From Kidd and Carter</title>
    <meta content="30nets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/sports/basketball/30nets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844109"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Toronto Raptors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Toronto Raptors</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Basketball Assn</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Kidd, Jason</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Carter, Vince</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE2DA133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="805" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nets Get Healthy Boost From Kidd and Carter</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nets Get Healthy Boost From Kidd and Carter</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eligon, John</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., April 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In creating a strikingly familiar sequel to their script of two nights earlier, the Nets' Jason Kidd and Vince Carter might have been putting the preliminary touches on their legacy as a backcourt tandem.</p>
        <p>Kidd directed the stage Sunday night at Continental Arena, and Carter took care of the high-flying stunts. By the time they were sitting next to each other on the bench early in the fourth quarter, the credits were already rolling on Game 4. The Nets demolished the Raptors, 102-81, to take a 3-1 lead in the first-round Eastern Conference playoff series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The sixth-seeded Nets won for the second consecutive time at home to take a 3-1 advantage in the series. They are a game from knocking off the third-seeded Raptors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In creating a strikingly familiar sequel to their script of two nights earlier, the Nets' Jason Kidd and Vince Carter might have been putting the preliminary touches on their legacy as a backcourt tandem.</p>
        <p>Kidd directed the stage Sunday night at Continental Arena, and Carter took care of the high-flying stunts. By the time they were sitting next to each other on the bench early in the fourth quarter, the credits were already rolling on Game 4. The Nets demolished the Raptors, 102-81, to take a 3-1 lead in the first-round Eastern Conference playoff series.</p>
        <p>Having won at home for the second consecutive time, the sixth-seeded Nets are one victory from knocking off the third-seeded Raptors and advancing to the conference semifinals. Game 5 will be Tuesday night in Toronto.</p>
        <p>Kidd finished with 17 points, 13 assists and 8 rebounds, and would have probably had his second consecutive triple-double had he not sat out the entire fourth quarter. Carter, who sat out the game's final 10 minutes, had 27 points, 7 rebounds and 7 assists. He made 9 of 15 shots, and Kidd shot 6 for 10.</p>
        <p>Kidd and Carter hit five 3-pointers each, leading the way for a Nets playoff record of 14, on 27 attempts.</p>
        <p>''I think the thing that's unique about Jason and Vince is that they compete for each other,'' Nets Coach Lawrence Frank said. ''Sometimes, you have situations where you have two high-level All-Stars, they compete against each other. These guys totally relish in making sure the other one plays well.''</p>
        <p>Kidd and Carter were as synchronized as a pair of ballroom dancers. It is difficult to imagine that in February the Nets were seriously considering trading one or both.</p>
        <p>With their stellar play over the past two games, Kidd and Carter may be putting pressure on team management to keep them together. Carter can opt out of the final year of his contract after the playoffs.</p>
        <p>''Hopefully, when it's all said and done, we can be with some of the best backcourts who have ever played,'' Kidd said. ''Only time will tell.''</p>
        <p>The Nets' third star, Richard Jefferson, scored 23 points. The three helped the Nets lead by as many as 33 points, perhaps sucking the life out of an already deflated Raptors team.</p>
        <p>Jefferson has been growing accustomed to solid performances that go unnoticed because of the sizzle of the Nets' starting backcourt.</p>
        <p>''If you look at ability, if you look at All-Star selections, if you look at just sheer numbers, there's not too many 1 and 2 combos that have had as much personal success or individual success as those two,'' Jefferson said.</p>
        <p>Kidd's success in Game 3 on Friday night was somewhat overshadowed by a minor controversy that started afterward. He missed a day of practice last week after bruising his knee in Game 2. After Kidd had 16 points, 16 rebounds and 19 assists in Game 3 -- becoming the third player in postseason history to have at least 15 in three categories -- Raptors Coach Sam Mitchell referred to Kidd's injury as ''so-called.'' On Saturday, Mitchell was animated in discussing the topic.</p>
        <p>''The man just did something that only three men in the history of the N.B.A. have done, and you're asking me, Is he faking?'' he said. ''Do you think he's really hurt? He just set a record. What do you think?''</p>
        <p>After Sunday night's game, Kidd said, ''The comments didn't really bother me.''</p>
        <p>Nothing fazed Kidd or Carter from the opening tip of Game 4.</p>
        <p>They strung together long-range shots, alley-oops and no-look passes.</p>
        <p>They got the crowd of 20,032 buzzing midway through the first quarter when they hit 3-pointers on consecutive possessions less than 30 seconds apart.</p>
        <p>Later in the first quarter, Kidd and Carter really got the arena rocking. On two occasions, Kidd threw a lob pass from the top of the 3-point arc, and Carter caught the ball midair for a reverse dunk. The second one came with 3 minutes 34 seconds remaining in the first quarter and gave the Nets a 26-15 lead. The Nets were ahead after the first quarter by 32-15, and they led by 19 (56-37) at halftime.</p>
        <p>The Nets' stars again outperformed those of the Raptors -- Chris Bosh (13 points; 5 of 12 shooting), T. J. Ford (13 points; 6 of 16) and Anthony Parker (5 points; 1 of 6).</p>
        <p>Those three entered Game 4 having accounted for 65 percent of the Raptors' points in the series. Mitchell, looking for contributions from others, changed his starting lineup by inserting the rookie forward Andrea Bargnani for Joey Graham. Bargnani led Toronto with 16 points.</p>
        <p>''We need some other guys to step in, join the party, start playing better,'' Mitchell said before the game.</p>
        <p>But Kidd and Carter made the Raptors' lineup all but irrelevant.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
