<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Vestige of the Past Shutters Its Stalls</title>
    <meta content="30claremont" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/nyregion/30claremont.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844074"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Claremont Riding Academy</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CEEDB133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1130" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Vestige of the Past Shutters Its Stalls</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Vestige of the Past Shutters Its Stalls</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MANNY FERNANDEZ; Sean McManus contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fernandez, Manny</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The horses relaxed upstairs in their wooden stalls as the radio played, munching on hay and oblivious to history, controversy and other human concerns. Downstairs, in an old office lined with dusty saddles, Paul Novograd pulled out a black-and-white photo from the 1930s. It was a picture of his father.</p>
        <p>Mr. Novograd's Polish-born father, Irwin, started working at the Claremont Riding Academy during the Depression, as a bookkeeper. He took over the business in 1943, and his son, who grew up playing hide-and-seek among the hay bales, eventually became the owner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Claremont Riding Academy, the oldest continuously operated stable in New York City, shut its doors for good on Sunday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The horses relaxed upstairs in their wooden stalls as the radio played, munching on hay and oblivious to history, controversy and other human concerns. Downstairs, in an old office lined with dusty saddles, Paul Novograd pulled out a black-and-white photo from the 1930s. It was a picture of his father.</p>
        <p>Mr. Novograd's Polish-born father, Irwin, started working at the Claremont Riding Academy during the Depression, as a bookkeeper. He took over the business in 1943, and his son, who grew up playing hide-and-seek among the hay bales, eventually became the owner.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Paul Novograd, 63, ended the family tradition, closing the stables for good. Were this some other place, some place out West maybe, the shuttering of one old riding school might have gone unnoticed. But what made Claremont unique was not so much what it was but where it was: in the heart of Manhattan, on the Upper West Side, a few steps from a Papa John's pizzeria at the corner of Amsterdam Avenue and West 89th Street, and less than two blocks from Central Park.</p>
        <p>The academy was the oldest continuously operated stable in New York City and, according to Mr. Novograd, the oldest in the United States, offering riding lessons and the renting and boarding of horses. It was a patch of un-Manhattan in Manhattan, definitive proof that the city indeed had it all -- skyscrapers, a nearly naked cowboy in Times Square and horses you could rent for $55 an hour.</p>
        <p>Mr. Novograd's decision to close the academy shocked many of his customers and even many of his 30 employees. All day yesterday, the last official day of business at Claremont, people stood around as if at a wake.</p>
        <p>Upstairs, Chelsea Roberts, 47, who started riding the horses at Claremont in the early 1970s, said goodbye to one of her favorites, Bach. She brought along her 10-year-old son, Maxwell Roberts-Pereira, who learned how to ride at the academy. Downstairs, in the main office just outside the riding ring, someone taped a letter to Claremont to the glass panes of the door: ''You are more than brick, mortar, wood, dirt and hay. Your soul is made of all those souls that have come through your doors.''</p>
        <p>And down a muddy, cleated ramp on the sidewalk outside, Christina Valauri snapped a picture and shook her head.</p>
        <p>''I've ridden here, my daughter's ridden here,'' said Ms. Valauri, a research director at a brokerage firm. ''This is a real loss. I actually feel like I am at a funeral.''</p>
        <p>The riding school was formed in 1927, in a tan-brick building erected in 1892 as a public livery stable. It had escaped death before, when the city condemned and took over the property from Irwin Novograd in the 1960s as part of an urban renewal program. The city never followed through on its plans for public housing at the Claremont site, and in the late 1990s Mr. Novograd's son bought it back.</p>
        <p>But insurance costs, payments on a loan for a $2 million restoration and taxes had become too costly, Paul Novograd said, while business decreased over the years by hundreds of riders on an average weekend.</p>
        <p>''It's a wonderful institution,'' he said. ''It's a shame it has to go. But I can't go into bankruptcy. I've taken out a second mortgage on my house to put money into this place.''</p>
        <p>He said that the popularity of nearby Central Park worked against him and the horses. Riders could take the horses for a stroll on the scenic bridle path in the park, but as the path became more congested with joggers and other pedestrians, the path's upkeep decreased, as did the number of customers willing to navigate the crowds, he said. ''The bridle path has become like an obstacle course, with dogs nipping at horses' heels, people pushing baby strollers,'' Mr. Novograd said.</p>
        <p>He declined to answer questions about what would happen to the building, which would be worth millions on the market. ''I can't say anything about the future,'' Mr. Novograd said, though he added that the building could not be torn down because it is a registered national and city landmark.</p>
        <p>The parents of many children who were Claremont regulars expressed frustration with Mr. Novograd and the speed with which he announced the closing. Mr. Novograd told his employees last Sunday evening that the academy was shutting its doors, and many customers found out about it the next day. There was an awkwardness at the stable yesterday, as Mr. Novograd walked among so many of his critics, some quietly and others not so quietly making their frustrations known.</p>
        <p>Mary Hanlon, whose 11-year-old daughter has been to the riding school twice a week, said she found it hard to believe that all the options to keep the stable open had been exhausted, from seeking help from nonprofit groups to creating a public-private partnership. ''I can't believe one person can take this away,'' she said. ''It's a community center.''</p>
        <p>Councilwoman Gale A. Brewer of Manhattan and Scott M. Stringer, the borough president, condemned the closing at a news conference at the academy on Saturday, but it is unclear what, if anything, riders and city officials could do. Yesterday, as former and current Claremont riders flocked to the academy for one last look or one last ride, the nostalgia for New York City's equestrian anachronism was everywhere. There are other nearby places to go horseback riding, including in Riverdale in the Bronx, but they said they went to Claremont not out of habit but out of love.</p>
        <p>Ms. Roberts, who visited Bach in the stalls upstairs, remembered riding a Claremont horse through Central Park after her grandmother died. ''Horses listen to you,'' she said. Riders young and old spoke of Claremont horses as a means of escape from city life, however temporary.</p>
        <p>Claremont horses were 1,500-pound New Yorkers who had a way of making fans and making news. Casco, a 17-hand gelding, starred in ''Aida'' at the Metropolitan Opera. On an annual spring ride, waiters from Tavern on the Green used to serve the horses carrot treats on silver trays.</p>
        <p>Some were caught up in tragedy and drama. Escargot threw off its rider in Central Park in November 1983 and struck a 71-year-old woman on a bicycle. The woman later died from her injuries. In 1969, a state court ruled that a civil rights law did not apply to horses, after a complaint was brought against the academy for refusing to stable a horse.</p>
        <p>Mr. Novograd said the academy's roughly 45 horses will be sent to good homes. Some are going to the Potomac Horse Center, which Mr. Novograd operates in Gaithersburg, Md. Others are being sold privately or donated to the Yale University riding team.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
