<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METROPOLITAN DIARY</title>
    <meta content="30diary" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/nyregion/30diary.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844049"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Metropolitan Diary"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metropolitan Diary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E4DB133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="757" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METROPOLITAN DIARY</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Dear Diary</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>With baseball season upon us, I am reminded of a trip to Yankee Stadium a few years ago.</p>
        <p>I took a friend visiting from Poland to a Yankees-Red Sox game. He had never been to a game before, so I very carefully described the rules as the game progressed -- a nail-biter that ended in a victory for the home team and an unfortunate finish for me, a loyal Sox fan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A European visitor takes in a nail-biter between the Yankees and the Red Sox in the Bronx.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>With baseball season upon us, I am reminded of a trip to Yankee Stadium a few years ago.</p>
        <p>I took a friend visiting from Poland to a Yankees-Red Sox game. He had never been to a game before, so I very carefully described the rules as the game progressed -- a nail-biter that ended in a victory for the home team and an unfortunate finish for me, a loyal Sox fan.</p>
        <p>Upon returning to our home, my wife asked our friend how he had enjoyed the game. ''It was great,'' he said, ''and Max explained it so well that I understood everything by the first awning.''</p>
        <p>G. Max Bernheimer</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>Hoping to avoid a line at the post office, I stopped in my office mailroom to weigh my tax returns. I was holding a clutch of old stamps, hoping to use them up.</p>
        <p>When I began to affix the correct denominations, the clerk stopped me. ''I don't think I'd use those on mail to the I.R.S.,'' he said.</p>
        <p>I looked at the colorful oversized stamps, left from a Disney series issued long ago. I had almost sent my returns to the government embellished with an attention-getting row of Pinocchios.</p>
        <p>P. J. Matson</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>A recent Tuesday, 10 p.m., back in my building after a concert at Lincoln Center; in the elevator with a lady I have seen off and on for the 28 years that I have lived here. We exchange pleasantries, and catch up a bit on things.</p>
        <p>And then I offer:</p>
        <p>''What a cute dog you have! What's his name?''</p>
        <p>''Rudy.''</p>
        <p>''After Giuliani?''</p>
        <p>My fellow New Yorker draws herself up.</p>
        <p>''This is the West Side. Nureyev.''</p>
        <p>Warren Jones</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>My daughter, a recent college graduate, moved into her first apartment, on Broome Street in Lower Manhattan, directly across the street from the beautiful old firehouse of Engine Company 55.</p>
        <p>The other day, as she was shopping in the local supermarket, she spotted a group of the firefighters and overheard one of them say to the others:</p>
        <p>''I don't believe it. We can rush into burning buildings and put out fires, but we can't agree on what to cook for dinner!''</p>
        <p>Cynthia Rothstein</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>The fine weather today reminds me of another beautiful spring day several years ago.</p>
        <p>I was walking up Broadway in the low 90s enjoying the warm air and bright sunshine.</p>
        <p>Stopping for a traffic light, I noticed a couple of women on the opposite curb, also waiting for the light to change. When it did we all started to cross the street.</p>
        <p>A fast-moving car appeared from nowhere, speeding toward us. We all froze as the car screeched to a halt only a few feet from us.</p>
        <p>One of the women I had noticed earlier wheeled to face the driver. I expected to hear a few choice epithets.</p>
        <p>Instead, with a hand gesture worthy of the Supremes, she sang, ''Stop, in the name of love!'' Without a thought I sang the next phrase, ''Before you break my heart.''</p>
        <p>Startled by our spontaneity, we stared at each other for a moment, and then sang together, ''Think it o-o-ver.''</p>
        <p>We laughed, high-fived, and continued on our ways.</p>
        <p>Richard Maxwell</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>On a recent Sunday, my wife deposited me at the cheese counter of the Fairway store near 125th Street with a list of items, and left to shop for other products. One of the items on my list was Greek feta.</p>
        <p>When I requested that item, the clerk replied that they did not have Greek feta in stock, but only French feta.</p>
        <p>I asked him what the difference was between Greek and French. His reply: ''They are different countries.''</p>
        <p>Ray Simon</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>While seeking a particular address on West 67th Street, my wife and I passed No. 17, whose half-opened door revealed a lobby packed with happy people. Overheard at the same time from a man on the sidewalk was the comment, ''He should be here in about five minutes.''</p>
        <p>It had all the appearance of a surprise party. We stayed across the street just long enough to see the honoree walk into the lobby to the sound of a very loud ''Surprise!''</p>
        <p>The next day I went back to the site of the celebration and learned that the surprise party was held for the night doorman's 72nd birthday and his more than 40 years of extraordinary service.</p>
        <p>Congratulations to him, and kudos to those thoughtful residents.</p>
        <p>Sy Sarnoff</p>
        <p>Metropolitan Diary</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
