<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Patriots Accelerate an Overhaul By Trading for the Raiders' Moss</title>
    <meta content="30moss" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/sports/football/30moss.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844086"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New England Patriots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Oakland Raiders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New England Patriots</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Oakland Raiders</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Moss, Randy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E5DA133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Patriots Accelerate an Overhaul By Trading for the Raiders' Moss</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Patriots Accelerate an Overhaul by Trading for the Raiders’ Moss</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New England Patriots have built a dynasty by stockpiling draft picks, avoiding big-name veterans and shunning players with character problems.</p>
        <p>But the Patriots blew up their own blueprint yesterday, acquiring the supremely talented and mercurial receiver Randy Moss in a trade with the Oakland Raiders for a fourth-round draft pick.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Patriots have loaded up on talent during the off-season, but the acquisition of Randy Moss is their most dramatic move yet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New England Patriots have built a dynasty by stockpiling draft picks, avoiding big-name veterans and shunning players with character problems.</p>
        <p>But the Patriots blew up their own blueprint yesterday, acquiring the supremely talented and mercurial receiver Randy Moss in a trade with the Oakland Raiders for a fourth-round draft pick.</p>
        <p>This off-season, the Patriots have loaded up on talent, but the acquisition of Moss is their most dramatic move yet. It is a testament to the Patriots' aggressiveness in shoring up their most glaring weaknesses. In addition to linebacker Adalius Thomas, one of the prizes of the free-agent class, the Patriots have overhauled the receiver spot, adding Wes Welker, Kelley Washington, Donte' Stallworth, and now Moss.</p>
        <p>Moss spent two mostly disgruntled years in Oakland, enhancing his reputation for being a coaching headache, and he made clear his desire to be traded by refusing to show up for any off-season work under the Raiders' new coach, Lane Kiffin.</p>
        <p>Now Moss, in his 10th season, joins the most talented and most disciplined team of his career, a perennial Super Bowl contender led by quarterback Tom Brady. It is a far cry from Oakland, where Moss became an afterthought in an offense that featured dreadful quarterback play and resulted in only 12 offensive touchdowns. Moss appeared to take plays off last season, catching just 42 passes for 553 yards and 3 touchdowns, figures so low that they mystified even Kiffin.</p>
        <p>Moss said in a conference call: ''I don't think you all understand how excited I am to really be a part of this organization. I think their record and what they're about speaks massive volumes, and I'm just very happy to find some happiness and get back to what I love to do, which is play football and go out there and compete.''</p>
        <p>But Moss's presence also figures to test his willingness to behave, as well as the veteran influence of the Patriots' locker room.</p>
        <p>Moss has admitted to smoking marijuana, and he declined to say yesterday whether he was in the N.F.L.'s program for substance abusers. Coach Bill Belichick is not known to tolerate much backtalk from players. But Belichick and the Patriots have had success absorbing problem players before. Most recently, Corey Dillon complained his way from the Bengals to the Patriots and was a model citizen in Foxborough.</p>
        <p>''I talked to a lot of people that were all close to him, both teammates and coaches, people that were on his team, they have a lot of respect for him,'' Belichick said in a conference call last night. ''I had a lot of respect for him competing against him and that all lined up pretty consistently.''</p>
        <p>Moss said: ''I don't really like to answer questions like that because the people that question it probably never played football in their life or have never been on the same pedestal that I've been on. The people that talk about me, as far as my work ethic and my competitive nature and me going out there and playing football, the best thing I can say to you, male or female, all you have to do is line up against me and see what happens.''</p>
        <p>The Moss trade also signifies the impact the ballooning of the salary cap had in player acquisition this off-season. The talent pool in free agency was shallow, and the Patriots could not have gotten the sort of talent in the fourth round that they are getting with Moss.</p>
        <p>The Patriots usually treat draft picks like precious commodities, hoarding and accumulating as many as possible. They have rarely traded draft picks for players in building their championship teams. But the Patriots have not won the Super Bowl since the 2004 season -- an eternity in their dynasty. And getting Moss, even at age 30, for a fourth rounder seems to be a steal, taking advantage of the Raiders' need to dump an unhappy player. Last year, for example, the Seahawks sent a first rounder to the Patriots for Deion Branch, a younger receiver, but not as talented as Moss.</p>
        <p>The Patriots were more than $20 million under the $109 million salary cap when free agency began this year and they have been on a spending spree. In the current climate, with teams having so much to spend because of the windfall of money from rich television contracts, paying a free agent, rather than a second-day draft pick, is no longer burdensome.</p>
        <p>Moss's apparent desire to play for a winning franchise and have a shot at a championship played in the Patriots' favor. Moss agreed to rework his contract, which had included base salaries of $9.25 million in 2007 and $11.25 million in 2008. According to The Boston Globe, he will make $3 million in 2007 -- a pay cut of more than $6 million -- but still much more than a fourth-round draft pick would have earned.</p>
        <p>''I didn't think that money was a big factor to me,'' Moss said. ''I think over the course of my career, I've made a lot of money, and I still have money in the bank, so by me coming to an organization like the New England Patriots, why would money be a factor?''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>Troy Smith, the Heisman Trophy winner from Ohio State who at 6-foot-1 was considered too slight to be a top-flight prospect, was picked in the fifth round by Baltimore.  Jordan Palmer of Texas-El Paso, the younger brother of Cincinnati quarterback Carson Palmer, went to the Redskins in the sixth round. ... Hampton linebacker Justin Durant went in the second round to Jacksonville.  Walter Thomas, the 374-pound defensive tackle from Northwest Mississippi Community College, and Chris Leak, the former Florida quarterback, were not drafted.  San Francisco acquired the veteran receiver Darrell Jackson from Seattle for a fourth-round draft choice.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
