<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To Fans' Dismay, Gordon Passes an Icon</title>
    <meta content="30nascar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/sports/othersports/30nascar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844080"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn of Stock Car Auto Racing</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Earnhardt, Dale</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gordon, Jeff</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Glier, Ray</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7DA133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To Fans' Dismay, Gordon Passes an Icon</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">To Fans’ Dismay, Gordon Passes an Icon</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAY GLIER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glier, Ray</byline>
      <dateline>TALLADEGA, Ala., April 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the day Dale Earnhardt would have turned 56, and in a part of the country where his son Dale Jr. is especially revered by stock-car racing fans, Jeff Gordon won a race and passed the elder Earnhardt on the Nascar Nextel Cup career victory list.</p>
        <p>It was too much for the rowdiest of Earnhardt fans to handle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the day Dale Earnhardt would have turned 56, Jeff Gordon won a race and passed him on the Nascar Nextel Cup career victory list.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the day Dale Earnhardt would have turned 56, and in a part of the country where his son Dale Jr. is especially revered by stock-car racing fans, Jeff Gordon won a race and passed the elder Earnhardt on the Nascar Nextel Cup career victory list.</p>
        <p>It was too much for the rowdiest of Earnhardt fans to handle.</p>
        <p>As Gordon came around to the front stretch of Talladega Superspeedway after his victory in the Aaron's 499, the 77th win of Gordon's career, his car was showered with beer cans, presumably thrown by unhappy Earnhardt fans.</p>
        <p>One can bounced off the windshield and, as the police started handcuffing some of the debris throwers, track officials advised Gordon by radio to move away from the grandstand to avoid damage to his car from full cans of beer cascading onto the sheet metal.</p>
        <p>''On one side, I want to jump up and down and be fired up about getting 77 here at Talladega knowing that three-quarters of the grandstand are pulling against us,'' said Gordon, who moved into sixth on the career victories list. ''On the other side, I respected Dale so much, learned so much from him, and today being his birthday and knowing how many of those people up there wanted to see Dale Earnhardt Jr. win this race today, it's tough. I certainly didn't want to start a riot today.''</p>
        <p>Earnhardt said of Gordon's surpassing his father's victory total: ''It was bound to happen. He's a great racecar driver. I knew years ago he would eventually pass my old man. I think he has the opportunity to pass a couple of more.''</p>
        <p>As for the rowdy fans, Earnhardt, who finished fifth, said, ''It don't look like it's something you can control.''</p>
        <p>Gordon won for the second consecutive week and took a 203-point lead in the series over Jeff Burton, who finished 34th. Gordon, who has won four championships but has not won a title since 2001, has led the points standings for the past five weeks.</p>
        <p>The race was supposed to finish in 188 laps, but it was extended to 192 laps because of a late caution flag. The race finished under a yellow flag because of two separate crashes on the first lap of a two-lap shootout to the finish.</p>
        <p>When there were 10 laps to go, Gordon was running 14th and impatient for the field to make a break for the checkered flag. But the field was in single file, and drivers were reluctant to pull out and make a move for fear of being left behind without a suitable drafting partner.</p>
        <p>''I didn't think we were going to win,'' Gordon said. ''I thought we would get to fifth or sixth.''</p>
        <p>Everything changed, as Gordon came up behind David Stremme with four laps to go. Gordon said that he was in front of Tony Stewart and Jimmie Johnson when Stremme moved up the racetrack, giving Gordon a shot to take off to the front.</p>
        <p>But then Stremme came down on Gordon, who said that he came off the gas and went on to the apron.</p>
        <p>''Usually, that momentum change kills you,'' Gordon said.</p>
        <p>Stremme, however, moved up the track, out of the way. Stewart, meanwhile, had pulled out to try to go around Gordon. Johnson's momentum carried into Gordon, who said that Johnson, his Hendrick Motorsports teammate, gave him a bump-draft toward the lead coming into Turn 1 on Lap 185.</p>
        <p>As Gordon got the lead, Nascar called for a caution flag because David Reutimann's engine failed, spewing oil on the track.</p>
        <p>Nascar kept the caution out for five laps before ordering a two-lap shootout to the finish. Only one lap was completed before two separate wrecks behind Gordon ended the race.</p>
        <p>Stewart, who was admonished by Nascar last week for suggesting that it was unfairly making sure races were close by employing excessive caution flags -- he backed off his comments after meeting with Nascar officials -- was back in brash form after the last crash swept him out of a top-10 finish. He finished 38th.</p>
        <p>''No talent there,'' Stewart said of David Gilliland, who sent Stewart into an inside wall on the final restart.</p>
        <p>Stewart was penalized on Lap 44 by Nascar for going too fast down pit road and was given a drive-through penalty. But in a twist, he managed to get back in contention because of several caution flags that bunched the field.</p>
        <p>In Sunday's race, it was hard to predict what would happen on a newly paved track where there was good grip. Several drivers were able to reach 199 miles an hour despite this being a race using restrictor plates, which are designed to limit speeds.</p>
        <p>It was here that Dale Earnhardt Sr. won 10 races and intimidated opponents. Earnhardt used to tease Gordon 15 years ago when Gordon first came into the sport, and Earnhardt's fans made Gordon the enemy. By their reaction to his victory here Sunday, those fans were not willing to give Gordon his due.</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
