<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Flood Begets A Paper Ark</title>
    <meta content="30carr" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/business/media/30carr.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844022"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA EQUATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana/New Orleans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Orleans (La)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E2DC133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1042" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Flood Begets A Paper Ark</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Flood Begets a Paper Ark</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CARR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For a visiting newspaper guy, the coffee shop in New Orleans last Thursday morning looked like some kind of golden age fantasy. People at every table, regardless of race, class or age, seemed to have a newspaper open, chatting over the articles and trading sections back and forth. Even the people who were hunched over computers seemed mostly using the connection to link to the newspaper.</p>
        <p>In a week when the Audit Bureau of Circulations announced that newspaper circulation nationwide was down (again) in the six months through March, it was tough to know which to believe: the statistics or my own lying eyes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Times-Picayune of New Orleans has become a beacon of tough questions, vigorous reporting and high-quality, relentlessly local coverage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For a visiting newspaper guy, the coffee shop in New Orleans last Thursday morning looked like some kind of golden age fantasy. People at every table, regardless of race, class or age, seemed to have a newspaper open, chatting over the articles and trading sections back and forth. Even the people who were hunched over computers seemed mostly using the connection to link to the newspaper.</p>
        <p>In a week when the Audit Bureau of Circulations announced that newspaper circulation nationwide was down (again) in the six months through March, it was tough to know which to believe: the statistics or my own lying eyes.</p>
        <p>It makes a difference that the paper in question was The Times-Picayune of New Orleans, the 171-year-old paper that distinguished itself during Hurricane Katrina and the flooding that followed. Sitting across from each other sharing the paper and a cup of coffee at CC's Coffee House on Esplanade Avenue, John Bidwell was anticipating tearing into Fishing Friday for some local intelligence on what's biting where, while Kent Hardouin was enjoying an article about the New Orleans Saints reaching a contract agreement with Charles Grant, a star defensive end.</p>
        <p>Just behind them, John Richie was reading up on the comeback of the Gentilly neighborhood and complications with the federally financed Road Home project to repair damaged or destroyed houses.</p>
        <p>''New Orleans is a place with a coffee shop on every corner, and you find people reading the paper because they almost have to,'' said Mr. Richie. ''We are at a very critical moment in the city's history, and everybody is waiting to find out if things are going to turn out O.K.. Almost everyone reads the paper.''</p>
        <p>The newspaper's circulation, which effectively dropped to zero in the aftermath of the hurricane (when there briefly was no paper version), has come back to 185,000, far below its prestorm level of 270,000 but something of a miracle when you remember that by some estimates, half the city's population has yet to return.</p>
        <p>In that respect, it reflects broader trends here. This first weekend of Jazzfest, the signature musical festival of New Orleans, suggests that this town will swing again.</p>
        <p>Yes, the federal bureaucracy is grinding away with breathtaking inefficiency, and the local government still seems at loose ends in coming up with a plan, but The Times-Picayune -- long a journalistic also-ran that gained renewed stature in the '90s -- has become a beacon of tough questions, vigorous reporting and high-quality, relentlessly local coverage.</p>
        <p>''The newspaper, oddly enough, is stabilizing, albeit at a reduced level from before the storm,'' said Jim Amoss, the paper's editor. ''It has not come roaring back -- it is a smaller business, but it is healthy business and that can't be said of many American newspapers. The reporters and editors who work here accomplished something amazing.''</p>
        <p>Some of them are no longer in New Orleans, worn out by reporting the story and living it at the same time. But Mr. Amoss has been able to hire and fill some empty slots -- another rarity in the industry -- and he says recruiting is not a problem.</p>
        <p>''I don't have to talk anybody in to coming here,'' he said. ''If you are in the news business, this is what you got in it for. There is no better place in the world for journalism than right here.''</p>
        <p>In a city where every day can seem like Groundhog Day -- the Ninth Ward is mostly gone, crime continues to threaten the recovery and the check for rebuilding is still in the mail -- Mr. Amoss said the story continued to deepen in a way that had kept his remaining reporters energized.</p>
        <p>''It is like being trapped in the second to last chapter of a novel and you want to hang around and find out what happened,'' he said. ''We are constantly torn between getting away from here and being drawn into a story that mutates and is never ending.''</p>
        <p>The 4:30 news meeting last Thursday at the paper included the tick-tock of daily news, talk of the Saints and, as will be the case for many years to come, a fair amount of discussion about what people need to know in order to make their way in a broken city.</p>
        <p>As often happens in any newsroom huddle, especially at this outfit, there was plenty of gallows humor. A sidebar about a 20-year-old entrepreneur who bought and is rehabbing a house that literally faces the notorious breach in the London Avenue Canal brought a suggestion from one editor that he ''may be a millionaire by the time he is 30 -- or a victim of another flood.''</p>
        <p>New Orleans, which has long eschewed Yankee concepts about time management, has always seemed to find time for a cup of coffee and a little time with the newspaper in the morning. Back in 1999, Scarborough Research estimated that The Times-Picayune was the top newspaper in the country in regional daily penetration, with 47.8 percent. It was able to grab attention by feeding a cultural penchant for gossip about local doings.</p>
        <p>''The Times-Picayune had religion before the flood. It has always paid a lot of attention to local news,'' said JoAnn Clevenger, the owner of Upperline, a restaurant in Uptown. ''And now, after the storm, their local coverage has been astonishing. The people who have made a decision to stay or come back need a lot of information and the paper is seen by everyone, including a lot of young people, as the place to turn.''</p>
        <p>While most news institutions struggle for attention and credibility, The Times-Picayune is able to ride down rails it laid during the storm.</p>
        <p>''I think that the paper really stepped up during Katrina and after, and people here recognize that,'' said Christopher Chambers, a professor of creative writing who has The Times-Picayune delivered every day to his doorstep in the Algiers Point neighborhood. Professor Chambers, a friend I've known for years, said that the paper was filling a vacuum.</p>
        <p>''The ball just continues to be dropped here, and the paper has been the one consistent advocate that we have had,'' he said. ''Getting good information is incredibly difficult, and I have to say that I trust what I read in The Times-Picayune.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA EQUATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
