<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Young Bulls Make Defending Champ Old News</title>
    <meta content="30heat" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/sports/basketball/30heat.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844089"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Chicago Bulls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Miami Heat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Chicago Bulls</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Miami Heat</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Basketball Assn</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Riley, Pat</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Skiles, Scott</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jordan, Michael</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wallace, Ben</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wade, Dwyane</person>
        <person class="online_producer">O'Neal, Shaquille</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gordon, Ben</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE5DA133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Young Bulls Make Defending Champ Old News</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Young Bulls Make Defending Champ Old News</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, April 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Miami fans started streaming early for the exits, mirroring the Heat's own imminently abrupt departure from the playoffs, the arena's white noise had already died to a disappointed hush.</p>
        <p>By the final buzzer, there was nothing left for the Heat to say -- except congratulations and good luck to the young Bulls. Chicago had so thoroughly outhustled and outclassed the defending champion Heat to sweep their first-round series in the Eastern Conference playoffs that last June's N.B.A. title seemed to belong to another franchise from a distant era.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chicago won a playoff series for the first time since the 1997-98 season, and the Heat were the first defending champ to be swept in the first round since 1957.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Miami fans started streaming early for the exits, mirroring the Heat's own imminently abrupt departure from the playoffs, the arena's white noise had already died to a disappointed hush.</p>
        <p>By the final buzzer, there was nothing left for the Heat to say -- except congratulations and good luck to the young Bulls. Chicago had so thoroughly outhustled and outclassed the defending champion Heat to sweep their first-round series in the Eastern Conference playoffs that last June's N.B.A. title seemed to belong to another franchise from a distant era.</p>
        <p>The same quick and hungry Bulls team that ruined Miami's ring ceremony on opening night in October with a 42-point shellacking here fittingly bookended Miami's miserable season with a 92-79 triumph in Game 4 on Sunday afternoon at American Airlines Arena.</p>
        <p>Like a man starting to acknowledge the blur of the youth movement before him, Miami Coach Pat Riley, 62, leaned into Chicago's 43-year-old coach, Scott Skiles, as the game ended.</p>
        <p>''Look,'' Riley said he told Skiles, ''You can go a long way.''</p>
        <p>Later, Riley added soberly: ''We ran into more than a formidable opponent: a team that's on the rise. They deserved to win.''</p>
        <p>The Bulls won a playoff series for the first time since the 1997-98 season, the last of the Michael Jordan era, and now get to play the Eastern Conference stalwart and Chicago center Ben Wallace's former team, the Detroit Pistons, in the semifinals. The series will start Saturday.</p>
        <p>The Heat, having limped through the season with injuries to its three most important people -- Dwyane Wade, Shaquille O'Neal and Riley were together for only 8 of 82 games in the regular season -- now goes home to an off-season of surgery and uncertainty.</p>
        <p>''It's still April,'' Wade said in disbelief at being eliminated. ''Ain't been like this since college.''</p>
        <p>It has not been like this in the N.B.A. for a half-century. Miami became the first defending champion to be swept in the first round since the 1957 Philadelphia Warriors won two in a row against the Syracuse Nationals in a best-of-three series.</p>
        <p>''When you get to the top of the mountain, you don't camp out,'' Riley said. ''You come back down and you got to climb it again. We didn't climb it very well this year.''</p>
        <p>O'Neal said softly: ''We tried to make a series out of it. They did everything right -- shot the ball well, played good defense, got a lot of loose balls.''</p>
        <p>The Bulls also made their free throws, the disparity no more telling than between two centers who usually struggle from the free-throw line. Wallace hit 7 of 8 free throws, and O'Neal missed all seven of his.</p>
        <p>The older Heat team was the one crumbling under pressure as the Bulls caused 17 turnovers and committed only 5.</p>
        <p>The most crucial turnover came with 3 minutes 53 seconds remaining and the Bulls ahead by 3 points. Luol Deng intercepted Wade's pass intended for Jason Kapono, burst upcourt for a layup and a foul. He did not convert the free throw, but his basket gave the Bulls an 82-77 lead and a cushion they never relinquished.</p>
        <p>''I feel like we really grew up a lot in the four games,'' Skiles said. ''Nothing seemed to faze us. We looked like in every game we were going to win.''</p>
        <p>Ben Gordon led the Bulls with 24 points, and Deng once again made the biggest shots for his team. He finished with 22 points and 12 rebounds, averaging 26.3 points and 9 rebounds this series.</p>
        <p>Skiles called him the biggest factor in the series victory. Deng, a 6-foot-9 small forward in his third season, emerged as the prototype for the perimeter-oriented basketball barnstorming the N.B.A.</p>
        <p>Never mind that the Heat scored 46 points to Chicago's 18 in the lane; the Bulls deflated O'Neal's low-post advantage and Riley's style of play.</p>
        <p>''The game has become a game of speed,'' Riley said before the game. ''I've always been a post-oriented coach. I've been blessed to have four of the greatest players ever: Kareem and Patrick and Zo and Shaq. I don't know any other way to go.</p>
        <p>''I mean, I could learn it,'' Riley added with a laugh. ''But I choose not to.''</p>
        <p>Instead, old habits made his team die hard.</p>
        <p>Not having Wade be able to drive aggressively to the basket, with one injured arm and an aching knee, also did in Miami. After missing six weeks to rehabilitate his dislocated shoulder, rather than have season-ending surgery, Wade was not the same player who single-handedly stole a championship from the Dallas Mavericks last summer.</p>
        <p>''Great players take it on their shoulder,'' Riley said. ''We put a little too much on him. Maybe he put a little too much on himself.''</p>
        <p>Wade finished with 24 points, 10 assists and 7 turnovers, saying he would soon discuss having surgery with his doctors.</p>
        <p>As the Bulls' bus left the arena, Skiles was in the front seat, intently scanning the box score. He said he had already begun preparing for the Pistons.</p>
        <p>''I have great admiration for him,'' Riley said. ''I think he knows he has a team that's almost there.</p>
        <p>''Their challenge is ahead of them. It's going to be quite a contest with Detroit.''</p>
        <p>And with that, Riley said goodbye to the news media and to Miami's ill-fated season. ''I'll see you somewhere down the road,'' he said, ''or in utopia.''</p>
        <p>That was last season for the Heat. It may never return.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
