<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Briefly a Suspect, a Virginia Student Now Copes With Loss</title>
    <meta content="30thornhill" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/us/30thornhill.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844047"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Blacksburg (Va)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Radford University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zezima, Katie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cho, Seung-Hui</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hilscher, Emily Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thornhill, Karl D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cho, Seung-Hui</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Thornhill, Karl D</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Hilscher, Emily J</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E5DB133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="599" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Briefly a Suspect, a Virginia Student Now Copes With Loss</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Briefly a Suspect, a Virginia Student Now Copes With Loss</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATIE ZEZIMA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zezima, Katie</byline>
      <dateline>BLACKSBURG, Va., April 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Karl D Thornhill, who was first suspect in killings at Virginia Tech, grieves for his girfriend Emily Hilscher, first victim of Seung-Hui Cho; Thornhill and Hilscher were high school sweethearts who continued their relationship after she enrolled at Virginia Tech and he went to nearby Radford University (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Around 7 a.m. on April 16, Karl D. Thornhill dropped off his girlfriend, Emily Hilscher, at her Virginia Tech dormitory after the two had spent the weekend together, cuddling on the couch during a movie Sunday night.</p>
        <p>Soon after, Ms. Hilscher would be shot in her dormitory, the first victim of a gunman, Seung-Hui Cho, and Mr. Thornhill would be questioned by police in relation to the crime, and his apartment here searched for guns and bloody clothing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Early on April 16, a student dropped off his girlfriend at her Virginia Tech dormitory; soon after, she would be the first victim of a gunman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Around 7 a.m. on April 16, Karl D. Thornhill dropped off his girlfriend, Emily Hilscher, at her Virginia Tech dormitory after the two had spent the weekend together, cuddling on the couch during a movie Sunday night.</p>
        <p>Soon after, Ms. Hilscher would be shot in her dormitory, the first victim of a gunman, Seung-Hui Cho, and Mr. Thornhill would be questioned by police in relation to the crime, and his apartment here searched for guns and bloody clothing.</p>
        <p>The police soon cleared Mr. Thornhill of wrongdoing, and he would quickly become a double victim of the crime, having to cope with losing the girlfriend he adored and being falsely implicated in her murder.</p>
        <p>''Karl's been taking the situation very hard,'' said Tori White, 19, a friend of Mr. Thornhill's family, in an e-mail message. ''He kept thinking that if he had just kept her in the car for a minute or two longer she'd still be here. I think he feels a bit responsible, though by no means is it his fault.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Thornhill, 19, a sophomore prebusiness major at nearby Radford University, has not responded to requests for an interview. But Ms. White said he did not plan to return to his apartment here because there are too many memories of Ms. Hilscher. He and his sister Lauren live in a student-filled apartment complex where Virginia Tech stickers are affixed to cars and a beer bottle or two lie on the grass.</p>
        <p>A woman wearing a Virginia Tech T-shirt who answered the door of his apartment said Mr. Thornhill was probably not coming back.</p>
        <p>''The police ransacking the house overwhelmed them,'' Ms. White said. ''He just kept looking at Emily's picture and was torn up inside.''</p>
        <p>At Mr. Thornhill's home in Boston, Va., about 190 miles northeast of here, ''Do Not Enter'' and ''No Trespassing'' signs lined the family's gravel driveway. Two horses grazed in the grass nearby.</p>
        <p>Those who know Mr. Thornhill describe him as a laid-back, friendly baseball player, hunter and outdoorsman who was devoted to Ms. Hilscher.</p>
        <p>''Him and Emily were great together. I never once saw them fight. They were in a great relationship,'' said Zachary Csik, a student at Virginia Tech who used to spend time with Mr. Thornhill and Ms. Hilscher, playing video games and watching movies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thornhill and Ms. Hilscher met at Rappahannock County High School and started dating more than a year ago, said Rowan Webster, a high school friend of Ms. Hilscher's.</p>
        <p>''She loved him,'' Mr. Webster said. ''She was nuts about him.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Webster said he and Ms. Hilscher had a serious conversation last summer about her relationship with Mr. Thornhill and how it would last while the two were at different colleges.</p>
        <p>''We talked about coping with distance,'' he said. ''I told Emily that Karl would be more than willing to make the drive because he was really devoted to her and she needn't worry about maintaining the relationship.''</p>
        <p>''He gave her all his time,'' Mr. Webster added. ''Really, that's everything she would ever have wanted, someone who loved her as much as she loved them, and she was a very loving person, so that's quite an accomplishment on his part.''</p>
        <p>Ms. White said her family attended Ms. Hilscher's memorial service on April 21, and that Mr. Thornhill sat quietly in the service and never took off his leather jacket.</p>
        <p>''He is too kind and considerate of a person to be hurting this badly,'' she wrote. ''He is too good of a person. He deserves the best. He hasn't done anything to anyone.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
