<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>That Elusive Race On the First Saturday in May</title>
    <meta content="30racing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/sports/othersports/30racing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070502T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <meta content="BEATING THE ODDS: One Trainer, Five Horses" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844094"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horsemanship and Equestrian Events</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Barbaro (Race Horse)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horsemanship and Equestrian Events</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Churchill Downs Incorporated</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pletcher, Todd</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE4DA133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1567" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>That Elusive Race On the First Saturday in May</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">That Elusive Race on the First Saturday in May</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Todd Pletcher watched from the rail as the seven horses in the Blue Grass Stakes turned for home. He had trained none of them, and that was by design. With three weeks left until the 133rd running of the Kentucky Derby, he wanted his contenders well rested. Besides, he needed to catch his breath.</p>
        <p>In the previous six weeks, Pletcher, 39, had traveled to Florida, Louisiana, Dubai, New York, Kentucky and California, business trips to check on his 200 racehorses and 150 employees. And to win some races.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Acclaimed horse trainer Todd Pletcher has saddled 14 Kentucky Derby horses without a victory. He hopes this year will be different.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Todd Pletcher watched from the rail as the seven horses in the Blue Grass Stakes turned for home. He had trained none of them, and that was by design. With three weeks left until the 133rd running of the Kentucky Derby, he wanted his contenders well rested. Besides, he needed to catch his breath.</p>
        <p>In the previous six weeks, Pletcher, 39, had traveled to Florida, Louisiana, Dubai, New York, Kentucky and California, business trips to check on his 200 racehorses and 150 employees. And to win some races.</p>
        <p>Last year, Pletcher set records for stakes victories, with 100, and purse earnings, of $26.8 million. He also won the Eclipse Award as the nation's best trainer for the third year in a row.</p>
        <p>At Keeneland Race Course in Lexington, Ky., on April 14, Pletcher watched Dominican finish a nose in front of Street Sense in the Blue Grass, the last major prep race for the Derby, but he had already established the credentials of Scat Daddy, Circular Quay and Cowtown Cat by winning the Florida, Louisiana and Illinois Derbys.</p>
        <p>Two of his other colts, Any Given Saturday and Sam P., had also earned their way to Churchill Downs, where Pletcher intends to send five colts in chase of the blanket of roses on Saturday. Only his former boss D. Wayne Lukas (in 1996) and Nick Zito (2005) have mustered that much horsepower for a single Kentucky Derby.</p>
        <p>But the feat means little to him.</p>
        <p>''I want to have one that wins,'' said Pletcher, who has saddled 14 Derby horses without a victory. ''That's more important to me. That said, I don't feel in years past that we've brought the best horse to the race. Maybe one of ours is the best this time.''</p>
        <p>He is breaking some rules of thumb that for decades have dictated how trainers prepare their horses for the Derby.</p>
        <p>Last year, Barbaro was the first horse in 50 years to win it without racing in the previous four weeks. Scat Daddy will be coming off five weeks' rest, and Circular Quay will not have raced in eight weeks. Unlike each of the previous 14 Derby winners, Circular Quay has never raced the Derby distance, a mile and an eighth.</p>
        <p>''If I have a horse run really well, I generally won't run them back in two or three weeks,'' Pletcher said. ''I'm trying to put these horses in a position where they were coming into this off at least four weeks' rest.''</p>
        <p>The rules Pletcher says he has never broken are the ones governing medications. Still, he began this year away from the racetrack after accepting a 45-day suspension in December for a 2004 incident at Saratoga. One of his horses there tested positive for a trace amount of an anesthetic. He gave up the appeal and turned the horses over to his assistants in Florida, New York and California, but he is pursuing a lawsuit to clear his name.</p>
        <p>''It's unjust,'' he said of the penalty, which he and his lawyers say was an amount so minuscule that it suggests accidental contamination.</p>
        <p>On the backside of the racetrack, suspicion and jealousy are as common as the pursuit of an advantage. Cheating has taken several forms, from battery-powered devices to shock horses to run faster, to the perhaps equally unusual but still undetectable injection of venom from a cone snail, which has joint-numbing qualities.</p>
        <p>Two other leading trainers have run afoul of medication rules and have also denied wrongdoing. Steve Asmussen, who recently completed a six-month suspension for use of a prohibited performance-enhancing drug on a horse in Louisiana, will saddle Curlin in the Derby. Last year, Doug O'Neill, who has three horses in the Derby, was subjected to unusual scrutiny after one of his horses tested positive for an alkalizing agent known as a milkshake, a concoction of baking soda, sugar and electrolytes that helps a horse ward off fatigue. His horses had to be saddled in a detention barn, where California authorities had them under surveillance for 30 days.</p>
        <p>As a boy, Pletcher learned about horses from his father, J. J., a trainer on the modest circuits of the Midwest. He also learned that the business environment could be poisonous. He joked about a response he has often given to rivals who wish him luck to his face and criticize him behind his back.</p>
        <p>''I wish you the same,'' Pletcher said with a wry smile.</p>
        <p>But the horse owners he works for, a group that includes dozens of some of the wealthiest people in the world, remain his staunchest supporters. They admire his work ethic, which has him at the barns by 4:30 a.m., and his executive mentality, which allows him to give the best care to racehorses worth millions and to stroke the egos of their owners.</p>
        <p>It is not always easy, and it means time away from his young family. Pletcher met his wife, Tracy, when they were in high school in San Antonio. They spend most the year at their home in Garden City, N.Y. In the winter, Tracy and their three children -- Payton, 8; Kyle, 7; and Hannah, 4 -- join Pletcher at their home in Boynton Beach, Fla.</p>
        <p>''Tracy is really the one who holds it all together,'' J. J. Pletcher said. ''He's running a big business and caring for some of the best horses in the world. She's a partner in every sense of the word.''</p>
        <p>In March, Todd Pletcher accompanied Michael Tabor to New Orleans, where they watched Circular Quay run away with the Louisiana Derby. Tabor, a former betting-shop owner in England, bred and owns Circular Quay. He is a billionaire speculator in horses, currency and real estate.</p>
        <p>''You have to trust your trainer, to like him and to know that the bad news is always coming,'' Tabor said. ''Todd gives it to you straight and makes sure you see the fun in a sport that we all love.''</p>
        <p>Later, in Southern California, Tabor heard some bad news. Something appeared to be wrong with his colt Ravel.</p>
        <p>''He had this little head knock when he walked,'' said Pletcher, who ordered a nuclear bone scan. Ravel had fractured his left front cannon bone and was off the Derby trail.</p>
        <p>Tabor, 65, has been in the horse business long enough to have owned the 1995 Derby winner, Thunder Gulch. He understands that bad news is more common than good news.</p>
        <p>Last year in Florida, he and two others bought a colt, The Green Monkey, at a 2-year-old in-training sale for a record $16 million. The Green Monkey was bought by partners of Coolmore, based in Ireland and perhaps the most powerful breeding operation with stallions in the world. The Green Monkey, however, has yet to run a race and was not even nominated for the Triple Crown because of a pulled muscle and other injuries.</p>
        <p>Besides Circular Quay, Tabor owns a half-interest in Scat Daddy, a purchase that perhaps showed how owners reward Pletcher's diplomacy and horsemanship.</p>
        <p>In September 2005, in the sales pavilion about 75 yards from the trainers' barn at Keeneland, Jim Scatuorchio paid $250,000 for Scat Daddy, a son of Johannesburg, and gave the Pletchers a half-interest in him.</p>
        <p>''I was around when Todd had 30 horses, and we have had a lot of success together,'' said Scatuorchio, 59, who retired in 1998, after 30 years on Wall Street, to race horses. ''It was a way of saying thank you.''</p>
        <p>In 1999, Scatuorchio owned More Than Ready, a colt J. J. Pletcher helped select. He was their first good horse, winning five of seven starts as 2-year-old and placing fourth in the 2000 Kentucky Derby.</p>
        <p>In September 2006, Tabor bought the Pletchers' half-interest in Scat Daddy for several million dollars, just before Scat Daddy won the Grade I Champagne Stakes at Belmont Park for his third victory in four starts.</p>
        <p>''It was a lot of money,'' Pletcher said, refusing to disclose the price.''It was an opportunity to get enough security for my family.''</p>
        <p>In the wee hours April 1, Scat Daddy provided a triumphant moment for what had been a miserable evening in the desert of Dubai. Pletcher had taken five horses there to compete in the world's richest racing card. One of them was Scatuorchio's turf star English Channel. Neither trainer nor owner did well: Pletcher went 0 for 5, and English Channel finished 12th in the $5 million Dubai Duty Free.</p>
        <p>At 1:30 a.m., Todd and J. J. Pletcher and the Scatuorchio family gathered around a computer in the business center of their hotel to watch Scat Daddy in his final prep race, the Florida Derby.</p>
        <p>They followed the choppy images on the screen, hearing the announcer declare him a winner long before they saw it.</p>
        <p>They uncorked Champagne, ordered pizza and celebrated until it was time for the Pletchers to leave for their 7 a.m. flight home.</p>
        <p>On Saturday, if one of Pletcher's five colts gives him his first Kentucky Derby victory, the postrace celebration will be far more elegant.</p>
        <p>If that does not happen?</p>
        <p>''We'll hopefully be back with a couple more next year,'' Pletcher said. ''This isn't the sort of thing you give up on.''</p>
        <p>Beating the Odds</p>
        <p>Articles in this series are examining the preparation of horses and the motivation of owners and trainers who are striving to win the Kentucky Derby on Saturday.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 2, 2007, Wednesday  Because of an editing error, a sports article on Monday about the success of the trainer Todd Pletcher in horse racing and his efforts to win the Kentucky Derby misstated the length of the Derby and the distance run by 14 Derby winners in preparation for the race. The Derby is a mile and a quarter -- not a mile and an eighth, which is the distance those winners had run.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 2, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, a sports article on Monday about the success of the trainer Todd Pletcher in horse racing and his efforts to win the Kentucky Derby misstated the length of the Derby and the distance run by 14 Derby winners in preparation for the race. The Derby is a mile and a quarter -- not a mile and an eighth, which is the distance those winners had run.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
