<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rostropovich Is Laid to Rest Near Another Russian Titan</title>
    <meta content="30rostropovich" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/world/europe/30rostropovich.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070503T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844081"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Moscow (Russia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rostropovich, Mstislav</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kishkovsky, Sophia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/Moscow</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Russia</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Rostropovich, Mstislav</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Yeltsin, Boris N</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E6DA133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="636" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rostropovich Is Laid to Rest Near Another Russian Titan</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rostropovich Is Laid to Rest Near Another Russian Titan</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SOPHIA KISHKOVSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kishkovsky, Sophia</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, April 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thousands of Russians pay their respects in Moscow to Mstislav Rostropovich, cellist and conductor who has funeral service at Cathedral of Christ the Savior and is buried in Novodevichy Cemetery; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thousands of Russians paid their respects here in the Russian capital this weekend to Mstislav Rostropovich, the cellist and conductor who was laid to rest on Sunday just feet from the fresh grave of former President Boris N. Yeltsin. It was the second time in less than a week that the country buried a public figure considered a symbol of his time.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rostropovich and Mr. Yeltsin had funeral services at the Cathedral of Christ the Savior and burials at the Novodevichy Cemetery, the resting place of luminaries from Chekhov to Khrushchev.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mstislav Rostropovich, the cellist and conductor, was laid to rest just feet from the fresh grave of former President Boris N. Yeltsin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Thousands of Russians paid their respects here in the Russian capital this weekend to Mstislav Rostropovich, the cellist and conductor who was laid to rest on Sunday just feet from the fresh grave of former President Boris N. Yeltsin. It was the second time in less than a week that the country buried a public figure considered a symbol of his time.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rostropovich and Mr. Yeltsin had funeral services at the Cathedral of Christ the Savior and burials at the Novodevichy Cemetery, the resting place of luminaries from Chekhov to Khrushchev.</p>
        <p>With the grand memorial services in recent days, the Cathedral of Christ the Savior has acquired the status of the country's most exclusive funeral site, welcoming presidents -- former Presidents Bill Clinton and George Bush attended Mr. Yeltsin's funeral -- cultural luminaries and at least one queen.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rostropovich's service began and ended with ''Christ is Risen,'' the hymn that is sung throughout the paschal season, even at funerals. Among those mourning him was the wife of the writer Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn, Natalya.</p>
        <p>''The death of Mstislav Rostropovich is a bitter blow for our culture,'' Mr. Solzhenitsyn said in a statement after the cellist's death.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rostropovich and his wife, Galina Vishnevskaya, provided shelter at their country home to Mr. Solzhenitsyn and his family shortly before the writer was expelled from the Soviet Union in 1974. Mr. Rostropovich and Ms. Vishnevskaya were expelled and stripped of their Soviet citizenship soon afterward.</p>
        <p>A letter from Patriarch Aleksy II of the Russian Orthodox Church, read at the opening of the funeral service, said Mr. Rostropovich's charity toward the Solzhenitsyns was one of the main markers of his life, not only civic but also Christian.</p>
        <p>''The Lord Jesus Christ gave us an image of true love and sacrifice, saying, 'Greater love has no one than this, that someone lay down his life for his friends,' and Mstislav Leopoldovich with this gesture convincingly demonstrated his adherence to high Christian ideals,'' the letter said.</p>
        <p>President Vladimir V. Putin, whom Russian state television described as Mr. Rostropovich's friend, paid his respects at the conservatory where the cellist's body lay in an open coffin for viewing on Saturday. There, the Russian State Academic Symphony Orchestra played Mr. Rostropovich's favorite compositions, from Tchaikovsky to Rachmaninoff to Schumann.</p>
        <p>The services for Mr. Rostropovich, at the cathedral, the cemetery and the Moscow Conservatory, were open to the general public. Among the mourners were Queen Sofía of Spain and Bernadette Chirac, the wife of President Jacques Chirac of France, President Ilham Aliyev of Azerbaijan and young cellists, bearing witness to Mr. Rostropovich's reputation as a man of the world whose appeal cut across class lines.</p>
        <p>Karlen Asriyants, 55, a metal worker originally from Baku, the capital of Azerbaijan, where Mr. Rostropovich was born, spoke emotionally about the cellist's death.</p>
        <p>''He was a genius, not only as a musician, but also in his actions,'' he said, speaking of Mr. Rostropovich's shelter of the Solzhenitsyns, his performance before the Berlin Wall in 1989 and his defense of the Russian White House against the coup plotters in 1991.</p>
        <p>A wreath at his grave had a touching inscription: ''To the most wonderful husband, father and grandfather, your Galina.''</p>
        <p>The conservatory reported that more than 10,000 mourners streamed past Mr. Rostropovich's coffin there.</p>
        <p>At the Novodevichy Cemetery, the graves of Mr. Yeltsin and Mr. Rostropovich now flank the central alley.</p>
        <p>''Rostropovich, like Yeltsin, was a moral guarantor of our freedom in the 1990s,'' said Victor Erofeyev, the novelist and essayist, as he exited the cemetery gates.</p>
        <p>In a touching scene, Naina I. Yeltsin, Mr. Yeltsin's widow, who came to the cemetery with her daughters, Tatiana and Yelena, embraced Ms. Vishnevskaya. The two widows, dressed in black, wept in each other's arms.</p>
        <p>Then each escorted the other to her husband's grave.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 3, 2007, Thursday  A picture in some copies with an article on Monday about the funeral and burial of the Russian cellist Mstislav Rostropovich was published in error. It showed a farewell ceremony for the actor Kirill Lavrov, not the burial of Mr. Rostropovich.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 3, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>A picture in some copies with an article on Monday about the funeral and burial of the Russian cellist Mstislav Rostropovich was published in error. It showed a farewell ceremony for the actor Kirill Lavrov, not the burial of Mr. Rostropovich.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
