<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Ill Feelings: Producers Bet on a 'Superwoman'</title>
    <meta content="30murp" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/theater/30murp.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844028"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Murphy, Donna</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E1DC133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1474" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Ill Feelings: Producers Bet on a 'Superwoman'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">No Ill Feelings: Producers Bet on a ‘Superwoman’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAMPBELL ROBERTSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robertson, Campbell</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Donna Murphy is feeling fine.</p>
        <p>She's a few days from opening in the Manhattan Theater Company's production of ''LoveMusik,'' the Hal Prince-directed musical about the 25-year romance between Kurt Weill and Lotte Lenya, and she's out there every night, crooning ''Speak Low'' with her co-star, Michael Cerveris, and belting out ''Surabaya Johnny'' in her meticulously researched Lotte Lenyese accent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite all the gossip and sniping that has been directed at Donna Murphy, she also happens to be one of the most ecstatically reviewed musical actresses around.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Donna Murphy is feeling fine.</p>
        <p>She's a few days from opening in the Manhattan Theater Company's production of ''LoveMusik,'' the Hal Prince-directed musical about the 25-year romance between Kurt Weill and Lotte Lenya, and she's out there every night, crooning ''Speak Low'' with her co-star, Michael Cerveris, and belting out ''Surabaya Johnny'' in her meticulously researched Lotte Lenyese accent.</p>
        <p>No, nothing is bothering Ms. Murphy.</p>
        <p>Well, there is that malady that she has been trying to shake for the last several years, a little condition that Broadway wags refer to as the ''Donna Murphy syndrome.''</p>
        <p>Strictly speaking, it means a tendency to miss a lot of performances; more broadly, it is all the gossip and sniping that has been directed at Ms. Murphy, who also happens to be one of the most ecstatically reviewed musical actresses around.</p>
        <p>Not that long ago the gossip around Broadway was that Donna Murphy the star performer had been felled for good by the syndrome. It was about four years ago, with the troubled 2003 revival of ''Wonderful Town.'' The show was supposed to be, for Ms. Murphy, a delightful relief. She had shined in the Encores! production at City Center in 2000, but resisted joining a Broadway transfer for the next several years, despite near-constant courting by the producers Roger Berlind and Barry and Fran Weissler; Kathleen Marshall, the director; and even Adolph Green and Betty Comden, the lyricists.</p>
        <p>Maybe later, she said; first, she and her husband wanted to have a child. But then came two miscarriages, one after the other. At that point, the stage was starting to look like a reliable place to find peace of mind. So in 2003 she finally agreed, and the show was up and running.</p>
        <p>Then she coughed.</p>
        <p>It was only the second preview, she said, and she was rushing into her dressing room for a change. She went on a coughing jag, and something felt wrong.</p>
        <p>''I remember saying to my management that night, 'I'm afraid I've hurt myself,' '' she recalled in an interview last week in her dressing room at the Biltmore, in which she addressed the experience in greater detail than she has before.</p>
        <p>The next morning she went to her doctor and her hunch was right: she had hemorrhaged in one of her vocal cords. The doctor ordered her to get out of the show.</p>
        <p>Ms. Murphy went to two more doctors that day and the diagnosis was the same, though they said she might be able to continue with the show if she had some time off. The producers decided to cancel the next six performances; her understudy, the soon-to-be-quite-busy Linda Mugleston, went on in two performances after that.</p>
        <p>Ms. Murphy had already developed, for one reason or another, a reputation for fragility, and the blatherskites around Broadway began whispering. The production insisted, as Mr. Weissler told The New York Times a week later, that it was simply ''a bad flu.'' Technically, that was accurate.</p>
        <p>''The ultimate decision was made to focus on the fact that I did have the flu and not make a mention of the fact that I'd hemorrhaged my cord,'' Ms. Murphy said.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Weissler said that what he said publicly was what he was told by her doctors at the time.</p>
        <p>Whatever the case, Ms. Murphy's vocal trouble was jeopardizing a $5 million production that had been waiting for her for years. And she knew it. ''I felt guilty and responsible,'' she said.</p>
        <p>She came back into the show, at the consent of her doctor, a week after leaving. People were still asking questions about what had happened, how serious her problems were. But the reviews for the show were good and for Ms. Murphy, as usual, some were downright rapturous.</p>
        <p>''On your knees, citizens of Broadway,'' Ben Brantley's review in The Times began. ''A superwoman walks among you.'' She didn't endear herself to anyone by being two hours late to her opening-night party. It seemed like a publicity hiccup at the time, but little things like that would add up to a big black mark in the press to come.</p>
        <p>But for now Mr. Brantley's impression was the definitive one. So back to the show, to the interviews, the recording sessions, the photo shoots and the packed holiday schedule. And before too long, back to Ms. Murphy's doctor.</p>
        <p>''You're at risk if you sing on this, if you speak on it,'' Ms. Murphy recalled the doctor saying at one point in mid-December. '' 'Let's take it day by day.' That began the period of on again, off again.''</p>
        <p>On her doctor's orders, Ms. Murphy took a day off here, a weekend off there, and it all began adding up, she said. As the show's grosses -- and Ms. Murphy's reputation -- began disintegrating during the spring, it was still unclear to many what was going on. Even people in the company were in the dark; all they knew was that she was out often and she didn't speak much when she was around.</p>
        <p>''There was a point where I asked if I could be open about what had happened and I was asked not to be'' by the producers, Ms. Murphy said. ''I had many thoughts about how I should have handled it. But I kept trying to come back to 'O.K., what's best for the show?' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Weissler disputes that. ''In no way did I ever, ever, declare that we should not tell the public about this,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Against the advice of her doctor, she occasionally took steroids to keep her voice going, but the absences continued. Frustrated ticket buyers rescheduled when they arrived at the theater to find Ms. Murphy absent, only to find her out again when they went back.</p>
        <p>It became conventional wisdom that her absences scuttled what would have been a strong possibility of a third Tony Award. Publicity missteps -- like Ms. Murphy not appearing at the Drama League luncheon or taking a few performances off to tape a pilot -- further dented her reputation.</p>
        <p>In the summer, as the show limped along, Ms. Murphy tried to get out of her contract a month early, but there was no replacement who could be ready in time. She lost most of that month anyway, though. A Sunday matinee performance in late August for a Republican convention crowd turned out to be her last.</p>
        <p>The next day Ms. Murphy's doctor told her she was at great risk for another hemorrhage, one much more serious, and ordered her to take a few weeks off, she said. Though Ms. Murphy had a scrap with the producers over whether she could return for the last handful of shows (she wanted to; the producers didn't want her to), the run for her was over. An unnamed producer told The New York Post that she would never be hired to star in a Broadway show again.</p>
        <p>''I felt bereft at the end of 'Wonderful Town,' '' Ms. Murphy said. ''Personally, I felt extremely sad, extremely disappointed, as if I had let people down. And there was the irony of having gone into something that I thought was both a way to experience and give joy.''</p>
        <p>The next two years she spent away from long-running shows, performing occasionally in one-night concerts and in movies and television shows. Most of her time, though, she spent on the process of adopting a daughter, Darmia, from Guatemala.</p>
        <p>Ms. Murphy did not return to the stage in earnest until this year, first in the City Center Encores! production of ''Follies'' and now in ''LoveMusik.''</p>
        <p>The reviews for the ''Follies'' production were glowing. (Mr. Brantley called Ms. Murphy one of ''the finest portraitists working in musicals.'') And once again, there was talk of Broadway transfer (talk that has dwindled somewhat). And once again, Barry and Fran Weissler were pushing for the transfer, the same Weisslers who were rumored to be at wits' end with Ms. Murphy during ''Wonderful Town.''</p>
        <p>Hard feelings?</p>
        <p>''Not at all,'' Mr. Weissler said. ''I called her personally.''</p>
        <p>There was one other lead producer of ''Wonderful Town'': Mr. Berlind. What is he producing these days? For one thing, ''LoveMusik.''</p>
        <p>''Donna was my first choice right from the beginning,'' he said. He did take time to reassure the other backers that she would be dependable. But as for himself, ''I had no trepidation at all.''</p>
        <p>So Mr. Weissler and Mr. Berlind insist that they have nothing against Ms. Murphy, and that, while the ''Wonderful Town'' experience was frustrating, Ms. Murphy's problems resulted from a streak of bad luck. But talk is cheap.</p>
        <p>There is perhaps no statement of trust stronger than staking a multi-million-dollar production on someone.</p>
        <p>''She's one of the hardest working actors I've ever worked with,'' Mr. Weissler said. ''I just hope she doesn't get the flu.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
