<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Resignation Could Be Part Of World Bank Compromise</title>
    <meta content="30bank" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/washington/30bank.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844070"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Bank for Reconstruction and Development</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weisman, Steven R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wolfowitz, Paul D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riza, Shaha Ali</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Merkel, Angela (Chancellor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">World Bank</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wolfowitz, Paul D</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EEDB133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="953" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Resignation Could Be Part Of World Bank Compromise</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Resignation Could Be Part of World Bank Compromise</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN R. WEISMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weisman, Steven R</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>World Bank's 24-member board of directors will meet to hear its embattled president Paul D Wolfowitz, and possibly his companion Shaha Ali Riza, before deciding what to do about charge that he showed favoritism to Riza in giving her raise and promotion when he became bank president in 2005; there is talk at bank of avoiding confrontation by having Wolfowitz resign in return for reprimand that acknowledges that he acted in good faith at time and that ethics officials at bank had approved of his actions when they examined them in 2005 and 2006; European officials say that German Chancellor Angela Merkel, who will visit White House as current president of European Union, is prepared to tell Pres Bush that Europe favors Wolfowitz's resignation; Pres Bush and Vice Pres Dick Cheney are leading defense of Wolfowitz and preparing to confront Merkel if necessary (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the eve of what seems likely to be an ugly showdown between Paul D. Wolfowitz, president of the World Bank, and its board of directors over his future there, both sides are talking about trying to avert a prolonged confrontation that could cripple the bank and its mission of aiding poor countries.</p>
        <p>For a week at least, the bank's board has seemed determined to force Mr. Wolfowitz out on grounds that he showed favoritism to his companion, a bank employee, in giving her a raise and promotion when he became bank president in 2005.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>One way of avoiding a confrontation that could cripple the World Bank is for Paul D. Wolfowitz to voluntarily resign.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the eve of what seems likely to be an ugly showdown between Paul D. Wolfowitz, president of the World Bank, and its board of directors over his future there, both sides are talking about trying to avert a prolonged confrontation that could cripple the bank and its mission of aiding poor countries.</p>
        <p>For a week at least, the bank's board has seemed determined to force Mr. Wolfowitz out on grounds that he showed favoritism to his companion, a bank employee, in giving her a raise and promotion when he became bank president in 2005.</p>
        <p>More recently, however, there is talk at the bank of avoiding a confrontation by having Mr. Wolfowitz resign in return for a reprimand that acknowledges that he acted in good faith at the time and that ethics officials at the bank had approved of his actions when they examined them in 2005 and 2006.</p>
        <p>''I think the board has been looking for a way out of this,'' said a bank official briefed on the board's thinking, who was not authorized to discuss it publicly. ''The directors do not want to set a precedent by ousting Wolfowitz. I'm convinced that they are hopeful that he will see the light and give a way out by resigning or proposing something palatable from a political perspective.''</p>
        <p>The bank's 24-member board of directors is to meet Monday to hear Mr. Wolfowitz -- and possibly his companion, Shaha Ali Riza, who is now working at a foundation that promotes democracy in the Middle East -- before deciding later in the week what to do.</p>
        <p>It is unclear whether the issue will come up during President Bush's scheduled meeting on Monday with the chancellor of Germany, Angela Merkel, who is to visit the White House as the current president of the European Union.</p>
        <p>European officials say that Mrs. Merkel is prepared to tell Mr. Bush that Europe favors Mr. Wolfowitz's resignation. Some Europeans view his leadership as divisive, and as an obstacle to rich countries meeting their commitment to raise $30 billion over the next three years for poor countries.</p>
        <p>But German officials say Mrs. Merkel may not raise the matter on her own because the Germans have been told that Mr. Bush would reply forcefully that the United States still stands behind Mr. Wolfowitz.</p>
        <p>On the fringes of the Merkel-Bush meeting, however, there could be discussions about a way out of the impasse, based on a growing recognition that if Mr. Wolfowitz stayed, the bank's aid flows would be jeopardized and a raft of other senior bank leaders would resign.</p>
        <p>New talk of averting a confrontation is based partly on Mr. Wolfowitz's display of tough tactics since his hiring of Robert S. Bennett, a high-powered Washington lawyer known for adept legal skirmishing and negotiation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolfowitz last week accused the bank's board of directors, which had assumed the task of evaluating his conduct in 2005, of treating him ''shabbily'' by giving him insufficient time to defend himself.</p>
        <p>More recently, he has signaled that at the meeting on Monday, scheduled to give him a day in court, he will cite documents indicating that top officials at the bank cleared his actions in 2005 and early 2006. His argument is that if he was to blame for any of dereliction of duty, that dereliction was shared by the board.</p>
        <p>For example, a document that Mr. Wolfowitz is expected to cite, dated June 22, 2005, from Ad Melkert, chairman of the board's ethics committee, suggests that Ms. Riza was entitled to ''full recognition of her (considerable) professional qualifications'' in arranging for her to be compensated for moving to another job.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bennett, in an interview on Sunday, said Mr. Wolfowitz had no intention of resigning and would continue to fight for his job. But Mr. Bennett seemed to signal that if the bank were willing to recognize a shared responsibility for the current crisis, it could clear the way for resolving the conflict.</p>
        <p>''We are going to be presenting to the committee tomorrow powerful evidence that Mr. Wolfowitz acted in the best interest of the bank,'' he said. ''Mr. Wolfowitz also believes that not only he but the bank acted in good faith. Perhaps with the benefit of hindsight everyone could have done a better job. But everyone acted in good faith.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bennett said that he was convinced that ''if the temperature is lowered'' both sides could talk about what was good for the future of the bank. But he also indicated that he was prepared to keep the temperature raised, possibly by demanding the public release of the salaries and perquisites of others at the bank.</p>
        <p>A full public airing of the high salaries at the bank is not something that top bank officials want, many bank officials say. They may seek to avoid a confrontation if only to avoid calling Mr. Bennett's bluff.</p>
        <p>There are rumors at the bank that Mr. Wolfowitz may cancel trips to Europe and Africa to discuss aid projects for poor countries, but Mr. Bennett said Mr. Wolfowitz would probably proceed with his duties at the bank.</p>
        <p>But in the Bush administration, where Mr. Bush and Vice President Dick Cheney are leading the defense of Mr. Wolfowitz and preparing to confront Chancellor Merkel and other Europeans if necessary, there also appears to be a recognition that the bank is ailing and likely to become close to dysfunctional if Mr. Wolfowitz stays.</p>
        <p>Officials say they cannot discuss the possibility of his resigning because that is not the formal position of the administration. But it would not be a surprise to many if Mr. Wolfowitz eventually stepped down because of the widespread antipathy at the bank toward his leadership.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
