<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Okajima Invaluable To Boston In Relief</title>
    <meta content="30redsox" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/sports/baseball/30redsox.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844076"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Japan</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Okajima, Hideki</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7DA133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="644" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Okajima Invaluable To Boston In Relief</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Okajima Invaluable to Red Sox in Relief</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAT BORZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Borzi, Pat</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The suggestion, translated from English into Japanese, that Hideki Okajima might be the most valuable player on the Red Sox for the first month of the season made Okajima laugh out loud.</p>
        <p>Okajima, a veteran left-handed reliever from Japan, considered the notion absurd, even though at least one Yankee put it out there after Okajima baffled and stifled the Yankees again yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Okajima struck out four and allowed only one hit in two scoreless innings in relief of starter Julián Tavárez on Sunday, as the Red Sox beat the Yankees 7-4.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The suggestion, translated from English into Japanese, that Hideki Okajima might be the most valuable player on the Red Sox for the first month of the season made Okajima laugh out loud.</p>
        <p>Okajima, a veteran left-handed reliever from Japan, considered the notion absurd, even though at least one Yankee put it out there after Okajima baffled and stifled the Yankees again yesterday.</p>
        <p>''Their M.V.P. is that left-hander,'' first baseman Doug Mientkiewicz said. ''Every time he's been in there, he's held us in check and allowed them to come back and take the lead or keep the lead.</p>
        <p>''He's funky. He's got something different.''</p>
        <p>Whatever it is, the Yankees cannot seem to solve it. Okajima struck out four and allowed only one hit in two scoreless innings in relief of starter Julián Tavárez yesterday, maintaining the 4-3 lead Tavárez passed to him.</p>
        <p>Mike Timlin and Jonathan Papelbon finished up the 7-4 victory, Boston's fifth win in the six games these teams have played the past two weekends.</p>
        <p>Tavárez, Boston's No. 5 starter, got the victory over Chien-Ming Wang, the Yankees' 19-game winner last season. ''When you look at the pitching matchup today,'' Manager Terry Francona said, ''this was a great game for us to win.''</p>
        <p>Boston's bullpen has been exceptional, posting the lowest earned run average in baseball while allowing only one earned run in its last 15 2/3 innings. But not even the dominant Papelbon, who has eight saves in eight chances, has pitched better than Okajima, who was spectacular in every victory over the Yankees.</p>
        <p>In five appearances, Okajima allowed three hits and no runs in five innings, striking out seven and holding Yankee batters to a .167 average (3 for 18).</p>
        <p>''It seems like every time he comes in the game,'' Alex Rodriguez said, ''he's been a rally killer for us.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday's effort capped a remarkable first month for the 31-year-old Okajima. John Buck of Kansas City homered on the first major league pitch Okajima threw, on April 2. Okajima has not allowed a run since, and has a 0.71 E.R.A. with 17 strikeouts in 12 2/3 innings.</p>
        <p>''He has been terrific,'' Francona said. ''That's stating the obvious.''</p>
        <p>But an M.V.P.?</p>
        <p>''It's still very early in the season,'' Okajima said through an interpreter. ''If I heard that at the end of the season, I'd be very, very happy. But I'm going to stay humble and keep working hard.''</p>
        <p>Okajima, signed with the Red Sox after pitching parts of 12 seasons in Japan, almost all with the Tokyo Yomiuri Giants.</p>
        <p>Last year, Okajima was 2-2 with four saves and a career-low 2.14 E.R.A. in a setup role for Hokkaido.</p>
        <p>With an average fastball (in the high-80s), Okajima relies on a sharp-breaking curve and a tough-to-pick-up changeup. Both dive down and away from left-handed batters. Jason Giambi struck out flailing at Okajima's off-speed stuff in the sixth, two batters after Bobby Abreu was out on a called third strike.</p>
        <p>''Theo said in spring training, 'Two weeks into the season, you'll want to give this guy the ball,' '' said Francona, referring to the Red Sox general manager, Theo Epstein. ''And he was right.''</p>
        <p>Catcher Jason Varitek would not discuss what makes Okajima so tough. ''I won't even tell our guys that,'' he said, meaning reporters who cover the Red Sox regularly. The Red Sox left town with the best record in the American League, a six-and-a-half-game lead on the last-place Yankees in the A.L. East, and a much more effective pitching staff than the team they beat yesterday.</p>
        <p>''It's way too early in the season to talk about separating yourself,'' first baseman Kevin Youkilis said. ''But we're playing good ball. Our pitching has been great.''</p>
        <p>And, against the Yankees, a certain funky left-hander in particular.</p>
        <p>''Hopefully,'' Rodriguez said, ''us and the rest of the league will get to know him a little better.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
