<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>California Democrats Cheer Talk They Sought 4 Years Ago</title>
    <meta content="30dems" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/us/politics/30dems.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844044"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vetoes (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Foreign Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vetoes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E7DB133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1004" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>California Democrats Cheer Talk They Sought 4 Years Ago</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">California Democrats Cheer Talk They Sought 4 Years Ago</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nagourney, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>SAN DIEGO, April 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Presidential hopefuls at California Democratic Party convention, like Democratic leaders in Congress, are divided over how to respond to Pres Bush's expected veto of legislation setting timeline for removing troops from Iraq; candidates and party activists agree that war should end, but differ over how quickly troops should be withdrawn, over whether withdrawal should be done by cutting off troops financing, and over how forcefully to react to veto; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When John Edwards attended the California Democratic Party convention as a presidential candidate four years ago, he was heckled with shouts of ''No war'' as he struggled to defend his support of the Iraq invasion. That tense weekend in Sacramento crystallized how divided Democrats were over a war that overshadowed the presidential race of 2004.</p>
        <p>Mr. Edwards returned to the convention here on Sunday, this time as a presidential candidate firmly opposed to the war. He heard cheers when he demanded a withdrawal of the troops, and again apologized for his original position. Indeed, all the presidential candidates who spoke here Saturday and Sunday were cheered as they denounced the war, suggesting that the candidates and the Democratic base are now in line on this critical issue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>All the presidential candidates who spoke at the California Democratic Party convention were praised as they denounced the war in Iraq.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When John Edwards attended the California Democratic Party convention as a presidential candidate four years ago, he was heckled with shouts of ''No war'' as he struggled to defend his support of the Iraq invasion. That tense weekend in Sacramento crystallized how divided Democrats were over a war that overshadowed the presidential race of 2004.</p>
        <p>Mr. Edwards returned to the convention here on Sunday, this time as a presidential candidate firmly opposed to the war. He heard cheers when he demanded a withdrawal of the troops, and again apologized for his original position. Indeed, all the presidential candidates who spoke here Saturday and Sunday were cheered as they denounced the war, suggesting that the candidates and the Democratic base are now in line on this critical issue.</p>
        <p>But in fact, as the weekend here made clear, the Democratic presidential field, like Democratic leaders in Congress, is divided over how to respond to President Bush's expected veto of legislation setting a timeline for removing troops from Iraq. While the candidates and party activists agree that the war should end, they differ over how quickly troops should be withdrawn, over whether the withdrawal should be accomplished by cutting off financing for troops in the field, and over how forcefully to react to a veto.</p>
        <p>Senators Barack Obama of Illinois and Hillary Rodham Clinton of New York described the bill Congress passed and sent to Mr. Bush as the best possible road map to ending the conflict. In separate speeches, Mr. Obama and Mrs. Clinton said that if Mr. Bush vetoed the bill, Democrats should try to find enough votes to overturn the veto, a prescription that -- if highly implausible at the moment -- was a clear winner with this crowd, probably as perfect a snapshot of the party's liberal base as could be found anywhere in America.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Bush refuses to sign the bill, Mr. Obama said, Democrats will find the votes ''we need to end this war without him.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''We will turn up the pressure on all those Republican congressmen and senators who refuse to acknowledge the reality that the American people know so well, and we will get this done. We will bring our troops home.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Edwards, of North Carolina, suggested another course of action to his former colleagues in the Senate. ''We need the Congress to stand firm and strong,'' he said. ''If the president vetoes this bill, they should send him back another bill with a timetable for withdrawal. If he vetoes that bill, they should send him back another bill with a timetable for withdrawal.''</p>
        <p>By contrast, Senator Christopher J. Dodd of Connecticut, Gov. Bill Richardson of New Mexico and Representative Dennis J. Kucinich of Ohio all suggested that the bill being sent to the president was too leisurely in its deadlines and urged Congress to adopt even tougher legislation by cutting off financing for the war.</p>
        <p>''Democrats need to speak loudly and clearly on this issue,'' Mr. Dodd said. ''The American public is so far ahead of the political leadership on this issue. They want this war over with.''</p>
        <p>For the presidential candidates in the Senate, who must cast votes on the issue as they campaign for the presidential nomination, this is complicated terrain. At a time when Republican presidential contenders have been portraying the Democratic Party as the face of weakness in a dangerous world, Democrats are wary of supporting a bill that could be portrayed as cutting off money for the troops or forcing a precipitous end to the conflict.</p>
        <p>Mr. Obama may be particularly vulnerable to this line of attack after the Democrats' first debate last week. In responding to a question about what he would do as president if two American cities were attacked by terrorists, he did not mention a counterattack as an option. He later amended his remarks to say he would advocate retaliation, echoing what Mrs. Clinton and Mr. Edwards had said in response to the question.</p>
        <p>As it was, Mr. Obama had been attacked by Democrats on the left after suggesting almost a month ago that Congress should respond to Mr. Bush's almost certain veto with legislation that would ensure continued financing for the troops.</p>
        <p>Amid all the attention here to the Democratic field and its response to the war, one of the most intriguing dramas involved the return of Mr. Edwards. His speech showed how much his view of the war has changed as he tries in his second bid for the presidency to capture the support of the party's left which eluded him in 2003.</p>
        <p>Four years ago, Mr. Edwards was heckled here as he defended his vote in favor of the war. He presented his position as one of principle as Democrats rallied around the antiwar candidacy of Howard Dean, who is now the party's national chairman.</p>
        <p>''I have the responsibility to have the backbone to tell you directly what my position is and what my beliefs are,'' Mr. Edwards said.</p>
        <p>Sunday, he brought the crowd to its feet with some of the toughest antiwar language heard this weekend. He said he would withdraw 50,000 troops immediately, and remove the rest within 18 months.</p>
        <p>''They should not back down from this president and let him continue on this terrible course in Iraq,'' he said. ''We have to show strength and courage. This is about life and death. This is about war.''</p>
        <p>The sentiment of Democrats in this hall was clear from the moment the convention opened Friday through Sunday morning, when Representative Maxine Waters, Democrat of California, led the crowd in a chant reflecting a decidedly unnuanced view of what the United States should do in Iraq: ''Not another nickel, not another dime, not another soldier, not this time.''</p>
        <p>When Mrs. Clinton recounted the history of the war and asked, ''What do we do now?'' the crowd interrupted, shouting, ''Bring them home!'' before she got to talk about her idea of pressing Republicans in the Senate to join in overriding the expected veto.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
