<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Worker Is Killed and One Is Hurt, Struck by a G Train in Brooklyn</title>
    <meta content="30train" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/nyregion/30train.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844114"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">New York City Transit</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Metropolitan Transportation Authority</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E1DA133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="832" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Worker Is Killed and One Is Hurt, Struck by a G Train in Brooklyn</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Worker Is Killed by a G Train in Brooklyn</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER 8. LEE and WILLIAM NEUMAN; Thomas J. Lueck contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Jennifer 8</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One transit worker was killed and another injured yesterday afternoon when they were hit by a G train at a Brooklyn station, city officials said. It was the second fatal accident involving track workers in less than a week.</p>
        <p>The northbound G train hit the workers in the Hoyt Street-Schermerhorn Street station just after 4 p.m. One of them, Marvin Franklin, 55, of St. Albans, Queens, a transit employee for more than 20 years, was apparently dragged half the length of the station and was found dead under the train. The second worker, Jeff Hill, 41, a track worker since 2005, was taken to Bellevue Hospital Center, where he was in stable condition last night, the police said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>All work on New York subway tracks was suspended after the second fatal subway accident in less than a week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One transit worker was killed and another injured yesterday afternoon when they were hit by a G train at a Brooklyn station, city officials said. It was the second fatal accident involving track workers in less than a week.</p>
        <p>The northbound G train hit the workers in the Hoyt Street-Schermerhorn Street station just after 4 p.m. One of them, Marvin Franklin, 55, of St. Albans, Queens, a transit employee for more than 20 years, was apparently dragged half the length of the station and was found dead under the train. The second worker, Jeff Hill, 41, a track worker since 2005, was taken to Bellevue Hospital Center, where he was in stable condition last night, the police said.</p>
        <p>As a result of the back-to-back accidents, maintenance and construction work on subway tracks was suspended and workers were being called in for refresher safety training. An investigation will be held by a transit board of inquiry.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's accident happened during a weekend-long shutdown of the A and C lines in part of Brooklyn, to allow for a major renovation of the concrete track bed. Mr. Franklin and Mr. Hill were not working on that project but were part of a maintenance crew that was taking advantage of the shutdown to do routine repairs that involved replacing metal plates that sit between the rails and the track ties. While no trains were running on the A and C lines at Hoyt-Schermerhorn, there was normal service on the G, which runs on parallel tracks at that station.</p>
        <p>A senior official at the Metropolitan Transportation Authority, who spoke about the accident on the condition of anonymity, said that a preliminary investigation indicated that the men had gone to fetch a dolly and were carrying it across the G track on their way back to the A and C track when they were hit.</p>
        <p>The official said that an alternative route would have involved taking the dolly up the platform stairs, through the station and down another set of stairs to the opposite platform.</p>
        <p>The operator of the G train apparently saw the two workers and tried to stop, but it was too late. Based on the preliminary investigation, officials believe that warning lights that would have made the train operator slow down and watch out for track workers may not have been placed on the G track, the official said.</p>
        <p>Service on the G line was suspended for about three hours after the accident.</p>
        <p>Howard H. Roberts Jr., president of New York City Transit, which is part of the authority, had been on his way to Brewster, N.Y., for a wake for Daniel Boggs, the transit worker who was killed Tuesday night at the Columbus Circle station in Manhattan, when he got word about yesterday's accident. He went to the Hoyt-Schermerhorn station, as did Elliot G. Sander, the executive director of the authority, and Roger Toussaint, the president of Local 100 of the Transport Workers Union, who had also been on their way separately to the wake.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roberts, who began his job this month, announced a temporary suspension in maintenance and construction. ''We are going to make sure that everything that needs to be done gets done before we send people out on the tracks,'' he said in an interview.</p>
        <p>He said that the suspension and training aimed to ''review rules, emphasize the danger, how dangerous it is out there.''</p>
        <p>Some workers were allowed to finish projects that were necessary to enable the subways to run normally during this morning's rush. Those workers were instructed to complete their tasks, but only after two hours of what he termed ''reinstruction'' in safety procedures.</p>
        <p>Mr. Toussaint said the ''back-to-back tragedies'' represented ''a massive blow to transit workers.''</p>
        <p>''The nature of this work we're doing in the subway environment is fraught with exposure to catastrophic conditions,'' he said. ''It's unfortunate it takes these types of events for New Yorkers to realize what is taking place underground to keep those trains moving.''</p>
        <p>He said that even though the men were not working on the G track, rules require that tracks adjacent to the ones being worked on be flagged with warning lights to alert train operators to reduce speed and to watch for people ahead. If the investigation reveals that the track was not flagged, he said, ''That would be a problem.''</p>
        <p>Reached by telephone last night, Mr. Franklin's family declined to talk about the accident. An authority statement described him as having a wife and son.</p>
        <p>There did not appear to be much similarity between the two fatal accidents in the last week, as the victims in each case were doing very different types of work, according to the senior transit official.</p>
        <p>Mr. Boggs, who had been placing warning lights and stepped onto an express track as a train was coming through, was the first transit worker killed on the job in more than a year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
