<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Clashes With Militia In Baghdad</title>
    <meta content="30iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/30/world/middleeast/30iraq.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844038"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE REACH OF WAR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baghdad (Iraq)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mahdi Army</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Semple, Kirk</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sadr, Moktada Al-</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mudaris, Amal Kadhum al-</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Mahdi Army</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Sadr, Moktada Al-</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DEFDC133EF933A05757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="643" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Clashes With Militia In Baghdad</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Clashes With Militia in Baghdad</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK SEMPLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Semple, Kirk</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, April 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mahdi Army clashes with American forces in Baghdad, indicating its re-emergence from two months of self-imposed dormancy on orders of its leader Moktada al-Sadr; its return could complicate American-led effort to tame violence in capital; some members of Shiite community have sought return of Mahdi Army in recent weeks, as car bombings killed hundreds of people in Baghdad's Shiite neighborhoods; many Shiites regard Mahdi Army as bulwark against militant Sunni Arabs; gunmen in passing car gravely wound one of Iraq's most famous broadcasters, Amal Kadhum al-Mudaris, near her house in western Baghdad; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Militiamen loyal to the Shiite cleric Moktada al-Sadr clashed with American forces in northern Baghdad on Sunday, an Interior Ministry official said, the latest in a series of indications that the militia might be emerging from two months of self-imposed dormancy.</p>
        <p>On the orders of Mr. Sadr, the militia, known as the Mahdi Army, has remained largely underground since the intensified security plan for Baghdad took effect in mid-February. But a steady increase in the number of corpses recovered from the streets in recent weeks, and sporadic clashes between Mahdi fighters and government forces, have suggested a possible resurgence of the militia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Militiamen loyal to the Shiite cleric Moktada al-Sadr clashed with American forces in northern Baghdad on Sunday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Militiamen loyal to the Shiite cleric Moktada al-Sadr clashed with American forces in northern Baghdad on Sunday, an Interior Ministry official said, the latest in a series of indications that the militia might be emerging from two months of self-imposed dormancy.</p>
        <p>On the orders of Mr. Sadr, the militia, known as the Mahdi Army, has remained largely underground since the intensified security plan for Baghdad took effect in mid-February. But a steady increase in the number of corpses recovered from the streets in recent weeks, and sporadic clashes between Mahdi fighters and government forces, have suggested a possible resurgence of the militia.</p>
        <p>Its return could significantly complicate the American-led effort to tame violence in the capital because it would split the attention of American and Iraqi forces, already struggling to subdue the Sunni Arab insurgency and interrupt its campaign of vehicle bombings against Shiite targets.</p>
        <p>The circumstances of the latest fighting remained unclear late Sunday.</p>
        <p>The Interior Ministry official said American soldiers and Mahdi militiamen exchanged heavy gunfire near a prominent Shiite shrine in the Shiite neighborhood of Kadhimiya, and that two American Humvees had burst into flames. The ministry official offered no explanation for the clashes.</p>
        <p>Sheik Khalid al-Kadhumy, an official in Mr. Sadr's organization, said that American forces surrounded the Sadr offices in the Kadhimiya neighborhood in the evening. Something prompted the Americans to open fire on the office and surrounding buildings, he said, resulting in casualties among local residents, though he did not know how many.</p>
        <p>Lt. Col. Christopher Garver, an American military spokesman in Baghdad, said that he had no comment on reports of the fighting but that the military was working on a statement about the clashes.</p>
        <p>Some members of the Shiite community have been agitating for a return of the Mahdi Army in recent weeks, as spectacular car bombings against Shiite communities in Baghdad killed hundreds of people. The militia is regarded by many Shiites as a bulwark against militant Sunni Arabs.</p>
        <p>Three weeks ago, American forces fought Mahdi cells in the southern city of Diwaniya. And late last month, Mahdi fighters battled Iraqi Army soldiers in southwestern Baghdad. But military officials hoped those were localized clashes.</p>
        <p>Also on Sunday, a roadside bomb in the Zaafaraniya district of southern Baghdad killed two people and wounded seven, and three garbage collectors were killed by gunmen in Adhamiya, the Interior Ministry official said.</p>
        <p>An Iraqi soldier was killed in a drive-by shooting at a checkpoint in the Salaam neighborhood in western Baghdad, the official added, and the authorities recovered 11 bodies dumped on the streets.</p>
        <p>A British soldier was shot and killed in the southern city of Basra on Sunday, the 12th British soldier to die this month, Reuters reported. Four members of the Yezidi faith were killed in Mosul: two civilians on Saturday and two police officers on Sunday, a police officer in Mosul said.</p>
        <p>Gunmen in a passing car gravely wounded one of Iraq's most famous broadcasters, Amal Kadhum al-Mudaris, near her house in the Khudra neighborhood of western Baghdad, the police said. She was in serious but stable condition on Sunday night, officials said.</p>
        <p>During her 43-year career in radio and television, Ms. Mudaris, 60, has become a familiar voice to many Iraqis. She has recently been the host of a morning call-in show on the Iraqi Net radio station, in which she seeks to assuage people's suffering and help resolve their problems with government ministries.</p>
        <p>The police, as well as friends and colleagues of Ms. Mudaris, said they did not know why she was attacked. The shooting came nearly four weeks after another Iraqi broadcaster, Khamael Mohsin, was slain by gunmen in Baghdad.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mudaris ''is one of the most distinguished voices on Iraqi radio and has touched families' hearts,'' said Hafid al-Adelie, the head of Iraq's Radio and Television Broadcasters Union.</p>
        <p>THE REACH OF WAR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
