<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gifts Are Accepted at Shea Homecoming</title>
    <meta content="10mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/sports/baseball/10mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839347"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Philadelphia Phillies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Philadelphia Phillies</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Alou, Moises</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Green, Shawn</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Franco, Julio</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Reyes, Jose</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Duca, Paul Lo</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Beltran, Carlos</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Delgado, Carlos</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wright, David</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Howard, Ryan</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rollins, Jimmy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E1DB153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="952" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gifts Are Accepted at Shea Homecoming</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Gifts Are Accepted at Shea Homecoming</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shpigel, Ben</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The sun was shining, the temperature stayed a few degrees north of bone chilling and the Shea Stadium stands were packed tighter than a clown car. The only ones not cooperating for the Mets' home opener yesterday were their opponents, the Philadelphia Phillies, whose young left-hander Cole Hamels thwarted them through six innings before he left with a two-run lead.</p>
        <p>With Hamels gone, the Mets did what good teams are supposed to do against suspect bullpens, erupting for seven runs in the eighth inning to coast to an 11-5 victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Mets took advantage of the Phillies’ relievers and a crucial error to score seven runs in the eighth inning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The sun was shining, the temperature stayed a few degrees north of bone chilling and the Shea Stadium stands were packed tighter than a clown car. The only ones not cooperating for the Mets' home opener yesterday were their opponents, the Philadelphia Phillies, whose young left-hander Cole Hamels thwarted them through six innings before he left with a two-run lead.</p>
        <p>With Hamels gone, the Mets did what good teams are supposed to do against suspect bullpens, erupting for seven runs in the eighth inning to coast to an 11-5 victory.</p>
        <p>To the delight of the sellout crowd of 56,227, a franchise record for a home opener, the game turned when Philadelphia shortstop Jimmy Rollins, whose preseason proclamation that the Phillies were the team to beat in the division provided good tabloid fodder, booted a one-out, bases-loaded grounder by José Reyes that allowed the tying run to score. In a matter of minutes, after David Wright's two-run double and Moises Alou's two-run single, the Mets had demoralized a Philadelphia team that lost its third consecutive game and dropped to 1-6 this season. ''It just happened,'' Carlos Beltrán said. ''When Jimmy made that error, everything changed.''</p>
        <p>Coming home after a good but slightly dissatisfying 4-2 trip to St. Louis and Atlanta, the Mets overcame their first poor starting pitching performance of the season and a curious decision by Manager Willie Randolph that forced them to come from behind and highlighted the vulnerability of their right-handed relief corps.</p>
        <p>Unable to throw his fastball for strikes, John Maine allowed six walks in four and two-thirds innings and was replaced, with the bases loaded and two outs, by Ambiorix Burgos. Burgos induced a groundout from Abraham Núñez to end the threat and came out to pitch the sixth. ''I needed some length,'' Randolph said.</p>
        <p>With one out, Burgos hit Rollins and allowed a bloop single to Shane Victorino that pushed Rollins to third. In the Mets' bullpen, the left-handed specialist Pedro Feliciano was warming up, ostensibly to face the Phillies' dynamic left-handed hitters, Chase Utley and Ryan Howard, who were up next. Burgos struck out Utley in an exhausting 12-pitch at-bat in which Victorino stole second, leaving first base open if the Mets were interested in intentionally walking Howard, the reigning most valuable player in the National League.</p>
        <p>Randolph went to the mound -- ''He told me to make good pitches,'' Burgos said, with the third-base coach, Sandy Alomar, serving as interpreter -- while in the bullpen, Feliciano assumed he was coming in and opened the gate before he was told to come back.</p>
        <p>Randolph made his decision as much out of necessity as to boost Burgos's confidence. Aaron Heilman, who is battling elbow tendinitis, threw 41 pitches Sunday and was unavailable except in an emergency. Randolph said he did not want to use Feliciano because he could have been forced to turn to the right-handed specialist Joe Smith to pitch to the on-deck hitter, Pat Burrell, if the inning continued.</p>
        <p>Burgos went right after Howard, getting ahead, 1-2. But on a 2-2 count, Howard blasted Burgos's seventh consecutive splitter 390 feet over the fence in right-center field to put the Phillies ahead, 5-3. It was the first homer allowed by Burgos this season, but his 17th in his last 751/3 innings.</p>
        <p>For a manager who trusts his gut, the outcome could have been enough to give Randolph indigestion. But it was nothing compared with what Phillies Manager Charlie Manuel must have felt later.</p>
        <p>Hamels allowed three runs, two earned, in six innings while striking out seven with his deadly changeup. But when he left, the Mets' approach changed almost immediately. They took the first pitch in their five plate appearances against Hamels's replacement, Matt Smith, and worked the count to get a better pitch to hit. They scored one run in the seventh, on a single by Carlos Delgado, but had settled into a rhythm at the plate when they faced Geoff Geary in the eighth.</p>
        <p>''It had that feeling like we were kind of waiting in the weeds and getting ready to strike,'' Wright said.</p>
        <p>Alou and Shawn Green ignited the rally with consecutive singles. Green was replaced by Endy Chávez because Randolph wanted a faster runner to be the potential go-ahead run and also to play right field for defensive purposes. That strategy almost backfired when José Valentín's bunt attempt forced out Alou at third when a faster runner might have beaten the throw.</p>
        <p>Then Geary made his first crucial mistake, walking the pinch-hitter Julio Franco on four pitches to load the bases for Reyes. If there is any player who understands how speed can put pressure on a defender, particularly a shortstop eager to turn a double play, it is Reyes.</p>
        <p>''You get kind of nervous,'' Reyes said. ''And when you try to hurry up or rush, something bad can happen.''</p>
        <p>Reyes tried hitting to the left side of the infield to give himself a better chance to reach base safely, and his grounder caromed off Rollins's glove, allowing Chávez to score the tying run.</p>
        <p>''This is frustrating because we definitely gave them chances to win the game and they took advantage,'' Rollins said.</p>
        <p>Up came Paul Lo Duca, who watched ball three of his four-pitch walk sail over the catcher's head for a wild pitch that scored Valentín with the go-ahead run. Jon Lieber came in for his first relief appearance since 1998, and gave up a sacrifice fly to Beltrán, a walk to Delgado, a two-run double to Wright and a two-run single to Alou.</p>
        <p>It was Alou's second hit of the inning, a feat, he said, he had accomplished a few times before. But never on an opening day.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
