<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Moonlit Night on the Farm, Graveyard Ready</title>
    <meta content="10moon" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/theater/reviews/10moon.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839263"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Old Vic Theater Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brantley, Ben</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Neill, Eugene (1888-1953)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davies, Howard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spacey, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Best, Eve</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Moon for the Misbegotten, A (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Old Vic Theater</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Spacey, Kevin</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Best, Eve</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Meaney, Colm</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Crowley, Bob</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Davies, Howard</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Moon for the Misbegotten, A (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE7DD153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1246" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Moonlit Night on the Farm, Graveyard Ready</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Moonlit Night on the Farm, Graveyard Ready</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN BRANTLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brantley, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Brantley reviews Old Vic Theater Co production of Eugene O'Neill play A Moon for the Misbegotten, directed by Howard Davies; Kevin Spacey and Eve Best star; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The woman who knows him best describes Jim Tyrone as a ''dead man walking slow behind his own coffin.'' But that's sure not the impression given by Kevin Spacey's beat-the-clock performance in Eugene O'Neill's ''Moon for the Misbegotten,'' which opened last night at the Brooks Atkinson Theater.</p>
        <p>Playing a graveyard-bound alcoholic in this off-kilter revival, a production of the Old Vic Theater Company from London, Mr. Spacey is as lively as a frog on a hot plate. When his Tyrone rails against the universe, it is with the frenzy of a fractious 2-year-old who has been told to eat his spinach. And he rattles off the play's big confessional soliloquies as if they were the final verses of Gilbert and Sullivan patter songs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kevin Spacey gives a beat-the-clock performance in this off-kilter revival, which also stars Eve Best in a commanding Broadway debut.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The woman who knows him best describes Jim Tyrone as a ''dead man walking slow behind his own coffin.'' But that's sure not the impression given by Kevin Spacey's beat-the-clock performance in Eugene O'Neill's ''Moon for the Misbegotten,'' which opened last night at the Brooks Atkinson Theater.</p>
        <p>Playing a graveyard-bound alcoholic in this off-kilter revival, a production of the Old Vic Theater Company from London, Mr. Spacey is as lively as a frog on a hot plate. When his Tyrone rails against the universe, it is with the frenzy of a fractious 2-year-old who has been told to eat his spinach. And he rattles off the play's big confessional soliloquies as if they were the final verses of Gilbert and Sullivan patter songs.</p>
        <p>What makes this Tyrone run -- and I mean run? Is Mr. Spacey trying to evoke a man desperate to outrace his demons? Or is it just a matter of an artistic director, a role Mr. Spacey fills at the Old Vic, determined to hustle a famously long-winded show to the final curtain in less than three hours?</p>
        <p>Such questions drift through the mind during this streamlined (two hours, 50 minutes -- whew!) version of O'Neill's last completed drama, a resounding critical hit in London, directed with an emphatically comic slant by Howard Davies. Mercifully Mr. Spacey's hyperkinetic doings do not block the view of the actress playing his unlikely love interest, Eve Best, a sweetheart of the London stage in a commanding Broadway debut.</p>
        <p>It may be the marquee power of Mr. Spacey, a two-time Oscar winner, that draws audiences to the Brooks Atkinson. But it is Ms. Best's centered turn as a strapping country girl that will keep them from growing as antsy as her co-star.</p>
        <p>During the past decade Ms. Best has emerged as London's all-purpose leading lady in roles that run from mouse (''The Heiress'') to man-eater (''Hedda Gabler''). New Yorkers now have the welcome opportunity to savor the care and intelligence with which she constructs a character. The part of Josie, the rural giantess (''so oversize that she is almost a freak,'' O'Neill writes), is not a natural one for the fine-boned Ms. Best, but she makes it fit.</p>
        <p>Whether her presence alone warrants another trip to the run-down Connecticut tenant farm where Josie lives with her crafty father (Colm Meaney), and where Tyrone finally finds peace, is debatable. ''A Moon for the Misbegotten'' was last on Broadway only seven years ago, in a production starring a brilliant Gabriel Byrne as Tyrone, with Cherry Jones as Josie. Older theater addicts cherish memories of the 1973 revival with Jason Robards and Colleen Dewhurst, still regarded by many as definitive.</p>
        <p>Both those versions emphasized the pathos of ''Moon,'' written in 1943 and first produced on Broadway in 1957. Inspired by the unhappy final chapters in the life of O'Neill's ne'er-do-well older brother, James, the play is singular within its author's body of work for its forgiving spirit. The other drama in which Jim Tyrone appears, ''Long Day's Journey Into Night,'' left him in limbo. ''Moon'' grants the same man absolution as he nears the end of a self-destructive existence.</p>
        <p>The flip side of the haunted face of ''Moon'' is the mask of comedy, Irish yokel style. And it is this side that is stressed by Mr. Davies, who brought an irresistible tension several years ago to O'Neill's unwieldy ''Mourning Becomes Electra,'' in a dynamite version at the National Theater in London, starring Ms. Best and Helen Mirren.</p>
        <p>O'Neill was never, to put it kindly, a light-fingered humorist. Nor could his sentimental touch ever be called feathery. His greatness is in his despair. At times, especially as Josie and her father swap insults and scheme to outfox an arrogant patrician neighbor (played by Billy Carter), ''Moon'' can feel like a prequel to ''The Beverly Hillbillies,'' an impression confirmed by Bob Crowley's Dogpatch set. And when Tyrone, the Hogans's landlord, shows up for a drink, he fits right into their vaudevillian rhythms.</p>
        <p>What the 2000 production, directed by Daniel Sullivan, brought out so affectingly was the extent to which the comic shenanigans are so much posturing -- clownish roles assumed to keep harsher truths at bay. A great ''Moon'' progresses into the heart of the pain beneath the laughter.</p>
        <p>Yet even in the play's climactic scene, in which Tyrone reveals his love for Josie and the cancerous self-disgust that makes him drink, the audience keeps laughing. Mr. Spacey brings a stand-up artist's timing to Tyrone's reversals of mood so that they land like punch lines.</p>
        <p>That Tyrone is a former small-time actor may have been the cue for the artificiality with which Mr. Spacey invests much of his dialogue. But I was always more conscious of the actor Kevin Spacey than of the actor James Tyrone. Mr. Spacey is a polished pro who can play himself like an organ. He dexterously pulls out the stops for sincerity, contempt and the swelling anger of an attention-starved, tantrum-prone child who never grew up.</p>
        <p>But aside from a couple of searing moments, as when a delirious Tyrone mistakes Josie for a whore, these disparate notes never blend into the integrated music that makes a character real. The I'm-talking-as-fast-as-I-can delivery, which Mr. Spacey used to more persuasive effect in Mr. Davies's fine 1999 production of ''The Iceman Cometh,'' mostly registers as shtick.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spacey, by the way, was an excellent Jim Tyrone in the 1986 Broadway revival of ''Long Day's Journey,'' a staging that -- come to think of it -- also had unusual breakneck pacing. Here, he often seems to be paying homage to the star of that production, Jack Lemmon, an actor who specialized in comic distress and sentimental anguish. This is a mistake, since even Mr. Lemmon wasn't always convincing as Mr. Lemmon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Meaney gives a solid, likable performance as Hogan that resists Pappy Yokum cuteness. But the night belongs to Ms. Best, who clearly and winningly maps the contradictory levels of Josie Hogan, both the blustery facade and the sensitive core. Her not matching O'Neill's description of a big bruiser only feeds our sense that Josie has created a persona to hide behind, as Ms. Best clomps about the stage like a wrestler in search of a match.</p>
        <p>The toll of sustaining this facade registers with touching specificity in the play's penultimate scene, when a weary Josie collapses like a marionette with its strings cut. It has been hard shouldering all that pretense for so long. Of course the realism of the moment is probably enhanced by Ms. Best's also having had to shoulder the entire emotional weight of a heavy play.</p>
        <p>A Moon for the Misbegotten</p>
        <p>By Eugene O'Neill; directed by Howard Davies; sets by Bob Crowley; costumes by Lynette Mauro; lighting by Mark Henderson; sound by Christopher Shutt; sound system design by T. Richard Fitzgerald and Carl Casella; original music by Dominic Muldowney; production manager, Brian Lynch; production stage manager, Bruce A. Hoover; general manager, Peter Bogyo. An Old Vic Theater Company production, presented by Elliot Martin, Max Cooper, Ben Sprecher, Nica Burns, Max Weitzenhoffer, the Old Vic, Spring Sirkin, Wendy Federman, Louise Forlenza, Ian Osborne, Thomas Steven Perakos and James L. Nederlander. At the Brooks Atkinson Theater, 256 West 47th Street, Manhattan; (212) 307-4100. Through June 10. Running time: 2 hours, 50 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Eve Best (Josie Hogan), Kevin Spacey (Jim Tyrone), Colm Meaney (Phil Hogan), Billy Carter (T. Stedman Harder) and Eugene O'Hare (Mike Hogan).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
