<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Again, Question of Fair Jury For Officers in City They Serve</title>
    <meta content="10nyc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/nyregion/10nyc.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839355"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NYC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/NYC</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nightclubs and Cabarets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bell, Sean</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EEDB153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="751" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Again, Question of Fair Jury For Officers in City They Serve</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Again, Question of Fair Jury for Officers in City They Serve</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE HABERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Haberman, Clyde</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The case against the three police detectives charged in the Sean Bell killing enters a new legal phase tomorrow. The lawyers are supposed to work out procedural details with a Queens judge. Fireworks are not expected.</p>
        <p>But in a case like this, crackling with racial and political tensions, you never know. Jockeying has begun over an issue that hangs in the air as if in colloidal suspension:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lawyers for the indicted officers in the Sean Bell shootingssay they are considering asking to have any trial moved out of town.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The case against the three police detectives charged in the Sean Bell killing enters a new legal phase tomorrow. The lawyers are supposed to work out procedural details with a Queens judge. Fireworks are not expected.</p>
        <p>But in a case like this, crackling with racial and political tensions, you never know. Jockeying has begun over an issue that hangs in the air as if in colloidal suspension:</p>
        <p>Will the indicted detectives -- Michael Oliver, Gescard F. Isnora and Marc Cooper -- try to have their trial moved out of town? Their argument would be that news coverage of them has been so unflattering that their chances of finding 12 unbiased New York City jurors roughly equal the odds of Don Imus's being asked to coach women's basketball at Rutgers University.</p>
        <p>No decisions have been made, say lawyers for the three men, who were among five police officers responsible for the 50-shot barrage that killed the unarmed Mr. Bell near a Queens nightclub last November.</p>
        <p>That having been said, a request to move the trial is ''something that we're seriously, seriously considering,'' said Philip E. Karasyk, representing Detective Isnora. James J. Culleton, Detective Oliver's lawyer, said much the same, though he added that a lot must first be done, perhaps including polling potential Queens jurors.</p>
        <p>Detectives Oliver and Isnora, who fired a total of 42 shots, have the most at stake. They could go away for up to 25 years if convicted of first-degree manslaughter charges. Detective Cooper, who fired 4 shots, faces up to a year in jail on misdemeanor charges of reckless endangerment.</p>
        <p>While the case may be in an embryonic stage, battle lines have already been drawn on the question of venue. When the Queens district attorney, Richard A. Brown, announced the indictments three weeks ago, he made clear that he would ''vigorously oppose'' any attempt to look elsewhere. ''It is a case that should be tried in Queens County by a jury that reflects the diversity of Queens County,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Rev. Al Sharpton has drawn his own lines. Speaking on behalf of the two surviving victims of the police fusillade, he said they would not cooperate with the authorities if the trial was moved.</p>
        <p>Not that the never-silent Mr. Sharpton is allergic to a change of venue if it suits his own purposes. A decade ago, when he was sued for (and then found responsible for) defamation in the notorious Tawana Brawley debacle, he tried to have the case moved out of Dutchess County. He did not get his way.</p>
        <p>But that was no surprise. Most attempts to relocate trials fail.</p>
        <p>For the Bell detectives, the obvious precedent is the murder trial in 2000 of four New York police officers who fired 41 shots in killing the unarmed Amadou Diallo in the Bronx. Citing ''a tidal wave of prejudicial publicity,'' an appellate court ordered the case moved from the Bronx to Albany. There, the four officers were found not guilty.</p>
        <p>Are the Bell and Diallo situations comparable? Frankly, it is hard to see how the news coverage of recent months, over all, amounts to a Diallo-level tsunami.</p>
        <p>Mr. Culleton has a different take, though, ''especially with respect to my client.'' More than his fellow suspects, Detective Oliver has certainly been the subject of unflattering news reports, including one about a complaint of excessive force once made against him. Speaking of excessive force, Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg's use of that very phrase to describe the Bell shooting -- along with words like ''inexplicable'' and ''unacceptable'' -- might well be cited by the defense team.</p>
        <p>Anything can happen. Look at the Diallo case.</p>
        <p>In lifting it out of the Bronx, the judges cited three instances of prejudicial publicity: a New York Post column that used the word ''bang'' 41 times, a cover illustration in The New Yorker of a smiling police officer firing at human figures in a shooting gallery, and an American Civil Liberties Union advertisement in The New York Times that showed 41 bullet holes -- the police way of informing suspects of their right to remain silent, the civil liberties union said.</p>
        <p>Those choices by the court were, to put it mildly, odd.</p>
        <p>No New York newspaper was more reflexively pro-police than The Post. And neither The New Yorker nor The Times, sad to say, could claim a muscular circulation in the Bronx. How an entire borough could have been prejudiced by material that few people there ever saw was never explained.</p>
        <p>Then again, you never know.</p>
        <p>NYC E-mail: haberman@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: haberman@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
