<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pfizer Drug For Diabetes Is Lagging</title>
    <meta content="10drug" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/business/10drug.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839381"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diabetes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Exubera (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Januvia (Drug)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pfizer Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Merck &amp; Co Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berenson, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Diabetes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)/Exubera (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Exubera (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Diabetes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diabetes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Exubera (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Pfizer Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5DA153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1056" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pfizer Drug For Diabetes Is Lagging</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pfizer Drug for Diabetes Is Lagging</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX BERENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berenson, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Exubera, first and so far only commercially available inhaled-insulin diabetes treatment, is on verge of turning into expensive failure for its maker Pfizer Inc; Exubera receives only about one of every 500 prescriptions for insulin written in US; Merck &amp; Co's new diabetes drug Januvia is already prescribed about 40,000 times per week in US, 25 times as often as Pfizer drug; Wall Street analysts are cutting their sales estimates for Exubera, which has been dogged by questions about its safety, cost and convenience; Pfizer says it has not given up on Exubera and last week started new marketing campaign to persuade doctors to prescribe medicine; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Exubera, the first and so far only commercially available inhaled-insulin diabetes treatment, is on the verge of turning into an expensive failure for its maker, Pfizer.</p>
        <p>At one point, the company regarded the drug as a potential blockbuster. But despite six months of marketing to doctors, Exubera receives only about one of every 500 prescriptions for insulin written in the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wall Street analysts are cutting their sales estimates for Exubera, which has been dogged by questions about its safety, cost and convenience.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Exubera, the first and so far only commercially available inhaled-insulin diabetes treatment, is on the verge of turning into an expensive failure for its maker, Pfizer.</p>
        <p>At one point, the company regarded the drug as a potential blockbuster. But despite six months of marketing to doctors, Exubera receives only about one of every 500 prescriptions for insulin written in the United States.</p>
        <p>A new diabetes pill, Januvia, which is made by Merck and was approved after Exubera, is already prescribed about 40,000 times a week in the United States, 25 times as often as the Pfizer drug.</p>
        <p>And so Wall Street analysts are cutting their sales estimates for Exubera, which has been dogged by questions about its safety, cost and convenience.</p>
        <p>Pfizer says it has not given up on Exubera and last week started a new marketing campaign to persuade doctors to prescribe the medicine. In January the company projected that despite its slow start, Exubera would eventually achieve worldwide sales of $2 billion. But doctors and analysts are skeptical.</p>
        <p>''I don't think the drug can be saved,'' said David Risinger, an analyst at Merrill Lynch, who last week cut his estimates for Exubera sales. Mr. Risinger now expects that Exubera will have $310 million in sales worldwide in 2012, down from his previous estimate of $800 million. Other analysts have also cut their forecasts.</p>
        <p>Exubera's problems add to the uncertainties facing Pfizer, whose shares have lost almost half their value since 2000.</p>
        <p>While the company remains highly profitable, its financial health is increasingly tied to Lipitor, a best-selling cholesterol-lowering medicine that faces competition from cheaper drugs and in several years, patent expiration.</p>
        <p>In interviews yesterday, Pfizer executives acknowledged Exubera's problems but said they believed that a new sales push would increase the drug's revenue. The company will work to convince doctors that insulin, in both inhaled and injectable forms, is underprescribed. And this summer, Pfizer plans to begin directly advertising the inhaler to patients.</p>
        <p>''Sales have been slower than expected,'' said Olivier Brandicourt, general manager for Pfizer's metabolic and cardiovascular division, which includes Exubera. ''It takes time to educate the physician.''</p>
        <p>Rochelle Chaiken, Pfizer's vice president for global medical affairs, said almost 60 percent of diabetes patients had overly high blood sugar levels despite being on standard oral diabetes medications. Many of those patients should be taking Exubera, she said.</p>
        <p>But Pfizer's marketing may not be enough to overcome the medical, economic, practical and legal concerns that have hurt Exubera. In theory, the drug's biggest advantage over standard injectable insulin is that it is more convenient and does not require needle pricks.</p>
        <p>In reality, though, the Exubera inhaler is bulky and can be hard to use, doctors say. The device is nearly as large as a tennis ball can when it is open, and must be repeatedly pumped before the insulin can be inhaled. Making matters worse, Exubera doses differ from those for standard insulin, and converting doses can be complicated, the doctors say.</p>
        <p>Also, insurers have been reluctant to pay for Exubera, which costs about $5 a day, compared with $2 to $3 a day for injectable insulin.</p>
        <p>In addition, the needles now used for conventional insulin injections are smaller and less painful than they once were.</p>
        <p>''Out of 2,000 times or more I've tried to start patients on insulin, I've only been turned down twice,'' said Dr. John Buse, professor of medicine at the University of North Carolina.</p>
        <p>Doctors and patients have many more options for managing diabetes than they did a decade ago, Dr. Buse said. In the last two years, three new diabetes medicines have reached the market -- Januvia, Byetta and Symlin -- as well as Levemir, a longer-acting version of injectable insulin.</p>
        <p>As with Januvia, sales of Byetta, which is made by Eli Lilly and Amylin Pharmaceuticals, have grown quickly.</p>
        <p>Another concern for doctors about Exubera is that long-term use of inhaled insulin can damage the lungs. Pfizer's clinical trials show that the drug causes lung function to drop in some patients.</p>
        <p>The decrease appears to be minor and to reverse if patients stop using the drug. Even so, patients must take a lung-function test before beginning Exubera, something that has discouraged doctors from prescribing it, said Dr. Joel Zonszein, a diabetes specialist at Montefiore Medical Center in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>Dr. Zonszein said he had tried to put about half a dozen patients on Exubera since the drug was introduced last summer. All have stopped using it, he said. ''The inhaled market may just not be there,'' he said. ''The needles we have nowadays are very friendly. They're easy to take.''</p>
        <p>Hoping to encourage sales, Pfizer has transferred responsibility for promoting Exubera from its pain management division to its cardiovascular division. The cardiovascular sales force, which helped turn Lipitor into the world's top-selling medicine, is highly regarded.</p>
        <p>But the change may not make a difference, said George Grofik, a drug industry analyst at Citigroup. In February, Mr. Grofik's team surveyed 35 doctors, polling primary care physicians and diabetes specialists, to get their opinions on Exubera.</p>
        <p>Nearly 9 of 10 doctors had ''medium'' or ''high'' awareness of the drug, the survey found. But more than half said they were concerned about Exubera's safety. They were also concerned about its price and the bulkiness of the Exubera inhaler.</p>
        <p>Because many doctors seem to have made up their minds about Exubera, Mr. Grofik said, Pfizer will face an uphill battle as it tries to change their views.</p>
        <p>And by having its representatives promote Exubera when they make sales calls, he added, Pfizer risks taking attention from Lipitor and other more profitable medications.</p>
        <p>''There's an opportunity cost in detailing Exubera that could be used on higher-margin products,'' Mr. Grofik said.</p>
        <p>Over the next five years, other drug companies, including Lilly, may receive approval for their own versions of inhaled insulin, said James Reddoch, a biotechnology analyst at Friedman, Billings, Ramsey. The next-generation inhalers are smaller and more convenient than the Exubera inhaler and may attract more prescriptions, Mr. Reddoch said.</p>
        <p>The lack of interest in Exubera has made Wall Street wonder whether the inhaled-insulin market is as large as drug companies once thought, he said. ''It sounds nice on the surface, the fact that you can now breathe in your insulin,'' Mr. Reddoch said. ''But there are problems from a practical standpoint.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
