<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Carter's Surge Magnifies The Nets' Inconsistencies</title>
    <meta content="10nets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/sports/basketball/10nets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839350"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Washington Wizards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Carter, Vince</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kidd, Jason</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E0DB153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="669" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Carter's Surge Magnifies The Nets' Inconsistencies</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Carter’s Surge Magnifies the Nets’ Inconsistencies</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eligon, John</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., April 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a jovial mood after practice Monday, the Nets' Vince Carter smiled, looked at the reporters surrounding him and said, ''The summer's almost here now.''</p>
        <p>Carter was responding to a question about his desire to wait until after the season to discuss the option he has to skip the final year of his contract with the Nets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>While Vince Carter is poised to surpass his own single-season scoring record, it is difficult to believe the Nets will advance past the first round of the playoffs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a jovial mood after practice Monday, the Nets' Vince Carter smiled, looked at the reporters surrounding him and said, ''The summer's almost here now.''</p>
        <p>Carter was responding to a question about his desire to wait until after the season to discuss the option he has to skip the final year of his contract with the Nets.</p>
        <p>But it was a response that could have been attached to several topics.</p>
        <p>This is a time for milestones: Carter enters Tuesday night's game against the Washington Wizards only 12 points short of breaking his single-season Nets scoring record (1,911). With six games remaining, he has an opportunity to become the first Net to score 2,000 points in a season.</p>
        <p>It is also the time of year when a team's playoff status can change overnight.</p>
        <p>But the most important thing on the Nets' minds this time of year is probably their level of play. Ideally, the Nets (36-40) would like to erase the memory of their up-and-down season by jelling in time to make a postseason run. But their inconsistency this season makes it difficult to believe they will advance past the first round.</p>
        <p>Saturday night's game against the Wizards may have provided evidence of the Nets' shaky status.</p>
        <p>They got triple-doubles from Carter (46 points, 16 rebounds and 10 assists) and Jason Kidd (10 points, 16 rebounds and 18 assists). They are only the fourth set of teammates to do that in the same N.B.A. game. But the Nets needed overtime to defeat the Wizards, who have lost their two All-Stars, Gilbert Arenas and Caron Butler, to injuries.</p>
        <p>''Nothing's guaranteed,'' Kidd said. ''You can have a great night and still lose. Triple-double, it doesn't matter. It's not about the stat line. It's about if you're able to win or lose.''</p>
        <p>The Nets do have some reason for optimism. They have won five of their past seven games. But, in doing so, they have proved to be no match for elite competition. Their defeats were against the Detroit Pistons and the Chicago Bulls, two of the top teams in the Eastern Conference.</p>
        <p>With a victory against the Wizards on Tuesday night, the Nets would pull two games behind Washington for the sixth seed in the East.</p>
        <p>''Right now, we're trying to bring everybody along,'' Carter said. ''Hopefully, everybody's playing well, on the upswing going into the playoffs. I think we'll be fine.''</p>
        <p>After tying his season high in scoring and recording the third triple-double of his career Saturday night, Carter appears to be finding the right gear. His scoring average is 25 points a game, the highest in his two-plus seasons with the Nets. He is also averaging a career-high six rebounds.</p>
        <p>He has scored at least 20 points in 8 of the past 10 games, and the Nets won the two games in which he did not reach 20.</p>
        <p>Carter could be sensing his team's urgent situation and he could be sensing that he continues to make history.</p>
        <p>''I definitely wanted to be in the record books in Toronto; I definitely wanted to be in the record books here,'' Carter said.</p>
        <p>''When we win games and the team's playing well, all of those type of things, all of the accolades come along with it.''</p>
        <p>Whether this season will be Carter's final chance to prove himself as a Net remains up in the air.</p>
        <p>Carter said he was not privy to any talks that his agent, Kurt Schoeppler, might be having with the Nets' president, Rod Thorn. Carter said Schoeppler understood when not to approach him about what has been discussed.</p>
        <p>''He kind of knows how I'm approaching this situation, especially now with us trying to focus on the playoffs and all that,'' Carter said.</p>
        <p>With Schoeppler based in Cleveland, and with the Nets playing there Thursday, the two could have a chat.</p>
        <p>''We might have a talk then; maybe, maybe not,'' Carter said in an uncertain tone that has been as difficult to read as the Nets' season.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
