<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Itineraries; Tax Bites on Travelers Go Deeper</title>
    <meta content="10traveltax" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/business/10traveltax.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839295"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Business Travel Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stellin, Susan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Business Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Industry News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E7DC153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1139" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Itineraries; Tax Bites on Travelers Go Deeper</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tax Bites on Travelers Go Deeper</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN STELLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stellin, Susan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Travel companies and trade associations are beginning to protest growing cost of taxes on flights, car rentals and hotel stays; National Business Travel Association, in partnership with major car rental companies; has focused on fighting high taxes on car rentals and has tried to raise awareness by lobbying state and local officials; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For all the complaints travelers have been voicing about delayed flights, declining service, crowded planes and invasive security procedures, there has been comparatively little outcry about another trend: escalating taxes on flights, car rentals and hotel stays.</p>
        <p>But travel companies and trade associations are beginning to reach for the megaphone on their customers' behalf, protesting the growing cost of taxes, many of them financing initiatives that have nothing to do with travel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Travel companies and trade associations are protesting the growing cost of taxes, many of them financing initiatives that have nothing to do with travel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For all the complaints travelers have been voicing about delayed flights, declining service, crowded planes and invasive security procedures, there has been comparatively little outcry about another trend: escalating taxes on flights, car rentals and hotel stays.</p>
        <p>But travel companies and trade associations are beginning to reach for the megaphone on their customers' behalf, protesting the growing cost of taxes, many of them financing initiatives that have nothing to do with travel.</p>
        <p>''It's probably our No. 1 legislative issue at the moment,'' said Bill Connors, executive director and chief operating officer of the National Business Travel Association, a trade group. ''Local politicians have this idea that travelers are an easy cash cow because they're not there to vote. But it's a form of taxation without representation.''</p>
        <p>In partnership with major car rental companies, the association has focused on fighting high taxes on car rentals and has tried to raise awareness by lobbying state and local officials. Taxes and other charges passed along by car rental companies, like vehicle licensing fees, raise the average rental bill 28 percent at airport locations, according to Travelocity, the online travel agency. These taxes and fees can exceed 50 percent at airports in Kansas City, Dallas, Atlanta and Seattle.</p>
        <p>Industry analysts say more municipalities are taxing rental customers to pay for local projects like sports stadiums, convention centers, public transportation improvements and even a rodeo arena.</p>
        <p>As of last October, there were ''something like 86'' special taxes and surcharges around the country levied on car rentals, and another 48 were being considered, said Neil Abrams, president of the Abrams Consulting Group, which follows the car rental industry.</p>
        <p>As an example, Mr. Abrams cited a proposal to increase the tax on car rentals in Racine, Wis., by $13 a rental to help finance a commuter rail line.</p>
        <p>''They see the rental customer who does not vote in local elections as basically an oil well with untapped resources,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Indeed, William McReynolds, Racine's county executive, has emphasized the point that most of the proposed increase in the car rental tax would be borne by out-of-state visitors and businesses. In an interview, he said the car rental fee was proposed as a way to finance the commuter rail line instead of raising the local sales tax. ''The increase in the rental fee is not exorbitant compared to other major communities,'' he said.</p>
        <p>One reason that these types of taxes have proliferated is that until lately, travelers have not had many advocates speaking on their behalf, while an increase in the sales tax is bound to anger local voters. There is also a lack of comprehensive data about the tax rates charged on car rentals and hotel stays, making tracking them a challenge.</p>
        <p>''It's not easy to fight this fight because you have to be all over the place,'' said Mr. Connors of the N.B.T.A. ''We've focused on car rental taxes because they're the most egregious, but it's also bad with hotels.''</p>
        <p>One of the most thorough studies of hotel taxes, conducted by the American Economics Group, a consulting firm, found that these taxes added 12 percent to an average hotel bill in 2003, compared with 9 percent in 1997. These ''bed taxes'' include local sales taxes as well as any taxes charged specifically on hotel rooms.</p>
        <p>''I think local politicians get the wrong idea that it's taxing outsiders,'' said Charles W. de Seve, the president of the firm. High taxes, he said, can have a ripple effect on a local economy, maybe causing companies to hold an event elsewhere or send fewer employees to a trade show.</p>
        <p>''There's a lot of calculating that goes on to figure the effect on any one place,'' he said. He cited New York as an example of a city that set off a backlash when state and local hotel taxes, including sales tax, reached about 20 percent of the total bill in the early 1990s. ''The slogan at that time was, 'New York: stay four, pay five,' because the tax added that much to the bill.''</p>
        <p>The total tax rate on hotel rooms is now roughly 14 percent in New York City. It typically falls in the 14 to 17 percent range in many other large cities.</p>
        <p>Joseph A. McInerney, president and chief executive of the American Hotel and Lodging Association, a trade group, said hotel groups were fighting hotel tax increases partly because of the way the money was spent. ''Only a small portion of it has been going to promote travel and tourism,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As with taxes on car rentals, taxes on hotel rooms are often used to pay for local projects that may not necessarily benefit visitors; Cincinnati officials have even proposed using money from the county hotel tax to help build a new jail, although a sales tax increase is being considered as a more likely source of financing.</p>
        <p>Although taxes on air travel have also increased in recent years, that revenue is typically used to pay for travel-related measures, especially security. But airlines -- and many travelers -- still say these taxes are too high.</p>
        <p>''Too often, airlines are looked at as a piggy bank with unlimited resources,'' said David Castelveter, a spokesman for the Air Transport Association of America, which represents most major airlines. ''We pay an unprecedented number of taxes and we will continue to oppose increases in the amount and number of taxes that consumers are forced to pay.''</p>
        <p>Because of the way airline taxes are calculated, it is difficult to pin down what percentage of a typical airline ticket goes toward taxes, and estimates placing the average as high as 25 percent have sometimes been met with skepticism. Some airline ticket taxes are charged based on the number of takeoffs and landings in a trip (and vary depending on the airport), so a relatively inexpensive flight with two connections may have a higher percentage of tax than a more expensive nonstop flight.</p>
        <p>Even so, there is little argument that airline taxes have been increasing. The total price for a domestic ticket includes a 7.5 percent federal tax; a Sept. 11 security fee of $2.50 a flight segment (or takeoff and landing), up to $10; passenger facility charges of $3 to $4.50 per airport, up to $18; and a federal fee of $3.40 a segment.</p>
        <p>Taxes on international tickets can add $200 or more to the total price, including domestic and foreign taxes, and those have been increasing as well. Britain, for example, recently doubled its departure tax.</p>
        <p>Ron Wagner, a senior vice president with Carlson Wagonlit Travel, a corporate travel management company, said rising airline taxes are definitely on clients' radar. He noted that airline tickets account for about 80 percent of most companies' spending on travel. ''They're certainly going to look at how taxes affect them,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
