<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Johnny Hart and His Wham-Wham World</title>
    <meta content="10hart" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/arts/design/10hart.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070414T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839262"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AN APPRAISAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">An Appraisal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cartoons and Cartoonists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Comic Books and Strips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comic Books and Strips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cartoons and Cartoonists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E7DD153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="686" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Johnny Hart and His Wham-Wham World</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Johnny Hart and His Wham-Wham World</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES MCGRATH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgrath, Charles</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the early days of his career, the cartoonist Johnny Hart signed his work with his first name and then a little outline of a heart. It was a lousy pun, and eventually he abandoned it, but Mr. Hart, who died at his storyboard on Saturday at the age of 76, retained a punning, gagman's sensibility.</p>
        <p>A Super Bowl cartoon he once did for ''B.C.,'' his widely syndicated comic strip, featured a giant bowling ball bearing down on one of his hapless cavemen. Like the comic strip artists a few years ahead of him -- Mort Walker, Mel Lazarus, Charles M. Schulz -- he grew up listening to radio comedians and watching the movies of Chaplin and Laurel and Hardy. He loved slapstick, pratfalls, one-liners.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mr. Hart, who was known for his widely syndicated comic strip “B.C.,” evoked an entire prehistoric world with eloquent simplicity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the early days of his career, the cartoonist Johnny Hart signed his work with his first name and then a little outline of a heart. It was a lousy pun, and eventually he abandoned it, but Mr. Hart, who died at his storyboard on Saturday at the age of 76, retained a punning, gagman's sensibility.</p>
        <p>A Super Bowl cartoon he once did for ''B.C.,'' his widely syndicated comic strip, featured a giant bowling ball bearing down on one of his hapless cavemen. Like the comic strip artists a few years ahead of him -- Mort Walker, Mel Lazarus, Charles M. Schulz -- he grew up listening to radio comedians and watching the movies of Chaplin and Laurel and Hardy. He loved slapstick, pratfalls, one-liners.</p>
        <p>Like those other artists, Mr. Hart received what now looks like a classic American art education, the kind of apprenticeship that enabled a golden age of cartooning: he pored over strips like ''Dick Tracy'' and ''Smokey Stover'' as a child; studied a little commercial art as a teenager; did some time in the military, where he drew cartoons for Stars and Stripes; and then peddled single-panel cartoons to Colliers and The Saturday Evening Post before finally catching on with a newspaper syndicate. By the time he created ''B.C.'' in 1958, influenced partly by Mr. Schulz, he had pared his style to one of eloquent simplicity.</p>
        <p>''The Wizard of Id,'' the strip he began in 1964 with Brant Parker, who always drew it, delighted in deploying the full comic-strip armamentarium: plewds, or flying sweat drops, for example, and starburst squeans to indicate dizziness or, as was often the case with Bung, the mead-swilling jester, the effects of over-imbibing.</p>
        <p>But ''B.C.'' relied on just a simple line, a little cross-hatching, a few minimal props -- clubs, rocks, those one-shoulder caveman suits favored by B.C., Thor, Wiley and the rest -- and some basic sound effects (''Wham, wham, wham!'') to evoke an entire prehistoric world.</p>
        <p>Over time, B.C. the title character, actually slimmed down, evolving from a bowling-pin shaped Pleistocenian to one taller and leaner, whose body language -- the tilt of his back, the crook of his head -- spoke volumes. The lettering, bold and unfussy, derived from Mr. Hart's years as apprentice sign painter in Endicott, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Long before Mr. Hart came along, caveman jokes were a staple of magazines like The New Yorker and The Saturday Evening Post, and there was even a caveman strip, V. T. Hamlin's ''Alley Oop.'' Mr. Hart's singular contribution to the genre was, on the one hand, to expand the single panel gag into a narrative and, on the other, to streamline the elaborations and complications of ''Alley Oop,'' which propelled Alley back and forth from the 20th century and his home kingdom of Moo in what was essentially a time machine riff, not unlike the one employed lately by those caveman commercials for Geico insurance. ''The Flintstones'' essentially made use of the same gag run backward, importing modern conveniences and lifestyles back into the Stone Age.</p>
        <p>''B.C.'' was subtler and more sardonic. In the beginning, especially, it owed something to the ''black humor'' of the early '60s, and in some classic strips, like the one in which ''B.C.'' discovers fire yet again, it made fun of the very conventions of caveman humor or time-travel jokes. B.C. and his gang weren't so much cave people as they were timeless human beings who just happened to find themselves in the Stone Age -- a revelation that came naturally to Mr. Hart because he didn't believe in evolution. ''The absurdity of it all is beyond reason,'' he said once.</p>
        <p>In his later years, Mr. Hart's religious fundamentalism got him into hot water more than once as he insisted on incorporating Gospel messages into his strips, most famously one that depicted a menorah morphing into a cross. But his literalism also enabled a kind of comic daring in which he could imagine his cavemen playing baseball and football, worrying about Noah and the flood, wisecracking about 21st-century dining habits. They lived in an eternal present that was also a kind of prehistoric paradise.</p>
        <p>AN APPRAISAL</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 14, 2007, Saturday  An appraisal in The Arts on Tuesday about the cartoonist Johnny Hart, who died last Saturday, misspelled the given name of another comic strip artist who, like Mr. Hart, grew up listening to radio comedians and watching the movies of Charlie Chaplin and Laurel and Hardy. He is Mell Lazarus, not Mel. The appraisal also incorrectly rendered the name of a weekly publication Mr. Hart sold cartoons to early in his career. It was Collier's, not Colliers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 14, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>An appraisal in The Arts on Tuesday about the cartoonist Johnny Hart, who died last Saturday, misspelled the given name of another comic strip artist who, like Mr. Hart, grew up listening to radio comedians and watching the movies of Charlie Chaplin and Laurel and Hardy. He is Mell Lazarus, not Mel. The appraisal also incorrectly rendered the name of a weekly publication Mr. Hart sold cartoons to early in his career. It was Collier's, not Colliers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
