<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Division I-AA Program, N.F.L. Is Closer Than Ever</title>
    <meta content="10hampton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/sports/football/10hampton.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070413T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839394"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Football League</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Hampton University</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2DA153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1062" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Division I-AA Program, N.F.L. Is Closer Than Ever</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">As N.F.L. Draft Nears, Hopes Rise at Hampton</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hampton University is attracting attention like never before as teams prepare for the National Football League draft.</p>
        <p>Five Hampton players were among the 325 athletes invited to the N.F.L. combine in February, the most from a non-Division I-A program since the scouting event began in 1984. The Pirates' top prospect in the draft (April 28-29) is linebacker Justin Durant, a potential second-round pick who ran a 4.56 40-yard dash, third fastest for his position.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hampton University, a Div. I-AA school on the Eastern shore of Virginia, had five players at the N.F.L. combine, more than major programs like U.S.C. and Wisconsin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hampton University is attracting attention like never before as teams prepare for the National Football League draft.</p>
        <p>Five Hampton players were among the 325 athletes invited to the N.F.L. combine in February, the most from a non-Division I-A program since the scouting event began in 1984. The Pirates' top prospect in the draft (April 28-29) is linebacker Justin Durant, a potential second-round pick who ran a 4.56 40-yard dash, third fastest for his position.</p>
        <p>Durant said he was proud to learn that Hampton, which plays Division I-AA football and is on Virginia's Eastern shore, had more players at the combine than major Division I programs like Southern California (four) and Wisconsin (two). Like many players from smaller colleges, Durant says he has something extra to prove.</p>
        <p>''I played my career with a little chip, a little edge, and I plan to carry that chip into the N.F.L.,'' Durant said last week during a telephone interview. ''It felt good, having so many teammates at the combine, knowing that your path to the N.F.L. doesn't necessarily have to start at a big school. We don't get nearly as much exposure, or nearly as much recognition. But we think we can play, and hopefully the N.F.L. does, too.''</p>
        <p>Hampton's five draft prospects -- Durant, running back Alonzo Coleman, cornerback Travarous Bain and wide receivers Onrea Jones and Marquay McDaniel -- hope to join the list of recent non-Division I players who have made successful transitions to the N.F.L. Marques Colston, a former star at Division I-AA Hofstra, was one of the league's top receivers last season. A seventh-round draft pick, Colston caught 70 passes for 1,038 yards, helping the New Orleans Saints make the playoffs. Tony Romo, an undrafted quarterback from Division I-AA Eastern Illinois, developed into a Pro Bowl quarterback with the Dallas Cowboys.</p>
        <p>Despite the success of players like Colston and Romo, teams remain reluctant to risk a high pick on a player from a lower-lever college. In the past four drafts, only 10 of the 256 players selected in the first two rounds were from non-Division I-A programs.</p>
        <p>That made Hampton's heavy presence at the combine even more impressive. Two players from Hampton are on N.F.L. rosters: Jerome Mathis, a wide receiver for the Houston Texans who made the Pro Bowl in 2005 as a kick returner, and Darian Barnes, a fullback who signed with the Jets in March.</p>
        <p>The five Pirates who participated in this year's combine helped Hampton win three consecutive Mid-Eastern Athletic Conference championships, including last season's 10-2 team. Durant is not expected to last past the third round. Even if Coleman, Bain, Jones and McDaniel are not drafted, they could make a roster as free agents. They said they were already proud to have drawn more attention to their college team.</p>
        <p>''It says something about the talent and coaching we had,'' said Bain, who began his college career at the University of Miami but transferred to Hampton because he wanted more playing time. ''We're still at a disadvantage in some ways. If a team drafts a top player from Miami, nobody's going to argue. If a team takes a player from a small school, immediately people ask more questions. But to have as many guys as we did at the combine, we had to be doing something right.''</p>
        <p>Players from colleges like Hampton face pressure to excel at the combine, during all-star games, and during face-to-face workouts and interviews with teams that are interested in drafting them.</p>
        <p>''When you see players at the combine and in all-star games, that's when you're comparing apples to apples, rather than apples to oranges,'' Bill Polian, the general manager of the Indianapolis Colts, said last week during a phone interview. ''You see them compete against the same players, rather than during the season, when the week-to-week competition may not be as strong.</p>
        <p>''I don't think the recent success of some players has changed the philosophy of teams,'' Polian added. ''It's still difficult for a team to commit a first-round draft choice to a player from a small school. I'm not saying it can't happen with success, but it's still difficult. But you can go way back during the draft, like with Andre Reed from Kutztown State during the 1980s, and find players from small schools who stepped into the N.F.L. and became stars. If you can play football, an N.F.L. team wants to find you, no matter how small your school is.''</p>
        <p>Players from non-Division I-A programs who may be drafted this year include Ben Patrick, a tight end from Delaware; Maurice Price, a wide receiver from Charleston Southern; and Michael Allan, a tight end from Whitworth, who was the only Division III player invited to the combine.</p>
        <p>Joe Taylor, who has coached Hampton for 15 years, attributed this year's deep talent pool to the steady improvement of his program. Five of Taylor's assistant coaches played in the N.F.L., giving the Hampton players first-hand knowledge of what it takes.</p>
        <p>''We feel we can offer a young man the same things he'd get at a bigger program, it's just that we're smaller,'' Taylor said last week during a phone interview. ''I can't point to one reason why we'd have five guys at the combine this year. It's a combination of good recruiting, good coaching, and the strong work ethic of the guys. They were a good group.''</p>
        <p>Durant said he visited the Tampa Bay Buccaneers last week, and he expected to visit the Tennessee Titans and St. Louis Rams this week. He said he hoped he had impressed teams with his knowledge as well as his ability.</p>
        <p>His agent, Adisi Bakari, called Durant ''a student of the game.</p>
        <p>''Like a lot of guys from smaller schools, Justin is hungry,'' Bakari said. ''He didn't get a lot of Division I-A offers out of high school, because he was just north of 215 pounds and wanted to play linebacker. That wasn't going to happen. Other guys, late bloomers, have gone through the same thing. But by the time they get to the N.F.L., they are at their best. Justin is going to help someone's football team.''</p>
        <p>No matter what happens during draft weekend, Taylor and others affiliated with Hampton will watch this year's event more closely than usual.</p>
        <p>''We've certainly got players to keep track of,'' Taylor said. ''That's a nice feeling to have.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 13, 2007, Friday  A sports article on Tuesday about professional football prospects from Hampton University referred imprecisely to the university's location. It is on the peninsula of the Hampton Roads region in southeastern Virginia; it is not on the state's Eastern Shore.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 13, 2007, Friday</p>
        <p>A sports article on Tuesday about professional football prospects from Hampton University referred imprecisely to the university's location. It is on the peninsula of the Hampton Roads region in southeastern Virginia; it is not on the state's Eastern Shore.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
