<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Critic's Choice: New DVD's</title>
    <meta content="10dvd" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/movies/homevideo/10dvd.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839249"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Critics Choice"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/DVD and Video</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EFDE153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1004" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Critic's Choice: New DVD's</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New DVDs</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dave Kehr</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kehr, Dave</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Mario Bava Collection, Volume 1</p>
        <p>For those of us who received our film education through the art houses and film societies that flourished in the last century, the name Mario Bava may not mean much. But this once-obscure Italian genre filmmaker was one of the first directors to be discovered through the emerging medium of home video, thanks to perceptive video-specific critics like Tim Lucas, who has documented Mr. Bava's career in the pages of Video Watchdog, his handsomely produced fanzine.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lucas is a guiding spirit behind ''The Mario Bava Collection, Volume 1,'' a box set from Anchor Bay Entertainment that offers five Bava features, including his first and most famous effort, ''Black Sunday'' (1960). The excellent prints restore Mr. Bava's original cuts and in several cases the original Italian soundtracks for films that were routinely redubbed and re-edited by American distributors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New this week is “The Mario Bava Collection, Volume 1,” an opportunity to discover a once-obscure Italian genre filmmaker.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Mario Bava Collection, Volume 1</p>
        <p>For those of us who received our film education through the art houses and film societies that flourished in the last century, the name Mario Bava may not mean much. But this once-obscure Italian genre filmmaker was one of the first directors to be discovered through the emerging medium of home video, thanks to perceptive video-specific critics like Tim Lucas, who has documented Mr. Bava's career in the pages of Video Watchdog, his handsomely produced fanzine.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lucas is a guiding spirit behind ''The Mario Bava Collection, Volume 1,'' a box set from Anchor Bay Entertainment that offers five Bava features, including his first and most famous effort, ''Black Sunday'' (1960). The excellent prints restore Mr. Bava's original cuts and in several cases the original Italian soundtracks for films that were routinely redubbed and re-edited by American distributors.</p>
        <p>Movies that passed well below the critical radar when they were first released in the United States -- in urban grindhouses and Southern drive-ins -- are now returning in prestige editions, loaded with commentary (by Mr. Lucas) and extra features. For Mr. Bava, a modest man who died in 1980 without ever making any claims for himself or his work, the road from the grindhouse to the art house -- or at least, the virtual art house of the DVD player -- has turned out to be surprisingly, encouragingly short.</p>
        <p>The son of Eugenio Bava, a cinematographer whose credits go back to Giovanni Pastrone's 1914 ''Cabiria,'' one of the first great epics of Italian cinema, Mario Bava was himself a successful cinematographer, with a reputation for saving troubled international co-productions, when he was invited to direct a project of his own. The result, based on a story by Nikolai Gogol and influenced by the new line of Gothic horror films being produced by Hammer in Britain, was ''La Maschera del Demonio,'' starring an unknown British actress, Barbara Steele, whose burning black eyes immediately made her one of the very few women to achieve stardom in horror movies. Released in the United States as ''Black Sunday'' by American International Pictures, it became, Mr. Lucas says in his detailed commentary, the highest grossing film in that company's tawdry history, and a new career was born for Mr. Bava.</p>
        <p>Taking the basic Hammer formula -- which consisted of sexing up the classic Universal horror films of the early '30s -- Mr. Bava added a level of compulsive visual refinement. Complex in-depth compositions, full of varying textures and insinuating shadows highlighted by Mr. Bava's characteristic use of focused baby spotlights, make ''Black Sunday'' look less like one of the functional Hammer productions than a throwback to the ''calligraphic'' period of Italian filmmaking. At that time masters like Alessandro Blasetti (''The Iron Crown,'' 1941) created visuals of such improbable opulence and baroque styling that they teetered on the brink of mannerist decadence.</p>
        <p>There was no teetering with Mr. Bava: his decadence was full bodied and assertive, with explicit elements of sadomasochism. With his first horror film in color, ''I Tre Volte della Paura'' (''The Three Faces of Fear''), an anthology film recut and retitled ''Black Sabbath'' by American International Pictures but presented here in its complete Italian language version, Mr. Bava introduced his most singular stylistic trope. He masked his spotlights with colored gelatin filters, projecting pools of hot, electric colors onto his sets -- great washes of golden yellow, emerald green, inky blue and sanguinary puce that seem to dissolve any remaining links to reality, plunging the viewer into a claustrophobic dream world entirely of Mr. Bava's fevered imagination.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bava made films in most of the popular Italian genres of the era. In one busy year, 1966, he made a spaghetti western, a spy spoof, a Viking adventure (''Knives of the Avenger,'' included in this set and a nice surprise) and what may be his finest supernatural film (the unfortunately titled ''Kill, Baby Kill!,'' in this set as well). But he is most venerated by his fans for the series of slasher films he began in 1964 with ''Sei Donne per l'Assassino'' (called ''Blood and Black Lace'' in English). Introducing a disturbing element of voyeurism, the so-called ''gialli,'' or ''yellow,'' films (after the distinctive covers of the mystery novels published in Italy by Mondadori), present a series of stylish murders of attractive women by faceless assailants, a blunt invitation for misogynist audience identification and probably the source of their enduring appeal to anxious adolescents.</p>
        <p>The one crime film in the Anchor Bay set, the 1963 ''Ragazza che Sapeva Troppo'' (''The Girl Who Knew Too Much,'' but released here as ''The Evil Eye''), is Mr. Bava's first step in that direction, though it remains basically a comic thriller about an innocent American (Letícia Román) who discovers that Rome is not quite the tourist's paradise of ''Roman Holiday.'' Volume 2 will probably move further into this more disreputable territory; in the meantime, there is plenty for fans to parse and analyze in this elegant little collection. ($49.98, not rated)</p>
        <p>Also Out Today</p>
        <p>THE UNTOUCHABLES, SEASON 1, VOLUME 1 -- Fourteen episodes from the inaugural 1959-60 season of the classic television series, with Robert Stack as the unsmiling Eliot Ness, the federal agent charged with cleaning up Prohibition-era Chicago. Includes ''The Scarface Mob,'' the theatrical feature edited from the first two episodes of the series and directed by the major noir stylist Phil Karlson. (CBS/Paramount, $38.99, not rated)</p>
        <p>THE DORIS DAY COLLECTION, VOL. 2 -- Six more musicals from Ms. Day's Warner Brothers days, including three titles directed by her champion at the studio, Michael Curtiz: ''Romance on the High Seas'' (1948), ''My Dream Is Yours'' (1949) and ''I'll See You in My Dreams'' (1951). (Warner Home Video, $59.98, not rated)</p>
        <p>BOBBY -- Emilio Estevez's film follows 22 characters through the Ambassador Hotel in Los Angeles on the day of Robert F. Kennedy's assassination. A cameo studded cast includes Demi Moore, Anthony Hopkins, Lindsay Lohan and Laurence Fishburne. (The Weinstein Company, $28.95, R)</p>
        <p>Critics Choice</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
