<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Citigroup's Revamp May Trim Its Compliance Corps</title>
    <meta content="10place" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/business/10place.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839314"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET PLACE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Citigroup Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dash, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Prince, Charles O III</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Market Place (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Citigroup Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE2DC153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="781" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Citigroup's Revamp May Trim Its Compliance Corps</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Citigroup’s Revamp May Trim Its Compliance Corps</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC DASH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dash, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Market Place column; Citigroup's chief executive Charles O Prince III is set to release plans for bank's first major overhaul since merger forged Citigroup decade ago; is planning to eliminate 26,000 jobs, or about 8 percent of work force, as part of broad effort to streamline bank's unwieldy global operations and get its costs under control; consumer and investment banking businesses are expected to face most severe cuts; legal and compliance departments are being heavily scrutinized; cuts in compliance would represent reversal from few years ago, when Citigroup was beefing up its compliance staff after several scandals; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHARLES O. PRINCE III spent his first two years as chief executive of Citigroup adding more compliance officers and improving the bank's controls after a series of messy scandals.</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Prince is looking to slim its bulging compliance ranks in an effort to keep the bank from getting bogged down.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Under pressure from investors, Citigroup’s chief is looking to slim its compliance ranks to keep the bank from getting bogged down.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CHARLES O. PRINCE III spent his first two years as chief executive of Citigroup adding more compliance officers and improving the bank's controls after a series of messy scandals.</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Prince is looking to slim its bulging compliance ranks in an effort to keep the bank from getting bogged down.</p>
        <p>Under pressure from investors, Mr. Prince is set to release plans on Wednesday for the bank's first major overhaul since a merger forged Citigroup a decade ago. He is planning to eliminate or reassign more than 26,000 jobs, or about 8 percent of the work force, as part of a broad effort to streamline the bank's unwieldy global operations and get its costs under control.</p>
        <p>Citigroup's consumer and investment banking businesses are expected to face the most severe cuts. But across the company, legal and compliance departments are being heavily scrutinized, according to people who have been briefed on the plans.</p>
        <p>Cuts in compliance would represent a reversal from a few years ago, when Citigroup was beefing up its compliance staff after several scandals. Citigroup, like other banks, was tarred by its dealings with Enron and WorldCom and by investigations into analysts' conflicts during the Internet boom.</p>
        <p>A series of rapid, huge eurobond trades by Citigroup bankers, referred to as a ''Dr. Evil'' trading strategy, roiled markets in Europe in August 2004. That fall, Citigroup's private bank had a run-in with Japanese regulators over lax money laundering controls. For more than a year, Citigroup was banned by the Federal Reserve from making a big acquisition until its financial house was in order.</p>
        <p>Shortly after Mr. Prince took the helm in October 2003, he moved to tighten compliance. The effort resulted in a lot of belt-and-suspenders oversight functions. But some have suggested that the compliance overhang has made it difficult to be competitive.</p>
        <p>Now, the pendulum is swinging in the other direction. With several scandals behind them, Citigroup officials are now looking to consolidate overlapping compliance departments and eliminate others that unnecessarily slowed the company down. Citigroup officials cautioned that any changes would be an effort to improve efficiency and coordination, not relax controls. They also suggested that any effort to ''optimize compliance'' was distinct from the expense review.</p>
        <p>''We remain utterly committed to a strong control environment,'' said Christina Pretto, a Citigroup spokeswoman. ''It's about getting things to work as efficiently and effectively as they can.''</p>
        <p>Citigroup officials recognized that compliance had become cumbersome as early as last summer. In August, Lewis B. Kaden, the company's chief administrative officer, began examining ways to streamline the bank's compliance operations, starting a pilot program in its private bank and brokerage division and a review of other businesses. But with less urgency and internal support, the project was left unfinished.</p>
        <p>Only in December, when Mr. Prince elevated Robert Druskin to the role of chief operating officer and gave him the task of a big expense review, did the compliance project gain new currency.</p>
        <p>Of course, the company is also looking elsewhere for cost savings. Citigroup is planning major upgrades to its technology systems and is looking for ways to use its real estate more efficiently. But another big source will be cutting jobs: 10,000 to 12,000 positions are in the balance. Meanwhile, Citigroup is also planning to relocate thousands more to cheaper places, including India and several smaller American cities.</p>
        <p>Citigroup's consumer and credit card operations will experience most of the job cuts, with customer service employees and back-office workers among the groups most affected. Citigroup's investment bank is also taking a harder look at less productive junior managers between the vice president and managing director ranks, with the goal of improving productivity. And last week, Citigroup's private bank announced the departure of several top managers in what could foreshadow future shake-ups to streamline operations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Prince's plans to create a ''leaner, thinner'' Citigroup come at a crucial time. Investors have grown impatient with expense growth that has outpaced revenue growth and a stock price that has remained.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Prince laid out a strategy to deliver internal and international growth, signs of progress on the financial front, so far, have been hard to find. In the face of growing investor pressure, Mr. Prince has cut back on some planned investment spending and placed a greater emphasis on acquisitions, including a $427 million purchase of the Bank of Overseas Chinese, based in Taiwan, that it announced yesterday.</p>
        <p>But investors are also looking to see whether Mr. Prince can get the bank's high costs in line. Alongside the expense review that Mr. Druskin is leading, Citigroup's new chief financial officer, Gary L. Crittenden, is reviewing the company's overall finances and operations.</p>
        <p>MARKET PLACE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
