<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Voices United Yet Distinct, Relating Bach's 'Passion'</title>
    <meta content="10pass" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/arts/music/10pass.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839266"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Collegium Vocale</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Herreweghe, Philippe</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E6DD153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="526" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Voices United Yet Distinct, Relating Bach's 'Passion'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Voices United Yet Distinct, Relating Bach’s ‘Passion’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was no surprise to see music lovers lined up outside Alice Tully Hall on a nippy Sunday afternoon, hoping to get returned tickets for the sold-out Easter performance of Bach's ''St. John Passion'' by the conductor Philippe Herreweghe and the Collegium Vocale Gent Choir and Orchestra. This Belgian conductor and the early-music ensemble he founded in 1970 have rightly won an enormous following for their concerts and recordings. And this performance, though not flawless, was magnificent.</p>
        <p>It is hard to explain exactly why it was so compelling. Mr. Herreweghe defies categorization. Though he comes from the early-music world, his performances are not necessarily characterized by the lean textures and fleet tempos we associate with that movement. Sometimes his spacious timing and his feel for musical architecture make him seem the Wilhelm Furtwängler of early-music conductors. Then again, he can surprise you with his crisp articulations and quick tempos.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Philippe Herreweghe elicited a gripping account of Bach’s towering Passion from the Collegium Vocale Gent Choir and Orchestra at Alice Tully Hall on Sunday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was no surprise to see music lovers lined up outside Alice Tully Hall on a nippy Sunday afternoon, hoping to get returned tickets for the sold-out Easter performance of Bach's ''St. John Passion'' by the conductor Philippe Herreweghe and the Collegium Vocale Gent Choir and Orchestra. This Belgian conductor and the early-music ensemble he founded in 1970 have rightly won an enormous following for their concerts and recordings. And this performance, though not flawless, was magnificent.</p>
        <p>It is hard to explain exactly why it was so compelling. Mr. Herreweghe defies categorization. Though he comes from the early-music world, his performances are not necessarily characterized by the lean textures and fleet tempos we associate with that movement. Sometimes his spacious timing and his feel for musical architecture make him seem the Wilhelm Furtwängler of early-music conductors. Then again, he can surprise you with his crisp articulations and quick tempos.</p>
        <p>Whatever the case, Mr. Herreweghe elicited a gripping account of Bach's towering Passion from choristers and instrumentalists who clearly revere him. The two parts of the work were played without interruption, lasting two inexorable hours.</p>
        <p>That drama looms large in a Herreweghe performance was clear from the stern opening chorus, a plea for the Lord to teach us through the story of his Passion. The churning 16th-note figures in the strings that propel the music were insistent, even disturbing. Clarity of texture was hardly the goal here. The obsessively repeated eighth-note bass line in the gravelly cellos and string bass was almost mind-numbing.</p>
        <p>Though the 16 voices of the splendid choir were beautifully blended, there was no sense of enforced uniformity in the robust and flexible singing. Here the chorales that run through the Passion truly emerged as essential timeouts from Bach's poignant and graphic musical depiction of Christ's crucifixion: moments to reflect on the story through Bach's solid, serene and comforting four-part harmony.</p>
        <p>The vocal soloists put a premium on directness of expression rather than fancy vocalism, especially the dusky-toned alto Ingeborg Danz and the lyric tenor Jan Kobow. Two scheduled soloists, the soprano Camilla Tilling and the bass Peter Kooij, who had canceled because of illness, were replaced on short notice by Johannette Zomer, a bright-voiced soprano, and Christian Immler, a sturdy bass. Perhaps it was the last-minute reshuffling that accounted for a very troubled moment in the soprano aria ''Zerfliesse, mein Herze,'' when Ms. Zomer and the players seemed to drift apart. It must also be said that though the instrumentalists took what seemed an inordinate amount of time to tune up before each part of the Passion, there were some inexplicable lapses with shaky intonation.</p>
        <p>The refined baritone Konrad Jarnot made a dignified Christ. Singing the crucial part of the Evangelist was Christoph Prégardien. That this distinguished German tenor began his musical life as a choirboy seems crucial to his mature artistry. Though his singing was elegant, clarion and worldly wise, there was still an affecting element of choirboy purity in his voice. During the Evangelist's long stretches of narrative recitative, Mr. Herreweghe put his hands at his side and simply listened, seemingly captivated along with the rest of us.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
