<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In East Harlem School Closing, Talk of a Class Divide</title>
    <meta content="10citywide" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/nyregion/10citywide.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839339"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CITYWIDE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Private and Sectarian Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Harlem (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DB153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1396" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In East Harlem School Closing, Talk of a Class Divide</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In East Harlem School Closing, Talk of a Class Divide</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID GONZALEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gonzalez, David</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lourdes Velasquez has seen it all in East Harlem. In the old days, it was a neighborhood for poor and working-class families. In the bad days, it was beset by guns and drugs. And now?</p>
        <p>Doormen. New high-rise buildings. Higher prices at the local supermarket. Young couples pushing strollers that cost more than a month's rent in yet-to-be-renovated buildings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gentrification continues to sweep over East Harlem, engulfing, it seems, a neighborhood parish school  much to parents’ dismay.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lourdes Velasquez has seen it all in East Harlem. In the old days, it was a neighborhood for poor and working-class families. In the bad days, it was beset by guns and drugs. And now?</p>
        <p>Doormen. New high-rise buildings. Higher prices at the local supermarket. Young couples pushing strollers that cost more than a month's rent in yet-to-be-renovated buildings.</p>
        <p>While she resented these gentrifiers who ''discovered'' the only neighborhood she has known for all of her 35 years, she also tried to ensure that her daughter, Chrystal, would be able to deal with the changes. She sent the girl to St. Francis de Sales School on East 97th Street off Lexington Avenue, paying $3,000 a year to give her the kind of Catholic education that enabled previous generations of working-class children to become professionals.</p>
        <p>But now St. Francis de Sales School itself may be joining the gentry.</p>
        <p>Ms. Velasquez and the other parents of almost 200 students in the school's eight grades were abruptly told in early March that the school would close in June. But officials at the Archdiocese of New York, as well as other parents and clergy familiar with recent events, said they expected that the school would reopen in a year, possibly as a more expensive private academy or preschool.</p>
        <p>''They just want us out to make room for the new and improved people,'' Ms. Velasquez said. ''There is a plan for this neighborhood. I mean, look at First Avenue. They got doormen! It's all connected. Look at Second Avenue. Why do they want to finish the subway now? These are not different issues. It's all connected.''</p>
        <p>A little more than a decade ago, archdiocesan officials considered the school exemplary in its efforts to educate students in East Harlem. Then it was known as St. Francis de Sales &amp; St. Lucy Academy, with some 600 students in two buildings. (Full disclosure: this reporter wrote a long article about the school's success and was later made an honorary eighth-grade graduate).</p>
        <p>Falling enrollment led to St. Lucy's closing three years ago. St. Francis de Sales continued as its own school in its building on East 97th Street, serving the working-class families, even as new and more expensive housing was springing up all over the neighborhood, including a high-rise next door. Parents saw the school -- located in a pristine, if bland, red-brick building -- as a haven that nurtured their dreams for their children.</p>
        <p>But as the neighborhood changed, so did things at the school. A new pastor, the Rev. Victor Muzzin, came in about three years ago, inheriting a school that had had a stormy relationship with its previous pastor. A new principal soon followed.</p>
        <p>Father Muzzin said he arrived at the parish to find $1,000 in its account and the school in debt. The school, he said, now has a $250,000 deficit. Tuition was raised only recently to $3,000 a year from $2,600 a year. Numbers like that, he said, made it hard to keep it open.</p>
        <p>''I am not the kind of pastor who wakes up and says, 'Gee, I have a $250,000 debt.' I saw it coming three years earlier,'' Father Muzzin said. ''There was no hope for me to save this school.''</p>
        <p>An archdiocesan spokeswoman said that the decision to close the school was the parish's, but that the archdiocese accepted it. Nor was it tied to the recent announcement that another shuttered Catholic school in Greenwich Village will reopen as a Catholic academy, with annual tuition approaching $25,000, said the spokeswoman, Jacqueline Lofaro.</p>
        <p>''They felt they could not support the school in its current incarnation,'' Ms. Lofaro said. ''What they plan to do is step back for a year and reopen it as some kind of parish school.''</p>
        <p>Just what kind remains to be seen. Father Muzzin said he had no plans at the moment, and that he was not inclined to rent out the school building to another private, secular school. Many parents said that might be because he wants to open a more expensive academy there.</p>
        <p>A little over a year ago, Father Muzzin said as much in the Sunday bulletin distributed at Mass. In it, he described how the school -- which parents said served primarily black and Latino students -- needed to attract a greater ''variety of people'' from the area.</p>
        <p>''Some parents have to wake up to the realization that they cannot afford Catholic Education,'' he wrote. ''Period.''</p>
        <p>The pastor's message became clearer a few lines later: ''I see the day in the not distant future when it will become the school of choice of all the Catholic parents in the neighborhood who now send their children to prestigious and pricey private schools,'' he wrote. ''Why spend $25,000 when you can get the same thing for much, much less?''</p>
        <p>The bluntness of his comments riled many parents, who felt betrayed. After several generations of the church's siding with the poor, parents saw in the remarks their pastor declaring a preferential option for the middle class.</p>
        <p>''But he wants the black and Hispanic children out first,'' said Helen Torres, whose granddaughter Alexis attends the school. ''Ninety-sixth Street is an up-and-coming area. But 30 years ago, it was us, the immigrants and the working class who donated our little pennies faithfully. He is turning his back on this community.''</p>
        <p>Father Muzzin countered that many of the students in the school were actually from other neighborhoods and commuted there with their parents, who worked at nearby hospitals. (A former teacher said the school has always drawn about a third of its students from commuters).</p>
        <p>''They dump their kids here, but they're not creating a community,'' Father Muzzin said. ''What has changed is East Harlem is now creating community. From the dump it was in the '90s, now it is a flourishing community.''</p>
        <p>He added that there were other Catholic schools in East Harlem that had improved. But he noted that with all the changes in the southern fringe of the neighborhood, middle-class parents needed other educational options, too.</p>
        <p>''They pay $3,000 rent for an apartment, and they have these jobs, which are O.K. and provide them with money, but at the end of the day they are under the same pressure as the poor who want to do good for themselves,'' he said. ''There is the poor middle class. What has the church done for them?''</p>
        <p>He suggested that while he could not see himself opening an academy charging $25,000 a year or more, some local families might respond to a Catholic school charging $12,000.</p>
        <p>''These are the people who come to church and leave the little money that keeps the place open before the marshal comes to close it down,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Last Wednesday, children and parents huddled outside the school in the drizzle at the start of Easter recess. Down the block, a construction crew went about finishing a glass and metal sliver of a building that sprouted on what had been a parking lot. Across the street, an otherwise plain red-brick building that had been renovated only recently was for sale as a townhouse.</p>
        <p>Benedicta Almeida, a retired seamstress, slowly walked away with her granddaughter, Faith Angelique, a first grader at the school. The child, whom she is raising, was doing well when she attended preschool at St. Francis de Sales. First grade has been a little rockier: her mother died from cancer last year.</p>
        <p>''It has been a trauma,'' she said. ''She did not eat or sleep for a while. She still cries.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Almeida feels like crying herself. She, like many other parents, said the closing came without warning. She has yet to find another school for the girl.</p>
        <p>''This has affected her,'' she said. ''She is disoriented. She asks me: 'Where am I going? What will happen to me?' ''</p>
        <p>Ms. Velasquez is asking the same questions when it comes to her neighborhood. First St. Lucy's closed. Now St. Francis de Sales. She is not taking a chance with another local school and plans to send her daughter, Chrystal, now a sixth grader, to a school on the West Side.</p>
        <p>''I am all for progress, but do they have to push us out?'' she asked. ''My daughter has been in two schools that closed. It's ridiculous. Everybody is going to leave. It's ridiculous, but that's what they want us to do.''</p>
        <p>CITYWIDE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
