<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pavano Gives the Relievers Time to Watch the Offense</title>
    <meta content="10yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839388"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Minnesota Twins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E4DA153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="888" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pavano Gives the Relievers Time to Watch the Offense</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>MINNEAPOLIS, April 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Sidney Ponson era in Yankees history never would have happened if Carl Pavano had been healthy. The Yankees were desperate for rotation help in Pavano's absence last summer, and they turned briefly to Ponson.</p>
        <p>On Monday night at the Metrodome, Pavano pitched against the man who replaced him. It was not a fair fight. The Yankees bruised Ponson for 8 runs and 10 hits, and Pavano earned his first victory since May 22, 2005.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Sidney Ponson era in Yankees history never would have happened if Carl Pavano had been healthy. The Yankees were desperate for rotation help in Pavano's absence last summer, and they turned briefly to Ponson.</p>
        <p>On Monday night at the Metrodome, Pavano pitched against the man who replaced him. It was not a fair fight. The Yankees bruised Ponson for 8 runs and 10 hits, and Pavano earned his first victory since May 22, 2005.</p>
        <p>''Some days it feels like yesterday, and some days it feels like a lifetime,'' Pavano said. ''I'm glad to have all that behind me and move forward.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees stomped the Minnesota Twins, 8-2, with Bobby Abreu and Alex Rodriguez hitting homers off Ponson. According to the Elias Sports Bureau, Rodriguez became the first player in Yankees history with five home runs in the first six games of the season.</p>
        <p>The Yankees already knew they could hit, and their ease with Ponson was no surprise. Pavano was the revelation.</p>
        <p>He pitched well for four innings on opening day last Monday before unraveling in the fifth. That had been one of the better starts so far for the Yankees, whose starters did not exceed five innings in the first five games.</p>
        <p>Before Monday, the combined earned run average for the rotation was 9.97. Andy Pettitte could feel panic setting in.</p>
        <p>''It was kind of humorous, because people were asking me if we were going to go four innings all year,'' Pettitte said. ''But any time you have a bad stretch, the way to get out of it is with a good start from your starting pitcher. He got it, and that was big.''</p>
        <p>In the controlled atmosphere of the Metrodome, all of the Yankees seemed more comfortable. They looked spry on defense, and the offense gave Pavano a big early lead. He used it to pitch aggressively, plowing through the Twins' order on just 79 pitches over seven innings.</p>
        <p>''When he was on the Marlins, he was pretty aggressive on the mound,'' said Abreu, who faced Pavano when both played in the National League East. ''That's the way I saw him back in the day. Today was a pretty good start to going back.''</p>
        <p>Pavano allowed two runs, six hits and no walks, striking out two and using double plays to end the first and fifth innings. He even had three 1-2-3 innings, exceeding by one the starters' combined total for the first five games.</p>
        <p>Pavano had gone 687 days without a victory, since he beat the Mets on a Sunday at Shea Stadium. Ponson has not won since he pitched for the St. Louis Cardinals last season. In his five-game fling with the Yankees, he went 0-1 with a 10.47 E.R.A.</p>
        <p>But after having elbow surgery, Ponson earned a spring-training invitation from the Twins, who guaranteed him $1 million when they put him on the roster. After one start, it looks like a poor investment for a cost-conscious team.</p>
        <p>Five of the first six Yankees reached base, and it was 5-0 after two innings. Johnny Damon led off with a broken-bat double to right and scored on a single by Abreu, who was just getting started.</p>
        <p>Jorge Posada knocked in two more in the first with a double. After a single by Damon in the second, Abreu ripped a curveball off the suite level above right field for his first home run of the season. His presence is helping Rodriguez, who bats behind him.</p>
        <p>''Bobby's just one of those real underrated players,'' Rodriguez said. ''The at-bats he puts together are incredible. You get to see 30 pitches a game before you get to hit. There's a residual there.''</p>
        <p>With two out in the sixth, Abreu and Rodriguez chased Ponson from the game. Abreu singled in Derek Jeter to give the Yankees a 6-1 lead, and two pitches later, Rodriguez finished Ponson with an opposite-field homer.</p>
        <p>Rodriguez said he could not remember the last time he felt so good, but that seemed hard to believe.</p>
        <p>''I guess if you give me five minutes, I could come up with some good ones,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Rodriguez has had many hot stretches in his career; last week's effort earned him his 11th player of the week award and third with the Yankees. But he is proving that he may really have the peace of mind he has been talking about.</p>
        <p>''We just want to keep him right there,'' Manager Joe Torre said. ''You can just feel the confidence he has when he goes to the plate.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Manager Joe Torre said Melky Cabrera would start in left with Hideki Matsui on the disabled list. Cabrera batted .206 in spring training and is 2 for 21 this season.  The Yankees have not revised their timetable for Chien-Ming Wang's return. ''He's coming along,'' General Manager Brian Cashman said. ''We're lining him up for sometime in late April.'' Wang, who strained his right hamstring in spring training, threw batting practice Monday in Tampa, Fla. Billy Connors, the team's pitching troubleshooter, told Torre that Wang's arm strength was fine but that his location was off. Torre said Wang would probably need two minor league starts before returning.  Darrell Rasner will be skipped the next time through the rotation and will pitch in long relief.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
