<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Consumer Reports Names 2 Editors and Says Magazine Will Be Redesigned</title>
    <meta content="10mag" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/business/media/10mag.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839305"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Consumer Reports (Magazine)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Story, Louise</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kleman, Kimberly</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daugherty, Greg</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Consumer Reports</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E6DC153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="514" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Consumer Reports Names 2 Editors and Says Magazine Will Be Redesigned</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Consumer Reports Names 2 Editors and Says Magazine Will Be Redesigned</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOUISE STORY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Story, Louise</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Consumer Reports names two new editors and announces redesign; Kimberly Kleman becomes magazine's editor in chief; she will remain second in command at editorial division of Consumers Union; Greg Daugherty, longtime editor at Consumer Reports, is named to newly created position to oversee personnel issues for all company's reporters and editors (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As it struggles to recover from a recent flawed article about children's car seats, Consumer Reports has named two new editors and announced a redesign.</p>
        <p>Kimberly Kleman has become the magazine's editor in chief, and she will remain second in command at the editorial division of Consumers Union, a nonprofit company that publishes consumer product magazines, books and newsletters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The changes come as the magazine struggles to recover from a recent flawed article about children’s car seats.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As it struggles to recover from a recent flawed article about children's car seats, Consumer Reports has named two new editors and announced a redesign.</p>
        <p>Kimberly Kleman has become the magazine's editor in chief, and she will remain second in command at the editorial division of Consumers Union, a nonprofit company that publishes consumer product magazines, books and newsletters.</p>
        <p>The company also named Greg Daugherty, a longtime editor at Consumer Reports, to a newly created position to oversee personnel issues for all the company's reporters and editors.</p>
        <p>The magazine, long considered an independent arbiter of consumer products, will also be redesigned this year.</p>
        <p>The new editors will have to work on regaining readers' trust, industry specialists said.</p>
        <p>''Kimberly and Greg will have to try to bring back the trust and the brand; one mishap tarnishes a lot,'' said Samir A. Husni, chairman of the journalism department at the University of Mississippi.</p>
        <p>In a ''Safety Alert'' article in its February issue, Consumer Reports said that 10 infant car seats failed its safety test and called for one seat to be recalled.</p>
        <p>In an editorial in that issue, the magazine's president, James Guest, wrote that the images he saw of the tests ''filled me with dread: Dummies tumbled like Raggedy Anns, seats flew across the lab, plastic bases cracked.''</p>
        <p>Within weeks, the magazine's executives retracted the article and apologized, saying the tests, which the magazine said were conducted by an outside company, had been botched. The May issue contains an explanation of the mistake.</p>
        <p>''When Consumer Reports has to come out and apologize in public and in print, that's big for a magazine that has been trusted for years,'' Mr. Husni said. ''This is going to require a big forgiveness.''</p>
        <p>Circulation did not drop at Consumer Reports, nor has its subscription growth slowed since it retracted the car seat article, said Ken Weine, a company spokesman.</p>
        <p>Newsstand sales have reached 160,000 each month this year, twice those three years ago. The magazine, which does not accept advertising, has 4.3 million print readers, and 2.8 million who pay to read its online version, Mr. Weine said.</p>
        <p>The redesign will provide more information about the magazine's product-testing methods, but Ms. Kleman said that the change was not in response to the car seat episode. Instead, the additional testing information will be provided as a way for the magazine to set itself apart from other sources of product information like consumer review sites, she said.</p>
        <p>''We'll focus a little bit more on our testing and how we test,'' she said. ''I think that's one thing that makes our magazine really unique. A lot of times we make news with our test results.''</p>
        <p>The redesign will also be partly aimed at attracting more women -- about 70 percent of its 4.3 million readers are male, Ms. Kleman said. The magazine will also try to extend its coverage beyond consumer product reviews and delve into consumer issues like health care, she said.</p>
        <p>The previous editor in chief, Margot Slade, left in October, and the position has been vacant since.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
