<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lives on the Record and on the Web</title>
    <meta content="10web" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Retirement" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Job Market" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/business/retirement/10web.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839404"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FOR KEEPS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blogs and Blogging (Internet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Youtube</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Timegoesby.net</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bennett, Ronni</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oakley, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schneider, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blogs and Blogging (Internet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EFDA153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1416" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lives on the Record and on the Web</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lives on the Record and on the Web</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schneider, Keith</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Low-cost video cameras, simplified software and rise of video-sharing sites like YouTube have enabled growing number of elderly and retired people to tell their stories; Ronni Bennett, retired former managing editor of CBSNews.com, whose popular blog Timegoesby.net, covers aging, comments; most popular Internet legacy producers is Peter Oakley, 79-year-old retired motorcycle dealer from Derbyshire, Eng, known as Geriatric1927; photo (special section, Retirement) (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LOW-COST video cameras, simplified software and the rise of video-sharing sites like YouTube have enabled a growing number of elderly and retired people to tell their stories.</p>
        <p>By posting what are often called video legacy projects to the Internet, retirees are finding audiences that extend far beyond their own families -- sometimes numbering in the hundreds of thousands -- and building new networks of online friends. For people whose vigor or mobility has become limited, posting videos can significantly expand their range of contacts and experiences.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A growing number of elderly and retired people are telling their stories with Internet video.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LOW-COST video cameras, simplified software and the rise of video-sharing sites like YouTube have enabled a growing number of elderly and retired people to tell their stories.</p>
        <p>By posting what are often called video legacy projects to the Internet, retirees are finding audiences that extend far beyond their own families -- sometimes numbering in the hundreds of thousands -- and building new networks of online friends. For people whose vigor or mobility has become limited, posting videos can significantly expand their range of contacts and experiences.</p>
        <p>''Among Carl Jung's seven tasks of aging is reflection, putting a story line to your life,'' said Ronni Bennett, 66, the retired former managing editor of CBSNews.com, whose popular blog, Timegoesby.net, covers aging. ''The Internet provides people with a new way to tell their story. When the grandkids aren't interested in listening anymore, older people can still share their stories and get feedback. The technology makes it simple.''</p>
        <p>''It's a trope that the Internet is a young person's medium,'' she added. ''That is just not true.''</p>
        <p>By far the most popular of the Internet legacy producers is Peter Oakley, a 79-year-old retired motorcycle dealer from Derbyshire, England, known as Geriatric1927. Last August, Mr. Oakley, a widower, began starring in videos that described his life. He records the episodes on a simple Logitech Webcam, downloads them into the MovieMaker program that was included with the Microsoft Windows operating system of his personal computer, and then uploads the videos to YouTube, following the prompts posted by the Internet site.</p>
        <p>Mr. Oakley's debut ''Telling It All'' program, which opened with what has become his signature ''Hello YouTubers'' greeting, attracted 500,000 viewers its first week, and was featured on the BBC.</p>
        <p>Almost 40,000 people now subscribe to Geriatric1927 episodes: When a new video is posted to YouTube (four or five times a month), the subscriber is sent an e-mail message with the link that will call it up. After each new episode, Mr. Oakley said, he receives 50 to 60 e-mail messages from around the world.</p>
        <p>''After retirement I became interested in computer and graphic design and attended local colleges to learn,'' Mr. Oakley said. ''I found that there were facilities within the Windows operating system that would do this, and with the 'help files' made my first video.</p>
        <p>''I don't really know why I uploaded it. I guess just to see if I could learn how to do it. The media picked up on it and highlighted the fact that an old man could or would do such a thing -- invade a site that was the domain mostly of the young. Actually I had no idea that it was.''</p>
        <p>Many of the legacy video projects focus on World War II veterans, including ''The Paratrooper's Story,'' produced by Guy Anhorn, a 60-year-old retired police officer from suburban Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>The five-part, 90-minute film, which Mr. Anhorn completed in March, tells the story of Mr. Anhorn's 82-year-old uncle, Joseph Daniel McGinley, who, as a 19-year-old paratrooper, was among the thousands of American soldiers who fought to hold their ground against eight German divisions and deadly bombardment in Bastogne, Belgium, during the Battle of the Bulge.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Anhorn finished the second part of the film, ''A Trooper Gets His Wings,'' he posted it on YouTube, where it has been viewed by more than 1,200 people since December. Mr. Anhorn's film, his first, was shot with a $450 Panasonic Mini-DV camera, recorded on a $60 wireless microphone and edited on Windows Moviemaker. (The film can be viewed at mywebpages.comcast.net/paratrooperstory/index.htm.)</p>
        <p>''The same technology that only the Hollywood elite could afford to buy is now available to Joe Six-pack,'' said Mr. Anhorn.</p>
        <p>Leslie Boswell Loken, a retired military officer and electronic research manager from Rohnert Park, Calif., began taping episodes of his life story last September, using a $295 Panasonic Mini-DV digital video camera, and posting them to YouTube. The idea for the project came from his daughter, Judy Loken, a graphic artist and Web designer who studied filmmaking in college.</p>
        <p>Ms. Loken said that her father had told so many interesting stories that she was convinced his narrative would find an audience. She set the video camera on a tripod, sat her father in a comfortable chair, prompted him with a couple of questions, and recorded his answers with the camera's microphone.</p>
        <p>She downloaded the raw footage into the iMovies program in the Apple operating system on her Mac G5 computer. She added still pictures from her photo albums, and uploaded the finished videos to YouTube.</p>
        <p>The 94-year-old father of nine, frail and breathing oxygen, soon found himself a minor Internet celebrity after YouTube featured his video project on its home page on Veterans Day last year. By the time he died in mid-February, some 30,000 people had subscribed to receive Mr. Loken's videos. His life attracted such interest on the Internet that the family taped his memorial service and posted that online, too.</p>
        <p>''It was so gratifying to my Dad,'' Ms. Loken said. ''He received e-mails and he responded to them. Doing this project just added to the quality of the end of his life. Before we started, he was at the point where he was going downhill rapidly. Then we posted that first video to YouTube, and all of a sudden people paid attention. He was getting all this acclaim. It brightened the last months of his life.''</p>
        <p>Chris Calloway, a singer, writer, actress and the 62-year-old daughter of Cab Calloway, the jazz singer and band leader, has discovered similar benefits with her family legacy project. With the help of John Biethan, a friend and technology consultant, Ms. Calloway created a Web site, ''The Heartbeat of Hi De Ho'' (callowayhideho.com). It started a year ago and serves as the home for a series of radio episodes, or podcasts, broadcast on the Internet.</p>
        <p>Ms. Calloway, who lives in Santa Fe, N.M., writes the scripts and records them in a studio in Mr. Biethan's home. Cab Calloway's music is explored, along with recorded interviews with members of her famous family, all of it tied together by ''your Main Queen,'' the sultry character Ms. Calloway created to narrate.</p>
        <p>The shows are recorded on a $295 Edirol R-1 digital recorder, a $195 Mackie 1202 VLZ mixer to meld voice and music, and a $200 studio-quality AKG C-3000-B microphone.</p>
        <p>With roughly 350 visitors weekly, the site hasn't yet met one of its goals: producing income from sponsorships, advertising and sales of music and merchandise.</p>
        <p>But the project provided something more valuable: a stage close to home for Ms. Calloway, who is being treated for breast cancer.</p>
        <p>''I have a lot to offer still,'' said Ms. Calloway, who spent 20 years performing all over the world with her father, who died in 1994. ''I have a great story, my father's life, that is real and authentic. Chemotherapy impedes my ability to get out and do songs and entertain. But this project allows me to move beyond the confines of my physical limitations and still be an entertainer. Technology has made that possible.''</p>
        <p>A Walk in Spielberg's Shoes</p>
        <p>PRODUCING a legacy video, while perhaps not as easy as driving, has become fairly simple. Here are some basic tools you will need and the steps to get started.</p>
        <p>1. USE A GOOD COMPUTER -- Almost every Apple and Windows-compatible PC built in the last three years is powerful enough to store and edit video files. Apple's iMovie and Microsoft's Moviemaker are generally included with Apple and Windows operating systems. Also make sure you subscribe to a cable or DSL (broadband) Internet provider. Dial-up Internet service is too slow.</p>
        <p>2. BUY A VIDEO CAMERA -- The cheapest are webcams that can be mounted directly on your computer monitor; they cost $20 to $50. Mini-digital-video cameras cost $295 to $650. Panasonic, Canon, JVC, Sony, Samsung and Sanyo all make high-quality, easy-to-use models.</p>
        <p>3. BUY A DECENT MICROPHONE -- Though most video cameras and many webcams have built-in microphones, the quality does not come close to the sound recorded by a hand-held or wireless microphone. A popular and moderately priced hand-held microphone is the Shure SM58 Mic (about $100), which records professional quality sound. A good site on recording equipment is Musiciansfriend.com.</p>
        <p>4. UPLOAD TO A FILE-SHARING SITE -- The leader is YouTube. It requires you to have an account, which is free -- just follow the site's prompts. The same goes for uploading videos. It takes about a minute.</p>
        <p>KEITH SCHNEIDER</p>
        <p>FOR KEEPS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
