<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At the Local Abbey, Singing Unto the Lord an Old Song</title>
    <meta content="10chant" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/world/europe/10chant.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839280"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SOLESMES JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Solesmes (France)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tagliabue, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">France</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Roman Catholic Church</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905EFDD153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="859" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At the Local Abbey, Singing Unto the Lord an Old Song</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At the Local Abbey, Singing Unto the Lord an Old Song</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TAGLIABUE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tagliabue, John</byline>
      <dateline>SOLESMES, France, April 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Monks in Benedictine abbey in Solesmes, France, have gained measure of fame for their dedication to Gregorian chant; tourists flock to monastery church to listen to monks sing psalms and prayers of sacred liturgy; monks of Solesmes, ages 22 to 95, spend their days researching ancient Gregorian manuscripts, publishing updated texts and retaining Latin as language of their chanting; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the tasks of Roger Server as mayor of this quaint village in western France is to console misguided tourists who want to hear the monks in its 11th-century monastery singing in Gregorian chant. ''People come and ask, 'Can you visit the concerts?' ''</p>
        <p>Tourists are restricted to the back of the church, he said, shaking his white hair in mock exasperation. ''I tell them: 'You can visit at the offices. You can admire the sculptures in the church.' But the monks say, 'We're not here to receive tourists; we're contemplatives.' ''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tourists flock to an 11th-century monastery to hear Gregorian chant, bringing unwanted fame to the reclusive monks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of the tasks of Roger Server as mayor of this quaint village in western France is to console misguided tourists who want to hear the monks in its 11th-century monastery singing in Gregorian chant. ''People come and ask, 'Can you visit the concerts?' ''</p>
        <p>Tourists are restricted to the back of the church, he said, shaking his white hair in mock exasperation. ''I tell them: 'You can visit at the offices. You can admire the sculptures in the church.' But the monks say, 'We're not here to receive tourists; we're contemplatives.' ''</p>
        <p>The monks, 55 of them, inhabit the monastery that hovers over the village like some great granite mother hen over her chicks. But in recent times the monks have gained a measure of fame for their dedication to Gregorian chant, the simple vocal music whose cadences, in Latin, for centuries adorned the Roman Catholic liturgy.</p>
        <p>Now, a constant stream of visitors comes to Solesmes to sit in the monastery church and listen while the monks sing the psalms and prayers, seven times a day, of the sacred liturgy.</p>
        <p>''They want their calm,'' Mr. Server, 65, a retired schoolteacher, said of the monks. ''And after all, the monastery was there before us.''</p>
        <p>The monks' dedication to Gregorian chant dates to the 19th century, when the monastery was refounded as the Benedictine abbey of St. Pierre de Solesmes, after having been closed after the French Revolution.</p>
        <p>When it came to life again, in 1833, the monks resolved to restore Gregorian chant to its proper place in the church, after centuries of neglect. With time the papacy came to recognize Solesmes's role as the guardian and propagator of the chanting.</p>
        <p>''Monasteries have always been places where you conserved a patrimony in the church,'' said Dom YvesMarie Lelièvre, who left a career as a professional violinist to become a monk and the monastery's choirmaster.</p>
        <p>That mission was hurt in the 1960s by the Second Vatican Council, which opened up the liturgy to contemporary musical forms and a greater use of instruments. ''The council was an opening, an evolution,'' said Dom Lelièvre, 42, taking time between Holy Week services to receive a visitor. ''But after the council, parishes dropped Gregorian chant,'' he said, and deserted the Latin texts of the liturgy for the vernacular.</p>
        <p>But with the church's sanction, the monks of Solesmes, the oldest now 95, the youngest 22, remained faithful to their mission, spending their days researching ancient Gregorian manuscripts, publishing updated texts and retaining Latin as the language of their chanting.</p>
        <p>They were encouraged recently when Pope Benedict XVI, in a papal pronouncement known as an apostolic exhortation, decreed that -- especially at international gatherings -- the liturgies should be celebrated in Latin, except for the readings and the homily. Moreover, he said, ''If possible, selections of Gregorian chant should be sung.''</p>
        <p>Some saw the pope's remarks as a sop to traditionalists, like the followers of the schismatic Archbishop Marcel Lefèvre, who have steadfastly refused to accept the liturgical changes adopted by the Vatican council.</p>
        <p>Others saw the remarks as a slap in the face to contemporary church music, with its sometimes lively public participation. ''Exit the guitars and the xylophones,'' wrote Henri Tincq, Le Monde's Vatican correspondent, adding, ''Condemned are all 'abuses' in the adaptation of liturgies to local cultures.''</p>
        <p>Dom Lelièvre, a compact, friendly man who entered Solesmes 14 years ago, was naturally pleased with the pope's endorsement of Gregorian chant. Yet he said that Gregorian chant did not need the pope's support for revival.</p>
        <p>''Beginning 10 or 15 years ago in France, chant has regained interest in the musical milieu,'' he said, ''as have baroque music and medieval song.'' The monks of a Benedictine monastery in Spain, Santo Domingo de Silos, recorded several internationally popular CD's of Gregorian chant in the 1990s.</p>
        <p>Despite their cloistered life and flight from the world, the monks of Solesmes have accepted invitations to lecture and provide demonstrations at conservatories in Paris and other places.</p>
        <p>More recently other church choirs in France have begun to adopt Gregorian chant. In nearby Le Mans, the cathedral choir has begun using Gregorian chants, as has a church choir in Nantes.</p>
        <p>The mayor here is pleased that the growing interest is translating into a somewhat heavier flow of tourists. The monks, for their part, take in visitors in several monastery guesthouses, some for religious retreats, and are generally content with the flow of tourists, who recently have shown signs of better preparation for their visit.</p>
        <p>''Tourism has always existed,'' said Dom Lelièvre. ''Maybe it's more specific today. Before it was just a visit. Now there is less of that. Now there is more interest in discovering this way of life.''</p>
        <p>Most townspeople say relations between the village and the monks are good. Didier Guillot, a chauffeur who occasionally drives for the monks, recalls the kind of open house -- for men only, of course -- that the monks organize every year at Christmas for people they do business with. ''Electricians, plumbers, drivers, everyone who works for them is invited,'' he said. ''They are very agreeable.''</p>
        <p>He paused, then added, ''They are men of another age.''</p>
        <p>SOLESMES JOURNAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
