<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Captivating at Last, Mets Can Dare to Dream</title>
    <meta content="10roberts" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839348"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Selena Roberts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Philadelphia Phillies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E1DB153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Captivating at Last, Mets Can Dare to Dream</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The latest phase of the Mets' makeover is under way on a construction site about 600 feet from home plate, with Caterpillars soon to push aside an aging Shea Stadium that was born in the ''Flipper'' and ''Bewitched'' era, with cranes rising above Queens like index fingers as if to say, we're No. 1.</p>
        <p>Symbols of superiority and renewal are not misplaced in this case. The Mets have earned the confidence around what is, and the excitement over what will be, after having lived through an inferiority complex fed by forever playing Gilligan to Skipper in their race for respectability and relevance against the Yankees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The latest phase of the Mets' makeover is under way on a construction site about 600 feet from home plate, with Caterpillars soon to push aside an aging Shea Stadium that was born in the ''Flipper'' and ''Bewitched'' era, with cranes rising above Queens like index fingers as if to say, we're No. 1.</p>
        <p>Symbols of superiority and renewal are not misplaced in this case. The Mets have earned the confidence around what is, and the excitement over what will be, after having lived through an inferiority complex fed by forever playing Gilligan to Skipper in their race for respectability and relevance against the Yankees.</p>
        <p>Now the Mets have it all, too: a network to call their own; record attendance figures, including one for yesterday's rowdy 11-5 home-opening victory against the Phillies; a new stadium in the works; a Jeteresque pinup darling in David Wright; and a team assembled to win a World Series.</p>
        <p>Even in punishing the Phillies, the Mets did it in vintage Yankee style, patiently waiting out the starting pitching before devouring the bullpen in the kind of muscle flexing you'd see in the gym mirrors at Bally's.</p>
        <p>Is a display of Yankee vanity a sign of the Mets' ascent? Do they believe -- in a Stuart Smalley, self-affirmation way -- that they are good enough, smart enough and people like them?</p>
        <p>If so, the Mets should feel worthy enough to ask, ''Why not us?'' should Roger Clemens hit the sales rack. If so, they should feel free to join the conversation around Clemens to challenge old assumptions about the pecking order in New York.</p>
        <p>Certainly, Clemens has made his wish list clear: He will choose the Red Sox, Yankees or Astros when he revs up his 44-year-old wonder arm in May as he readies for re-entry in June.</p>
        <p>But if only to make a point about their market confidence, the Mets should make a pitch for the Rocket. Why not give him an alternative to think about? The Mets cannot offer Clemens the same full-circle of closure the Red Sox can; they cannot guarantee a hunting buddy on the roster like the Yankees' Andy Pettitte; they cannot compete with a mansion full of antlers, sons with names beginning in K and awards Clemens could go home to in Houston.</p>
        <p>But to a legendary pitcher noticeably fixated on his legacy, the Mets, in their current spirit of reinvention, can offer Clemens image reclamation and, more important, the best chance at another World Series ring.</p>
        <p>Clemens, in the eyes of Mets fans, is remembered for two things. First, knocking Mike Piazza nearly unconscious with a pitch to the head in 2000 interleague play and then turning the barrel of Piazza's broken bat into nunchucks during that World Series.</p>
        <p>But no player is left from the 2000 Mets. And fans slip in and out of loving and loathing with uniform changes. Clemens wouldn't have the comfort of Joe Torre, but he would see a familiar face in Willie Randolph.</p>
        <p>The Mets have a lot to offer. They have a mature pitching staff that can remember when MTV played music, a play-making defense to turn singles into outs and a potent offense to provide run support.</p>
        <p>In one home opener, the Mets unveiled a nice sales pitch. In the fifth inning, José Reyes displayed why he is one of baseball's most captivating players, with enough speed to beat out raindrops.</p>
        <p>That's basically what he did in the fifth inning when he launched a pop fly over the pitcher's mound. By the time the ball dropped from the blue sky, and in between two Phillies' gloves, Reyes was safe on the error -- and standing on second base. In the eighth inning, trailing by 5-4, the Mets put up runs as if hanging laundry, adding seven runs to the board.</p>
        <p>They can dominate like the Yankees. But what the Mets don't possess are the Yankee psychodramas. Instead of updates on the inner peace of Alex Rodriguez or uncertainties about the organization's hierarchy, instead of issues like the contract extension for Mariano Rivera or the whereabouts of Bernie Williams, the Mets are all but gathering around a bonfire.</p>
        <p>''Baseball is meant to be played with a smile,'' said Wright, adding, ''I've never been in the Yankee clubhouse, so I don't know about any psychodramas, but I know in this clubhouse we don't have cliques. We go to dinner together. It doesn't matter what nationality you are, what language you speak, who you are.''</p>
        <p>The Mets are as close to nirvana as Clemens could ask for unless, of course, he needs to be treated differently, requiring Rocket Rules. In that case, Clemens wouldn't be a fit for the Mets.</p>
        <p>But there is no harm in pursuing the idea, if only to validate the Mets position as a Yankee equal, with as much or more to offer a Hall of Fame pitcher looking for a glorious exit.</p>
        <p>In the midst of a makeover, enjoying what is and thrilled over what will be, the Mets have become a destination every bit as appealing as the Yankees, and an organization that should have the confidence to ask any legend with his heart set on pinstripes, ''Why not us?''</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: selenasports@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: selenasports@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
