<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Masters Champion, Life Is About to Change</title>
    <meta content="10golf" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/sports/golf/10golf.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839349"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Johnson, Zach</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E1DB153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="844" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Masters Champion, Life Is About to Change</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Life Is About to Change for Masters Champion</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK; Michael S. Schmidt contributed reporting from New York.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hack, Damon</byline>
      <dateline>AUGUSTA, Ga., April 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the morning after his cocktail party ran deep into the Georgia night, Zach Johnson was on a charter flight to New York with a size 40 regular green jacket and little sleep.</p>
        <p>Between the toasts and the tears that greeted his Masters victory Sunday and the coos and the cries of his 14-week-old son, Will, Johnson was a golfer thankful he had no more shots to play.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the wake of his unexpected victory, Zach Johnson will face demands, expectations and opportunities to cash in on his triumph.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the morning after his cocktail party ran deep into the Georgia night, Zach Johnson was on a charter flight to New York with a size 40 regular green jacket and little sleep.</p>
        <p>Between the toasts and the tears that greeted his Masters victory Sunday and the coos and the cries of his 14-week-old son, Will, Johnson was a golfer thankful he had no more shots to play.</p>
        <p>''I can count the sleep I've had in minutes,'' he said Monday in a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>In truth, Johnson will have many more shots to play, starting Thursday at the Heritage in Hilton Head Island, S.C., and for the rest of his career. Like many major champions before him who burst into prominence out of obscurity, Johnson will face more analysis and scrutiny than he did on Sunday's back nine at Augusta National, when, as he said Monday, ''I had nothing to lose.''</p>
        <p>There will be demands, expectations and opportunities to cash in on his triumph. There may be choices between practicing and making an appearance for a fee.</p>
        <p>No major winner lacks for attention in the aftermath of victory.</p>
        <p>On Monday, during a visit to the ''Late Show with David Letterman,'' an assistant with the show told Johnson that another guest wanted to meet him. It was Senator Barack Obama of Illinois.</p>
        <p>''I've got a great support system, starting with my wife and family, to my agent, my instructor and my mental coach,'' Johnson said when asked how he would handle his celebrity. ''It can be hard to say no. Unfortunately, at some point, I have to.''</p>
        <p>The transition for a new major champion is not always smooth.</p>
        <p>Todd Hamilton, after a decade playing the Japan Golf Tour, captured the 2004 British Open for his second PGA Tour victory, but he has not won since. In 2005, he missed 14 of 31 cuts; in 2006, he missed 19 of 27. (He has missed eight of nine cuts this year.)</p>
        <p>Shaun Micheel, since winning the 2003 P.G.A. Championship, has also not won a PGA Tour event. He fell to 146th on the money list in 2005 before rebounding to 46th last year.</p>
        <p>''It's tough trying to keep up with your own expectations, let alone the expectations other people have for you,'' he said last year.</p>
        <p>Ben Curtis, who won the 2003 British Open when he was ranked 396th, went three years before winning again on the PGA Tour.</p>
        <p>In some ways, the 31-year-old Johnson may be better equipped than any of them to handle his elevated status.</p>
        <p>His career has been a steady climb from Cedar Rapids, Iowa, to the Prairie Golf Tour, to the Nationwide Tour, to the PGA Tour, to the United States Ryder Cup team, to a major champion.</p>
        <p>''This isn't going to change Zach one bit,'' said Larry Gladson, the head professional at Elmcrest Country Club in Cedar Rapids, where he began working with Johnson when he was 10.</p>
        <p>Gladson flew from Moline, Ill., to Atlanta at 5:30 a.m. Sunday and arrived at Augusta National just before lunch to watch Johnson win by two strokes.</p>
        <p>''When he first started having success, becoming Nationwide Tour player of the year, winning the BellSouth Classic, he told me all along that this won't change who Zach Johnson is,'' Gladson said in a telephone interview. ''His schedule will get intensified and he'll have to make more choices, but he will be the same kid.''</p>
        <p>Johnson, who is 5 feet 11 inches, was undersized as a junior golfer and was often overpowered by peers who were not as fundamentally sound, Gladson said.</p>
        <p>In an echo of his youth, Johnson laid up on Augusta National's par-5 holes for four days and still played them in 11 under par.</p>
        <p>''In our era, it's definitely the biggest golf story in Iowa,'' said Steve Riley, the head professional at Sunnyside Country Club in Waterloo, Iowa, who met Johnson when he was 14. ''He's so motivated, and I just think he has things in the right perspective. He's won at every level that he's played in. It was always just a matter of getting comfortable. He's learning how to adapt.''</p>
        <p>Johnson said: ''Goal setting will never stop. I will continue to work hard and practice hard and see where things go. There's no reason I will stop here.</p>
        <p>''The most interesting thing about this week was I played well, but I felt like I left shots out there. Given that, there is still potential to make things more polished.''</p>
        <p>But, first, there was some play time Monday. Johnson and his wife, Kim, made the rounds on television and radio in New York.</p>
        <p>Unsure how much he should wear his green jacket in public -- he said he did not want to offend Augusta National's members -- Johnson arrived at the ESPN Zone in Times Square and hung it on a chair with a white trash bag around it.</p>
        <p>''We don't have a garment bag,'' Kim said. ''We didn't plan on winning the Masters.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
