<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rangers Hope Experience and Discipline Can Offset the Thrashers' Firepower</title>
    <meta content="10rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/sports/hockey/10rangers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839390"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Atlanta Thrashers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Atlanta Thrashers</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE4DA153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="803" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rangers Hope Experience and Discipline Can Offset the Thrashers' Firepower</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rangers Hope Poise Can Offset Thrashers’ Power</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinser, Lynn</byline>
      <dateline>GREENBURGH, N.Y., April 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The matchup between the Rangers and the Thrashers in the first round of the playoffs is a study in contrasts. One team, the Rangers, is a tradition-rich Original Six franchise, the other an expansion team dropped into the market in 1999. The Rangers are a veteran group that sprinkled in some youth as the season went along, while a young Atlanta team imported experience at the trading deadline.</p>
        <p>And while the Thrashers have lived on their offensive firepower, the Rangers are a defense-first team that has frequently won, or lost, by 2-1 scores.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the defense-minded Rangers face off against the firepower of the Thrashers, the playoff series will likely swing on which style can prevail.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The matchup between the Rangers and the Thrashers in the first round of the playoffs is a study in contrasts. One team, the Rangers, is a tradition-rich Original Six franchise, the other an expansion team dropped into the market in 1999. The Rangers are a veteran group that sprinkled in some youth as the season went along, while a young Atlanta team imported experience at the trading deadline.</p>
        <p>And while the Thrashers have lived on their offensive firepower, the Rangers are a defense-first team that has frequently won, or lost, by 2-1 scores.</p>
        <p>The series, which starts Thursday in Atlanta, will most likely swing on which team can impose its style on the other.</p>
        <p>''They are a strange team to play,'' Rangers forward Jaromir Jagr said. ''They're like a snake. They make you sleep and they jump. They've got so much power, they just hit you with three goals with the skill they have.</p>
        <p>''You have to be ready for that. I think you just have to play your game, don't adjust to their game.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers lost three of their four regular-season games against Atlanta, two of them in overtime.</p>
        <p>But the Rangers have also remade their playing style over the course of the season, changing from a team susceptible to offensive onslaughts into one that learned how to clamp down. Atlanta scored four more goals than the Rangers this season, 246 to 242, and gave up 245. The Rangers finished second to the Devils in the Eastern Conference in goals allowed with 216.</p>
        <p>That is a big reason the Rangers carry some confidence into the playoffs. Since the beginning of March, they have played 13 games decided by one goal, winning seven.</p>
        <p>''Playoffs are about how you handle those situations, the pressure situations,'' forward Brendan Shanahan said. ''Do you stay disciplined and take a punch in the face or a slash in the wrists? And we've basically been doing that for the last month and a half. We couldn't afford mental lapses.''</p>
        <p>The Thrashers have not avoided mental lapses so much as they have overcome them by scoring goals. They have two players, Marian Hossa and Ilya Kovalchuk, who have scored more than 40 goals. They have two, Hossa and Vyacheslav Kozlov, with more than 50 assists.</p>
        <p>To make up for their lack of experience, the Thrashers acquired the veteran forwards Keith Tkachuk and Éric Bélanger at the trading deadline. They upgraded a lackluster defense with the veteran defenseman Alexei Zhitnik.</p>
        <p>Still, the heart of the Thrashers is their offense.</p>
        <p>''They will use their attributes to their advantage,'' Rangers Coach Tom Renney said. ''If their forward group is not forced to defend, forced to come 200 feet, forced to play through some duress, they can be daunting. We have to make sure we don't give them the freedom to do what they want to do.''</p>
        <p>The teams even have contrasting Hossa brothers. The Thrashers' Marian, 28, was the early superstar, with 270 goals in eight seasons in the N.H.L. The Rangers' Marcel, 25, has come into his own this season. He was added to the top line midway through the season and has 10 goals.</p>
        <p>Marcel Hossa missed the last 16 games of the regular season with a knee injury. He is expected back for Thursday's game and will probably play alongside Jagr and center Michael Nylander in the series opener.</p>
        <p>Marcel Hossa's scouting report on his brother sounds pretty much like everyone else's.</p>
        <p>''Everybody knows he's a great player,'' he said of Marian. ''Anybody who is on the ice against him has got to play pretty good defense. He's very good one on one, a good skater. Everybody knows they have a great offense. You've got to be alert.''</p>
        <p>While the Thrashers are trying to make the most of the franchise's first playoff appearance, the Rangers are trying to win a playoff game for the first time in 10 years. Last season, their playoffs consisted of four consecutive losses to the Devils.</p>
        <p>The remaking of the Rangers started in the off-season with the signing of Shanahan and center Matt Cullen, both winners of the Stanley Cup who added toughness as well as experience. The transition was still evolving late in the season, with a kick provided by the deadline deal that brought in forward Sean Avery, 26, and installed two rookies, forward Ryan Callahan and defenseman Dan Girardi, in the lineup.</p>
        <p>''I think good teams always have a balance,'' Shanahan said. ''You can't have a team full of experienced guys and you can't have a team full of young guys. I think this is a very balanced team: some guys that have been there a few times and some that are getting their very first taste.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers are hoping their mix trumps the Thrashers' offense-first formula.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
