<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Shea Stadium, Police Choose a Crime-Fighting Perch 20 Feet Above the Crowd</title>
    <meta content="10towers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/nyregion/10towers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070412T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839338"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Surveillance of Citizens by Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveillance of Citizens by Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE3DB153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Shea Stadium, Police Choose a Crime-Fighting Perch 20 Feet Above the Crowd</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At Shea Stadium, Police Choose Perch 20 Feet Above Crowd</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS J. LUECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lueck, Thomas J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From his perch in a metal box 20 feet above Parking Lot A at Shea Stadium yesterday, Officer Abelardo Solano used a joystick to point one of five digital cameras, first at someone's face then at a license plate, across several acres of parked cars. Both came into passable focus.</p>
        <p>''It allows you to see over a large area,'' said Chief Carlos Gomez, a Police Department executive officer for northern Queens, who estimated that the camera was capturing images 300 yards away. He had joined Officer Solano in one of the five sky watchtowers that are being used by the department to provide better surveillance capability, and a highly visible police presence at public events, busy intersections or high-crime sites.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The sky watchtower has taken its place on the streets of New York as a highly visible police presence at public events, busy intersections or high-crime sites.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From his perch in a metal box 20 feet above Parking Lot A at Shea Stadium yesterday, Officer Abelardo Solano used a joystick to point one of five digital cameras, first at someone's face then at a license plate, across several acres of parked cars. Both came into passable focus.</p>
        <p>''It allows you to see over a large area,'' said Chief Carlos Gomez, a Police Department executive officer for northern Queens, who estimated that the camera was capturing images 300 yards away. He had joined Officer Solano in one of the five sky watchtowers that are being used by the department to provide better surveillance capability, and a highly visible police presence at public events, busy intersections or high-crime sites.</p>
        <p>''Everybody knows we are here,'' Chief Gomez said. ''It makes people feel at ease.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps, but not everyone at Shea yesterday for the Mets home opener agreed.</p>
        <p>''I think that thing is ridiculous,'' said Angela Giannotti, who was tailgating nearby with friends. She pointed out that more than 20,000 parking spaces had been lost at the stadium this year because of construction. ''Here we have this thing taking up 19 more spaces.''</p>
        <p>Elsewhere in the city, where the towers have been deployed for parades and festivals, and on blocks known as magnets for drug dealing, some residents caution that they may be seen as an intimidating police presence and harm community relations.</p>
        <p>''You are never going to please everybody,'' Police Commissioner Raymond W. Kelly said in a phone interview. ''But by and large, people appreciate a police presence.''</p>
        <p>No matter whether the public is completely won over, the police tower at Shea reflected growing confidence among Mr. Kelly and other police officials in a device that may appear better suited to stocking the upper shelves of an industrial warehouse than controlling crowds and preventing crime. Originally designed for deer hunters in Georgia, the towers have been used by the military and police departments across the country over the last decade.</p>
        <p>''Knowing that someone from the police is up there keeping an eye out tends to encourage those who would do no good to go elsewhere,'' said Don Aaron, a spokesman for the Metropolitan Nashville Police Department, which has been using one of the towers for a year.</p>
        <p>In New York, the presence of a tower at the Mets home opener came at a time when two others have been bought, and are being painted with the department's insignia before being deployed. Mr. Kelly said the two new towers will replace the two that are now being leased, and that the department had no plans to own or operate more than five of the towers.</p>
        <p>The towers combine advanced electronics along with pre-World War II hydraulics technology. Mounted on a trailer that is towed around the city, each of the towers has a metal cab that is lifted as high as 24 feet by a hydraulic motor once the entire tower is fixed in place.</p>
        <p>Operating the tower is not complicated.</p>
        <p>''It took five minutes to learn,'' Officer Solano said yesterday, as he pressed a lever and the cab began lowering with an unsettling jerk from its elevated perch to the pavement. Beside him in the cab was a video screen displaying an unbroken stream of video images from five mounted cameras, which police officials say operate continuously while the tower is in use.</p>
        <p>The surveillance technology, similar to what is used by the police and business owners elsewhere in the city, has been criticized by the New York Civil Liberties Union, where lawyers have charged the police with invading people's privacy and retaining images of innocent bystanders for years.</p>
        <p>''One wonders if baseball fans at Shea now have reasons to wonder if their innocent fun at the ball park will end up as images in a police archive,'' said Donna Lieberman, the group's executive director. But Mr. Kelly said yesterday that only images used in arrests and as court evidence would be saved, and that the cameras of the police towers are designed to record over unsaved images.</p>
        <p>Chief Gomez, who ordered the use of the tower at Shea yesterday, said that it was a one-day assignment, and that the tower would frequently be used at other locations.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, the towers have been assigned outside the Jacob K. Javits Convention Center in Manhattan during the New York auto show and to Flushing Meadows-Corona Park in Queens, where a string of robberies took place in December.</p>
        <p>One of the towers was also set up in December at 110th Street and Lexington Avenue, a corner that the police say is known for drug activity, and its presence did not sit well with East Harlem Councilwoman Melissa Mark-Viverito. She wrote to Mr. Kelly, describing the tower as ''eerily reminiscent of a jailhouse turret,'' and said in an interview that police resources would better be spent on foot patrols.</p>
        <p>''We need to build community relations, and these things send the wrong message,'' she said. ''There should be interaction on the street, instead of towering over people.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Kelly said Ms. Mark-Viverito's complaint was the only one he had heard. ''The feedback we have gotten is very positive,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 12, 2007, Thursday  An article on Tuesday about the New York Police Department's use of a surveillance watchtower in a parking lot at Shea Stadium during the Mets' home opener misstated the number of parking spaces that have been lost at the stadium this year because of construction -- a point raised by a fan who complained about the tower taking up parking spaces. About 2,100 have been lost, not 20,000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 12, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article on Tuesday about the New York Police Department's use of a surveillance watchtower in a parking lot at Shea Stadium during the Mets' home opener misstated the number of parking spaces that have been lost at the stadium this year because of construction -- a point raised by a fan who complained about the tower taking up parking spaces. About 2,100 have been lost, not 20,000.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
