<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Last There's Time to Defend the Barricades</title>
    <meta content="10protest" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Retirement" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Job Market; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/business/retirement/10protest.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839400"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GETTING INVOLVED"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Dirk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Northern Illinois University</org>
        <org class="online_producer">AARP</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E0DA153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1185" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Last There's Time to Defend the Barricades</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">To the Barricades, Oldsters of the Republic</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Dirk</byline>
      <dateline>DEKALB, Ill.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Retirement for many older Americans means chance to devote themselves to social and political causes; they have time, and since they no longer need to worry about employers, they can speak without fear of repercussions; retirees represent potent force in political movements of every stripe and are likely to become even more important as number of older people increase; photos (special section, Retirement) (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is a Friday afternoon in this college town on the prairie, and the demonstrators at First Street and Lincoln Highway are raising a political ruckus. Some hoist signs that declare, ''Stop the War!'' But across the street, people are waving signs with other messages -- ''Support the Troops'' and ''Danger: Traitors'' -- gibing at the antiwar contingent.</p>
        <p>Whatever their politics, a big share of the demonstrators on both sides of the street have one thing in common: retirement. Although this is the home of Northern Illinois University, with an enrollment of nearly 25,000, it is the retirees, far more than the students, who are taking to the streets to chant slogans and sing political anthems.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the number of older Americans grows, retirement for many means a chance to devote themselves to social and political causes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is a Friday afternoon in this college town on the prairie, and the demonstrators at First Street and Lincoln Highway are raising a political ruckus. Some hoist signs that declare, ''Stop the War!'' But across the street, people are waving signs with other messages -- ''Support the Troops'' and ''Danger: Traitors'' -- gibing at the antiwar contingent.</p>
        <p>Whatever their politics, a big share of the demonstrators on both sides of the street have one thing in common: retirement. Although this is the home of Northern Illinois University, with an enrollment of nearly 25,000, it is the retirees, far more than the students, who are taking to the streets to chant slogans and sing political anthems.</p>
        <p>''People in cars drive by and wave at us,'' said Cele Meyer, 84, a retired social worker who opposes the war. ''Sometimes they use two fingers. Sometimes just one.''</p>
        <p>As the number of older Americans grows, retirement for many of them means a chance to devote themselves to social and political causes. They have the time, and since they no longer need to worry about employers, they can speak out without fear of repercussions. Retirees represent a potent force in political movements of every stripe and are likely to become even more important as the number of older people increases.</p>
        <p>Jerry Thompson, 71, a retired college-newspaper adviser, stands with the camp in DeKalb favoring military action in Iraq. ''It wouldn't have been appropriate for me to do this when I was a newspaper person,'' said Mr. Thompson, who worked as a reporter and editor before joining the college.</p>
        <p>But now he is liberated to show his conservative leanings. In retirement, Mr. Thompson became a Republican precinct captain and a village trustee. He also writes letters to editors calling for tax limits.</p>
        <p>On the other side of the spectrum, Marilyn Kawakami, 64, a retired executive in the fashion industry, became so disillusioned with the war that she found herself ''talking back to the TV at President Bush.''</p>
        <p>She now spends much of her time volunteering for the liberal group MoveOn.org. She makes phone calls, gathers signatures for petitions and even cleans up after political rallies.</p>
        <p>''I look at myself in the mirror sometimes and wonder where she came from,'' Ms. Kawakami said. ''But we're at a period in our lives where it's time to give back. As jaded and cynical as I am, I still think that we in America are the good guys, the guys in the white hats.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile in New Hampshire, Maureen Barrows, is working hard to advance the presidential cause there of Senator John McCain, Republican of Arizona. She had met him four years ago on a campaign stop, sensed ''an instant rapport'' and decided he was the right candidate to lead the nation.</p>
        <p>''As people get older, they get more selective about what is paramount,'' said Mrs. Barrows, 70. ''And maybe it's because I've now got two little grandchildren, but I think we're coming up on the most important election of my time.''</p>
        <p>Conservative or liberal, many older Americans are fighting for a cause, sometimes quietly, sometimes with bullhorns. Politicians know well that older people are more likely to visit the voting booth than their younger counterparts are. But sometimes it goes far beyond voting and recalls the tie-dyed demonstrations of long ago. For instance, members of the Granny Peace Brigade have been arrested in New York and Philadelphia in the last year in connection with protests over military recruitment.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bill Pinsoff of the Family Institute at Northwestern University, said that retirement offered many people a chance to reshape their imprint on the world.</p>
        <p>''Retirement represents an opportunity for spiritual or psychological rebirth or renaissance,'' said Dr. Pinsoff. ''In many cases, people engage in activities that have been long postponed. People who have devoted their lives to making money now have the opportunity to work for what they believe in.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Phyllis Moen, a sociologist at the University of Minnesota, has written that Americans in the 21st century are witnessing the creation of a new life stage. ''Just as we have seen the social construction of adolescence as a way station from childhood to adulthood during the first half of the 20th century, there is now emerging a life stage between the years of career building and old age,'' she wrote. She calls this stage ''midcourse.''</p>
        <p>These are people roughly from age 50 to 75 who choose to scale back on careers, switch careers or leave the workforce. Many of them are healthy, wealthy and wise, and bring plenty of talents and experiences to whatever cause they follow.</p>
        <p>The political clout of older people is scarcely a secret. One of the most powerful lobbies in America is AARP, which claims a membership of some 38 million people over 50, said Shereen Remez, a top official for the group. But nearly half of these ''retired'' people are still working, Ms. Remez added.</p>
        <p>''The very word 'retirement' has taken on new meaning,'' she said. ''Now work -- maybe a new career -- is part of retirement.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Remez said that AARP had an ''e-active list'' of about five million people at the ready to help push causes supported by the group. ''Look back at what they were doing in the '60s -- on the Vietnam War, on feminism, on civil rights,'' Ms. Remez said. ''Now the leading edge of boomers is in their 60s, and it's just natural that they want to stay active in the affairs of the world.''</p>
        <p>In DeKalb, activism is inspired by all sorts of earlier events. Mrs. Meyer, a former marine who was raised in the segregated South, would seem to have an unlikely background for a radical. When she was a child in Florida, she recalled, her parents would not let blacks enter the house. She joined the military at age 21 out of a sense of duty to defend America, which had been attacked at Pearl Harbor just a few years earlier.</p>
        <p>While in the service, she read ''Native Son'' by Richard Wright, a book that brought home to her the cruelties visited upon blacks in American society.</p>
        <p>In the years since, much of her life has been given over to protesting what she perceives as injustices. In DeKalb, she founded the Interfaith Network for Peace and Justice. The group has raised money for the poor in Nicaragua, staged a protest during a visit to the town by Vice President Dick Cheney and rallied against the war outside the offices of the local representative, J. Dennis Hastert, the former speaker of the House.</p>
        <p>''I was physically dragged out of Hastert's office,'' Mrs. Meyer said with a triumphant chuckle.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson, the former newspaperman, said that his group also wanted the war in Iraq done and the troops safely back home. He noted, too, that his fellow conservatives have grown frustrated at the length of the war and its rocky course.</p>
        <p>Despite the words that were sometimes exchanged during the Friday protest and counterprotest, all the demonstrators said they celebrated the right of their foes to speak.</p>
        <p>The rocking chairs can wait.</p>
        <p>GETTING INVOLVED</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
