<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Searching for Mat Glory In a Sweaty Gym in Iowa</title>
    <meta content="10sand" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/books/10sand.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839248"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wrestling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wrestling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Four Days to Glory: Wrestling With the Soul of the American Heartland (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403EFDE153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="823" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Searching for Mat Glory In a Sweaty Gym in Iowa</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Searching for Mat Glory in a Sweaty Gym in Iowa</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four Days to Glory  Wrestling With the Soul of the American Heartland  By Mark Kreidler  Illustrated. 262 pages. HarperCollins. $24.95.</p>
        <p>At the 2000 Summer Olympics in Sydney, a 119-pound American wrestler named Sammie Henson reacted to a close loss by fleeing the stage, keening as if in the deepest emotional pain, and flinging himself to the floor under the hall's bleachers, sobbing and rocking on his back. Even as Mr. Henson accepted his silver medal, his face was etched in utter grief.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In this extraordinary look at several months in the singular culture of amateur wrestling, there are no big stadiums, no March Madness, no payday. Just plenty of determination.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Four Days to Glory  Wrestling With the Soul of the American Heartland  By Mark Kreidler  Illustrated. 262 pages. HarperCollins. $24.95.</p>
        <p>At the 2000 Summer Olympics in Sydney, a 119-pound American wrestler named Sammie Henson reacted to a close loss by fleeing the stage, keening as if in the deepest emotional pain, and flinging himself to the floor under the hall's bleachers, sobbing and rocking on his back. Even as Mr. Henson accepted his silver medal, his face was etched in utter grief.</p>
        <p>I had forgotten that pitiful, wrenching scene until ''Four Days to Glory: Wrestling With the Soul of the American Heartland'' reminded me of the passion the sport is capable of inspiring at high schools in Iowa, where families and communities are defined by wrestling tournaments in sweaty gyms; where teenage boys, like female gymnasts, starve to make weight; and where boys as young as 5 are groomed to hope for future mat glory.</p>
        <p>It is a sport, Mark Kreidler writes in this extraordinary look at several months in the singular culture of Iowa wrestling, where teenagers ''pound their bodies until they scream, and sweat out boxes worth of salt; they push their muscles somewhere beyond whatever they may have imagined as the snapping point.'' He adds, ''And they do all of this, or at least most of it, absent the expectation that anyone in particular will applaud or even really notice.''</p>
        <p>Most of the world is barely aware of the amateur wrestling described by Mr. Kreidler. Great interest is paid to the sport's satanically possessed stepbrother: the scripted, costumed and slick-chested professionals of Vince McMahon's World Wrestling Entertainment, whose stars write best-selling memoirs (Steve Austin), become action movie hunks (The Rock) or get elected governor of Minnesota (Jesse Ventura).</p>
        <p>The wrestlers in ''Four Days to Glory'' will not achieve fame outside their state, or fortune, at least not from looking to pin opponents. But they are as captivating -- if not nearly as outrageous and absurd -- as if they were seeking toeholds and takedowns inside a steel cage at Madison Square Garden instead of gymnasiums in eastern Iowa.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kreidler structures ''Four Days to Glory'' around the parallel quests by two senior wrestlers, Jay Borschel, from outside Cedar Rapids, and Dan LeClere, a farm boy from rural Coggon, to win their fourth consecutive high school state championships. Only 14 other Iowans had done it, a nearly impossible achievement given the growth patterns of adolescent bodies, injuries, luck, nerves, tournament draws and the 8,600 other wrestlers accompanying Mr. Borschel and Mr. LeClere on a journey ''right on through hell, an extended stay replete with wind sprints and projectile vomiting and blood and contortionist acts and stinging, salty sweat.''</p>
        <p>But this book covers more than the stories of these two wrestlers; it is about their teammates and their families, whose lives revolve around their sons' matches and practices. It is about the living deity Dan Gable, the Olympic gold medalist who is the great evangelist of amateur wrestling. And it is about Mr. Borschel and Mr. LeClere's surprise decisions to defect from the heart of wrestling to attend college at Virginia Tech, not the University of Iowa.</p>
        <p>In their own way, Mr. Kreidler's portraits are as incisive as those in Buzz Bissinger's ''Friday Night Lights,'' which offered a similar look into the world of Texas high-school football.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kreidler's deftness in ''Four Days'' is in turning a niche sport into one as accessible as baseball or basketball. It doesn't take place in major stadiums. There is no March Madness. There are no big paydays being dangled to four-time champions. He understands that readers want close-up portraits of athletes who've been through a crucible -- which doesn't mean wearing a bridal gown like Dennis Rodman. Those who wrestle are hurt by design, the same goal as in boxing and football. And anyone familiar with Nascar knows that fans are entranced by incendiary crashes even if they prefer that their drivers emerge from their stock cars without a scratch.</p>
        <p>For a winning wrestler, Mr. Kreidler writes, ''There is no quality of mercy.''</p>
        <p>''Four Days'' teems with great match descriptions and knowing details of Mr. Borschel's and Mr. LeClere's family lives, from how Mr. LeClere teases his mother to the portrait of the central character in his family: Doug, who is too obsessed and too invested in his four sons' wrestling, who cannot understand the depression that chased his eldest boy from what he calls the ''family business'' and who, as assistant coach of Dan's team, still wrestles with teenagers.</p>
        <p>At one point, Doug takes on Dan, body-on-body, on a mat, his weight keeping Dan from escaping, until the son elbowed his father in the eye, and the father punched his son right back. ''This was a father and a son going at it,'' Mr. Kreidler writes, ''sprawling and brawling around the mat, venting months and years of whatever was bottled up inside.''</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
