<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Couple's Killing in 1992 Is Focus of New Mob Trial</title>
    <meta content="10mob" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/nyregion/10mob.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839354"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07EEDB153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="902" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Couple's Killing in 1992 Is Focus of New Mob Trial</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Couple’s Killing in 1992 Is Focus of New Mob Trial</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. RASHBAUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rashbaum, William K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The piece of paper is, by any measure, an insignificant artifact that sheds little light on organized crime's 100-year reign in New York: It bears a list of names and telephone numbers that prosecutors contend was scrawled by one Joseph Delmonico, an aging mob figure who investigators say retains little of the influence he once held over the Gambino crime family.</p>
        <p>The list will nonetheless be entered into evidence in United States District Court in Brooklyn in the coming days to help prove that a young married couple from Queens embarked on one of the most ill-advised crime sprees in city history: robbing a series of mob social clubs armed with an Uzi submachine gun and what can only be described as a poor grasp of their own mortality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A federal trial now getting under way is expected to shed light on the 1992 killings of a young couple from Queens who robbed a series of mob social clubs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The piece of paper is, by any measure, an insignificant artifact that sheds little light on organized crime's 100-year reign in New York: It bears a list of names and telephone numbers that prosecutors contend was scrawled by one Joseph Delmonico, an aging mob figure who investigators say retains little of the influence he once held over the Gambino crime family.</p>
        <p>The list will nonetheless be entered into evidence in United States District Court in Brooklyn in the coming days to help prove that a young married couple from Queens embarked on one of the most ill-advised crime sprees in city history: robbing a series of mob social clubs armed with an Uzi submachine gun and what can only be described as a poor grasp of their own mortality.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, the robberies ended with the 1992 slayings of the couple, Thomas and Rosemarie Uva. The killings seemed to close out an episode that caused the mob more than a little embarrassment, since such establishments had long been deemed sanctuaries where crime figures sipped coffee, played cards and schemed.</p>
        <p>Perhaps that is why the killings, during the morning rush on Christmas Eve, had the air of a public execution. Mr. and Mrs. Uva were both shot in the head as they sat in his red 1990 four-door Mercury Topaz at a traffic light at 103rd Avenue and Woodhaven Boulevard in Ozone Park, Queens, a neighborhood where the Gambinos had long held sway.</p>
        <p>Now the killings are the focus of a federal murder and racketeering trial set to begin today before Judge Jack B. Weinstein.</p>
        <p>No one had been charged in the killings, long one of organized crime's mysteries, until nearly two years ago when the F.B.I. arrested Dominick Pizzonia, 65. Prosecutors say he is a Gambino captain whose social club on Liberty Avenue was among those the couple robbed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pizzonia is also charged in the case with the 1988 killing of Frank Boccia, and with gambling and loansharking. A co-defendant, Alfred DiCongilio, 77, is also charged in Mr. Boccia's slaying.</p>
        <p>John A. Gotti, once the Gambino crime family acting boss and long the subject of federal authorities' quiet accusations of having a role in ordering the double killing, was officially named as a co-conspirator in the case for the first time yesterday. The prosecutors, Joey Lipton and Paige Peterson, assistant United States attorneys, made the allegation in a letter to Judge Weinstein, but they did not elaborate.</p>
        <p>No charges have been brought against Mr. Gotti in the killings, and in fact federal prosecutors in Manhattan acknowledged at his unrelated trial last year that he was unaware of the killings until they were committed. Mr. Gotti, through his lawyers, has long denied any role in the killings.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pizzonia's lawyer, Joseph Corozzo, has maintained his client's innocence and has said he will defend him aggressively.</p>
        <p>Mr. Delmonico's list, a veritable who's who of the Gambino family, was recovered days after the Uvas' killings, when the police searched the couple's Queens apartment, law enforcement officials have said. The police were told after the killings that it had been folded up inside Mr. Delmonico's wallet, which had been taken from him in a robbery.</p>
        <p>Court records indicate that it will be entered into evidence at the trial, along with samples of the 86-year-old Mr. Delmonico's handwriting, and testimony by an F.B.I. handwriting expert who is expected to tell the jury that it was written by Mr. Delmonico.</p>
        <p>To establish a motive for killing the couple, prosecutors want to show the jury that they committed the robberies. The number of robberies has varied in different accounts, as some law enforcement officials have it at about 6 and a lawyer involved in the case at as many as 10. The final tally remains uncertain, largely because none of the victims were inclined to report the robberies to the police.</p>
        <p>Several law enforcement officials have said that in addition to at least two Gambino clubs, the couple robbed clubs belonging to the Bonanno family, with Mrs. Uva, 31, driving the getaway car and her husband, 28, wielding the Uzi.</p>
        <p>Several Mafia turncoats are set to testify at the trial, including at least two who are expected to tell the jury about what they have described as a dispute between the Bonanno and Gambino family bosses over which family killed the Uvas and put an end to the embarrassing robberies. According to F.B.I. documents, both families eventually agreed that the Gambinos did it, specifically Mr. Pizzonia and another mob figure, Ronald Trucchio.</p>
        <p>Much of the testimony about the killings at the trial, which is expected to last several weeks, will be second-hand accounts from Mafia turncoats who will recount what they were told.</p>
        <p>One veteran investigator who has tracked the crime for more than a decade noted that for years, little was known about the robberies because they were discussed so little.</p>
        <p>''It was pretty hush-hush,'' the investigator said. ''They didn't want to talk about it because they were embarrassed. It was a pretty quiet thing.''</p>
        <p>Another investigator with knowledge of the case said a story had made the rounds inside some organized crime circles that Mr. Uva, during one of the robberies, messed up the hair of an elder Gambino soldier, humiliating him in front of his confederates.</p>
        <p>''You don't mess with a wiseguy's hair,'' the investigator said. ''That adds insult to injury.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
