<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Caroming Into a Second Career in the Land of Green Felt</title>
    <meta content="10casino" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Retirement" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Job Market" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/business/retirement/10casino.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839402"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ACT 2"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Older Workers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Las Vegas (Nev)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Station Casinos Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Foxwoods Resort Casino</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Villano, Matt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murzl, Valerie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Human Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nevada/Las Vegas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nevada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Las Vegas (Nev)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EFDA153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="956" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Caroming Into a Second Career in the Land of Green Felt</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Caroming Into a Second Career in the Land of Green Felt</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT VILLANO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Villano, Matt</byline>
      <dateline>LAS VEGAS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Increasing number of retirees have embarked on second careers as casino ticket writers, card dealers, even floor managers as $85 billion casino industry has grown in recent years; Valerie Murzl, corporate vice president for human resources at Station Casinos, company that operates 11 casinos in and around Las Vegas, says 1,500 of company's 15,000 employees are over 50; more than 1,200 of 10,000 employees at Foxwoods in Connecticut are over age 59; photos (special section, Retirement) (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BILL SHEIKEWITZ has always loved being part of the action.</p>
        <p>So after almost 40 years working various jobs on the trading floor of the New York Stock Exchange, Mr. Sheikewitz recently retired, moved here and began a second career in a fast and furious environment that involves wagers of a different kind: a casino.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the growth of the casino industry, an increasing number of retirees are working as ticket writers, card dealers, even floor managers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BILL SHEIKEWITZ has always loved being part of the action.</p>
        <p>So after almost 40 years working various jobs on the trading floor of the New York Stock Exchange, Mr. Sheikewitz recently retired, moved here and began a second career in a fast and furious environment that involves wagers of a different kind: a casino.</p>
        <p>Today, as what's called a ticket writer, Mr. Sheikewitz, 61, sits behind a giant counter in the sports book at the Red Rock Casino, Resort and Spa in nearby Summerlin, Nev., and takes wagers on sports. He said that while the atmosphere was much tamer than Wall Street's, there were enough similarities to make him feel right at home.</p>
        <p>''In my new job I'm counting out thousands and thousands of dollars at times, and in that respect, it's almost like someone coming in and buying 100 shares of I.B.M.,'' said Mr. Sheikewitz, who had worked his way up to director of floor operations at the exchange before retiring in 2003. ''Who knew retirement could be so fun?''</p>
        <p>As the $85 billion casino industry has grown in recent years, an increasing number of retirees have embarked on second careers as ticket writers, card dealers, even floor managers.</p>
        <p>While no national organization keeps track of how many casino employees have retired from other jobs, figures from individual gambling corporations indicate that older faces are becoming more prevalent.</p>
        <p>Valerie Murzl, corporate vice president for human resources at Station Casinos, the company that operates Red Rock and 10 other casinos in and around Las Vegas, said 1,500 of the company's 15,000 employees were over 50. Many of these people, she said, ''worked years in other jobs before coming to us.''</p>
        <p>Closer to New York, at Foxwoods in Mashantucket, Conn., the numbers are similar -- more than 1,200 of 10,000 employees are over age 59, said Steve Heise, vice president for human resources.</p>
        <p>Mr. Heise said these second-career workers were a great benefit to the casino because, for the most part, they were hard-working, reliable and personable.</p>
        <p>''We find that people who have been around the block a while have a great work ethic and a real sense of ownership of the business as a whole,'' he said. ''It doesn't hurt that they're good role models for our younger folks, finishing up one career and coming here to start another.''</p>
        <p>For Wayne Lubin, a dealer at Foxwoods since 2001, the transition from his first career was easy. He simply followed a dream.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lubin, 62, was a veterinarian from 1969 until his retirement in 1998. With endless hours of free time, Mr. Lubin said, he started thinking about how he wanted to spend the next phase of his life. That's when it dawned on him -- he always had enjoyed the casino environment, so why not try to work there?</p>
        <p>''All my life I wanted to be a blackjack dealer,'' he said. ''It took me a little while, but I finally got there.''</p>
        <p>Sal Silva took a similar path to his current job as dealer at River Rock, a casino in Geyserville, Calif.</p>
        <p>Mr. Silva, 58, worked 33 years as a letter carrier for the United States Postal Service in nearby Santa Rosa, Calif., before retiring in 2004. When he heard the casino was hiring, Mr. Silva said, he swung by and applied in person. His application received first priority, since he is a member of the Dry Creek Rancheria Band of Pomo Indians that operates River Rock.</p>
        <p>Mr. Silva said the job provided him and his wife with a little spending money, a luxury the family had lived without for years.</p>
        <p>''Between my retirement and what I get from working at the casino, for the first time in my life we have some extra cash,'' said Mr. Silva, whose son works the same shift, also as a card dealer. ''It's nice to be secure for once.''</p>
        <p>Few retirees make the transition into the gambling industry without some casino-sponsored training.</p>
        <p>The duration and intensity of this schooling varies by employer, though most courses last 4 to 12 weeks.</p>
        <p>At Thunder Valley Casino in Lincoln, Calif., Gary Benko, a dealer, said he was surprised at how much he learned in school. Mr. Benko, 67, joined the casino in 2005 after service in the Marine Corps and years as a contractor, so he was accustomed to the process of assimilating new information quickly.</p>
        <p>''My first day of dealer school, I remember laughing to myself and thinking, 'This won't even take a week,' '' Mr. Benko said recently. Over the next six weeks, he learned an entire casino's worth of games, including blackjack, pai gow poker and mini-baccarat, to name a few.</p>
        <p>''It was much tougher than I expected,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Of the retirees who begin second careers in the gambling industry, those with perhaps the toughest jobs are the ones who become floor managers, or pit bosses. Besides learning how to deal table games, they have to learn how to monitor play -- a complicated business in busy casinos.</p>
        <p>Marty Puschnig, 57, has experienced this firsthand. After a 21-year career in the Air Force, Mr. Puschnig retired and was hired as a floor manager at Harrah's on the Las Vegas Strip in 2005. Today, he manages an entire gambling pit, doing everything from tracking rated players to keeping tabs on who is betting what.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Puschnig described the work as demanding at times, he said it was one of the most fulfilling jobs he'd ever had, and added that he could see himself working in the gambling industry well into his 70s.</p>
        <p>''Between the people and the constant action, there's never a dull moment around here,'' he said. ''For a second career, this is a pretty great gig.''</p>
        <p>ACT 2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
