<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Defense Rests in Trial of Ex-Qwest Chief</title>
    <meta content="10qwest" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/technology/10qwest.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839292"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insider Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Qwest Communications International Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nacchio, Joseph P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frosch, Dan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insider Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Qwest Communications International Inc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Nacchio, Joseph P</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E7DC153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="462" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Defense Rests in Trial of Ex-Qwest Chief</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Defense Rests in Trial of Ex-Qwest Chief</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN FROSCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Frosch, Dan</byline>
      <dateline>DENVER, April 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Defense arrests its case in insider trading case of Qwest Communications former chief executive Joseph P Nacchio, ending widespread anticipation that Nacchio might take stand on his own behalf (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The defense rested its case Monday in the insider trading case of Joseph P. Nacchio, the former chief executive of Qwest Communications, ending widespread anticipation that Mr. Nacchio might take the stand on his own behalf.</p>
        <p>The trial of Mr. Nacchio, who faces 42 counts of insider trading related to his sale of more than $100 million in Qwest stock in 2001, has gone more swiftly than expected, with Judge Edward W. Nottingham of Federal District Court here pushing both sides to move quickly and often admonishing the defense.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Joseph P. Nacchio, charged with insider trading, never took the stand on his own behalf.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The defense rested its case Monday in the insider trading case of Joseph P. Nacchio, the former chief executive of Qwest Communications, ending widespread anticipation that Mr. Nacchio might take the stand on his own behalf.</p>
        <p>The trial of Mr. Nacchio, who faces 42 counts of insider trading related to his sale of more than $100 million in Qwest stock in 2001, has gone more swiftly than expected, with Judge Edward W. Nottingham of Federal District Court here pushing both sides to move quickly and often admonishing the defense.</p>
        <p>Federal prosecutors contend that Mr. Nacchio expedited his stock sales because he was aware that Qwest was in financial trouble, even as he issued optimistic guidance to analysts. Defense lawyers argued that Mr. Nacchio believed that the company's future was on the upswing and that he sold his stock at a pace consistent with his stock sales during previous years.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Nacchio's name did not appear on an initial defense witness list, legal specialists had speculated that he might take the stand to testify on potential secret government contracts that defense lawyers say he expected to bolster company revenue.</p>
        <p>But some specialists said the decision not to call him was safer than leaving Mr. Nacchio vulnerable to potentially withering cross-examination from prosecutors.</p>
        <p>''Considering the defense accomplished through cross-examination much of what it promised to deliver in opening statements, it is anything but surprising that Joe Nacchio elected not to testify,'' said Scott Robinson, a criminal defense lawyer and legal analyst in Denver.</p>
        <p>Mr. Robinson, who has been observing the trial, said that it was often risky for executives accused of white-collar crimes, like Mr. Nacchio, to take the stand because they ran the risk of coming across to juries as arrogant and evasive.</p>
        <p>Though he did not take the stand, Mr. Nacchio did appear Monday in a video clip of a Qwest sales meeting, played for the jury by the defense team. In the video clip, Mr. Nacchio is seen explaining to analysts that he needed to use his stock options quickly before they expired and urging people not to view the sales as indicative of anything else.</p>
        <p>Witnesses for the government, some of them former Qwest executives, testified that Mr. Nacchio exaggerated the company's financial projections and set unrealistic internal performance goals.</p>
        <p>Among the witnesses called by Mr. Nacchio's defense team was Qwest's founder, Philip F. Anschutz. Mr. Anschutz, who was called in an effort to show Mr. Nacchio's state of mind at the time of the stock sales, testified that Mr. Nacchio tried to resign in 2001 after his son attempted suicide.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors may call a final witness, after which both sides will most likely make closing arguments within the next two days, followed by jury deliberations.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
