<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Many Ways to Fight Heart Disease</title>
    <meta content="l10heart" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839334"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anatomy and Physiology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Exercise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E4DB153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="994" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Many Ways to Fight Heart Disease</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Lessons of Heart Disease, Learned and Ignored'' (''Six Killers'' series, front page, April 8):</p>
        <p>You are quite right to highlight the many missed opportunities to prevent heart attacks and save lives by early recognition of heart disease symptoms and consistent, timely use of the best available medications and technologies. But early recognition of heart attack is a sadly limited approach to heart disease prevention.</p>
        <p>We have long known that populations with comparable genetic susceptibilities, living in different environments, experience dramatically varying rates of heart disease. Most experts concur that routine application of what we already know about healthful lifestyle could reduce heart disease rates in the United States by 80 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Lessons of Heart Disease, Learned and Ignored'' (''Six Killers'' series, front page, April 8):</p>
        <p>You are quite right to highlight the many missed opportunities to prevent heart attacks and save lives by early recognition of heart disease symptoms and consistent, timely use of the best available medications and technologies. But early recognition of heart attack is a sadly limited approach to heart disease prevention.</p>
        <p>We have long known that populations with comparable genetic susceptibilities, living in different environments, experience dramatically varying rates of heart disease. Most experts concur that routine application of what we already know about healthful lifestyle could reduce heart disease rates in the United States by 80 percent.</p>
        <p>Many of us believe that the disease is essentially eradicable. Instead of moving in that direction, poor diet and lack of physical activity are driving legions of ever younger people toward both obesity and Type 2 diabetes. Diabetes, in turn, portends the almost certain development of heart disease.</p>
        <p>Even as we work to ensure optimal use of the powerful armaments of modern cardiovascular medicine, we should work at least as diligently to ensure that fewer of us wind up needing them.</p>
        <p>David L. Katz, M.D.  Dir., Prevention Research Center  Yale University School of Medicine  New Haven, April 8, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I had a near-fatal heart attack in 2004.</p>
        <p>Fortunately, the E.M.S. rescue team in Deerfield Beach, Fla., got to me within about 11 minutes and revived me, and the cardio team at Broward General Medical Center was able to do stenting quickly enough that, while my heart muscle was severely damaged, I am alive and functioning today.</p>
        <p>I'm both pleased and proud to say that I take eight medications every day and that I intend to continue doing this until the actual end of my days.</p>
        <p>The idea that I'd not want to do this because my ego has trouble accepting that I'm sick and need this sort of help has never occurred to me.</p>
        <p>The very idea that illness carries some sort of social stigma, that we think less of ourselves because of it, and that we want to conceal our condition from others because of it is just foolishness.</p>
        <p>Stephen Jones  Deerfield Beach, Fla., April 8, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your article about heart disease scared me. You stressed the urgency of speed in obtaining immediate care.</p>
        <p>One morning a year ago, I woke up with chest pains. I was taken by my wife to the emergency room of a local hospital. Once there, I was asked by a receptionist to fill out a lengthy form one gets when becoming a new patient at a doctor's office. The receptionist then had to get all my insurance data. She even asked me if the month of February was a 2 or a 3 because she had to enter all these data into a computer.</p>
        <p>I was then asked to sit down and wait. After about 10 minutes, the emergency room doors swung open, several doctors and nurses approached and put me in a wheelchair. They then raced me through the doors, placed me on another chair or bed, and attached me to various I.V. needles, gadgets and instruments.</p>
        <p>All this struck me as humorous nonsense. Why were they in such a hurry when their admissions staff couldn't have cared less?</p>
        <p>Andrew Zwarun  Austin, Tex., April 8, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The reader of ''Lessons of Heart Disease, Learned and Ignored'' should not be left with the impression that Keith Orr's efforts to lose weight by restricting the amount of food he ate and increasing his level of physical activity were useless, as evidenced by his having a second heart attack. The real issue is that lifestyle modification alone in a high-risk individual is often not enough to adequately lower heart disease risk.</p>
        <p>The multipronged approach of diet, physical activity and drug therapy results in maximal risk reduction. We can't pick and choose which of these we decide are the ones we like and which we don't like, but should follow our doctor's advice and adhere to all of them simultaneously to achieve maximum benefit</p>
        <p>Alice H. Lichtenstein  Boston, April 8, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is a professor of nutrition science and policy at Tufts University.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The primary reason people do not rush to an emergency room at the first sign of chest pains may be the cost of an emergency room visit.</p>
        <p>Most people cannot pay well over $1,000 for an emergency room visit and the required tests, and so will not go to the emergency room until they are sure that it is a life-threatening situation. By that time, as the article shows, the damage is done.</p>
        <p>You also point out that the reason hospitals fail to transfer cardiac patients is a financial incentive to keep them. It is time that we eliminated the perverse incentives for poor health care and provided universal access to health care.</p>
        <p>Michael Scheinberg  Austin, Tex., April 8, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>You say ''the toll from the nation's No. 1 killer could be reduced if the medical system delivered care that is known to make a difference.'' For the most part, it is the patient that makes the difference, not the medical system.</p>
        <p>The risk factors are well known, and the responsibility lies with the patient to reduce them. The inability of some people to comply with prescribed recommendations for the prevention and treatment of heart disease should not be attributed to the medical system.</p>
        <p>We have come a long way in our ability to treat and prevent heart attacks, and we should aim at making emergency care more universally available. If only we had known risk factors that cause nonsmoking-related cancers, I am sure that many of us cancer survivors would have followed them.</p>
        <p>Marta Meyers, M.D.  Morristown, N.J., April 8, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
