<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Knicks' Playoff Hopes Fade Into the Distance</title>
    <meta content="10knicks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/sports/basketball/10knicks.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839389"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Detroit Pistons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Detroit Pistons</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E4DA153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="895" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Knicks' Playoff Hopes Fade Into the Distance</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Knicks’ Playoff Hopes Fade Into the Distance</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beck, Howard</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jared Jeffries had three stitches over his left eye, and Channing Frye had a nasty knot over his right eye. The wounds were essentially self-inflicted, Knick on Knick, which pretty much summed up the night.</p>
        <p>The Detroit Pistons dealt the Knicks' playoff hopes a potentially decisive blow last night, sending them to a 91-83 defeat at Madison Square Garden. But it was the Knicks' own missteps -- careless passes, lost rebounds, technical fouls and the occasional head bonk -- that lost the game and probably ended their playoff push.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the loss, the Knicks fell four games behind Orlando for the eighth and final playoff spot, with five games to play.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jared Jeffries had three stitches over his left eye, and Channing Frye had a nasty knot over his right eye. The wounds were essentially self-inflicted, Knick on Knick, which pretty much summed up the night.</p>
        <p>The Detroit Pistons dealt the Knicks' playoff hopes a potentially decisive blow last night, sending them to a 91-83 defeat at Madison Square Garden. But it was the Knicks' own missteps -- careless passes, lost rebounds, technical fouls and the occasional head bonk -- that lost the game and probably ended their playoff push.</p>
        <p>The Orlando Magic (36-41) routed the Milwaukee Bucks last night, leaving the Knicks (32-45) four games out of the playoff field with five games to play. The stubborn optimism has finally begun to fade.</p>
        <p>''Anything can happen; stranger things have happened,'' Malik Rose said of a playoff berth. ''But am I planning for it? No. Am I hoping for it? Yes.''</p>
        <p>A loss to the Pistons (50-27), the No. 1 team in the Eastern Conference, might have been expected. The Knicks were again missing three of their top scorers, and neither David Lee (sore leg) nor Renaldo Balkman (stomach virus), their top providers of hustle and energy, played.</p>
        <p>Yet the game was in reach until the final two minutes, when the Knicks simply disintegrated. Mardy Collins, the rookie guard who has stepped in for the injured Stephon Marbury, threw an ill-advised entry pass for Eddy Curry. It turned into a steal and a Richard Hamilton 3-pointer that gave the Pistons an 84-79 lead with 2 minutes 2 seconds left.</p>
        <p>A minute later, Collins's inbounds pass skipped past Nate Robinson and out of bounds for another turnover.</p>
        <p>It had been that kind of night. Frye and Jeffries were hurt when they collided in the paint early in the third quarter. Late in the fourth quarter, Frye and Curry battled for an offensive rebound, and lost it out of bounds. Twice, Robinson saved a ball out of bounds, only to throw it right to the Pistons.</p>
        <p>''Our margin of error is very slim,'' Coach Isiah Thomas said, ''and the little things that add up in the course of a ball game, in terms of a blockout on the foul line or we mishandle an inbounds possession, that ends up giving the other team 2 or 3 extra points. Those type of things eventually hurt you in the long run.''</p>
        <p>The sense among the Knicks was that a more veteran lineup might have handled the final minutes with more precision. Collins and Robinson, a second-year guard, are playing in crunch time only because of the injuries to Marbury, Jamal Crawford and Quentin Richardson.</p>
        <p>''We've lost the experience in situations like this,'' Jeffries said.</p>
        <p>The Knicks got one of those veteran players back last night, but lost him again. Steve Francis returned after a five-game absence, but was ejected early in the fourth quarter after snapping at the referee Steve Javie. Francis had been tied up by Antonio McDyess, and Javie called for a jump ball. Francis, apparently wanting a foul, turned and bellowed, ''Come on, Steve!'' After Javie called a technical, Francis snapped again and Javie gave him the second technical, an automatic ejection.</p>
        <p>''It was tough losing him,'' Thomas said, acknowledging that Francis let his emotions get the best of him. ''However, I'd rather have him out on the floor competing and playing with that type of intensity and energy than not.''</p>
        <p>Curry and Robinson had 24 points each. Curry, coming off a career-best 43-point effort at Milwaukee, was in early foul trouble and was roughed up by the Pistons' veteran front line of Rasheed Wallace, Chris Webber, Dale Davis and McDyess. Curry spent a considerable amount of time on his backside.</p>
        <p>''I think they made it a point to really make me feel them out there tonight, let me know I wasn't just going to have my way with them,'' Curry said. ''It's a tough group of guys over there in that locker room.''</p>
        <p>Chauncey Billups led Detroit with 22 points. Hamilton had 19, including 7 straight points that helped the Pistons pull away down the stretch.</p>
        <p>The game followed a familiar script. The Knicks fell behind early, rallied in the third quarter, took a big lead and then disintegrated again.</p>
        <p>The Pistons led by 10 points early in the third quarter, but the Knicks bounced back with a 21-4 run. The Knicks had a 68-58 lead late in the third quarter, but Billups scored 5 points in the final 6.7 seconds of the period, starting the Pistons on a 17-2 run that gave them a 5-point lead.</p>
        <p>The Knicks tied the score at 75-75 on a Robinson 3-pointer, at 77-77 on a Rose tip-in and at 79-79 on a Collins layup. The Pistons took over from there.</p>
        <p>Detroit have lorded over the Eastern Conference for the last few seasons, winning conference titles in 2004 and 2005.</p>
        <p>''When it's all said and done, when they step off the throne, we want to be stepping on it,'' Thomas said. ''We want to be the team that's following them and Miami.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>Stephon Marbury sat out his second straight game because of turf toe and is almost certain to miss tonight's game at Chicago as well. Isiah Thomas said he hoped Marbury would return ''by the end of the week,'' possibly for Friday's game against the Nets.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
