<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Talk of Group To Make a Bid On Bell Canada</title>
    <meta content="10deal" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/business/10deal.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070413T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839380"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ontario Teachers Pension Plan</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bce Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bell Canada</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Caisse De Depot Et Placement Du Quebec</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Canada Plan Investment Board</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Austen, Ian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Canada</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Bell Canada</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE6DA153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="993" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Talk of Group To Make a Bid On Bell Canada</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Report of Talk to Take Over Bell Canada</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN and IAN AUSTEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross; Austen, Ian</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ontario Teachers' Pension Plan is in early talks with other investors to form consortium to mount $45 billion takeover bid for parent company of Bell Canada in what would be largest buyout in history; pension plan, which is largest shareholder of BCE, telephone company's parent, has reached out in recent weeks to Caisse de Depot et Placement du Quebec and Canada's Plan Investment Board about pursuing takeover; has also held talks with at least one private equity firm (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of Canada's largest pension funds is in early talks with other investors to form a consortium to mount a $45 billion takeover bid for the parent company of Bell Canada in what would be the largest buyout in history, according to people briefed on the discussions.</p>
        <p>The Ontario Teachers' Pension Plan, which is the largest shareholder of BCE, the telephone company's parent, has reached out in recent weeks to Caisse de Dépôt et Placement du Québec and the Canada Pension Plan Investment Board about pursuing a takeover, these people said. The Ontario Teachers' Pension Plan has also held talks with at least one private equity firm, these people said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The $45 billion takeover bid from a consortium led by a Canadian pension fund would be the largest buyout in history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of Canada's largest pension funds is in early talks with other investors to form a consortium to mount a $45 billion takeover bid for the parent company of Bell Canada in what would be the largest buyout in history, according to people briefed on the discussions.</p>
        <p>The Ontario Teachers' Pension Plan, which is the largest shareholder of BCE, the telephone company's parent, has reached out in recent weeks to Caisse de Dépôt et Placement du Québec and the Canada Pension Plan Investment Board about pursuing a takeover, these people said. The Ontario Teachers' Pension Plan has also held talks with at least one private equity firm, these people said.</p>
        <p>A takeover bid would represent a rare effort by a pension fund, rather than a private equity firm, to lead a buyout of this size. It also illustrates a growing tendency among pension funds to make direct investments themselves, a trend that is becoming particularly popular in Canada.</p>
        <p>Gilles des Roberts, a spokesman for the Caisse, which manages the Quebec government's public pension plan, said that the fund was not involved in any discussions about BCE.</p>
        <p>''We deny any involvement in this deal in every way,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission yesterday, Ontario Teachers' rebutted an earlier report in The Globe and Mail that it was in talks with Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Company about pursuing a deal for BCE, but said it was ''closely monitoring developments and is exploring its options.''</p>
        <p>K.K.R. had held talks with BCE on its own earlier this year, but was rebuffed, people involved in the discussion said. Separately, Ontario Teachers' also recently approached BCE, but the discussions were only preliminary and appeared to have been rejected.</p>
        <p>On March 29, BCE said ''there are no ongoing discussions being held with any private equity investor with respect to any privatization of the company or any similar transaction.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday, William J. Fox, BCE's executive vice president for communications and corporate development, said: ''Our statement of March 29th stands. We are not in any current talks with any other parties.''</p>
        <p>Still, BCE's stock has jumped on speculation of a possible deal, and an approach from its largest shareholders, like Ontario Teachers', could put pressure on it to consider a sale.</p>
        <p>Any prospective change of ownership at BCE involves politics as much as regulatory or investment issues. A takeover by K.K.R was considered virtually impossible, according to people involved in the talks, because of the political dimension.</p>
        <p>Politics also came into play in October when the company said it planned to reorganize as an income trust, an ownership structure that avoids corporate taxes by paying out most of the profits directly to unit holders, as the trust's shareholders are known.</p>
        <p>While a large number of companies, including BCE's smaller rival Telus, have made the switch, the idea of such a change at BCE was too much for even the business-friendly Conservative government. It swiftly moved to introduce politically unpopular legislation to kill trust conversions by imposing a new tax. Shortly after, BCE abandoned its conversion scheme.</p>
        <p>Canadian law prohibits foreign investors from controlling more than 46.67 percent of a telecommunications company's voting equity. While some investors in the United States effectively circumvented that limit in the past by taking on Canadian partners for some small telecommunications takeovers, it is unlikely that the government will let a similar arrangement pass without challenge in BCE's case.</p>
        <p>It is the dominant carrier in Ontario and Quebec, the most populous provinces, and is one of Canada's largest corporations and employers.</p>
        <p>On top of that, a series of recent foreign takeovers of major Canadian corporations in unregulated sectors of the economy like mining have led to concerns in Canada about a loss of economic control.</p>
        <p>In many respects, BCE is in a stronger position than many of its counterparts in the United States. Unlike AT&amp;T, it has always been allowed to operate a full range of both local and long-distance services. The company was also among Canada's first mobile phone providers.</p>
        <p>While local telephone service is open to cable companies and others, traditional phone companies, including BCE's Bell Canada unit, controlled about 90 percent of local lines at the end of 2005. Even in the more competitive mobile market, a study released last month by the SeaBoard Group found that the average cellphone user in Canada pays 33 percent more than an American user.</p>
        <p>Canada had limited the ability of Bell Canada and other BCE operating units to compete against cable companies and other newcomers by substantially reducing local service prices. Both the regulator and a parliamentary committee were concerned that Bell would eliminate competitors by deeply cutting prices and then, once competitors were eliminated, imposing equally large price increases over time.</p>
        <p>Last week, however, the concerns of both the regulator and the parliamentary committee were dismissed by the government when it effectively deregulated most local telephone service through a cabinet order.</p>
        <p>BCE's financial and operating performance has generally lagged that of Telus and other competitors. Dvai Ghose, an analyst with Genuity Capital Markets, estimates that Telus generated free cash flow, before dividends, of 1.6 billion Canadian dollars (about $1.38 billion) last year, an increase from 845 million Canadian dollars in 2003. At BCE, cash flow dropped to 1.9 billion Canadian dollars ($1.65 billion) in 2006, from 2 billion Canadian dollars in 2004.</p>
        <p>Even that slippage, however, is an improvement over the situation that Michael J. Sabia inherited when he became BCE's chief executive five years ago.</p>
        <p>His predecessor, Jean Monty, after spinning off BCE's control of Nortel Networks to shareholders, went on a buying spree. BCE ultimately acquired Canada's largest private broadcaster, CTV, and The Globe and Mail, a national newspaper based in Toronto.</p>
        <p>Critics say the company's emphasis on acquisitions led it to neglect investment in infrastructure that would have allowed it to sell its customers lucrative services like pay television today.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 13, 2007, Friday  An article in Business Day on Tuesday about possible plans by a Canadian pension fund to form a consortium and mount a $45 billion takeover bid for BCE, the parent company of Bell Canada, misstated the legal status of a rival company, Telus. While Telus had announced plans to convert to an income trust, it abandoned the move because of changes in the law.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 13, 2007, Friday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day on Tuesday about possible plans by a Canadian pension fund to form a consortium and mount a $45 billion takeover bid for BCE, the parent company of Bell Canada, misstated the legal status of a rival company, Telus. While Telus had announced plans to convert to an income trust, it abandoned the move because of changes in the law.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
