<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Run-for-a-Flight Treadmill</title>
    <meta content="10flier" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/business/10flier.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839290"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FREQUENT FLIER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PrintingForLess.com</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Field, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">raymond, joan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Frequent Flier</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Business Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Industry News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Running</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CEEDD153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="606" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Run-for-a-Flight Treadmill</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Run-for-a-Flight Treadmill</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Andrew Field as told to Joan Raymond.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Field, Andrew; raymond, joan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>PrintingForLess.com chief executive Andrew Field, in Frequent Flier column, on some airline travel experiences, including learning to run for connecting flights; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Business travel has forced me to get into shape. I bought a treadmill. And now I can run. I can sprint. I can go the distance, with barely a hitch in my breath, as I try to make my flights.</p>
        <p>If I were a superhero, my name would be Connection Man. That's because my business is literally out in the middle of nowhere. Livingston, Mont., is not an airport hub. I'm not even sure that we're part of flyover country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Business travel has forced me to get into shape. I can go the distance, with barely a hitch in my breath, as I try to make my flights.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Business travel has forced me to get into shape. I bought a treadmill. And now I can run. I can sprint. I can go the distance, with barely a hitch in my breath, as I try to make my flights.</p>
        <p>If I were a superhero, my name would be Connection Man. That's because my business is literally out in the middle of nowhere. Livingston, Mont., is not an airport hub. I'm not even sure that we're part of flyover country.</p>
        <p>To get out of here, I have to get to the nearest big city, which is Bozeman, population 30,000. Out here, that's huge.</p>
        <p>A lot of my business travel involves getting back east to Chicago, Boston, New York or any point east of Bozeman which, when you think about it, is most of the country. That means I have to take a series of bizarre connecting flights that I may or may not make, depending on my endurance and the whim of the airlines.</p>
        <p>I was coming back from Chicago recently and had to go through Minneapolis. My plane was late getting out of Chicago, which could have made me late for the connecting flight. But I was literally the first guy off the plane. If I weren't so physically fit, I would never have been able to run and leap onto the back of a cart, and hang on with muscles I didn't know I had, while some guy is trying to get me to the gate.</p>
        <p>I actually got there three minutes before my scheduled departure. But there was no plane. It left without me. The gate agent told me they got an early pushback. They knew I was coming. They have computers. I had to wait in Minneapolis for nine hours for the next available flight. I tried my best, but it just wasn't good enough. They must get bonus points for leaving early. At least, I got in a nice workout.</p>
        <p>On another recent flight out of Dallas, one of our guys was late due to heavy traffic. We waited and the six of us went rushing up to the ticket counter and told our tale of woe to the agent. We had connections through Salt Lake and then Bozeman and if we missed anything, we would probably have been stuck in Dallas for five years or something. We had about eight minutes to make the flight and we got ushered through security. We had a nice little run to the plane, which they held for us. The agent probably bent the rules a little bit, but it was awesome. I not only got in my workout but I had the pleasure of dealing with an airline agent who actually cared.</p>
        <p>There's always some trepidation when I leave Livingston. We pay practically double for any flight we take, even with advance notice. And I usually have to leave earlier than most other business types. For an event on Saturday out east, most folks would leave Saturday morning, take a flight, and maybe get home the same day. I leave Friday morning and hope for the best.</p>
        <p>I wish there was a better way to do this. I wish the airlines would actually use their systems and pay attention to folks like me who have to make a lot of connections. But I'm a glass-half-full kind of guy. I've gotten pretty good on the treadmill in the last couple of years. And my cardiovascular health has never been better. I don't even break a sweat running through the airport. After all, I am Connection Man.</p>
        <p>FREQUENT FLIER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
