<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Zionist Firebrand's War Against Bystanders' Silence</title>
    <meta content="10acco" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/theater/reviews/10acco.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839265"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Group Theater Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ng, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weinraub, Bernard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morgan, Ian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sauli, Daniel</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Accomplices, The (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Group</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Weinraub, Bernard</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Accomplices, The (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E6DD153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="450" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Zionist Firebrand's War Against Bystanders' Silence</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Zionist Firebrand’s War Against Bystanders’ Silence</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID NG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ng, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Ng reviews New Group production of Bernard Weinraub play The Accomplices, directed by Ian Morgan; Daniel Sauli stars; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It seems rude, even sacrilegious, to fault a Holocaust drama for failing to entertain. Most of us don't associate genocide with a fun night at the theater after all. But neither should we be expected to endure a mind-numbing history lesson. ''The Accomplices,'' which opened last night at the Acorn Theater, is a soporific lecture of a play. If humorlessness were the measure of good art, it could rank among the best productions of the year.</p>
        <p>The play, presented by the New Group, dusts off a little-known chapter in Jewish-American history. In 1940 the young Zionist activist Hillel Kook arrived in New York from Palestine, determined to persuade the United States government to open its arms to Jewish refugees fleeing the Nazis. Renaming himself Peter Bergson, he pursued his mission with fervent devotion, clashing with Jewish-American officials who refused to help. He eventually reached the White House, which he found to be even more hostile to his pleas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If humorlessness were the measure of good art, Bernard Weinraub’s play could rank among the best productions of the year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It seems rude, even sacrilegious, to fault a Holocaust drama for failing to entertain. Most of us don't associate genocide with a fun night at the theater after all. But neither should we be expected to endure a mind-numbing history lesson. ''The Accomplices,'' which opened last night at the Acorn Theater, is a soporific lecture of a play. If humorlessness were the measure of good art, it could rank among the best productions of the year.</p>
        <p>The play, presented by the New Group, dusts off a little-known chapter in Jewish-American history. In 1940 the young Zionist activist Hillel Kook arrived in New York from Palestine, determined to persuade the United States government to open its arms to Jewish refugees fleeing the Nazis. Renaming himself Peter Bergson, he pursued his mission with fervent devotion, clashing with Jewish-American officials who refused to help. He eventually reached the White House, which he found to be even more hostile to his pleas.</p>
        <p>''The Accomplices'' places the Holocaust first in a line of initial American noninvolvement in the face of genocide. The play seeks to correct, or at least complexify, the notion of America as a force of pure good during World War II. On paper Mr. Bergson is a fascinating person, whose story certainly deserves to be told. But in his first play Bernard Weinraub takes a hagiographic approach, portraying him as a historical hero first and a human being second. Over and over we're reminded of his nobility, usually via reams of dry, expository dialogue. As Bergson, Daniel Sauli brings a welcome touch of mischief and sex appeal, but the role mostly requires him to maintain an earnest pose.</p>
        <p>Mr. Weinraub, a former reporter for The New York Times who covered foreign affairs, Hollywood and other beats, has clearly spent a great deal of time researching his protagonist. What he hasn't done is shape that research into a compelling drama. Scenes unfold at such an uninflected pace that you'd think you were watching C-Span, and the director Ian Morgan's monotonous staging doesn't help.</p>
        <p>The few glimmers of unpredictability come from the supporting cast: David Margulies plays the politically compromised Rabbi Stephen Wise, a prominent Jewish figure during the war, with wit and ambiguity; and Jon DeVries gives two deliciously over-the-top performances, first as a rowdy Franklin D. Roosevelt and later as a rowdier Ben Hecht.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bergson spent much of his life upsetting others for a higher cause. If ''The Accomplices'' had tapped into that same spirit, he might have come off as more than just a historical figurine.</p>
        <p>''The Accomplices'' continues through May 5 at the Acorn Theater, Theater Row, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW David Ng writes theater reviews for The Village Voice. He also covers theater and the arts for The Los Angeles Times, American Theater magazine and ARTnews.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Ng writes theater reviews for The Village Voice. He also covers theater and the arts for The Los Angeles Times, American Theater magazine and ARTnews.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
