<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Photos of a 'Pat' Yield a Decree Against a Pakistani Minister</title>
    <meta content="10pakistan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/world/asia/10pakistan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839283"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Threats and Threatening Messages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pakistan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Masood, Salman</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bakhtiar, Nilofer (Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Musharraf, Pervez (Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Threats and Threatening Messages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Pakistan</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803EFDD153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="756" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Photos of a 'Pat' Yield a Decree Against a Pakistani Minister</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Photos of a ‘Pat’ Yield a Decree Against a Pakistani Minister</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SALMAN MASOOD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Masood, Salman</byline>
      <dateline>ISLAMABAD, Pakistan, April 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Radical clerics in Pakistan issue religious decree, or fatwa, against country's tourism minister Nilofer Bakhtiar after local newspapers print photographs showing her holding onto male colleague after landing from parachute jump in France; clerics urge government of Pres Pervez Musharraf to 'punish and fire her'; Pakistani officials dismiss fatwa, and human rights and political activists and many other Pakistanis express support for her; radical clerics have latched onto opportunity to criticize her and also to attack Musharraf for what he calls his approach of 'enlightened moderation'; cleric Maulana Abdul Aziz threatens suicide attacks if government does not enact Islamic law and stop immorality within month; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A group of radical clerics has issued a religious decree against Pakistan's tourism minister after some local newspapers printed photographs showing her holding onto a male colleague after landing from a parachute jump in France.</p>
        <p>The decree, or fatwa, was issued by a religious parallel court set up last week by a group of activist clerics in the Lal Mosque here. The clerics also have also demanded that the government enact Islamic law, or Shariah.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The tourism minister is denounced by radical clerics after she was pictured holding a male colleague after a parachute jump.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A group of radical clerics has issued a religious decree against Pakistan's tourism minister after some local newspapers printed photographs showing her holding onto a male colleague after landing from a parachute jump in France.</p>
        <p>The decree, or fatwa, was issued by a religious parallel court set up last week by a group of activist clerics in the Lal Mosque here. The clerics also have also demanded that the government enact Islamic law, or Shariah.</p>
        <p>The fatwa issued Sunday accuses the minister, Nilofer Bakhtiar, of un-Islamic behavior. The clerics urged the government of President Pervez Musharraf to ''punish and fire her from the government.''</p>
        <p>Pakistani officials dismissed the fatwa, saying it had no legal, religious or moral authority. Human rights and political activists and many other Pakistanis have condemned the action and expressed support for her.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bakhtiar also dismissed the criticism and, in an interview on Monday, said that the photographs were taken out of context and that they showed her being congratulated for making the jump at a charity event.</p>
        <p>After the photographs were published, incensed radical clerics and some other conservative Pakistanis latched onto the opportunity not only to criticize her but also to attack General Musharraf for what he calls his approach of ''enlightened moderation.'' The pictures, in their view, violated acceptable moral norms in this Muslim country.</p>
        <p>Maulana Abdul Aziz, the chief cleric of Lal Mosque, and his brother, Abdur Rashid Ghazi, have made headlines in recent months for openly challenging the government.</p>
        <p>On Friday, Mr. Aziz threatened suicide attacks if the government did not enact Islamic law and stop immorality within a month.</p>
        <p>Since January, hundreds of women who are students at Jamia Hafsa, a seminary affiliated with Lal Mosque, have occupied a public children's library here and staged a sit-in to protest a government campaign to raze mosques built illegally on state-owned land.</p>
        <p>The government has allowed the library occupation to continue, saying it fears a violent escalation if it uses force to evict the demonstrators.</p>
        <p>Some critics of the government say it has buckled under pressure from the clerics, emboldening them. Others say that the government has allowed the clerics a free hand in order to divert attention from a constitutional crisis. Last month, General Musharraf removed the chief justice, Iftikhar Mohammad Chaudhry, who had taken on cases challenging the president's authority. There have been widespread protests over Mr. Chaudhry's removal.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bakhtiar said in the interview that the newspapers that printed the photographs mischaracterized the pictures and the cause for which she agreed to the parachute jump. ''They had horrible captions,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bakhtiar said she had gone on the parachute jump at an event held by a private aid group that plans to raise money for the victims of the devastating earthquake that struck Pakistan in October 2005.</p>
        <p>''I had gone to Germany on an official visit exactly a month ago,'' she said. ''On the way back, I had a stopover in France.'' The group was holding the event in Normandy, she said, and, ''as an act of solidarity, I agreed to jump.''</p>
        <p>The photographs appear to show a Frenchman giving her a hug, which she described as a congratulatory pat, after the jump. ''But the pictures published totally distorted the context,'' she said.</p>
        <p>She added: ''I did it for a good cause. I did not have any practice of parajumping. I thought it was brave on my part.''</p>
        <p>Many here have expressed fears that such religious decrees mark the beginning of a dangerous precedent and are reminiscent of a continuing fatwa against the author Salman Rushdie, issued almost two decades ago over his novel ''The Satanic Verses.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Bakhtiar, however, said that she was not intimidated and that the government and her political party, the Pakistan Muslim League, were fully behind her.</p>
        <p>''One is naturally concerned for the family, but there have been no additional security measures,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''I am surprised they did not ask for my side of the story before giving out this so-called fatwa,'' added Ms. Bakhtiar, who was previously the minister for women's affairs.</p>
        <p>She said that while Mr. Musharraf's government had been trying to put Pakistan on the path toward moderation and enlightenment, ''opposition to women participating in all walks of life by hard-line Islamic clerics is only natural.''</p>
        <p>''Pakistan is going through a transitional phase,'' she added. ''Such negative forces are bound to come up. We are adamant that we will face them, but the world has to understand that it will take time.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
