<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Romantic Revulsion in the New Century: Flaw-O-Matic 2.0</title>
    <meta content="10tier" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/science/10tier.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839274"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FINDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Findings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Psychology and Psychologists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dating (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Psychology and Psychologists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Psychology and Psychologists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dating (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5DD153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1162" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Romantic Revulsion in the New Century: Flaw-O-Matic 2.0</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Romantic Revulsion in the New Century: Flaw-O-Matic 2.0</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By John Tierney</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tierney, John</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ABSTRACT.  In this meta-analysis of online dating and speed dating, we propose a corollary to the Flaw-O-Matic theory of romantic revulsion. Current research reveals that the Flaw-O-Matic, a mechanism in the brain that instantly finds fault with any potential mate, can be reoriented positively in certain conditions through a newly identified process, the Sally Field Effect.</p>
        <p>When I first identified the Flaw-O-Matic, in a 1995 column, it seemed primarily a mechanism to kill romance. After studying picky daters -- like a guy who couldn't tolerate dirty elbows, and a woman who insisted on men who were at least 5-foot-10 and played polo -- I predicted that they would remain permanently single.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Instead of asking people about their mate preferences, scientists can now watch mating rituals in real time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ABSTRACT.  In this meta-analysis of online dating and speed dating, we propose a corollary to the Flaw-O-Matic theory of romantic revulsion. Current research reveals that the Flaw-O-Matic, a mechanism in the brain that instantly finds fault with any potential mate, can be reoriented positively in certain conditions through a newly identified process, the Sally Field Effect.</p>
        <p>When I first identified the Flaw-O-Matic, in a 1995 column, it seemed primarily a mechanism to kill romance. After studying picky daters -- like a guy who couldn't tolerate dirty elbows, and a woman who insisted on men who were at least 5-foot-10 and played polo -- I predicted that they would remain permanently single.</p>
        <p>Today I'm more hopeful. Thanks to a revolution in dating research over the past decade, the Flaw-O-Matic now looks like a more versatile mechanism than we theoretical pioneers imagined.</p>
        <p>My early work was done using personal ads, a crude tool (although state of the art in 1995). I found that people looking for love in New York magazine listed far more prerequisites (like polo skills) for a partner than did people advertising in other cities. Based on these numbers, and many dinners with friends who could never find anyone good enough, I concluded that the high percentage of single-person households in New York was due to New Yorkers' hyperactive Flaw-O-Matics.</p>
        <p>This new theory of a neural mechanism did not immediately gain wide acceptance in the social-science literature. By my count, it has been cited a total of one time (in a psychotherapist's treatise on the ''avoidant lover''). But the study of romantic revulsion has expanded because of the rise of online dating services and speed-dating events -- gold mines of data.</p>
        <p>Instead of asking people about their mate preferences, scientists can now watch mating rituals in real time. They've tracked who asks out whom -- and who says yes -- at online dating services by watching the customers' clicks and scanning their messages to look for telephone numbers and phrases like ''let's meet.''</p>
        <p>They've analyzed the courtship choices of more than 10,000 customers of a commercial speed-dating service. On campuses, they've even organized their own speed-dating events, at which you talk for several minutes apiece with perhaps a dozen people, sometimes two dozen. You discreetly mark on your scorecard which partners you'd like to see again, and the organizers match you afterward with any of them who reciprocated your interest.</p>
        <p>Just as Darwin could have predicted, the researchers have found that women are pickier than men. While men concentrate mainly on looks and will ask out a lot of women as long as they're above a certain threshold of attractiveness, women focus on fewer prospects.</p>
        <p>They're less willing to date someone of another race. When using online services, they pay more attention than men do to a potential partner's education, profession and income. They prefer taller men, but they're willing to relax their standards for the Ron Perelmans of the world, as revealed in a study of more than 20,000 online daters by Gunter Hitsch and Ali Hortacsu of the University of Chicago and Dan Ariely of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology.</p>
        <p>They found that a 5-foot-8 man was just as successful in getting dates as a 6-footer if he made more money -- precisely $146,000 a year more. For a 5-foot-2 man, the number was $277,000. [For more of these trade-offs, see nytimes.com/TierneyLab.]</p>
        <p>Online dating reveals the most exquisite calibrations of the Flaw-O-Matic because the daters fill out questionnaires listing more attributes than could ever fit in a personal ad. They can spend all day finding minute faults in hundreds of potential partners. But that's also why so many people never make a lasting match.</p>
        <p>''When you have all these criteria to consider, and so many people to choose from, you start striving for perfection,'' Dr. Ariely says. ''You don't want to settle for someone who's not ideal in height, age, religion and 45 other dimensions.''</p>
        <p>It's the same problem afflicting New Yorkers: with so many prospects in the big city, they refuse to stop searching.</p>
        <p>Customers of online dating services typically end up going out with fewer than 1 percent of the people whose profiles they study online. But something very different happens at a speed-dating event. The average participant makes a match with at least 1 in 10 of the people they meet; some studies have found the average is 2 or 3 out of 10. Women are still pickier than men, and in some speed-dating experiments they still prefer affluent, well-educated men, but the preference is less strong -- and in some other studies they don't discriminate at all by income or social status.</p>
        <p>What happens to speed daters' Flaw-O-Matics? The people at these events realize that there aren't an infinite number of possibilities. If they want to get anything out of the evening, they have to settle for less than perfection. They also can't help noticing that they have competition, and that their ideal partner just might prefer someone else.</p>
        <p>But these speed daters don't simply shut down their Flaw-O-Matics. They still have their standards, as demonstrated in speed-dating sessions organized by Paul Eastwick and Eli Finkel at Northwestern University. The researchers, working with Daniel Mochon and Dr. Ariely of M.I.T., analyzed the preferences of more than 150 students at the sessions.</p>
        <p>The students were particularly turned off by prospects who exhibited what the researchers call ''unselective romantic desire.'' Another way to put it would be ''desperate.'' The speed daters were very good at guessing which of their partners were indiscriminately friendly -- willing to go out with lots of the other people -- and which dates had eyes only for them. They much preferred the ones with ''selective desire.''</p>
        <p>Being able to make this distinction in a four-minute speed date, the researchers write in the April issue of Psychological Science, ''suggests that humans possess an impressive, highly attuned ability to assess such subtleties of romantic attraction. In fact, the need to feel special or unique could be a broad motivation that stretches across people's social lives.''</p>
        <p>The scientists don't propose a name for this phenomenon; nor, as usual, do they deign to mention the Flaw-O-Matic when discussing this ''impressive, highly attuned ability'' to make snap romantic judgments. But to me this clearly looks like a redirection of the Flaw-O-Matic's power, because of what I call the Sally Field Effect.</p>
        <p>These speed daters were looking for someone who shared their distaste for the others in the room: someone who was just as picky as they were. When they found that person, and neither one of them sneered or bolted, that hectoring little voice in the brain was suddenly transformed into a purring engine of love. They gazed dreamily into each other's eyes, channeled a certain actress on Oscar night, and thought: ''Your Flaw-O-Matic likes me! It really likes me!''</p>
        <p>That may not be enough to sustain the relationship through the trials of dirty elbows and long, polo-less weekends. But it's a start.</p>
        <p>FINDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
