<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Bank Chief Seeks to Quell Favoritism Talk</title>
    <meta content="10wolfowitz" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/washington/10wolfowitz.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839308"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blogs and Blogging (Internet)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Bank for Reconstruction and Development</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Washington Post</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weisman, Steven R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wolfowitz, Paul D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riza, Shaha Ali</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blogs and Blogging (Internet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">World Bank</org>
        <org class="online_producer">State Department</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wolfowitz, Paul D</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE5DC153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="511" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Bank Chief Seeks to Quell Favoritism Talk</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">World Bank Chief Seeks to Quell Favoritism Talk</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN R. WEISMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weisman, Steven R</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>World Bank president Paul D Wolfowitz defends himself against accusations of favoritism; claims he arranged for job at State Dept for woman friend, Shaha Ali Riza, only after consulting bank's executive board on how to handle her reassignment; sends e-mail message to bank employees taking full responsibility for Riza's transfer when he became bank president in 2005; notes that transfer occurred because of bank rules barring bank employees from supervising anyone with whom they had personal relationship; Wolfowitz's highly unusual message comes after weeks of discussions, within bank and elsewhere, following article in The Washington Post and in various Internet blogs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Paul D. Wolfowitz, president of the World Bank, sought on Monday to quell a spreading debate among bank employees over accusations of favoritism, saying he had arranged for a job at the State Department for a woman friend only after consulting the bank's executive board on how to handle her reassignment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolfowitz also said, in an e-mail message to bank employees, that he took full responsibility for the transfer of the bank employee, Shaha Ali Riza, when he became bank president in 2005.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Paul D. Wolfowitz said he arranged for a job at the State Department for a woman friend only after consulting the bank’s executive board.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Paul D. Wolfowitz, president of the World Bank, sought on Monday to quell a spreading debate among bank employees over accusations of favoritism, saying he had arranged for a job at the State Department for a woman friend only after consulting the bank's executive board on how to handle her reassignment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolfowitz also said, in an e-mail message to bank employees, that he took full responsibility for the transfer of the bank employee, Shaha Ali Riza, when he became bank president in 2005.</p>
        <p>He said that he would ''cooperate fully'' with the board's review of the case.</p>
        <p>The transfer occurred because of bank rules barring bank employees from supervising anyone with whom they had a personal relationship, Mr. Wolfowitz said.</p>
        <p>He added that he understood that many were understandably concerned about ''the rights, obligations and fair treatment of all employees.''</p>
        <p>''I would like to assure the staff that I have always acted to uphold these rules to the best of my ability, and I will continue to do so,'' Mr. Wolfowitz said in his message.</p>
        <p>The highly unusual message sent out by Mr. Wolfowitz, a former deputy defense secretary who was appointed to the bank presidency by President Bush, came after weeks of discussions, both within the bank and, following an article about the subject in The Washington Post, elsewhere around Washington and in the world of Internet blogs.</p>
        <p>Bank employees were generally critical of Mr. Wolfowitz's appointment two years ago, focusing on his role as an architect of the Iraq war. They have also accused him of relying on a small group of advisers brought from the Pentagon.</p>
        <p>Last week, the staff association of the World Bank charged that Mr. Wolfowitz had violated bank rules by arranging for the reassignment of Ms. Riza, a former communications officer in the Middle East division, to the State Department, where she is still on the bank payroll while directing a program promoting democracy in the Middle East.</p>
        <p>The association also charged that Ms. Riza had gotten a substantial raise. The Government Accountability Project, an independent watchdog group, says her salary is $193,590, more than the $183,500 drawn by Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice and other cabinet members. Bank officials would not confirm Ms. Riza's salary, saying that such matters were confidential.</p>
        <p>The raise Ms. Riza received was twice as large as bank rules allow, the staff association said, Bloomberg News reported.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolfowitz issued his statement less than a week before the annual spring meetings of the World Bank and the International Monetary Fund in Washington.</p>
        <p>The meetings are to discuss policy issues, like alleviating global poverty, with more than 180 finance ministers from around the world.</p>
        <p>Bank officials say the debate over Ms. Riza and her salary has been overblown as a result of unhappiness with some of Mr. Wolfowitz's policies, including his campaign against corruption and steps taken last year to suspend funding for certain countries deemed to be rife with graft. The statement from Mr. Wolfowitz was seen as an attempt to defuse the issue.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
