<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Look for the Nest Egg</title>
    <meta content="10plan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Retirement" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Job Market" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/business/retirement/10plan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839399"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PENSIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hawthorne, Fran</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E0DA153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1271" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Look for the Nest Egg</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New Look for the Nest Egg</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRAN HAWTHORNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hawthorne, Fran</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on various types of retirement plans being offered by companies; says trend is to pay lump sum to retirees, not checks for life; some plans detailed; chart; drawing (special section, Retirement) (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Phoenix Companies, an insurance concern in Hartford, traces its roots to 1851. Its pension plan goes back almost as far, to 1911.</p>
        <p>But the world has changed, and last year, Phoenix decided to revamp its ancient pension program, replacing its defined benefit plan with something called a pension equity plan, starting in July.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>More companies have moved away from traditional pension plans and towards giving employees a fixed amount when they leave.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Phoenix Companies, an insurance concern in Hartford, traces its roots to 1851. Its pension plan goes back almost as far, to 1911.</p>
        <p>But the world has changed, and last year, Phoenix decided to revamp its ancient pension program, replacing its defined benefit plan with something called a pension equity plan, starting in July.</p>
        <p>As with the old system, the company will provide all the financing and make all the investment decisions. But retirees will no longer get a check every month for life. Instead, Phoenix will give employees a fixed amount when they leave, whether by retirement or other reasons.</p>
        <p>Bonnie J. Malley, senior vice president for human resources and corporate services at Phoenix, said the change would be especially good for ''high performers'' whose pay rises quickly, and for new employees in their mid-to-late 20s and those who leave the company early.</p>
        <p>Louis DePonte, 38, an assistant vice president for expense management, expects to do well. He says that incentive pay will now be included in the pension calculation, and that the company will contribute a bigger share to its 401(k) plan. ''So long as you continue to do a good job and stay with the company, I think you reap the benefits of it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Yet even with the rosiest situation, the company's actuarial model showed that 80 percent of the 1,300 eligible employees would receive slightly less than they would have under the old system. The remaining 20 percent, mainly people hired in their mid-40s and early 50s, would do even worse. (Phoenix has not calculated what they could lose.)</p>
        <p>Over the last two decades, more companies have moved away from traditional pension plans like the one Phoenix is dropping. The open-ended cost of benefits for longer-living retirees has stretched far beyond companies' original expectations.</p>
        <p>Moreover, employees who change jobs often fare poorly under conventional defined benefit plans, which usually calculate benefits based on late-career salaries.</p>
        <p>Phoenix is at the forefront of a third generation of changes in corporate retirement plans, and it is still not clear whether this version will succeed better than the others.</p>
        <p>The first big change, in the 1980s, was the shift to 401(k) plans, in which employees contribute their own money and manage the investments. But many people fail to save enough in their 401(k)s, while many also make poor investment decisions.</p>
        <p>A second wave of changes came in the 1990s. Hybrid plans like Phoenix's pension equity plan, and another type, known as cash balance, seemed to solve several problems.</p>
        <p>These plans guarantee a fixed benefit, addressing both employees' insufficient contributions to 401(k)s and the uncontrollable costs of conventional defined benefit plans.</p>
        <p>In a cash balance plan, each employee gets a fixed percentage of salary -- typically 5 or 6 percent -- each year plus an interest credit that is usually pegged to United States Treasury bill rates. In a pension equity plan, the amount an employee gets is based on a percentage of the average salary earned in the final few years on the job. In either case, the company does not owe anything beyond that employee payment.</p>
        <p>The growth of hybrid plans slowed drastically in 2003, when a federal court ruled that I.B.M.'s cash balance plan discriminated against older employees.</p>
        <p>The gates reopened last year, thanks to new federal legislation and court decisions upholding plans at I.B.M. and elsewhere. Since October, at least three big companies besides Phoenix have announced that they were adopting these plans. Steven J. Kerstein, a managing director at Towers Perrin, a benefits consulting firm in Stamford, Conn., predicts that more than half of all large companies will switch.</p>
        <p>Paul Strella, a partner at Mercer Human Resources Consulting in New York City, said, ''Anybody looking at plan design is going to at least look at whether cash balance and pension equity are right for them.'' .</p>
        <p>In the newest hybrids, companies are tweaking the benefits to protect older employees. Experts say these hybrids represent the best chance to preserve anything close to the traditional model, in which companies provide the money for retirement.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, not all employees take the same career path, so not all will benefit from hybrids. To complicate matters, plans vary in detail.</p>
        <p>Although I.B.M. won its age-discrimination lawsuit on appeal, experts agree that older workers generally fare better with traditional plans because the benefit jumps significantly in an employee's last few years. Norman Stein, a law professor at the University of Alabama who specializes in pension issues, has calculated that ''it is somewhere around age 40 that the traditional plan becomes more valuable.'' Mr. Strella, the Mercer consultant, put the transition period in the mid-50s.</p>
        <p>Accordingly, most companies that now change their plans let employees in the range of 40 and older choose to stay with the old plan or switch. As further protection for these workers, some hybrids slightly increase the percentage of pay that workers get in accordance with age and seniority.</p>
        <p>The FedEx Corporation, which adopted a voluntary cash balance plan in 2003 and will make it mandatory in 2008, allocates extra benefit credits to employees 40 and over.</p>
        <p>''If the company gives a choice, that basically mitigates the losses'' related to age, said Karen Friedman, the policy director of the Pension Rights Center, an advocacy group for employees.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the biggest losers are people who had hoped to retire at age 55 or 60. That is because traditional plans, unlike hybrids, often include incentives that let employees retire before age 65 with bigger pensions than they normally would be entitled to. When this factor is added to the loss of the traditional plan's end-of-career tilt, without any compensating credits or choice, ''many workers lose 50 percent of their expected benefits,'' Ms. Friedman said.</p>
        <p>People who change jobs often do best in the hybrid plans.</p>
        <p>In a traditional plan, people who leave a job in midcareer forgo the late-stage jump in benefits. But since there are no late-stage jumps in cash balance plans, people miss little if they move from job to job.</p>
        <p>For people who stay in jobs ''less than 20 years, which is typical, the earnings could be two to three times greater'' in a cash balance plan, said Kevin Wagner, a senior retirement consultant in the Detroit office of Watson Wyatt Worldwide.</p>
        <p>Pension equity plans suffer the same disadvantages as conventional pensions in this instance because both are usually based on the salary at the end of the career.</p>
        <p>Pension equity and cash balance plans give job hoppers a more controversial perk. Workers can take their money as a lump sum when they leave. ''It puts a lot more of your retirement future in your own hands,'' said Mr. DePonte, the Phoenix employee. But experts fear that they might spend that windfall instead of saving it.</p>
        <p>People who expect generous salary raises may prefer to stick with conventional pension plans. ''If your pay is growing rapidly, then a traditional plan is usually better for you because your whole benefit is based upon your final years' pay,'' said Ari Jacobs, a consultant at Hewitt Associates, a firm in Lincolnshire, Ill.</p>
        <p>The advantages and disadvantages can boil down to gut feelings. When FedEx began its voluntary cash balance plan four years ago, about 10 percent of the eligible employees chose it, said John Merino, the chief accounting officer.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people made the decision not so much on the dollars and cents, but in terms of the portability,'' he said. ''Also, there were those who valued a dollar in hand as opposed to a stream of payments in the future. It was a personal choice.''</p>
        <p>PENSIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
