<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rollins Gives Shea Fans All They Could Hope For</title>
    <meta content="10curry" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/sports/baseball/10curry.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839346"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Philadelphia Phillies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Philadelphia Phillies</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E1DB153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="814" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rollins Gives Shea Fans All They Could Hope For</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rollins Gives Shea Fans All They Could Hope For</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the Mets were enjoying a giddy seven-run eighth inning, the fans at Shea Stadium picked a perfect time to torment their newest enemy by chanting, ''Jim-my Roll-ins, Jim-my Roll-ins.'' They chanted Rollins's name again and again, the sarcasm increasing with each syllable.</p>
        <p>Rollins knew he would be a verbal target yesterday because he said before the season that the Philadelphia Phillies would be the team to beat in the National League East. So what if the Mets won the division by 12 games last season. Rollins liked his Phillies and he let everyone know it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the Mets were enjoying a seven-run inning, the fans at Shea Stadium picked a perfect time to torment their newest enemy, Phillies shortstop Jimmy Rollins.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the Mets were enjoying a giddy seven-run eighth inning, the fans at Shea Stadium picked a perfect time to torment their newest enemy by chanting, ''Jim-my Roll-ins, Jim-my Roll-ins.'' They chanted Rollins's name again and again, the sarcasm increasing with each syllable.</p>
        <p>Rollins knew he would be a verbal target yesterday because he said before the season that the Philadelphia Phillies would be the team to beat in the National League East. So what if the Mets won the division by 12 games last season. Rollins liked his Phillies and he let everyone know it.</p>
        <p>But a week into the season, Rollins's words seem imprudent. A week into the season, the Phillies are improbably trying to ensure that 2007 does not slip away in April. Rollins and the Phillies looked sluggish as they botched a two-run lead and lost to the Mets, 11-5.</p>
        <p>What made the day especially delightful for the 56,227 fans was the way in which Rollins, the shortstop they love to hate, contributed to Philadelphia's loss. Rollins bobbled José Reyes's bases-loaded grounder in the eighth, allowing the Mets to score the tying run and helping them continue pounding the Philadelphia bullpen.</p>
        <p>Rollins said that because the speedy Reyes had hit the ball to his backhand side, he tried to be too quick to turn what could have been an inning-ending double play. It would have taken a superb play by Rollins to turn two on Reyes, but he did not even get one. Then the inning kept going and going.</p>
        <p>''We believe in ourselves,'' Rollins said, still talking positively. ''It's not where we want to be.''</p>
        <p>The Phillies stumbled to 1-6, the 12th time in franchise history that they have lost six of their first seven games. Charlie Manuel, who looked forlorn as he lingered in the dugout longer than anyone after the game, may not last as manager until May if the Phillies do not show significant improvement soon.</p>
        <p>''We got to fix our team,'' he said.</p>
        <p>There is a lot to fix. After Rollins's error, reliever Geoff Geary uncorked a 1-0 fastball to Paul Lo Duca that Carlos Ruiz would have needed stilts to catch. The ball glanced off Ruiz's glove and enabled José Valentín to score the go-ahead run. That sequence has typified Philadelphia's season.</p>
        <p>Geary said: ''It was over Carlos's head. Don't get me wrong. I wasn't trying to throw a pitch 10 feet over Carlos's head.''</p>
        <p>With the Phillies disintegrating at all the wrong times and in all the wrong areas, Rollins still smiled in a subdued clubhouse. He said that he liked being serenaded by the fans at Shea Stadium and considered it a bit of an honor. The fans do not usually boo boring or mediocre players.</p>
        <p>''They're fans,'' Rollins said. ''They're supposed to get under your skin. It's fun.''</p>
        <p>Rollins waved to some fans behind the third-base dugout after the eighth inning mercifully ended, but he laughed and said that he could not repeat what they were yelling at him. Before and after the game, Rollins said he still believed that the Phillies were the team to beat in the division and that he did not regret his off-season remarks.</p>
        <p>''Our record doesn't show that, but, shoot, that's the beauty of the season,'' he said. ''You have times when you're up and times when you're down.''</p>
        <p>For seven innings, it looked as if the Phillies might be up. Ryan Howard must have licked his lips when Manager Willie Randolph did not summon the left-handed reliever Pedro Feliciano in the sixth inning, and Howard promptly blasted a three-run homer off the right-handed Ambiorix Burgos. Howard's first homer of the season gave the Phillies a 5-3 lead.</p>
        <p>When Shane Victorino made a nifty diving catch on David Wright's sinking liner to right field to end the seventh and strand two runners, the Phillies were still up. When third baseman Abraham Núñez fielded Valentín's bunt and threw to Rollins at third to nail the lead runner in the eighth, the Phillies were still up.</p>
        <p>But after Geary's four-pitch walk to the pinch-hitter Julio Franco loaded the bases, Rollins tried to be too quick on Reyes's grounder and then Geary threw a wild pitch. Suddenly, the eighth inning was about the Phillies flopping and the fans happily reminding Rollins that they did not look like the class of the N.L. East.</p>
        <p>''If we talk, we got to back it up,'' Manuel said. ''That's how we look at it.''</p>
        <p>Manuel probably does not want to study the history of the other Phillies teams that started 1-6. The 1977 Phillies rebounded to win 101 games and the N.L. East, but seven other clubs finished under .500 and three landed in last place.</p>
        <p>These Phillies are a long way from being the team to beat, as Rollins predicted. Right now, they look like a beaten team.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
