<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>4 Bank Robbery Suspects Are Arraigned in Newark</title>
    <meta content="10bank" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/nyregion/10bank.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839319"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Newark (NJ)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E0DC153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="702" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>4 Bank Robbery Suspects Are Arraigned in Newark</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">4 Bank Robbery Suspects Are Arraigned in Newark</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD G. JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jones, Richard G</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, April 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One stared straight ahead, impassively. Another kept shaking his head and closing his eyes as though trying to extinguish a bad dream. A third wept. And the fourth kept telling his lawyer that he wanted to kill himself.</p>
        <p>Hands and feet shackled, four men from New Brunswick suspected in a string of bank robberies -- the most recent of which, last week, led to the fatal shooting of an F.B.I. agent -- were arraigned in federal court here on Monday on charges of attempted armed robbery. United States Magistrate Judge Madeline Cox Arleo ordered them held without bail pending a yet-unscheduled hearing, and their lawyers did not request anything less.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEWARK, April 9  One stared straight ahead, impassively. Another kept shaking his head and closing his eyes as though trying to extinguish a bad dream. A third wept. And the fourth kept telling his lawyer that he wanted to kill himself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One stared straight ahead, impassively. Another kept shaking his head and closing his eyes as though trying to extinguish a bad dream. A third wept. And the fourth kept telling his lawyer that he wanted to kill himself.</p>
        <p>Hands and feet shackled, four men from New Brunswick suspected in a string of bank robberies -- the most recent of which, last week, led to the fatal shooting of an F.B.I. agent -- were arraigned in federal court here on Monday on charges of attempted armed robbery. United States Magistrate Judge Madeline Cox Arleo ordered them held without bail pending a yet-unscheduled hearing, and their lawyers did not request anything less.</p>
        <p>Even as the suspects made their first court appearance, federal investigators continued to search for additional members of the gang they say is responsible for at least four holdups in the last two months.</p>
        <p>The authorities also continued to piece together details of the slaying of Barry Lee Bush, 52, a 19-year veteran of the Federal Bureau of Investigation who, officials said, was struck by a fellow F.B.I. agent's bullet.</p>
        <p>And after court on Monday afternoon, a lawyer for Francisco Herrera-Genao, one of the suspected robbers, shed new light on the chain of events that led to his client's capture early Friday morning after an overnight manhunt involving some 300 officers.</p>
        <p>The lawyer, John C. Sinuk, said that after Mr. Herrera-Genao fled the scene of the shooting outside the PNC Bank in Readington Township, N.J., on Thursday morning he spent much of the rest of the day traveling four miles east toward Branchburg.</p>
        <p>Once night fell, Mr. Sinuk said, a despondent Mr. Herrera-Genao -- who Mr. Sinuk said suffers from depression -- tried to commit suicide by jumping into a small pond.</p>
        <p>''He tried to drown himself in the water but it was all muddy,'' Mr. Sinuk said. So Mr. Herrera-Genao, who Mr. Sinuk said had shed his shirt and lost a shoe while eluding officers, spent a cold, wet night by the pond until officers found him covered in mud the next morning.</p>
        <p>When he was captured, the authorities said, Mr. Herrera-Genao begged the arresting officers to kill him. Mr. Sinuk said on Monday that his client was still suicidal, and that before the hearing with Judge Arleo, Mr. Herrera-Genao had told him: ''John, don't worry about it; I'm going to die anyway. I don't want to live.''</p>
        <p>''He's in it pretty deep right now,'' Mr. Sinuk said.</p>
        <p>During the hearing, Mr. Herrera-Genao, 22, listened intently as a court interpreter translated Judge Arleo's questions into Spanish. He answered in English ''Yes'' to inquiries as to whether he understood the charges and whether he had retained a lawyer.</p>
        <p>To Mr. Herrera-Genao's right was Wilfredo Berrios, 28, who showed little emotion during the 20-minute hearing. To Mr. Herrera-Genao's left was Michael Cruz, 21, who had a quizzical expression on his face throughout the hearing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cruz, Mr. Berrios and Mr. Herrera-Genao were each charged with attempted armed robbery in connection with Thursday's botched robbery attempt in Readington, although the authorities have said that additional charges may be filed in connection with Mr. Bush's death.</p>
        <p>The fourth suspect, Efrain Lynn, 21, was charged with a previous bank robbery, in South Brunswick, N.J. on March 16. He sat closest to the row of spectators in the courtroom and wept through much of the hearing. As Mr. Lynn tried to wipe his eyes with his cuffed hands, a young woman sobbed in the back row.</p>
        <p>On the other side of the courtroom, seated in the spectators' section behind Julia Epstein, an assistant United States attorney, was a row of F.B.I. agents. Other agents who could not find seats in the narrow courtroom crowded into an aisle.</p>
        <p>After the hearing ended, Charles McKenna, a federal prosecutor, said that the case against the men would be presented to a grand jury, which could decide within a month whether additional charges were warranted.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lynn's mother died in a car crash last year. As Jose Nieves, 60, her companion, left the courthouse, he said he was still shocked. ''What can I say? It's sad that this happened. He's a good kid, but he followed the wrong kind of people.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
