<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inspections For Rodents To Be Stricter</title>
    <meta content="10rats" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/nyregion/10rats.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839345"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Rats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Greenwich Village (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E1DB153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inspections For Rodents To Be Stricter</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Inspections for Rodents to Be Stricter</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANE CARDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cardwell, Diane</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The city's Health Department is revamping the way it inspects restaurants for potential rodent infestation after a review prompted by a widely seen news video of rats swarming in a KFC/Taco Bell in Greenwich Village, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The announcement came on the same day that the inspector who gave the restaurant a passing grade resigned, just as the Department of Investigation released its recommendation that she be fired.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The city’s Health Department is revamping the way it inspects restaurants for potential rodent infestation after a review prompted by a video of rats swarming in a Greenwich Village fast-food eatery.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The city's Health Department is revamping the way it inspects restaurants for potential rodent infestation after a review prompted by a widely seen news video of rats swarming in a KFC/Taco Bell in Greenwich Village, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The announcement came on the same day that the inspector who gave the restaurant a passing grade resigned, just as the Department of Investigation released its recommendation that she be fired.</p>
        <p>Officials of the Department of Investigation said the inspector, Cemone Thomas, may have performed a shoddy inspection -- done the day before the video was broadcast -- to avoid the time it would take to follow up on evidence of rodent infestation. The report found no indication of bribery or other criminal activity.</p>
        <p>At two telephone numbers thought to be Ms. Thomas's, those answering the calls said she was not there.</p>
        <p>Both agencies found broader problems in the way the city handles complaints about rodent infestation in restaurants, and health officials said that in response they would create a new system.</p>
        <p>''We have identified weaknesses in our system for handling restaurant complaints and combating rodent infestations,'' Dr. Thomas R. Frieden, commissioner of the Department of Health and Mental Hygiene, said. Calling rats ''an unfortunate fact of urban life,'' he said that they were not associated with illness in New York City, but that the department needed to do better in ensuring that restaurants prevent and control infestations.</p>
        <p>Under the current system, the Health Department review found, severe infestations can go unnoticed because a complaint to the 311 hot line about rodents in a restaurant generally spurs only a warning letter, not an inspection. Some other types of complaints -- including those about the use of nonpasteurized milk or the presence of raw sewage -- do require an inspection within varying time frames.</p>
        <p>Additional rodent complaints within 21 days are treated as duplicates and do not prompt additional warnings or action, although officials may inspect if further complaints are received 22 to 60 days after the first one.</p>
        <p>Now, officials said, the department plans to more actively monitor records from 311 for repeated complaints of infestation, and set a lower threshold for inspection.</p>
        <p>The department also plans to change the way it evaluates restaurants, to focus more on conditions that can give rise to an infestation. The current system puts a greater emphasis on direct signs of pests, like droppings.</p>
        <p>In addition, health officials plan to better coordinate the food safety and pest control divisions, develop better methods to measure the severity of infestations, and verify compliance with requirements. They also plan to require more training of restaurant operators with violations and may amend the health code to emphasize rodent prevention.</p>
        <p>In its review of Ms. Thomas's performance, Health Department officials did not find a pattern of poor performance, but said she admitted failing to report violations she observed in her February inspection of the KFC/Taco Bell. According to health officials, Ms. Thomas did not report violations that were severe enough for the department to automatically fail or close the restaurant.</p>
        <p>In her inspection, on Feb. 22, she identified three areas with a total of 76 to 87 rat droppings, as well as a 15-inch hole in the kitchen's dishwasher area where rats could enter from other parts of the building, but did not tell her supervisor about other conditions she noticed indicating that rodents were present, the Health Department report says.</p>
        <p>Health and Investigation officials said that the conditions mentioned in Ms. Thomas's report, though incomplete, were severe enough that when a supervisor, Marina Politis, learned of them, she should have ordered a full inspection of the restaurant, which could have produced a failing grade that would have closed the restaurant.</p>
        <p>The Department of Investigation report says that Ms. Politis did not correctly interpret the Health Department's scoring guidelines, and health officials said that she was being reassigned and would not keep her supervisory duties. Efforts last night to find Ms. Politis's telephone number were unsuccessful.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
