<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Youthful Chronicle Of Wartime In Prague</title>
    <meta content="10ginz" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/books/10ginz.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070414T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839270"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E5DD153FF933A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="967" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Youthful Chronicle Of Wartime In Prague</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Youthful Chronicle of Wartime in Prague</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ASHLEY PARKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Parker, Ashley</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first sign that things aren't quite right comes when Jews are required to wear a badge, a black and yellow star of David, on the outside of their clothes. And yet 13-year-old Petr Ginz remains wryly amused, writing in his diary: ''When I went to school, I counted sixty-nine 'sheriffs.' ''</p>
        <p>Such is the life of a young Czechoslovakian Jewish boy living in Prague in 1941, and it is a life that Petr meticulously documented in his diary until he was sent on a transport to Theresienstadt and, ultimately, to his death in an Auschwitz gas chamber two years later. On Sunday, to coincide with Holocaust Remembrance Day, Atlantic Monthly Press will officially release Petr's story, ''The Diary of Petr Ginz: 1941-1942.'' The book is already available in stores and online.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The forthcoming publication of “The Diary of Petr Ginz: 1941-1942” adds another adolescent voice to the literature of the Holocaust.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first sign that things aren't quite right comes when Jews are required to wear a badge, a black and yellow star of David, on the outside of their clothes. And yet 13-year-old Petr Ginz remains wryly amused, writing in his diary: ''When I went to school, I counted sixty-nine 'sheriffs.' ''</p>
        <p>Such is the life of a young Czechoslovakian Jewish boy living in Prague in 1941, and it is a life that Petr meticulously documented in his diary until he was sent on a transport to Theresienstadt and, ultimately, to his death in an Auschwitz gas chamber two years later. On Sunday, to coincide with Holocaust Remembrance Day, Atlantic Monthly Press will officially release Petr's story, ''The Diary of Petr Ginz: 1941-1942.'' The book is already available in stores and online.</p>
        <p>The publication adds another adolescent voice to the literature of the Holocaust. If Anne Frank's diary is her friend and confidante, full of flowery prose and hopes and dreams, Petr's offers an unsentimental perspective on his changing world, and one that fits his personality: half scientist, half reporter and all, still, little boy.</p>
        <p>''I think one of the reasons Petr wrote so laconically every day what happened was more that he wanted to make a document, like a newspaper writer, without any feelings, what really happened on these days,'' said his sister, Chava Pressburger, 77, who edited the diaries and wrote the book's introduction. ''I think he was feeling that he's living in an unusual period, and he wanted to document the facts.''</p>
        <p>Indeed. The weather changes, Petr does his homework, his family lights three Hanukkah candles. And then, one day, Jews can no longer sit in the front of trams and buses. Another day, Petr and his friends are supposed to have a race but, as he writes, ''it didn't happen, because some boys (age 14-15) kept throwing stones at us.'' So it goes. His tone is ''matter of fact but not dry,'' said the book's translator, Elena Lappin.</p>
        <p>''He wants to be precise, he doesn't want to forget things, but what's also very important is what he leaves out,'' Ms. Lappin said. ''He wants to make sure every day is captured, that he doesn't forget what he did each day, because I think he's already realizing that even though they may seem routine, his days are no longer routine. Nothing is routine anymore.''</p>
        <p>The one constant seems to be Petr's sense of mischief, which pervades the book, popping up in unlikely entries and understated asides. ''During recess at PE I locked the locker room with a wire with three trainers inside,'' he writes one day, and on another: ''We had a test in music; I didn't know anything, but I was clever enough to copy it.'' On April Fool's Day 1942, he recounts: ''We wanted to trick the teacher Mr. Beinkoles with an exploding pencil, but our attempt failed and B. confiscated our pencil with capsules. That's how our 1st of April turned out.''</p>
        <p>Still, underlying the frequent yet seemingly unconcerned entries is a sense of growing alarm -- if not for Petr, then certainly for his reader -- and he occasionally allows this unease to slip through.</p>
        <p>''In the morning I did my homework,'' he writes on Jan. 1, 1942. ''Otherwise nothing special. Actually, a lot is happening, but it is not even visible. What is quite ordinary now would certainly cause upset in a normal time.'' But then Petr just as soon moves on. The next day, he offers only one line: ''In the morning I did my homework, in the afternoon went for a walk.''</p>
        <p>The diaries came to light in 2003, discovered because of another tragedy: the explosion of the space shuttle Columbia on Feb. 1, the day Petr would have turned 75. On the flight Ilan Ramon, the first Israeli astronaut and the son of an Auschwitz survivor, had taken a pencil drawing by Petr, borrowed from the collection of the Yad Vashem Museum in Israel. When the shuttle exploded over Texas and the story of Petr's drawing was told, a man contacted Yad Vashem saying that he had discovered Petr's old copybooks in the attic of his home in Prague.</p>
        <p>''When I saw the pages from Petr's diary, I recognized immediately his handwriting, I remembered some of the events he was describing,'' Ms. Pressburger said from her home in Israel. ''I thought that it actually does not belong to me only, that if I may say so, it belongs to humanity.''</p>
        <p>At the recommendation of Ms. Lappin, who also scouts books, Atlantic Monthly Press snapped up the diary without any editor even having read it, making an early joint offer with its sister company in Britain, Atlantic Books. Originally published in the Czech Republic, ''The Diary of Petr Ginz'' has been published or is set to be published in more than 10 countries.</p>
        <p>The book also includes pictures of Petr and his family; a handful of his drawings and paintings; excerpts from Vedem, the weekly magazine he founded in Theresienstadt; and even two poems -- one about Prague and one, both angry and satiric, about the restrictions the Jews increasingly had to endure. One verse, as translated by Ms. Lappin, begins:</p>
        <p>And especially the outcast Jew  must give up all habits he knew:  he can't buy clothes, can't buy a shoe,  since dressing well is not his due.</p>
        <p>For the most part, however, Petr acts as a child historian, and this is where the book derives much of its haunting power.</p>
        <p>''This kind of belief that he's going to get past these circumstances was totally extraordinary,'' said Lauren Wein, a senior editor at Grove/Atlantic, the parent company of Atlantic Monthly Press. ''There's a lightness to it that belies the gravity of what's going on.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 14, 2007, Saturday  An article in The Arts on Tuesday about ''The Diary of Petr Ginz: 1941-1942,'' a teenager's chronicle of life in wartime Prague, omitted a translator of an untitled poem in the book that was quoted in the article. While Elena Lappin translated the book from the Czech, David Curzon helped her translate that poem and another in the book called ''Remembering Prague.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 14, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article in The Arts on Tuesday about ''The Diary of Petr Ginz: 1941-1942,'' a teenager's chronicle of life in wartime Prague, omitted a translator of an untitled poem in the book that was quoted in the article. While Elena Lappin translated the book from the Czech, David Curzon helped her translate that poem and another in the book called ''Remembering Prague.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
