<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Critic's Choice: New DVD's</title>
    <meta content="01dvd" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/movies/homevideo/01dvd.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844169"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Critics Choice"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/DVD and Video</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Ruth, Babe</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E6D9133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="993" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Critic's Choice: New DVD's</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New DVDs</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dave Kehr</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kehr, Dave</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Reel Baseball: 1899-1926</p>
        <p>I know about as much about baseball as I do about quantum physics, but I found much of the material in this two disc-set, recently released by Kino, absolutely fascinating. Cinephiles who reflexively avoid sports movies (not the most distinguished of genres) will find ''Reel Baseball: 1899-1926'' a thinly disguised attempt to smuggle some lesser-known early films onto the DVD market. Baseball fans will be delighted by the dramatic presence of a young, slim Babe Ruth, playing an imaginary version of himself in the 1920 feature ''Headin' Home,'' and by the great New York Giants manager John McGraw, playing himself in an excerpt from the 1917 Edison feature ''One Touch of Nature.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>I know about as much about baseball as I do about quantum physics, but I found much of the material in the two disc-set "Reel Baseball" absolutely fascinating.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Reel Baseball: 1899-1926</p>
        <p>I know about as much about baseball as I do about quantum physics, but I found much of the material in this two disc-set, recently released by Kino, absolutely fascinating. Cinephiles who reflexively avoid sports movies (not the most distinguished of genres) will find ''Reel Baseball: 1899-1926'' a thinly disguised attempt to smuggle some lesser-known early films onto the DVD market. Baseball fans will be delighted by the dramatic presence of a young, slim Babe Ruth, playing an imaginary version of himself in the 1920 feature ''Headin' Home,'' and by the great New York Giants manager John McGraw, playing himself in an excerpt from the 1917 Edison feature ''One Touch of Nature.''</p>
        <p>The DVD's producer, Jessica Rosner, a film scholar and baseball fan, chose the two features and 11 shorts in the collection, and covers a large range of materials. From the hand-cranked Bioscope days (spectators dropped a penny in a slot, then peered through a viewfinder to watch the brief action) comes the 1899 ''Casey at the Bat, or the Fate of a 'Rotten' Umpire,'' a one-minute film from the Edison company that depicts said umpire being beaten to a pulp by angry team members, a movie gag that remains an audience favorite to this day.</p>
        <p>The 1906 ''How the Office Boy Saw the Ball Game'' is another Edison title. (Exhibition had moved to the nickelodeons by then.) Here, an impish boy perches atop a telephone pole and peers into the Polo Grounds with a telescope; it's a disguised way of introducing audiences to the unnatural (at the time) sense of closeness created by the telephoto lens (much as George Albert Smith's British film of 1900, ''Grandma's Reading Glass,'' accustomed audiences to the shock of the close-up by presenting the magnified images ''as seen by'' a little girl playing with a magnifying glass).</p>
        <p>''Casey at the Bat'' returns for a 1922 short produced by Lee De Forest, an inventor who created an early sound-on-film process that failed to catch on. In this six-minute movie, the Broadway star DeWolf Hopper steps before a curtain to perform his famous interpretation of this dramatic poem, written by Ernest Thayer.</p>
        <p>As a narrative medium, movies made tremendous strides between 1906 and 1909, when the curious ''His Last Game'' was released, without any production credits, by the Independent Motion Picture Company (IMP), one of the companies later folded into Universal. The technique is not very advanced; this 12-minute film includes perhaps five or six shots, all from a static position. But the story is unusually pointed: a Choctaw Indian, the star pitcher of his local (integrated!) baseball team, is plied with drink by a pair of gamblers who want him to throw the game; in an argument he kills one of them and is immediately sentenced to death by firing squad.</p>
        <p>But as he is digging his own grave, the townspeople show up and press him into service for a game. He pitches, wins for the home team and then returns to the open grave, where he is summarily executed.</p>
        <p>The pro-Indian stance is quite typical for westerns, which have been caricatured for years as racist and genocidal, though I have yet to find an early one in which those sentiments were not placed in the mouths of villains: the evil Eastern capitalists who want to cleanse the West ethnically for their own purposes.</p>
        <p>The centerpiece of the program is ''Headin' Home,'' a 1920 feature, produced by the New York Yankees in the first year of Ruth's contract. The film, directed by Lawrence Windom, is an early piece of spin control: the hard-drinking, hard-living Ruth, who as a child was turned over by his saloon-owning parents to a strict orphanage and reform school in Baltimore, is shown as an aw-shucks village boy, living with his saintly widowed mother in a trellis-shaded home with his adorable kid sister, Pigtails (Frances Victory) and her adorable mutt, Herman. When Babe isn't rescuing Herman from the local dogcatcher, he's in the woods, chopping down trees to carve into baseball bats.</p>
        <p>Both ''Headin' Home'' and the other feature in the collection, Jerome Storm's 1919 film ''The Busher'' (Charles Ray as a rural boy who catches the attention of a major-league scout), suggest that even as early as the teens, baseball had already become symbolically associated with the nostalgia for small-town life that was growing as millions of Americans abandoned farms for the big cities.</p>
        <p>It's an association that Major League Baseball has done its best to shake off these last few years, probably to the sport's detriment. It isn't easy to recognize the contemporary sports industry in the pick-up games and casual attitudes in these early films, in which nary a sports agent appears, celebrity endorsements were not yet the norm, and anabolic steroids had not yet been discovered. (Kino International, $29.95, not rated)</p>
        <p>Also Out Today</p>
        <p>DREAMGIRLS -- Bill Condon's adaptation of the Broadway musical based on the rise and fall and rise of a female rhythm and blues group, starring Jamie Foxx, Beyoncé Knowles, Eddie Murphy and Jennifer Hudson, who won an Oscar for best supporting actress. It's available in four flavors: the two disc ''Showstopper'' edition ($34.99), the high-definition Blu-ray edition ($39.99) and two single-disc editions, one widescreen and one pan-and-scan ($29.99). (DreamWorks, PG-13)</p>
        <p>LITTLE CHILDREN -- From Tom Perrotta's novel, Todd Field's film compares and contrasts the plights of two unhappily married couples (Kate Winslet and Gregg Edelman; Jennifer Connelly and Patrick Wilson) and that of a convicted pedophile (an Oscar-nominated performance by the former child actor Jackie Earle Haley) who has been paroled from prison and is looking for a place where he might be allowed to live. (New Line, $27.98, R)</p>
        <p>OLD JOY -- Kelly Reichardt's acclaimed independent film, in which a pair of old college friends go on a camping trip and discover how much now separates them. (Kino International, $29.95, not rated)</p>
        <p>Dave Kehr  Critics Choice</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
