<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Simple Need, All Too Often Unmet</title>
    <meta content="01brod" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health&amp;Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/health/01brod.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844322"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PERSONAL HEALTH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Columns/Personal Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bathrooms and Toilets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bathrooms and Toilets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E0D6133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1176" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Simple Need, All Too Often Unmet</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Simple Need, All Too Often Unmet</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jane E. Brody</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a recent trip to Sydney, Australia, I discovered the true meaning of civilization -- public toilets, lots of them, clean, neat, safe, free of graffiti, working flushes and faucets, and well-stocked with toilet paper, along with paper towels or hand dryers. Most are free (some are automatic pay toilets) and available 24 hours. One free 24-hour toilet under the Darling Harbor Bridge appeared to have just been remodeled with colorful tiles.</p>
        <p>And these facilities are easy to find. Street signs point to their locations and indicate if they are accessible to people in wheelchairs or have changing tables for babies. In 10 days of walking all over the city, I found not one public toilet that harbored drug users, vagrants, or people seeking sex.Then it was back to reality -- New York City, where the decades-long promise of decent public toilets has thus far proved more fragile than toilet tissue. I've yet to see any of the contracted-for 20 public toilets that Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg promised to have open by this year (installation is scheduled to begin this summer). And 20 scattered through the five boroughs is hardly sufficient for a city of 8.2 million people that gets 40 million tourists a year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The expression “When you’ve got to go, you’ve got to go” is more often true than not. But where?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a recent trip to Sydney, Australia, I discovered the true meaning of civilization -- public toilets, lots of them, clean, neat, safe, free of graffiti, working flushes and faucets, and well-stocked with toilet paper, along with paper towels or hand dryers. Most are free (some are automatic pay toilets) and available 24 hours. One free 24-hour toilet under the Darling Harbor Bridge appeared to have just been remodeled with colorful tiles.</p>
        <p>And these facilities are easy to find. Street signs point to their locations and indicate if they are accessible to people in wheelchairs or have changing tables for babies. In 10 days of walking all over the city, I found not one public toilet that harbored drug users, vagrants, or people seeking sex.Then it was back to reality -- New York City, where the decades-long promise of decent public toilets has thus far proved more fragile than toilet tissue. I've yet to see any of the contracted-for 20 public toilets that Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg promised to have open by this year (installation is scheduled to begin this summer). And 20 scattered through the five boroughs is hardly sufficient for a city of 8.2 million people that gets 40 million tourists a year.</p>
        <p>In case you're thinking this is not a health issue, think again. The stench of urine on subway platforms, city streets and building alcoves, the occasional deposit of human waste, and the desperation experienced by those in dire need of a safe, clean and open facility add up to a public health problem in my book.</p>
        <p>Need vs. Reality</p>
        <p>I'll never forget what I saw years ago from my Times Square office window. It was not yet theater time and all the nearby restaurants had signs saying ''Restrooms for customers only.'' A well-dressed woman standing near Shubert Alley had an accident in the middle of the sidewalk and collapsed in tears in her companion's arms.</p>
        <p>No one should have to suffer such humiliation. The expression ''When you've got to go, you've got to go'' is more often true than not. But where?</p>
        <p>The problem in New York City is more than a century old. In 1898, the Citizens Union, in its first pamphlet, decried the city's lack of public toilets. Now, when the word to the health-wise is to stay well hydrated and millions of people walk around with water bottles, the need for readily accessible toilets is that much greater.</p>
        <p>Near my neighborhood in Brooklyn, the beautiful 585-acre Prospect Park has 10 restrooms, few of them open during nonbusiness hours and several open only sporadically. It's a 10-minute walk to the nearest facility for the hundreds of young children who visit the park's Third Street playground. Small children are notorious for waiting until the last minute, and many of them -- girls as well as boys -- wind up using the ground.</p>
        <p>Adults, too, are often forced to use the great outdoors, like a large stand of bamboo (now cut down) that long provided some privacy midpark.</p>
        <p>New York is not alone in its shortage of public toilets. London, once a sterling example of a city that took toilets seriously, is busily shutting down many of them and letting others go to ruin.</p>
        <p>City government is not always to blame. Community groups sometimes organize opposition to public toilets. In 2001, residents of the Holliswood section of Queens blocked construction of a two-toilet comfort station in a local playground, saying it would fall into disrepair and attract child molesters and vagrants.</p>
        <p>My suggestion some years ago that 24-hour portable toilets be placed strategically around Prospect Park was ignored. I was told that they would be chronically vandalized, overturned by rambunctious teenagers. Minneapolis circumvented this problem by surrounding its lakeside portable toilets with a brick or concrete structure, but that idea too was ultimately rejected.</p>
        <p>Most of New York's public toilets are in city parks, and many are in terrible condition and dangerous, hangouts for ne'er-do-wells. As for subway toilets, most are permanently closed, apparently to discourage criminal activity.</p>
        <p>Planning Ahead</p>
        <p>I've met many women who limit their consumption of liquids, ignore thirst and even risk dehydration for fear that they would have to find a public facility. From a health standpoint, this is a highly undesirable solution. My own approach, whether traveling by subway, car or on foot, is to be sure to use the toilet just before leaving home, office, restaurant, museum or theater.</p>
        <p>But if you are caught out and about and in need of relief in any American city, here are some suggestions. Most hotels and motels have clean, safe, free restrooms in their lobbies, though you may have to tip an attendant. Department stores have them as well (some also have an attendant), though usually on an upper floor and in the back of the store.</p>
        <p>Although most restaurants restrict use of their facilities to paying customers, fast-food establishments like McDonald's and Starbucks exert no control over who uses the toilets. If necessary, though, I wouldn't hesitate to plead with a headwaiter to allow me to use the restroom in a fancier restaurant. I once intervened at an upscale restaurant on behalf of a guest conductor for the New York Philharmonic who had prostate problems and simply couldn't wait.</p>
        <p>My advice: If you're desperate, don't take no for an answer.</p>
        <p>Many museums have bathrooms on the ground level that are accessible before paying an entrance fee. And public libraries, when they are open, always have free toilets. Hospitals, which are always open, and health clinics also have free, clean bathrooms accessible to the public.</p>
        <p>Chain bookstores like Barnes &amp; Noble and Borders have free public toilets. Big businesses like Target and Wal-Mart, warehouse stores, and many suburban supermarkets have accessible toilets. Sometimes you may have to ask for a key.</p>
        <p>In Manhattan, the 34th Street Partnership gave up waiting for the city to act and installed two automatic public toilets in Greeley Square and Herald Square. Users pay 25 cents for a 20-minute visit. As with the public toilets in San Francisco, these are clean and disinfect themselves after each use.</p>
        <p>San Francisco, by the way, has at least 17 of the self-cleaning public toilets that are wheelchair-accessible and have received good ratings from users. Admittedly, some of the remaining eight computerized restrooms have proved to be havens for drug users and prostitutes, who figured out how to bypass the 20-minute limit, after which the doors open automatically.</p>
        <p>Some Online Help</p>
        <p>In researching this topic on the Web, I came across an invaluable site that lists, describes and rates toilet facilities in cities throughout the world. Whether you stay close to home or are planning a trip, say, to China, Turkey or South Africa, you may want to check out www.thebathroomdiaries.com and print out the list of public facilities in the cities you plan to visit.</p>
        <p>For example, to find public restrooms in San Francisco, click on USA, which brings up scores of American cities. Then click on San Francisco and be amazed.</p>
        <p>PERSONAL HEALTH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
