<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two All-Stars Push Each Other, and the Nets, to New Heights</title>
    <meta content="01nba" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844337"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL: ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00EED6133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="899" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two All-Stars Push Each Other, and the Nets, to New Heights</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Coming off a two-game tour de force, the Nets stars Jason Kidd and Vince Carter are showing why they may be considered among the N.B.A.'s greatest perimeter tandems. But they are still without a championship, and their place in history remains to be determined.</p>
        <p>For now, the Nets will gladly leave that debate in the air, so long as they continue to get the panache from Kidd and Carter that vaulted them to consecutive victories against the Toronto Raptors and a 3-1 advantage in their first-round Eastern Conference playoff series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Coming off a two-game tour de force, the Nets stars Jason Kidd and Vince Carter are showing why they may be considered among the N.B.A.'s greatest perimeter tandems. But they are still without a championship, and their place in history remains to be determined.</p>
        <p>For now, the Nets will gladly leave that debate in the air, so long as they continue to get the panache from Kidd and Carter that vaulted them to consecutive victories against the Toronto Raptors and a 3-1 advantage in their first-round Eastern Conference playoff series.</p>
        <p>The Nets can advance to the conference semifinals with a victory in Toronto tonight.</p>
        <p>If Kidd and Carter continue the dominance they displayed in the previous two games, they could make a strong claim as the best backcourt tandem in these playoffs.</p>
        <p>The Detroit Pistons' Chauncey Billups and Richard Hamilton already have a championship ring each, and their team is favored to win the Eastern Conference title. The Chicago Bulls' Ben Gordon and Kirk Hinrich are a precocious pair that just helped their team sweep the defending N.B.A. champion Miami Heat. The Golden State Warriors' Baron Davis and Stephen Jackson, playing with a starting lineup of essentially five perimeter players, have helped push the Dallas Mavericks, the Western Conference's top-seeded team, to the brink of elimination.</p>
        <p>But even these perimeter pairings would have a difficult time matching what Kidd and Carter did in Games 3 and 4.</p>
        <p>Kidd averaged 16.5 points, 16 assists and 12 rebounds in the two games and shot 54.2 percent from the field. In Game 3, Kidd became the third player in postseason history to record at least 15 points, 15 rebounds and 15 assists in a game. Carter averaged 32 points and shot 61.2 percent in the two games. Both players could have had triple-doubles in Game 4, but Kidd sat out the fourth quarter and Carter sat out the game's final 10 minutes.</p>
        <p>''I think the thing that's unique about Jason and Vince is that they compete for each other,'' Nets Coach Lawrence Frank said. ''Sometimes, you have situations where you have two high-level All-Stars, they compete against each other. These guys totally relish in making sure the other one plays well.''</p>
        <p>Kidd seems to have an innate ability to get Carter going. When the Nets returned to New Jersey for Game 3 on Friday night, Carter was coming off disappointing performances in the first two games, when he averaged 17.5 points and shot 30.2 percent. But Carter was on point from the start of Game 3, and Kidd assisted him on 10 of his first 11 field goals. In Game 4, Kidd got Carter going with assists on 4 of his first 7 field goals. Carter returned the favor by assisting Kidd on 4 of his 6 field goals in Game 4.</p>
        <p>''We're trying to just make plays for ourselves, but also each other,'' Carter said. ''We feed off each other, we work well off each other.''</p>
        <p>Kidd, perhaps getting in touch with his inner perfectionist, has not been quick to crown himself or Carter. After his excellent Game 3, Kidd asked, ''What have I accomplished?'' After Game 4, he suggested Carter could find yet another gear.</p>
        <p>''Vince is playing some of his best basketball,'' Kidd said. ''I wouldn't say it's his best because, as teammates and professionals, we always want him to give us more. For him, he can't settle.''</p>
        <p>Kidd knows that in order for he and Carter to truly excel, they must do so in a hostile environment. Carter, a former Raptors star, has been especially subpar in front of his former home fans. In addition to his struggles in Toronto in Games 1 and 2, Carter averaged only 14.5 points and shot 28.1 percent in two regular-season games there.</p>
        <p>Kidd, despite averaging a triple-double in this series (13.8 points, 13.5 assists and 11.3 rebounds), struggled to make shots in the opening games.</p>
        <p>With the Raptors' season on the line tonight, there is little doubt that the Nets will be tested by the Toronto players and their raucous fans.</p>
        <p>''The hardest part about the playoffs,'' Kidd said, ''is being able to end a series.''</p>
        <p>SPURS 96, NUGGETS 89 -- Tim Duncan scored 22 points as visiting San Antonio took a 3-1 lead in the Western Conference series with its third straight victory. Carmelo Anthony led the Nuggets with 29 points and Allen Iverson had 22. (AP)</p>
        <p>CAVALIERS 97, WIZARDS 90 -- Cleveland completed a playoff sweep for the first time in franchise history, defeating host Washington with yet another unconvincing performance. LeBron James labored through an 8-for-22 shooting effort, but he made 14 of 17 free throws to finish with 31 points for the Cavaliers. (AP)</p>
        <p>ROCKETS 96, JAZZ 92 -- Tracy McGrady had 26 points and a career-high 16 assists as Houston defeated visiting Utah to take a 3-2 lead in their first-round series. Yao Ming scored 21 points, sealing the victory with two free throws with 11 seconds left. Yao also grabbed 15 rebounds. Game 6 is Thursday in Utah. (AP)</p>
        <p>DUNCAN HEADS ALL-DEFENSIVE TEAM -- Tim Duncan was named to the N.B.A. all-defensive first team for the 10th time yesterday, and his San Antonio teammate Bruce Bowen was the top vote-getter in being selected for the seventh time. Nets guard Jason Kidd was named to the second team. (AP)</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL: ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
