<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Day After a Fiery Crash, Bay Area Commuters Enjoy a Surprisingly Easy Ride</title>
    <meta content="01truck" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/us/01truck.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844302"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">San Francisco-Oakland Bay Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">San Francisco Bay Area (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Archibold, Randal C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Oakland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Oakland (Calif)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E4D6133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="878" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Day After a Fiery Crash, Bay Area Commuters Enjoy a Surprisingly Easy Ride</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Day After a Fiery Crash, Bay Area Commuters Enjoy a Surprisingly Easy Ride</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JESSE McKINLEY; Carolyn Marshall contributed reporting from Oakland, and Anahad O'Connor from New York.</byline>
      <dateline>OAKLAND, Calif., April 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Most major highway overpasses and bridges are not fireproof and probably never will be; fierce fires like one that warped and collapsed overpass of San Francisco Bay bridge connector on April 29 are considered anomalies in structural engineering world; engineers say applying fire-resistant materials to bridges and overpasses would substantially drive up costs for rare event (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A day after a fiery gasoline tanker crash melted and collapsed a critical highway interchange near the San Francisco-Oakland Bay Bridge, drivers in the Bay Area enjoyed a relatively painless commute on Monday as an expected rush hour nightmare largely failed to materialize.</p>
        <p>But officials warned that things could get worse as repairs continue and the thrill of mass transit fades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The commute was relatively painless for Bay Area drivers, as an expected rush hour nightmare largely failed to materialize.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A day after a fiery gasoline tanker crash melted and collapsed a critical highway interchange near the San Francisco-Oakland Bay Bridge, drivers in the Bay Area enjoyed a relatively painless commute on Monday as an expected rush hour nightmare largely failed to materialize.</p>
        <p>But officials warned that things could get worse as repairs continue and the thrill of mass transit fades.</p>
        <p>Gov. Arnold Schwarzenegger authorized state funds to pay for a day of free public transit around the bay on Monday, and by and large, traffic around the collapsed overpass was light during the morning and early evening commutes.</p>
        <p>The combination of telecommuting, free rides and good old absenteeism kept many workers off the roads. Trains were running half full for much of the day on Bay Area Rapid Transit lines, the region's light rail system and the additional ferries that plied the waters between San Francisco and the cities on the eastern side of San Francisco Bay had plenty of spare seats.</p>
        <p>''This morning was one of the easiest commutes I've ever had,'' said Jared Hirsch, associate production manager for American Conservatory Theater in San Francisco, who drives to work from Oakland. ''I think people, assuming that this evening's would be one of the worst commutes ever, elected to either take public transportation or stay at home.''</p>
        <p>The evening commute was, in fact, heavier than the morning one, as homebound workers from San Francisco and Silicon Valley traveling off the Bay Bridge to the suburbs east of Oakland were confronted with the collapsed overpass of eastbound Interstate 580.</p>
        <p>That section of roadway fell on a section of southbound Interstate 880, a north-south corridor that connects San Jose in the south with cities like Berkeley. The two roadways, in the heart of a tangle of freeways at the approach to the bridge known as the MacArthur Maze, are used by an estimated 160,000 cars daily. (Westbound 580 and northbound 880 were not damaged.)</p>
        <p>Diverted traffic was spilling into the streets of Oakland, including West Grand Avenue, a four-lane surface street turned potential superhighway. Some congestion resulted. Across the bay in San Francisco, Mayor Gavin Newsom said that while ''a very successful effort'' by various regional leaders had made Monday manageable, commuter cooperation was often short-lived.</p>
        <p>''By no stretch of the imagination is there anyone who believes we are out of the woods,'' Mr. Newsom said. And, sure enough, trains, ferries and freeways were fuller in the evening, though patience-trying waits are often the norm in California.</p>
        <p>Still, the lighter-than-normal morning rush kept diverted traffic moving along on Monday.</p>
        <p>''There's backup where the detour is coming into the maze, but I wouldn't call it excessive,'' said Sgt. Les Bishop of the California Highway Patrol. ''You are going to have motorists that are relearning the roadways, but I would assume that's going to smooth out as everybody figures out what the new flow is.''</p>
        <p>The highway patrol believes that the driver of the tanker, James Mosqueda, 51, was speeding with a full load of gasoline about 3:42 a.m. when he lost control on a curve, hit a guardrail and flipped the vehicle on to its side.</p>
        <p>The resulting fire, which shot flames high into the early morning sky, buckled a concrete and steel overpass above, sending it crashing onto the highway. Mr. Mosqueda, of Woodland, Calif., remains hospitalized in San Francisco with second-degree burns. No other injuries were reported.</p>
        <p>Demolition crews worked through the early hours on Monday picking at the collapsed section of Interstate 580 with backhoes and cranes, working to remove some 700 feet of concrete off the highway below.</p>
        <p>Will Kempton, the director of CalTrans, the state transportation agency, said that after demolition of the upper portion engineers would be able see how much damage had been done to the roadway below.</p>
        <p>''If we determine there's structural damage,'' Mr. Kempton said of Interstate 880, ''all bets are off.''</p>
        <p>Margena Wade, a spokeswoman for the agency, said that ample news coverage -- some local television stations committed several hours of live coverage to the fire and collapse -- had helped keep road volume down. ''I suspect people heard the message,'' said Ms. Wade, standing near a pile of rubble amid the hammering of demolition crews.</p>
        <p>CalTrans would not speculate on either the cost of rebuilding or how long repairs might take.</p>
        <p>Aaron McLear, a spokesman for Mr. Schwarzenegger, said the governor had asked the Federal Highway Administration for financial help for rebuilding. The free rides on public transit were for Monday only, though Mr. McLear said the state planned to help pay for whatever additional mass transit was needed.</p>
        <p>For all the preliminary good news, officials in San Francisco and Oakland, the two cities connected by the Bay Bridge, were expecting a wide variety of potential problems in the weeks to come. Additional San Francisco police and parking control officers, for example, were being stationed at entrances to the bridge to help guide -- and calm -- drivers.</p>
        <p>''I definitely anticipate road rage,'' said Kelly Beardall, 37, a telecom technician who usually drives to work from his home in Walnut Creek, east of Oakland. ''When things change like this it takes very little to set people off.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
