<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Satire With the Blessing of Lady Luck Herself</title>
    <meta content="01heff" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/arts/television/01heff.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844187"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SCREENS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E3D9133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1230" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Satire With the Blessing of Lady Luck Herself</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Satire With the Blessing of Lady Luck Herself</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIRGINIA HEFFERNAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Heffernan, Virginia</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most humor sites begin when some smart-aleck at an old media company begins nagging: ''We have to launch a more robust entertainment vertical, guys.'' But Black20 has a cool creation myth.</p>
        <p>The story is so suspiciously cool, it puts Black20.com closer to an enterprise like ''Ocean's Eleven'' or ''Easy Rider'' than to a technobabble online initiative you'll never hear of again. (Then again, you never know.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Black20’s videos crack you up, again and again. These guys are on a roll.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Most humor sites begin when some smart-aleck at an old media company begins nagging: ''We have to launch a more robust entertainment vertical, guys.'' But Black20 has a cool creation myth.</p>
        <p>The story is so suspiciously cool, it puts Black20.com closer to an enterprise like ''Ocean's Eleven'' or ''Easy Rider'' than to a technobabble online initiative you'll never hear of again. (Then again, you never know.)</p>
        <p>The near-perfect story goes like this. Last year two young funnymen, J. Crowley and Neil Punsalan, promising self-starters at NBC, were feeling trapped. Jeff Zucker, the president and chief executive of NBC Universal, had personally green-lighted a broadband series they had pitched called ''Out of Context.'' They were in their 20s, they'd shot the series, and suddenly they had the run of NBC's brand-new digital studios department. That was exciting.</p>
        <p>What was less exciting were the budget cuts, when they came last year. ''Out of Context'' was losing support; NBC had other ideas about mobisodes, Webisodes, monetizing ringtones, something. At the same time Mr. Crowley and Mr. Punsalan felt pangs of longing watching the growth of the free-form, lawless YouTube. They should be doing that kind of low-budget D.I.Y. work, they thought, instead of punching the clock for the establishment.</p>
        <p>What would Dean Martin or Dennis Hopper do? The gang that would become Black20 -- Mr. Crowley, 27; Mr. Punsalan, 29; and two comic actors, Mike O'Gorman and Michael Torpey, both 27 -- pulled together thousands in unspent expense money and drove to Atlantic City. Fighting nausea, they loaded their shared assets on one spin of the roulette wheel. Black. Before they could fully feel their fear (and all this they caught on video), the wheel stopped. Black-20. They had doubled their investment.</p>
        <p>It was sign from Lady Luck and seed money all at once. Instantly they quit their jobs, incorporated and hired two nimble video editors, Mike Aransky and Tom Seymour. In online video editors rule, and Mr. Aransky and Mr. Seymour became the de facto directors of Black20.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Punsalan says with the blank absurdism that has quickly come to be the house style: ''We call Mike 'the Shot Doctor,' because he makes everything we do look good. We call Thomas 'Tom,' because he is so good at editing.''</p>
        <p>So what does Black20 do? Well, like a television studio it makes shows, and, like a television channel, it broadcasts them. From a loud office in Bushwick, Brooklyn -- made deafening every nine minutes by the overhead rattle of the subway -- Black20 manages to produce a slate of episodic shows, including a workplace comedy called ''net--work,'' a mockumentary series called ''The Middle Show'' and a news parody called ''BLACK20 News.''</p>
        <p>The site features new videos every day, which is impressive for a shoestring outfit. But Black20's prolificacy is matched by its brio. The videos crack you up, again and again. These guys are on a roll.</p>
        <p>This Web site looks surprisingly moody for comedy. The home page has rathskellar lighting and emo ambience. This is not inviting, but it pays off, partly just because it skips the cartoons and polka dots that promise more merriment than anyone has ever delivered. A couple of clicks on Black20's slightly gummy navigational spots and you land on exciting opportunities: ''White Stereotypes.'' ''Unpleasant Messages.'' ''Alec Baldwin's Daughter Calls Back.''</p>
        <p>The two ''White Stereotypes'' episodes of ''The Middle Show'' are inspired. In one of them, to the tune of Paul Simon's ''You Can Call Me Al,'' David Price, who resembles the British TV personality Louis Theroux, ventures into Union Square in Manhattan to discuss white people with anyone he encounters. ''All white people are Jewish,'' says one budding cultural analyst. ''All gay people are white,'' says another. A third adds, ''White people don't put seasoning on their food.''</p>
        <p>''Unpleasant Messages'' plays two voice mails. The best one, delivered through a sigh in a nice baritone, goes: ''Hey, dude, listen. I don't know how to tell you this, but I love you. Not the kind of love you have when you say, like, your friend is your brother. I mean, like, the kind of love that we make fun of gay dudes for having. Give me a call.''</p>
        <p>''Alec Baldwin's Daughter Calls Back'' proceeds similarly. It's a phony voice mail message, delivered in the character of Mr. Baldwin's young daughter, who in real life was insulted and threatened by her father in a telephone message that played online. This gag presupposes a level of familiarity with -- and outrage at -- the earlier message.</p>
        <p>''I don't know how my phone being off makes you look like an ass,'' the video begins. ''Your movie career did that.'' It goes on to review Mr. Baldwin's career lows. ''Yeah, you come on home and set me straight on Friday, the 20th. 'Cause you know where I'll be? I'll be out with my friends watching you stink it up in 'Pearl Harbor,' you hack. Later.'' This is as much a revenge fantasy as a joke.</p>
        <p>The staff members at Black20 especially love ''net--work,'' their office comedy, and it's easy to see why. It's ''The Office,'' but for broadband types, offering melodrama instead of muffled understatement.</p>
        <p>Set in the Black20 office, ''net--work'' finds an apocalypse in lost Internet connections and rogue cursors. After a server crash in ''Lost Connection'' the office falls immediately into a ''Lord of the Flies'' state of depravity. Survivors of the lost connection instantly appear in rage and war paint; one's in clown face. Without the Internet they can't decide what to do in the office but seek water and murder one of their number, a scapegoat, who dies in spite of the return of the connection. That's human nature.</p>
        <p>''Wheels,'' at Black20's wheelsthemovie.com, made the rounds as a viral video a little while ago. It looks like a trailer for a romantic movie. It stars Jessie Cantrell, the boppy and good-sport host of ''Black20 News,'' as a paraplegic, opposite Mr. Torpey as the man who falls in love with her at first sight.</p>
        <p>The trailer is corny but polished, thick with the clichés of movie love -- ''the only thing 'love' has to do with 'legs' is the letter 'l' '' -- and it makes pitiless fun of the disabled. Or does it? It's possible it makes fun of making fun of the disabled, or makes fun of movie images of them. In any case there are at least seven existential twists to the humor, and yet the whole trailer can also be taken straight, perhaps excepting the misty scene when the couple are under the sheets, the woman still in her wheelchair.</p>
        <p>People over 35 might find the Black20 sensibility both exhilarating and disquieting. Disquieting not because the site doesn't show ''real movies'' or ''real television,'' but because the writers and producers are arch and deadpan at the same time they are evangelical. They're wry and surreal, but also extremely enthusiastic about what they're doing. And that's a dissonant mix for anyone used to comedy that's skeptical. Or even dark.</p>
        <p>The Black20 crew members do try to affect a sophistication from time to time, but their naïve exuberance is hard to conceal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Torpey confided in an e-mail interview last week: ''What the world really needs is frank open dialogue about all of the problems that afflict us, most importantly the ones mankind has brought upon itself. Until then there's Black20.</p>
        <p>SCREENS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
