<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fireproofing of Most Overpasses And Bridges Is Costly and Rare</title>
    <meta content="01bridge" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/us/01bridge.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844232"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">San Francisco-Oakland Bay Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">San Francisco Bay Area (Calif)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Oakland (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckinley, Jesse</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Oakland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Engineering and Engineers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Engineering and Engineers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Oakland (Calif)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE0D8133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="621" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fireproofing of Most Overpasses And Bridges Is Costly and Rare</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Fireproofing of Most Overpasses and Bridges Is Costly and Rare</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDAL C. ARCHIBOLD</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, April 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Drivers in San Francisco Bay area have relatively painless rush hour commute on day after fiery gasoline tanker crash melted and collapsed critical highway interchange near San Francisco-Oakland Bay Bridge; Gov Arnold Schwarzenegger authorizes state funds to pay for day of free public transit; combination of telecommuting, free rides and people taking day off keeps congestion down; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They are built in most cases to withstand ferocious winds and, here in California, the heaving of earthquakes. But most major highway bridges and overpasses are not fireproof and probably never will be.</p>
        <p>That is because fierce fires like the one that warped steel and collapsed part of a San Francisco Bay Area bridge connector Sunday are considered anomalies in the structural engineering world. While car and truck fires occur regularly, they most often damage the pavement on bridges, not the network of steel supporting them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most major highway bridges and overpasses are not fireproof and probably never will be.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They are built in most cases to withstand ferocious winds and, here in California, the heaving of earthquakes. But most major highway bridges and overpasses are not fireproof and probably never will be.</p>
        <p>That is because fierce fires like the one that warped steel and collapsed part of a San Francisco Bay Area bridge connector Sunday are considered anomalies in the structural engineering world. While car and truck fires occur regularly, they most often damage the pavement on bridges, not the network of steel supporting them.</p>
        <p>Although many recently built connectors and overpasses have much of their steel encased in concrete to protect them from the elements, it is not unusual for some of the steel, particularly in support beams underneath, to be exposed. And concrete, while affording some insulation, can crack and break up when exposed to extreme fire, too.</p>
        <p>''Even if it were a concrete bridge it would have had similar damage, but maybe not as dramatic,'' said Frieder Seible, dean of the engineering school at the University of California, San Diego, and chairman of the State Department of Transportation's seismic advisory board.</p>
        <p>The 170-foot section of an overpass that failed in Oakland, Calif., on Sunday endured tremendous heat from a burning gasoline tanker truck that had crashed and exploded. The driver of the truck suffered moderate burns, but no one else was injured.</p>
        <p>''It is not like there is a bridge design that would withstand this kind of thermal load,'' Dr. Seible said, calling the Oakland overpass ''a very common and economical type'' of design.</p>
        <p>Applying fire-resistant materials to bridges and overpasses, engineers said, would substantially drive up costs for a rare event.</p>
        <p>''The probability of these things happening are pretty low,'' said Andrew W. Herrmann, a consulting bridge engineer in New York City. ''The cost to protect every overpass would be outrageous.''</p>
        <p>The section of bridge that collapsed in the fire on Sunday was built in the 1950s. It landed on another overpass, built in the 1990s as part of the restoration of a freeway heavily damaged in an earthquake in 1989.</p>
        <p>Such intense fires have occurred from time to time. A section of Interstate 95 in Bridgeport, Conn., buckled in 2004 after a truck carrying heating oil caught fire and damaged steel supports.</p>
        <p>A trash fire under Interstate 78 in Newark in August 1989 twisted the steel and buckled the roadway.</p>
        <p>But many engineers, trained to consider the improbable, did not imagine a fire causing such extensive damage. In California, concerns most often focus on earthquakes, which in recent years have heavily damaged freeways and overpasses. Most of the bridges and overpasses have been retrofitted to prevent heavy quake damage, officials said.</p>
        <p>''We worry about the seismic things in California,'' said Loring A. Wyllie Jr., a San Francisco engineer and member of the International Association for Bridge and Structural Engineers who had frequently driven over the collapsed connector. ''I never thought about a fire doing that.''</p>
        <p>Engineers face several challenges in repairing the overpass.</p>
        <p>The cost of steel has been rising because of a boom in high-rise construction, causing some shortages. Engineers not involved in the repair said it appeared that at least some of the girders would need to be custom-made, further driving up costs.</p>
        <p>Will Kempton, director of the California Department of Transportation, said officials had not yet estimated the cost of the work or a timetable for completion. Engineers, he said, are still assessing the damage.</p>
        <p>Dr. Seible said that with a speedy contractor the work could probably be done in months, but keeping motorists happy will be difficult.</p>
        <p>''This can be done quickly,'' he said. ''But the traffic in the Bay Area does not stop because of it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
