<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Torn by University Shootings, Virginia Town Turns Inward to Mend</title>
    <meta content="01blacksburg" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/us/01blacksburg.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844303"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Blacksburg (Va)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hauser, Christine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cho, Seung-Hui</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cho, Seung-Hui</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E4D6133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1097" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Torn by University Shootings, Virginia Town Turns Inward to Mend</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Torn by University Shootings, Virginia Town Turns Inward to Mend</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTINE HAUSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hauser, Christine</byline>
      <dateline>BLACKSBURG, Va., April 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mass shooting at Virginia Tech takes emotional toll on college town of Blacksburg, Va; tragedy has bound already close community, with ribbons in university's orange and maroon colors affixed to lampposts, trees, restaurants and offices; town and university are co-producing annual arts festival in June that this year may take on hues of healing; at small yarn shop, residents gather to knit squares that will be sewn into 32 patchwork blankets in memory of Virginia Tech victims; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a small yarn shop near the Virginia Tech campus, Molly Heterick sat knitting at a wooden table with her friends this week, looping coarse strands of wool over her needles until a small patch in the colors of the university started to take shape.</p>
        <p>''We are so tired of crying,'' said Gina Bonomo, the owner of the Mosaic Yarn Shop.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A mass shooting has bound the community of Blacksburg, Va., like never before.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a small yarn shop near the Virginia Tech campus, Molly Heterick sat knitting at a wooden table with her friends this week, looping coarse strands of wool over her needles until a small patch in the colors of the university started to take shape.</p>
        <p>''We are so tired of crying,'' said Gina Bonomo, the owner of the Mosaic Yarn Shop.</p>
        <p>''So we knit,'' said Mrs. Heterick, 69, never looking up from her work. ''This is what we do.''</p>
        <p>Last week's mass shooting, in which Seung-Hui Cho killed 32 students and teachers at Virginia Tech, has taken an emotional toll on Blacksburg, which is as intertwined with the university as the knit squares that Mrs. Heterick, Ms. Bonomo and others will sew together into 32 patchwork blankets: one to comfort each family the victims left behind.</p>
        <p>That means they need 2,100 squares. But in a town like this, where residents take cake and cookies to welcome new neighbors and some do not bother to lock front doors, there are plenty of volunteers.</p>
        <p>''It's like living in a mill town, where every day you go in and work there,'' Ms. Bonomo said. ''Even if you don't know somebody who was shot and killed, you feel like it was someone in your family.''</p>
        <p>Like many others in this town of about 40,000, the women at the shop come from generations of family members who have attended or worked at the sprawling university less than a mile from where they sit.</p>
        <p>The tragedy has bound the community like never before, reflecting more than a century of economic, social and historical ties between the university and Blacksburg, which developed around it.</p>
        <p>On downtown North Main Street, most of the businesses -- from burger bars to dry cleaners to pizza parlors -- have put up signs that proclaim Hokie solidarity, invoking the nickname of the university's students.</p>
        <p>Ribbons in the university's orange and maroon colors are affixed to lampposts, trees, restaurants, and accountants' and lawyers' offices. After the killings, residents, students and students' families who came to Blacksburg wore orange-and-maroon shirts and caps.</p>
        <p>''Without the university, this whole area would not be what it is,'' said Charlie Whitescarver, associate director of Volume Two Bookstore, which sells university-themed clothing and memorabilia.</p>
        <p>''If Virginia Tech has something good going on, like a football game, the whole county benefits,'' Mr. Whitescarver said. ''If it has a tragedy, the whole county hurts.''</p>
        <p>After the shootings, classes were canceled for the rest of the week and some students left town, choosing not to return for the rest of the semester. But there is no indication that the reduced student body has hurt the regional economy. In fact, families who visited Blacksburg to show support appeared to have buoyed business, said Star Boling, manager of the Campus Emporium.</p>
        <p>Ms. Boling's observation was borne out by the lines of customers at downtown restaurants.</p>
        <p>''I have never seen such overwhelming support,'' she said. ''We are getting new stock in every day. We were just cleared out.''</p>
        <p>But there is still an unsettled air. One hotel arranged a comedy show to relieve the mood. Fliers advertising counseling services went up in shop windows. At least one gun shop owner in nearby Christiansburg said there was an increased interest in handguns.</p>
        <p>After the shootings, the Blacksburg Public Library organized a collection of books to reflect the times, stacking editions of ''Healing a Parent's Grieving Heart: 100 Practical Ideas After Your Child Dies'' with ''Lost Boy: Why Our Sons Turn Violent and How We Can Save Them'' next to a photograph of hundreds of Virginia Tech students at a candlelight vigil.</p>
        <p>With only one week left of classes this semester, the response to the bloodshed will probably seep into the cultural and intellectual life of the town as time goes on and students return in the fall.</p>
        <p>The town and the university are co-producing an annual arts festival in June, with concerts and cultural events that this year may take on hues of healing.</p>
        <p>''This is something that is a steppingstone,'' said E. Jane Harrison, the university's festival producer.</p>
        <p>Set amid gentle hills on a plateau between the Blue Ridge and the Allegheny Mountains, Blacksburg sees its population swell each semester by more than 26,000 students.</p>
        <p>The university has long helped the surrounding area thrive.</p>
        <p>''We go out and say we have a major research university and we would love your business,'' said Aric H. Bopp, the executive director of the New River Valley Economic Development Alliance.</p>
        <p>''Being a college town, we are a very international culture,'' Mr. Bopp said. ''It's a huge component of the regional economy.''</p>
        <p>According to figures provided by a Blacksburg town official, Heather D. Browning, the nearly 22,000 undergraduate students pump more than $81 million a year into the local economy and graduate students about $45 million. About $1.2 billion is generated from university-related spending in surrounding Montgomery County.</p>
        <p>In addition, the university has a dedicated following, with up to 60,000 people visiting for football games and patronizing hotels, restaurants and food stores to stock up for tailgating parties.</p>
        <p>University officials say it may be too soon to teach some classes, like those with violent content.</p>
        <p>''After something like this happens, every element and aspect of campus decisions will be re-examined over a period of time,'' Mark Owczarski, the director of news and information, said when asked if there had been any curriculum changes.</p>
        <p>''I can assure you every single faculty member is going to be looking at all they have done,'' Mr. Owczarski said. ''We owe that to this community to re-examine all that. All of those questions: that's occurring in every corner of this campus.''</p>
        <p>This year, Virginia Tech accepted 12,848 new students for the fall term. In an effort to return to normal, it resumed classes on April 23 and is conducting tours for prospective students.</p>
        <p>Mr. Owczarski said university administrators would not know the full effect of the shootings on admissions until the May 1 deadline for students to accept.</p>
        <p>But he said, ''We have received indications from five students that they will be declining our offer because of last week.''</p>
        <p>With the economies of the town and the campus inextricably linked, events in one place inevitably reverberate in the other.</p>
        <p>A plan to renovate an 1897 building for the town's new museum, for example, will be financed by selling parking spaces in Blacksburg to fans attending university football games, said Jessica Wirgau, the museum coordinator.</p>
        <p>''There is a real sense of community engagement,'' Ms. Wirgau said. ''The town melds into the campus.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
