<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Uptown, A Company No Longer Plays Nice</title>
    <meta content="01jump" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/theater/reviews/01jump.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070504T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844195"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jean Cocteau Repertory</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zinoman, Jason</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">McGee, Lisa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Neilson, Anthony</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Jump] (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Realism (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Jean Cocteau Repertory</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Edelson, Ari</person>
        <person class="online_producer">McGee, Lisa</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Neilson, Anthony</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Realism (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E0D9133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="652" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Uptown, A Company No Longer Plays Nice</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Uptown, a Company No Longer Plays Nice</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON ZINOMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinoman, Jason</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jason Zinoman reviews Jean Cocteau Repertory productions of Lisa McGee play Jump] and Anthony Neilson play Realism; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was not a major cultural event when the Jean Cocteau Repertory left its longtime home on the Bowery, a few blocks from CBGB, on the Lower East Side. No one protested. For unlike CBGB, which closed to much fanfare in 2006, the Jean Cocteau, which also left that year, was never at the forefront of anything -- and perhaps its charm was that it never tried to be.</p>
        <p>For years it was the downtown theater company with the uptown vibe, a serious and occasionally dull producer of classical plays staged with the respectfulness and reverence of a newly trained puppy. But since taking over as the troupe's artistic director, Ari Edelson has ordered that dog to attack.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>These new dramas are aggressive, casually coarse entertainments pitched to an audience reared on Beavis and Butt-Head rather than Strindberg and Shaw.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was not a major cultural event when the Jean Cocteau Repertory left its longtime home on the Bowery, a few blocks from CBGB, on the Lower East Side. No one protested. For unlike CBGB, which closed to much fanfare in 2006, the Jean Cocteau, which also left that year, was never at the forefront of anything -- and perhaps its charm was that it never tried to be.</p>
        <p>For years it was the downtown theater company with the uptown vibe, a serious and occasionally dull producer of classical plays staged with the respectfulness and reverence of a newly trained puppy. But since taking over as the troupe's artistic director, Ari Edelson has ordered that dog to attack.</p>
        <p>With his first two plays, Mr. Edelson (who changed the name of the company to the Exchange) announced a new sensibility that seems to reject everything that the Jean Cocteau once was. Seriousness is out the window. Forget stuffy chestnuts by dead white guys. The two plays, ''Jump!'' and ''Realism,'' new dramas from Britain currently in repertory on Theater Row, are aggressive, casually coarse entertainments pitched to an audience reared on Beavis and Butt-Head rather than Strindberg and Shaw.</p>
        <p>The Belfast-born Lisa McGee's ''Jump!'' -- the better of the two -- begins on a fateful New Year's night in a grimy Staten Island bar to the sound of Justin Timberlake's new album. (Both playwrights reset their plays in America with up-to-the-minute references.) Two dim friends, Ross (a cheeky Jordan Gelber) and Johnny (Stephen Plunkett) nervously talk about committing murder. Only one problem: they forgot the getaway car. Then there's the little issue that neither wants to pull the trigger.</p>
        <p>It's a funny scene -- a picture of the worst hired guns in the history of crime -- even if it's one seen countless times in films made by Quentin Tarantino followers. It's the first of several narratives that weave together and don't necessarily follow a linear time frame.</p>
        <p>The play, staged by Mr. Edelson, then shifts to the other side of the room, where three tipsy girlfriends (Ali Marsh, Sarah Grace Wilson and Meredith Zinner) wait for their tardy pal Gretta (Bree Elrod). She never shows, deciding instead to kill herself by jumping off a bridge -- only to find that another depressive has staked out her spot. Death is generally played for laughs in this quick and dirty play.</p>
        <p>Ms. McGee has a cinematic sense of structure, and this is one of those plays that seems as if it would be better as a movie. But she at least keeps your attention, which is more than can be said for Anthony Neilson's ''Realism,'' a day in the head of a slacker, Stuart (a vacant Mr. Plunkett), the least interesting protagonist to come along since Lassie.</p>
        <p>Mr. Neilson, a Scottish bad-boy playwright who was a pioneer of the confrontational in-yer-face English theater movement of the 1990s, has written several infamous provocations (''Penetrator,'' ''The Censor'') filled with all manner of bodily fluids. And while ''Realism'' (the title's ironic, get it?) has its share of toilet humor, it remains a shallow piece of goofy absurdism about the way dudes really think.</p>
        <p>Get ready to be shocked: the male mind is a mess of sex dreams, regret, mild racism and women problems. As portrayed in this cliché-filled production, organized in a series of disconnected scenes, it's filled with game-show theme songs, sit-com parodies and put-downs that seem out of a beer commercial.</p>
        <p>Mr. Edelson stages the work as a kind of cabaret with a cereal-eating slacker as the M.C. But the character's lethargy seems to infect the production, which includes Antje Ellermann's flimsy set that doesn't seem to fit its stage and often seems on the verge of collapsing, along with, I'm afraid, the rest of the show.</p>
        <p>''Realism'' and ''Jump!'' run through May 20 at the Kirk Theater on Theater Row, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton; (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 4, 2007, Friday  A picture caption on Tuesday with a theater review of ''Jump!'' and ''Realism,'' at the Kirk Theater on 42nd Street, misspelled the surname of an actress shown in ''Jump!'' She is Meredith Zinner, not Ziner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 4, 2007, Friday</p>
        <p>A picture caption on Tuesday with a theater review of ''Jump!'' and ''Realism,'' at the Kirk Theater on 42nd Street, misspelled the surname of an actress shown in ''Jump!'' She is Meredith Zinner, not Ziner.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
