<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Corzine Leaves the Hospital, Regretting His 'Bad Example'</title>
    <meta content="01corzine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/nyregion/01corzine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844273"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seat Belts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seat Belts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EFD7133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1085" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Corzine Leaves the Hospital, Regretting His 'Bad Example'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Corzine Leaves Hospital After Accident</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID KOCIENIEWSKI and DAVID W. CHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kocieniewski, David; Chen, David W</byline>
      <dateline>PRINCETON, N.J., April 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Jon S. Corzine apologized to New Jersey residents on Monday as he left the hospital 18 days after being critically injured in a car crash in which he was being driven at 91 miles per hour on the Garden State Parkway while riding without his seat belt.</p>
        <p>''I set a very bad example,'' said a contrite Mr. Corzine, who broke his left femur, his sternum and 11 ribs in the accident. He spoke from a wheelchair just outside Cooper University Hospital in Camden. His voice breaking with emotion, he added: ''I hope the state will forgive me. I will work very hard to set the right kind of example.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Jon S. Corzine apologized to New Jersey residents as he left the hospital 18 days after a devastating car crash.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Jon S. Corzine apologized to New Jersey residents on Monday as he left the hospital 18 days after being critically injured in a car crash in which he was being driven at 91 miles per hour on the Garden State Parkway while riding without his seat belt.</p>
        <p>''I set a very bad example,'' said a contrite Mr. Corzine, who broke his left femur, his sternum and 11 ribs in the accident. He spoke from a wheelchair just outside Cooper University Hospital in Camden. His voice breaking with emotion, he added: ''I hope the state will forgive me. I will work very hard to set the right kind of example.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine, 60, who spent more than a week on a ventilator and had three operations on his leg, spoke for less than a minute and refused to answer questions from reporters. It was his first public comments since the accident, save for telling an Associated Press photographer last week that he felt blessed.</p>
        <p>Wearing a red Cooper T-shirt, black track pants and running shoes, Mr. Corzine thanked his doctors as well as the emergency medical technicians and helicopter pilots who tended to him after the crash and who met with him on Monday before his release. His son Jeffrey, 24, pushed the wheelchair and his daughter, Jennifer Corzine-Pisani, 36, walked alongside.</p>
        <p>''I couldn't be more grateful for all the support I've been given from people around the state,'' said the governor, a Democrat in his first term. ''I don't think people realize just how much people care and show their support.</p>
        <p>''There is nothing more important in life than those people who care about you all the time in the moments of joy and the moments of pain,'' he added.</p>
        <p>After the brief comments, Mr. Corzine was helped into a black GMC Savana van, with tinted windows, which he bought and had specially modified for his wheelchair. He left the hospital in a six-car caravan about 1:45 p.m. His vehicle followed a black state police Crown Victoria, and was followed by a Chevrolet Suburban -- like the one he was riding in at the time of the crash -- a Mercedes station wagon, and two other cars.</p>
        <p>The motorcade did not use emergency lights, as it had been just before the accident.</p>
        <p>The governor's motorcade moved with the flow of traffic on Interstate 295, at some points sustaining speeds up to 70 miles per hour several minutes at a time, according to the speedometer of a vehicle traveling alongside; posted limits were 55 and 65.</p>
        <p>Capt. Al Della Fave, a state police spokesman, said the commander of the executive protection unit, which provides security and drivers for the governor, told him on Monday that the motorcade troopers had been instructed to adhere to posted speed limits. He declined to identify the driver of the governor's van or to make any of the drivers of the motorcade available for an interview.</p>
        <p>The motorcade shed about two cars before arriving about 2:45 p.m. at Drumthwacket, the official residence for New Jersey's governor, where Mr. Corzine will stay during the next stage of his recovery. It remained unclear when Mr. Corzine, who normally lives in Hoboken, would be well enough to resume his official duties, which were being handled by Richard J. Codey, the State Senate president, who has been acting governor since the accident.</p>
        <p>At Drumthwacket, an 1835 Greek Revival mansion on 11 acres, two news helicopters hovered overhead. Mr. Corzine's van was parked at a side entrance out of view of the news cameras on the front lawn, making it impossible to see him leaving the van. But one person exiting another car in the motorcade wore blue-gray medical scrubs, perhaps part of the team of nurses and therapists expected to care for the governor in the coming days and weeks.</p>
        <p>The governor's mansion has been altered in several ways to make him more comfortable for what his aides and doctors expect to be a long and arduous rehabilitation process.</p>
        <p>A portable chairlift has been installed to enable the governor to move easily between the public space of the first floor and the private quarters on the second. The outdoor pool will be converted into a heated one for his physical therapy, while rehabilitation equipment has been added to the second-floor gym. And video-conferencing equipment is being installed to enable the governor to take part in meetings.</p>
        <p>Anthony Coley, Mr. Corzine's communications director, said that Mr. Corzine had no public events scheduled so far, and that it was unclear what he would do this week other than rest. But the governor did invite about 10 members of his senior staff to Drumthwacket late Monday afternoon, Mr. Coley added.</p>
        <p>''He's happy to be home,'' Mr. Coley said.</p>
        <p>At the governor's first public appearance since the accident, his emergence from the hospital was carefully managed. A lectern was taken into the hospital foyer in the late morning, but later taken away, when Mr. Corzine's aides announced that he would not attempt to walk or stand during his statement. (They said last week that he had been able to take a few steps using a walker.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine's aides rebuffed reporters who asked for the chance to ask him about his recollections of the crash and his plans to return to work.</p>
        <p>They did, however, bow to suggestions from some of the two dozen camera crews on hand and relocated the press conference. Photographers had argued that the shadows and low light at the original spot near the hospital entrance might ruin their shots and make Mr. Corzine appear pallid.</p>
        <p>So aides to the governor agreed to locate the press conference a few feet away, where the shade and sun met. An X was placed on the pavement with duct tape and one of the governor's spokesmen, Andrew Poag, sat in a wheelchair to allow the photographers to adjust their camera settings.</p>
        <p>About 100 people gathered to watch the event, including hospital employees, visitors and pedestrians.</p>
        <p>Anne Theochrides, who works in the marketing department of a physical rehabilitation center across the street, said she had closely followed news accounts of Mr. Corzine's progress during his time in the hospital and wanted to be there as he left.</p>
        <p>''I was hoping he'd go to one of our facilities,'' she said. ''But I guess he wanted to go home to the mansion where he could do business, too. I hope it works out for him.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
