<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Getting the Clearest Look At a Hurting Hip</title>
    <meta content="01ortho" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="PersonalHealth" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/health/01ortho.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844161"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Bone Disease"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Magnetic Resonance Imagers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Magnetic Resonance Imagers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2DC1F3FF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="692" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Getting the Clearest Look At a Hurting Hip</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Getting the Clearest Look at a Hurting Hip</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By YUDHIJIT BHATTACHARJEE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LAST fall, after experiencing a dull ache in his hip for months, Frank Berger felt the pain escalating so much that he couldn't sleep. Walking became so difficult that Mr. Berger, a 59-year-old accountant in Nantucket, Mass., had to ask his secretary to bring him documents from the printer only 40 feet away.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berger's orthopedic surgeon, Dr. Rocco Monto, took an X-ray, which showed nothing unusual, and an M.R.I. scan, which revealed a lesion in the soft tissue above the left hip joint.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many surgeons say that hip arthroscopy is helping to identify bone and cartilage defects that do not show up in scans or appear too fuzzy to guide treatments.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LAST fall, after experiencing a dull ache in his hip for months, Frank Berger felt the pain escalating so much that he couldn't sleep. Walking became so difficult that Mr. Berger, a 59-year-old accountant in Nantucket, Mass., had to ask his secretary to bring him documents from the printer only 40 feet away.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berger's orthopedic surgeon, Dr. Rocco Monto, took an X-ray, which showed nothing unusual, and an M.R.I. scan, which revealed a lesion in the soft tissue above the left hip joint.</p>
        <p>But the M.R.I. didn't show enough detail to determine whether the problem was separation of cartilage from bone or avascular necrosis, which causes loss of blood flow to the affected area. Dr. Monto suggested another step: inserting a camera-mounted probe into the hip for a closer look.</p>
        <p>He told Mr. Berger that the arthroscopy might end up being diagnostic; if he found avascular necrosis or something else he could not repair, he would refer him for open surgery for a vascular graft or a hip replacement. But if it was something that could be fixed immediately, he could perform surgery with the arthroscope.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berger, who dreaded having his hip replaced, underwent a hip arthroscopy in January. Dr. Monto examined the spot and removed a lesion. In weeks, Mr. Berger was walking easily.</p>
        <p>Although surgeons in Europe began doing arthroscopy on hip patients decades ago, it has become a popular diagnostic tool in the United States only in the last few years. Many surgeons say that the technique is helping to identify bone and cartilage defects in the hip that do not show up in scans or appear too fuzzy to guide treatments. As a result, patients who until five years ago would have had hip replacements or hip resurfacing are now being treated with less drastic surgeries like removing tissue flap. Dr. Monto described the procedure as a sweet spot ''where diagnosis meets therapy.''</p>
        <p>But other surgeons and radiologists say that hip arthroscopy should be used for treating problems that have been diagnosed with conventional screening. Exploratory arthroscopy can be an unnecessary risk, they say, given that the space in the hip joint has little room for the instruments.</p>
        <p>''There are surgeons out there who will do hip arthroscopies at the drop of a hat to make money,'' said Dr. Joseph Lane, a professor of orthopedic surgery at Weill Medical College of Cornell University in New York and the medical director of the Osteoporosis Center at the Hospital for Special Surgery, which is affiliated with Weill Cornell.</p>
        <p>Before doing a hip arthroscopy, Dr. Lane said, surgeons should know what they will be treating. There is no reason, he said, that ''a good M.R.I. scan in the hands of a good surgeon'' combined with an X-ray shouldn't be enough to make a diagnosis. After that, ''the surgeon should be able to decide whether the condition can be treated by arthroscopy or open surgery,'' Dr. Lane said.</p>
        <p>Radiologists say that improvements in hip M.R.I.'s are a good reason to avoid diagnostic arthroscopy. Newer scanners use magnets that are more powerful than those in older machines, providing sharper images. During the M.R.I, many medical centers put a magnetic coil over the patient's hip for more detail. ''We've come a long way from traditional M.R.I. scans of the hip, which could only show if something huge was going on,'' said Dr. Hollis G. Potter, a radiologist at the Hospital for Special Surgery.</p>
        <p>Dr. Potter said that many imaging facilities still use conventional M.R.I. protocols for hip scans, which aren't helpful to surgeons. That is why, Dr. Lane said, getting a high-quality M.R.I. is essential. ''The patient needs to ask the doctor: 'How good will my M.R.I. be?' '' he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Monto, a fellow of the American Academy of Orthopaedic Surgeons, dismissed claims that newer M.R.I.'s were good enough to eliminate diagnostic arthroscopy. He said he had seen many patients who had had ''high-res, enhanced M.R.I. scans'' that showed little concern, yet pathologies appeared under an arthroscope. ''I am always amazed by what I find when I'm in there that has been missed by an M.R.I.,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Bone Disease</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
