<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Times Building Is Resold For 3 Times Its 2004 Price</title>
    <meta content="01times" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/nyregion/01times.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844299"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Times</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Tishman Speyer Properties</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E4D6133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="644" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Times Building Is Resold For 3 Times Its 2004 Price</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Times Building Is Resold for 3 Times Its 2004 Price</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GLENN COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Collins, Glenn</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Less than three weeks after putting the historic headquarters of The New York Times Company on the block, Tishman Speyer Properties sold the building for $525 million, three times the $175 million it paid in November 2004.</p>
        <p>The buyer, Africa Israel USA, a subsidiary of an Israel-based international holding and investment company, announced in a statement yesterday that it would invest $170 million to renovate the building, at 229 West 43rd Street, for office and retail tenants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tishman Speyer Properties sold the historic headquarters of The New York Times Company for $525 million, less than three weeks after putting it on the market.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Less than three weeks after putting the historic headquarters of The New York Times Company on the block, Tishman Speyer Properties sold the building for $525 million, three times the $175 million it paid in November 2004.</p>
        <p>The buyer, Africa Israel USA, a subsidiary of an Israel-based international holding and investment company, announced in a statement yesterday that it would invest $170 million to renovate the building, at 229 West 43rd Street, for office and retail tenants.</p>
        <p>''Everyone has been lucky in this market, and this price just confirms that,'' said Dan Fasulo, managing director of Real Capital Analytics, which tracks real estate deals. ''It is a nightmare to find prime office space in Midtown, where rents are up 15 to 20 percent in the last three months.''</p>
        <p>When Tishman Speyer bought the Times Building in 2004, some real estate executives suggested that it had overpaid. But rents have increased relentlessly as vacancy rates have declined. ''We are obviously pleased,'' said Robert Speyer, senior managing director of Tishman Speyer, after the deal was reported yesterday in The Wall Street Journal online.</p>
        <p>Mr. Speyer added: ''There is a lot of interest from investors all over the world to own real estate in New York City, and Times Square has become one of the most heated submarkets in the world.''</p>
        <p>A recent report by Cushman &amp; Wakefield, a real estate broker, said that the average rent for prime office space in Midtown Manhattan had attained a record high of $70.77 per square foot.</p>
        <p>In Midtown, ''for anyone looking for a block of space in excess of 300,000 square feet during the next two years for less than $100 per square foot, this is your only option,'' said Darcy A. Stacom, the broker at CB Richard Ellis who sold the property for The Times in 2004 and handled the sale to Africa Israel for Tishman Speyer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fasulo said that the new owners should expect ''above-average rents for the property, given its history and location,'' meaning that tower floors could fetch above $75 per square foot and lower floors slightly less.</p>
        <p>The 750,000-square-foot, 15-story Times Building, which opened in 1913, needs an extensive top-to-bottom refurbishing -- including a renovation of the lobby, the former newsprint loading bays, and the subbasements that once housed the newspaper's printing presses -- before it can be rented to corporate and retail tenants.</p>
        <p>''The loading docks will be prime retail space,'' Mr. Fasulo said, ''because that large a space just doesn't exist in Times Square.'' He added: ''They can get a blue-chip retailer there at a prime price.''</p>
        <p>The Times Company is in the process of moving into its new headquarters, a skyscraper at 620 Eighth Avenue between 40th and 41st Streets, opposite the Port Authority Bus Terminal.</p>
        <p>In a press release, Africa Israel Investments Ltd. said the property was the most expensive its United States subsidiary had bought in New York City.</p>
        <p>The Israeli billionaire Lev Leviev, as chairman, owns 76 percent of the Africa Israel holding company, ''and is looking to do more deals than this, even on a larger scale,'' said Rotem Rosen, the chief executive of Africa Israel USA. Africa Israel had a 50 percent interest in the recent purchase of the Apthorp apartment building on the Upper West Side for $426 million.</p>
        <p>''And we are looking to bring our model in New York to downtown Buenos Aires, buying exclusive properties and upgrading them,'' Mr. Rosen said. Africa Israel owns office and residential real estate and shopping malls, and has ventures in hotels, tourism, telecommunications and fashion.</p>
        <p>In recent years the company has become a player with deep pockets not only in New York real estate, but also in Miami, Los Angeles, Las Vegas, Phoenix and Myrtle Beach, S.C., where, Mr. Rosen said, the company is planning a Hard Rock music park to be completed in 2008.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
