<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Atlanta's Mayor Defends Chief Against Misconduct Accusations</title>
    <meta content="01atlanta" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/us/01atlanta.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844211"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Atlanta (Ga)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodman, Brenda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Franklin, Shirley Clarke (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, Kathryn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pennington, Richard (Police Chief)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia/Atlanta</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Atlanta (Ga)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E6D8133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="381" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Atlanta's Mayor Defends Chief Against Misconduct Accusations</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Atlanta’s Mayor Defends Chief Against Misconduct Accusations</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRENDA GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodman, Brenda</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, April 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mayor Shirley Franklin of Atlanta defends Police Chief Richard Pennington against charges by federal prosecutors that 'culture of misconduct' in Police Dept contributed to shooting death of elderly Kathryn Johnston in botched drug raid last Nov; mayor chastises reporters who question her about details in court documents suggesting that narcotics officers often lie to obtain search warrants and plant evidence to make drug cases, as they did when they raided home of Johnston; mayor is under pressure to respond to testimony given by officers involved in shooting that they were not given adequate training and were under pressure to meet 'performance targets' instituted by Pennington; Pennington denies imposing quotas but concedes there are 'performance measures' (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Shirley Franklin defended the city's police chief Monday against charges by federal prosecutors that a ''culture of misconduct'' in the Police Department contributed to the shooting death of an elderly woman in a botched drug raid last fall.</p>
        <p>''The suggestion that our officers performed at anything less than the highest standards of ethics and training is a problem,'' Ms. Franklin said in her first public response to the prosecutors' comments.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Shirley Franklin defended the police chief against charges that a “culture of misconduct” contributed to a shooting death last fall.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mayor Shirley Franklin defended the city's police chief Monday against charges by federal prosecutors that a ''culture of misconduct'' in the Police Department contributed to the shooting death of an elderly woman in a botched drug raid last fall.</p>
        <p>''The suggestion that our officers performed at anything less than the highest standards of ethics and training is a problem,'' Ms. Franklin said in her first public response to the prosecutors' comments.</p>
        <p>But she said she was satisfied with the job the police chief, Richard Pennington, was doing and had no plans to fire him.</p>
        <p>''It would never occur to me the people of Atlanta would want to reverse the trend'' of falling crime under Chief Pennington, Ms. Franklin said.</p>
        <p>With Chief Pennington and Assistant Police Chief Alan Dreher behind her, Ms. Franklin chastised reporters who were asking questions about details in court documents released on Thursday. Those documents suggested that narcotics officers often lied to obtain search warrants and planted evidence to make drug cases, as they had done when they raided the home of the woman, Kathryn Johnston.</p>
        <p>The mayor said she had already worked with Chief Pennington to adopt reforms in response to the shooting, including increasing the size of the narcotics unit to 30 officers from 8.</p>
        <p>She said that they were also reviewing the department's training procedures and that they planned to require police officers to take drug tests for the first time.</p>
        <p>Ms. Franklin was on a business trip to Asia on Thursday when David Nahmias, the United States attorney, released preliminary details of a federal investigation into the death of Ms. Johnston. Since her return she has been under pressure to respond to testimony given by officers involved in the shooting that they had not been given adequate training to do their jobs and that they cut corners by lying and falsifying evidence because they were under pressure to meet ''performance targets'' instituted by Chief Pennington.</p>
        <p>Chief Pennington has denied that the department asks officers to meet quotas, and he did so again on Monday.</p>
        <p>But he conceded: ''Yes, we have performance measures in the Atlanta Police Department. We have to have performance measures because if we don't have them, the officers would come in every day with nothing on their sheets.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
