<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Elliott Skinner, 82, Scholar and Former Ambassador</title>
    <meta content="01skinner" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Obituaries" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844208"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Politics and Gov't (U.S.)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Elliott P. Skinner</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Skinner, Elliott P (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hevesi, Dennis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Obituary (Obit)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Obituaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E7D8133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="350" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Elliott Skinner, 82, Scholar and Former Ambassador</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENNIS HEVESI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hevesi, Dennis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Elliott P Skinner, former US ambassador to Republic of Upper Volta, West African nation now known as Burkina Faso, and fromer chairman of anthropology department at Columbia University, dies at age 82 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Elliott P. Skinner, a former United States ambassador to the Republic of Upper Volta, the West African nation now known as Burkina Faso, and a former chairman of the anthropology department at Columbia University, died April 1 at his home in Washington. He was 82.</p>
        <p>The cause was heart failure, said his wife, Gwendolyn Mikell, director of African studies at the Edmund A. Walsh School of Foreign Service at Georgetown University.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Elliott P. Skinner, a former United States ambassador to the Republic of Upper Volta, the West African nation now known as Burkina Faso, and a former chairman of the anthropology department at Columbia University, died April 1 at his home in Washington. He was 82.</p>
        <p>The cause was heart failure, said his wife, Gwendolyn Mikell, director of African studies at the Edmund A. Walsh School of Foreign Service at Georgetown University.</p>
        <p>Dr. Skinner was a professor at Columbia from 1954 to 1994 and was named chairman of the anthropology department in 1972, becoming the first African-American department chairman in the university's history. In 1966, President Lyndon B. Johnson appointed him ambassador to Upper Volta, a post he held until 1969.</p>
        <p>Dr. Mikell said her husband, the author of 12 books, was particularly concerned that United States foreign policy ''be informed by accurate knowledge of Africa,'' and that African-Americans contributed to the formation of those policies. Among Dr. Skinner's books are ''The Mossi of Upper Volta'' (Stanford University Press, 1964) and ''African-Americans and United States Policy Toward Africa 1850-1924'' (Howard University Press, 1992).</p>
        <p>Elliott Percival Skinner was born in Port of Spain, Trinidad, on June 20, 1924. He came to the United States in 1943 and enlisted in the Army a month later. His military service, including combat in France, allowed him to become an American citizen.</p>
        <p>He graduated from New York University in 1951. He earned a master's degree at Columbia a year later and his doctorate there in 1955. For two years, he lived in West Africa, where he learned Mossi, the language of the Upper Volta region.</p>
        <p>Dr. Skinner and his first wife, Thelma, divorced in 1977.</p>
        <p>In addition to his wife, Dr. Mikell, Dr. Skinner is survived by two daughters, Gale Holland of Spring Valley, N.Y., and Luce Remy of Washington; three sons, Victor, of Manhattan, Sagha, of Yellow Springs, Ohio, and Touray, of Freehold, N.J.; two sisters, Patricia Smith of Wichita, Kan., and Bernice Walcott of Caracas, Venezuela; two brothers, Robert, of San Francisco, and Morris, of Brooklyn; seven grandchildren; and one great-grandchild.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
