<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Acting Governor's Balancing Act: Taking the Lead Without Stepping on Toes</title>
    <meta content="01codey" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/nyregion/01codey.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844276"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Codey, Richard J</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DEFD7133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1160" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Acting Governor's Balancing Act: Taking the Lead Without Stepping on Toes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Acting Governor’s Balancing Act: Taking the Lead Without Stepping on Toes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD G. JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jones, Richard G</byline>
      <dateline>WEST ORANGE, N.J.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>First, there was a vicious northeaster, a deadly, drenching storm that pinwheeled its way across New Jersey, soaking the state with one of its worst water-related disasters in more than a century.</p>
        <p>Then three New Jerseyans were among the 32 people killed at Virginia Polytechnic Institute in the largest shooting rampage in the nation's history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Richard J. Codey is facing a procession of challenges as he serves as acting governor of New Jersey for the third time in six years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>First, there was a vicious northeaster, a deadly, drenching storm that pinwheeled its way across New Jersey, soaking the state with one of its worst water-related disasters in more than a century.</p>
        <p>Then three New Jerseyans were among the 32 people killed at Virginia Polytechnic Institute in the largest shooting rampage in the nation's history.</p>
        <p>After that kind of start to his latest incarnation as acting governor of New Jersey, Richard J. Codey's next matter of business was certain to seem trivial by comparison, and it was. He spent some of the first few days of his tenure refereeing in-fighting between his staff members and assistants to Gov. Jon S. Corzine, whose severe injuries in an April 12 car crash thrust Mr. Codey into an extended run as acting governor for the third time in six years.</p>
        <p>Other than that, Mr. Acting Governor, how have things been?</p>
        <p>''Of course, it's been an easy transition,'' a poker-faced Mr. Codey quipped at a ribbon-cutting for a school for autistic children here last Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Codey, president of the State Senate, is more familiar than most with the peculiarities of filling in as the state's chief executive, having spent 14 months in the top job after Gov. James E. McGreevey resigned in 2004, and serving as the perennial understudy during Mr. Corzine's frequent trips out of town. But this latest stint has been particularly challenging because of the back-to-back disasters and the delicate dynamic of trying to assert himself as governor without seeming to step on the still-healing toes of a fellow Democrat, Mr. Corzine.</p>
        <p>''It's a tough situation, I don't deny it,'' Mr. Codey, 59, said in an interview at his district office here. ''It's not like when I took over for McGreevey; I had my own staff and I had the freedom to do what I wanted to as governor. This is different. I've got an elected governor over me. But at the same time it's not like Jon's in Israel for a week. It's a hybrid we really haven't had in New Jersey.''</p>
        <p>He thought a moment and added: ''You've got to walk a tightrope. You've got to show that the state has a leader, but at the same time, you've got to be respectful.''</p>
        <p>After the April 15 northeaster, Mr. Codey took a helicopter tour of New Jersey to survey the damage and spent days imploring Washington to release federal disaster aid for the state. Nine counties have been declared federal disaster areas.</p>
        <p>After the shootings at Virginia Tech, Mr. Codey ordered flags lowered to half-staff, declared a statewide day of mourning and attended services for the victims.</p>
        <p>Last week, the second full week of his time in office, was more low-key but no less busy. His schedule included attending an awards banquet at Seton Hall University in South Orange last Tuesday; the opening of a school for autistic children in West Orange last Wednesday; and the signing of a prevailing wages bill in Trenton on Thursday.</p>
        <p>Then he and Assembly Speaker Joseph J. Roberts Jr., a Democrat, visited Mr. Corzine at Cooper University Hospital in Camden on Friday.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Corzine was released from the hospital on Monday, it was unclear when he might be able to resume his duties as governor -- which leaves Mr. Codey in a kind of limbo that he said was not unlike the television reality show ''The Apprentice'': You never know when you might be fired.</p>
        <p>Unpretentious and prone to self-deprecating humor, Mr. Codey has just as much ego as any other politician, as evidenced by his successful effort to have the word ''acting'' removed from his title during that long post-McGreevey stand-in.</p>
        <p>But he insists that he is a rarity: a happy backup quarterback, ready to play when needed but willing to hand over the job when the starter is ready to go. Nor is he troubled by criticism from Mr. Corzine's camp that he has appeared to enjoy being acting governor a bit too much.</p>
        <p>The critics -- most of them reserve their observations for off-the-record conversations -- have chided Mr. Codey for everything from using a state police helicopter to survey storm damage to conducting a television interview from the governor's office rather than his more modest one.</p>
        <p>''Really, to be honest with you, at first, it bothered me,'' he said of the criticism, quick to point out that the television interview was the only time he had even stepped foot in the governor's State House suite since the accident. ''After that, I just said: 'You know, I'm doing the right thing here. I'm not trying to hurt anybody. I'm not trying to run for anything. I'm not running for governor. What's the problem here? Let's work together and make the man proud of what we're doing in his absence.' ''</p>
        <p>David P. Rebovich, director of the Institute for New Jersey Politics at Rider University, said Mr. Codey has struck a balance between leading and not stepping out of bounds, pointing to the northeaster and the Virginia shootings as examples.</p>
        <p>''In both cases, Codey stepped to the plate because it was required and New Jerseyans expected their leaders to do something,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Assemblyman John S. Wisniewski, a Democrat from Middlesex County, said, ''It's an uncomfortable situation,'' but added that Mr. Codey is nevertheless ''ably stewarding the state.''</p>
        <p>Senator Leonard Lance, Mr. Codey's Republican counterpart in the Senate leadership, said, ''He has been filling in well for Governor Corzine.'' Once they return to their respective elected positions, Mr. Codey and Mr. Corzine will sit across the table from each other during the state's budget negotiations, which will intensify during the next few weeks. They will also discuss the possibility of selling state assets like the New Jersey Turnpike.</p>
        <p>''How do we interact with Jon on this?'' Mr. Codey wondered in the interview. ''I don't know. Do we go to the governor's mansion, Hoboken?'' which is where Mr. Corzine's private residence is located. He added, ''But wherever we have to go we're going to go and slug it out with him and his staff.''</p>
        <p>For now, Mr. Codey is left with two jobs. He has been working from his Senate office on the second floor of the State House or his district office here in West Orange, relying mainly on his own staff to coordinate briefings for reporters, and regularly consulting with Tom Shea, Mr. Corzine's chief of staff, to stay on top of the governor's responsibilities. His schedule is a mix between things Mr. Corzine would have done -- like bill signings and news conferences -- and his routine Senate appearances.</p>
        <p>Last week, he was here for the opening of the Garden Academy, the new school for autistic children, as he had planned to be for weeks.</p>
        <p>''I bet when you decided to have a ribbon-cutting, you didn't think you'd get the governor, am I right?'' he asked the audience. After the laughter subsided, Mr. Codey added, ''Neither did I.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
