<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Work Stays On Hold After Deaths In Subway</title>
    <meta content="01transit" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/nyregion/01transit.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844275"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York City Transit</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EFD7133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1199" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Work Stays On Hold After Deaths In Subway</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Work Stays on Hold After Deaths in Subway</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM NEUMAN; Cassi Feldman and Colin Moynihan contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Moynihan, Colin; Feldman, Cassi; Neuman, William</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In response to the deaths of two track workers in accidents, transit officials yesterday suspended more than 20 maintenance projects for subway tracks, signals and tunnels for at least two more days.</p>
        <p>The decision was announced as workers attended the funeral of one transit worker, family members shared memories of another, and transit veterans recounted their own harrowing experiences of the dangers of life underground. The safety push will include refresher courses for all employees who work on the tracks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Over 20 subway maintenance projects remain on hold after the recent deaths of two track workers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In response to the deaths of two track workers in accidents, transit officials yesterday suspended more than 20 maintenance projects for subway tracks, signals and tunnels for at least two more days.</p>
        <p>The decision was announced as workers attended the funeral of one transit worker, family members shared memories of another, and transit veterans recounted their own harrowing experiences of the dangers of life underground. The safety push will include refresher courses for all employees who work on the tracks.</p>
        <p>''No one will be on the tracks performing any work whatsoever except for repairs on an emergency basis,'' said Howard H. Roberts Jr., the president of New York City Transit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roberts called the work halt on Sunday after the second accident, in which a Queens-bound G train entering the Hoyt-Schermerhorn station in Downtown Brooklyn struck and killed Marvin Franklin, 55, and injured another worker, Jeff Hill, 41. He said the interruption would last at least another 48 hours, beginning at 5:00 p.m. yesterday.</p>
        <p>The accident came less than a week after Daniel Boggs, a track worker, was killed last Tuesday when he stepped in front of a downtown No. 3 express train at the Columbus Circle station in Manhattan while he was setting out signal lights to warn train operators of work on the tracks ahead. Mr. Boggs's death was the first for a subway worker on the job in more than a year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roberts said a team of the transit agency's safety experts and representatives of the Transport Workers Union had worked through the night on Sunday to prepare what he called a curriculum for the safety refresher courses.</p>
        <p>He said the courses would include ''everything you need to know to work safely in that environment.''</p>
        <p>''Part of the emphasis,'' he said, ''is, look, you heard it before, maybe it seemed a little dry. We now have two tragedies within a week, and understand these rules are there to protect you, and you absolutely have to follow these rules or you're putting your future and your family's future in peril.''</p>
        <p>While the retraining goes on, two separate investigations into the fatal accidents are proceeding. Mr. Roberts, who took over the transit agency in April, said he was told the investigations could take up to a month, but added that he hoped to have the results by the end of next week.</p>
        <p>He said he would not recommend any changes in work procedures or safety rules until he saw the reports.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roberts attended the funeral yesterday for Mr. Boggs in Patterson, N.Y. Mr. Boggs was married, had three young children and lived in Brewster, in Putnam County.</p>
        <p>''I spent the day basically watching a father bury his son, a wife and mother bury her husband and three children bury their father,'' Mr. Roberts said at a news conference later in the day at the transit agency's headquarters on lower Broadway in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Several track workers who attended the funeral appeared at a separate news conference at the union headquarters on West End Avenue. They spoke about some of the dangers they have faced underground and the need to be constantly on the alert for approaching trains.</p>
        <p>''You look, you always look, you feel and you hear,'' said Michael Brown, who worked over the weekend on a major construction project on the A and C lines in Brooklyn near the station where Mr. Franklin was killed.</p>
        <p>He said it took several senses to stay alive underground, including staying alert for the vibrations of trains on the rails. But he said it was becoming more difficult to notice every train because newer trains are designed to make less noise. In addition, some new track components are designed to absorb the shock of the trains and muffle the sound -- innovations that make the subway environment more pleasant for straphangers but potentially more dangerous for workers.</p>
        <p>Jeffrey Lee, a 17-year veteran track worker who switched jobs about a year ago to become a safety representative for the union, recalled at least two close calls. About five years ago, he said, he was inspecting work in one of the Steinway tubes, which carry the No. 7 line under the East River. Suddenly, a train approached and he looked around for a spot to press up against the wall to get out of the way while the train passed. But there was none. The train operator saw him and blew his horn and Mr. Lee had to quickly lie down on a narrow ledge along the tube wall as the train lumbered past.</p>
        <p>Another time, he was working on a project in Brooklyn when a work train came barreling down on his crew. ''The train had no brakes and everybody started scattering,'' Mr. Lee said.</p>
        <p>He said that after such close calls, ''You sit down and you think about it and you think about your family. You think about what could have happened.''</p>
        <p>Several workers said that track crews and inspectors routinely operated without radios and that the job could be made safer if they had better communications with train operators and controllers.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, family members and friends recalled Mr. Franklin, the transit worker killed on Sunday. He worked for the transit agency for more than 20 years and had a second career as an artist.</p>
        <p>Mr. Franklin's son, Shah Franklin, 33, said his father sometimes talked about the dangers of his work. ''He told me many stories of other co-workers being killed in the line of duty. It was frightening and horrifying to me,'' he said, speaking outside his father's home in St. Albans, Queens.</p>
        <p>Mr. Franklin was an accomplished artist who loved to draw and paint. Dan Gheno, an artist who teaches classes at the Art Students League on West 57th Street, said that Mr. Franklin attended his class regularly and that they became friends. He said he was amazed by Mr. Franklin's dedication.</p>
        <p>''He would work at night, get off work early in the morning, come to my class, be in class for four hours and then go home and go to sleep and then start it all over again,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''Artists tend to be private, and he was a great artist but also somebody who reached out to other people, and it shows in his work. There's an incredible humanity in his work that not too many artists are able to convey.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Franklin's son said he hoped to be able to put on an exhibit of his father's drawings of homeless people in the subway.</p>
        <p>At the Hoyt-Schermerhorn station yesterday morning, the only sign of what had happened the day before was some sand that had been spread on the track bed. The Queens-bound G train enters the station from a sharp turn, and an official said that might have contributed to the accident, because it gives the workers little time to react. The official, who was briefed on the investigation, said the train operator saw Mr. Franklin and Mr. Hill lifting a dolly they had been carrying onto the G platform as the train rounded the turn. He was not able to stop in time.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
