<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Orleans Homecoming (for the Lucky Ones)</title>
    <meta content="01jazz" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/arts/music/01jazz.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070511T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844200"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana/New Orleans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Orleans (La)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Jones, Norah</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Raitt, Bonnie</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Burnett, T Bone</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD9133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="966" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Orleans Homecoming (for the Lucky Ones)</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New Orleans Homecoming (for the Lucky Ones)</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON PARELES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pareles, Jon</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ORLEANS, April 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Every so often at this year's New Orleans Jazz and Heritage Festival over the weekend, musicians would announce that they were finally back in their old homes after being displaced for a more than a year by Hurricane Katrina.</p>
        <p>The queen of New Orleans soul, Irma Thomas, returned to her house two weeks ago; Jean Knight, who had the hit ''Mr. Big Stuff,'' said she was back; and Brice Miller, the trumpeter for the Mahogany Brass Band, announced on Saturday that he had just spent his first night in his old bedroom.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 38th annual Jazzfest in New Orleans was its old celebratory self, with an undercurrent of determination.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Every so often at this year's New Orleans Jazz and Heritage Festival over the weekend, musicians would announce that they were finally back in their old homes after being displaced for a more than a year by Hurricane Katrina.</p>
        <p>The queen of New Orleans soul, Irma Thomas, returned to her house two weeks ago; Jean Knight, who had the hit ''Mr. Big Stuff,'' said she was back; and Brice Miller, the trumpeter for the Mahogany Brass Band, announced on Saturday that he had just spent his first night in his old bedroom.</p>
        <p>They're the luckier ones. They didn't live in destroyed neighborhoods like the Lower Ninth Ward that are still virtually empty. And they can return to a livelihood: jobs at clubs in the more-touristed parts of New Orleans, which are back in business and ready to party.</p>
        <p>The culture of New Orleans -- the thoroughly local music, food and rituals that are connected to African processions, European carnivals, Caribbean rhythms and America's history of slavery and intermingling -- is a draw not just for tourists, but for New Orleanians. Through sheer perseverance, it is being rebuilt.</p>
        <p>The 38th annual Jazzfest was its old celebratory self, with an undercurrent of determination. Jazzfest, which continues this coming weekend, has stoked the city's culture by gathering it for the outside world to see since 1970. More than 80 percent of this year's performers are Louisiana musicians who cover a century of music, from brass bands to bayou zydeco to hip-hop.</p>
        <p>To hear the pianist Henry Butler splashing free-jazz dissonances and wild whoops and hollers into New Orleans standards like ''Tipitina,'' or to hear the Hot 8 Brass Band mixing old-fashioned oompah with Latin and hip-hop beats was to hear the continuity of a culture that faces its troubles with rhythm and flamboyance. Only in New Orleans would a band -- Bob French and the Original Tuxedo Jazz Band, to be exact -- put a traditional jazz beat under P-Funk's chant, ''Tear the roof off the sucker.''</p>
        <p>The locals shared the first weekend's lineup with headliners like Norah Jones, Bonnie Raitt, T Bone Burnett, Jill Scott, Ludacris, Brad Paisley, Pharoah Sanders and the Mexican brass band Banda el Recodo. There were also performers who were born in Louisiana, including Lucinda Williams, Jerry Lee Lewis and Johnny Rivers, whose ''Secret Agent Man'' had a touch of bayou-country swamp-pop.</p>
        <p>The visitors didn't forget where they were. They performed with New Orleans musicians: Ms. Jones with Trombone Shorty, Mr. Sanders with the trumpeter Terence Blanchard, Ms. Raitt with half a dozen guests for a weekend-closing medley of New Orleans R &amp;B.</p>
        <p>Songs were addressed to the city for both its losses and its survival. When Ms. Raitt sang her ''God Was in the Water,'' an eerie song written before Katrina, she dedicated it to the Ninth Ward, the rest of the city and ''all the people still waiting for the help they deserved.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Williams choked up as she sang her mournful ''Everything Has Changed,'' and Mr. Burnett sang apocalyptic imagery to swampy blues-rock riffs. The zydeco and Cajun musicians from the bayou country to the west, which was harder hit by Hurricane Rita, also sang about the storms; the Cajun rocker Zachary Richard had a song that vowed, ''Seven generations we've been stuck here in the mud/But the only way that I'm leaving Louisiana is if I'm swept away in a flood.''</p>
        <p>As often happens at Jazzfest, the locals -- not all of them able to return yet -- stole the show. On Sunday afternoon a set by the New Orleans Social Club defined the heart of the festival. With George Porter Jr. and Leo Nocentelli from the definitive New Orleans funk band, the Meters, along with Dr. John and Irma Thomas, the group was an all-star contingent of New Orleans musicians who had gathered in Austin six weeks after Katrina to record a benefit album.</p>
        <p>Their set reached back into New Orleans tradition, including the Mardi Gras Indian song ''Indian Red,'' which insists, ''We won't bow down,'' and it mingled anger and optimism. It also dug deep into the parade-beat rhythms that are at the roots of jazz and New Orleans R&amp;B and funk. And it had a huge crowd dancing.</p>
        <p>Jazzfest has long since become a local ritual itself, one that became more important after the hurricane made clear that New Orleans could not be taken for granted. The festival is a nonprofit event, and its Jazz and Heritage Foundation owns the license to the gloriously New Orleans-centric radio station WWOZ-FM.</p>
        <p>It also supports, quietly and pragmatically, the street processions that maintain New Orleans rhythms and communities. In recent years the foundation has paid for police permits for second-line parades, which send brass bands and fancy-suited Social Aid and Pleasure Clubs strutting through the streets. The foundation has also started to buy plumes -- pricey ostrich feathers -- for the Mardi Gras Indians who spend a year sewing the outsize suits that they flaunt from Mardi Gras season in February through Jazzfest in May.</p>
        <p>Social Aid and Pleasure Clubs and Mardi Gras Indian gangs arose in the city's poorer neighborhoods -- including some that are still depopulated -- but they are tenacious. Last year the foundation bought plumes for 80 Indians; this year for 188. Among the Mardi Gras Indians parading at Jazzfest were the Ninth Ward Hunters.</p>
        <p>One of Jazzfest's staples is its gospel tent, where local church choirs and touring gospel groups perform all day. The hurricane gave them another reason to praise the Lord: making it through.</p>
        <p>''You hurt me, Katrina, but I'm still standing!'' preached Bishop Paul S. Morton, a dynamic singer and New Orleans gospel luminary who has worked with Aretha Franklin.</p>
        <p>Then he added another message. ''If you are not from New Orleans,'' he said, ''please don't forget about us.''</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 11, 2007, Friday  A music column on May 1 about the New Orleans Jazz and Heritage Festival referred incorrectly to a song performed by Bonnie Raitt, ''God Was in the Water.'' It is by Randall Bramblett and Davis Causey, not by Ms. Raitt.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 11, 2007, Friday</p>
        <p>A music column on May 1 about the New Orleans Jazz and Heritage Festival referred incorrectly to a song performed by Bonnie Raitt, ''God Was in the Water.'' It is by Randall Bramblett and Davis Causey, not by Ms. Raitt.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
