<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Washington Wants to Know: Who's on Escort Service List?</title>
    <meta content="01madam" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/washington/01madam.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844272"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prostitution</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Palfrey, Deborah Jeane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tobias, Randall L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ullman, Harlan K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Neil A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prostitution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prostitution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington (DC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01EFD7133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="659" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Washington Wants to Know: Who's on Escort Service List?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Washington Wants to Know: Who’s on Escort Service List?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL A. LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewis, Neil A</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Deborah Jeane Palfrey, who faces charges of running prostitution ring in Washington by telephone from her home in California, says she intends to force many of her prominent and powerful clients to testify on her behalf; claims that she was operating simple escort service and that if any sexual activity occurred, it was not authorized or intended by her; names of two prominent men who used service have been revealed, Randall L Tobias, businessman, and Harlan K Ullman, Defense Dept consultant; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The woman who faces charges of running a prostitution ring in Washington that serviced the prominent and powerful said Monday that she intended to force many of those clients to testify in her behalf.</p>
        <p>The woman, Deborah Jeane Palfrey, is offering a simple defense to government charges that the escort service she ran for 13 years by telephone from her home in California was actually a straightforward prostitution business.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A woman charged with running a prostitution ring said that she intended to force many prominent clients to testify.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The woman who faces charges of running a prostitution ring in Washington that serviced the prominent and powerful said Monday that she intended to force many of those clients to testify in her behalf.</p>
        <p>The woman, Deborah Jeane Palfrey, is offering a simple defense to government charges that the escort service she ran for 13 years by telephone from her home in California was actually a straightforward prostitution business.</p>
        <p>Although she promoted her business as a legal ''high-end erotic fantasy service,'' she said it was not intended as an exchange of sex for money. She told reporters Monday that her former clients, reported to include a Bush administration economics official and the head of a conservative research group, among others, should confirm that when they are called to testify.</p>
        <p>If any sexual activity occurred, she said, it was not authorized or intended by her but undertaken independently by her female subcontractors and male clients ''who disobeyed my directives, their signed contracts and participated in illegal behavior.''</p>
        <p>In other words, she is stunned at accusations that sexual activity had taken place between the women who worked for her and the men who paid them about $300 for 90 minutes of their attentions.</p>
        <p>Washington residents have been mildly titillated by the case but more than mildly curious about the one obvious question: Who were those powerful clients?</p>
        <p>As for now, the names of only two have been revealed. The most prominent was Randall L. Tobias, a veteran businessman and the top foreign aid adviser in the State Department, who resigned Friday after he acknowledged to ABC News that he was on the list of Ms. Palfrey's clients.</p>
        <p>The other, disclosed on Ms. Palfrey's Web site, was Harlan K. Ullman, a Defense Department consultant best known for coining the phrase ''shock and awe'' to describe the intended effect on Iraq of the war's opening barrage, but the phrase also might well describe his own reaction to being called by reporters on Friday about the disclosure, about which he declined comment.</p>
        <p>Ms. Palfrey says she does not know the actual names of her clients, just their telephone numbers. She said she gave them to ABC News without compensation so the network could use its resources to match names to the numbers.</p>
        <p>ABC has used the information to prepare a story to be broadcast this Friday on its show ''20/20.'' In a promotion for the segment, ABC said on its Web site Monday that the list includes ''a Bush administration economist, the head of a conservative think tank, a prominent C.E.O., several lobbyists and a handful of military officials'' in addition to Mr. Tobias and Mr. Ullman. The network did not identify the customers by name and a spokesman declined to say whether it would do so Friday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tobias told reporters that he had used the escort service but said he only received massages.</p>
        <p>Ms. Palfrey said Monday that she felt sorry for Mr. Tobias because of the unwanted attention he had received but was gratified that he supported her account that she had not run a sex-for-money service. She chided him, however, for choosing not to come forward earlier with his ''extremely valuable exculpatory evidence.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Palfrey was in United States District Court on Monday to ask Judge Gladys Kessler to replace her court-selected lawyer, A. J. Kramer, the city's public defender. Judge Kessler said that she could choose another local lawyer, but that the court would not pay the costs for her to retain her choice, Herald Price Fahringer, a New York lawyer well known for his defense work in obscenity cases.</p>
        <p>The indictment accuses Ms. Palfrey of engaging more than 100 women from 1993 to 2006 ''for the purpose of engaging in prostitution activity with male clients, including sexual intercourse and oral sex in exchange for money.'' She made more than $2 million running the operation, known as Pamela Martin and Associates, according to the indictment.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
