<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A West Coast Orchestra, Distinctly Unmellow</title>
    <meta content="01salo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/arts/music/01salo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844189"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Los Angeles Philharmonic</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Salonen, Esa-Pekka</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Thibaudet, Jean-Yves</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E3D9133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="450" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A West Coast Orchestra, Distinctly Unmellow</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A West Coast Orchestra, Distinctly Unmellow</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE MIDGETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Midgette, Anne</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Los Angeles Philharmonic is an exciting orchestra. First, it's exciting for superficial reasons: it plays in a hot new hall designed by Frank Gehry, and it has just announced its impending transition from one crack former wunderkind conductor, Esa-Pekka Salonen, to another, Gustavo Dudamel, in 2009. But it's also exciting because of the sound it makes, big and compelling, under Mr. Salonen, who, still boyish and very much in command, showed off the ensemble he has helped to shape on Sunday afternoon at Avery Fisher Hall.</p>
        <p>The concert opened by unleashing all of the orchestra's and Mr. Salonen's strengths, exhilaratingly, upon the audience with Mr. Salonen's own piece ''Helix.'' Mr. Salonen plans to compose full time when he leaves the orchestra, and he is certainly developing happily as a composer; into an oeuvre that has always been smart and sometimes thorny are creeping elements of ease, fluidity and fun.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Los Angeles Philharmonic is an exciting orchestra because of the sound it makes under its wunderkind conductor, Esa-Pekka Salonen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Los Angeles Philharmonic is an exciting orchestra. First, it's exciting for superficial reasons: it plays in a hot new hall designed by Frank Gehry, and it has just announced its impending transition from one crack former wunderkind conductor, Esa-Pekka Salonen, to another, Gustavo Dudamel, in 2009. But it's also exciting because of the sound it makes, big and compelling, under Mr. Salonen, who, still boyish and very much in command, showed off the ensemble he has helped to shape on Sunday afternoon at Avery Fisher Hall.</p>
        <p>The concert opened by unleashing all of the orchestra's and Mr. Salonen's strengths, exhilaratingly, upon the audience with Mr. Salonen's own piece ''Helix.'' Mr. Salonen plans to compose full time when he leaves the orchestra, and he is certainly developing happily as a composer; into an oeuvre that has always been smart and sometimes thorny are creeping elements of ease, fluidity and fun.</p>
        <p>''Helix'' is an exuberant showpiece, on a much smaller scale than the piano concerto he wrote that the New York Philharmonic played in February. Its gimmick is that the tempo markings steadily increase throughout, adding propulsive force to a work that, thick with detail, throws out sounds and ideas as it builds steam. Mr. Salonen clearly enjoys immersing himself in an orchestra's sound and playing with the many things it can do, as a composer as well as a conductor.</p>
        <p>This orchestra's big sound, however, is not to be confused with opulence: energy, not sensuality, was the afternoon's hallmark. With a swirling opening not unlike that of ''La Valse'' and a roaring close like a crashing wave, ''Helix'' was well paired with Ravel's Piano Concerto for the Left Hand.</p>
        <p>But Jean-Yves Thibaudet, the soloist, and Mr. Salonen seemed more a case of opposites attracting. Mr. Thibaudet's strongest moments came in passages of quiet tenderness; in the loud opening, his playing sounded muddy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Salonen and the orchestra, by contrast, maintained their lithe athleticism; their entrances after Mr. Thibaudet's cadenzas felt like the introduction of another idea in a dialogue rather than like the seamless continuation of a whole.</p>
        <p>As for tenderness, Mr. Salonen has not a drop of schmaltz in his body, and his orchestra's strings have a taut and sometimes fuzzy muscularity rather than warmth. This rendered uneven the concluding and generally excellent suite from Prokofiev's ''Romeo and Juliet.''</p>
        <p>Parts were breathtaking: ''The Morning Dance'' drove the orchestra into a frenzy, and during ''The Death of Tybalt'' Mr. Salonen's baton whiplashed a string of fierce white chords. But the young Juliet sounded like a dancer slightly past her prime, tendons standing out as she executed the moves of a young girl flawlessly, with a frozen smile.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
