<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Conduct Costs Some Players More Than Others</title>
    <meta content="01nfl" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/sports/football/01nfl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844312"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New England Patriots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Football League</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New England Patriots</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Moss, Randy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jones, Pacman</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Belichick, Bill</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E2D6133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="903" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Conduct Costs Some Players More Than Others</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Conduct Costs Some Players More Than Others</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Perhaps it was fitting that one of the biggest stories of the N.F.L. draft was the acquisition of a player with a long and colorful history of character issues by a team that usually stays away from them. Maybe that player, Randy Moss, will never pretend to moon a bunch of Jets fans. But the New England Patriots were willing to take that risk, one day after they also took one with their first-round pick, Brandon Meriweather, who was prominently involved in an on-field brawl last season only months after he fired his gun when defending his roommate during a robbery attempt.</p>
        <p>Player conduct dominated the conversation leading up to last weekend's draft, as teams grappled with how a crackdown on misbehavior should affect the ordering of their draft boards. But those two moves by the Patriots might have best summed up the impact of the emphasis on conduct: Somewhere at the busy intersection of talent, financial risk, misbehavior and team need was where most problem players landed. Several players clearly slipped because of previous trouble. But others did not slip as far as expected.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>N.F.L. teams grappled with how a crackdown on misbehavior should affect the ordering of their draft boards.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Perhaps it was fitting that one of the biggest stories of the N.F.L. draft was the acquisition of a player with a long and colorful history of character issues by a team that usually stays away from them. Maybe that player, Randy Moss, will never pretend to moon a bunch of Jets fans. But the New England Patriots were willing to take that risk, one day after they also took one with their first-round pick, Brandon Meriweather, who was prominently involved in an on-field brawl last season only months after he fired his gun when defending his roommate during a robbery attempt.</p>
        <p>Player conduct dominated the conversation leading up to last weekend's draft, as teams grappled with how a crackdown on misbehavior should affect the ordering of their draft boards. But those two moves by the Patriots might have best summed up the impact of the emphasis on conduct: Somewhere at the busy intersection of talent, financial risk, misbehavior and team need was where most problem players landed. Several players clearly slipped because of previous trouble. But others did not slip as far as expected.</p>
        <p>Rod Graves, the Arizona Cardinals' vice president for football operations, said Sunday that he was surprised to see certain players chosen in the first three rounds Saturday.</p>
        <p>''We saw a few players go that we would not have taken because of issues we were concerned about,'' Graves said in a telephone interview. ''It still gets down to weighing the risk. Even though a certain player was taken, the risk factors in as to where they go. If you hit under those conditions, it's different.''</p>
        <p>That philosophy might have been best illustrated in the case of Marcus Thomas, a defensive tackle so talented that he could have been taken in the top 10. But he was thrown off the University of Florida team for multiple drug-related issues, and he slipped to the fourth round, where he was picked by the Denver Broncos. Thomas had been candid in talking about his troubles before the draft, attempting to persuade teams to take a chance on him.</p>
        <p>He said Sunday that he had learned his lesson and that he knew he already had 2.9 strikes against him.</p>
        <p>''We talked about taking an educated gamble,'' Denver Coach Mike Shanahan said Sunday at a news conference. ''Some people do make mistakes, and those players are the luckiest players. They come into the N.F.L. without a second chance, and they know if they do make a mistake, then they are gone. Sometimes, I think that is better than a guy that hasn't been caught and he gets two or three chances. We know exactly where the guidelines are drawn.''</p>
        <p>Shanahan noted a critical dividing line in some minds: Thomas's troubles were personal, stemming from two failed drug tests, not legal. That left teams to divine for themselves how serious they thought a situation was and how indicative of a lifestyle problem it might be. Meriweather did not slide, and Coach Bill Belichick was apparently convinced that his transgressions were aberrations.</p>
        <p>Cornerback Eric Wright, who was dismissed from Southern California and transferred to Nevada-Las Vegas after allegations of sexual assault and possession of Ecstasy (the charges were dropped), was a first-round talent, but he slipped to the second round, where Cleveland took him. Nate Harris, a Louisville linebacker who served time in a boot camp after being a lookout for an armed robbery in 2002, might have been a late-round selection if not for his background. He went undrafted.</p>
        <p>''I think it's always the same formula,'' the former Titans general manager Floyd Reese, who drafted Pacman Jones, said last week. ''As soon as you get to a point where either by number or magnitude, you can't make it right with yourself or your franchise, then I think he's eliminated. There is a frat fight, a guy grabs your date, and you do something about it. In spite of whether you think it's right or wrong, I can see that happening. Versus taking a handgun and going to a 7-Eleven and robbing it.''</p>
        <p>The impact of the new personal conduct code may be realized only in the next few years, when players selected in the first draft under the new policy are required to behave despite the trappings of wealth and fame. Midway through the first round Saturday, Commissioner Roger Goodell said that he thought the new code, which has a provision that would allow him to penalize teams that repeatedly acquire troubled players, had made its point.</p>
        <p>''I think clubs understand that character is important,'' Goodell said. ''It always was. But maybe there is greater risk now. Almost every club I've heard from has been very supportive and said it was time to do it.''</p>
        <p>Moments later, the Buffalo Bills selected running back Marshawn Lynch, who had been accused of sexual assault by a former girlfriend, with the 12th pick. Perhaps they were swayed by a package his agents sent to all teams, which included a report from a district attorney and letters from Lynch's lawyers explaining that a lack of evidence meant that no charges would be brought against him.</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>In a letter sent to the league on Saturday, Tennessee Titans cornerback Pacman Jones appealed his season-long suspension for violating the personal-conduct policy. The appeal will be heard within 10 days unless both sides agree on a different timetable.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
