<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Names Are Vintage, the Touches Modern</title>
    <meta content="01adco" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/business/media/01adco.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844278"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Home Appliances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Paper Products</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Dairy Queen</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Whirlpool Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Georgia-Pacific Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paper and Pulp</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Appliances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Maytag Corporation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804EED7133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1188" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Names Are Vintage, the Touches Modern</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Names Are Vintage, the Touches Modern</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STUART ELLIOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Advertising column on how companies such as Whirlpool, which owns Maytag, Dairy Queen and Georgia-Pacific are updating familiar advertising characters for new campaigns; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THEY used to say that life begins at 40. For a familiar advertising character, the lonely Maytag repairman, a new life is beginning at 40 as he gets a major personality makeover.</p>
        <p>The character, who started appearing in national commercials in 1967, is becoming more active and gregarious, in a change meant to update the concept of ''Ol' Lonely'' for a new generation of shoppers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The lonely Maytag repairman is getting a personality makeover in a change meant to appeal to a new generation of shoppers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THEY used to say that life begins at 40. For a familiar advertising character, the lonely Maytag repairman, a new life is beginning at 40 as he gets a major personality makeover.</p>
        <p>The character, who started appearing in national commercials in 1967, is becoming more active and gregarious, in a change meant to update the concept of ''Ol' Lonely'' for a new generation of shoppers.</p>
        <p>No longer is the repairman a solitary layabout with nothing to do, waiting for calls to fix Maytag appliances that never come. Now he takes the initiative to repair other things that Maytag implies ought to be as dependable as its appliances, among them office copiers and cable TV.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the character retains his low-key attitude and aw-shucks manners, which are intended to personify what the new owner of Maytag, Whirlpool, considers to be core values of the Maytag brand.</p>
        <p>The curtain is to be raised today on the new character with a television commercial to appear from early morning, on shows like ''Today,'' through prime time, on shows like ''American Idol.''</p>
        <p>There will also be ads online, on Web sites like maytag.com and nextmaytagrepairman.com. And plans call for personal appearances in unexpected places by Clay Jackson, who recently became the fourth person to portray the repairman nationally since the character's creation by Leo Burnett in Chicago, part of the Publicis Groupe. Previous Maytag repairmen were the actors Jesse White, from 1967-88; Gordon Jump, 1989-2003; and Hardy Rawls, 2003-7.</p>
        <p>In undertaking such revampings, marketers confront a tricky balancing act. They want to ensure that well-known brand symbols stay current. But they prefer not to alter the characters so much that the changes alienate consumers who liked the original versions.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't say it's without risk,'' Jeffrey Davidoff, vice president for Maytag brand marketing at the Whirlpool Corporation in Benton Harbor, Mich., said of the changes to the repairman.</p>
        <p>''We believe we have retained the characteristics that made the character great,'' Mr. Davidoff said, in that ''he still has nothing to do because Maytag's product quality is so high.''</p>
        <p>''But in terms of what is the best way to make him part of today's world, we decided to get him out in today's world instead of just sitting in his office,'' he added, where the character had so frequently been seen over the last four decades.</p>
        <p>At one point, it seemed that it would not matter whether or not ad characters appealed to contemporary consumers because the characters were perceived as old-fashioned -- relics of the era of mass marketing through mass media.</p>
        <p>Recently, though, characters have been making something of a comeback, as illustrated by a lengthening list of advertisers who are bringing out new characters or freshening vintage ones.</p>
        <p>''There seems to be a bit of a resurgence of character-based advertising,'' said Michael Keller, chief brand officer at International Dairy Queen in Minneapolis, part of Berkshire Hathaway. Mr. Keller cited examples like a talking family of Whopper sandwiches, sponsored by Burger King, and a line of anthropomorphic mustards from the French's division of Reckitt Benckiser.</p>
        <p>Dairy Queen is getting into the act, too, introducing two characters to be the stars of a $25 million campaign beginning this week for new products like the Waffle Bowl Sundae. The characters, created by Grey Worldwide in New York, part of the WPP Group, are ''definitely a bit tongue in cheek,'' Mr. Keller said, to signal younger consumers that Dairy Queen has a sense of humor about dairy products behaving like people.</p>
        <p>The Maytag makeover is also meant to make the campaign more humorous, not by turning the repairman into a clown but by placing him in funny situations.</p>
        <p>''The new repairman is no longer fatalistic,'' Mr. Davidoff said, ''but optimistic.''</p>
        <p>For instance, in the new commercial, two office workers find the repairman visiting their workplace. The male worker is convinced he caused the visit by leaving leftovers too long in the office refrigerator.</p>
        <p>His female co-worker clues him in: The repairman is actually there to fix the copier, which is of course a product Maytag does not make.</p>
        <p>''So you're trying to keep busy, huh?'' she asks the repairman. He helpfully lets her know the copier is running low on toner.</p>
        <p>The character ''has clearly got a lot of time on his hands; that has been the setup for decades,'' said Ed Han, senior vice president and creative director at the present Maytag agency, Publicis USA in New York, part of the Publicis Worldwide unit of Publicis.</p>
        <p>''Now, he has a younger approach to life,'' Mr. Han said. ''He wants to be out there more, and since he's mechanically inclined -- he is a repairman -- this plays off the character's story.''</p>
        <p>Publicis New York, which creates campaigns for appliances bearing the Whirlpool brand, inherited the Maytag assignment last May from its sibling, Burnett, after Whirlpool acquired Maytag.</p>
        <p>''There were definitely discussions about 'do we or don't we' '' keep the character, Mr. Han said, but ''after research with consumers, we found there was so much equity left in him that it would be foolish to do away with the character.''</p>
        <p>Still, the consumers were telling the agency ''the repairman had become old-fashioned,'' Mr. Han said. That was hindering efforts to sell Maytag appliances on the basis of modernity, he added, to counter inroads by newer brands like LG and Samsung.</p>
        <p>Another benefit of the new personality for the Maytag repairman is that it lets the character be shown as competent in what he does.</p>
        <p>By contrast, all those years he sat around waiting to fix Maytags that did not break down, he showed his proficiency only at tasks like playing solitaire.</p>
        <p>Mr. Davidoff said the personality change would enhance the character's ability to sell Maytags on the basis of features and benefits because ''the idea he has familiarity and expertise with the products makes sense.''</p>
        <p>And by having the repairman spend his time repairing other things, Mr. Davidoff said, it avoids ''making him a huckster.''</p>
        <p>That type of persona for a brand character, which plays down the peddling, also appealed to Georgia-Pacific, which is introducing a stylish, make-believe wife and mother named Phoebe Fontaine as the personification of its Vanity Fair brand of paper napkins.</p>
        <p>Ads by the Seiden Group in New York present Phoebe not as an old-school ''brand icon,'' said Kimberlee Burrows, director for marketing communications at Georgia-Pacific in Atlanta, but more as a modern ''brand ambassador.''</p>
        <p>''It bridges the gap between our parents' generation and ours,'' Ms. Burrows said.</p>
        <p>Phoebe, being new, is a blank slate, whom Georgia-Pacific and Seiden can make as modern as they please. The Maytag repairman, on the other hand, dates to the year ''In the Heat of the Night'' was in movie theaters, the first microwave oven was sold for home use and the Beatles released ''Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band.''</p>
        <p>Whirlpool and Publicis New York are not minimizing the challenges inherent in making over so venerable a character.</p>
        <p>''It's like moving a china cabinet full of china,'' Mr. Davidoff said.</p>
        <p>''You can move it,'' he added, laughing. ''Just not too fast.''</p>
        <p>ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
