<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Costs and Divestitures Cut Verizon's Profit</title>
    <meta content="01verizon" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/technology/01verizon.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844231"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Verizon Communications</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flynn, Laurie J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Toben, Doreen A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Verizon Communications</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E0D8133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="701" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Costs and Divestitures Cut Verizon's Profit</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Costs and Divestitures Cut Verizon's Profit</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURIE J. FLYNN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Flynn, Laurie J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mergers costs and divestiture of some businesses drove Verizon's profit down 8.4 percent in first quarter, but company continues to have strong growth in wireless and broadband subscriptions; net income was $1.5 billion compared with $1.63 billion year earlier; revenue rose 6.4 percent, to $22.58 billion, from $21.23 billion year ago; chief financial officer Doreen A Toben comments (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Merger costs and the divestiture of some businesses drove Verizon's profit down 8.4 percent in the first quarter, but the company continued to have strong growth in wireless and broadband subscriptions.</p>
        <p>Verizon Communications, like its larger rival AT&amp;T, faces challenges as it tries to move beyond being just a phone company to offering services that include mobile, Internet and television in addition to its landlines.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Profit was down 8.4 percent but the company continued to have strong growth in wireless and broadband subscriptions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Merger costs and the divestiture of some businesses drove Verizon's profit down 8.4 percent in the first quarter, but the company continued to have strong growth in wireless and broadband subscriptions.</p>
        <p>Verizon Communications, like its larger rival AT&amp;T, faces challenges as it tries to move beyond being just a phone company to offering services that include mobile, Internet and television in addition to its landlines.</p>
        <p>Those challenges have the companies devising formulas for competing with the avalanche of services being introduced by cable companies.</p>
        <p>Verizon executives said yesterday that a strong point for the company had been customer adoption of its new television and Internet services, which resulted from a nearly $20 billion investment by Verizon in a fiber-optic network that can transmit video and data at high speeds.</p>
        <p>''We're off to a good start,'' Verizon's chief financial officer, Doreen A. Toben, said. ''We're very pleased with our results this quarter.''</p>
        <p>Verizon reported net income of $1.5 billion in the quarter, or 51 cents a share, compared with $1.63 billion, or 56 cents a share, a year earlier.</p>
        <p>The results include a one-time loss of $131 million, or 5 cents a share, related to the nationalization of Venezuela's main phone company, in which Verizon was a part owner. The company also completed the sale of assets in Puerto Rico in the quarter.</p>
        <p>Revenue rose 6.4 percent to $22.58 billion, from $21.23 billion a year ago.</p>
        <p>Excluding special items and discontinued operations, Verizon would have earned $1.56 billion, or 54 cents a share, up from $1.36 billion, or 46 cents a share, a year earlier. Analysts had expected Verizon to earn 53 cents a share on revenue of $22.49 billion, according to a survey by Thomson Financial. Verizon shares rose 29 cents, to $38.18.</p>
        <p>''The quarter was largely in line,'' said Qaisar Hasan, an analyst with Buckingham Research. ''Their wireless did a little better than we thought it would, and the wireline a little worse.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hasan said he was impressed by early growth that was better than expected of Verizon's new digital video and data network, called FiOS.</p>
        <p>''The reception is as good as it could be,'' Ms. Toben said. She said the company continued to add regions and expected to achieve the hefty subscriber goals it set for itself as it tries to meet growing consumer demand for access to video programming like that offered by YouTube.</p>
        <p>The continued high cost of introducing FiOS diluted Verizon's earnings by 11 cents a share, as the company had forecast. Company executives said they expect the dilution to amount to 10 cents a share in the second quarter.</p>
        <p>Verizon added 416,000 high-speed connections in the quarter, helping offset its losses in its landline business. The company added 141,000 customers to its FiOS TV service, ending the quarter with 348,000. As of last week, AT&amp;T had about 20,000 subscribers to its new television service, U-verse.</p>
        <p>Verizon's wireless business, which Verizon owns jointly with the Vodafone Group, reported revenue of $10.3 billion in the first quarter. The unit added 1.7 million wireless subscribers, ending the quarter with 60.7 million subscribers, second only to AT&amp;T Wireless, which serves 62.2 million customers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hasan said Verizon was also helped by the fact that a larger number of Verizon's wireless customers in the quarter were monthly subscribers, rather than prepaid customers.</p>
        <p>Adding to its good news, the rate at which Verizon customers canceled subscriptions, known as the churn rate, declined to 1.08 percent from 1.14 percent a year earlier.</p>
        <p>Verizon, like AT&amp;T, has struggled to stem defections from its wireline customers. Its wireline business had a 0.1 percent increase in revenue in the quarter, to $12.5 billion, with most of that coming from Verizon's acquisition of MCI last year. Adjusting for the acquisition of MCI, wireline revenue declined 1.7 percent.</p>
        <p>Verizon is embroiled in a lawsuit with Vonage Holdings, the Internet phone company, which Verizon has accused of patent violation. Last week, a federal appeals court ruled that Vonage could continue to sign up customers while it appealed an earlier ruling that found Vonage to be in violation. The court set a June court date to hear Vonage's appeal, several months sooner than expected.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
