<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Free Drug Samples? Bad Idea, Some Say</title>
    <meta content="01cons" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health&amp;Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/health/01cons.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844173"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE CONSUMER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Columns/The Consumer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E5D9133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="900" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Free Drug Samples? Bad Idea, Some Say</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Free Drug Samples? Bad Idea, Some Say</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONI CARYN RABIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Everyone loves freebies, and patients are no exception. So drug company sales representatives try to keep sample cabinets in medical offices well stocked with the latest medications, for doctors to dispense as the need arises.</p>
        <p>Patients like going home with free samples because it saves them a trip to the drugstore and a co-pay, and doctors are happy to oblige, because samples help patients get started on treatment right away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some leading academic medical centers are restricting the use of drug samples, and a smattering of physician practices are shutting down the sample cabinet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Everyone loves freebies, and patients are no exception. So drug company sales representatives try to keep sample cabinets in medical offices well stocked with the latest medications, for doctors to dispense as the need arises.</p>
        <p>Patients like going home with free samples because it saves them a trip to the drugstore and a co-pay, and doctors are happy to oblige, because samples help patients get started on treatment right away.</p>
        <p>But now some leading academic medical centers are restricting the use of samples, and a smattering of physician practices are shutting down the sample cabinet. These critics say doctors should be choosing the most appropriate medication for a patient based on the best scientific evidence available -- not just grabbing something from the office stash that happens to fit the bill.</p>
        <p>''The doctor will say, 'Here, start on this, and let's see how it works,' '' said David J. Rothman, president of the Institute on Medicine as a Profession, a research group at Columbia. ''The question to the doctor is: If you didn't have it in your drawer, would that have been your drug of choice?''</p>
        <p>The crackdown on free samples comes amid growing concern about the close ties between physicians and drug companies. Critics like Dr. Rothman say physicians don't realize the extent to which their medical judgment is influenced by their acceptance of the samples. They point to studies like a 2002 paper in the journal Annals of Family Medicine finding that the number of doctors who treated high blood pressure with the ''first line'' drugs recommended by national guidelines was low, but increased sharply when free samples were removed.</p>
        <p>So far, the University of Michigan Health System has banned free samples altogether, and the University of Pennsylvania and Stanford University medical schools have prohibited staff members from accepting them (though samples can be given to Stanford's pharmacy for use in free clinics).</p>
        <p>Some medical groups and solo practitioners have also changed their policies. Dr. Jonathan Mohrer, an internist in Forest Hills, Queens, said he closed his sample cabinet in part because his office was overrun with sales representatives. ''It was totally spinning out of control,'' Dr. Mohrer said. ''They were meeting each other and schmoozing in the waiting room -- it was like a party.''</p>
        <p>His office staff had to spend time arranging the cabinet, throwing out expired medications and rummaging around for the right drug. Patients were kept waiting while sales representatives were whisked in.</p>
        <p>But there's an upside to the samples. Using samples, a doctor can see if a patient can tolerate a new medication before the patient goes out and buys a 30-day supply. Physicians who treat poor people like to have samples on hand for them, and for uninsured patients.</p>
        <p>Samples also provide patients with the convenience of one-stop shopping, said Dr. Hema A. Sundaram, a dermatologist in suburban Washington. ''Usually a patient has waited some time to see a doctor and rearranged their whole working schedule, and then it may be another four or five days before they can fill a prescription,'' she said. ''They're often busy, working people, with family responsibilities. I feel there shouldn't be any further delay.'' (Dr. Sundaram acknowledges that she is paid for speaking on behalf of drug companies.)</p>
        <p>And many physicians say they like using samples because the sales representatives are an important source of medical education, helping to keep the doctors up to date on the latest therapies.</p>
        <p>''Doctors who are shutting the door to sales reps are cutting themselves off from a lot of valuable information,'' said Scott Lassman, senior assistant general counsel for the Pharmaceutical Research and Manufacturers of America, a trade association. ''Sales reps can explain when it's right to use a drug, when it's not right to use the drug, which patients might benefit and which patients it might not work for.''</p>
        <p>Some doctors are skeptical. ''The sales reps are nice people, and they try to do a really good job,'' said Dr. Judith Chamberlain, medical director of the Bowdoin Medical Group, a practice near Portland, Me., that banned samples this year. ''But their job is to get you to use their product.''</p>
        <p>A 1995 study in The Journal of the American Medical Association found that 11 percent of the statements drug company representatives made during presentations were inaccurate, and all of the inaccuracies were skewed in favor of their products.</p>
        <p>The drugs promoted through free samples tend to be the newer medications that doctors are less familiar with, experts say. Some critics of samples say they prefer using older drugs anyway, because their side effects are better known. Critics also point out that helping poor and uninsured patients is not the intent of the sample distribution, and they add that developments like Medicare's prescription-drug coverage, the proliferation of generic drugs and improvements in drug company patient-assistance programs have eased access to medication.</p>
        <p>As for the bottom line, it's not at all clear that samples save patients money. Critics say they may actually drive up the cost of health care in the long run, because the drugs being promoted are the most expensive brand-name medications. Since many conditions require lifelong treatment, the patient would have to buy the medicine sooner or later.</p>
        <p>''You're going to be paying more, because you're taking the new, advanced drug,'' Dr. Rothman said. ''And you may have done just fine on the old-fashioned generic.''</p>
        <p>THE CONSUMER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
