<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>One More Tango for Brando and His Golden Mumble</title>
    <meta content="01bran" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/arts/television/01bran.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844186"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Actors and Actresses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Actors and Actresses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Turner Classic Movies</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Brando, Marlon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E3D9133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="766" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>One More Tango for Brando and His Golden Mumble</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">One More Tango for Brando and His Golden Mumble</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIRGINIA HEFFERNAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Heffernan, Virginia</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''He was sort of a different type of a person,'' ventures Betty Gossell, who went to high school with Marlon Brando in Illinois. A different type of person. That may be the last word on Brando, who died in 2004.</p>
        <p>No significantly more penetrating insight is offered into Brando's character by Al Pacino, Robert Duvall, Johnny Depp, John Travolta and Jane Fonda in ''Brando,'' a two-part documentary about this big man that begins tonight on Turner Classic Movies. But their hymns to him are poignant and worth hearing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As this documentary makes clear, hitting its points with style, Marlon Brando wasn’t like other movie stars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''He was sort of a different type of a person,'' ventures Betty Gossell, who went to high school with Marlon Brando in Illinois. A different type of person. That may be the last word on Brando, who died in 2004.</p>
        <p>No significantly more penetrating insight is offered into Brando's character by Al Pacino, Robert Duvall, Johnny Depp, John Travolta and Jane Fonda in ''Brando,'' a two-part documentary about this big man that begins tonight on Turner Classic Movies. But their hymns to him are poignant and worth hearing.</p>
        <p>As the documentary makes clear, hitting its points with style, Marlon Brando wasn't like other movie stars. He wasn't like other serious actors. He wasn't like other rebels. He wasn't like other ladies' men. He was different.</p>
        <p>''He drummed on everything too,'' says Janet Aemisegger, a white-haired woman who said she used to sit in front of Brando in algebra class.</p>
        <p>Hmm. The image piques interest. Brando was one of those chronically drumming kids. What do you know? In a 1955 interview with Ed Sullivan, young Brando in suit and skinny tie talks of his love of rhythm, recalling the pulsation of the donkey engine for the water pump on his family's farm. With a half-smile, he even breaks into a jazzy whispery impression of the engine. Fwuhhh-fwuh-fwuh-fwuh-fwuh.</p>
        <p>Curse that Brando. At that fwuhhh he gets you all over again, from the grave this time, devilish and freakish and heartbreaking, even when we know how it ends: with Brando in Colonel Kurtz mode, obese, portentous, self-infatuated, preening. That too seems gorgeous, come to think of it.</p>
        <p>Brando fans may watch this program, as we watch the Brando movies or read the Brando books, in hopes of deciding the question of whether the big man was mostly a genius or mostly a fat fool. A decisive clue is not here.</p>
        <p>As image after beautiful image appears, the clearest conclusion is that we are the fools, for falling for him, like Stella, like that sulky Frenchwoman in ''Last Tango in Paris.'' Or, for that matter, like Tarita Teriipaia, Brando's former wife, who published a memoir in 2004 called, ''Marlon, My Love, My Suffering.''</p>
        <p>So first comes review. Brando's father was mean, and his mother was drunk. Ms. Fonda, in a garish cowboy hat that suggests her interview was taped during her fad years, complicates the picture of Brando's boozing mother somewhat by reminding viewers that Dorothy Brando gave her father, Henry Fonda, his start as an actor. It seems she recruited him for a community play in Omaha.</p>
        <p>Brando's father was a traveling salesman with girlfriends. He was cruel at home, but seldom there. Brando was sent to military school, where he acted, played football and hurt his knee. The injury exempted him from the World War II draft, and he moved to New York. At this cue ''Brando'' cuts to stock film of city girls in spackled makeup batting eyes at the camera. This is what Brando is believed to have found in Times Square.</p>
        <p>As the film chronicles Brando's career, fellow actors give head-shaking descriptions of his so-called mumbly-stumbly acting style. Broadway actors of the '40s were still accustomed to crisp presentationalism, while Brando, freshly anointed by the Method grande dame Stella Adler, would talk into his sweater, murmur and upstage himself, seeming to subvert the very purpose of performance.</p>
        <p>Later accounts of his hackwork (''Candy,'' anyone?), when he was acting to support his life in Tahiti or his forays into politics, are entertaining. Supremely bratty about his talents and lazy about memorizing dialogue, he only supplied directors with glimpses of what they were paying for.</p>
        <p>And then came ''The Godfather,'' and the part for which Mr. Pacino convincingly says he first proposed Brando, whose career was on the skids by then. James Caan and Robert Duvall reminisce like schoolboys about their hero. Then came ''Last Tango,'' and the butter. Brando was back, and, as Martin Scorsese says, he was also done.</p>
        <p>Everyone on film here, including Laurence Olivier and Quincy Jones, including the people Brando relentlessly hazed and wrong-footed, indulges in Brando worship. (A surprising moment: Olivier's undated insistence that Brando is a better actor than he is.)</p>
        <p>This film could use a skeptic, though it's eventually to be commended for refraining from bashing Brando too hard for his obvious personal failings. In the end there's something direct, simple and thorough about ''Brando.'' With the leading man gone, the film seems to come with remarkably little baggage and few strings. The same probably cannot be said about any production involving Brando when he lived.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
