<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unsatisfied With Results, but Sticking With Torre</title>
    <meta content="01yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/sports/baseball/01yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844311"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Texas Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Texas Rangers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <org class="online_producer">American League</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Steinbrenner, George M 3d</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Torre, Joe</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Cashman, Brian</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3D6133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1087" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unsatisfied With Results, but Sticking With Torre</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Torre and Cashman Are Safe, for Now</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>George Steinbrenner made it clear yesterday that he was not ready to fire anybody after 23 games. But with 14 losses already, and a pitching staff that has been exposed as inferior to that of the Boston Red Sox, it is convenient that the Yankees play in Texas this week.</p>
        <p>Texas, of course, is the home state of Roger Clemens, the man with more victories than any living pitcher. By the end of the month, Clemens is expected to decide whether to continue his career. With Brian Cashman, the Yankees' general manager, along for this trip, it is easy to imagine a meeting in Houston.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees’ owner said he supports the team’s manager and general manager but that he is also impatient.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>George Steinbrenner made it clear yesterday that he was not ready to fire anybody after 23 games. But with 14 losses already, and a pitching staff that has been exposed as inferior to that of the Boston Red Sox, it is convenient that the Yankees play in Texas this week.</p>
        <p>Texas, of course, is the home state of Roger Clemens, the man with more victories than any living pitcher. By the end of the month, Clemens is expected to decide whether to continue his career. With Brian Cashman, the Yankees' general manager, along for this trip, it is easy to imagine a meeting in Houston.</p>
        <p>''None of us will be in Arlington,'' Clemens's agent, Randy Hendricks, said in an e-mail message yesterday when asked about a possible meeting between Clemens and Cashman. ''Beyond that, I should not comment.''</p>
        <p>Reached by telephone yesterday right before the Yankees' charter took off from Newark Liberty International Airport, Cashman was vague about his reasons for traveling with the team, which Cashman rarely does.</p>
        <p>''We talked about what was best right now and we all agreed it was best for me to be here with the team,'' said Cashman, who canceled a trip to the Dominican Republic.</p>
        <p>Steinbrenner issued a 127-word statement yesterday in which he said he supported Torre, Cashman and the players, while trying to convey his impatience with the ragged start.</p>
        <p>''Let's get going,'' concluded the statement, issued through Steinbrenner's spokesman, Howard Rubenstein. ''Let's go out and win and bring a world championship back to New York. That's what I want.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees have lost eight of their past nine games, including five of six to the Red Sox, who are 16-8 and six and a half games ahead of the last-place Yankees in the American League East.</p>
        <p>''I appreciate his support,'' Cashman said. ''He's given us every opportunity to be successful, and he's going to continue to do that.''</p>
        <p>Two years ago, after 23 games, the Yankees had the same record and stood the same number of games out of first place. They recovered to win the division with a large assist from pitchers Shawn Chacon and Aaron Small, who combined to go 17-3 in the second half.</p>
        <p>Cashman said that he would continue to seek help outside the organization, although trades are rare so early in the season. The Yankees must recover soon, because the coming schedule has another batch of showcase games and Steinbrenner made no long-term promises.</p>
        <p>''He's saying, 'Go out there and win,' '' Rubenstein said. ''He's not firing them now. He's really being supportive of them now.''</p>
        <p>Rubenstein later said not to read into his use of the word ''now,'' saying that Steinbrenner discussed only the crisis of the moment. But with the Yankees already five games under .500, there will be urgency to win every game. The Yankees' next 10 games are against the Rangers and the Mariners, then they face the opponents who matter most to Steinbrenner. The Yankees play a three-game series with the Mets at Shea Stadium from May 18 to 20, then play host to the Red Sox the next three days. From June 1 to 3, the Yankees are at Boston for another series.</p>
        <p>If the Yankees have shown no signs of improvement by then, Steinbrenner may not be so forgiving. At such an early point in the season, though, Rubenstein said that Steinbrenner wanted to quell speculation on the fate of Torre, and, to a lesser extent, of Cashman.</p>
        <p>''The season is still very young, but up to now the results are clearly not acceptable to me or to Yankee fans,'' Steinbrenner's statement said. ''However, Brian Cashman, our general manager; Joe Torre, our manager; and our players all believe that they will turn this around quickly.</p>
        <p>''I believe in them. I am here to support them in any way to help them accomplish this turnaround. It is time to put excuses and talk away. It is time to see if people are ready to step up and accept their responsibilities. It is time for all of them to show me and the fans what they are made of.''</p>
        <p>Rubenstein said that he spoke yesterday morning on a conference call with Steinbrenner and the two top New York-based executives -- Randy Levine, the president, and Lonn Trost, the chief operating officer. But he added that the statement was Steinbrenner's alone.</p>
        <p>Rubenstein said that he did not know if Steinbrenner, 76, was consulted by his sons, Hank and Hal, who have taken a more active role as general partners this year, with Steve Swindal, another general partner, going through a divorce from Steinbrenner's daughter Jennifer.</p>
        <p>Several Yankees came out strongly in defense of Torre last weekend, especially the captain, Derek Jeter. Rubenstein said that he did not discuss Jeter's comments with Steinbrenner but that said Steinbrenner seemed to accept the idea that the players deserved blame.</p>
        <p>''There are a lot of terrific athletes, and now it's up to all three of them -- the athletes, the manager and the general manager,'' Rubenstein said. ''He's always said that about Torre and Cashman, but now he's including the ballplayers: 'All three of you, go out and win.' He kept saying that over and over to me.''</p>
        <p>Torre is in the final season of a three-year, $19.2 million contract he signed in April 2004. Since then, the Yankees have crumbled to the Red Sox in the American League Championship Series and lost in the division series the next two seasons.</p>
        <p>Yet Torre retains a revered status and is seemingly a lock for the Hall of Fame as a manager. Steinbrenner has been leery of the backlash that could come from firing Torre. There is also a sense in the organization that it would be unfair to Torre's most likely successor, Don Mattingly, to replace Torre under these circumstances. Mattingly is in his first full season as the bench coach and has never managed.</p>
        <p>The idea of succeeding Torre, though, is off the table for now. Steinbrenner made it clear yesterday that he wants this regime to start winning, and to do so immediately.</p>
        <p>''We're going to get through this, that's the bottom line,'' Cashman said. ''With our manager and our coaching staff and our players, we're going to pull through this together.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Center fielder Johnny Damon flew home to Orlando, Fla., to visit his chiropractor, hoping for improvement in his sore back. Brian Cashman said that he was not considering placing Damon on the disabled list.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
