<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets Falter And Face Test as Two Go on D.L.</title>
    <meta content="01mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/sports/baseball/01mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844314"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Florida Marlins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hernandez, Orlando</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Valentin, Jose</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E2D6133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="858" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets Falter And Face Test as Two Go on D.L.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mets’ Depth Faces Test as 2 Players Go on D.L.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID PICKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Picker, David</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By almost all measures, the Mets had an impressive April. On the last day of the month, however, they were confronted with injuries to two prominent players, then were hammered by the Florida Marlins at Shea Stadium.</p>
        <p>The right-handed starter Orlando Hernández was scratched before last night's game, which the Mets lost, 9-6, and placed on the 15-day disabled list, retroactive to April 25, with bursitis in his pitching shoulder. He is expected to miss two starts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Mets had an impressive April. But on the last day of the month, they were confronted with injuries to two prominent players, then were hammered by the Florida Marlins at Shea Stadium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By almost all measures, the Mets had an impressive April. On the last day of the month, however, they were confronted with injuries to two prominent players, then were hammered by the Florida Marlins at Shea Stadium.</p>
        <p>The right-handed starter Orlando Hernández was scratched before last night's game, which the Mets lost, 9-6, and placed on the 15-day disabled list, retroactive to April 25, with bursitis in his pitching shoulder. He is expected to miss two starts.</p>
        <p>The news for second baseman José Valentín was worse. He was also placed on the 15-day disabled list, retroactive to April 29. But he is expected to miss two to four weeks with a partly torn ligament in his right knee.</p>
        <p>''I'm never one to panic in a situation like this,'' Manager Willie Randolph said. ''It's early in the season. We have to pick each other up. It's a good thing we have some depth.''</p>
        <p>The Mets (15-9) brought up the right-hander Chan Ho Park from Class AAA New Orleans to start in Hernández's place last night. Rubén Gotay, an infielder, was also called up from New Orleans, but Damion Easley started at second base.</p>
        <p>Park did not allow a hit until Florida's starter, Scott Olsen, singled with two outs in the third inning. Things then spiraled out of control as Olsen and the next four batters scored to give the Marlins a 5-0 lead.</p>
        <p>After Olsen's hit, Park walked the next two batters to load the bases. Miguel Cabrera then hit a two-run single that popped out of Easley's glove, opening the floodgates.</p>
        <p>''It's tough luck today,'' Park said with a shrug.</p>
        <p>In the fourth inning, Alfredo Amézaga and Hanley Ramírez hit bases-empty homers as Florida (12-13) went ahead, 7-0.</p>
        <p>In four innings, Park allowed seven earned runs and six hits while striking out four and walking two. He was booed loudly after the top of the fourth, adding insult to two costly injuries.</p>
        <p>The injury to Hernández, although it does not appear to be as serious as Valentín's, is perhaps a bigger concern for the Mets because he is their No. 2 starter and has a history of breaking down.</p>
        <p>Hernández said that he first felt tightness in his shoulder Sunday at Washington. A magnetic resonance imaging test revealed no structural damage, General Manager Omar Minaya said. Hernández had a cortisone shot, although last night he said he did not feel any better.</p>
        <p>Asked if he thought he would need more than 15 days to recover, Hernández said, ''I don't know the future.''</p>
        <p>Hernández is 2-1 with a 2.53 earned run average. Although he is listed as 37, he is widely believed to be 41.</p>
        <p>Hernández did not appear in the postseason last year because he tore a muscle in his right calf while running in the outfield a day before the Mets' division series opener against the Los Angeles Dodgers. He missed the 2003 season after tearing his rotator cuff while playing for the Yankees, and he dealt with arthritis in his neck and a strained right hamstring this year in spring training.</p>
        <p>The Mets' rotation this season has been led by Tom Glavine and John Maine, but Mike Pelfrey, a rookie who is scheduled to start tonight against Florida, has struggled. If he pitches poorly again, he may be demoted.</p>
        <p>''Right now, we're expecting Pelfrey to pitch well,'' Minaya said when asked about the implications of tonight's game.</p>
        <p>Last night, the Mets chipped away at Florida's lead. Carlos Beltrán led the comeback attempt, tying a career high with four hits, including a solo home run in the fifth off Olsen.</p>
        <p>But the Mets were unable to make up for their deficiencies. It is not clear if Park, an off-season free-agent acquisition who was 3-1 with a 7.29 E.R.A. at New Orleans, will make another start.</p>
        <p>''It's too early to tell,'' said Randolph, who may consider Jorge Sosa or Philip Humber.</p>
        <p>Valentín was on crutches and wore a brace in the clubhouse yesterday but said he was not in pain. He was injured Saturday while covering second base during the third inning of a game at Washington. He sustained a similar injury to his right knee in 2005 and missed three months.</p>
        <p>Valentín, 37, said yesterday that he did not want to have surgery because it would end his season, and that he could have surgery after the season, if necessary. His one-year contract has a club option for next year that becomes guaranteed at $4.3 million if he has 400 plate appearances.</p>
        <p>''I'm kind of happy and relaxed now that I know it's not worse like I thought it was going to be,'' said Valentín, who is batting .279 and will wear the brace when he returns.</p>
        <p>The Mets will be pleased, too, if Valentín returns this month. For now, they will settle for May beginning on a better note.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>David Wright popped out with runners at second and third to end the first and third innings. He finished 0 for 5.  Moises Alou needed two stitches on his chin after crashing into the wall on Jason Wood's eighth-inning double.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
