<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Moscow in 1996, a Doctor's Visit Changed History</title>
    <meta content="01docs" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health&amp;Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/health/01docs.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844174"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE DOCTOR'S WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Columns/The Doctor's World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Heart</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anatomy and Physiology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">DeBakey, Michael E</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Yeltsin, Boris N</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E5D9133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1300" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Moscow in 1996, a Doctor's Visit Changed History</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Moscow in 1996, a Doctor’s Visit Changed History</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Lawrence K. Altman, M.D.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was the fall of 1996, and Boris N. Yeltsin was running for re-election as Russia's first president in the post-Soviet era. But he faced a crisis far more threatening than any opponent: he was desperately ill.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeltsin had had a heart attack. He was experiencing chest pain from angina. He needed a coronary bypass operation. But his Russian doctors said he could not survive such surgery.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dr. Michael E. DeBakey performed heart surgery on Boris Yeltsin that saved his life and altered the course of history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was the fall of 1996, and Boris N. Yeltsin was running for re-election as Russia's first president in the post-Soviet era. But he faced a crisis far more threatening than any opponent: he was desperately ill.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeltsin had had a heart attack. He was experiencing chest pain from angina. He needed a coronary bypass operation. But his Russian doctors said he could not survive such surgery.</p>
        <p>For independent advice, Mr. Yeltsin reached out to an American doctor as renowned in Russia as he was in the United States: Dr. Michael E. DeBakey, the pioneering Houston heart surgeon.</p>
        <p>Dr. DeBakey agreed to go to Moscow, and after examining Mr. Yeltsin he determined that the Russian leader could indeed survive a bypass operation. It was not widely noted in the obituaries for Mr. Yeltsin, who died last week at 76, but that consultation very likely saved his presidency, if not his life.</p>
        <p>In doing so, it changed the course of history. Among other things, if Mr. Yeltsin had not been re-elected, he would never have had the opportunity to reach deep into the Russian bureaucracy to select Vladimir V. Putin, then an obscure functionary, as his successor.</p>
        <p>''All the doctors agreed Yeltsin would have died if he did not have the bypass,'' Dr. DeBakey said in an interview yesterday. ''No question about that, because he was deteriorating and going into early heart failure.''</p>
        <p>Dr. DeBakey, now 98, had often visited the Soviet Union during the cold war to lecture on -- and occasionally perform -- the operations and procedures that he had developed. But in those days, Kremlin officials would hardly have asked for a consultation with an American surgeon, no matter how eminent.</p>
        <p>''Calling in Dr. DeBakey was very important, a signal that he was in very serious condition, and consulting with a world leader in surgery this way was almost unthinkable in the Soviet period,'' said Marshall I. Goldman, a Russian expert and senior scholar at Harvard. ''It was a measure of Dr. DeBakey's stature in Russia.''</p>
        <p>Thomas R. Pickering, who was the United States ambassador to Russia at the time, said it was not clear who would have been elected if Mr. Yeltsin had dropped out of the race. Both he and Mr. Goldman said in separate interviews that it could have been a member of the Communist Party.</p>
        <p>Dr. DeBakey has said in interviews, in 1996 and since, that he told Mr. Yeltsin he could withstand a coronary bypass operation after treatment, including transfusions, to correct anemia from internal bleeding and to restore his low thyroid function. Despite Mr. Yeltsin's reputation for excessive drinking, his liver function was normal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeltsin immediately asked about his chances of being able to get back to work. ''Excellent, possibly in two or so weeks,'' Dr. DeBakey said he replied. He then carried out Mr. Yeltsin's request to give the news to journalists.</p>
        <p>''The next morning, Mr. Yeltsin's doctors were kidding me that the Communist Party did not like your report,'' Dr. DeBakey said.Until then, he said, he did not appreciate his recommendation's political significance.</p>
        <p>Dr. DeBakey said his confidence in Mr. Yeltsin's ability to undergo bypass surgery was based on an examination far more thorough than the ones the Russian doctors had conducted. One of those doctors confirmed that assertion in an interview with me in 1996, when I went to Moscow to cover the operation for The New York Times.</p>
        <p>Dr. DeBakey told Mr. Yeltsin that he had confidence in the Russian heart surgeon who would eventually perform the quintuple bypass. That surgeon, Dr. Renat S. Akchurin, had briefly trained under Dr. DeBakey in Houston. Dr. Akchurin initially specialized in microsurgery, wearing jeweler-type loupes and using an operating microscope to magnify the surgical field when repairing human nerves injured in accidents. His medical bosses recognized his talent and asked him to become a heart surgeon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeltsin insisted on having the operation at Dr. Akchurin's hospital, even though it did not have all the emergency equipment Dr. DeBakey thought might be needed. (Dr. DeBakey knew the hospital because he had consulted on its design.)</p>
        <p>So Dr. DeBakey also promised Mr. Yeltsin that he would watch the bypass operation and bring a team that included his surgical partner, Dr. George P. Noon, along with the equipment in case it was needed. It was not.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeltsin's medical team followed Dr. DeBakey's advice to correct the thyroid and other problems to prepare him for the bypass operation. A key monitor of heart function is the ejection fraction, a test that measures the proportion of blood ejected from the main chamber of the heart in each beat. After the medical tuneup, Mr. Yeltsin's ejection fraction rose significantly, to 40 from the high 20s. After the operation, the fraction improved to 50, good but still a bit less than normal.</p>
        <p>As a patient, Mr. Yeltsin ''was not as bossy with me as he was with some of his Russian doctors,'' Dr. DeBakey said, adding: ''He didn't get along with some of the doctors there. But he took a liking to me, listened, and that made things much better.''</p>
        <p>''I'll do what you say if you can put me back in my office,'' Dr. DeBakey said Mr. Yeltsin told him.</p>
        <p>Dr. DeBakey said he and the Russian doctors set a return to office date ''a few days ahead of time,'' in part because he was recovering well and had access to around-the-clock care. Two weeks after his return, Mr. Yeltsin was treated for pneumonia.</p>
        <p>Although Dr. DeBakey last spoke with Mr. Yeltsin on a visit to Moscow in May 2004, doctors kept him posted on Mr. Yeltsin's medical progress.</p>
        <p>A few years ago, after Mr. Yeltsin developed symptoms of further heart trouble, doctors at the Berlin Heart Center in Germany performed an angioplasty. Dr. Roland Hetzer, who led the German team, called Dr. DeBakey the next day to report that the five grafts that Dr. Akchurin had sewn in Mr. Yeltsin's heart had remained open and functioning well.</p>
        <p>But the German team had to clear blockages and place stents in two other areas of Mr. Yeltsin's coronary arteries. As often happens, his coronary artery disease had become progressive, Dr. DeBakey said.</p>
        <p>Considering the amount of heart damage Mr. Yeltsin had suffered before the bypass, Dr. DeBakey estimated in 1996 that the surgery would allow Mr. Yeltsin to live comfortably for 10 to 15 years -- or as he put it last week, ''We gave him 10 1/2 years.''</p>
        <p>Russian officials have not reported whether an autopsy was performed.</p>
        <p>The Kremlin's choice of Dr. DeBakey was based on contacts he made among Russian officials over the half-century since he befriended a small group of Soviet doctors who sat by themselves at a surgical meeting in Mexico in the 1950s. Dr. DeBakey took them to lunch and invited them to watch him operate in Houston on their way home. Later, his guests invited Dr. DeBakey to speak at a surgical meeting in Moscow and then translated his text into Russian. It was the first of more than 20 trips that Dr. DeBakey said he made to the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>On one trip, in 1973, Dr. DeBakey performed a quintuple bypass on Mstislav V. Keldysh, a nuclear scientist and president of the Soviet Academy of Science. A year later, the nation's Academy of Medical Sciences elected Dr. DeBakey a foreign member.</p>
        <p>My requests for interviews with Mr. Yeltsin were always denied, so I was never able to ask him about Dr. DeBakey. But in a foreword to the Russian edition of Dr. DeBakey's book ''The New Living Heart'' (Adams, 1997), written with Antonio Gotto Jr., Mr. Yeltsin described Dr. DeBakey as ''a magician of the heart'' and ''a man with a gift for performing miracles.''</p>
        <p>THE DOCTOR'S WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
