<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Searching for Sleep And Decent Clothing</title>
    <meta content="01flier" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/business/01flier.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844244"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FREQUENT FLIER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jet Lag</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Benison International Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lara, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Raymond, Joan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Frequent Flier</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Business Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Industry News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DEED8133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="544" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Searching for Sleep And Decent Clothing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Searching for Sleep and Decent Clothing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michael Lara, as told to Joan Raymond.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Raymond, Joan; Lara, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Benison International Group chief executive Michael Lara, in Frequent Flier column, on ways he has tried to combat jet lag; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I never wanted to be the poster boy for the bad effects of jet lag. I always had visions of myself as being the archetypal business traveler: one of those folks who arrives at the airport fresh and pressed, and somehow manages to exit the plane looking the same way.</p>
        <p>When these masters of business travel get to their destinations and attend their various meetings they look great, are well rested, coherent and in charge. I was never that guy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you’re jet lagged, looking good is a real effort. But with a sleep mask, some earplugs and the melatonin, I’m in dreamland.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I never wanted to be the poster boy for the bad effects of jet lag. I always had visions of myself as being the archetypal business traveler: one of those folks who arrives at the airport fresh and pressed, and somehow manages to exit the plane looking the same way.</p>
        <p>When these masters of business travel get to their destinations and attend their various meetings they look great, are well rested, coherent and in charge. I was never that guy.</p>
        <p>I've traveled extensively to Europe over the years, especially Germany. It's a long flight, and most business types handle it well. Not me. I feel like a wreck and look like a wreck. And I don't know how to be effective when I'm in a state of zombiehood; the only neural connections I can make when I arrive are, at best, ''Tree, pretty. Fire, hot.''</p>
        <p>Well-meaning colleagues have offered advice. Covering your eyes is supposed to do the trick. I'm the guy wearing the sleep mask in a futile attempt to trick my internal clock into believing that it is night. Wearing earplugs was another little bit of wisdom given to me. I can't hear anything, but I'm still wide awake.</p>
        <p>I've tried to get some center aisle seats on the larger planes, even booking two seats for myself. Or I've taken early flights that usually have extra seats available. I figured maybe if I could stretch out, I could get some rest. That works in theory, but not necessarily in practice.</p>
        <p>If you're jet lagged, looking good is a real effort, and is especially difficult when your luggage has been lost. On one business trip, I spent three nights in Frankfurt, waiting for my suitcases. I had to shop at the local stores to find something suitable to wear to client meetings.</p>
        <p>Size was an issue. Most Europeans are slim. I'm over six feet tall and weigh about 290 pounds. I was able to find a pair of pants. They were wide enough, but one inch too short. I got a white shirt. The neck and chest fit, but the sleeves were too long.</p>
        <p>I found a tie. It was olive green, emblazoned with a picture of the Alps. Glitter was used to emphasize the snow-capped mountain peaks. I used a complimentary razor provided by the hotel. It was like shaving with a rock.</p>
        <p>When I arrived at my assigned meeting, I looked like a Barnum &amp; Bailey clown who didn't know how to shave.</p>
        <p>Once my clients stopped laughing at me, I did get the contract, which made my jet lag and my bad wardrobe a lot more acceptable.</p>
        <p>I try to be smarter now. I dress comfortably and in layers, and I pack an extra set of underwear and essentials that will be allowed in a carry-on bag.</p>
        <p>The best thing, though, is melatonin, which was recommended by a buddy of mine who is a doctor.</p>
        <p>I now take eight milligrams of melatonin about 11 p.m. local time or on board after being in flight for a couple of hours. With the sleep mask, some earplugs and the melatonin, I'm in dreamland. The only problem now is that seatmates tell me I snore.</p>
        <p>FREQUENT FLIER E-mail: joan.raymond@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: joan.raymond@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
