<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Raise for State Judges Gets Caught in Crossfire Between Spitzer and Bruno</title>
    <meta content="01pay" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844249"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E6D7133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="550" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Raise for State Judges Gets Caught in Crossfire Between Spitzer and Bruno</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, April 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>State judges have gone more than eight years without a pay raise. It appears they may not get one soon.</p>
        <p>While all sides in Albany agree that judges are overdue for a raise, the matter appears to be caught up in the escalating feud between Gov. Eliot Spitzer and the Senate majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, who have found little to agree on since they struck a budget deal in late March.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>State judges have gone more than eight years without a pay raise. It appears they may not get one soon.</p>
        <p>While all sides in Albany agree that judges are overdue for a raise, the matter appears to be caught up in the escalating feud between Gov. Eliot Spitzer and the Senate majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, who have found little to agree on since they struck a budget deal in late March.</p>
        <p>On Monday, the governor, along with Attorney General Andrew M. Cuomo and Judith S. Kaye, the chief judge of New York State, called for judicial pay raises in speeches on the steps of the Court of Appeals. But Senate Republicans insist on linking raises for judges to a proposal to create a commission to review raises for legislators, and passed legislation to that effect later on Monday.</p>
        <p>The governor, however, has refused to approve legislative pay raises until lawmakers pass more of his agenda, including an overhaul of campaign finance laws. Given that Mr. Bruno has rejected the campaign finance proposal, judicial pay raises appear to be in limbo.</p>
        <p>''We are not, and I want to be clear on this, we're not going to take this issue up again in this chamber, not while I'm here,'' a frustrated Mr. Bruno said on the Senate floor. He accused Democratic leaders in the Legislature of reneging on commitments they had reached with him and bowing to the governor's wishes that they abandon the proposal to raise their salaries.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bruno was especially exasperated that all 62 senators had co-sponsored the pay bill last week only to have most of the 29 Democrats in the Senate withdraw their support on Monday. Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver, who has co-sponsored a pay raise bill similar to the Senate's, said Monday that after discussions with the governor he would also hold off.</p>
        <p>''Apparently the governor is very persuasive,'' Mr. Bruno said, adding, ''I think that's unfortunate for elected leaders to be intimidated.''</p>
        <p>In a statement, Mr. Spitzer said of the Senate Republicans, ''Their action to raise their own pay before passing real reform is the ultimate misstatement of priorities.''</p>
        <p>Both the Senate and the governor had proposed pay increases for Supreme Court justices of nearly 21 percent, to $165,200, from the current $136,700 a year, to bring them in line with federal district court judges. Both proposals also included some retroactive increases. The Senate's legislation, based on a proposal made by Judge Kaye, would also create a commission to regularly review raises for all three branches of government.</p>
        <p>''Our judges expect to treat other people fairly,'' she said in her speech. ''They have committed themselves to that. They should be treated fairly themselves, don't you all agree?</p>
        <p>''So imagine their distress when we learned just weeks ago that we are caught, trapped, snared in the jaws of Albany politics,'' she said, referring to the lack of a pay raise in the recent budget.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bruno, for his part, threatened to stop talking to Democrats in the Legislature. ''We are going to deal with the governor and no one else,'' he told Democrats on the Senate floor. ''The governor has said he speaks for you and he said, 'I speak for the speaker.' That's wrong. We are a separate branch of government.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
