<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Google Calls Viacom Suit On YouTube Unfounded</title>
    <meta content="01google" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/technology/01google.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844309"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Copyrights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Video)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Google Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Viacom Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Youtube</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Music Television Networks Inc (Mtv)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Comedy Central</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nickelodeon</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Helft, Miguel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Copyrights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Copyrights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Google Inc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Viacom Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">YouTube.com</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E3D6133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="623" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Google Calls Viacom Suit On YouTube Unfounded</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Google Calls Viacom Suit on YouTube Unfounded</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIGUEL HELFT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Helft, Miguel</byline>
      <dateline>MOUNTAIN VIEW, Calif., April 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Google, responding to Viacom's $1 billion copyright infringement suit over video clips on YouTube, sys it will not back off, declaring law is on its side; says Viacom's claims are unfounded and asks for judgment dismissing complaint; Viacom, parent of MTV, Comedy Central and Nickelodeon, in March sued Google and YouTube, video sharing site it acquired last year, saying they were deliberately building business on library of copyrighted video clips without permission (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Responding to Viacom's $1 billion copyright infringement suit over video clips on YouTube, Google said Monday that it would not back off, declaring that the law was on its side.</p>
        <p>''We are not going to let this lawsuit distract us,'' Michael Kwun, managing counsel for litigation at Google, told reporters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Responding to Viacom’s $1 billion copyright infringement suit, Google said that it would not back off, declaring that the law was on its side.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Responding to Viacom's $1 billion copyright infringement suit over video clips on YouTube, Google said Monday that it would not back off, declaring that the law was on its side.</p>
        <p>''We are not going to let this lawsuit distract us,'' Michael Kwun, managing counsel for litigation at Google, told reporters.</p>
        <p>In its response to the lawsuit, filed Monday in Federal District Court in Manhattan, Google said that Viacom's claims were unfounded and asked for a judgment dismissing the complaint.</p>
        <p>In March, Viacom, the parent company of MTV, Comedy Central and Nickelodeon, sued Google and YouTube, the video sharing site it acquired last year, saying they were deliberately building a business on a library of copyrighted video clips without permission. Earlier this year, Viacom had asked YouTube to take down 100,000 clips that it said infringed on its copyrights.</p>
        <p>Google's court filing gives few new details of its legal thinking, which relies heavily on the so-called ''safe harbor'' provisions of the Digital Millennium Copyright Act, enacted in 1998. Those provisions generally hold that Web sites' owners are not liable for copyright material uploaded by others to their site as long as they promptly remove the material when asked to do so by the copyright owner.</p>
        <p>The 1998 law ''balances the rights of copyright holders and the need to protect the Internet as an important new form of communication,'' Google said in its filing. ''By seeking to make carriers and hosting providers liable for Internet communications, Viacom's complaint threatens the way hundreds of millions of people legitimately exchange information, news, entertainment, and political and artistic expression.''</p>
        <p>Viacom said Google's response misses the mark. ''This response ignores the most important fact of the suit, which is that YouTube does not qualify for safe harbor protection under the D.M.C.A.,'' Viacom said. ''It is obvious that YouTube has knowledge of infringing material on their site, and they are profiting from it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kwun, the Google lawyer, said there had been no talks between Google and Viacom to discuss a settlement. ''We feel pretty confident about the case and are ready to take it to court,'' he added.</p>
        <p>In the suit, Viacom had complained that it was unfairly forced to devote significant resources to police YouTube. ''Every day we have to scour the entirety of what is available on YouTube, so we have to look for our stuff,'' Philippe P. Dauman, Viacom's chief executive, said in an interview earlier this year.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, Google's chief executive, Eric E. Schmidt, has said that the company will soon unveil new tools that will make it easier for copyright owners to spot their content on YouTube. Mr. Schmidt had said that those tools, to be called Claim Your Content, will make Viacom's complaint moot.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Kwun said on Monday that Google was not compelled by law to develop those tools or to make them available to content owners.</p>
        <p>The first case management conference, at which the judge may set an initial timeline for the trial, is scheduled for July 27, Mr. Kwun said.</p>
        <p>Google has asked for a jury trial.</p>
        <p>Yahoo and Comcast in Deal  By Reuters</p>
        <p>The cable TV provider, the Comcast Corporation, and the Internet media company Yahoo said yesterday that they had agreed to a multi-year partnership for Yahoo to supply Web advertising to Comcast.</p>
        <p>The deal covers online display and video advertising to be featured on the site Comcast.net, which has 15 million monthly visitors, the companies said.</p>
        <p>The deal is the latest in a string that Yahoo has signed to supply media players with online advertising services. Yahoo wants to show that its own upgraded Web search advertising system, dubbed Panama, is gaining momentum against Google, the pay-per-click Web ad leader.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
