<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Don't Trust Your Ears: This Play Is Not a Musical</title>
    <meta content="01coram" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/theater/01coram.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844198"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations/Royal National Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Royal National Theater</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Still, Melly</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E0D9133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="990" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Don't Trust Your Ears: This Play Is Not a Musical</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Don’t Trust Your Ears: This Play Is Not a Musical</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT SIMONSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Simonson, Robert</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a recent evening, the creative team of a new Broadway show were entrenched in a technical rehearsal. A cast of 40 waited onstage for instruction while the show's composer, Adrian Sutton, consulted with its director, Melly Still, about an element of the sound design. Mr. Sutton then dashed down the aisle to the orchestra pit for a tête-à-tête with the musical director, Constantine Kitsopoulos.</p>
        <p>Despite appearances, the show in question is not a musical.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>"Coram Boy," a transfer from the Royal National Theater in London, is one of the most music-heavy plays seen in New York in some time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a recent evening, the creative team of a new Broadway show were entrenched in a technical rehearsal. A cast of 40 waited onstage for instruction while the show's composer, Adrian Sutton, consulted with its director, Melly Still, about an element of the sound design. Mr. Sutton then dashed down the aisle to the orchestra pit for a tête-à-tête with the musical director, Constantine Kitsopoulos.</p>
        <p>Despite appearances, the show in question is not a musical.</p>
        <p>It's ''Coram Boy,'' a transfer from the Royal National Theater in London that opens tomorrow at the Imperial Theater. It is one of the most music-heavy plays seen in New York in some time. It is, in fact, the first play to book the Imperial, a house favored by musicals, in 30 years.</p>
        <p>''There's 1,234 measures of music in this show, which is more than most book musicals,'' said Mr. Kitsopoulos, an experienced Broadway musical director and conductor. In ''Coram Boy'' he oversees an orchestra of 7 and a 20-member onstage choir.</p>
        <p>''One of the themes in the play is music, so we wanted the choir to be present,'' explained Ms. Still, who is making her Broadway debut. ''Every day of rehearsal would begin with a singing warm-up. The day was split between music and staging and acting. The music is completely integral. Constantine was always there in the room.''</p>
        <p>''Coram Boy,'' adapted by the playwright Helen Edmundson from Jamila Gavin's Whitbread Award-winning novel for young adults, takes place over eight years in 18th-century England. At the center of the action-packed, Dickensian plot are four boys. Two live in Gloucester; the other two are housed in the Coram Foundling Hospital in London, a pioneering orphanage of the time.</p>
        <p>Three of the boys long for a career in music, one of the few routes of escape from a punishing society populated by the likes of Otis Gardiner, a murderous scam artist who purports to represent the hospital to feed his lucrative trade in child trafficking.</p>
        <p>Among the real benefactors of the Foundling Hospital was the composer George Frideric Handel, who in 1750 arranged a benefit performance of his ''Messiah'' for the institution. He is also a character in the play, and fittingly, much of the 75 minutes of music in ''Coram Boy'' is either straight ''Messiah'' or thematic variations on it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sutton described the show's score as ''everything from verbatim Handel to things that sound a bit like Handel and things quite distant from Handel, all the way to parts of the score that are not like Handel in any way.'' Examples of Handelesque sequences include a rendition of ''O death where is thy sting'' that is meant to sound like ''a piece of material that Handel had in another form before he put it into 'Messiah,' '' Mr. Sutton said. There's also a creepy, Grand Guignol version of ''For unto us a Child is born,'' which accompanies the macabre events of the first act finale.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to make points about the characters in the story,'' Ms. Still said. '' 'O death where is thy sting' is thematically of this story, as is 'For unto us a son is born.' ''</p>
        <p>Despite the presence of a choir onstage -- each of the 20 a trained singer -- every cast member is called upon to sing at one point or another. The heaviest vocal burdens fall upon the boy characters, who are played not by children, but by young women. By Ms. Still's reasoning, female adults provide the depth of characterization and pure treble voices the roles require.</p>
        <p>The unusual casting needs resulted in exacting auditions. The Broadway casting notice read, in part, ''We are not seeking musical theater actresses but actresses who are musical and who can use their instruments to create the sound of a boy's choir as well as other effects.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kitsopoulos -- whose integration into the world of the show is so complete that he and the orchestra wear powdered wigs and breeches -- was present at all the auditions. Actors were asked to prepare a song, either something by Handel or an Italian art song. If they passed the first round, they were taught a piece of music from the show.</p>
        <p>Once rehearsal began, Mr. Kitsopoulos had to shape the actresses into credible prepubescent boys.</p>
        <p>''One of the critical things for the choir's boys is that they sing with no vibrato,'' he explained. ''Choirboys' voices are not mature. It's a matter of purity of sound.''</p>
        <p>The casting of the choir presented additional challenges. In the original London production Ms. Still and Mr. Sutton employed a rotating group of 50 musically adept students, from 18 to their mid-20s.</p>
        <p>''We couldn't afford a professional choir at all,'' Ms. Still said. ''We had a big pool of about 50 students. They didn't perform on a professional basis. From that pool, we'd try to get 20 each performance, but sometimes we were down to about 12. It was a more irregular and unreliable system.</p>
        <p>''And, of course, they were young, so they didn't have fully developed voices. They were backed by their recorded voices in certain moments.''</p>
        <p>The show's transfer to Broadway was so speedy that there was no time to investigate the possibility of a rotating system. Furthermore, American Actors' Equity, the performers' union, would not permit the taping of voices. So adult professional singers were hired, some handpicked by Mr. Kitsopoulos.</p>
        <p>''What's been great about this choir is the maturity of these voices,'' said Mr. Sutton, whose score is his first for the stage. ''It more than compensates for the fact that we can't use more voices in the tapes.''</p>
        <p>Still, that doesn't mean the choir isn't in need of vocal coaching. During a rehearsal Mr. Sutton warned the female members of the chorus against singing too loudly.</p>
        <p>''The balance of the female members of the choirs should be very angelic,'' he explained. ''It's got to be ethereal and from the heavens.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
