<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Fountain of Youth Is as Near as the Next Party</title>
    <meta content="01party" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/nyregion/01party.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844248"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Society</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Society</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E6D7133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="635" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Fountain of Youth Is as Near as the Next Party</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Fountain of Youth Is as Near as the Next Party</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE BRESCIA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brescia, Joe</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jules Peimer was a white-capped wave in a sea of staid blue suits. He wore a black velvet jacket, a white silk shirt and a psychedelic tie you might find in the artist Martin Sharp's closet.</p>
        <p>Mr. Peimer danced a few mambo steps in front of the piano, had his glass of wine refilled at the bar, then stopped to chat up a group of young women.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If there were an award for octogenarian nightlifer of the year, Jules Peimer, who has been fluttering around parties for 65 years, would seem a shoo-in.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jules Peimer was a white-capped wave in a sea of staid blue suits. He wore a black velvet jacket, a white silk shirt and a psychedelic tie you might find in the artist Martin Sharp's closet.</p>
        <p>Mr. Peimer danced a few mambo steps in front of the piano, had his glass of wine refilled at the bar, then stopped to chat up a group of young women.</p>
        <p>Iraq? ''We shouldn't have been there from the start,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Anna Nicole? ''Sad, but overdone.''</p>
        <p>The setting was the Christopher Awards at the McGraw-Hill Building on Avenue of the Americas. The annual event honors those who make a difference in movies, television and books.</p>
        <p>If they honored an octogenarian nightlifer of the year, Mr. Peimer, 85, would seem a shoo-in. This Social Security butterfly has been fluttering around parties for 65 years.</p>
        <p>A lifelong New Yorker, he has a background that made an interesting prep school for navigating New York's night life. His résumé includes stints as a car salesman, a dance instructor and a performer, specializing in mambo.</p>
        <p>In the 1980s, after retiring from his sales job, he became a radio show co-host with Doreen Davis on WNWK-FM, where he began to talk about parties, plays and movies. That job allowed him more invitations, and led to his 15 lines or so of fame in the culture sections of newspapers. Warner Brothers regularly used his quotes in their movie ads: ''Comic Genius!'' and ''Stand Up and Cheer!'' and ''You'll Laugh Until It Hurts. Then You'll Laugh Some More.''</p>
        <p>That all led to bigger and better parties, from restaurants and saloons to the China Club and the Waldorf-Astoria.</p>
        <p>These days he keeps busy writing about parties and celebrities for the Web site 15minutesmagazine.com.</p>
        <p>Mr. Peimer fills his datebook with invitations from seemingly endless mailing and e-mail lists, faxes, phone calls and by being the friend of a friend.</p>
        <p>His secret for perpetual pep?</p>
        <p>''Champagne and red wine,'' he said, jiggling his glass. ''Parties keep me young. It's my fountain of youth. I feel immune to the outside world. I hardly ever find myself talking about anything depressing.</p>
        <p>''Or it becomes less depressing at parties.''</p>
        <p>He admits to slowing down. Just a bit.</p>
        <p>''I usually go out three or four times a week instead of seven like I used to,'' he said. ''But I might go to two or three events in one day. For example, the other day I went to a Friars Club lunch in the afternoon and a restaurant opening at night.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Peimer sends out a message that the party never ends.</p>
        <p>''He has great vitality and great spirit,'' said Jessica Stammen, 26, left in the wake of one of Mr. Peimer's chats.</p>
        <p>''He's a good example for other people as they age,'' said Ms. Stammen, an artist. ''I hope to party until I'm 95.''</p>
        <p>The publicist David Reich of Reich Communications said: ''I don't see his age. I see him as a really a nice man. I love seeing him at events because I love to chat with him. He's always interesting and entertaining. And everyone, celebrities or not, finds him interesting to talk with.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Peimer said his personal highlights, in terms of celebrity encounters, included meeting Sean Connery and Warren Beatty.</p>
        <p>''Now I know Beatty's secret with women,'' Mr. Peimer said. ''Man, woman or animal, he gives you his full attention. He never looks away from you. And he uses his hands to get intimate while he talks. He touches you physically.''</p>
        <p>He laughed. ''He even had his hand on my knee at one point!''</p>
        <p>A lifelong bachelor, Mr. Peimer has dated his share of women. But priorities change.</p>
        <p>''Now when I take a woman back to my apartment,'' he said, ''I'm just hoping that she cleans it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
