<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Business Class to London: Cheaper Than You Might Think</title>
    <meta content="01road" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/business/01road.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844205"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON THE ROAD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">London (Eng)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Maxjet Airways</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Silverjet (Airline)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Eos Airlines</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sharkey, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/On the Road</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Business Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">London (England)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CEED9133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="781" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Business Class to London: Cheaper Than You Might Think</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Business Class to London: Cheaper Than You Might Think</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE SHARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sharkey, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York to London airline route, most lu7</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HOW about some good news for a change? Business-class fares on trans-Atlantic routes are coming down. Major airlines are improving their international routes and reducing capacity on domestic routes as lower-fare competition becomes more aggressive.</p>
        <p>Two low-fare start-ups -- MaxJet and Silverjet -- say they are creating a bigger pool of business-class passengers who are willing (or able, under corporate policies) to pay a little more for a lot more comfort. Meanwhile, the third low-fare all-business-class start-up, Eos, says it has settled comfortably into a new discount-fare niche in the top quality business-class market across the Atlantic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Major airlines are improving their international routes and reducing capacity on domestic routes as lower-fare competition becomes more aggressive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HOW about some good news for a change? Business-class fares on trans-Atlantic routes are coming down. Major airlines are improving their international routes and reducing capacity on domestic routes as lower-fare competition becomes more aggressive.</p>
        <p>Two low-fare start-ups -- MaxJet and Silverjet -- say they are creating a bigger pool of business-class passengers who are willing (or able, under corporate policies) to pay a little more for a lot more comfort. Meanwhile, the third low-fare all-business-class start-up, Eos, says it has settled comfortably into a new discount-fare niche in the top quality business-class market across the Atlantic.</p>
        <p>The New York to London route, the most lucrative in the industry for premium-class travel, is in flux. It's still possible to pay a fortune for a walk-up business class seat, of course. Yesterday, I checked walk-up fares on two international airlines that have what are considered to be top business-class service, British Airways and Virgin Atlantic. They were just over $10,000.</p>
        <p>''They're offering a superb product, but that is really an incredibly large amount of money,'' said Joshua Marks, the vice president for planning at MaxJet, which purports to be generating a good part of its market from business passengers who used to fly coach or premium coach.</p>
        <p>United States airlines used to closely match walk-up fares on competitors like British Airways, but not anymore. The walk-up New York to London round-trip fare on American Airlines yesterday was $7,723. And if booked yesterday for a flight in three weeks, business-class fares on major United States airlines dropped to the $3,500 level, while British Air was charging about $7,000.</p>
        <p>Airlines make most of their money on trans-Atlantic routes in first and business class. Coach is usually a drain on profits, which is why an all-business-class airline with an enticing fare structure can compete, even without the sort of scheduling frequency that major airlines offer.</p>
        <p>''We're not subsidizing cheapskates like me, who used to travel only in economy,'' said Lawrence Hunt, the chief executive officer and a founder of Silverjet, a British-based airline that has been flying New York to London (actually Newark to London) for just over two months.</p>
        <p>Silverjet flies a 767 with 100 all business-class seats. The average fare New York to London is ''slightly over $2,000,'' Mr. Hunt said.</p>
        <p>On major carriers, the average fare on that route is around $5,500, which takes into account volume discounts negotiated by major customers. A major American investment bank, considered one of the highest-volume customers, pays around $3,000 round trip on American Airlines, Mr. Hunt says. Typical high-volume corporate discount rates are about $6,000, but small-business travelers and entrepreneurs who don't book well in advance often end up paying the walk-up fare.</p>
        <p>On Silverjet, the walk-up fare can go as high as $4,000 in peak-demand periods. But, Mr. Hunt said, ''on some days you'll be paying $1,700 round trip.''</p>
        <p>Silverjet recently bought a second 767 aircraft. ''I took the keys on Thursday,'' Mr. Hunt said. It will be used for a second New York to London flight starting in July. The company expects to take delivery of a third aircraft in November and use it either for New York to London service, or to provide London service from another United States city, such as Los Angeles, Chicago or Miami.</p>
        <p>Silverjet says it had a load factor -- the percentage of seats full -- of 59 percent in March. ''That's almost unprecedented for a carrier in its second month of operation,'' Mr. Hunt said.</p>
        <p>MaxJet flies between New York and London and Las Vegas and London and is about to resume its flights between Washington and London, which were suspended for the winter.</p>
        <p>Average fares are about $2,000, Mr. Marks said. MaxJet says its business-class service is comparable to that on United States airlines. ''We're not trying to compete with the best of the best,'' Mr. Marks said. ''But we are showing that with a good product, people will pay more to get out of economy class.''</p>
        <p>Eos, on the other hand, competes with the luxury service on top-level business and first-class airlines like British Airways and Virgin Atlantic on the trans-Atlantic route.</p>
        <p>Eos flies 757s, which typically carry more than 200 passengers, outfitted with just 48 lie-flat seats. Its new schedule between New York and London offers three flights on most days, for a total of 32 flights a week.</p>
        <p>If you wanted to fly Eos today and booked yesterday, the walk-up fare would have been $7,500 -- still lower than most airlines. Booked weeks in advance, the fare is $3,200 and less.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Eos also just introduced a new advertising campaign with a keyword that we'll seldom hear applied ever again to air travel: ''Uncrowded.''</p>
        <p>ON THE ROAD E-mail: jsharkey@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: jsharkey@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
