<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Steroids Dealer Testified To the Bonds Grand Jury</title>
    <meta content="01steroids" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/sports/baseball/01steroids.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844293"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Radomski, Kirk</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bonds, Barry</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E5D6133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="452" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Steroids Dealer Testified To the Bonds Grand Jury</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Steroids Dealer Testified to the Bonds Grand Jury</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIET MACUR; Pat Borzi and Jack Curry contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Macur, Juliet</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kirk Radomski, the former Mets clubhouse assistant who has admitted selling performance-enhancing drugs to dozens of current and former professional baseball players, testified last Thursday in front of a federal grand jury investigating steroid use in sports.</p>
        <p>Radomski, a personal trainer from Manorville, N.Y., pleaded guilty to distributing steroids and to money laundering last Friday, and agreed to cooperate with the federal investigation into drugs and baseball. He apparently made good on that promise one day earlier, when he met with the same federal grand jury that is investigating the slugger Barry Bonds for perjury.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kirk Radomski, the former Mets clubhouse assistant who has admitted dealing performance-enhancing drugs to players, testified last Thursday to the federal grand jury investigating steroid use in sports.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Kirk Radomski, the former Mets clubhouse assistant who has admitted selling performance-enhancing drugs to dozens of current and former professional baseball players, testified last Thursday in front of a federal grand jury investigating steroid use in sports.</p>
        <p>Radomski, a personal trainer from Manorville, N.Y., pleaded guilty to distributing steroids and to money laundering last Friday, and agreed to cooperate with the federal investigation into drugs and baseball. He apparently made good on that promise one day earlier, when he met with the same federal grand jury that is investigating the slugger Barry Bonds for perjury.</p>
        <p>Radomski had been charged April 12, but a federal judge sealed the case until he spoke to the grand jury to protect Radomski from being intimidated or influenced before he spoke to that grand jury, according to The Associated Press, which cited records filed in a San Francisco court.</p>
        <p>John F. Reilly, a Long Island lawyer who is representing Radomski, said that neither he nor his client would discuss the grand jury testimony.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for United States Attorney Scott N. Schools also declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Last week's grand jury testimony connected Radomski to one of the biggest steroid distribution scandals in recent history, the Bay Area Laboratory Co-Operative case, which became public in 2003 when federal agents raided the Balco offices.</p>
        <p>A search warrant affidavit filed in Radomski's case named some of Radomski's clients, but those names were blackened out in the document. Still, the affidavit said that Radomski had been distributing performance-enhancing drugs to major league players, including at least one ''who was publicly identified as being associated with Balco Laboratories.''</p>
        <p>Bonds is the highest-profile player to be linked to Balco, but other players testified in front of the Balco grand jury, including Jason and Jeremy Giambi, Gary Sheffield and Randy Velarde. Other players who testified were A. J. Pierzynski, Benito Santiago, Armando Rios, Bobby Estalella and Marvin Benard.</p>
        <p>None of the players have been indicted, but Bonds is being investigated as he continues to march toward Hank Aaron's career home run record. In a telephone interview last Friday, Bonds's criminal defense lawyer, Michael Rains, said that he had never heard of Radomski.</p>
        <p>''This has nothing to do with Barry,'' he said.</p>
        <p>When asked about Radomski before a Yankees game last Friday, Jason Giambi also said that Radomski was a stranger to him.</p>
        <p>''Don't know who he is,'' Giambi said. ''There's nothing there. Sorry, guys.''</p>
        <p>He added that he was not worried about Radomski telling federal investigators the names of the players to whom he sold anabolic steroids, amphetamines and human growth hormone.</p>
        <p>''I did what I already did and I moved on,'' Giambi said.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
