<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Signs of Mourning Follow the Cardinals</title>
    <meta content="01cardinals" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/sports/baseball/01cardinals.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844313"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">St Louis Cardinals</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hancock, Josh</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E2D6133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="793" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Signs of Mourning Follow the Cardinals</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Signs of Mourning Follow the Cardinals</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <dateline>MILWAUKEE, April 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The little boy and the little girl wore St. Louis Cardinals jerseys and caps, stationed themselves by the third-base dugout and held a tribute sign for Josh Hancock. They had drawn a red-and-white uniform with Hancock's name, his No. 32 and the words ''Will Be Missed.''</p>
        <p>Several Cardinals spotted the sign as they stumbled to a 7-1 loss to the Milwaukee Brewers, the team's first game since Hancock, a reliever, was killed in an automobile accident on Sunday in St. Louis. Jeff Suppan, who was Hancock's teammate in St. Louis last season, tossed a complete game for Milwaukee.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Josh Hancock, the Cardinals pitcher who was killed in an automobile accident early Sunday in St. Louis, was involved in an auto accident days before his death.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The little boy and the little girl wore St. Louis Cardinals jerseys and caps, stationed themselves by the third-base dugout and held a tribute sign for Josh Hancock. They had drawn a red-and-white uniform with Hancock's name, his No. 32 and the words ''Will Be Missed.''</p>
        <p>Several Cardinals spotted the sign as they stumbled to a 7-1 loss to the Milwaukee Brewers, the team's first game since Hancock, a reliever, was killed in an automobile accident on Sunday in St. Louis. Jeff Suppan, who was Hancock's teammate in St. Louis last season, tossed a complete game for Milwaukee.</p>
        <p>Manager Tony La Russa said that the plane trip Sunday night from St. Louis was subdued and that the bus ride from the airport to the hotel was quiet, too. La Russa closed the clubhouse to reporters before the game and held a meeting to discuss Hancock. Several of the Cardinals looked drained after the game.</p>
        <p>''Family and friends, life and death, that's part of it,'' La Russa said. ''Players are not immune. We're not immune. You got to honor them and miss them and you got to go on.''</p>
        <p>The Cardinals honored Hancock by hanging his jersey in the dugout and in the bullpen. When the relievers placed Hancock's jersey in the bullpen, they carefully adjusted the sleeves so that Hancock's name would not be blocked. All of the Cardinals' uniforms included a black circular patch with the No. 32 on the left sleeves in memory of Hancock, who was 29.</p>
        <p>Once the Cardinals return home this week, the organization plans to install a memorial sign for Hancock, most likely in the bullpen. There is already a DK 57 sign there, which is in honor of Darryl Kile, the Cardinals pitcher who died of a heart blockage in 2002. Five years later, the Cardinals said that enduring the death of one young pitcher did not prepare them for another death of a young pitcher.</p>
        <p>''I don't think it'll help me,'' said the St. Louis pitching coach, Dave Duncan. ''Maybe you understand that you will get through it and it will pass in time. But it never goes away.''</p>
        <p>As La Russa described the meeting with his players, he fiddled with a fungo bat. He became testy while mentioning how he warned his players to be wary of ''the insincerity of some media people'' who are pursuing ''some kind of story that's not all sweet.'' La Russa did not specify what had upset him.</p>
        <p>''I've already seen signs of that,'' La Russa said. ''And, if it's not sincere, I'm sitting here listening. The first time I hear insincerity, I'm swinging this fungo.''</p>
        <p>At least one Cardinal was too overcome by dealing with Hancock's death to play Monday. La Russa said he noticed how emotional Scott Spiezio, the right fielder, was during a moment of silence for Hancock and replaced him in the lineup. ''Sometimes, you think you're tough,'' Spiezio said. ''All of a sudden, something catches you the wrong way. It just hit me at the wrong time.''</p>
        <p>Hancock died instantly at about 12:30 a.m. Sunday when his Ford Explorer crashed into a tow truck. The truck was parked in the far left westbound lane of Highway 40 in St. Louis with its lights blinking, according to Police Chief Joseph Mokwa.</p>
        <p>After Hancock pitched three innings in an 8-1 loss to the Cubs on Saturday, The St. Louis Post-Dispatch reported, he had dinner with friends at Mike Shannon's Steaks and Seafood. The restaurant is a few minutes from Busch Stadium.</p>
        <p>Pat Shannon, Shannon's daughter and the manager of the restaurant, told the newspaper that she ''called the police chief and told him everything I know about'' Saturday night. When The Post-Dispatch asked Pat Shannon if Hancock had consumed any alcohol, she declined to comment and said it was a police matter. Pat Shannon did not immediately respond to a telephone message.</p>
        <p>Mike Shannon, a longtime Cardinal broadcaster and former St. Louis outfielder and third baseman, would not discuss Hancock or whether he was at the restaurant.</p>
        <p>''I don't talk about any of our customers,'' Shannon said.</p>
        <p>Richard Wilkes, a police spokesman, said Hancock's death was in ''accident reconstruction'' and there would be no updates until that was completed, perhaps by the end of the week. An autopsy was performed Monday.</p>
        <p>Hancock, who was 0-1 with a 3.55 earned run average in eight games this season, was part of last year's World Series championship team. La Russa told his players they could honor Hancock's memory by competing as passionately as he did, even as they miss him.</p>
        <p>''Yesterday, you felt like you were hit with a sledgehammer,'' reliever Russ Springer said. ''Today, you're still numb. It's going to be tough for a while.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
