<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New York Art College Canceled Deal With Lender After Learning of High Interest Rates</title>
    <meta content="01loans" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/us/01loans.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pratt Institute</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Education Finance Partners</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cuomo, Andrew M (Atty Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glater, Jonathan D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Pratt Institute</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE7D8133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="623" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New York Art College Canceled Deal With Lender After Learning of High Interest Rates</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New York Art College Canceled Deal With Lender After Learning of High Interest Rates</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN D. GLATER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glater, Jonathan D</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pratt Institute, New York art and design college, ends deal it made in 2005 with Education Finance Partners of San Francisco, student loan company, after learning it was charging borrowers 15 percent in interest; details of arrangement and cancellation are disclosed by New York State Atty Gen Andrew M Cuomo; Pratt and five other colleges agree to adopt code of conduct governing relationships with loan companies (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pratt Institute, a New York art and design college, had a deal in 2005 with a student loan company: The lender would provide grant money for needy students if Pratt students over all took out $1 million or more in loans.</p>
        <p>But last year, Pratt found that the deal was not so good for its student borrowers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pratt Institute found that a deal it had with a student loan company was not so good for its student borrowers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pratt Institute, a New York art and design college, had a deal in 2005 with a student loan company: The lender would provide grant money for needy students if Pratt students over all took out $1 million or more in loans.</p>
        <p>But last year, Pratt found that the deal was not so good for its student borrowers.</p>
        <p>The company, Education Finance Partners of San Francisco, was charging borrowers 15 percent in interest -- more than double the 6.8 percent rate on some federal loans and higher than what some credit cards charge. Pratt canceled the deal and stopped recommending Education Finance to its students.</p>
        <p>Details of the arrangement, and its cancellation, were disclosed yesterday by Pratt and Attorney General Andrew M. Cuomo of New York.</p>
        <p>Pratt, along with five other colleges, agreed to adopt a code of conduct governing relationships with loan companies. Mr. Cuomo's office, which has been investigating ties between loan companies and universities for months, announced the new agreements yesterday.</p>
        <p>Pratt's findings that its students were being charged such high interest rates are the first evidence to emerge from Mr. Cuomo's inquiry showing how students could have suffered from undisclosed arrangements between universities and lenders that the attorney general has branded a conflict of interest.</p>
        <p>As numerous cases have emerged of universities' getting payments to steer loan volume to a lender, or of university officials' getting gifts and payments, many college officials have said that the rates offered by recommended lenders were competitive. It appears that in this case, as soon as Pratt learned of the high interest rate, it acted to cancel the relationship with the lender.</p>
        <p>Thomas F. Schutte, president of Pratt, said in a statement released to students and faculty members that he was ''pleased to inform you that Pratt is in complete compliance'' with the code of conduct.</p>
        <p>Besides Pratt, three New York colleges -- Marist College, Manhattanville College and Mercy College -- agreed to the code of conduct. So did Lewis &amp; Clark College in Oregon and Texas Christian University, which also agreed to pay to student borrowers more than $13,000 that it received from one lender in exchange for greater student loan volume.</p>
        <p>''Schools and lenders are no longer defending these practices or refusing to recognize the problem,'' Mr. Cuomo said. ''They are looking for a solution.''</p>
        <p>With the six new colleges, 21 institutions, along with some of the nation's largest student loan companies, have adopted the code of conduct, according to Mr. Cuomo's office, and the New York Senate has passed legislation to put it into law.</p>
        <p>At Pratt, in addition to the arrangement with Education Finance Partners, an employee served on the advisory board and received trips from another lender. Education Finance reached a separate agreement with Mr. Cuomo's office in mid-April, adopting his code of conduct and paying $2.5 million into a fund for education of students and parents about financial aid.</p>
        <p>Mercy College had a contract with Sallie Mae, the nation's largest student lender, to operate a call center on behalf of the financial aid office, Mr. Cuomo's office said, and call center operators did not identify themselves as Sallie Mae employees.</p>
        <p>At Marist College, employees served on advisory boards to loan companies and received trips. An employee at Manhattanville College received theater tickets from Nelnet, another student loan company, and some lenders provided printing services to the institution.</p>
        <p>Lewis &amp; Clark and Texas Christian both had ''revenue sharing'' agreements, in which Education Finance paid the college based on loan volume. Lewis &amp; Clark has already returned the money.</p>
        <p>Separately, the New York State Higher Education Services Corporation, which administers scholarship programs in New York and that guarantees federal student loans against default, also adopted the code of conduct.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
