<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Iraq Puzzle: Getting In, Getting Out</title>
    <meta content="l01iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844255"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Central Intelligence Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swensen, Ken</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perkins, Ken</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davison, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norman, Liane Ellison</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Patalinjug, Mariano</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popovic, Darlene</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gotkin, Michael B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tenet, George J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E5D7133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Iraq Puzzle: Getting In, Getting Out</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Seven letters comment on April 28 and 30 articles and April 29 editorial on Iraq war; Ken Swensen says investigations into use of suspect intelligence before invasion are probably only way to end catastrophic war; Ken Perkins scores former CIA director George J Tenet for coming clean about phony case for war only after Pres George Bush was re-elected; Andrew Davison says administration should apologize to Iraqi people for pain and destruction it caused them; Liane Ellison Norman scores administration for refusing to end war; Mariano Patalinjug says idea of war czar is transparent attempt to find scapegoat for disaster; Darlene Popovic says president should be only war czar; Michael B Gotkin says czar will probably have to take blame if things continue going badly and Bush the credit if things go well; drawing</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''Still Waiting for Answers'' (editorial, April 29) demands Congressional investigations into the administration's use of suspect intelligence before the invasion of Iraq. These investigations, for the purpose of informing the American people, are probably the only way to end this catastrophic war.</p>
        <p>After four years of spiraling death and destruction, the Bush administration and Congressional Republicans absurdly deny reality in Iraq. Only the forceful opposition of a broad majority of Americans from across the political spectrum can end the conflict.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''Still Waiting for Answers'' (editorial, April 29) demands Congressional investigations into the administration's use of suspect intelligence before the invasion of Iraq. These investigations, for the purpose of informing the American people, are probably the only way to end this catastrophic war.</p>
        <p>After four years of spiraling death and destruction, the Bush administration and Congressional Republicans absurdly deny reality in Iraq. Only the forceful opposition of a broad majority of Americans from across the political spectrum can end the conflict.</p>
        <p>That forceful opposition will emerge when Americans are fully informed about the depth of the deceptions that brought us to war.</p>
        <p>Ken Swensen  Pound Ridge, N.Y., April 29, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>So now we add George J. Tenet, the former director of central intelligence, to the ever-growing list of former Bush administration officials and accomplices finally coming clean about manufacturing the phony case for war with Iraq in a desperate effort to avoid forever being tainted by the stain of the Bush legacy.</p>
        <p>No doubt these faux patriots are counting on history to overlook the fact that they waited to do so until after the 2004 election -- long after President Bush's incompetence and duplicity were clear to many and when it was too late for the country to change course.</p>
        <p>Ken Perkins  Pittsburgh, April 30, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''The White House Scales Back Talk of Iraq Progress'' (front page, April 28):</p>
        <p>As an alternative to ''redeployment/timetable'' versus ''surge/no surrender,'' why not a sincere and explicit statement from the highest levels of our government to the following effect:</p>
        <p>''To the people of Iraq: We made a mistake. We believed that we would all be safer by doing what we did. We were wrong. We grieve as deeply for your dead as we do for ours. We are so sorry for the pain and destruction. We do not want to stay forever. Let us find a way, without more and more bloodshed, for us to leave.''</p>
        <p>Andrew Davison  Poughkeepsie, N.Y., April 28, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>President Bush and Vice President Dick Cheney have responded to Congressional action meant to bring an end to the Iraq war in ways that are petty, petulant and unprincipled.</p>
        <p>This war was entered into on fictional grounds, but it's real lives, both American and Iraqi, that are destroyed.</p>
        <p>We have elections in the United States so that the people, who are sovereign, can instruct their representatives. In November 2006, they told their elected designates to end the war in Iraq. The administration, confusing itself with an emperor, believes that it need not listen.</p>
        <p>This is unacceptable to me as the president's and vice president's employer.</p>
        <p>Liane Ellison Norman  Pittsburgh, April 27, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Quiet Bush Aide Seeks Iraq Czar, Creating a Stir'' (front page, April 30):</p>
        <p>The idea of a war czar for Iraq cannot be one of Stephen J. Hadley's better proposals. It is transparently an attempt to find a scapegoat for the disaster that is Iraq these days.</p>
        <p>If President Bush actually needs somebody to keep him abreast of developments in Iraq, even on a daily basis, he already has Gen. David H. Petraeus, the commander of United States forces in Iraq. And he has Adm. William J. Fallon, the chief of the Central Command; Gen. Peter Pace, the chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff; Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates; and his national security adviser, Mr. Hadley. This is not to mention the director of intelligence.</p>
        <p>To interpose a war czar between the president and these men is obviously not conducive to making the critical judgments it is the commander in chief's responsibility to make daily.</p>
        <p>At bottom, the president, as commander in chief, is the war czar. There is no evading this responsibility.</p>
        <p>Mariano Patalinjug  Yonkers, April 30, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I'm a bit confused about Stephen J. Hadley's remark about the Iraq czar he's trying to find. In a recent interview he said, ''What we need is someone with a lot of stature within the government who can make things happen.'' Isn't this why we have a president of the United States?</p>
        <p>Darlene Popovic  San Francisco, April 30, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>What a compelling job offer. If things (continue to) go badly in Iraq, the czar can take the blame. If things go well, the president takes the credit. What an inducement to take the job!</p>
        <p>Michael B. Gotkin  New York, April 30, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
