<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ortiz Writes Another Chapter In a Yankees Horror Story</title>
    <meta content="01araton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/sports/baseball/01araton.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844307"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ortiz, David</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Torre, Joe</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E3D6133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="991" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ortiz Writes Another Chapter In a Yankees Horror Story</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ortiz Writes Another Chapter in a Yankees Horror Story</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's a good thing for Joe Torre's tenuous job security that the Tampa-based George Steinbrenner seldom ventures into Midtown Manhattan anymore. The Boss, already in a blue statement-making mood yesterday, would have had the same visceral reaction that some Yankees fans had on their lunchtime strolls past the Barnes &amp; Noble bookstore on Fifth Avenue.</p>
        <p>''Sox fans in Manhattan, disgusting,'' one said as he passed by the line that snaked from the front door around the corner to 46th Street, almost all the way to Madison Avenue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nobody impacted the Game 4 and 5 classics of the 2004 A.L.C.S. and changed the decades-old dynamic of the Yankees-Red Sox rivalry the way David Ortiz did.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's a good thing for Joe Torre's tenuous job security that the Tampa-based George Steinbrenner seldom ventures into Midtown Manhattan anymore. The Boss, already in a blue statement-making mood yesterday, would have had the same visceral reaction that some Yankees fans had on their lunchtime strolls past the Barnes &amp; Noble bookstore on Fifth Avenue.</p>
        <p>''Sox fans in Manhattan, disgusting,'' one said as he passed by the line that snaked from the front door around the corner to 46th Street, almost all the way to Madison Avenue.</p>
        <p>''Stupid Red Sox,'' mumbled another.</p>
        <p>The people in line -- some in business suits, many in Red Sox gear, even the occasional traitor in a cap with the interlocking NY -- paid them no mind. The procession inside the store continued, up the escalator, through the maze of aisles and finally to the table where David Ortiz was happily ensconced with a ready handshake, a black felt pen and a six-and-a-half-game lead over the last-place Yankees in the American League East.</p>
        <p>Deep in the heart of enemy country one day after he hit a mammoth home run against Chien-Ming Wang and the Sox beat the Yankees this season for the fifth time in six games, Ortiz was flaunting his unconventional fame, signing hundreds of freshly published copies of his autobiography, ''Big Papi: My Story of Big Dreams and Big Hits'' (St. Martin's Press).</p>
        <p>He took a short break from the two-hour event to say the book, which will hit the New York Times extended best-seller list this weekend, is all about family, inspiration and ''big messages.'' It follows Ortiz's unlikely ascension from Minnesota Twins reject to the modern-day Bambino in Boston -- body type, stooped batting stance and all.</p>
        <p>Asked if he contemplated in the book how radically different this decade would look if Pedro Martínez hadn't made a call to the Red Sox on his behalf, Ortiz said: ''I have never sat down and analyzed that. Someday I will.''</p>
        <p>Fodder for the sequel and food for thought: How did this likable, Dominican-born player with the perfect Yankee Stadium stroke wind up in Boston, anyway? Wouldn't the Bronx have been the perfect place for ''Big Dreams and Big Hits'' to unfold?</p>
        <p>Never mind. The Yankees, their payroll soaring unhesitatingly toward $200 million, weren't much interested in low-budget solutions when Ortiz signed with the Sox for 2003 after hitting 20 home runs and driving in 75 runs for the Twins.</p>
        <p>Anywhere but Boston, and the Red Sox would now be working on their 89th season without a World Series title. Others contributed mightily to the comeback from a 3-0 deficit in the 2004 League Championship Series, but nobody had an impact on those Game 4 and 5 classics and changed the decades-old dynamic of the Yankees-Red Sox rivalry the way Ortiz did.</p>
        <p>The concurrence of Ortiz taking Manhattan and Steinbrenner's first missive of the season -- telling Torre and General Manager Brian Cashman in particular that April was ''clearly not acceptable'' -- was coincidental but instructive. Without Ortiz in the picture, who knows what the ultimate outcome of the 2004 season would have been? But had the Yankees gone to the World Series and beaten the St. Louis Cardinals, we can assume that Torre would have been set up as manager for the rest of the decade, if not for life.</p>
        <p>It wasn't just losing to the Red Sox that changed the ground rules. It was that Torre lost in such historic fashion, creating a bonanza for second-guessers that drew a clear line of demarcation between his four-time champion Yankees and the team that now disappoints year in, year out, despite a run of 11 consecutive playoff appearances.</p>
        <p>To fire him now for a 9-14 April would be a mindless overreaction to a sliver of the season, especially when Steinbrenner could make a better case against Cashman for all the disappointing (and expensive) pitchers he has acquired, without a John Maine in the bunch. But if the languid play continues into, say, June? Given the investment in this team, the devotion of its fans, how could Steinbrenner and even Cashman not vote to shake it up by removing their lame-duck manager?</p>
        <p>It is understandable why people in New York have a fervent wish for Torre to not finish his great, dignified run by falling through the trap door, like the rest of Steinbrenner's managers. But there came a point when Casey Stengel and Miller Huggins and Joe McCarthy weren't allowed to manage the Yankees anymore. This can't be about the perfect ending for Torre anymore than it wasn't for Bernie Williams.</p>
        <p>Torre didn't exactly lobby hard for Williams to return this season, now did he? Nor did he make a peep of protest when Lee Mazzilli, his bench coach last season, was made the 2006 scapegoat. The past couple of years, Torre has become something of a survivor, which is no crime, but does require the occasional body to be thrown under the bus.</p>
        <p>If his rotation straightens itself out this month, the firing talk will subside. Torre will make it through his 12th year, at least Ortiz thinks so.</p>
        <p>''Yeah, well, every year it seems like they have a tough time putting it together in the beginning,'' he said. ''But they usually find a way later on in the season.''</p>
        <p>He laughed and said, ''Hopefully not,'' before returning to his signing table.</p>
        <p>As the book buyers kept coming, the Barnes &amp; Noble people recalled a similar crowd after the 2004 World Series for the then-bearded and self-styled ''Idiot,'' Johnny Damon. We know how the Yankees solved that problem, but don't count on seeing Ortiz in pinstripes anytime soon, even though he dons a Yankees cap in a new ESPN commercial featuring him and Jorge Posada.</p>
        <p>''It's not what you think,'' Ortiz cries when the Red Sox mascot catches him in the act.</p>
        <p>The book, big dreams and Yankee-deflating hits that keep on coming are the proof.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
