<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To: The Temporarily Able-Bodied</title>
    <meta content="01tue1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/opinion/01tue1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844250"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Editorial"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Disability Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Social Security (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Astrue, Michael J (Comr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Social Security (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Security (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Social Security Administration</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE6D7133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="474" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To: The Temporarily Able-Bodied</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">To: The Temporarily Able-Bodied</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial blames Congress for bottleneck in processing of disability claims, due to shrinking budget of Social Security Adm, which administers disability program; calls on Congress to provide needed funds for 2008 budget and to work closely with new Social Security commissioner Michael Astrue</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just about everyone who works pays taxes into the fund for federal disability benefits. But mercifully, relatively few people ever collect. To qualify, you must be unable to work, and your disability must be of such severity that you'll be out for at least a year or you're likely to die from it.</p>
        <p>Those criteria are tough but necessary to ensure that resources go to the neediest Americans. In the past several years, however, another hurdle has been erected, one that is unacceptable and inhumane. Processing delays, mounting since 2000, have left more than one million applicants languishing without help, some for years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The current Congress can begin to fix the federal disability program by providing the needed funds in the coming budget for 2008.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just about everyone who works pays taxes into the fund for federal disability benefits. But mercifully, relatively few people ever collect. To qualify, you must be unable to work, and your disability must be of such severity that you'll be out for at least a year or you're likely to die from it.</p>
        <p>Those criteria are tough but necessary to ensure that resources go to the neediest Americans. In the past several years, however, another hurdle has been erected, one that is unacceptable and inhumane. Processing delays, mounting since 2000, have left more than one million applicants languishing without help, some for years.</p>
        <p>The most acute bottlenecks are at the appeals level, where the average processing time is now 515 days -- compared with 274 days in 2000. Such delays are especially pernicious because slightly more than one-quarter of all approved claims are awarded after an appeal hearing, and nearly two-thirds of the people who appeal ultimately prevail. Without the benefits they are entitled to, far too many applicants get sicker and experience severe economic hardship, including foreclosures and even homelessness. Some applicants die before their appeals are heard.</p>
        <p>The fault lies primarily with Congress. For many years, lawmakers have consistently cut into the budget for the Social Security Administration, which administers the disability program. Since 2000, the cumulative shortfall -- the difference between what the agency has asked for and what Congress has appropriated -- is $4.4 billion, with more than $2 billion of that in the last few years.</p>
        <p>In the same period, demands on the agency have grown, resulting in a chronic shortage of people to do the work. Disability claims have risen, to 2.5 million in 2006 from 1.3 million in 2000, driven in part by the aging of the population. Disability claims also tend to rise when jobs are scarce, as was the case during much of the Bush-era economic expansion. Research shows that people who would tough out their disabilities during good times turn to government aid when they lose their jobs and are unable to find new ones. Congress has also recently imposed new tasks on the Social Security Administration, like assisting with immigration issues.</p>
        <p>You get what you pay for. When it comes to helping disabled workers -- as with so many other duties of government -- recent Congresses have not been willing to pay for service that is prompt, professional and compassionate.</p>
        <p>The agency generally gets high marks for productivity and efficiency, and estimates that it needs about $10.5 billion a year to be able to do its work adequately. The current Congress can begin to fix the disability program by providing the needed funds in the coming budget for 2008. Congress must also work closely with the new commissioner of Social Security, Michael Astrue, to ensure that a plausible plan to conquer the backlog is put in place quickly.</p>
        <p>Editorial</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
