<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Woman Describes 13 Hours of Sexual Torment, and Clues Left Behind</title>
    <meta content="01fake" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/01/nyregion/01fake.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070504T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844300"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Braunstein, Peter</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E4D6133EF932A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="770" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Woman Describes 13 Hours of Sexual Torment, and Clues Left Behind</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Victim Describes 13 Hours of Sexual Torment, and Clues Left Behind</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANEMONA HARTOCOLLIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hartocollis, Anemona</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>She was putting the finishing touches on a Halloween costume from Cheap Jack's Vintage Clothing store on Oct. 31, 2005, when she heard the pounding at the door of her Chelsea apartment. Through the peephole, she saw thick white smoke and a man in full firefighting gear, a plastic visor obscuring his face, who demanded to be let in.</p>
        <p>With no reason to question that he was an actual firefighter, she allowed him in, then followed as he opened windows and complied when he ordered her to put a towel under the door, the 36-year-old woman told a Manhattan jury yesterday on the first day of the sex-abuse and kidnapping trial of Peter Braunstein, a former writer for Women's Wear Daily.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The jury heard graphic testimony of the first day of the sex-abuse and kidnapping trial of Peter Braunstein, a former writer for Women’s Wear Daily.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>She was putting the finishing touches on a Halloween costume from Cheap Jack's Vintage Clothing store on Oct. 31, 2005, when she heard the pounding at the door of her Chelsea apartment. Through the peephole, she saw thick white smoke and a man in full firefighting gear, a plastic visor obscuring his face, who demanded to be let in.</p>
        <p>With no reason to question that he was an actual firefighter, she allowed him in, then followed as he opened windows and complied when he ordered her to put a towel under the door, the 36-year-old woman told a Manhattan jury yesterday on the first day of the sex-abuse and kidnapping trial of Peter Braunstein, a former writer for Women's Wear Daily.</p>
        <p>As she got her keys and searched for her cat, preparing to flee, she felt a gun at her head, the woman testified in State Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>''Get down on the ground,'' the man in the firefighter's gear told her.</p>
        <p>When she did, he tied her wrists with plastic handcuffs and put a chloroform-soaked rag over her mouth. ''I immediately passed out,'' she said.</p>
        <p>So began a 13-hour nightmare, the woman said, in which she was sexually tormented by Mr. Braunstein, 43.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors say Mr. Braunstein was acting out his rage at the fashion industry after being fired from his job and dumped by his girlfriend, the beauty editor at W magazine. The victim, who had been a colleague in the Women's Wear Daily newsroom, was a surrogate target for those grievances, the prosecutor, Maxine Rosenthal, said in her opening statement yesterday.</p>
        <p>A defense lawyer, Celia Gordon, said that Mr. Braunstein was suffering a mental breakdown.</p>
        <p>The victim testified that Mr. Braunstein had stripped her naked and tied her to the bed with a green nylon cord that was connected to her right hand and her left hand and leg. Along with the gun, he had a hunting knife, she said.</p>
        <p>A court officer held up a lavender sweatshirt and a pink thong, and the woman said that Mr. Braunstein had cut them off her body.</p>
        <p>He also taped her eyes and mouth with duct tape, she said, and he administered chloroform four more times during the night, although she had taught herself not to inhale the fumes and to feign unconsciousness. She said that she could see a little through the tape, but that he wore a ski mask throughout most of the attack.</p>
        <p>He touched her breasts and tried to abuse her further, she said, but when she pretended to regain consciousness, he stopped. He offered her cough medicine, saying it would relax her, and swigged some himself, she said. Under cross-examination, she said he had cut the cord that was binding one arm when she complained that it hurt and that he held an ice pack on her swollen eye. She said she suspected that Mr. Braunstein had beaten her while she was unconscious.</p>
        <p>She said that she tried to ''pacify'' him by talking to him. He told her he was Jewish, an only child, and that his birthday was Jan. 26, born under the sign of Aquarius -- details that would later help the police identify him.</p>
        <p>During the ordeal, she said, friends telephoned and came to the door, but she would not respond, fearing that Mr. Braunstein would hurt them. Mr. Braunstein taunted about the calls and visits, she said. ''He referenced, 'You're worse than Paris Hilton,' '' she recalled.</p>
        <p>He rummaged through boxes of shoes in her closet, and put two pairs of high heels on her feet, a pair of lavender strapped sandals and another pair that she described as bronze colored.</p>
        <p>She had resigned from Women's Wear Daily, she told the jury, for reselling shoes from the fashion closet, and she realized that her attacker must be someone who had worked there when he offered to disclose who had reported her.</p>
        <p>As dawn broke the following morning, she said, Mr. Braunstein cleaned up the mess he had made and left her naked and tied up. She said she used her free hand and her teeth to untie herself and called a friend. The friend encouraged her to call 911.</p>
        <p>When four police officers came to her apartment door, she at first refused to let them in. Her trust in men in uniform had been shattered, she said, losing her composure for the only time on the witness stand.</p>
        <p>''I was scared,'' she said. ''I just let a fireman in a couple of hours ago, and I was adamant that no one else in uniform was coming in the house.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 4, 2007, Friday  Because of an editing error, an article on Tuesday about the victim's testimony in the Manhattan trial of Peter Braunstein, a former magazine writer accused of sexual abuse and kidnapping, misidentified the publication from which the victim, a 36-year-old woman, resigned. It was W, not Women's Wear Daily.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 4, 2007, Friday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article on Tuesday about the victim's testimony in the Manhattan trial of Peter Braunstein, a former magazine writer accused of sexual abuse and kidnapping, misidentified the publication from which the victim, a 36-year-old woman, resigned. It was W, not Women's Wear Daily.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
