<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Look Who's Reboarding That Clintonian Shuttle</title>
    <meta content="01cooper" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/weekinreview/01cooper.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837361"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE NATION: REDUX"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Middle East</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Israel</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Rice, Condoleezza</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Clinton, Bill</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Baker, James A III</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Nixon, Richard Milhous</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kissinger, Henry A</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Zelikow, Philip D</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E7D71130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1332" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Look Who's Reboarding That Clintonian Shuttle</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Look Who’s Reboarding That Clintonian Shuttle</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HELENE COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Helene</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT the State Department, it's beginning to look a lot like  Bill Clinton?</p>
        <p>Just hours before boarding her plane to fly off to the banks of the Nile for Middle East peace talks nine days ago, a reporter asked Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice whether she was prepared to advance her own proposals to the Israelis and Palestinians on the entrenched ''final status'' issues that have bedeviled peace negotiators since 1979.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice has well and truly abandoned the hands-off-Israel approach that President Bush once insisted on.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT the State Department, it's beginning to look a lot like  Bill Clinton?</p>
        <p>Just hours before boarding her plane to fly off to the banks of the Nile for Middle East peace talks nine days ago, a reporter asked Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice whether she was prepared to advance her own proposals to the Israelis and Palestinians on the entrenched ''final status'' issues that have bedeviled peace negotiators since 1979.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rice gave a cheerful shrug. ''I don't rule out that at some point that might be a useful thing to do,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Two days later, during another press roundtable -- this one in Jerusalem -- another reporter asked if she might appoint a special Middle East envoy. ''I've not ruled out anything,'' she repeated. ''I'm quite flexible on what geometry we use.''</p>
        <p>Once upon a time, the Bush administration was a strict adherent of what some privately called the ABC -- Anything But Clinton -- approach. That meant no special Mideast envoys, no pushing the Israelis into anything they didn't want to do -- particularly no pushing them to discuss the final-status issues -- and no imposing American ideas onto an Israeli-Palestinian problem.</p>
        <p>To be fair, the Clinton approach to Middle East problem-solving was pretty similar to the shuttle diplomacy approach of former President George H. W. Bush, with James A. Baker III shuttling as secretary of state, or former President Richard M. Nixon, for whom Henry Kissinger did the shuttling.</p>
        <p>But Bush administration officials came to power in 2001 taking pains to distinguish themselves from their immediate predecessors. One of the first things President Bush did was to get rid of the State Department's special Middle East envoys. ''He wants to empower the desks at the State Department,'' Ari Fleischer, the White House spokesman at the time, explained. A few days later, Mr. Fleischer went even further to drive a stake into the heart of the Clinton approach, which had included an ambitious but unsuccessful last-ditch push to forge an Israeli-Palestinian peace in 2000.</p>
        <p>''It is important to be careful in the region, to proceed at a pace that is achievable and doable, and not to raise people's expectations falsely so high by trying to reach something that the parties cannot agree to themselves,'' Mr. Fleischer said. ''Failure to reach that level created unmet expectations in the region and that resulted in violence.'' (Mr. Fleischer quickly expressed regret and absolved Mr. Clinton from responsibility for the second Palestinian intifada.)</p>
        <p>But Bush administration officials maintained their hands-off policy. Until now.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rice returned from the Middle East on Tuesday after three intense days of shuttle diplomacy that largely revolved around trying to get Israel to agree to allow peace talks with the Palestinians to include the big three final-status issues: Jerusalem's fate, a Palestinian state's borders, and what to do about Palestinian refugees who fled, or were forced to leave, homes in Israel.</p>
        <p>She didn't get Israel's agreement, but for the first time in six years, signs emerged of a United States government clearly pushing Israel toward peace negotiations. Beyond the Israeli-Palestinian issue, Ms. Rice has adopted her predecessors' maneuvers in North Korea. In February, she successfully prodded President Bush to approve a nuclear deal in which North Korea would shut down its main nuclear reactor in exchange for food and fuel; conservatives, even within the administration, complained that the agreement was no better, and perhaps worse, than the one signed by President Clinton in 1994.</p>
        <p>There are two possible explanations for the new diplomacy. The first is that deep down, Ms. Rice has always held the view expressed by her former counselor, Philip D. Zelikow, that progress on the Palestinian-Israeli dispute was a ''sine qua non'' in order to get moderate Arabs to cooperate with the administration on the things America cares about.</p>
        <p>Before accepting the job of secretary of state, Ms. Rice pressed Mr. Bush to say he was serious about pushing a two-state solution, according to Bob Woodward's ''State of Denial.'' This view holds that Ms. Rice is just being herself: she secretly thought this way all the time, and now that most of the conservative hawks have left the administration, she can do what she wants -- especially since she is at the State Department now, rather than in the White House.</p>
        <p>''There are some who wave the claim that she's just got the Foggy Bottom bug,'' said David Makovsky, an Israel analyst here. ''But that's too convenient; I think she has always believed in this.''</p>
        <p>The second explanation is that the shortcomings of the administration's strategy in Iraq and North Korea, combined with the loss of Congress to the Democrats last November, have forced Mr. Bush and Ms. Rice to shift into reverse. ''They have no choice,'' said Gary Samore, a vice president at the Council on Foreign Relations who helped negotiate the Clinton administration's 1994 agreement with North Korea. ''They tried a new approach, it utterly failed, so now they're trying something different.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Rice argues that a new opportunity to reach an agreement between the Arabs and Israelis has arisen because of rising fear in the Sunni Arab world of an influential Iran armed with a nuclear weapon. It's a twist on the enemy-of-my-enemy-is-my-friend theory, but one that administration officials hope will lead to a historic Arab-Israeli alliance.</p>
        <p>Aaron David Miller, a scholar at the Woodrow Wilson Center, disputes the whole thesis that Ms. Rice has turned into Bill Clinton. ''What she's becoming is Colin Powell,'' he said, referring to the former secretary of state whose wings were clipped by the Bush White House when he tried to push for a more robust peace effort. Mr. Miller worked for Mr. Powell at the State Department as a Mideast adviser.</p>
        <p>''What I find so intriguing having worked for Powell for two years is, this is what we were trying to do,'' Mr. Miller said, adding that the White House ''fought every step of the way to keep permanent-status issues out of the strategy.'' Ms. Rice, he said, ''can't become the Clinton administration because she doesn't have a president who is prepared to do what he did.''</p>
        <p>President Clinton put his personal reputation on the line, with eight years of detailed attention to the Arab-Israeli issue that included physically maneuvering a reluctant Israeli prime minister, Yitzhak Rabin, to shake the hand of Yasir Arafat on the South Lawn of the White House on Sept. 13, 1993. After Mr. Rabin was assassinated, Mr. Clinton pushed and prodded Benjamin Netanyahu to continue peace negotiations, at the Wye River Plantations. In his last days in office, he had anguished conversations with Mr. Arafat in which he exhorted the Palestinian leader to take the deal offered by Israel's Ehud Barak.</p>
        <p>Many Middle East analysts say Mr. Clinton's actions are something only a president can do. It remains unclear whether Ms. Rice has convinced Mr. Bush to spend his own energy on the process. State Department officials were heartened when President Bush said before Ms. Rice's trip that Mideast peace ''is a priority for this administration.'' But if Ms. Rice does gain traction on her efforts, she will have to get Mr. Bush to engage more personally, analysts say.</p>
        <p>Of course, Mr. Clinton started out with a huge advantage: the Oslo accords, which the Palestinians and Israelis did on their own, with little input from America. Mr. Bush, by contrast, started out at a disadvantage: the collapse of the Clinton plan and the Palestinian intifada made it difficult to re-launch lasting peace talks. Even now, Israeli-Palestinian relations are fraught with tension and mistrust. So Ms. Rice has a higher mountain to climb.</p>
        <p>But the Washington Institute's Mr. Makovsky pointed out that, for all of his efforts, Mr. Clinton didn't succeed in getting a peace deal. And Ms. Rice, he says, still has time to beat him.</p>
        <p>''Having learned from what Clinton went through, she can fill in the missing piece of the puzzle,'' he said. ''This story could have a different ending.''</p>
        <p>THE NATION: REDUX</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
