<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Funny Things Happened on the Way to the Condo</title>
    <meta content="01woll" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/arts/01woll.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837113"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="COMEDY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rusoff, Jane Wollman</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Amsterdam, Morey</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Buttons, Red</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Arnaz, Lucie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E2DD1330F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2393" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Funny Things Happened on the Way to the Condo</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Funny Things Happened on the Way to the Condo</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE WOLLMAN RUSOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rusoff, Jane Wollman</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on condo circuit in Southeast Florida, where mostly Jewish comedians play to mostly Jewish retirees at their community clubhouses; condo circuit seen as descendant of Catskill Borscht Belt; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONSTAGE at the Bonaventure Town Center Club in Weston, Fla., near Fort Lauderdale, the comedian Vic Arnell, 69, has the Saturday-night crowd right where he wants them: laughing so hard they're dabbing away tears.</p>
        <p>''I'll tell you a Jewish fairy tale,'' he says. ''A man asks a woman, 'Will you marry me?'</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Comedians from the Catskills are now a hit in South Florida. But as the comics and their audience ages, it’s clear that the condo circuit will go the way of the borscht belt.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONSTAGE at the Bonaventure Town Center Club in Weston, Fla., near Fort Lauderdale, the comedian Vic Arnell, 69, has the Saturday-night crowd right where he wants them: laughing so hard they're dabbing away tears.</p>
        <p>''I'll tell you a Jewish fairy tale,'' he says. ''A man asks a woman, 'Will you marry me?'</p>
        <p>''She says, 'No.' '' Pause. ''And he lived happily ever after.'' The audience, retirees who live in this condominium and homeowners' association community, erupts in laughter.</p>
        <p>Here, at the height of the winter season in retiree complexes, it's showtime for year-round residents and snowbirds alike nearly every night of the week. From December to April, there are singers, musical revues, and Elvis and Liberace impersonators. But by far the most popular entertainers are the stand-up comedians who have or would have once worked the Catskill Mountains resorts known as the borscht belt. When it comes to shows at the condos, South Florida might just as well be called the Catskills redux.</p>
        <p>Starting in the 1950s borscht belt comics came here to entertain the mostly Jewish retirees who had moved to Miami condominiums. They were the same entertainers -- Morey Amsterdam, Red Buttons, Jan Murray, Henny Youngman and others -- who made them laugh in the Catskills, a birthplace of modern stand-up.</p>
        <p>When retirement communities in West Palm Beach, Boca Raton and other cities popped up, the comedians began playing multiple South Florida dates: as many as 10 clubhouse theaters, condo ballrooms or social halls in as little as two weeks. That's how the condo circuit got its name. Today the booking agent Howard Rapp estimates that the annual circuit -- more active now in newer developments, like those in Boca Raton or Boynton Beach, than in Miami Beach -- is a $10 million business.</p>
        <p>Not just anyone can attend these shows. They are put on expressly for the hundreds of thousands of people, mainly ages 55 to 95, who live full or part time in these communities. The heart of the circuit runs about 60 miles along the Southeast Florida coastline.</p>
        <p>From the beginning Catskill comedians dominated the circuit, even as the mountain resorts themselves fell into decline. But in the last few years a fresh generation of snowbirds has arrived, with different tastes in comedy. At the same time many new residents relate zilch to the Catskills. They're younger and interested more in music than in traditional comedy. With the comics and their audiences aging, it's becoming clear that the historic condo circuit will, before long, go the way of the borscht belt.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arnell, who toured with Tom Jones and Engelbert Humperdinck, has been playing the circuit for four decades. Born in Brownsville, Brooklyn, he began his stand-up career at the Hotel Irvington in the Catskills as social-athletic director, with a little comedy on the side.</p>
        <p>Before the recent Saturday show, he mixes and mingles in the Bonaventure clubhouse lobby. Then he ambles to his dressing room, where rugelach and carrot sticks sit on a coffee table for a postshow nosh. With his blondish-reddish hair slicked back and four chains around his neck, Mr. Arnell talks about his work.</p>
        <p>''The condo circuit is the last vestige of any kind of variety in the United States on a regular basis,'' he says. ''These people are laughers.''</p>
        <p>Tickets to the shows can sell for as little as $5, and the pay for entertainers varies as well. ''There are acts down here who work for $150 and acts that work for $5,000,'' Mr. Arnell says. ''Luckily, I'm in the Cadillac family."</p>
        <p>Out front the stage is adorned with a crimson velvet curtain. Two large video screens hang from the ceiling to give people in the rear a better view. Walkers are parked here and there.</p>
        <p>There's a rousing opening act in which a singer, Judy Scott, serves up comic patter (''Like my dress? Oscar de la Yenta!'') and leads the crowd in songs like ''Shake, Rattle and Roll.'' Then Mr. Arnell, who has changed into black, comes on. He animates his comic routines with inspired gestures and a loud voice: for one bit about being trussed up in traction for a slipped disc, he strikes a crucifixionlike pose.</p>
        <p>He switches to a riff about Florida doctors: ''They have these fancy diplomas hanging in their offices. But we don't know how they really did in school. My hemorrhoids are killing me. What if I get a doctor that failed tuchis? Who needs him!</p>
        <p>''But I love it down here!''</p>
        <p>On a Friday night about 20 miles away, Lonnie Shorr, 64, is about to regale the audience at the Palace, the 1,000-seat theater at Kings Point Tamarac, another large condo complex. Mr. Shorr began working the condos just three years ago and does not have a background in the Catskills. Reared in North Carolina, he came up playing rooms in Oklahoma, Texas and Montana and at the Playboy Clubs. Later he co-headlined in Las Vegas and at the Copacabana in New York.</p>
        <p>Before the Tamarac show Tony Bennett's ''Rags to Riches'' is piped through the sound system. A woman using a wheelchair is helped to her seat. A man tests the view through binoculars.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shorr, short and dressed in suit and tie, takes the stage and with his slight Southern drawl works the front row. ''What's your first name?'' he asks, leaning down a little, microphone in hand.</p>
        <p>''Bud.''</p>
        <p>''Is that Mrs. Bud with you?''</p>
        <p>He delivers a batch of jokes ribbing Bill Clinton, Monica Lewinsky, Linda Tripp, Jack Kevorkian. Resting an elbow on the mike stand, he asks one man: ''What did you used to do? I bet you were a senator. You show me a senator who doesn't have his hand out there, and I'll show you Bob Dole.''</p>
        <p>Suddenly Mr. Shorr makes an announcement. ''I brought a friend with me tonight. Give a young comedian a shot. His name is Shecky Greene!''</p>
        <p>''Oh my God! I don't believe it!'' cries one woman, thrilled. This veteran comedian, 80, started in the Catskills and has been mostly retired for years. He's wearing glasses, a casual light-blue shirt and matching pants with white slip-ons.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greene's bit include one about a gross Florida counterman serving him a bagel and cream cheese. The crowd is hysterical.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greene played the circuit last year, but he says he prefers impromptu appearances like this one with Mr. Shorr. ''I do better when I'm not paid; there's no pressure,'' he explains. ''But I enjoyed doing the circuit. I really needed it because I hadn't worked in a long time. Just performing was very satisfying.''</p>
        <p>For about five years Mr. Shorr hesitated to join the circuit. Although an array of bigger names -- Lucie Arnaz, Theodore Bikel, Carol Channing, Robert Klein -- are increasingly making appearances, Mr. Rapp, the agent, says that some comics and their agents consider the bookings to be a career ender.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shorr found that ''it's actually not bad,'' he says, adding, ''Just because they're older doesn't mean they don't understand.''</p>
        <p>Younger comedians whose material resonates with the aging residents are hard to find. But Century Village, a large complex with nearly 30,000 units in four communities -- Red Buttons was its spokesman in commercials -- has found one in Wendy Liebman, 46. The condo bills her as ''A Nice Jewish Girl.''</p>
        <p>This season is Ms. Liebman's third on the circuit. Her comedy signature is the throwaway line voiced almost under her breath. But for these audiences, she says, ''I talk a little louder, a little slower, I'm more expressive. I try to throw in a little Yiddish -- like maybe 'mishegas.' ''</p>
        <p>Ms. Liebman, who grew up in Roslyn, on Long Island, and won the 1996 American Comedy Award for best female stand-up, says she never aspired to perform in the condos. But like Mr. Shorr, she has a new view of the Florida gigs. ''The people are so appreciative,'' she says. ''They want to be entertained. Sometimes they want to fix me up with their son or grandson.''</p>
        <p>On a Thursday night the 1,600-seat Deerfield Beach theater is sold out. Taking the stage Ms. Liebman is dressed modestly: long black skirt, boxy top and short boots.</p>
        <p>''What's the secret to a good marriage?'' she asks. A man in the audience yells out, ''Viagra!'' She continues: "My grandmother said it's separate bedrooms and don't go to sleep angry. She's been awake since 1936.''</p>
        <p>Her medical jokes strike a major chord: ''I hope they reform the health care system in this country. They charge me for a self-breast exam. It's a flat fee. I wear an 18-hour bra in just 15 minutes!'' Pause. ''Is that too racy?''</p>
        <p>''No!'' the crowd assures her. At the condos off-color jokes with mild profanity get laughs, but audiences frown on coarse four-letter words.</p>
        <p>After the show one audience member, Doris Picker, 77, says: ''She was good. She's not that risqué. But you really have to listen to pick up her jokes.''</p>
        <p>Gathered around a decorative fountain, four snowbird couples who call themselves the Newbies Club are having a lively chat. They're in their 60s and are new arrivals to Century Village. ''Every show I've seen is terrific,'' says Rebecca Karan, 61, here with her husband, Aaron, 63. ''I'd be rotting away in my bedroom upstairs in Westchester if I didn't come down here.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rapp has been booking acts in the condos for 25 years. Now he's seeking comedians who will appeal to more than one type of audience. ''Comedy is very difficult here,'' he says. ''You have to find acts that can work to these middle-of-the-road people as well as to the younger ones who go to comedy clubs.''</p>
        <p>Jack Carter, 83, who has been playing the condo circuit for 20 years, insists that ''a lot of the acts they put in don't belong and bomb terribly.'' He continues: ''They're trying to have a lot of the comedy-club guys down here, and they die. It takes time to develop an act and rapport with this kind of crowd.''</p>
        <p>That's why condos are also booking more and more '50s and '60s singing groups, popular with nostalgic baby boomers. This season's debuts include Jay Black, former lead singer of Jay and the Americans and the voice behind the group's hits ''This Magic Moment'' and ''Cara Mia.'' For jobs at places like the Westbury Music Fair on Long Island, he throws in raunchy comedy between songs. But before his condo tour he was told to tone it down.</p>
        <p>''I've always thought of myself as a comedian who sings,'' says Mr. Black, who was born in Corona, Queens, and who, at 68, has silver hair and a pot belly.</p>
        <p>Just 10 minutes after his first show on a Friday night ended, miles away, Mr. Black charges onstage at Huntington Pointe in Delray Beach. ''We flew here!'' he tells the audience. ''Billy Crystal told me that when you start to do the condos, you're close to death.'' There's a big laugh. ''I know what he means now.''</p>
        <p>After a standing ovation at show's end, some in the audience, like Beverly Berman, remember Mr. Black from his early days. ''I knew him from way back,'' she says. ''He used to come to my sister's house in Woodmere in the '70s. He's still great after all these years.''</p>
        <p>Another woman, nearby, chimes in: ''He doesn't look anything like he used to. But not a single walkout. When they don't like you, they walk right out.''</p>
        <p>In a move to offer new and different entertainment, some condos are booking family acts. Kings Point Delray Beach, with about 7,200 units, is experimenting with a country-western singing group, the Hughes Brothers, direct from Branson, Mo.</p>
        <p>The five brothers, who have served as missionaries, try to engage the audience one Wednesday evening. ''How many New Yorkers do we have here? Oh, a lot. So do you say, 'Youse guys?' ''</p>
        <p>''No!'' comes the response. ''That's not New York. That's the Bronx.'' A flatulence joke and one about ''the crabs'' misfires too. But the song ''Close Every Door,'' from ''Joseph and the Amazing Technicolor Dreamcoat,'' is a crowd-pleaser.</p>
        <p>After ''Old McDonald Had a Band,'' featuring bagpipes, the lead singer, Jason, 37, induces a resident, Norma Reubens, to dance. She polkas in the aisle with him to ''Roll Out the Barrel,'' then tangos and ends with a fox trot. When she announces that she's 91, she gets a huge hand.</p>
        <p>The Hugheses' finale includes a salute to what they say has held their family together, principally love and ''the gospel of Jesus Christ.''</p>
        <p>Afterward audience members give the show mixed reviews. ''I love country music; they're very talented,'' says Dave Segal, 67, who took his wife, Miriam's hand during a ballad.</p>
        <p>Two thumbs down, says Liz. ''We have to keep our religion in our homes.'' She declines to give her last name or age. (''Pick a number. If you like it, that's what I am.'')</p>
        <p>Perhaps the happiest person in the room is Ms. Reubens. She used to teach folk dancing at the 92nd Street Y in Manhattan. Now she beams, ''I became a star tonight.''</p>
        <p>To be sure, demographic shifts account for the changes in condo entertainment. The mainly Jewish older generation is dying; many elderly residents who can no longer live independently are moving back north to nursing homes or to be with their children. At the same time condos are seeing an influx of Hispanic residents and increasing numbers from Canada too.</p>
        <p>''I can see the writing on the wall of who will be doing the condo circuit in the future,'' says Selma E. Hazouri, social director of Kings Point Delray Beach. She expects acts from the '60s and '70s, like Marilyn McCoo and Billy Davis Jr. -- on the circuit this season -- to replace the comics. ''The people from 55 to 70 years old are not going to be so open to entertainers who had their roots in vaudeville.''</p>
        <p>But for now, at least, comedians like Freddie Roman, 69, still have an enthusiastic audience. He has played the condos since 1974 and calls his appearances ''love fests'': ''After the show about 200 people come up to the stage and talk to me. They remember when they saw me at the Concord or Grossinger's. They come with love. I feel the love and give it back.''</p>
        <p>COMEDY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
