<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Of Rocks and Apples And the Disappearance Of 20-Game Winners</title>
    <meta content="01chass" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/sports/baseball/01chass.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837436"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Chass, Murray</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Santana, Johan</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wang, Chien-Ming</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05EFDD1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1303" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Of Rocks and Apples And the Disappearance Of 20-Game Winners</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Of Rocks and Apples and the Disappearance of 20-Game Winners</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The question was about 20-game winners, and Rich Donnelly wanted to talk about apple fights.</p>
        <p>''As kids we had apple fights,'' said Donnelly, the Los Angeles Dodgers' third-base coach. ''I'll bet you there's no one in here who ever had an apple fight.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pitchers now throw fewer strikes, which leads to more pitches, fewer innings and explains to a large extent why the 20-game winner has become an endangered species.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The question was about 20-game winners, and Rich Donnelly wanted to talk about apple fights.</p>
        <p>''As kids we had apple fights,'' said Donnelly, the Los Angeles Dodgers' third-base coach. ''I'll bet you there's no one in here who ever had an apple fight.''</p>
        <p>Growing up in Steubenville, Ohio, Donnelly had apple fights.</p>
        <p>''You'd try to hit somebody, smash them in the head with a green apple,'' he related one day in spring training in Fort Myers, Fla. Because today's pitchers never had apple fights, he added, ''their accuracy is awful.''</p>
        <p>''Some of these guys, you watch them, they have a hard time playing catch sometimes,'' he said.</p>
        <p>They especially have difficulty throwing strikes, which means they throw more pitches, pitch fewer innings and have less of a chance to win games, which explains to a large extent why the 20-game winner has become an endangered species.</p>
        <p>For the first time in a complete season, the major leagues had no 20-game winners last season. Johan Santana of Minnesota and Chien-Ming Wang of the Yankees each had 19 victories. Half a dozen National League pitchers had 16 wins, the lowest league-leading total in either league in a complete season.</p>
        <p>''That's weird,'' said Boston's Curt Schilling, a three-time 20-game winner. ''That's odd. That's a low total. But it's just one of those years. Nobody had that perfect season.''</p>
        <p>In other words, Schilling does not believe that the 20-game winner is being threatened with extinction. ''I think there's a lot more good pitching in the game now,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Tom Glavine of the Mets echoed the thought that last season was an aberration.</p>
        <p>''I'm not saying you're going to have 10 20-game winners this year,'' he said, ''but you should see a few. I'm sure last year some pitchers could have won 20, but they had some tough games or the bullpen lost it for them. There are just too many talented pitchers out there not to see it again.''</p>
        <p>But Schilling noted that pitchers didn't go as far into their starts as they used to, reducing their chances of receiving credit for a victory.</p>
        <p>''Guys go six, seven innings, and when they come out, there's a third of the game left,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The culture of pitching has changed over the years. Gone are the days, as recently as in the mid-1970s, when pitchers worked 300 innings a season, started every fourth day and often finished what they started.</p>
        <p>''I don't think it's as much a statement about starting pitchers as the way baseball is run today,'' said Rick Peterson, the Mets' pitching coach.</p>
        <p>When the Baltimore Orioles had four 20-game winners in 1971, they started 142 of the team's 158 games, and three of them worked 282 or 292 innings and pitched 18 to 21 complete games. But that quartet, Pat Dobson, Jim Palmer, Mike Cuellar and Dave McNally, was one of the last four-man rotations.</p>
        <p>Concerned for the health and well-being of their pitchers' arms, teams began pampering their pitchers, giving them an extra day of rest by inserting a fifth starter. Worse, they eventually applied more restrictions, installing a pitch limit that magically became 100.</p>
        <p>Beyond that count, teams concluded, many, if not most, pitchers became more hittable and also risked injury. Organizations put in those restrictions in their minor league systems so that young pitchers would reach the major leagues thinking all they had to do was pitch five or six innings and they had done their job.</p>
        <p>''You have guys who aren't throwing 70 or 80 pitches in the minors,'' said Andy Pettitte, the Yankees' veteran left-hander.</p>
        <p>Donnelly said: ''It used to be if you're tired, you're coming out. Now you get around 100, you're coming out. How many innings can you fit into 100 pitches? I think everybody is overprotective.''</p>
        <p>With teams constantly complaining about a lack of pitching, always searching for capable starters and overpaying mediocre pitchers, it would make sense to revert to the four-man rotation.</p>
        <p>But teams are paying pitchers so much that they don't want to risk injury and pay them that money while they sit on the disabled list.</p>
        <p>So pitchers start fewer games, pitch fewer innings and have fewer chances to win 20.</p>
        <p>''You don't see too many pitchers throwing complete games,'' said Santana, a two-time Cy Young award winner who once won 20 games. ''Now teams are built different from the past. You have bullpen guys, you got a setup man, you got a closer. Once you're out of the games, there's nothing you can do. It's up to your teammates to do their job.''</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, he said, 20-game winners are not an endangered species.</p>
        <p>''One thing I can tell you,'' said Santana, who completed one of his 34 starts last season. ''We're not animals. So I don't think there's any danger.''</p>
        <p>Pettitte, who won 21 games in 1996 and in 2003, wasn't certain which way the trend would go, but said: ''I still think you should have one or two. Guys are still getting 35, 36 starts, the guys who lead the league, so you have to think if you get enough of those guys, you're going to get guys that win 20. But it's definitely getting rare.''</p>
        <p>Asked if pitchers still considered winning 20 games special, he said: ''Of course it's special. It's a number as a starter you'd love to get to. I won 19 twice and had a couple of shots at 20 and wasn't able to get it. It's definitely disappointing if you have a chance to get to 20 but you're not able to do it.''</p>
        <p>Ron Guidry, Pettitte's pitching coach, won more than 20 games three times in his career with the Yankees. He also led the league with 21 complete games in 1983.</p>
        <p>''I don't know if there are as many quality guys as you used to have, but I don't think it's endangered,'' he said. ''I just think last year was probably one of those freak years. We had a good chance to have one. One game sticks out in your mind that Wang should have won, in Washington when we didn't have anybody to help him in the bullpen because the bullpen was dead.''</p>
        <p>With Mariano Rivera unavailable after having pitched in the previous two games, Wang entered the ninth inning with a 2-1 lead and gave up a one-out, two-run home run to Ryan Zimmerman. Although that game was in midseason, on June 18, it could have deprived Wang of being the only 20-game winner in the majors.</p>
        <p>Peterson, the Mets' pitching coach, is not surprised at the scarcity of 20-game winners. ''I would say yes,'' he said, answering the endangered-species question, saying that circumstances had made it more difficult for even premier pitchers to win enough of their starts to get to 20.</p>
        <p>Peterson said pitchers had to win two-thirds of their starts to have a shot at 20, and he asked how many starters had a career winning percentage of .667 or better. Of those with 20 or more victories, the answer is three -- Pedro Martínez, Roy Oswalt and Wang.</p>
        <p>Chances are, even they did not have apple fights in their youth.</p>
        <p>''I hit Raymond Paine with an apple right in the middle of the forehead,'' Donnelly recalled. ''I also hit him with a clinker. I'll bet these guys don't know what a clinker is.''</p>
        <p>Nor did his listener. ''I was raised in an alley,'' the 60-year-old Donnelly said. ''They would deliver coal for the furnaces, and waste would come out and there would be a clinker, a rock. We had rock fights all the time. These guys never had an apple fight or a rock fight in their life. I'll bet all the no-parking signs in their neighborhoods are clean.''</p>
        <p>And they don't win 20 games.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
