<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Design Intervention</title>
    <meta content="04talk.icons.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="T: Design Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="84" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Style; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/style/tmagazine/04talk.icons.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837078"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Icons"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00EEDA1230F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="774" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Design Intervention</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Design Intervention</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Herberrt Muschamp</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Muschamp, Herbert</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>All our hearts beat in unison with the hope that certain places of public accommodation will not always be the scenes of mass misery that they are today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Deliver us from the evil of the banal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>All our hearts beat in unison with the hope that certain places of public accommodation will not always be the scenes of mass misery that they are today.</p>
        <p>The multiplex, the back of the plane, the convention hotel: do they have to be so awful?</p>
        <p>But the awfulness has been going on so long now that surely it is a waste of breath to go on complaining about it. Perhaps the time has come to turn the question around. Instead of hoping that the designers of such places will make them better, why not organize a campaign to make them even worse?</p>
        <p>Consider the multiplex at Union Square, for example, where someone has tried to brighten the escalator wells by dangling what appear to be tubes of sparkly, light-refracting gift wrap against the walls. Every time you ride the stairs, it feels as if you're opening a present from somebody you wish you'd never met. Why not make it cheaper? Why not decorate the joint with little cardboard tubes of empty toilet-paper rolls? Or fishing lines with lures made of crumpled foil gum wrappers?</p>
        <p>On that note, the seats in coach should be whacked with a crowbar between flights to ensure that they are all properly broken. They will neither recline nor return to the upright position but instead freely adjust themselves in response to the subtlest motions of the passenger's body. Old newspapers will be tossed artlessly over the cushions in a deliberately botched procedure for concealing stains. Restrooms? Banished.</p>
        <p>Convention hotels will become more aggressive in the methods they use to dissuade guests from leaving the hotel and spending their money elsewhere. In addition to such standard techniques as atriums, disorienting carpet patterns and the placement of lobbies six stories above street level, guests will be subject to inspection by dogs, metal detectors and retired prison matrons from the former East Germany. If these methods fail to produce the desired effect, break-apart handles will be installed on the inside of doors.</p>
        <p>Let's be realistic. John Edwards is cute. His wife I adore madly. But I see few signs that our great country will reverse course away from the extreme economic polarization that we've been moving toward since the late 1960s. If we're determined to live in a plantation society, why pretend that the slave quarters can be magically transformed into the planter's mansion? Why should a slave ship resemble the Queen Mary? Why add delusion to discomfort?</p>
        <p>It is a historical fact that austerity has sparked more than one revolution in taste. Think of the severe neo-Classicism that Europeans embraced in the late 18th century, with the rise of social conscience fostered by the Enlightenment.</p>
        <p>Or the design reforms undertaken by the British designer William Morris and the Viennese architect Adolf Loos. Or think of the Bauhaus, and its refinement of industrial production amid the economic hardships of Weimar Germany.</p>
        <p>These movements all managed to make things better by, paradoxically, making them worse. They adhered to Arthur Danto's concept of ''the transfiguration of the commonplace'' -- the process of aestheticizing forms and images that were thought to lie beyond the boundaries of aesthetic experience. This process resulted in more than different kinds of objects. It also produced fresh ways of looking at and thinking about the changing modern world.</p>
        <p>And let us not forget the Shakers. Mother Ann Lee! Oh, my goodness, Mother Ann Lee! Whether or not it is true, as Mies van der Rohe believed, that Less is More, we can all say with absolute certainty that Less is Lee. ''Shake shake out of me all that is carnal!'' Can you think of a better step in our magnificent Land of a Thousand Dances?</p>
        <p>Sadly, Shaker practice has guaranteed that few Shakers are still with us today. But I am convinced that the few remaining ones can contribute at least one more shake to our littered paradise. Indeed, if Mother were alive, she would probably be running the design shop at Apple. Her spirit of austerity flows through almost every Mac and iPod out there.</p>
        <p>In fact, the most useful solution to all our design problems would be to transform Apple into a religion. For many of the brand's devotees it practically is one, anyhow. But if their reverential attitudes could somehow be formalized, providers of public accommodations might be forced to go along with the company's aesthetic. Just as airlines have long felt obliged to offer kosher dinners on flights, so hotel and multiplex designs would have to be prepared under the supervision of Father Steve Jobs. I can't wait to hang my hat on an iPeg.</p>
        <p>Icons</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
