<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WHEN THE GAME ABSORBS THE GLOBE</title>
    <meta content="01vecsey" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/sports/baseball/01vecsey.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837443"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Japan</location>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Matsuzaka, Daisuke</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Selig, Bud</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Pujols, Albert</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E6DC1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WHEN THE GAME ABSORBS THE GLOBE</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Universal Language of America’s Pastime</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN HIS NEW LIFE as a retired pitcher, Al Leiter made a trip last October to his ancestral home, the Czech Republic, and was invited to the championship game of the domestic baseball league.</p>
        <p>''I looked around and said, 'Hmm, that's odd,' '' Leiter recalled. ''The uniforms, the demeanor, the body language were absolutely like an American game.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With a quarter of its players categorized as coming from outside the 50 states, is Major League Baseball heading for some psychological tipping point where it no longer seems like the traditional American game?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN HIS NEW LIFE as a retired pitcher, Al Leiter made a trip last October to his ancestral home, the Czech Republic, and was invited to the championship game of the domestic baseball league.</p>
        <p>''I looked around and said, 'Hmm, that's odd,' '' Leiter recalled. ''The uniforms, the demeanor, the body language were absolutely like an American game.''</p>
        <p>As any baseball fan knows, there is a universal language. Along with the uniform comes the standard way of strutting, scratching and spitting -- maybe from the ubiquitous tapes now being studied in the 112 member nations in the International Baseball Federation.</p>
        <p>For better or worse, but mostly for money, the best players in this world continue to migrate to the United States -- not only Daisuke Matsuzaka of Japan and Albert Pujols of the Dominican Republic, but players from Australia, and, who knows, soon from China and Africa.</p>
        <p>Last year, 28 percent of the players in the majors came from outside the 50 states. (Major League Baseball includes Puerto Rican players, who are American citizens, in the international category.) That percentage is expected to be about the same when rosters are set for opening day this year.</p>
        <p>There is no sudden phenomenon, like the foreign stars who have changed the face of the N.B.A. The impact on Japanese baseball is being felt with its top stars heading to the United States. And that raises the question in North America: With a quarter of its players categorized as coming from outside the 50 states, is Major League Baseball heading for some psychological tipping point where it no longer seems like the traditional American game?</p>
        <p>''There's not a scintilla of negative effect,'' Commissioner Bud Selig said, citing the attendance that he expected to surpass last year's record of more than 76 million.</p>
        <p>''Baseball fans look at players as players,'' said Ed Goren, the president of Fox Sports, reflecting the impact on sponsors and ratings. ''I'm thinking of Pedro Martínez and David Ortiz and young José Reyes with the Mets. The camera captures him in the dugout, having fun.''</p>
        <p>Part of the universal reaction is that baseball players come off as average people, although obviously their hand-eye coordination is anything but typical. (The bulked-up physiques seem to be returning toward normal dimensions, for some mysterious reason.) Leiter, who broadcasts 50 games a year on the YES Network, cited body types as disparate as the stocky David Wells and the spindly David Eckstein as signs of universality.</p>
        <p>Along with the daily soap opera and timeless pageantry, baseball breeds a certain attitude that can be quickly acquired. I remember when the Soviet Union taught a crash course in baseball to former javelin hurlers and kayakers. These guys came to the Goodwill Games in Seattle in 1990, ambling around like characters out of ''Bull Durham.''</p>
        <p>No players developed in Russia have made the majors yet, but Leiter (whose Czech family was originally named Literbatzky, and hailed from Breclav) saw a catcher and an infielder in that championship game in Brno who are now in minor league camps here.</p>
        <p>Participation in nearly every sport in the United States is becoming more international, with the exception of pro football, which has a huge world television audience for its megachampionship, the Super Bowl. Other borders have broken down. Two decades ago, the great European soccer clubs were still distinctly national: A.C. Milan might start nine Italians and two charismatic Dutchmen. Now, under European law, there are no quotas, so fans in England watch their Ghanaian battle the other team's Nigerian for a loose ball -- and the fans come to grips with old racial attitudes.</p>
        <p>The United States has its own problem with the decreasing percentage of African-American baseball players, which I attribute mostly to the challenges and rewards of other great sports like basketball and football. Major League Baseball is trying to combat the drop-off of black players, Selig volunteered while discussing his pleasure with the otherwise diverse face of baseball.</p>
        <p>Paul Archey, the international vice president of Major League Baseball, said he expected the percentage of international players to ''flatten out.'' He predicted that the baseball academy in Italy would produce more European major leaguers and that Asian nations would continue to send their best players to the United States, but, he added, ''The U.S. players are not going away.''</p>
        <p>To face the multiple cultures in baseball, Goren said Fox had occasionally used José Mota, the son of the great pinch-hitter Manny Mota, as a bilingual reporter, and the network has also shown interviews with Japanese players in their own language, with English subtitles, ''so you can get a feel for them.''</p>
        <p>Americans, with their traditionally provincial side, were slow to embrace the first World Baseball Classic last year. The best possible thing happened: Japan and Cuba, nations with vastly different systems, met in the final, which Japan won.</p>
        <p>For all the worldwide growth, the sport took a huge hit two years ago when the International Olympic Committee, looking to downsize, voted men's baseball and women's softball out of the 2012 London Games. The well-connected Harvey Schiller, the newly elected president of the International Baseball Federation, is lobbying for the return of baseball to the Olympics in 2016, but that may depend on whether M.L.B. will make its players available during its season.</p>
        <p>For now, it is time to play ball. The Red Sox have a Japanese starter. The Yankees have a Taiwanese starter. The Anglo-Saxon imprecations in both ballparks sound eternal.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
