<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hiding In Plain, Padded Sight</title>
    <meta content="01POSS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/fashion/01POSS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837265"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="POSSESSED"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE7DD1130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="595" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hiding In Plain, Padded Sight</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hiding in Plain, Padded Sight</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID COLMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Colman, David</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Karen Russell's mother, Janice, packed her daughter off to Northwestern University in September 1999, she was concerned for the girl. Having lived in Miami her entire life, the junior Ms. Russell had never seen snow or felt the icy breath of winter. And like overprotective mothers everywhere, she assuaged her anxieties by giving her daughter a little bit of overprotection.</p>
        <p>The object in question was as light as a feather but, visually speaking, a lead balloon. Bought marked down at a Lands' End outlet, it was an irregular man's down parka -- a very large man's down parka -- which completely overwhelmed Ms. Russell, the sprightly young writer whose life last year was turned into a Cinderella story with the publication of her darkly witty book of fairy tale-ish stories, ''St. Lucy's Home for Girls Raised by Wolves'' (Knopf).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Karen Russell, author of “St. Lucy’s Home for Girls Raised by Wolves,” a darkly witty book of fairy tale-ish stories, and her very large man’s down parka.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Karen Russell's mother, Janice, packed her daughter off to Northwestern University in September 1999, she was concerned for the girl. Having lived in Miami her entire life, the junior Ms. Russell had never seen snow or felt the icy breath of winter. And like overprotective mothers everywhere, she assuaged her anxieties by giving her daughter a little bit of overprotection.</p>
        <p>The object in question was as light as a feather but, visually speaking, a lead balloon. Bought marked down at a Lands' End outlet, it was an irregular man's down parka -- a very large man's down parka -- which completely overwhelmed Ms. Russell, the sprightly young writer whose life last year was turned into a Cinderella story with the publication of her darkly witty book of fairy tale-ish stories, ''St. Lucy's Home for Girls Raised by Wolves'' (Knopf).</p>
        <p>Perhaps overwhelm is not the exact verb. Encase? Envelop? Enshroud?</p>
        <p>It certainly insulated her. ''It's so warm, you really have to guess what the weather's like,'' said Ms. Russell, who has lived in Manhattan since 2003. ''It's like it has its own microclimate. That terrible winter we had a few years ago, when the mayor came on TV and apologized for how cold it was, people would be complaining, and I would just nod my head and empathize, but I'd be wearing a tank top underneath and sipping iced coffee.''</p>
        <p>More important, its formidable presence protects her from more than cold. ''It's really aggressively ugly,'' she said. ''It makes me look like the world's shortest linebacker. It's been too big for every guy I've ever dated. Even people who don't care about fashion at all have a strong reaction to it.</p>
        <p>''It used to have this hood, which completely covered my face except for my eyes, but I lost it. It made me look like some kind of obese ninja. It completely obscured my identity. I would wave to people on campus, and they would just inch slowly away.''</p>
        <p>By the time her mother realized that her daughter did not need a coat suitable for climbing a Himalaya, it was too late. The ''trash man coat,'' as Ms. Russell calls it, was her favorite, and subsequent gifts of more girlish and attractive winter coats were shrugged off, one and all.</p>
        <p>''They're all on hangers,'' Ms. Russell said. ''One thing I love is that, without any diet or exercise, I can have this transformation from linebacker to girl every day,'' she said. ''I went on a date once with someone I'd just met, and when I walked into the restaurant and then took off the coat, there was the purest look of relief on the guy's face. It's like some Harry Potter magical vestment, but it's just a really, really ugly coat.''</p>
        <p>Unlike most clothes we imbue with magical powers, the nice thing about the coat is that she can experience its charm not just by wearing it, but by taking it off, too.</p>
        <p>She has worn the coat less this winter because her boyfriend begged her to wear something that makes her ''identifiably a woman.''</p>
        <p>At this point, though, it has already done its job, not just as insulator but also as incubator. Ms. Russell has a vision of a world that teeters between the natural and the supernatural, just as her awkward childhood and adolescence in Miami teetered between the tropically natural and the cheerily artificial. It is hardly surprising that she would want and appreciate a tundra-grade cocoon. You can't emerge, like some defiant and clever butterfly, from a nice navy peacoat.</p>
        <p>POSSESSED</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
