<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Too Many Men on the Fields (And Women and Children, Too)</title>
    <meta content="01fields" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/01fields.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070405T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837449"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Parks and Recreation Department (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Timothy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Parks Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E5DC1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1574" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Too Many Men on the Fields (And Women and Children, Too)</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Too Many Men on the Fields (and Women and Children, Too)</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY WILLIAMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Williams, Timothy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City Parks and Recreation Dept is unable to keep up with demand for playing fields for leagues in soccer, lacrosse, rugby, softball and other sports, which have increased in all age groups; adding to problem are new schools that lack space for playing fields, forcing their tenants to practice in city parks; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At 11 p.m., with the temperature well below freezing, two teams of men in their 30s possessing varying degrees of athletic prowess played a spirited, if sloppy, game of soccer atop a Hudson River pier. A cold wind blew ball and bodies about in unpredictable ways.</p>
        <p>The men slipped and shouted and laughed, ignoring the burn of artificial turf on their hips and knees. During an abbreviated halftime, largely spent shivering, the players acknowledged that given better options, late at night in the dead of winter would not be their first choice for a soccer match.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A surge in organized sports in the city has led to fierce competition before the games can even begin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At 11 p.m., with the temperature well below freezing, two teams of men in their 30s possessing varying degrees of athletic prowess played a spirited, if sloppy, game of soccer atop a Hudson River pier. A cold wind blew ball and bodies about in unpredictable ways.</p>
        <p>The men slipped and shouted and laughed, ignoring the burn of artificial turf on their hips and knees. During an abbreviated halftime, largely spent shivering, the players acknowledged that given better options, late at night in the dead of winter would not be their first choice for a soccer match.</p>
        <p>''We want to play soccer, and in the city, this is the only time, the only place,'' said Trevor Howe, a 32-year-old stock analyst, who wore a fleece sweatshirt and a ski cap. ''So here we are and it's bitter cold and miserable, but you drink a shot or two of schnapps, run around with your mates and you almost forget how silly it is until you stop moving.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Howe and his team -- among more than three dozen who participated in a Winter Warriors nighttime soccer league at Pier 40 in the West Village from December through March -- are part of a surge in organized sports that has contributed to an acute shortage of playing fields in the city.</p>
        <p>The problem, officials say, will get worse as temperatures rise and more teams vie for playing space. Players sometimes have to wait a year or more to reserve a field.</p>
        <p>The demand is driven by a variety of factors, including adults staying active longer, more children's leagues, and immigration trends. It is but one more measure of how the city has been transformed from a generation ago, when playing fields were often used not for sport, but for having sex, getting high on drugs or settling fights.</p>
        <p>''When I was a kid there were almost no organized baseball and soccer leagues, except in parts of Brooklyn,'' said Adrian Benepe, 50, the parks commissioner. ''If there were games, they were pickup games. People with kids would move out of the city to safer, cleaner neighborhoods, where there were backyards or fields for their kids to play.</p>
        <p>''Now,'' he continued, ''the middle class is staying put, and you have a tremendous demand for sports fields.''</p>
        <p>In 1999, the Parks and Recreation Department handled about 66,500 requests for permits to use the city's playing fields and tennis courts. By 2005, that number had more than doubled, to 137,000.</p>
        <p>Along with children as young as 5, men and women as old as 65 have become fixtures on the city's sports fields, competing in leagues whose games are played as early as 8 a.m. or as late as midnight.</p>
        <p>In addition to the traditional leagues, there are now teams reserved for older men and women, lesbians, or gay men.</p>
        <p>While soccer is the most popular sport, particularly among children and young adults, thousands of other people demand field time to play softball, lacrosse, baseball, rugby, cricket, football, field hockey and ultimate Frisbee.</p>
        <p>As new leagues have sprouted, and space on playing fields has become increasingly difficult to get, pickup games have become virtually extinct.</p>
        <p>The competition has pitted adults against children, soccer against baseball, and women against men.</p>
        <p>''We're battling with everyone to get fields -- we're battling with the kids, with women. It's tough out there,'' said Peter Strumpf, president of the Cosmopolitan Soccer League, a men-only group that was founded in 1923 and now has 89 teams and 1,800 players. It's so tough that Cosmopolitan Soccer now competes with its former youth division for time on fields. The two leagues broke ties several years ago.</p>
        <p>The department has tried to meet the demand by building new playing fields and resurfacing others with synthetic turf, which is more durable than grass.</p>
        <p>But the city is having trouble keeping up with the proliferation of leagues filled with children as young as 3 or 4 who, a generation ago, might have waited until they were 7 or 8 to play; with middle-aged men who in years past may have been content to watch sports on television; with women and girls who had been left out of many team sports; and with immigrants who have moved to the city, bringing with them a love for soccer, cricket and baseball.</p>
        <p>Adding to the problem are new schools that lack space for playing fields, forcing their teams to practice in city parks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Benepe said that the Parks Department was in the midst of its largest expansion and improvement of ball fields since the 1930s. There are now about 800 playing fields in the city. The city is adding to that total and renovating others by replacing the grass and asphalt with synthetic turf or installing lights for nighttime play.</p>
        <p>Last month, the Parks Department signed an agreement with some of Manhattan's elite private schools -- including Dalton, Buckley, Spence and Chapin -- under which the schools would pay the city $52.4 million to build or refurbish and maintain 63 playing fields at Randalls Island over a 20-year period. The city would also get a virtual monopoly on two-thirds of the fields during after-school hours.</p>
        <p>Though the deal was criticized by parks advocates and some elected officials as an unfair pay-to-play solution to the playing fields shortage, Mr. Benepe said such private-public ventures are necessary to meet the demand.</p>
        <p>Some recreational leagues say they have given up trying to get Parks Department permits for use of the fields. Instead, they pay as much as $300 an hour to play at private facilities like Chelsea Piers or Asphalt Green on the Upper East Side.</p>
        <p>''It's elitist, ridiculously so, to be paying so much to play a soccer game, but it's so much easier than dealing with the Parks Department to try to get a permit,'' said Abby Lancaster, 26, a publicist who plays in a league that holds games at Asphalt Green.</p>
        <p>For a Parks Department permit, the cost is only $10 for each period of about four hours on an asphalt or concrete field, $16 for grass or turf and $32 for a field with lights. But it can take months to obtain one.</p>
        <p>The Parks Department prefers that groups file permit requests over the Internet, but most still submit paper forms. Any group that has held a permit for a certain field on a particular day has priority to use the same field the following year. Children's groups get priority over adult leagues, women's groups over men's, and organized groups over individuals.</p>
        <p>''The Parks Department says kids come first, women second, and then you,'' said Mr. Strumpf, the president of the men's soccer league.</p>
        <p>For Michael Harris, who founded a youth baseball program in Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn, five years ago, permits are a recent concern. When he started, only 15 children showed up to play and basketball was king among neighborhood sports. Baseball wasn't even on the map.</p>
        <p>But when Mr. Harris's Inner City Sports League starts the season this month, its roster will include 300 boys playing on 22 baseball teams, and 60 girls on 4 softball teams.</p>
        <p>The league has become so popular that 14-year-olds must try out for teams because there is not enough field space for everyone to play, and the youngest teams will be forced to play on Sunday mornings.</p>
        <p>''The problem is there's only one baseball field in Bed-Stuy, and we have to share it,'' Mr. Harris said. ''We're going to try to accommodate as best we can. Space is always going to be a problem.''</p>
        <p>In Manhattan, Dr. Gavril Pasternak, co-founder of Doc's NYC Youth Lacrosse League, is also trying to make the best out of unexpected success: Having too many players show up for a little-known sport.</p>
        <p>The league, now in its 12th season, has more than 200 players. The search for playing space for games and practices has come to dominate much of the league's time, taking players to fields from Randalls Island off the East Side of Manhattan to Riverdale in the western Bronx.</p>
        <p>''What I think is unfair is the total domination of all the fields by soccer -- and it's not just a season, it's year-round,'' said Dr. Pasternak, who played on three national championship lacrosse teams at Johns Hopkins University in Baltimore in the late 1960s. ''Basically, they become their private fields.''</p>
        <p>Space is so tight that six lacrosse teams, with about 150 children, must practice on one field at the same time, Dr. Pasternak said.</p>
        <p>Officials' concern about preserving the condition of the fields contributes to the problem, he said.</p>
        <p>''If it rains the day before, they cancel the games,'' Dr. Pasternak said. ''What is the purpose of having a field if you don't let people use them? The fields sit there idle because they don't want to mess up the grass. They don't worry about the kids. They're worried about the grass.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Benepe, who remembers when asphalt fields were the rule rather than the exception in the city, said that building new playing fields and improving others created a Catch-22.</p>
        <p>''The irony is that the better job we do, the more people want to stay here, which will make the demand go up,'' he said. ''But I honestly think that with all we're doing, we'll one day be able to meet the demand, and I hope to have a superfluity of fields where you can go out there and play pickup games.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 5, 2007, Thursday  An article on Sunday about a shortage of playing fields for organized sports leagues in New York City referred incorrectly to an agreement between the city and some elite private schools regarding 63 playing fields on Randalls Island. The schools -- not the city -- would also get a virtual monopoly on two-thirds of the fields during after-school hours for 20 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 5, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article on Sunday about a shortage of playing fields for organized sports leagues in New York City referred incorrectly to an agreement between the city and some elite private schools regarding 63 playing fields on Randalls Island. The schools -- not the city -- would also get a virtual monopoly on two-thirds of the fields during after-school hours for 20 years.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
