<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Housing Land Trust</title>
    <meta content="WE--Housing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/opinion/WEHousing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837201"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Westchester"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spano, Andrew J (County Exec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Spano, Andrew J</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06EEDA1030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="535" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Housing Land Trust</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Housing Land Trust</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial praises Westchester County Executive Andrew Spano's call for creation of Housing Land Trust; parcels would be bought by county and transferred to nonprofit organization, which would lease them to developers on condition that units built on them be priced affordably in perpetuity</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Residents of Westchester can always mark the arrival of spring by the emergence of the annual crop of initiatives in County Executive Andrew Spano's State of the County address.</p>
        <p>They pop up like crocuses -- small and colorful and impossible to dislike. This year's batch included the announcement that the county's new weapon against identity theft -- the ShredMobile, a paper shredder mounted in a truck -- had driven around and destroyed more than 12 tons of confidential household documents, and the news that the county would be giving away 5,000 energy-saving light bulbs in honor of Earth Day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Few problems in the New York region are more pressing than the cost of housing, and few seem more intractable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Residents of Westchester can always mark the arrival of spring by the emergence of the annual crop of initiatives in County Executive Andrew Spano's State of the County address.</p>
        <p>They pop up like crocuses -- small and colorful and impossible to dislike. This year's batch included the announcement that the county's new weapon against identity theft -- the ShredMobile, a paper shredder mounted in a truck -- had driven around and destroyed more than 12 tons of confidential household documents, and the news that the county would be giving away 5,000 energy-saving light bulbs in honor of Earth Day.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Spano's speech on March 22 also included something bigger, bolder and more interesting than usual, a proposal that deserved closer scrutiny than it got. That was his announcement that the county would help to create an affordable-housing land trust.</p>
        <p>Few problems in the New York region are more pressing than the cost of housing, and few seem more intractable. Westchester, with a tight housing market and high tax burden, is an acutely unaffordable place to live. Despite the best efforts of people like Mr. Spano to invite, cajole or tempt developers to build lots of units that middle-class people can afford, the market has not responded.</p>
        <p>The county, in fact, may even be losing ground, Mr. Spano said, noting that the supply of government-subsidized Mitchell-Lama housing was steadily dwindling. These are units built under a 1950's state law that gave substantial financial breaks to developers who supplied apartments for low- and moderate-income New Yorkers. Tens of thousands of such units were built, with restrictions that they be kept affordable for decades. Now, however, landlords of these aging properties are exercising their right to opt out of the system -- forgoing tax breaks in return for the ability to charge market rents, or converting their units to high-priced condominiums. Thousands of residents are thus facing the looming possibility of being priced out of an ever-shrinking rental market.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spano is looking for a way to shelter affordable units from market forces forever. Under his proposal, parcels would be bought by the county and transferred to a nonprofit organization, the Housing Land Trust, which would lease them to developers on the condition that the units built on them be priced affordably in perpetuity. This tactic has been used on a modest scale by private, nonprofit organizations and cities. But Mr. Spano says his proposal -- a county-run land trust made up of parcels scattered over a wide area -- is the first of its kind in New York State.</p>
        <p>The challenge Mr. Spano faces, of course, is making the proposal reach critical mass, to build an entity big enough to avoid being a small-bore curiosity. That is why he also urged local communities to consider donating land to the trust. Those who do would be endorsing Mr. Spano's laudable conviction that the highest and best use of a given parcel of land may not be one more Westchester McMansion for a hedge-fund manager, but a half-dozen units, say, for regular people -- the teachers, firefighters, young couples and retirees who are increasingly unable to find a place to live in a county they would so love to call home.</p>
        <p>Westchester</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
