<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PBS Buys a Lot Of Arguments For $20 Million</title>
    <meta content="01jens" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/arts/television/01jens.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837169"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Public Broadcasting Service (PBS)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jensen, Elizabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perle, Richard</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">America At A Crossroads (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Public Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Public Broadcasting Service</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403EFDE1030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1537" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PBS Buys a Lot Of Arguments For $20 Million</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">PBS Buys a Lot of Arguments for $20 Million</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH JENSEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jensen, Elizabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on new 11-part PBS series America At A Crossroads, meant to encourage debate over contentious post-9/11 issues; episode entitled The Case For War, in which Bush adviser Richard Perle presents his arguments in favor of invading Iraq, proved most controversial; political infighting at PBS, questions over who had final film editing rights and appropriateness of such material for PBS discussed; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LAST August, Richard N. Perle, the former Bush administration adviser who advocated strongly for the Iraq invasion, found himself surrounded by antiwar demonstrators on the Mall in front of the Washington Monument.</p>
        <p>He didn't want to be there, but for ''The Case for War,'' a documentary laying out his arguments, his producers insisted that he confront his most emotional critics, with television cameras rolling, to add journalistic balance. He clearly looks uncomfortable in the film, to be shown on PBS in two weeks. ''It wasn't a particularly pleasant experience,'' Mr. Perle said in an interview. ''What you don't see is a long period where they are hurling epithets at me.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a politicized struggle, a series on post-9/11 America arrives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LAST August, Richard N. Perle, the former Bush administration adviser who advocated strongly for the Iraq invasion, found himself surrounded by antiwar demonstrators on the Mall in front of the Washington Monument.</p>
        <p>He didn't want to be there, but for ''The Case for War,'' a documentary laying out his arguments, his producers insisted that he confront his most emotional critics, with television cameras rolling, to add journalistic balance. He clearly looks uncomfortable in the film, to be shown on PBS in two weeks. ''It wasn't a particularly pleasant experience,'' Mr. Perle said in an interview. ''What you don't see is a long period where they are hurling epithets at me.''</p>
        <p>For six consecutive nights beginning April 15 PBS will turn over two hours of prime time to ''America at a Crossroads,'' a series of 11 programs, including Mr. Perle's, meant to engage debate over contentious post-9/11 issues, from the origins of Islamic fundamentalism to the perceived tradeoffs the United States has made between security and liberty.</p>
        <p>Getting past the epithets hasn't been easy. The series was conceived in 2004 by the Corporation for Public Broadcasting, the entity that administers federal money for public radio and television, to prove to Congress that public television was worthy of its more than $300 million annual subsidy. Even now Congress is debating the White House's request to cut public broadcasting's funds by 25 percent.</p>
        <p>The corporation financed the series with $20 million in federal money, an enormous sum for chronically struggling independent filmmakers. But, perhaps inevitably, such a charged project became caught up in the nation's culture wars.</p>
        <p>At a ''Crossroads'' briefing in New York in March 2004 filmmakers angrily vented concerns that the series was being politically manipulated. Their ire was directed at Michael Pack, then the corporation's senior vice president for television. He had been brought in the year before to diversify the voices on public television, a mandate that included financing more conservative programming to balance a lineup that his superiors perceived as overly liberal.</p>
        <p>Skeptical PBS programmers, who have autonomy over their schedule, had to be persuaded to show the series, even as relations with the corporation deteriorated amid revelations that its chairman, Kenneth Y. Tomlinson, had improperly monitored PBS for the political leanings of some guests. Mr. Tomlinson was forced out in November 2005. Delays while a new team did its own due diligence pushed the air date back.</p>
        <p>Given all that was happening behind the scenes, the project was ''inevitably going to be seen in a political context,'' said Robert MacNeil, the longtime PBS journalist.</p>
        <p>Mr. MacNeil was hired to be host of ''Crossroads'' and to add editorial expertise, one of many steps public television officials took to save the investment. The corporation's advisory team of experts was replaced by five new advisers. WETA, the Washington public television station that oversees Ken Burns's documentaries, was brought in to manage the project.</p>
        <p>''I think the genesis of it was distorted, and that was a shame,'' said Jacoba Atlas, an independent producer who was a top PBS programming executive when ''Crossroads'' was developed. ''It did not feel that the genesis of it was organic to the needs of public television,'' she said, but added that ''it has been rescued'' by the WETA team and Mr. MacNeil.</p>
        <p>Of the 440 proposals submitted, some of them solicited by corporation officials, 34 were given production money, and 21 finalists received sums, from $350,000 to more than $1 million. But even more than the money, the issue of who would be given plum access to the public airwaves caused intense debate. Some of the 10 finalists that didn't make the lineup this month will be shown later.</p>
        <p>The series incorporates numerous voices that might not usually be found on public television, including, in an odd twist, President Bush's chief domestic policy adviser, Karl Zinsmeister. He has a producer credit on ''Warriors,'' a sympathetic portrait of soldiers, filmed in Iraq in 2005. Mr. Zinsmeister, an editor at the American Enterprise Institute when the film was commissioned, recused himself from finishing it after his White House appointment last May, turning the production over to his wife, Ann Zinsmeister, and the director Ed Robbins.</p>
        <p>''The Case for War'' survived the gantlet as well, although the British producer who conceived it, Brian Lapping, also recused himself after publicity over his friendship with Mr. Perle.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perle said his critics had a straightforward goal: ''They simply didn't want public television, which they think they own, to do a program that included me.'' He said the film was necessary because ''one of the administration's failures has been a failure to communicate why we went there, what the thinking was behind it.''</p>
        <p>''Now I think it is very hard to have a constructive dialogue,'' he added. ''It has descended into accusations of misrepresentation.''</p>
        <p>In the film he debates forceful opponents of his Iraq reasoning, including Richard C. Holbrooke, former American ambassador to the United Nations, and Abdel Bari Atwan, editor of Al Quds al Arabi, a London-based newspaper. Critics will argue which side is more persuasive, but Mr. Perle has the last word. That was too much for John Schidlovsky, founding director of the International Reporting Project at Johns Hopkins University and one of the ''Crossroads'' outside advisers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schidlovsky resigned from that post in December after the Perle film made the final cut. He did not respond to requests for comment. In an e-mail message to the WETA team he wrote, ''In a series as comprehensive as this nationwide 12-hour production, I believe it is editorially imbalanced for PBS to present only one viewpoint on this important story.''</p>
        <p>Leo Eaton, the series's producer, defended the film's inclusion. ''Whatever one thinks of Perle and of the philosophies that took us into Iraq,'' he said, ''it is a hugely important part of American policy, and I don't think the neoconservative view has ever been put out on American television.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile some Muslim leaders are unhappy about ''Faith Without Fear,'' in which a Canadian journalist, Irshad Manji, gets an hour to outline her call for changes in what she sees as overly monolithic Muslim societies. As in Mr. Perle's film, Ms. Manji's views come with a counterpoint: her observant Muslim mother.</p>
        <p>According to PBS guidelines the ''Crossroads'' producers had no editorial control. ''That doesn't mean they can't make comments,'' said Mr. Robbins, the director of ''Warriors.'' ''And right from the start there was the competition of who was going to be chosen.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Manji engaged in intense debates with WETA and PBS, which cited sensitivity in forbidding her to show some of the Danish editorial cartoons that provoked Muslim riots last year. ''Was that my decision?'' she said. ''Ultimately no.'' But she decided to take a strategic approach: ''Is the message of this film important enough to get out, and if it is, then am I going to throw myself on the sword of a cartoon?''</p>
        <p>Not all the filmmakers were as willing to compromise. Martyn Burke, who didn't make the initial cut -- his work is still in progress -- objected to what he called heavy-handed oversight, including improper interference from one adviser, who was later reprimanded by WETA.</p>
        <p>The styles of the films vary. A two-hour history, ''Jihad: The Men and Ideas Behind Al Qaeda,'' opens the series. ''Operation Homecoming'' is an impressionistic view of war through soldiers' writing. ''Europe's 9/11'' uses re-creations to look at European struggles with extremism. And ''The Muslim Americans'' is as straightforward as its title. Two Newsweek reporters investigate the Muslim Brotherhood from Egypt, and New York Times Television profiles Indonesia, the world's largest Muslim nation.</p>
        <p>Viewers who watch the entire series are ''going to have a much more nuanced view of Islam,'' Mr. MacNeil said. ''I think it's going to perform a valuable service.''</p>
        <p>The new corporation president, Patricia Harrison, interviewed before she made her case for financing to the House Appropriations Committee, said ''Crossroads'' needed to be seen in the context of public broadcasting's wide array of programming. ''We truly are the only place where that viewer or listener gets treated as the citizen they should be, that they are, as opposed to just a consumer all the time,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pack, who left the corporation in February 2006, said in an interview that the final series, with its diversity of voices, ''vindicates the process.'' There was, he said, ''a sort of paranoia that these would all be right-wing shows, that this was part of some conspiracy.''</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, given the long, difficult path for ''Crossroads,'' there are lingering doubts about whether the Corporation for Public Broadcasting, a lightning rod for political controversy, is best suited to initiate similar future projects.</p>
        <p>Geneva Overholser, a Washington-based faculty member of the Missouri School of Journalism, said ''Crossroads'' appeared to be worth the effort. PBS, because of its federal financing, must grapple with issues of journalistic balance that are ''more complex than that of mainstream media,'' she said. But she cautioned public broadcasters to be wary of the constant cries of political bias: ''We've come to a juncture in this country that if we don't charge on despite all the criticism, then we're just not going to have journalism in the public interest.''</p>
        <p>TELEVISION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
