<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TEAMS FOR ALL SEASONS</title>
    <meta content="01buckeyes" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/sports/ncaabasketball/01buckeyes.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837451"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Ohio State University</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Georgetown University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Oden, Greg</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E5DC1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="825" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TEAMS FOR ALL SEASONS</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Timing Is Perfect for Oden and Buckeyes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETE THAMEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Thamel, Pete</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, March 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Georgetown Coach John Thompson III and Ohio State Coach Thad Matta say they do not use a handbook when managing players in foul trouble.</p>
        <p>In Ohio State's 67-60 victory before a crowd of 53,500 at the Georgia Dome on Saturday, Matta said that he went with what he called his ''gut feeling'' when dealing with star center Greg Oden's foul trouble.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ohio State Coach Thad Matta’s patience in substituting led to the defining swing in top-seeded Ohio State’s victory against Georgetown in the national semifinals on Saturday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Georgetown Coach John Thompson III and Ohio State Coach Thad Matta say they do not use a handbook when managing players in foul trouble.</p>
        <p>In Ohio State's 67-60 victory before a crowd of 53,500 at the Georgia Dome on Saturday, Matta said that he went with what he called his ''gut feeling'' when dealing with star center Greg Oden's foul trouble.</p>
        <p>Matta has had plenty of opportunities to consult that feeling during the N.C.A.A. tournament. Oden has struggled with foul trouble, and Matta has been judicious about reinserting him into the game.</p>
        <p>On Saturday, Matta's patience and his feeling were on point. With the score tied at 44-44 with 8 minutes 50 seconds left in the game, Matta had Oden sitting on the bench with three fouls when Georgetown's star center, Roy Hibbert, picked up his fourth on a foolish hold to prevent a long rebound.</p>
        <p>Matta immediately put Oden back in the game, and he hit a hook shot in the lane that sparked a 7-0 Ohio State run. The cushion from that run allowed Ohio State to hold on and win, as Georgetown never cut the lead below 4 the rest of the way.</p>
        <p>''I think people think I have this master plan in my mind,'' Matta said after the game. ''It's a gut feeling.''</p>
        <p>Ohio State (35-3) has won 22 consecutive games and will be playing in its first national title game since 1962. On Monday night, the Buckeyes will play the Florida Gators, who won the tournament last year, for the championship.</p>
        <p>Mike Conley Jr. led Ohio State with 15 points. All of Oden's 13 points came in the second half. Because of early foul trouble, he played less than three minutes in the first half.</p>
        <p>Hibbert scored 19 points in 24 minutes to lead Georgetown, which also got 19 points from Jonathan Wallace.</p>
        <p>The Hoyas' season ended short of the championship game because they got no points from their bench players, the star forward Jeff Green took only five shots, and they turned the ball over 14 times.</p>
        <p>''We turned the ball over at key times, which is not indicative of how this team plays,'' Thompson said. ''You have to give credit to them for that.''</p>
        <p>That defining 7-0 Buckeyes run with Hibbert out of the game provided a good synopsis of Georgetown's ills. Oden's hook over Green started the spurt, as Georgetown (30-7) struggled to stop Oden. The next Ohio State baskets came after Georgetown missed 3-point attempts, as the Buckeyes flourished in transition. Ohio State outscored Georgetown by 14-4 in fast-break points.</p>
        <p>The play that led to the final point of the run was one that is likely to be memorable. The 7-foot Oden took off from a few feet inside the free-throw line and tried to dunk over the 6-foot-9 Green. Oden did not score on the drive, but the effort, athleticism and subsequent jarring collision showed just how devastating he can be on the basketball court.</p>
        <p>''I was out for 17 minutes,'' Oden said. ''I wanted to get in there and just tear the rim down.''</p>
        <p>What may be lost in the reshowing of that highlight is that the referee Ted Valentine appeared to make a bad call, as Green's feet looked well planted in the lane as he absorbed the blow.</p>
        <p>After Georgetown cut the lead to 4 points with less than three minutes remaining, Green again ended up on the wrong side of a call by Valentine. This time, Green was whistled for an offensive foul with 2:32 remaining. Oden rolled in a 12-foot jumper on the subsequent possession, and Georgetown never threatened again.</p>
        <p>''Those were calls that the referee made,'' Green said. ''I'm just going to live with it.''</p>
        <p>Green finished with 9 points and 12 rebounds in 40 minutes, but his meager shot total was the most striking element of the way he played. Green's lack of assertiveness was especially surprising considering that Oden played only 20 minutes, meaning there was more room for Green to operate in the lane.</p>
        <p>While Oden finished the game with a flourish, Conley kept the Buckeyes in the game after Oden went to the bench after picking up two offensive fouls before three minutes had passed in the first half. Conley, a freshman who was Oden's high school teammate, scored 11 first-half points and displayed his typical aplomb in managing the game. He had six assists and one turnover in a game in which the Buckeyes only had eight turnovers as a team.</p>
        <p>''His poise is terrific,'' Thompson said of Conley. ''I mean, he just has an uncanny feel for the game and how to manage the game, how to manage his teammates.''</p>
        <p>Matta said after the game that the first time he saw Conley play, he knew he was the perfect point guard for his system.</p>
        <p>As the result of Saturday's game shows, good things happen when Matta listens to his gut.</p>
        <p>N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
