<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Billionaire Beachcombers</title>
    <meta content="01malibu" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/fashion/01malibu.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837332"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions/Western States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Malibu</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Malibu (Calif)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E5D81130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1295" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Billionaire Beachcombers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Billionaire Beachcombers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURA M. HOLSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holson, Laura M</byline>
      <dateline>MALIBU, CALIF.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE two newest beachfront hoteliers here made their fortunes separately, one in computers, the other promoting Cher and Joni Mitchell.</p>
        <p>Larry Ellison, the chief executive of the software giant Oracle and the world's 11th-richest man, according to Forbes magazine, recently bought the 21-room Casa Malibu Inn on Carbon Beach for $20 million. A few blocks away, David Geffen, a friend of Mr. Ellison's, with whom he owns a yacht, will reopen the Malibu Beach Inn, which the mogul is turning into a 47-room luxury hotel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Malibu, Calif., pushing millionaires aside and rebuilding the beachfront.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE two newest beachfront hoteliers here made their fortunes separately, one in computers, the other promoting Cher and Joni Mitchell.</p>
        <p>Larry Ellison, the chief executive of the software giant Oracle and the world's 11th-richest man, according to Forbes magazine, recently bought the 21-room Casa Malibu Inn on Carbon Beach for $20 million. A few blocks away, David Geffen, a friend of Mr. Ellison's, with whom he owns a yacht, will reopen the Malibu Beach Inn, which the mogul is turning into a 47-room luxury hotel.</p>
        <p>Why these two friendly rivals are spending what some describe as ''couch change'' on chaise longues and 500-thread-count linens has left many locals scratching their heads.</p>
        <p>''The word gentrification is used when wealthy people move into a new neighborhood and fix it up,'' said Richard Riordan, the former Los Angeles mayor whose mansion on Carbon Beach is steps away from the weekend homes of Terry Semel, the chief executive of Yahoo, and Jeffrey Katzenberg, a movie executive and a friend of Mr. Geffen's. ''But when it is billionaires taking over from multimillionaires, I'm not sure what you call that.''</p>
        <p>Friends of Mr. Geffen and Mr. Ellison said that each man wanted to create a resort they might frequent themselves, in a seaside colony that was the birthplace of California surf culture and more recently has been a weekend retreat for Hollywood power brokers. Twenty-five miles from Beverly Hills, moguls stroll the white sand along Carbon Beach and sometimes gather at ''Dealmakers' Rock,'' an outcropping where movie deals are said to have been made.</p>
        <p>Only the very wealthy -- and those who bought years ago -- can afford Malibu today. Property prices along the coast have increased 15 to 20 percent since 2005, according to real estate brokers.</p>
        <p>And commercial rents are rising, too. So much so that Wolfgang Puck, the celebrity chef famous for his Spago culinary empire, said he shut down his Malibu eatery, Granita, two years ago because the rent was too high.</p>
        <p>''I think it's great that someone like Larry Ellison comes in,'' Mr. Puck said. ''If he is going to park his yacht there, it will be the new Hamptons. For a while Malibu was hot. Then everyone went to the Hamptons. Maybe it is going to be hot again.''</p>
        <p>Outside the unfinished three-story Malibu Beach Inn, which Mr. Geffen bought for $29 million in 2005, a sign reads, ''The Real Malibu Experience Is Coming.'' Under tarp and scaffolding, the bare wood frame is visible. Richard Sherman, the chief financial officer of David Geffen Company, who is overseeing the renovation, said the billionaire spent tens of millions of dollars remodeling, attracted by the location. Mr. Geffen, who recently sought to buy The Los Angeles Times for $2 billion, lives in a gray and white Cape Cod-style beachfront compound a 20-minute walk south.</p>
        <p>''There will be new everything,'' Mr. Sherman said. ''It's going to be luxurious and appropriate for Malibu -- casual and comfortable.''</p>
        <p>Presumably, it will be the kind of hotel Mr. Geffen's rich out-of-town friends are likely to visit. A night's stay won't be cheap; a 600-square-foot oceanfront suite will go for $850 in July. Rooms will have a 32-inch flat screen television and interactive touch screen telephone.</p>
        <p>The restaurant will serve only hotel guests and their invitees. And Mr. Sherman said they plan to open the Carbon Beach Club, a members-only club to give those who are not guests access to the hotel restaurant and the beachfront patio.</p>
        <p>Irene Dazzan-Palmer, a Malibu real estate agent and longtime resident, said the new hotels and restaurants had pros and cons. But of Mr. Geffen and Mr. Ellison, she added, ''At least these people who bought are classy.''</p>
        <p>She, like many residents, wants Malibu to retain its offbeat charm. Here the local Nobu, part of the expensive Japanese sushi empire, is found in a shopping plaza on the same stretch of Pacific Coast Highway where a storefront spiritual adviser charges $20 for a palm reading. ''We don't want it to be the new Newport Beach,'' said Ms. Dazzan-Palmer, referring to the nouveau riche Orange County town better known for its cookie-cutter mansions and airport-size malls. ''We like it the way it is.''</p>
        <p>Compared with Mr. Geffen, Mr. Ellison is a newcomer to Malibu, although he has been on something of a spending spree. Besides the Casa Malibu Inn, he bought five adjacent houses for an estimated $65 million along Carbon Beach. He is unlikely to remodel Casa Malibu soon; the people who manage it have a lease. And unlike the Malibu Beach Inn, Casa Malibu caters to a less affluent crowd. Garden-view rooms rent for as little as $99 a night in the spring while the Catalina Suite, where Lana Turner stayed, goes for $269. But two restaurants next door that Mr. Ellison also owns -- the Windsail, purchased in 2003, and the PierView Café acquired a year later -- are another story. Recently he won approval to demolish the restaurants and build two new ones.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ellison, who lives in Silicon Valley, declined to comment for this article, but Scott Mitchell, the architect hired to rebuild the restaurants, who referred to Mr. Ellison as ''the client,'' said they talked frequently.</p>
        <p>''It's usually in person,'' Mr. Mitchell said. ''I drive up to the Bay Area or we meet in Malibu a lot.''</p>
        <p>Since Mr. Ellison bought the restaurants, Mr. Mitchell said, he has hired 35 consultants to review the plans, including spending $1,200 for a butterfly consultant who examined a small grove of eucalyptus trees that needed to be removed.</p>
        <p>The plans for the site of the PierView Café allow for a two-story beach-house-style restaurant with a wraparound porch, which has caused locals to speculate that the Ivy, a fixture of Beverly Hills, was moving in. ''That was two rumors ago,'' Mr. Mitchell said, laughing, adding that the design will change once there is a tenant.</p>
        <p>Whatever the gossip about the PierView Café, it is the former Windsail restaurant that has caused the bigger ruckus. Malibu City Council meetings are rarely the stuff of community dissent, but last month it argued over a provision that would have forced Mr. Ellison to abide by an agreement made by the Windsail's previous owner to donate $400,000 to the local school district and allow for a community center on the site. In the end, Mr. Ellison's plan to build a restaurant, not a community center, was approved.</p>
        <p>''Nobody likes change,'' said Ken Kearsley, Malibu's mayor (and a surfer), who voted against Mr. Ellison.</p>
        <p>He looked out the window at the bay where Mr. Ellison now sometimes parks his 192-foot yacht, Ronin. ''Have you seen Larry Ellison's aircraft carrier out there?'' he asked. ''Nothing is forever.''</p>
        <p>According to plans, the restaurant will be a 5,904-square-foot Japanese theme with floor-to-ceiling windows, Australian tea trees and an exterior made of wood. Mr. Mitchell said his client hopes to build a 40-foot-long glass-walled indigenous tide pool, which will be designed by the same people who modeled the Monterey Bay Aquarium. Many residents expect Nobu to move in once both restaurants are finished as early as summer 2008. Mr. Mitchell would not comment.</p>
        <p>''The mayor is in a hard spot because he wants to keep the Old World charm, but at the same time he's got rich people pounding him,'' said Jefferson Wagner, a 50-something Clint Eastwood look-alike who owns the Zuma Jay surf shop across the highway from Casa Malibu.</p>
        <p>''There are two feelings out here. There are the profit people, the realtors and the mortgage brokers. For them it creates a lot of work. And then there are the bleached blue jeans people like me. I've got a wallet. But who wants to pay $40 for a piece of sushi? Not you and me.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
