<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BASEBALL PREVIEW: N.L.</title>
    <meta content="01nleast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837442"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Philadelphia Phillies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Florida Marlins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Washington Nationals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Houston Astros</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cincinnati Reds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Milwaukee Brewers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Dodgers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Diego Padres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Colorado Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Arizona Diamondbacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E7DC1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="3136" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BASEBALL PREVIEW: N.L.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MURRAY CHASS examines the strengths and weaknesses of the National League.</p>
        <p>East</p>
        <p>PROJECTED FINISH  1. METS  2. BRAVES  3. PHILLIES  4. MARLINS  5. NATIONALS</p>
        <p>The rule of thumb for picking the National League East winner was postulated here a year ago: Do not pick against the Atlanta Braves as long as they are defending their title. They did not finish in first place last season, so feel free to look elsewhere for a winner this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MURRAY CHASS examines the strengths and weaknesses of the National League.</p>
        <p>East</p>
        <p>PROJECTED FINISH  1. METS  2. BRAVES  3. PHILLIES  4. MARLINS  5. NATIONALS</p>
        <p>The rule of thumb for picking the National League East winner was postulated here a year ago: Do not pick against the Atlanta Braves as long as they are defending their title. They did not finish in first place last season, so feel free to look elsewhere for a winner this year.</p>
        <p>If you believe Jimmy Rollins, you will pick Philadelphia. Rollins, the Phillies' shortstop, said that the Phillies were the team to beat. It's doubtful that even Phillies fans believe that. General Manager Pat Gillick said he didn't.</p>
        <p>What about the Braves? They have presumably fixed their most glaring problem of last season, their bullpen, and they have some good young players who have sufficient offense. Hmmm. Interesting thought.</p>
        <p>But it's hard to overlook the defending champion Mets, even with their pitching problems. The Mets fell a game short of reaching the World Series last year in part because of pitching injuries, and some of those problems persist.</p>
        <p>Pedro Martínez, recovering from a torn rotator cuff, remains unavailable until sometime in the second half of the season; Orlando Hernández seems to incur an injury every once in awhile; and Duaner Sánchez, who was an outstanding reliever the first half of last season, has a broken bone in his shoulder that could keep him out until at least August.</p>
        <p>A succession of veteran pitchers (Chan Ho Park, Aaron Sele, Jorge Sosa) failed to win starting jobs in spring training, making it easy and necessary for Manager Willie Randolph to write in the names John Maine, Oliver Pérez and the rookie Mike Pelfrey to go with the 41-year-olds Tom Glavine and Hernández.</p>
        <p>Is this any way to win a division title? It's going to have to be, because it says here the Mets should win again. They should win with a glittering lineup that produced one of the highest-scoring offenses in the league last year. If Shawn Green (.257 in 34 Mets games) rediscovers his hitting ability, the offense will be even better.</p>
        <p>The Atlanta Braves scored 15 more runs than the Mets, so they should not be regarded lightly. With the addition of Rafael Soriano and Mike Gonzalez to work in the bullpen with Bob Wickman, the Braves will be dangerous.</p>
        <p>If the new, young right side of the infield, Scott Thorman and Kelly Johnson, hits like Jeff Francoeur and Brian McCann, two even younger players who made impressive debuts two years ago, more danger would lurk in the Braves' dugout.</p>
        <p>The Philadelphia Phillies are not to be ignored, not with Ryan Howard (league-leading 58 homers and 149 runs batted in, to go with a .313 average) and Chase Utley (32, 102, .309). But Howard will get the Barry Bonds treatment -- walk after walk after walk -- and will have to practice patience to avoid those pitching traps.</p>
        <p>When Rollins offered his proclamation, he did so because he was optimistic about the team's new pitchers. He was elated by the addition of two starters, Freddy García (17-9 with the White Sox) and Adam Eaton (7-4 in 13 starts with Texas). The Phillies already had Jamie Moyer, 44, from a trade late last season.</p>
        <p>On second thought, maybe Rollins is just an excitable kind of guy.</p>
        <p>The Florida Marlins became excited about their team last year, winning 78 games despite a major-league-low $15 million payroll, but then they fired Manager Joe Girardi. Now it's up to Fredi González to continue the job Girardi began.</p>
        <p>He will do it with basically the same team Girardi had. The Marlins' payroll may rise because their players will be earning slightly more than they did last year, when many of them were rookies, but the Marlins added almost no one. On the other hand, they lost their closer, Joe Borowski (36 saves), and replaced him with Jorge Julio (16 saves).</p>
        <p>The Washington Nationals lost two hitters, Alfonso Soriano (46 homers, 41 stolen bases) and José Vidro (.289), and two of their starting pitchers, Ramón Ortiz (11-16) and Tony Armas Jr. (9-12), and did not acquire anyone of substance.</p>
        <p>That will not make Manny Acta's first managing job any easier as he replaces Frank Robinson, the team's manager for five years.</p>
        <p>A rookie, Kory Casto, will be among those trying to replace Soriano in left field. Felipe López, acquired from Cincinnati last season, is the second baseman. New starting pitchers? The Nationals' five starters made a total of 36 starts in the majors last season.</p>
        <p>HEAVY HITTERS</p>
        <p>Scoring was no problem for the Phillies (865 runs), Braves (849) and Mets (834) last year; they were the top three teams in the league. CHASE UTLEY led the N.L. in runs.</p>
        <p>METS  2006: 97-65, first place</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Carlos Delgado  2B José Valentín  SS José Reyes  3B David Wright  LF Moises Alou  CF Carlos Beltrán  RF Shawn Green  C Paul Lo Duca  SP Tom Glavine  Pedro Martínez (d.l.)  Orlando Hernández  John Maine  Oliver Pérez  Mike Pelfrey*  Closer Billy Wagner</p>
        <p>ATLANTA BRAVES  2006: 79-83, third</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B S. Thorman/C. Wilson  2B Kelly Johnson  SS Édgar Rentería  3B Chipper Jones  LF R. Langerhans/M. Diaz  CF Andruw Jones  RF Jeff Francoeur  C Brian McCann  SP John Smoltz  Tim Hudson  Chuck James  Lance Cormier  Mark Redman  Mike Hampton (d.l.)  Closer Bob Wickman</p>
        <p>PHILADELPHIA PHILLIES  2006: 85-77, second</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Ryan Howard  2B Chase Utley  SS Jimmy Rollins  3B Wes Helms  LF Pat Burrell  CF Aaron Rowand  RF Shane Victorino  C Rod Barajas  SP Brett Myers  Cole Hamels  Freddy García  Adam Eaton  Jamie Moyer  Closer Tom Gordon</p>
        <p>FLORIDA MARLINS  2006: 78-84, fourth</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Mike Jacobs  2B Dan Uggla  SS Hanley Ramírez  3B Miguel Cabrera  LF Josh Willingham  CF Alejandro De Aza*  RF Joe Borchard  Jeremy Hermida (d.l.)  C Miguel Olivo  SP Dontrelle Willis  Aníbel Sánchez  Scott Olsen  Ricky Nolasco  Sergio Mitre  Closer Jorge Julio</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON NATIONALS  2006: 71-91, fifth</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Dmitri Young  Nick Johnson (d.l.)  2B Felipe López  SS Cristian Guzmán  3B Ryan Zimmerman  LF Ryan Church/Kory Casto*  CF Nook Logan  RF Austin Kearns  C Brian Schneider  SP John Patterson  Jerome Williams  Matt Chico  Jason Bergmann  Shawn Hill  Closer Chad Cordero  *-Rookie</p>
        <p>Central</p>
        <p>PROJECTED FINISH  1. CARDINALS  2. BREWERS  3. ASTROS  4. CUBS  5. PIRATES  6. REDS</p>
        <p>For a team that was supposed to be the next World Series champion, the Chicago Cubs were embarrassingly bad last year. Instead of following the Red Sox and the White Sox as champions after long droughts, the Cubs created the league's worst record.</p>
        <p>How embarrassed were the Cubs? They were so embarrassed they spent as they had never spent before. Start with $136 million for Alfonso Soriano and go from there.</p>
        <p>The Cubs, a fiscally conservative organization, signed Soriano, a second baseman turned left fielder, and pronounced him their center fielder. They signed Mark DeRosa to play second base. They signed Cliff Floyd to share playing time in left field. They signed Ted Lilly and Jason Marquis to be their Nos. 2 and 3 starting pitchers, giving Lilly an eyebrow-raising $10 million a year.</p>
        <p>That's $10 million a year for a pitcher with a 59-58 career record who has never won more than two games more than he lost in a season. Marquis got only $7 million a year for his 56-52 record, though he has a winning record only once in six full seasons. He pitched so poorly last season (14-16, 6.02 earned run average) that he was left off the St. Louis Cardinals' World Series roster.</p>
        <p>The Cubs have become a managers' graveyard, and Dusty Baker was the latest to be buried at Wrigley Field. Lou Piniella began whistling as soon as he was named the new manager.</p>
        <p>At the opposite end of the division from the Cubs, the St. Louis Cardinals won only 83 games, but they also won the World Series.</p>
        <p>The Cardinals will try to do it again with a revamped rotation. Jeff Suppan, Jeff Weaver and Marquis are gone. Mark Mulder is recovering from shoulder surgery and will miss a good portion of the season. Chris Carpenter and Anthony Reyes are the holdovers, Kip Wells (1-5, 6.69) is a newcomer via free agency and Adam Wainwright and Braden Looper are recruits from the bullpen.</p>
        <p>Wainwright was the postseason closer last season after Jason Isringhausen had hip surgery, and Looper has never started a game in 572 major league appearances.</p>
        <p>Roger Clemens has started 690 games, 84 for the Houston Astros the past three years. But while the Astros await their Clemens fix this year, they may figure out how to score more runs. Their inability to score cost them a spot in the playoffs last year.</p>
        <p>They spent $100 million for Carlos Lee's potent bat. Last year Lee had career highs of 37 home runs and 116 runs batted in, making it the fourth successive season he had hit more than 30 homers. The Astros also added infielder Mark Loretta, who has a .299 career batting average and hit .424 in 21 games for Houston in 2002.</p>
        <p>The Cincinnati Reds were the division's biggest surprise last year, standing only a percentage point from first place Aug. 24 before slipping and finishing three and a half games from the top.</p>
        <p>They have already sprung their surprise this year. They have moved Ken Griffey Jr. to right field and put Ryan Freel in center. Griffey, who was 19 years old when he began playing in the majors and has somehow become 37, has just finished recovering from a broken wrist, his eighth serious injury since he joined the Reds in 2000.</p>
        <p>The Milwaukee Brewers could use surprises for their offense, defense and pitching. They were in the lower strata in all three phases last year, which explains why they dropped back under .500 (75-87) after finishing at .500 following 12 consecutive losing seasons.</p>
        <p>They traded one of their best pitchers, Doug Davis, for a good-hitting catcher, Johnny Estrada (.302), and signed Suppan to replace Davis. They have also moved Bill Hall, their best run producer (35 homers, 85 R.B.I.), to center field from shortstop.</p>
        <p>While the Brewers are no longer burdened by a long streak of consecutive losing seasons, the Pittsburgh Pirates enter the season with their streak intact at 14.</p>
        <p>But the Pirates think they are on the right track. They finished last season with a 37-35 record in their last 72 games after a 30-60 start, and they had a 16-6 record in their last 22 one-run games after being 8-25 in their first 33.</p>
        <p>One of their biggest problems was a lack of a strong left-handed hitter, and they may have corrected it with the acquisition of first baseman Adam LaRoche, who hit 32 homers and drove in 90 runs for the Braves last season.</p>
        <p>A DROUGHT IN PITTSBURGH</p>
        <p>After winning three straight division titles from 1990 to '92, the Pirates have had 14 consecutive losing seasons. JASON BAY has been a bright spot with 30-homer seasons in 2005 and 2006.</p>
        <p>ST. LOUIS CARDINALS  2006: 83-78, first</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Albert Pujols  2B Adam Kennedy  SS David Eckstein  3B Scott Rolen  LF Chris Duncan  CF Jim Edmonds  RF Spiezio/Taguchi/Wilson  Juan Encarnación (d.l.)  C Yadier Molina  SP Chris Carpenter  Kip Wells  Adam Wainwright  Anthony Reyes  Braden Looper  Mark Mulder (d.l.)  Closer Jason Isringhausen</p>
        <p>MILWAUKEE BREWERS  2006: 75-87, fourth</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Prince Fielder  2B Rickie Weeks  SS J. J. Hardy  3B Counsell/Graffanino  Corey Koskie (d.l.)  LF G. Jenkins/K. Mench  CF Bill Hall  RF Corey Hart  C Johnny Estrada  SP Chris Capuano  Ben Sheets  Jeff Suppan  Dave Bush  Claudio Vargas  Closer Francisco Cordero</p>
        <p>HOUSTON ASTROS  2006: 82-80, second</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Lance Berkman  2B Craig Biggio  SS Adam Everett  3B Morgan Ensberg  LF Carlos Lee  CF Chris Burke  RF Jason Lane/Luke Scott  C Brad Ausmus  SP Roy Oswalt  Jason Jennings  Woody Williams  Wandy Rodríguez  Fernando Nieve  Closer Brad Lidge</p>
        <p>CHICAGO CUBS  2006: 66-96, sixth</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Derrek Lee  2B Mark DeRosa  SS César Izturis  3B Aramis Ramírez  LF Matt Murton/Cliff Floyd  CF Alfonso Soriano  RF Jacque Jones  C Michael Barrett  SP Carlos Zambrano  Ted Lilly  Jason Marquis  Rich Hill  Wade Miller  Closer Ryan Dempster</p>
        <p>PITTSBURGH PIRATES  2006: 67-95, fifth</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Adam LaRoche  2B Freddy Sanchez  SS Jack Wilson  3B José Bautista  LF Jason Bay  CF Chris Duffy  RF Xavier Nady  C Ronny Paulino  SP Zach Duke  Ian Snell  Paul Maholm  Tom Gorzelanny  Tony Armas Jr.  Closer Salomón Torres</p>
        <p>CINCINNATI REDS  2006: 80-82, third</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Scott Hatteberg  2B Brandon Phillips  SS Álex González  3B Edwin Encarnación  LF Adam Dunn  CF Ryan Freel  RF Ken Griffey Jr.  C David Ross  SP Aaron Harang  Bronson Arroyo  Eric Milton  Kyle Lohse  Matt Belisle  Closer Dustin Hermanson  *-Rookie</p>
        <p>West</p>
        <p>PROJECTED FINISH  1. DODGERS  2. PADRES  3. GIANTS  4. DIAMONDBACKS  5. ROCKIES</p>
        <p>For this division, off-season activity seemed to be a ceaseless whirlwind of activity, a spirited game of ''Can You Top This?''</p>
        <p>San Diego signs Greg Maddux away from Los Angeles, Los Angeles signs Jason Schmidt away from San Francisco and Randy Wolf away from Philadelphia, San Francisco signs Barry Zito -- for a whopping $126 million, no less. And before the pitching merry-go-round stops, Arizona trades for Randy Johnson and Doug Davis.</p>
        <p>Los Angeles re-signs Nomar Garciaparra and signs Juan Pierre. San Francisco signs Dave Roberts and Bengie Molina. San Diego signs Marcus Giles. And throughout all this, San Francisco re-signs Barry Bonds and re-signs him and re-signs him.</p>
        <p>And to add a special touch to the frenetic activity, the Giants snatch Bruce Bochy from San Diego to manage them after he had managed the Padres for a dozen years.</p>
        <p>None of the teams called a timeout, but at some point everyone gave in to exhaustion and prepared for spring training. Will anyone have anything left for the season?</p>
        <p>Among all the moves, the strangest was Bochy's. Not only had he spent his entire major league managerial career in San Diego, but he had also managed the Padres to the division title the past two seasons and had a long, close relationship with the Padres' general manager, Kevin Towers, who was his minor league teammate.</p>
        <p>His relationship with Towers, however, could not withstand the desire of Sandy Alderson, the team's chief executive, to make a change when Bochy's contract was up. Knowing an extension was not on the horizon, Bochy jumped.</p>
        <p>Now Bud Black, a hotly pursued candidate in recent years, is the rookie manager of the San Diego Padres, who have lost six of seven playoff games against the Cardinals the past two Octobers.</p>
        <p>They have made changes in search of a new outcome. Giles, the younger brother of Padres right fielder Brian Giles, is at second base instead of Josh Barfield; Kevin Kouzmanoff, a rookie with home run potential, is at third, which had several occupants last year; and Terrmel Sledge is in left field in place of Roberts.</p>
        <p>Maddux, a 333-game winner who will be 41 in two weeks, joins a pitching staff that was the league's best last season with the only earned run average under 4.00.</p>
        <p>The Los Angeles Dodgers, who matched the Padres' record but had to settle for the wild card, have changed, too. Schmidt and Wolf join the rotation, and Luis Gonzalez and Pierre make up two-thirds of a new outfield. Pierre made the most outs in the majors last season, but he also had at least 200 hits for the fourth time in his seven-year career.</p>
        <p>The San Francisco Giants have struggled the past two seasons, and that is why they have a bunch of new players -- Rich Aurilia at first, Roberts in center, Molina behind the plate and Zito and Russ Ortiz in the rotation.</p>
        <p>Zito is the centerpiece of the new-look team, a pitcher who has never missed a start and has pitched more than 210 innings in each of his six full seasons.</p>
        <p>But no matter who Zito is or how much his contract is worth, he still takes second billing to Bonds, who needs 22 home runs to become the career leader, no matter how many he might have hit with chemical aid.</p>
        <p>The Giants should be able to compete with the Padres and the Dodgers, but the Arizona Diamondbacks and the Colorado Rockies do not appear to be in their class.</p>
        <p>At age 43 and coming back from back surgery, Johnson may be past his prime, but the Diamondbacks badly need him to provide a spark. A spark could come, too, from shortstop Stephen Drew, the brother of J. D. who hit .316 in 59 games for Arizona last season.</p>
        <p>The Rockies continue to bumble along, having had six successive losing seasons. They have a new center fielder, Willy Taveras, and a rookie shortstop, Troy Tulowitzki, but the same old cast will most likely produce the same old result.</p>
        <p>MARK YOUR CALENDAR</p>
        <p>BARRY BONDS needs 22 home runs to break Hank Aaron's career record of 755. Bonds played in 130 games last season and hit his 22nd on Sept. 4. He had 26 over all.</p>
        <p>LOS ANGELES DODGERS  2006: 88-74, wild card</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Nomar Garciaparra  2B Jeff Kent  SS Rafael Furcal  3B Wilson Betemit  LF Luis Gonzalez  CF Juan Pierre  RF Andre Ethier  C Russell Martin  SP Derek Lowe  Randy Wolf  Jason Schmidt  Brad Penny  Brett Tomko  Closer Takashi Saito</p>
        <p>SAN DIEGO PADRES  2006: 88-74, first</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Adrian Gonzalez  2B Marcus Giles  SS Khalil Greene  3B Kevin Kouzmanoff*  LF Terrmel Sledge/José Cruz  CF Mike Cameron  RF Brian Giles  C Josh Bard  SP Jake Peavy  Chris Young  Clay Hensley  Greg Maddux  David Wells  Closer Trevor Hoffman</p>
        <p>SAN FRANCISCO GIANTS  2006: 76-85, third</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Rich Aurilia  2B Ray Durham  SS Omar Vizquel  3B Pedro Feliz  LF Barry Bonds  CF Dave Roberts  RF Randy Winn  C Bengie Molina  SP Barry Zito  Matt Cain  Matt Morris  Noah Lowry  Russ Ortiz  Closer Armando Benítez</p>
        <p>ARIZONA DIAMONDBACKS  2006: 76-86, fourth (tied)</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Conor Jackson  2B Orlando Hudson  SS Stephen Drew  3B Chad Tracy  LF Eric Byrnes  CF Chris Young*  RF Carlos Quentin  C M. Montero/C. Snyder  SP Brandon Webb  Édgar González  Liván Hernández  Doug Davis  Enrique González  Randy Johnson (d.l.)  Closer José Valverde</p>
        <p>COLORADO ROCKIES  2006: 76-86, fourth (tied)</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Todd Helton  2B Kazuo Matsui  SS Troy Tulowitzki*  3B Garrett Atkins  LF Matt Holliday  CF Willy Taveras  RF Brad Hawpe  C Chris Iannetta*  SP Aaron Cook  Jeff Francis  Rodrigo López  Jason Hirsh*  Josh Fogg  Closer Brian Fuentes</p>
        <p>*-Rookie</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
