<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Big Hispanic Undercount? Town Wants Its Own Tally</title>
    <meta content="01litopicLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/01litopic.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837151"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DEMOGRAPHICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Population</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Census</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Greenport (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kapell, David (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cotroneo, Nicole</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/North Fork</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Population</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Census</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Census</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Population</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E1D61330F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="691" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Big Hispanic Undercount? Town Wants Its Own Tally</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Big Hispanic Undercount? Town Wants Its Own Tally</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICOLE COTRONEO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cotroneo, Nicole</byline>
      <dateline>GREENPORT</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Outgoing Mayor David Kapell of Greenport, NY, announces results of local census which shows 2000 federal census grossly underestimated Hispanic population and did not count many part-time residents; new census reports population at 3,450 and Hispanic full-time residents at 353; total includes 1,000 part-time residents, none of them Hispanic; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH an uncalculated influx of Hispanic immigrants living in a finite pool of affordable housing, the situation in this North Fork village is a common one across Long Island. But a recent response by village government is not.</p>
        <p>Beginning in November, the village dispatched 11 pairs of canvassers, with English and Spanish speakers, to gather data for what Suffolk County officials say they think is the first official census undertaken by a local government within the county.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>GREENPORT.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH an uncalculated influx of Hispanic immigrants living in a finite pool of affordable housing, the situation in this North Fork village is a common one across Long Island. But a recent response by village government is not.</p>
        <p>Beginning in November, the village dispatched 11 pairs of canvassers, with English and Spanish speakers, to gather data for what Suffolk County officials say they think is the first official census undertaken by a local government within the county.</p>
        <p>Mayor David E. Kapell, who will step down this year, has said the census data could help the village better provide services to all residents and plan for the future. Mayor-elect David Nyce said he hoped to use the data to help create a master plan for the village.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kapell publicly announced the results on Tuesday, and the results were in line with his prediction that the 2000 federal census grossly underestimated the Hispanic population in Greenport and did not count many part-time residents.</p>
        <p>The federal census calculated the village's full-time population at 2,048 and Hispanic full-time residents at 353 (17 percent of the total). The new census reports the population at 3,450 and Hispanic residents 730 (or 21 percent of the total). The total includes 1,000 part-time residents, none of them Hispanic.</p>
        <p>Trained village residents collected data from 203 households chosen at random, Mr. Kapell said. The report says the census had a 5 percent margin of error.</p>
        <p>The census was not universally popular. Some Hispanic residents were initially wary. And Steve Levy, the county executive, has condemned Mr. Kapell for taking it on. ''To squander precious funds on those who broke the law to get here seems foolhardy,'' Mr. Levy said when canvassers were sent out in November.</p>
        <p>The project was largely financed by a grant from the Horace Hagedorn Foundation, in Port Washington, which supports initiatives to diminish tensions between citizens and immigrants. The foundation's executive director, Darren Sandow, said it also hired a pollster to analyze the data.</p>
        <p>A week before he went public with the results, Mr. Kapell said in an interview that he saw two accelerating trends. ''One is the conversion of historically year-round residences to part time,'' he said, ''and the other is this influx of largely Hispanic immigrants coming in to provide the labor that would have been lost by the ones who sold out to the part-timers.''</p>
        <p>Those trends will soon lead to a housing crisis, Mr. Kapell said. ''The problem with our real estate economy on the East End is that it's monopolized by people earning Wall Street incomes,'' he said. ''People earning Main Street incomes simply can't compete.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Nyce, who was elected last month to succeed Mr. Kapell, said he did not believe the housing situation had reached a crisis point.</p>
        <p>Sister Margaret Smyth of the North Fork Spanish Apostolate, based in Riverhead, coordinated the canvassing teams, and Antonio Secaida was among her recruits. A Guatemalan immigrant, he has lived in Greenport with his wife and three children for 11 years and became an American citizen in December.</p>
        <p>Immigrants have been wary of participating in federal censuses, he said, because ''they think Immigration will get the census.'' He said he and his neighbors were guaranteed anonymity in the Greenport census.</p>
        <p>Mr. Secaida said that he and his neighbors were assured the data would help the village ''provide better services -- the hospitals and the schools,'' but that he was skeptical.</p>
        <p>Sister Smyth said she was optimistic the data would help the school system determine how many children would enroll in the fall. ''Greenport School has always said that they've been undercounted as far as free lunches were concerned,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kapell said the biggest challenge for the village board in responding to the data was how to embrace the growing Hispanic population.</p>
        <p>''We know that many of these people are undocumented,'' he said. ''Given the fact that they have embedded themselves so completely in our midst, it is now incumbent on village government to pursue policies to promote progress for Latinos.''</p>
        <p>The census was meant to be only the beginning of such an effort, Mr. Sandow said.</p>
        <p>DEMOGRAPHICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
