<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vibrant Food, Energetic Atmosphere</title>
    <meta content="01LIDineLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/01LIDine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837158"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/WESTBURY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chi (Westbury, NY, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starkey, Joanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE0D61330F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="729" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vibrant Food, Energetic Atmosphere</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Vibrant Food, Energetic Atmosphere</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOANNE STARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Starkey, Joanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joanne Starkey reviews Chi restaurant in Westbury, NY; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHI is the Chinese word for energy, and the Westbury restaurant of that name, which opened in November, is filled with it. Don't expect Chinese food, however; the fare is that eclectic assembly of Italian favorites, Asian hits and steaks and chops that is often labeled New American.</p>
        <p>Patrons enter through the active and very attractive bar, with its marble top and pressed-tin ceiling, then are led up a few steps, past a lounge area with leather couches and low tables, to a dining room that shouts ''supper club!'' Here the walls are painted burnt orange or covered with gold leatherlike fabric, and the very comfortable banquettes and chairs are apricot plush.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chi is the Chinese word for energy, and the Westbury restaurant of that name is filled with it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CHI is the Chinese word for energy, and the Westbury restaurant of that name, which opened in November, is filled with it. Don't expect Chinese food, however; the fare is that eclectic assembly of Italian favorites, Asian hits and steaks and chops that is often labeled New American.</p>
        <p>Patrons enter through the active and very attractive bar, with its marble top and pressed-tin ceiling, then are led up a few steps, past a lounge area with leather couches and low tables, to a dining room that shouts ''supper club!'' Here the walls are painted burnt orange or covered with gold leatherlike fabric, and the very comfortable banquettes and chairs are apricot plush.</p>
        <p>Chi is as much a lounge as a restaurant; indeed, the bar is probably the senior partner in the relationship. Diners old enough to remember the Carter administration may not enjoy it. Even though the bar cannot be seen from most tables, the noise generated by the crowd there and the driving beat of the music invade the dining room and make conversation difficult.</p>
        <p>Busboys and waiters get the job done: Water glasses are always full and dishes delivered to the right person, but the service is not polished. Our jocular waiter sometimes crossed the line from friendly to familiar.</p>
        <p>The restaurant pulses with life, and the food is just as vibrant. Among the appetizers, one hit was a special of three sliders -- mini Kobe beef burgers -- each crowned with a small slice of pickled onion and perched on a little bun. They were cooked medium rare and accompanied by three sauces: horseradish cream, chipotle ketchup and aioli.</p>
        <p>Another terrific starter was the shrimp and vegetable tempura: two jumbo shrimp and assorted vegetables in the lightest of batters.</p>
        <p>Yet another Asian delight was a creation called Chino pan. It resembled two giant egg rolls cut on the bias and accompanied by a five-vinegar-ginger-hoisin sauce. It had a tasty filling of spicy sausage, julienned Asian vegetables and bean sprouts.</p>
        <p>A half-rack of Asian ribs was flavorful but not fall-away tender. Grey Goose shrimp translated to a gussied-up shrimp cocktail with the seafood cut into chunks and served in a martini glass. We gave high marks to the gyoza: lump crab and corn in the familiar dumpling wrappers, fried until crisp.</p>
        <p>But lobster bisque was pallid and not nearly creamy enough. The Caesar salad was also anemic.</p>
        <p>The menu's pastas certainly had energy in spades. Linguine Sinatra was sauced with tiny Manila clams in their shells, crumbled spicy sausage, cherry tomatoes, lots of garlic and slices of very hot green chilies. Penne in a pink grappa sauce (similar to a vodka sauce) also hit the spot, with prosciutto, broccolini and chunks of grilled chicken.</p>
        <p>We also liked the cooked-to-order rack of lamb, the fork-tender short ribs braised in red wine and served over a creamy porcini risotto, the moist breast of chicken and the juicy pork chop with creamy polenta. A tender, juicy porterhouse steak, a special at $48, was the highest-priced entree but was deemed worth it by the diner who ordered it. It was crowned with sautéed onions and mushrooms and served with mashed potatoes and asparagus.</p>
        <p>All the desserts made the grade. The very creamy New York-style cheesecake was our favorite; mixed berries in a wineglass topped with whipped cream also made a delicious finale, as did the rich chocolate ganache cake and the mousselike espresso tear, named for its teardrop shape.</p>
        <p>Chi  103 Post Avenue  Westbury  (516) 385-3795  www.chidininglounge.com</p>
        <p>VERY GOOD</p>
        <p>THE SPACE -- Elegant restaurant; popular lounge. Not wheelchair accessible.</p>
        <p>THE CROWD -- Young and lively. Mainly small groups and couples. No children.</p>
        <p>THE BAR -- Where the action is, along with the adjacent lounge. There is a list of 42 wines by the bottle ($28 to $350) and 14 by the glass ($6.50 to $10.50).</p>
        <p>THE BILL -- Dinner entrees, $24 (pasta) to $48. American Express, MasterCard, Visa and Discover are accepted.</p>
        <p>WHAT WE LIKE -- Chino pan, Grey Goose shrimp, shrimp tempura, gyoza, sliders; pork chop, linguine Sinatra, penne in grappa sauce, rack of lamb, short ribs, chicken breast, porterhouse steak; all desserts.</p>
        <p>IF YOU GO -- Dinner: Tuesday to Sunday, 5 to 11 p.m. Bar open till 4 a.m. Reservations are recommended on weekends.</p>
        <p>Reviewed April 1, 2007</p>
        <p>DINING/WESTBURY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
