<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Meadowlands</title>
    <meta content="04well.belgarden.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="T: Design Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="144" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Style; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/style/tmagazine/04well.belgarden.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837085"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Belgium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Belgium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Belgium/Antwerp</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E7D91230F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="627" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Meadowlands</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Meadowlands</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Cathy Horyn</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Horyn, Cathy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Domein hemelrijk is a private garden of more than 250 acres a half hour's drive from Antwerp on the border with the Netherlands. Its name is the merger of the Dutch words for ''sky'' and ''kingdom,'' and certainly in Belgium's lowlands, where everything is flat and there is no break from the drab neatness of centuries-old tree lines and drainage ditches, you have a different feeling when you see sweeping vistas and irregular lines. Hemelrijk is also the romantic result of the union between the late horticulturists Robert De Belder and his wife, Jelena, who, along with Robert's brother, Georges, created this magical place as well as the better-known public arboretum at nearby Kalmthout.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A horticulturist’s paradise in northern Belgium is romantic to its roots. Cathy Horyn digs in.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Domein hemelrijk is a private garden of more than 250 acres a half hour's drive from Antwerp on the border with the Netherlands. Its name is the merger of the Dutch words for ''sky'' and ''kingdom,'' and certainly in Belgium's lowlands, where everything is flat and there is no break from the drab neatness of centuries-old tree lines and drainage ditches, you have a different feeling when you see sweeping vistas and irregular lines. Hemelrijk is also the romantic result of the union between the late horticulturists Robert De Belder and his wife, Jelena, who, along with Robert's brother, Georges, created this magical place as well as the better-known public arboretum at nearby Kalmthout.</p>
        <p>Today, Robert and Jelena's son Daniel De Belder lives at Hemelrijk with his wife, Barbara, and their three children, while Daniel's sister, Diane Van Strydonck, occupies another house on the property with her family. Like his father and his grandfather, Danny, as friends call him, works in the diamond business in Antwerp, returning nightly to Hemelrijk, where he seems only too aware that he is preserving not just one of the great naturalistic gardens, home to 15,000 plants and trees, but also the particular vision of his parents.</p>
        <p>''When my sister and I were young, we always knew it was time to go to bed when my parents came in from the garden,'' Danny said. ''My father would come home from work, and he and my mother would go for a walk. And whenever he traveled for his business, he would bring her a new plant. The garden is really the love story between my parents.''</p>
        <p>I first came to Hemelrijk with the designer Dries Van Noten, in May 2005, and we tramped the fields and the rhododendron-laced woods until dark and then sat down to a delicious meal of asparagus with chopped egg and ham in the De Belders' farmhouse, where Danny, in his seemingly limitless spare time, has created a kind of ''Swiss Family Robinson'' atmosphere with wood milled from fallen trees. Barbara, who works for the antiques dealer and interior designer Axel Vervoordt, brings a sense of harmony to everything. I returned the next spring, my long walks with the De Belders beginning shortly after dawn and resuming after lunch in the kitchen garden, attended by the family's two Jack Russell terriers.</p>
        <p>It's easy to understand why the English landscape designer Russell Page liked to come to Hemelrijk to unwind. The garden is the opposite of control and is, in fact, closer to the looseness and individualistic spirit of 19th-century Romanticism. To see the great collections of beeches, oaks, maples and fruit trees that Robert De Belder assembled and to look across the ponds that he and his brother, Georges, dug in the 1960s is to understand what motivated him. ''Robert was very interested in Rousseau, and a very romantic person,'' Barbara told me. ''He was always setting free the animals. If the dogs were in the house, he let them out. He was the same with people. He gave them ideas, and he set them free.''</p>
        <p>With the nurturing Jelena, who grew up in Serbia, Robert was well matched. ''My father created the vistas and the openings, and my mother furnished them,'' Danny said. ''She was very aware of the light and the canopy and what would grow there. Her vision was to see that plants were happy. My father's vision was to buy a big place.'' He smiled. ''If you're reasonable, you don't do it.'' Hemelrijk is wildly unreasonable, thank God, vast and mysterious, but to come upon a group of apple and cherry trees, their pink canopies as round and gorgeous as a new spring bonnet, is to feel the tug of Jelena's influence.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
