<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Battle for a Mortgage</title>
    <meta content="01cov" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/realestate/01cov.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837233"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haughney, Christine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Subprime Lending</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Foreclosures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreclosures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E6D81030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2116" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Battle for a Mortgage</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Battle for a Mortgage</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTINE HAUGHNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Haughney, Christine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Red flags of any kind on mortgage applications in New York City, even those considered insignificant only months ago, are resulting in delays in approval and higher fees; banks are limiting all types of loans as subprime lending market falls, and are imposing increasingly stringent conditions on applicants; some experts foresee many previously favored applicants being treated as subprime borrowers for fairly common mistakes like not paying some bills on time or carrying high debt; advice on getting credit score; drawing; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS homeowners across the country have dealt with the declining values of their houses and their ballooning mortgage payments, most New Yorkers seem to believe that the market here doesn't play by the same rules.</p>
        <p>But in recent weeks, a growing number of New Yorkers, often with six-figure salaries and reasonably good credit, have begun to find that mortgages are harder to get as lenders try to stem losses from loans to the weakest, or subprime, borrowers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A growing number of New Yorkers, often with six-figure salaries and reasonably good credit, have begun to find that mortgages are harder to get as lenders try to stem losses from loans to the weakest, or subprime, borrowers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS homeowners across the country have dealt with the declining values of their houses and their ballooning mortgage payments, most New Yorkers seem to believe that the market here doesn't play by the same rules.</p>
        <p>But in recent weeks, a growing number of New Yorkers, often with six-figure salaries and reasonably good credit, have begun to find that mortgages are harder to get as lenders try to stem losses from loans to the weakest, or subprime, borrowers.</p>
        <p>While mortgage brokers insist that most buyers in New York can still close deals, they also warn that people with any red flags on their mortgage applications will face delays and will pay higher fees. Potential problems include low credit scores or high credit-card balances or listing a suspiciously high salary for a given job.</p>
        <p>''You're going to pay the piper for any little mistake,'' said Melissa Cohn, the president of Manhattan Mortgage Inc. She said her brokers -- who last year arranged more than $3 billion in mortgages, mainly in New York City -- were spending twice as much time on each application as they did a month ago because of new lending requirements, and she expects the situation only to get worse.</p>
        <p>''The impact is going to be much greater as banks demand that people have clean credit to get the best mortgages,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Buyers like Lee and Kimberly Au had to adjust their expectations. The Aus wanted to buy a one- or two-bedroom condominium costing $800,000 to $1.25 million at the Atelier on West 42nd Street, now that their 8-year-old son has a modeling contract in New York. But they quickly learned that they could no longer get 100 percent financing, even though Dr. Au makes more than $700,000 a year as a surgeon in Hawaii. So the couple settled on a $625,000 studio and used $62,500 in savings for the down payment.</p>
        <p>Eric Eisenberg, the mortgage broker handling the deal, said that even though the Aus put up more cash, the transaction was far more difficult to close than it once would have been.</p>
        <p>''About three weeks ago, I would have gotten this done by snapping my fingers,'' said Mr. Eisenberg, who is the executive vice president of the EFI Capital Corporation, a mortgage brokerage based in Garden City, N.Y. ''Now it's a very lengthy and time-consuming process where every bit of paperwork has to be done to the T. The guidelines are literally changing every hour.''</p>
        <p>Until recently, many New Yorkers found it fairly easy to get mortgages. Then banks that made loans to subprime borrowers started running into trouble when the borrowers found it impossible to pay their mortgages and fell into foreclosure. As a result, banks have cut back on all types of loans.</p>
        <p>Nationally, indicators show that the real estate market is in turmoil. A report issued on March 23 by the National Association of Realtors said that existing home sales in February 2007 jumped 3.9 percent from the month before but were 3.6 percent lower than the same month the year before. A report issued on March 26 by the Commerce Department said that new home sales in February dropped by 18.3 percent from the year before, to a seven-year low.</p>
        <p>In any case, lenders who are experiencing an increase in foreclosures are tightening standards on mortgages across the board.</p>
        <p>''Lenders are going to scrutinize borrowers more carefully'' in the next six to nine months, said Doug Duncan, the chief economist at the Mortgage Bankers Association in Washington. He added, ''The pendulum is probably going to swing too far in the other direction before it settles.''</p>
        <p>That means more New Yorkers are already having to provide more documents to get approvals for all types of mortgages. For example, some brokers who used to get loans approved by lenders without proof of assets from divorces now require the actual decrees. Other mortgage lenders are requiring W-2 forms or pay stubs that they didn't ask for before.</p>
        <p>In one example, Nora Walsh, a loan officer at Preferred Empire Mortgage in Manhattan, spent two weeks trying to get a mortgage for a client who lived in New York City. The client, who would not agree to be interviewed, is the information technology director for a global financial company who was seeking a $550,000 mortgage to buy an apartment in Greenwich Village.</p>
        <p>He had excellent credit and had been working in the industry for 13 years, but the underwriter in Florida who was reviewing the file did not believe that his job would pay $156,000 a year in salary and bonuses.</p>
        <p>Ms. Walsh said that was the first time this question had come up in the last decade. ''They thought his income was exaggerated,'' she said. Getting the question resolved delayed the deal by two weeks.</p>
        <p>Banks are also depending more than ever before on high credit scores before making deals and are even tightening their standards.</p>
        <p>Credit scores typically measure a number of factors, from how promptly borrowers pay their bills to how much credit-card debt they have. The rankings range from 300 to 850. David Strause, a private mortgage banker with Countrywide Financial in New York, said that prime borrowers who can negotiate the best rates typically have scores of 700 or more. Borrowers in the ''Alt-A'' category have mid-tier credit levels, with scores between 620 and 680. Subprime borrowers have scores below 620.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cohn of Manhattan Mortgage said that six months ago she could negotiate mortgages at good rates for borrowers with credit scores of more than 660. That score now has shifted to 700 ''to open any doors,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In many cases, economists say, borrowers are going to be treated like subprime and Alt-A borrowers for what would seem to be fairly common mistakes, like not paying a few bills on time or carrying a lot of debt.</p>
        <p>''One of the myths is that subprime is a province of the poor,'' said Mr. Duncan of the Mortgage Bankers Association. ''Subprime is a province of people who don't manage credit well,'' regardless of their incomes.</p>
        <p>The Aus recently found that their credit scores had slipped into these lower categories. Dr. Au, who has four surgical offices in Hawaii, saw his score dip to a subprime level after he and a relative invested in a project, which Ms. Au would not discuss. She said the relative had missed some payments.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the couple's 8-year-old son, Lee Jr., got a contract with a modeling agency. Since their 26-year-old son, Isaac Calpito, performs in ''Mamma Mia'' on Broadway, and their 17-year-old daughter, Tatiana Echevarria, and 16-year-old daughter, Nataysha Echevarria, hope to pursue Broadway careers, the Aus thought it made sense to buy a Manhattan apartment.</p>
        <p>The Aus tried to tap into the equity in their four-bedroom house in Honolulu or their rental property at Haiku Plantation nearby in Kaneohe, but banks refused to refinance or to lend on these investments.</p>
        <p>The couple are using Ms. Au's credit score, which falls in the Alt-A category, to qualify for a 7.5 percent first mortgage and an 8.5 percent second mortgage.</p>
        <p>''We have a lot of our money tied up in real estate in Hawaii,'' she said. ''I knew we had to find something quick.''</p>
        <p>Some borrowers are trying to beef up their credit scores before applying for mortgages.</p>
        <p>Corey Miller, a technical designer of men's and women's outerwear who makes about $140,000, counting his salary and rental income, bought a three-family house in 2005 in Crown Heights, Brooklyn, with a friend for $525,000.</p>
        <p>At the time, he and his friend were able to get 100 percent financing for the property because Mr. Miller had a credit score of more than 720. After spending nearly $50,000 on renovations -- new floors, kitchens and cabinets -- he signed leases on his two apartments that brought in about $3,000 in monthly income. He and his friend live in the third unit. He then had the property reappraised and found out that its value had risen to $750,000.</p>
        <p>But the $25,000 he charged to five credit cards for the renovation work lowered his credit score to 690, and his prospects for refinancing were diminished. When he tried to refinance the building, applying for a 30-year mortgage for $550,000 at an interest rate of 6.25 percent, his application was rejected.</p>
        <p>His broker, Joe Levy, the president of Middlegate Mortgage in Manhattan, said that Mr. Miller had too much debt on his credit cards and because his was a three-family property, he was applying for an unconventional mortgage.</p>
        <p>So Mr. Miller, who recently received a large tax refund, paid down his credit-card balance to about $15,000. Now he carries a lower ratio of overall debt to available credit. He plans to reapply for a new mortgage when his credit score is updated this month.</p>
        <p>''We're playing the waiting game until April 15,'' he said. ''Then we're going to resubmit.''</p>
        <p>Other borrowers are just taking much longer to get the right deal.</p>
        <p>Last April, Dan Simonette, a labor and employment lawyer, took out a $200,000 second mortgage on his home in Prospect Heights. He wanted to renovate the first floor to make it accessible for his 75-year-old mother, Noreen, who is blind.</p>
        <p>His credit score had dipped to about 500 because of bills incurred in a divorce and the cost of hiring a home attendant for his mother. At the time, Mr. Simonette, who makes more than $100,000 a year, got a second mortgage with an 11.75 percent interest rate from the Emigrant Savings Bank.</p>
        <p>By December, he had improved his credit score slightly and tried to refinance at more than a dozen banks. Early last month, he finally was able to get a 6.8 percent interest rate with Fremont General, a subprime lender based in Santa Monica, Calif. But the day the loan was supposed to close, Fremont said it was selling its subprime business. Mr. Simonette's mortgage ended up being one of the last loans that Fremont executives approved.</p>
        <p>He said that based on his experience, borrowers can expect the application process to take more time than normal. ''It was harder to get answers,'' he said. ''It was harder to get a return call.''</p>
        <p>Others potential buyers are bowing out.</p>
        <p>Since Labor Day, Ellen Kapit, an agent with Sotheby's International Realty in Manhattan, has been trying to sell her two-bedroom co-op in Midtown for $1.375 million so that she can buy a smaller apartment in her building. She has also been trying to sell a house she owns in Southampton for $875,000.</p>
        <p>She found a $995,000 house in Sag Harbor that she thought might be easier to rent out when she wasn't in residence. She wanted to get a 90 percent mortgage until she sold her apartment or the Southampton house, or both. She didn't expect any difficulties, because she has an excellent credit score in the mid-700s and annual income of more than $100,000 a year.</p>
        <p>Her mortgage broker, Lenny Holler, a senior loan officer at Preferred Empire Mortgage in Manhattan, suggested that she take out a ''cross-collateralized loan,'' which means that it would include both Hamptons houses and that the lender could foreclose on both if there were any problems.</p>
        <p>But the lenders wanted to charge more than they would have even a few months ago. Ms. Kapit was to pay about 7.5 percent in interest on the mortgage for the new house and 10.25 percent on a $500,000 bridge loan, plus two percentage points as a closing fee. The points translate to $10,000, meaning her closing costs would total of $29,000.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kapit finally backed out of the deal for the Sag Harbor house until she sells her apartment or her Southampton house.</p>
        <p>''Maybe at that time I won't need to borrow as much,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Your Score</p>
        <p>BORROWERS should know their credit scores before they try to get a loan.</p>
        <p>Credit scores, also known as FICO scores, were developed by the Fair Isaac Corporation, which created a formula to track several years of credit history. Three major credit agencies -- Equifax, TransUnion and Experian -- use this formula to calculate scores. Banks use the scores to decide how much to lend home buyers. The information is available at myfico.com. Requesting one score costs $16.95; getting scores from all three companies is $47.85.</p>
        <p>Borrowers also can request free credit histories once a year at annualcreditreport.com, so that they can check whether any errors have been posted. After navigating through the Web site to get their free credit histories, borrowers can click on links to individual sites to get the credit scores at lower prices than myfico's. Equifax charges $7.95, Experian $5.95 and TransUnion $7.95.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
