<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For a Student of the Arts, a Gallery to Call Her Own</title>
    <meta content="01wepeopleWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/01wepeople.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837193"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CREATIVE LIFE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jewels and Jewelry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Croton-on-Hudson (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rutheny, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hodara, Susan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jewels and Jewelry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jewels and Jewelry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E0DA1030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="630" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For a Student of the Arts, a Gallery to Call Her Own</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For a Student of the Arts, a Gallery to Call Her Own</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN HODARA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hodara, Susan</byline>
      <dateline>CROTON-ON-HUDSON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Jennifer Rutheny, who has converted storefront in Croton-on-Hudson, NY, into studio, gallery, gift shop and classroom for her custom jewelry creations; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the blocklong warehouse district of Croton-on-Hudson, Jennifer Rutheny has converted a 700-square-foot storefront into a space that is part studio, part gallery, part gift shop, part classroom and part showcase for her custom designs.</p>
        <p>At Rutheny's Brook Street Gallery, orchids, day lilies and other lifelike flowers dangle from necklaces and earrings. Butterflies, roses and stones in the colors of the four seasons are set into rings. Pins and pendants take the form of dragonflies, ferns and bees with movable glass wings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An artist in Croton-on-Hudson enjoys gathering people in her creative space.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the blocklong warehouse district of Croton-on-Hudson, Jennifer Rutheny has converted a 700-square-foot storefront into a space that is part studio, part gallery, part gift shop, part classroom and part showcase for her custom designs.</p>
        <p>At Rutheny's Brook Street Gallery, orchids, day lilies and other lifelike flowers dangle from necklaces and earrings. Butterflies, roses and stones in the colors of the four seasons are set into rings. Pins and pendants take the form of dragonflies, ferns and bees with movable glass wings.</p>
        <p>Selected pieces have been featured on NBC's ''Today'' show and in Brides magazine; Lolita Lopez, a WPIX-TV sportscaster, recently wore Ms. Rutheny's jewelry on the air; and the Tarrytown-based environmental organization Riverkeeper has ordered several hundred silver fish pins to give as gifts to alumni at its coming Shad Fest. The pins are based on Hudson River species and were inspired by Ms. Rutheny's boyfriend, Mark Sofranko, a photographer, woodworker and avid fisherman.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rutheny, 35, who lives with Mr. Sofranko in Croton, grew up in Stamford, Conn., and, she said, ''had top-notch parents.'' Her mother, Marcia Taylor, was a metalsmith and is now a ceramicist; her father, Eugene Rutheny, a retired educator, was the chairman of Westchester Community College's biology department for 30 years.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rutheny began making jewelry during high school. She studied art education at SUNY New Paltz and, after graduating, worked simultaneously as an art teacher and an apprentice to jewelers, including David Yurman and Constance Wicklund Gildea.</p>
        <p>For years, she rented a garage near Brook Street, where she refurbished antique jewelry, made customized engagement rings and sold her designs at crafts shows.</p>
        <p>Now, she said, ''I am downsizing the shows and basing myself more in my studio.''</p>
        <p>Her latest creations incorporate jewelry into miniatures. A silver pillbox adorned with turquoise comes with stud earrings that fit through its side and a cover that doubles as a brooch. A two-inch-tall vase holds a bouquet of flower stickpins, and a pair of bird earrings with movable feet perch in a tiny birdbath.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rutheny's work ranges in price from $25, for glass-beaded silver bracelets, to more than $1,000, for gold pieces. She has created lines for Anne Klein and Jones New York, and her jewelry is also sold at galleries in Beacon and Peekskill.</p>
        <p>Her dream, she said, ''is to have my own line at Barneys.''</p>
        <p>Later in the month, Ms. Rutheny will begin using her studio as a classroom, when the weekly metalsmithing classes she has been teaching at the Croton-Cortlandt Center for the Arts relocates to Brook Street.</p>
        <p>Whimsy pervades Ms. Rutheny's year-old gallery, thanks in part to its ever-changing art exhibitions and regular performance events, many featuring the works of local artists. A Hurricane Katrina benefit presenting the work of Laura Ayres, a photographer who recently moved to New Orleans from Croton, is to open on April 14. On April 21, Marcy B. Freedman, a Croton videographer, will be the host of a variety show including music, poetry, video and performance.</p>
        <p>Past exhibits have included the canvases of three Westchester painters, Joe Mullins, Sandy Shapiro and Tom Smith; the sculptural creations of Rob Shepperson and Ed Radford, Croton artists; and an evening of live painting and music by the members of E.Y.E., a Westchester arts collective.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rutheny enjoys gathering people in her creative space. ''I love the energy that is sparked by the various relationships,'' she said, ''artwork with artwork, artist with artist, viewer with artist, and viewer with artwork. ''</p>
        <p>Ms. Freedman called Rutheny's Brook Street Gallery ''a godsend.'' Lora Friedman, a writer and regular patron of the gallery, noted Ms. Rutheny's proclivity for generating connections. ''Croton has long been home to an intellectual and artistic community,'' she said. ''She is helping to spawn its next generation.''</p>
        <p>CREATIVE LIFE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
