<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Season, But Wounds That Are Forever</title>
    <meta content="01roberts" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/sports/baseball/01roberts.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837406"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Selena Roberts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Roberts, Selena</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE6DD1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="997" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Season, But Wounds That Are Forever</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At Bluffton, a New Season, but Wounds That Are Forever</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <dateline>BLUFFTON, Ohio</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The pitcher's mound was more like an observation deck. At 6 feet 7 inches, as solid as the silos up the road, the right-hander Chris Waite could see everything from the rubber on Friday afternoon.</p>
        <p>Down the left-field line, tied to a chain-link fence in foul territory, five white banners were hung to represent the jersey numbers of the Bluffton players who died when their charter bus plunged off an Interstate overpass in Atlanta four weeks ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four weeks ago, a charter bus carrying the Bluffton University baseball team plunged off an Interstate overpass in Atlanta, killing five players.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The pitcher's mound was more like an observation deck. At 6 feet 7 inches, as solid as the silos up the road, the right-hander Chris Waite could see everything from the rubber on Friday afternoon.</p>
        <p>Down the left-field line, tied to a chain-link fence in foul territory, five white banners were hung to represent the jersey numbers of the Bluffton players who died when their charter bus plunged off an Interstate overpass in Atlanta four weeks ago.</p>
        <p>With his discolored right foot set in a halolike brace and his jaw wired shut, Bluffton Coach James Grandey urged his team on as he sat near the corrugated-steel press box behind home plate.</p>
        <p>The Holp family stood near a donation jar a few feet from the backstop and wore T-shirts that read, ''In loving memory of Cody Holp.'' The father of David Betts, wearing his son's Bluffton ball cap, consoled another parent next to police tape that cordoned off an area for players' families only.</p>
        <p>Almost everyone wore black. The Bluffton students, who hauled plaid La-Z-Boys from the Archie Bunker era to the field to ensure seats, pulled out any black T-shirts they could find, no matter the logo. Harley-Davidson was popular.</p>
        <p>The Bluffton players, whose purple-and-white uniforms had been soaked in fuel at the accident scene, slipped into new black jerseys for their first game back since the funerals for their teammates.</p>
        <p>Bluffton's opponent was Mount St. Joseph of Cincinnati. Waite was the visitors' starting pitcher. His curly hair was tucked beneath his cap and his lumberjack's beard disguised his square jaw as he took the mound.</p>
        <p>He was surrounded by 2,000 fans at an admission-free ballpark that usually draws 100; by 12 satellite trucks in the parking lot behind the visitors' dugout; by townspeople who took the afternoon off; by Bluffton hitters with sprains and bruises not fully healed.</p>
        <p>How do you pitch to mourners, to the wounded?</p>
        <p>''I definitely had more nerves going into this game than any other,'' said Waite, who gave up three earned runs in seven innings during Mount St. Joseph's 10-5 victory, if you call it that. ''There was so much emotion coming here.''</p>
        <p>It is understandable to overlook the visitors on a day that is all about the home team. But, in many ways, Mount St. Joseph was faced with its own mortality, too.</p>
        <p>In the small world of Division III baseball in Ohio, players know each other from youth league ball and high school tournaments, experiencing the wonder years together, talking over the game, girlfriends, PlayStation tactics and long bus rides.</p>
        <p>''We all ride buses in D-III,'' Mount St. Joseph Coach Chuck Murray said. ''You know it could have been you.''</p>
        <p>Mount St. Joseph's charter bus rolled into town around 2:30 p.m., past the purple Village of Bluffton welcome sign, a rock quarry and the Dari-Freeze with a sign that detailed Friday's special: fried bologna.</p>
        <p>The Lions arrived to meet their conference foes on the same route as always but in a different role: as the adversaries of comfort.</p>
        <p>Bluffton needed Mount St. Joseph as much as its players needed the moment of silence, fungos and the national anthem before the game.</p>
        <p>The parents of the Mount St. Joseph players wore purple ribbons out of respect for Bluffton. The Lions uttered a few notes of ''you O.K?'' and ''good to see you'' to Bluffton fielders when they crossed on the bases. They stood quietly in their dugout after the game while Bluffton gathered in prayer in front of the left-field banners, and they put their arms around Grandey when he boarded his crutches to greet them before they left.</p>
        <p>Better to be consoled by rivals than by strangers.</p>
        <p>The Lions never looked awkward or overwhelmed by the part. As the opposition, they made for the perfect support group.</p>
        <p>''We were here to do whatever they needed us to do,'' Murray said.</p>
        <p>Bluffton could have canceled the season -- there is an argument to be made for that -- but it decided that playing out the season would be the best therapy. Winning seems irrelevant.</p>
        <p>''You don't know me very well,'' Grandey joked afterward.</p>
        <p>Baseball brought relief and levity, but, certainly, there are trauma-related issues that will go on and on, like the survivor's guilt of those who emerged from the bus accident.</p>
        <p>Wasn't Grandey grateful to be alive? He paused, shook his head but didn't offer an answer. Other players, perhaps feeling the same way, have been seeing counselors provided by the university.</p>
        <p>''They're just starting to talk it out,'' said Lisa Hill, whose son, Tyler, a pitcher, called her within seconds of the accident.</p>
        <p>As Hill recounted: ''Tyler was dealing with his friend stuck under the bus. And he knew a couple of others were dead. He knew it wasn't good. He kept saying, 'It's not good. It's not good.'</p>
        <p>''I was listening to him. I could hear the sirens coming.''</p>
        <p>Tyler Hill, with lingering soreness from the accident, pitched in relief Friday. The score was lopsided by then.</p>
        <p>Should Mount St. Joseph have let up? Should the Lions have pulled back?</p>
        <p>That wouldn't be normal. That wouldn't be baseball. So Waite pounded his left leg in frustration and probably rubbed the color off the baseball's stitches after he gave up a hit with a 10-3 cushion.</p>
        <p>If Waite had chosen, he could have looked around him at all the symbols of grief at the ballpark. He had the perfect vantage point on the mound. And while he stopped on occasion to absorb the special feel to the game, all he wanted to do was throw strikes.</p>
        <p>''We knew it wouldn't be a normal game,'' Waite said, ''but we all were glad to see those guys back on the field. Just take three hours and get away from everything they've been through.''</p>
        <p>Mount St. Joseph's players wanted to be there for their rivals. In some ways, playing Bluffton was easier than knowing what to say to the grieving.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: selenasports@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: selenasports@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
