<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Raising Old Barns To Make a New Village</title>
    <meta content="01post" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/realestate/01post.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837241"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="POSTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Barns</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lumberland (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lumberland Post and Beam</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hughes, C J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smyth, Hall</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Upstate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Rural Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rural Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E3D81030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="711" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Raising Old Barns To Make a New Village</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Raising Old Barns to Make a New Village</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C. J. HUGHES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hughes, C J</byline>
      <dateline>LUMBERLAND, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Developer Hall Smyth awaits final zoning approval for subdivision of 15 antique barns to be reconstructed as housing on 76-acre site in Lumberland, NY; Lumberland Post and Beam, Smyth's company, already owns half dozen old barns from around Northeast, each of which has been taken apart, stored and is awaiting reconstruction; seventh barn, from Maine, has already been reassembled; three-bedroom, 4,500-square-foot structure is listed at $689,000; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RESIDENTS of this little Sullivan County town are acutely aware that their bucolic corner could one day be an appealing target for developers as a site for tract housing.</p>
        <p>''When the real estate market heats up again, tag, we're it,'' is how Van B. Krzywicki, a former member of the town planning board, put it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For a 76-acre site in the Delaware River Valley, Hall Smyth has proposed a subdivision of 15 antique barns, reclaimed from sites throughout New York, New Jersey and New England.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RESIDENTS of this little Sullivan County town are acutely aware that their bucolic corner could one day be an appealing target for developers as a site for tract housing.</p>
        <p>''When the real estate market heats up again, tag, we're it,'' is how Van B. Krzywicki, a former member of the town planning board, put it.</p>
        <p>That is unless Hall Smyth, a developer with a different sensibility, beats others to it. For a 76-acre site in the Delaware River Valley, he is proposing a subdivision of 15 antique barns, reclaimed from sites throughout New York, New Jersey and New England, and configured to preserve as much wilderness as possible.</p>
        <p>Barns are as likely as land to fall victim to development, say preservation experts, who point out that they are expensive to paint, reroof and keep up; nowadays they shelter pickup trucks more often than cows.</p>
        <p>In fact, New England alone has lost a quarter of its barns in just a decade, according to Thomas Durant Visser, author of ''Field Guide to New England Barns and Farm Buildings'' (University Press of New England, 1997) and director of the historic preservation program at the University of Vermont.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smyth's company, Lumberland Post and Beam, already has ownership of half a dozen old barns from New Jersey, New York, Pennsylvania and Maine. Each has been taken apart, tagged and stored, and is awaiting reconstruction at the site in Pond Eddy, a hamlet of Lumberland.</p>
        <p>And a seventh, pulled from a dairy farm in Livermore Falls, Me., is the first to have been reassembled and restored. A three-story structure, it has three bedrooms, three and a half baths and 4,500 square feet, and is listed at $689,000. It awaits a chimney and wraparound deck, to be completed this spring, Mr. Smyth said.</p>
        <p>Though the subdivision still requires final zoning approval, he ultimately envisions a homeowners association linking a series of individual lots of two acres, rather than the five that are standard in these developments. That will allow more land to be conserved in its current state, thick with pines and hickories, and cut with streams.</p>
        <p>Also, under a state conservation program, if a developer makes at least 50 acres off-limits to construction, association homeowners can see an 80 percent discount on their property tax bills.</p>
        <p>The planned tight zoning and close-in layout intentionally recall a 20th-century feature of Sullivan County's low-rolling landscape: bungalow colonies, arranged in semicircles, which played host to generations of clean-air-seeking city dwellers.</p>
        <p>Building on such a small footprint also meshes with the philosophy of Lumberland's planning board, so far.</p>
        <p>''Hall's type of subdivision is creative, provides employment and is sensitive to the environment both in terms of visual impact and impact on habitat,'' said Mr. Krzywicki, the former board member, who has seen the plan.</p>
        <p>In January, to promote his 21st-century colony, Mr. Smyth outfitted a former barbershop that he owns with his brother, Ben, on the Lower East Side of Manhattan to resemble the inside of his barn homes.</p>
        <p>For two months, the 350-square-foot space, at 139 Norfolk Street, featured salvaged tin roofing on its walls and oak siding on its floor, as well as oversize photos of the Sullivan County landscape, in a bid to attract passers-by. A few people seem interested, Mr. Smyth said.</p>
        <p>Irwin Richman, a professor emeritus of American studies at Pennsylvania State University at Harrisburg, who has written books about both barns and bungalow communities, applauds the mission to reclaim the barns.</p>
        <p>''You have to respect the architecture of the bones themselves,'' said Mr. Richman, who lives in Bainbridge, Pa., ''because you can adapt them beautifully, or you can adapt them in a sloppy way. But this would be an interesting change from the proliferation of McMansions.''</p>
        <p>And Mr. Smyth's fixation has also yielded a barn home of his own, a red 1860s wood structure with hay rakes strewn across its front pasture. (Unlike the others, it sits just where it was first built.)</p>
        <p>''I moved here from New York City, and wasn't planning on being a developer at all,'' said Mr. Smyth, who used to design exhibitions for museums and galleries.</p>
        <p>''But when you look around,'' he added, ''you recognize something that is necessary in the area that is missing.''</p>
        <p>POSTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
