<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Prisoner of Park Avenue</title>
    <meta content="01CTblum" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/opinion/nyregionopinions/01CTblum.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837203"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E4D91030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="985" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Prisoner of Park Avenue</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Prisoner of Park Avenue</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Howard Blum</byline>
      <dateline>REDDING</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I SPENT a night in jail. I was handcuffed, fingerprinted, had my mug shot taken and locked in a holding cell in the basement of the Lower Manhattan jail known as the Tombs for more than 17 hours until I was brought before an arraigning judge and released.</p>
        <p>My crime?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Talking tough on crime has its downsides.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I SPENT a night in jail. I was handcuffed, fingerprinted, had my mug shot taken and locked in a holding cell in the basement of the Lower Manhattan jail known as the Tombs for more than 17 hours until I was brought before an arraigning judge and released.</p>
        <p>My crime?</p>
        <p>At 10:45 on a Wednesday evening I was driving up Park Avenue on my way back home to Connecticut. Suddenly flashing lights appeared in my rearview mirror; a patrol car wanted me to pull over. The officer approached and informed me that one of my rear brakes lights was out. ''Let me see your papers,'' he said.</p>
        <p>My Connecticut license, registration and insurance card were all produced, scrutinized and judged valid. Nevertheless, the officer instructed me to wait as he went back to his patrol car.</p>
        <p>''Out of the car!'' he ordered when he returned. ''Hands behind your back!'' Then he handcuffed me.</p>
        <p>''What's going on? There's got to be some mistake.''</p>
        <p>''Stop whining -- no one likes a whiner,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''Would you please just tell me what I've done?'' I tried to remain calm, but things had in an instant escalated beyond my imaginings. This was absurd -- and frightening. I was standing on Park Avenue and 85th Street in my black cashmere topcoat with my arms handcuffed behind my back.</p>
        <p>The officer led me, still cuffed, to his patrol car and in response to more of my ''whining'' showed me what was on his computer screen. My Connecticut license was valid, but my license to drive in New York -- a state where I had not lived for more than a decade -- had been suspended in 1998.</p>
        <p>It did not apparently matter that I had moved from the address on the computer screen about 14 years ago and had never received any notification of the suspension. Nor did it matter that for nearly a decade Connecticut had routinely renewed my license and my insurance company had issued coverage -- all without noting New York State's suspension.</p>
        <p>All that mattered, according to the patrol car computer, were the three alleged strikes against me:</p>
        <p>1. A 2006 Southampton, N.Y., speeding ticket that I had paid. I even had the receipt in my car.</p>
        <p>2. A 1998 lapse in my auto insurance. Later, my insurance company faxed a letter saying there was never a break in my coverage. The New York Department of Motor Vehicles agreed, could not explain why this citation was in my files and, a further mystery, decided to resolve the non-issue with my paying $25.</p>
        <p>3. An unpaid 2001 speeding ticket in Westchester County that I cannot recall receiving. But this probably happened. I'm guilty. I messed up and forgot to pay the $50 ticket. Still, if any notices had been sent reminding me to pay the summons, they were apparently mailed to a house that I had sold and moved from in the mid-1990s. I never got them. And this unpaid violation never set off the alarms on the Connecticut computers when it came time to renew my license.</p>
        <p>For these crimes, my Kafkaesque incarceration began. Fingerprinting at the precinct was not easy; after more than a dozen attempts by the frustrated arresting officers, my prints would still not register on the computerized machine. At 1 a.m. they decided to bring me, hands cuffed behind my back, downtown to the Tombs. They would complete the process by manually inking my fingers. It was more time-consuming, but the officers did not mind; they talked gleefully about the overtime they would be earning. Then, after confirming I had no debilitating medical conditions, I was locked up with ''the general population.''</p>
        <p>''Keep your mouth shut,'' the arresting officer warned before he disappeared. ''You whine, they'll eat you up alive.''</p>
        <p>I was crammed into a basement holding cell with 25 other alleged felons for 17 stifling, humiliating, uncomfortable and often disturbing hours. I spent the time with drug dealers, a hard-eyed teenager accused of a street corner stabbing, a ''professional'' poker player, a child molester whom I overheard crying on the phone to his wife, ''So sorry, I never thought I'd do this again,'' and a man who kept insisting, despite the skeptical teasing of his fellow inmates, that he was innocent -- his girlfriend had picked him up in the stolen Chevy.</p>
        <p>I saw the medics revive a prisoner pulled from an adjacent cell after he had nearly succeeded in hanging himself with the cord from his hooded sweatshirt. I kept my distance as a skinny teenager who had been sitting on the floor across from me abruptly stood up to confront a towering, broad-shouldered man and then with swift, calculated fury knocked him down. And I ignored a few snarled threats.</p>
        <p>But the specifics of my time in jail are ultimately irrelevant. I'm out, and after a couple of hundred dollars in fines (and a $5.59 brake light), I'm back driving in New York.</p>
        <p>The legal and judicial mindset, however, that helped create the circumstances that resulted in my brief incarceration are, I believe, significant.</p>
        <p>It is an often repeated wisdom, at least in certain political circles, that ''a liberal is someone who hasn't been mugged.'' Well, let me suggest that a conservative is someone who has not been jailed.</p>
        <p>As a new national election cycle looms, candidates are scurrying to talk tough on crime, to pledge their commitment to enforcing laws that protect the quality of life. And who can blame them? A night in the Tombs will convince any doubter that it is reasonable, even vital, that law and order continue to be part of the national narrative.</p>
        <p>Yet my experience has also taught me that a strident, narrow pandering to middle-class fears can backfire. Authority wields a double-edged sword. In an instant, anyone can find himself standing on Park Avenue in a cashmere topcoat with his hands cuffed behind his back.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor Howard Blum, a contributing editor at Vanity Fair, is the author of the forthcoming ''American Lightning,'' about the 1910 Los Angeles Times bombing.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Howard Blum, a contributing editor at Vanity Fair, is the author of the forthcoming ''American Lightning,'' about the 1910 Los Angeles Times bombing.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
