<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BEST SELLERS: April 01, 2007</title>
    <meta content="Besthard.nonfiction" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837010"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEEDC1530F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1257" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BEST SELLERS: April 01, 2007</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended March 17, at almost 4,000 bookstores plus wholesalers serving 50,000 other retailers, statistically weighted to represent all such outlets nationwide. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available at The New York Times on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>CHRISTINE FALLS, by Benjamin Black. (Holt, $25.) In foggy 1950s Dublin, a pathologist becomes an accidental detective; by John Banville, writing pseudonymously.</p>
        <p>RUMSFELD: His Rise, Fall, and Catastrophic Legacy, by Andrew Cockburn. (Scribner, $25.) The roots of Rumsfeld's disastrous tenure.</p>
        <p>THE BEAUTIFUL THINGS THAT HEAVEN BEARS, by Dinaw Mengestu. (Riverhead, $22.95.) A first novel about an Ethiopian exile in Washington, D.C., evokes loss, hope, memory and the solace of friendship.</p>
        <p>TALES FROM THE TORRID ZONE, by Alexander Frater. (Knopf, $25.95.) Travels from Zanzibar to the Galápagos to Vietnam.</p>
        <p>THE BURIED BOOK: The Loss and Rediscovery of the Great Epic of Gilgamesh, by David Damrosch. (Holt, $26.) A history of a work written in ancient Mesopotamia and rediscovered by British scholars in the 19th century.</p>
        <p>INHERITANCE, by Natalie Danford. (St. Martin's, $23.95.) In this first novel, a young woman uncovers a family secret from Fascist Italy.</p>
        <p>LONELY AVENUE: The Unlikely Life and Times of Doc Pomus, by Alex Halberstadt. (Da Capo, $26.) This songwriter cracked rock 'n' roll's code in the early 1960s.</p>
        <p>LOST CITY RADIO, by Daniel Alarcón. (HarperCollins, $24.95.) A first novel set in a South American country 10 years after a dirty civil war.</p>
        <p>WINTERTON BLUE, by Trezza Azzopardi. (Grove, $24.) An unhappy young woman meets an even unhappier drifter.</p>
        <p>LENI: The Life and Work of Leni Riefenstahl, by Steven Bach. (Knopf, $30.) How Hitler's favorite director made ''Triumph of the Will'' and convinced posterity that she didn't know what the Nazis were up to.</p>
        <p>LENI RIEFENSTAHL: A Life, by Jürgen Trimborn. Translated by Edna McCown. (Faber &amp; Faber, $30.) This biography is especially good on Riefenstahl's long later years, when she moved to Africa and outlived her enemies. The full reviews of these and other recent books are on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended March 17, at almost 4,000 bookstores plus wholesalers serving 50,000 other retailers, statistically weighted to represent all such outlets nationwide. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available at The New York Times on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>CHRISTINE FALLS, by Benjamin Black. (Holt, $25.) In foggy 1950s Dublin, a pathologist becomes an accidental detective; by John Banville, writing pseudonymously.</p>
        <p>RUMSFELD: His Rise, Fall, and Catastrophic Legacy, by Andrew Cockburn. (Scribner, $25.) The roots of Rumsfeld's disastrous tenure.</p>
        <p>THE BEAUTIFUL THINGS THAT HEAVEN BEARS, by Dinaw Mengestu. (Riverhead, $22.95.) A first novel about an Ethiopian exile in Washington, D.C., evokes loss, hope, memory and the solace of friendship.</p>
        <p>TALES FROM THE TORRID ZONE, by Alexander Frater. (Knopf, $25.95.) Travels from Zanzibar to the Galápagos to Vietnam.</p>
        <p>THE BURIED BOOK: The Loss and Rediscovery of the Great Epic of Gilgamesh, by David Damrosch. (Holt, $26.) A history of a work written in ancient Mesopotamia and rediscovered by British scholars in the 19th century.</p>
        <p>INHERITANCE, by Natalie Danford. (St. Martin's, $23.95.) In this first novel, a young woman uncovers a family secret from Fascist Italy.</p>
        <p>LONELY AVENUE: The Unlikely Life and Times of Doc Pomus, by Alex Halberstadt. (Da Capo, $26.) This songwriter cracked rock 'n' roll's code in the early 1960s.</p>
        <p>LOST CITY RADIO, by Daniel Alarcón. (HarperCollins, $24.95.) A first novel set in a South American country 10 years after a dirty civil war.</p>
        <p>WINTERTON BLUE, by Trezza Azzopardi. (Grove, $24.) An unhappy young woman meets an even unhappier drifter.</p>
        <p>LENI: The Life and Work of Leni Riefenstahl, by Steven Bach. (Knopf, $30.) How Hitler's favorite director made ''Triumph of the Will'' and convinced posterity that she didn't know what the Nazis were up to.</p>
        <p>LENI RIEFENSTAHL: A Life, by Jürgen Trimborn. Translated by Edna McCown. (Faber &amp; Faber, $30.) This biography is especially good on Riefenstahl's long later years, when she moved to Africa and outlived her enemies. The full reviews of these and other recent books are on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This</p>
        <p>Last</p>
        <p>On</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>List</p>
        <p>FICTION</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>NINETEEN MINUTES, by Jodi Picoult. (Atria, $26.95.) The aftermath of a high school shooting reveals the fault lines in a small New Hampshire town.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>SHOPAHOLIC &amp; BABY, by Sophie Kinsella. (Dial, $24.) Becky is pregnant, and the obstetrician turns out to be her husband's ex-girlfriend.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>DADDY'S GIRL, by Lisa Scottoline. (HarperCollins, $25.95.) A law professor caught in a prison riot must defend herself when she is unjustly accused of murder.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>WHITETHORN WOODS, by Maeve Binchy. (Knopf, $25.95.) A proposed highway threatens the existence of a religious shrine in a rural Irish village.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>STEP ON A CRACK, by James Patterson and Michael Ledwidge. (Little, Brown, $27.99.) A detective raising 10 children alone must rescue 34 high-level hostages.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>SISTERS, by Danielle Steel. (Delacorte, $27.) After a family tragedy, four sisters with very different lives decide to share a Manhattan brownstone.</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>THE DOUBLE BIND, by Chris Bohjalian. (Shaye Areheart, $25.) A young woman who works at a homeless shelter struggles to understand the mysterious photographs taken by a recently deceased resident.</p>
        <p>8*</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>THE WATCHMAN, by Robert Crais. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $25.95.) A former Los Angeles police officer becomes the bodyguard of a troubled heiress marked for death.</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>INNOCENT IN DEATH, by J. D. Robb. (Putnam, $25.95) Lt. Eve Dallas investigates the murder of a history teacher; by Nora Roberts, writing pseudonymously.</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>25</p>
        <p>FOR ONE MORE DAY, by Mitch Albom. (Hyperion, $21.95.) A troubled man gets a last chance to reconnect and restore his relationship with his dead mother.</p>
        <p>11*</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>WHAT THE DEAD KNOW, by Laura Lippman. (Morrow, $25.95.) A woman claims to be one of two sisters who disappeared mysteriously 30 years earlier.</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>THE POST-BIRTHDAY WORLD, by Lionel Shriver. (HarperCollins, $25.95.) In parallel narratives, a London woman stays with her boyfriend and leaves him for another.</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>HEYDAY, by Kurt Andersen. (Random House, $26.95.) A British gentleman and three American friends are caught up in the California gold rush of 1848.</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>PLUM LOVIN', by Janet Evanovich. (St. Martin's, $16.95.) A mysterious man in Stephanie Plum's life helps her track down a matchmaker who skipped bail.</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>THE ALEXANDRIA LINK, by Steve Berry. (Ballantine, $25.95.) A former Justice Department operative turned bookseller hides a link to the secrets of the vanished library of Alexandria from wealthy international thugs.</p>
        <p>16*</p>
        <p>16</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>HEART-SHAPED BOX, by Joe Hill. (Morrow, $24.95.) An aging rock star who buys what's advertised as a ghost is stunned when it turns out to be the real thing.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This</p>
        <p>Last</p>
        <p>On</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>List</p>
        <p>NONFICTION</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>IN AN INSTANT, by Lee and Bob Woodruff. (Random House, $25.95.) The aftermath of the ABC co-anchor's traumatic brain injury in Iraq in 2006.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>A LONG WAY GONE, by Ishmael Beah. (Sarah Crichton/Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $22.) A former child soldier from Sierra Leone describes his drug-crazed killing spree and his return to humanity.</p>
        <p>3*</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>33</p>
        <p>I FEEL BAD ABOUT MY NECK, by Nora Ephron. (Knopf, $19.95.) A witty look at aging from a novelist and screenwriter (''When Harry Met Sally'').</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>22</p>
        <p>THE AUDACITY OF HOPE, by Barack Obama. (Crown, $25.) The Illinois junior senator proposes that Americans move beyond their political divisions.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>INFIDEL, by Ayaan Hirsi Ali. (Free Press, $26.) A memoir by the Somali-born advocate for Muslim immigrant women, once a member of the Dutch Parliament, who has been threatened with death.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>THE HARDCORE DIARIES, by Mick Foley. (World Wrestling Entertainment/Pocket, $24.) The former professional wrestling champion discusses his fame and his life at World Wrestling Entertainment.</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>HOW DOCTORS THINK, by Jerome Groopman. (Houghton Mifflin, $26.) A doctor and New Yorker staff writer describes how doctors arrive at diagnoses and what patients can do to make sure they don't err.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>SECOND CHANCE, by Zbigniew Brzezinski. (Basic, $26.95.) The former National Security adviser discusses how America can regain the global power and prestige squandered by its three post-cold-war presidents.</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>SOMEBODY'S GOTTA SAY IT, by Neal Boortz (HC/HarperCollins, $25.95.) A radio talk-show host discusses government, poverty, prayer in the schools, race relations, gun control and other topics.</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>23</p>
        <p>THE INNOCENT MAN, by John Grisham. (Doubleday, $28.95.) Grisham's first nonfiction book concerns a man sentenced to death for a crime he did not commit.</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>74</p>
        <p>MARLEY &amp; ME, by John Grogan. (Morrow, $29.95 and $21.95.) A newspaper columnist and his wife learn some life lessons from their neurotic dog.</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>POWER, FAITH, and FANTASY, by Michael B. Oren. (Norton, $35.) A history of America's relations with the Middle East starting in 1776.</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>97</p>
        <p>FREAKONOMICS, by Steven D. Levitt and Stephen J. Dubner. (Morrow, $27.95.) A maverick scholar and a journalist apply economic theory to nearly everything.</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>26</p>
        <p>THE GOD DELUSION, by Richard Dawkins. (Houghton Mifflin, $27.) An Oxford scientist asserts that belief in God is irrational.</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>102</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>THE WORLD IS FLAT, by Thomas L. Friedman. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $30.) A columnist for The Times analyzes 21st-century economics and foreign policy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
