<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Fairy Godmother for the High-End Fashion Set</title>
    <meta content="01licolLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/01licol.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837154"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE ISLAND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Port Washington (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Janet Brown (Store)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finn, Robin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Janet</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E1D61330F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="832" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Fairy Godmother for the High-End Fashion Set</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Fairy Godmother for the High-End Fashion Set</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robin Finn</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finn, Robin</byline>
      <dateline>PORT WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Robin Finn The Island column on Janet Brown, owner of high-end Janet Brown boutique in Port Washington, NY, who suffered heart attack and died in car crash in March; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EPONYMOUS boutiques dedicated to dressing boldface clients of the utmost means are not just out of fashion but also nearly extinct -- too limited in vision, too inconvenient and oh, the killer overhead!</p>
        <p>Not to mention that this one, hatched in 1983 in a location best described as off the beaten path, would look more at home along a seedy boardwalk than it does menacing the boundaries of Manhasset's Americana sprawl, the glistening competition two miles down the pike. Janet Brown (this puny store's exclusive if not inventive name) screams consignment shop chic from its rickety, 50s-style vinyl storm door to the fringe on the funky brown Prada sandals in the window.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At a boutique in Port Washington, appearances can be deceiving.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EPONYMOUS boutiques dedicated to dressing boldface clients of the utmost means are not just out of fashion but also nearly extinct -- too limited in vision, too inconvenient and oh, the killer overhead!</p>
        <p>Not to mention that this one, hatched in 1983 in a location best described as off the beaten path, would look more at home along a seedy boardwalk than it does menacing the boundaries of Manhasset's Americana sprawl, the glistening competition two miles down the pike. Janet Brown (this puny store's exclusive if not inventive name) screams consignment shop chic from its rickety, 50s-style vinyl storm door to the fringe on the funky brown Prada sandals in the window.</p>
        <p>But appearances can be deceiving. And fashion is so fickle as to permit glaring exceptions to its own haute rules. This may explain why business kept booming at Janet Brown, a pricey hole-in-the-wall at 4 Carlton Avenue at the frowsy end of Main Street, on March 16. That was the turbulent Friday morning that Janet Brown, the emporium's feisty proprietor and namesake, suffered a heart attack while driving to work in an ice storm from the Oyster Bay home she shared with two Labrador retrievers.</p>
        <p>So, if eponymous boutiques are a dying breed, what will be the fate of Janet Brown (the place) without Janet Brown (the purveyor)?</p>
        <p>Mentored by Nan Duskin, the owner of the leading (and now defunct) women's clothing store in her hometown, Philadelphia, Ms. Brown was divorced, childless and devoted to shopping for, and arranging, outfits like artwork. She favored a navy cashmere jacket, white shirt and Keds for her own working uniform, which tended to be rumpled.</p>
        <p>Ms. Brown was a soup-to-nuts clothier who would sell a customer (say, Julieann Orso of Sands Point) a $6,000 beaded Lanvin dress and, in the search for appropriate jewelry to complete the ensemble, reject her own inventory of expensive bling as well as Ms. Orso's, experience a brainstorm, dash across the street, and pluck the perfect pair of $10 rhinestone danglers from a merchant. ''My favorite Janet story,'' Ms. Orso said.</p>
        <p>''It wasn't about the money or how much she could sell you,'' added Ms. Orso, who admitted that her husband, Anthony, had mixed feelings about that when she deserted Barneys and Bergdorf's for Janet's magic touch. ''It was about style and helping you put yourself together to look your best.''</p>
        <p>For a price. The average one-stop shopping spree at Janet Brown yielded $12,000 of sartorial embellishments. But for those who could afford her shop, Ms. Brown was, to quote Ms. Orso, ''a fairy godmother who made you feel like Cinderella.'' In other words, she was a life-altering experience, even for Anthony Orso: his wife said tears ran down his face at the funeral.</p>
        <p>Ms. Brown, 59, died from injuries sustained in the crash. Disinclined to fuss over her own health or appearance despite obsessing over everyone else's to the point of solicitude bordering on control freakdom, she apparently neglected to fasten her seat belt.</p>
        <p>Worn out from being the host of a successful trunk show at the Regency Hotel in New York City -- she was both mountain and Mohammed when it came to interacting with the 300 or so clotheshorses who comprised her client base -- she was nonetheless in a rush to get back, be it ever so humble, to the home storefront. Ms. Brown, like her business, thrived on reinvention.</p>
        <p>Her granite desk was waiting. She got only halfway there.</p>
        <p>Randi Newman, Ms. Brown's hand-trained sales associate for 20 years and presumably her heir apparent, rushed to the hospital. Back at the shop, Ms. Brown's so-called secret weapon, her seamstresses, continued putting the final touches on orders: the boss would have been furious if they hadn't.</p>
        <p>Service beyond the pale was a Janet Brown staple (she served complimentary salads and beverages but joked that her store needed no parking lot because customers arrived by limo); that and one-upping trends. Prada, Jil Sander and Marni were pioneers she proselytized and popularized.</p>
        <p>Her eye, according to Brooke Garber Neidich, a longtime customer and friend (Ms. Brown combined the two when possible), was impeccable. ''She had that unerring eye for quality, always with a bit of an edge, never a one-designer look, chic and bold without making you look silly,'' said Ms. Neidich, organizer of a March 19 memorial service where the eulogists included Gov. Jon S. Corzine of New Jersey, who wore suits selected for and personally delivered to him by Ms. Brown during his Goldman Sachs tenure.</p>
        <p>''Her life was her customers,'' said Ms. Newman, who started as an assistant buyer at Bloomingdale's and in 1986 ventured to Port Washington to interview with Ms. Brown. ''It was like 'Sesame Street' and she was Big Bird opening up her wings to me and teaching me how to fly in this business. Four Carlton Avenue was a club, and it will remain a club. I want her to be proud of me.''</p>
        <p>Her customers say the same.</p>
        <p>THE ISLAND E-mail: theisland@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: theisland@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
