<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Bridge Over the Atlantic, in Labor Policy</title>
    <meta content="01view" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/business/yourmoney/01view.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070415T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837315"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ECONOMIC VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic View</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E0DB1130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Bridge Over the Atlantic, in Labor Policy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Bridge Over the Atlantic, in Labor Policy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDUARDO PORTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Porter, Eduardo</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FROM issues of crime and punishment to the proper domain of the spiritual and temporal powers, Americans and Europeans have long cast a skeptical eye at one another across the Atlantic.</p>
        <p>Perhaps nowhere has the gaze been more jaundiced than in the area of work. From the perspective of Western Europe, American employers have a relatively free hand to hire and fire, coupled with meager and short-lived unemployment benefits. America's deregulated labor markets seem to provide hardly any safety net when it comes to economic dislocations of workers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Competition from workers in China and other poor countries is pushing American and European policy makers to borrow from each other’s playbooks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FROM issues of crime and punishment to the proper domain of the spiritual and temporal powers, Americans and Europeans have long cast a skeptical eye at one another across the Atlantic.</p>
        <p>Perhaps nowhere has the gaze been more jaundiced than in the area of work. From the perspective of Western Europe, American employers have a relatively free hand to hire and fire, coupled with meager and short-lived unemployment benefits. America's deregulated labor markets seem to provide hardly any safety net when it comes to economic dislocations of workers.</p>
        <p>Americans, by contrast, have found it hard to resist a touch of schadenfreude at the joblessness stoked by European governments' intervention in labor markets, with rules on everything from wages to layoffs, on top of generous unemployment benefits.</p>
        <p>But global change is pushing Europe and the United States to borrow from each other's playbooks.</p>
        <p>Faced with relentless competition from workers in China and other poor countries, American policy makers are considering extending a little more generosity to the low-skilled and unemployed. In Europe, the debate focuses on pushing the unemployed back to work.</p>
        <p>''There is a convergence across the Atlantic,'' said Hans-Werner Sinn, president of the Ifo Institute for Economic Research in Munich, whose proposals to get the unemployed back to work have been partially adopted in Germany.</p>
        <p>In the United States, after Democrats took hold of Congress, they increased the minimum wage for the first time in a decade. Now Democratic lawmakers are considering a plan to extend unemployment insurance coverage, which excludes all sorts of laid-off workers, including those who had part-time jobs and those leaving work because of family needs.</p>
        <p>Some Democrats are also proposing a wage insurance plan, intended to cover part of the difference between the wages a laid-off worker formerly earned and the wages paid in the new job, which are typically 16 percent lower.</p>
        <p>''You can think of it as subsidizing the re-acquisition of skills by workers,'' said Lael Brainard, an economist at the Brookings Institution in Washington.</p>
        <p>Representative Jim McDermott, a Democrat from Washington State who has drafted proposals to retool unemployment insurance and introduce wage insurance, said: ''In the mid-1990s, globalization accelerated to 100 miles per hour. Unfortunately nobody was standing around and thinking about what was happening to American workers.''</p>
        <p>Most economists argue that American workers have long been buffeted by similar forces. ''I wouldn't think of globalization as fundamentally different from other changes the United States economy has undergone over hundreds of years,'' said Robert Shimer, a professor of economics at the University of Chicago. ''Now jobs are lost in part because they are going to other countries, but buggy makers lost their jobs when the car was introduced.''</p>
        <p>There is an ideological component in the policy proposals to address the current dislocations. In an address to the American Economic Association two years ago, Martin Feldstein, a former economic adviser to President Bush, suggested that unemployment insurance could be replaced with private unemployment accounts -- similar in approach to private retirement accounts -- for workers to prepare for potential joblessness.</p>
        <p>Critics of the wage insurance proposal argue that it would subsidize employers who pay substandard wages. In addition, some say that it is inefficient to distort workers' incentives this way. Some Republican-leaning economists support the new ideas, in principle. ''There's a clear social contract between capital and labor,'' said John Silvia, chief economist of the Wachovia Corporation -- who was formerly an economist for two Republican-controlled Congressional committees. ''When a corporation reallocates its resources we cannot just leave these people flat and dead.''</p>
        <p>Moreover, many economists say, helping workers deal with the dislocations wrought by a fast-changing economy would help temper their fears about globalization and forestall a protectionist backlash.</p>
        <p>Global competition from manufacturers in poor countries, meanwhile, is driving some Western European countries in the opposite direction. Realizing that high long-term unemployment benefits established a very high ''reservation wage'' -- below which a person who is out of work would not accept a job -- many are trying to coax the unemployed back into active work.</p>
        <p>In Denmark, home to one of Europe's most generous unemployment programs, public munificence has eroded somewhat in the last decade. The unemployed must now accept either a job offer or a place in a training program if they are to keep their benefits; the maximum benefit period has been cut to four years from five.</p>
        <p>IN Germany, the former left-of-center government passed a package of laws in 2003 that cut benefits, pared the duration of unemployment insurance to 16 months from 32 and required workers on long-term benefits to accept any ''reasonable'' job offers.</p>
        <p>The program allows workers to earn up to 100 euros a month tax-free without losing benefits. And the government set up a system to provide low-wage public jobs for the long-term unemployed. Mr. Sinn, the German economist, said that if his country is to employ its less-skilled workers in the face of global competition, companies will have to be allowed to pay lower wages.</p>
        <p>To achieve that, Mr. Sinn said, the government must stop providing a long-term, well-paid alternative to work. But he argued that there should be a higher threshold at which benefits begin to be reduced. This would provide an effective subsidy to wages, he said, allowing workers to accept low-paid jobs and still maintain an acceptable income. ''The minimum wages desired for social purposes are higher than the wages employers are willing to pay,'' Mr. Sinn said.Europeans and Americans take very different approaches to the labor market -- with Europeans concerned primarily with guaranteeing some decent level of income for its citizens, the United States with encouraging an efficient labor market that provides lots of jobs. Still, a common perspective may be emerging: the unemployed must be encouraged to work. But it may be the government's role to step in when wages are insufficient.</p>
        <p>ECONOMIC VIEW</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 15, 2007, Sunday  The Economic View column on April 1, about labor policies in the United States and Europe, misstated the status of efforts in Congress to raise the minimum wage. Separate bills to raise the wage have been approved by the Senate and the House, but legislation has not been enacted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 15, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>The Economic View column on April 1, about labor policies in the United States and Europe, misstated the status of efforts in Congress to raise the minimum wage. Separate bills to raise the wage have been approved by the Senate and the House, but legislation has not been enacted.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
