<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Can the Star Maker Make Himself a Star?</title>
    <meta content="01sann" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/arts/music/01sann.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837142"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanneh, Kelefa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Timbaland (Rapper)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Rap Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rap Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Pussycat Dolls</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Furtado, Nelly</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Timberlake, Justin</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EED91330F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1780" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Can the Star Maker Make Himself a Star?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Can the Star Maker Make Himself a Star?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KELEFA SANNEH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanneh, Kelefa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kelefah Sanneh article profiles Timbaland, seen as most exciting producer in pop music and composer who has changed way rappers and singers think about rhythm; over last year or two, he has redoubled his efforts to achieve pop stardom; songs on new album described; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TIMBALAND is not an invisible man -- not exactly. He has released four major-label albums, none a big hit but all respectfully received. He tried to become a music mogul by starting his own label, Beat Club, which didn't take off. For years he has popped up in music videos: hiding in the shadows of Aaliyah's ''Are You That Somebody,'' haunting Justin Timberlake's ''Cry Me a River.'' He has popped up on albums too, murmuring encouragement to Missy Elliott or seconding Jay-Z's boasts.</p>
        <p>But he has spent much of the last decade hidden in plain sight, his name buried in the liner notes. He long ago established himself as the most exciting producer in pop music, a composer who has changed the way rappers and singers -- and their fans -- think about rhythm. It's no exaggeration to compare him to James Brown, another rhythm fanatic who found new possibilities in old grooves. The only difference: James Brown was a bona fide star.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Timbaland is determined to come out from behind the mixing board.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TIMBALAND is not an invisible man -- not exactly. He has released four major-label albums, none a big hit but all respectfully received. He tried to become a music mogul by starting his own label, Beat Club, which didn't take off. For years he has popped up in music videos: hiding in the shadows of Aaliyah's ''Are You That Somebody,'' haunting Justin Timberlake's ''Cry Me a River.'' He has popped up on albums too, murmuring encouragement to Missy Elliott or seconding Jay-Z's boasts.</p>
        <p>But he has spent much of the last decade hidden in plain sight, his name buried in the liner notes. He long ago established himself as the most exciting producer in pop music, a composer who has changed the way rappers and singers -- and their fans -- think about rhythm. It's no exaggeration to compare him to James Brown, another rhythm fanatic who found new possibilities in old grooves. The only difference: James Brown was a bona fide star.</p>
        <p>Timbaland has never seemed very comfortable in front of the camera, and collaborators have occasionally complained about his gruff mixing-board-side manner. Nonetheless over the last year or two he has redoubled his efforts to achieve pop stardom, even if he's not well suited for it. He has been writing himself into the hit songs he produces, turning his clients into duet partners. He spars with Justin Timberlake on ''SexyBack'' and ''My Love'' and flirts awkwardly with Nelly Furtado on ''Promiscuous'' and with the Pussycat Dolls on ''Wait a Minute.''</p>
        <p>All this has been building up to the release, on Tuesday, of ''Timbaland Presents Shock Value'' (Mosley Music Group/Interscope), his fifth album and his most ambitious. Timbaland now has more clout than ever. Over his sharp and twitchy beats, teen heartthrobs sound daring, established pop stars sound hip, rough rappers sound radio-friendly. ''Shock Value'' proves that just about everyone returns his phone calls. The guest list ranges from Fall Out Boy to Elton John, from Dr. Dre to 50 Cent. And for the first single, ''Give It to Me,'' he delivers a verse alongside Mr. Timberlake and Ms. Furtado.</p>
        <p>Nowadays a real star needs a real feud, so Timbaland used ''Give It to Me'' to vent long-simmering frustration with Scott Storch, the Miami-based producer (and, before a rift, a Timbaland collaborator) who has emerged as a hitmaker in his own right. ''I'm a real producer and you just the piano man,'' Timbaland sneers, and those two words, ''real producer,'' suggest a whole constellation of claims and paradoxes. How can some guy who plays the piano compare himself to Timbaland, who  wait, what exactly does he do again?</p>
        <p>Ever since there have been pop stars, there have been people charged with making them sound their best; these people soon realized that working in a recording studio could be a musical job, not just a mechanical one. But often being a producer meant being a bandleader: Phil Spector worked with the musicians known as the Wrecking Crew, and Norman Whitfield worked with the Funk Brothers.</p>
        <p>As electronic production took over, the process of music-making got more abstract, and it got harder for a nonexpert to figure out exactly what tools a producer was using. (Although we're all pretty sure computers are involved.) It has become much easier to see the product -- the star, the video, the live performance -- and much harder to picture the process. Producers who want to be players in the image-driven world of pop music have to find ways to fight off obscurity.</p>
        <p>In hip-hop the answer is simple: Start rapping. That's what Dr. Dre did (effectively), and what Kanye West did (brilliantly). You can create an outrageous character for yourself, as Lil Jon has done; no doubt many listeners don't realize that the doofus with the pimp cup is also a first-rate knob-twiddler. Or you can demand attention in other ways. The New Orleans-raised hip-hop producer Mannie Fresh appends a ridiculous -- and attention-getting -- announcement to every song he produces. (''Yo! Rednecks, coloreds, Asians, Africans, Ethiopians, whatever you is: It's your boy, Freshly Snipes, ya heard?'') Even if the song circulates on MP3, with no liner notes attached, there can be no mistaking who made it.</p>
        <p>Timbaland, 35, was born Timothy Mosley in Norfolk, Va., and he spent about a decade as a D.J. and fledgling producer. He broke through in 1996, the year he produced Ginuwine's space-age mating call, ''Pony,'' and Aaliyah's live come-on, ''If Your Girl Only Knew'' The next year he produced ''Supa Dupa Fly,'' the dazzling debut album from Ms. Elliott, an old high school friend.</p>
        <p>Also in 1997 Timbaland made his full-length rapping debut when he joined with the Virginia rapper Magoo to release the album ''Welcome to Our World.'' It was a modest success, and though it didn't turn either man into an A-list rapper, it was a sleek showcase for Timbaland's signature style: heavy, indolent beats enlivened by skittering syncopation. (Like James Brown before him, he found a way to emphasize the downbeat, not the backbeat.) Then as now Timbaland was a rapper whose main subject was producing: ''It's time to change my style/My rhythm, my ism, my prism, my beat mannerism.''</p>
        <p>Since then Timbaland has never stopped making hits, although some years were better than others. (The year of Ms. Elliott's ''Get Ur Freak On,'' 2001, was one triumphant year; 2006 was another.) And as part of his long campaign for visibility he never stopped making albums, all of which have included at least a fistful of breathtaking tracks. His 1998 solo debut, ''Tim's Bio: From the Motion Picture: Life From Da Bassment,'' was fidgetier and more severe than his earlier work. (It also introduced the world to a young rapper billed as ''Ludichris.'')</p>
        <p>His next album with Magoo, ''Indecent Proposal,'' from 2001, scrambled influences and rhythms and samples: fluttering tabla drums here, a smudgy house track there. And in 2003 the two released ''Under Construction Part II,'' a sequel of sorts to Ms. Elliott's ''Under Construction''; it was full of sparse, drum-driven dance music.</p>
        <p>Throughout, the common lyrical theme was frustration: Timbaland complained that he wasn't being given his due. No doubt most producers feel this way, including Timbaland's current antagonist, Mr. Storch. In ''Built Like That,'' his rather lame response to Timbaland's ''Give It to Me,'' Mr. Storch takes credit for Mr. Timberlake's ''Cry Me a River.'' (Mr. Storch is listed as one of three songwriters, alongside Timbaland and Mr. Timberlake; he isn't listed as a co-producer but does receive a credit for playing keyboards.) He also mentions Timbaland's protégé Nate Hills, known as Danja, who is emerging as a first-rate producer with a knack for melody. (He helped produce five of these songs, including ''Give It to Me,'' and produced one himself.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Storch raps, ''Your boy Danja got to hate you with a passion, man/He makes the hits while you taking all the credit, damn.'' It's inevitable, perhaps, that a beef between producers would devolve into a squabble over liner notes.</p>
        <p>In any case Timbaland wins this round, not just because of his decadelong track record but also because ''Give It to Me'' sounds so much better than ''Built Like That.'' It's an instantly addictive song built from a muscular rhythm and a few well-placed synthesizer notes. And Timbaland's half-rapped, half-sung verse fits snugly between Ms. Furtado's spooky segment (she always sounds as if she's just seen a ghost) and Mr. Timberlake's boyish taunts.</p>
        <p>Not every collision on ''Shock Value'' works this well, but all of them are worth hearing, even for those perverse people who don't consider themselves Timbaland fanatics. ''The Way I Are,'' featuring Keri Wilson and D.O.E., is a swirling electronic come-on. ''Oh Timbaland,'' the album's only true solo track, is built from a playful piano loop, menacing syncopations and strobed synthesizers. (He's obsessed with this last technique right now; you can hear it in Mr. Timberlake's ''My Love'' and in Omarion's ''Icebox.'')</p>
        <p>Even more intriguing are his experiments with rock, which dominate the album's second half. ''One &amp; Only,'' the Fall Out Boy collaboration, must be the most futuristic emo song ever: Timbaland creates a breakneck rock 'n' roll backbeat and then, after the second chorus, shifts to half time, changing the rhythm while keeping most of the sounds the same. ''Apologize'' showcases One Republic, a young band based in Los Angeles; Timbaland's hissing counterrhythms turn a handsome rock ballad into something even better.</p>
        <p>Inevitably, there are times when this CD feels more like a compilation, and times when Timbaland goes overboard trying to prevent that. Elton John's appearance comes at the end, in a song called ''2 Man Show.'' He doesn't sing, he only plays piano, but Timbaland goes out of his way to remind listeners who they're listening to. ''Come on, Elton,'' he keeps saying. Doesn't he trust us to read the liner notes?</p>
        <p>Maybe not, and who can blame him? In an age when songs are often mislabeled or unlabeled or sold without production information (as often happens at the iTunes shop), liner notes themselves are starting to seem obsolete. One day Timbaland will get his box set, including all the hits but also the shoulda-been-hits, by Brandy and Ms. Jade and Petey Pablo and -- well, it's a long list. In the meantime you can't blame him for seeking the spotlight any way he can. Unlike Mr. West, Timbaland will never be mesmerizing on the microphone, and so he'll probably never be an old-fashioned star. But maybe he's a new-fashioned star: a spectral one.</p>
        <p>Even when he doesn't have the microphone, Timbaland often overshadows whoever does. He's not one of those musical therapists who make singers sound more like themselves. On the contrary, he prides himself on challenging his clients. They have to find a way to work around his weird beats. (Many of his productions don't really make sense until you hear them a few times; he loves songs that sound wrong at first.) His music isn't predictable, but it's definitely recognizable. In that sense he's among the most assertive pop producers of all time.</p>
        <p>''Shock Value'' includes a track called ''Bounce,'' featuring Ms. Elliott, Mr. Timberlake and Dr. Dre. There's a heavy downbeat that almost sabotages the rapped verses; you can feel some syncopation, but you can't quite hear it. And then, at the end, everything stops. All that's left is a looped hiccupping sound -- the syncopation you thought you had imagined. It had been there the whole time, pushing the track forward, mischievously throwing the rappers off balance. And once you've heard it clear, it's impossible to ignore. Everything else about the song seems like an afterthought; that tricky little rhythm is the star.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
