<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Torture Chamber</title>
    <meta content="Sorrentino.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/books/review/Sorrentino.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837025"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Good War Is Hard to Find, A: The Art of Violence in America (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E6DB1530F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="932" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Torture Chamber</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Torture Chamber</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER SORRENTINO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorrentino, Christopher</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A GOOD WAR IS HARD TO FIND</p>
        <p>The Art of Violence in America.</p>
        <p>By David Griffith.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 189 pp. Soft Skull Press.</p>
        <p>Paper, $15.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fitting the Abu Ghraib photos into the context of American pop culture.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A GOOD WAR IS HARD TO FIND</p>
        <p>The Art of Violence in America.</p>
        <p>By David Griffith.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 189 pp. Soft Skull Press.</p>
        <p>Paper, $15.</p>
        <p>David Griffith opens his meditation on the Abu Ghraib photographs with an epigraph from Flannery O'Connor's story ''The Displaced Person'': Mrs. Shortley, awaiting the arrival of the Polish refugee family coming to work on the farm where she's employed, recalls newsreel footage of death camp victims: ''Before you could realize that it was real and take it into your head, the picture changed and a hollow-sounding voice was saying, 'Time marches on!' '' Mrs. Shortley's view of the displaced Guizac family is, in fact, prejudiced by the fleeting images she's seen on the screen: she fears they will have imported such ''murderous ways'' from Europe, ''like rats with typhoid fleas.''</p>
        <p>In a sense, the authors of our understanding of degradation, torture and mass murder aren't those zealous instructors of the previous century, the Hitlers and Pol Pots, but the technicians -- the photographers and cameramen who documented these genocidal achievements. Unlike Mrs. Shortley, we have had more than a half-century to learn the visual language of depravity, and to insulate ourselves from the raw shock of what we see. When the Abu Ghraib prison photos came to light in 2004, they entered a public sphere already saturated with graphic portrayals of horror. To Griffith, such images should ''have the power to obliterate all other circumstances of the day.'' It is the fact that we have ''taken them into our heads'' so utterly, so imperturbably, that concerns him. His objective in this, his first book, is to understand the sodden familiarity of the evidence of what took place at Abu Ghraib, and to grasp what he sees as our impoverished response to that evidence.</p>
        <p>In the manner of Susan Sontag's ''Regarding the Pain of Others'' and Roland Barthes's ''Camera Lucida,'' the book is quiet, offbeat, at times intensely personal. Griffith claims that ''the Abu Ghraib photos are the very picture of the American soul in conflict with itself,'' that the reaction to them ''calls attention not to a difference but a similarity in belief between author and audience.'' He sees an enormous gap between the viewing of disturbing images and contemplation of the ways in which we are implicated in the acts they portray. It's a valid observation, as we continue to fight a war whose strategic rationale, in part, is surely to allow us to continue to pay less for a gallon of gasoline than we do for a bag of Chips Ahoy. Regarding the United States, he asks, ''was there ever a country more naïvely, optimistically moral?'' It's not merely a species of political blindness to which he's referring; he's deeply distrustful of the tendency ''to seek a modern answer instead of an ancient one. The modern answer is abnormal psychology; the ancient problem is the existence of evil.'' Time marches on, indeed. Our reflexive reaction -- that the people involved were ''bad apples'' whose actions are inconsistent with the motives and overall conduct of the Americans in Iraq, he suggests, ''is the most harmful response imaginable from a spiritual standpoint.'' Likewise, Griffith is leery of the equally modern idea of seeking a legal solution to what is in his view a moral problem. ''The vast majority of attention given to the issue of torture has not focused on measures to ensure that human beings are not tortured, but in legalistic squabbles over what constitutes torture.''</p>
        <p>Griffith is less cogent when he identifies postmodern culture, which he views as an amoral void that desensitizes us to such imagery and converts it into spectacle, as a large component of the problem. For example: ''The language of 'Pulp Fiction,' '' he says, ''gives us the vocabulary to drown out the screams, to dismiss what we've seen, because it denies the seriousness of the violence.'' We've heard this before, and Griffith fails to bolster a specious argument. He overlooks the possibility that postmodern culture is a response to postmodernity itself, which is at least equally amoral, and that, for every ''Pulp Fiction,'' with its jive insouciance and willful moral vacuity, there are a dozen variations of ''Rambo,'' triumphally self-righteous films where a monochromatic moral certitude in favor of family, loyalty, patriotism and apple pie serves as the pretext for wanton slaughter and mayhem. These movies put on display what Barthes called ''the euphoria of men raised for a while above the constitutive ambiguity of everyday situations'' -- a fitting rubric for the gleeful sadism that stares back at us from the Abu Ghraib pictures.</p>
        <p>It's clear that Griffith is aware of and disturbed by his place in the postmodern moment: he describes his uneasiness when, at a Halloween party, he agrees to be photographed with a guest dressed as Charles Graner, the Army reservist convicted of mistreating prisoners, both men flashing the ''thumbs-up'' sign that punctuated many of the Abu Ghraib photos. Of course, Griffith is pondering a thoroughly postmodern episode; he observes that the poses of the soldiers that he imitates themselves comprise a farrago of Internet pornography, keg-party posturing and fraternity hazing. He might have subtitled his book ''The Evil of Banality.'' These collages were intended not to be hidden away but shared; digital keepsakes instantly forwarded around the globe -- an almost ingenuous approach to malice. The look in the eyes of Graner and his fellow tormentors doesn't fail to anticipate the world's gaze -- I have little doubt that they expected some measure of fame. What is absent from their expressions is any expectation of the world's opprobrium.</p>
        <p>Christopher Sorrentino's most recent novel is ''Trance.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Christopher Sorrentino's most recent novel is ''Trance.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
