<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Italian Scandal: The Sweet Life Turns Sour</title>
    <meta content="01rome" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/world/europe/01rome.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837373"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Extortion and Blackmail</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Italy</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kiefer, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corona, Fabrizio</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Extortion and Blackmail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prostitution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prostitution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Extortion and Blackmail</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Italy</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E5D61130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="858" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Italian Scandal: The Sweet Life Turns Sour</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Italian Scandal: The Sweet Life Turns Sour</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER KIEFER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kiefer, Peter</byline>
      <dateline>ROME, March 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Italian investigators in so-called Valettopoli scandal contend some valettes, or lightly-clothed showgirls, were lured by promise of stardom only to be used as bait in blackmailing scheme rigged by photographer Fabrizio Corona; say Corona hoped to lure rich and famous into compromising situations and threaten to publish photographs; scandal caught up sports stars, politicians and actors; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the list of Italy's countless contributions to Western civilization is the phenomenon of the paparazzi. Immortalized in Fellini's ''La Dolce Vita,'' the Italian character Paparazzo was originally romanticized as a photographer of the stars who was more mischievous than hazardous, a necessary appendage to Roman glamour.</p>
        <p>But that character has now been reduced to the likes of Fabrizio Corona. Mr. Corona, 33, is entering his third week in jail in southern Italy where he is being investigated on suspicion of involvement in a sex and blackmailing scheme that has shocked this country, which is no stranger to scandal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A blackmail scandal known as Valettopoli has tarred an array of sports stars, respected politicians, actors and general fame seekers in Italy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the list of Italy's countless contributions to Western civilization is the phenomenon of the paparazzi. Immortalized in Fellini's ''La Dolce Vita,'' the Italian character Paparazzo was originally romanticized as a photographer of the stars who was more mischievous than hazardous, a necessary appendage to Roman glamour.</p>
        <p>But that character has now been reduced to the likes of Fabrizio Corona. Mr. Corona, 33, is entering his third week in jail in southern Italy where he is being investigated on suspicion of involvement in a sex and blackmailing scheme that has shocked this country, which is no stranger to scandal.</p>
        <p>''I am like Robin Hood,'' Mr. Corona said during a televised interview just before his arrest. ''I steal from the rich and I give to myself.''</p>
        <p>The scandal, which has tarred an array of sports stars, respected politicians and actors, and general fame seekers, is called Valettopoli because of the central role played by valettes, the lightly clothed showgirls who serve as ornaments on a number of television talk shows.</p>
        <p>As investigators have framed their case, some valettes were lured by promises of stardom, only to be used as bait in a blackmailing scheme rigged by Mr. Corona and a well-known talent agent, Lele Mora.</p>
        <p>Investigators suspect that Mr. Mora, who has been warned not to leave the country and so is confined to one of his mansions, was drawing in the rich, the famous and the not so famous to parties where he hoped to create and document, with the aid of Mr. Corona and his camera, compromising situations involving celebrities and politicians.</p>
        <p>Though some of the pictures were tame, the threat of publication was enough for some of the subjects to succumb to blackmail, according to news reports.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corona, who ran a well-known photo agency, was arrested with a dozen other people this month. Prosecutors are considering charging him and other suspects with bribery, prostitution and the selling of drugs in high-end discos. Mr. Corona and Mr. Mora have denied wrongdoing; Mr. Corona said he was offering stars the chance to buy pictures and gossip at the same rates he would offer to publications.</p>
        <p>Investigators recently discovered Mr. Corona's secret photo archive, which includes tens of thousands of photos, suggesting that more incriminating photos could be found.</p>
        <p>But the drama does not stop with Mr. Mora, Mr. Corona and the showgirls .</p>
        <p>There are the soccer stars Francesco Totti and Adriano Leite Ribeiro, known simply as Adriano, both of whom, according to the investigators, were threatened with the publication of photos and details of supposed dalliances unless they paid blackmail. (According to widespread news reports, Mr. Totti paid but Mr. Ribeiro did not.)</p>
        <p>There is the 22-year-old daughter of the former prime minister Silvio Berlusconi, who allegedly paid 20,000 euros (about $26,600) to keep a photo of her leaving a Milan nightclub out of the newspapers.</p>
        <p>There is Clemente Mastella, Italy's minister of justice and a staunch defender of Catholic values, who denied that he was present on a yacht off the Amalfi coast on which prostitutes and cocaine were circulating; there is no firm evidence against him.</p>
        <p>And there is Silvio Sircana, right-hand man and spokesman for Prime Minister Romano Prodi. Mr. Sircana wrote a mea culpa letter after newspapers printed a photo of him in his car, pulled curbside, chatting with a transsexual prostitute through the passenger-side window. He said this was an innocent mistake.</p>
        <p>The whole affair is spilling out in Italian newspapers and on talk shows and has more than one commentator making the obvious parallels between Italy's seamier side and its love affair with reality television.</p>
        <p>''Unfortunately, Valettopoli is something that is very much part of the Italian culture,'' said Aldo Grasso, who writes a column for Corriere della Sera about television and Italian culture.</p>
        <p>The foil to the type of people that Mr. Grasso objects to is the lead prosecutor in the case, Henry John Woodcock, a 39-year-old Anglo-Italian. Mr. Woodcock has interrogated a string of A-list celebrities, businessmen and showgirls. And each day newspapers are filled with his plans for the investigation and the previous day's discoveries.</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Woodcock's calls was to Raoul Bova, a movie star in Italy and Hollywood. Mr. Bova was interviewed this week in Potenza. He said investigators found a photo of him seated at a dinner table with more than a dozen people from Mr. Corona's archive. Investigators wanted to know if Mr. Bova had been blackmailed. He said he had not been.</p>
        <p>''The sensation that I had was crazy,'' said Mr. Bova, who in an interview expressed anger at Italian authorities, magistrates and the media over his treatment in what he said was obviously a trifling event.</p>
        <p>''In some way, even being an honest person who didn't do anything, like me, and then to find myself in the newspapers and on the news programs and in Italian magazines, in a certain way it has created suspicion or doubts,'' he said. ''Like, if you are on the news, then you had to have done something. The people don't think that is all just show business. It has become buffoonery.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
