<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Secret Sharer</title>
    <meta content="01room" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/thecity/01room.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837285"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEW YORK OBSERVED"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Beyer, Gregory</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Upper West Side (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E5DB1130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="992" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Secret Sharer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Secret Sharer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GREGORY BEYER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beyer, Gregory</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gregory Beyer New York Observed essay on his mysterious roommate, Ben, who rarely appears but always pays his rent on time; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LAST November, when our previous roommate left our Upper West Side apartment, we acquired a cheerful graduate student named Ben. My roommates, Tim and Justin, agreed with me that he seemed like a nice enough fellow when we interviewed him, and we didn't think much of it when a few weeks passed with no sign of him. Probably he had a month left on his previous lease and was taking his time.</p>
        <p>Then one day he arrived, and I left him shuffling around his room, fully expecting to find him settled when I returned. Hours later I came back and found five garbage bags by the front door, some labeled ''Trash,'' some ''Goodwill.'' I peered into the room. It was much cleaner than before, and nothing had been moved in. Ben was gone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Absence makes the heart grow fonder. So we are very fond of our roommate Ben.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LAST November, when our previous roommate left our Upper West Side apartment, we acquired a cheerful graduate student named Ben. My roommates, Tim and Justin, agreed with me that he seemed like a nice enough fellow when we interviewed him, and we didn't think much of it when a few weeks passed with no sign of him. Probably he had a month left on his previous lease and was taking his time.</p>
        <p>Then one day he arrived, and I left him shuffling around his room, fully expecting to find him settled when I returned. Hours later I came back and found five garbage bags by the front door, some labeled ''Trash,'' some ''Goodwill.'' I peered into the room. It was much cleaner than before, and nothing had been moved in. Ben was gone.</p>
        <p>Weeks went by with no sign of him. Rent checks appeared on time, slipped under the door. Far better, we agreed, than a couch-dwelling slob, or someone who couldn't pay, or an oboe player. As weeks and months passed, there was nothing much to say about the situation, until one evening Justin announced, ''Ben came by the other night.''</p>
        <p>''Ah, a sighting?'' I asked, leaning against my bedroom door. ''What did he want?''</p>
        <p>''Oh, nothing,'' Justin said. ''He just dropped off the check.'' I marveled at this, then slunk back to my room.</p>
        <p>Mostly the three of us keep to ourselves and have at best vague understandings of what the others do with their lives.</p>
        <p>Justin, a jovial 27-year-old (five years my senior) who sometimes begins sentences addressed to me with ''When I was your age,'' works in tree maintenance. Once he mentioned a gardening job on a rooftop, and ever since I have imagined that he spends his days trimming bonsai trees and shaping hedges to look like historical figures on the swanky rooftops of New York's elite. To save time, he swings among the buildings on a vine.</p>
        <p>Tim, who is near 30, does something with computers, and if you ask how he is doing, he will sigh and say ''Hanging in there'' to let you know how busy he is. An entire rack of his bookshelf is devoted to Superman books, comics and movies, and the stern superhero gazes out on our living room and hallway from framed posters that barely contain the rippling muscle and cape-filling wind. When I have people over, I am quick -- perhaps too quick -- to point out that these items do not belong to me.</p>
        <p>''My roommate is really into Superman,'' I say.</p>
        <p>''I'll bet he is,'' they reply.</p>
        <p>But in spite of our varied interests and pursuits, we share a fascination with our mysterious visitor.</p>
        <p>Our chief and most-discussed theory is that Ben is crazy. One night, perhaps, we will be hacked to bits. Or else his room will be used, at some undisclosed point down the line, as a secret meeting place for a gang of slippery characters who speak in clipped and cryptic sentences, and call him ''Boss.'' There can be little doubt that his friendliness, boyish looks and unerring punctuality with the delivery of rent checks (obviously acquired in some cunning and bloody way) are designed to put us at ease and conceal his sinister purposes.</p>
        <p>THERE is also the matter of the vacant room. So far, questions of convenience have trumped those of roommate ethics (murky to begin with): we use the room for bike storage, and one night, instead of relegating a visiting friend to the couch, I offered him the empty bed (''Leave it looking like you found it,'' I instructed). For a time I toyed with the idea of posting a sign on the door that said ''Library,'' but we settled on converting it to a bar, and figure Ben will be pleased with the speakeasy ambience it will lend to the secret meeting.</p>
        <p>A few weeks after the first sighting, it was Tim who caught a glimpse.</p>
        <p>''He brought his girlfriend,'' Tim said. ''He showed her the place, and then they walked through Riverside Park.''</p>
        <p>I imagined and enacted their conversation: ''This is where I don't go running. This is where I don't watch the sunset and where I don't admire the slow barges on the Hudson.''</p>
        <p>Tim interjected: ''Actually, he used the conditional tense. 'This is where I could go running.' ''</p>
        <p>One recent Friday afternoon, the front-door buzzer rang, and a minute later Ben appeared at the door. He said he was headed out West for spring break to go skiing with his girlfriend and wanted to pick up some things. This was puzzling. We stood in the hallway talking for a while. He said he would be graduating in May, and I wanted to ask what would happen then. Could it really be true? Would he leave us?</p>
        <p>Our conversation felt very natural, and it occurred to me that it would be a perfect time for him to kill me. He didn't. For a criminal mastermind, I thought, he was awfully likable. I'd fallen into his trap, but I didn't care. I stifled a ''Will I see you again?'' and he disappeared into his room to gather up whatever it was that he needed.</p>
        <p>It's a very nice room, and the only one in the apartment that lets in any natural light. The bed, which Ben could sleep on, is made up, and there are two pillows on which he could rest his head after a long day. His closet contains a rack of 10 collared shirts he could wear, and, inexplicably, a hamper of dirty laundry, which he could one day load into the washing machine in the basement. On the closet shelf sits a board game called New York in a Box, a Monopoly knockoff that allows two to six players to enjoy New York experiences like traffic jams, muggings and getting elected mayor. Someday, if he ever comes back, we could play it.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK OBSERVED</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
