<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Now, the Next Big Project</title>
    <meta content="01hunt" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/realestate/01hunt.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837239"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE HUNT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Joyce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lunney, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/The Hunt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E4D81030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1097" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Now, the Next Big Project</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Now, the Next Big Project</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>The Hunt column on search by Alex Lunney for co-op apartment in Manhattan for under $400,000; found alcove studio apartment in Lincoln Towers complex on West End Avenue near Hudson River for $385,000; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALEX LUNNEY wanted his first co-op apartment to have one distinctive feature -- possibly a lovely view, a wood-burning fireplace or an outdoor space suitable for grilling. He wasn't especially clear on what that feature would be, as long as there was ''one thing that popped, something about the apartment I really liked.''</p>
        <p>Still, he said, ''beggars can't be choosers.'' With a price range of $300,000-something, ''I certainly was not in any position to demand anything.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alex Lunney wanted his first co-op apartment to have one distinctive feature. He found an alcove studio with a remarkable view.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALEX LUNNEY wanted his first co-op apartment to have one distinctive feature -- possibly a lovely view, a wood-burning fireplace or an outdoor space suitable for grilling. He wasn't especially clear on what that feature would be, as long as there was ''one thing that popped, something about the apartment I really liked.''</p>
        <p>Still, he said, ''beggars can't be choosers.'' With a price range of $300,000-something, ''I certainly was not in any position to demand anything.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lunney, 28, grew up in Bronxville, N.Y. While he attended Colgate University, he lived in student housing, always with roommates, except for one semester by himself in a room that was ''smaller than the cells allowed under the Geneva Convention for prisoners of war,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Afterward, he returned to his parents' home, commuting by train to his job in television advertising sales. But he said he knew it was ''time to start leading my adult life for real,'' which meant buying his own place.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lunney always enjoyed having a big project to tackle, some kind of ''challenge or hobby outside of work and my personal life,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''I am better at taking on one big thing at a time than multiple small things at a time.'' He had already met three goals: He earned his private pilot's license, he took improvisation classes and performed onstage, and he ran a marathon. The hunt for a home was next.</p>
        <p>Agents holding open houses often asked who his agent was, so he contacted Marzia Verdi Kennedy of the Fox Residential Group, who had helped a friend buy a place. They began the hunt in Hell's Kitchen, near Mr. Lunney's office, which he knew to be a lively neighborhood. He aimed for a one-bedroom co-op costing up to $350,000. (That was later adjusted down in size and up in price, to a studio for up to $400,000.)</p>
        <p>Having seen some low-floor apartments with airshaft views, he knew he needed light. And visits to some tiny Greenwich Village apartments taught him that he needed enough space for ''a real table and real chairs around that table,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''A half-fridge against the wall in the living room wasn't going to do it for me,'' Mr. Lunney said.</p>
        <p>He checked out a one-bedroom co-op on West 45th Street. It was ''a nice block but across from a strip club,'' he said. What would his parents think when they visited?</p>
        <p>The layout, with almost no wall space, was a problem. One wall held the kitchen, while the others had windows or doors. ''It was terrible as far as a setup,'' Mr. Lunney said. ''Where are you going to put your couch?''</p>
        <p>A one-bedroom on far East 72nd Street was tempting, but inconveniently located. ''The crosstown bus at rush hour can drive you crazy,'' he said. ''And a taxi takes just as long.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Kennedy was fond of Lincoln Towers, the eight-building complex on West End Avenue in the 60s that converted from rentals to co-ops 20 years ago. The apartments had the kind of layouts and light that Mr. Lunney wanted.</p>
        <p>In most places, she said, ''the priority of the view doesn't go to the small apartments.''</p>
        <p>Not here. These buildings had well-oriented studios on high floors. Mr. Lunney was surprised to find one with a view of the Hudson River, ''something I hadn't seen in a studio,'' he said.</p>
        <p>That one was a real fixer-upper. The seller was ''going through a divorce, and it was showing,'' he said. ''The kitchen and bathroom were falling apart. It looked like the bathroom had been flooded and nobody cleaned it up.''</p>
        <p>His offer of $350,000 was accepted. But he backed out, because he felt pressured to close, and the seller neglected to provide some requested documents. After nearly a year of hunting, it was the first place he felt was worth buying. (It later sold for $340,000.)</p>
        <p>A building on nearby Broadway had a similarly nice view, but it had a loft area with a ceiling six feet high. Mr. Lunney is 6-foot-1. It seemed like half of a two-bedroom that had been split.</p>
        <p>''A lot of apartments had a wonky layout, and after seeing the layout in the Lincoln Towers buildings and knowing you could have a nice, simple alcove studio that was actually designed to be an alcove studio, then I didn't want to settle for a six-foot ceiling,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He returned to Lincoln Towers. He wasn't interested in units on low floors, or those with views soon to be obliterated by new construction.</p>
        <p>Two north-facing alcove studios came available at the same time. One had a stark black-and-white kitchen. He was dazzled. But the windows opened directly onto the construction site for a new condominium tower, 200 West End Avenue.</p>
        <p>The other, a few floors higher and down the hall, had a remarkable view that would be only partly obscured by the construction. Both were listed at $399,000, with a monthly maintenance in the mid-$800s.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lunney chose the view, knowing he was in a good negotiating position because he had a fallback. He bought his apartment, more than 550 square feet, for $385,000.</p>
        <p>In the winter, he moved in with just an air mattress and a card table. He had fun buying furniture -- a real table with real chairs, and a couch big enough for lounging and lying down. He didn't know that the couch was so big it wouldn't fit in the elevator, thereby requiring the use of a furniture disassembly service, or that his building had rigid rules governing delivery hours and insurance.</p>
        <p>''It is the first time I have been living on my own since my Geneva Convention room back at school, and I have thoroughly enjoyed it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lunney has more closet space than he can use. He was stunned to learn the alcove studio had previously been home to a married couple with three young children.</p>
        <p>The view is better than he realized. ''I see planes traveling up the V.F.R. corridor,'' he said -- along the Hudson River, where aircraft use visual flight rules. ''I didn't know about the aviation traffic when I was looking at the apartment. It is something I realized after, which has endeared the apartment to me even more.''</p>
        <p>As for his next big challenge, ''it's tough because I've clocked off big things at the top of my list so I am actually struggling a little,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lunney said it might be a bareboat charter -- renting a boat with no captain or crew -- in the Virgin Islands.</p>
        <p>THE HUNT E-mail: thehunt@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: thehunt@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
