<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Recalling Wild Last Day In 1970</title>
    <meta content="01hockey" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837385"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY: SUNDAY SHOOTOUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Minnesota Wild</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E3DE1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1080" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Recalling Wild Last Day In 1970</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF Z. KLEIN and KARL-ERIC REIF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Jeff Z; Reif, Karl-Eric</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With eight closely bunched teams vying for the last four playoff slots in the N.H.L.'s Eastern Conference, an intriguing, even wacky finish could well be in store when the regular season draws to a close next weekend.</p>
        <p>But it would have to go a long way to be as bizarre and tension-filled as the denouement of the 1970 East Division playoff race.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With eight closely bunched teams vying for the last four playoff slots in the N.H.L.'s Eastern Conference, an intriguing, even wacky finish could well be in store when the regular season draws to a close next weekend.</p>
        <p>But it would have to go a long way to be as bizarre and tension-filled as the denouement of the 1970 East Division playoff race.</p>
        <p>On the final day of the regular season 37 years ago, the badly slumping Rangers trailed defending champion Montreal by 2 points for the fourth and final playoff berth. The Rangers played host to third-place Detroit in a matinee, and the Canadiens visited Chicago that night.</p>
        <p>''It was a tremendous season,'' recalled Vic Hadfield, who scored 20 goals off the left wing for those Rangers. ''It was so tight all the way right down to the end.''</p>
        <p>A Rangers victory and a Montreal loss would have left them tied in points. But the Canadiens had a five-goal advantage in the tie breaker then in effect -- goals for. The Rangers needed more than a victory; they needed a blowout.</p>
        <p>They got it. Throwing everything they had into the attack, the desperate Rangers poured 65 shots on Detroit goalie Roger Crozier and rolled up a 9-3 lead early in the third period. Looking for even more, Coach Emile Francis repeatedly pulled goalie Ed Giacomin for the extra attacker. It did not add anything; in fact, the Red Wings hit the empty net twice for a 9-5 final score. But the Rangers had the high-scoring victory they needed.</p>
        <p>''That was really unbelievable because that just never happens,'' Hadfield said. ''But I remember the fans just going crazy.''</p>
        <p>The pressure was on the Canadiens. But they did not necessarily have to win in Chicago. All they had to do to make the playoffs was score at least five goals.</p>
        <p>But the Blackhawks were playing for first place, and they needed to win. Sure enough, the Canadiens fell behind by 5-2 early in the third period. They needed three more goals. So they put goalie Rogie Vachon on the bench for the extra man -- and proceeded to surrender five empty-netters without adding to their total. Montreal lost, 10-2, and missed the playoffs for the only time from the 1948-49 season to the 1994-95 season.</p>
        <p>Hadfield remembered the evening, saying: ''Emile Francis was able to bring in Tim Horton to strengthen our blue line. Timmy and myself, we took our wives after the matinee game to the Copacabana to see Tom Jones. We were going in and out of the Copacabana to find out who was winning and what the score was'' in Chicago.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, Mickey Redmond, who was playing with the Canadiens that night, remembers almost nothing about it.</p>
        <p>''I just remember that it was a strange situation,'' Redmond said. ''And that for us on the Canadiens, coming off Stanley Cups in '68 and '69, it was a real drop. It was a tough night for the organization all right.''</p>
        <p>Valuing Home Ice</p>
        <p>At the top of the standings, the race for first place over all is even hotter than it has been all season. Buffalo, Nashville, Detroit, Anaheim and Vancouver are all contending for the Presidents' Trophy that comes with first place, as well as home-ice advantage throughout the playoffs.</p>
        <p>That advantage is a fairly substantial one. Since 1980, when the N.H.L. playoffs expanded to 16 teams, the home team's record in Game 7 is 56-31, a .644 winning percentage.</p>
        <p>Home ice seems to count for even more in the ultimate situation: Game 7 of the Stanley Cup finals. The last three Cups were won in Game 7 by the home team -- Carolina last year, Tampa Bay in 2004 and the Devils in 2003. In fact, in the 14 times that the Cup finals have gone to Game 7, the visiting team has won only twice (when the Maple Leafs won in Detroit in 1945 and the Canadiens won in Chicago in 1971).</p>
        <p>Still, with many fans and players expressing something like contempt for the idea of trying to win the Presidents' Trophy (because, supposedly, it saps players' energy), some have suggested that the reward be increased. One suggestion is that the trophy winner be given an automatic place in a projected international club championship tournament.</p>
        <p>Such action, however, remains speculation.</p>
        <p>''While we have agreed that we will actively explore additional games and competitive tournaments between N.H.L. and International Ice Hockey Federation teams,'' Bill Daly, the N.H.L.'s deputy commissioner, said Friday in an e-mail message, ''we have not reached a definitive agreement on the specifics of those opportunities.''</p>
        <p>The Hockey Poll</p>
        <p>For its current issue, The Hockey News polled 283 N.H.L. players from all 30 teams on various topics. Some answers are surprising.</p>
        <p>The players chose overwhelmingly to change nothing about the way the game is played in areas like fighting, penalties, schedule length and shootouts. The only change they endorsed: more interconference games.</p>
        <p>Other poll findings:</p>
        <p>The team they would most like to be traded to: Toronto, followed by the Rangers. Team they would least like to be traded to: Buffalo, followed by Edmonton and the Islanders.</p>
        <p>Best player in the league this season: Sidney Crosby of Pittsburgh. Most respected player: Joe Sakic of Colorado. Most hated player: Sean Avery of the Rangers. Most overrated player: a virtual dead heat among Avery, Bryan McCabe of Toronto and Brad Richards of Tampa Bay.</p>
        <p>Notes</p>
        <p>The Atlanta Thrashers are on the verge of qualifying for the postseason for the first time since the club was founded in 1999. Playoff dates would help the finances of the team, which leads the league in comp tickets. According to N.H.L. figures, the Thrashers have given away an average of more than 2,800 tickets a game this season.</p>
        <p>Jack Johnson made his much-anticipated N.H.L. debut Thursday in Los Angeles. Johnson, a 20-year-old Indianapolis native, completed his sophomore year at Michigan as his team's leader in penalty minutes and was first among college defensemen in goals and second in points.</p>
        <p>He is expected to be a star rearguard in the mold of Rob Blake, his Kings teammate and childhood idol, but his coming-out party was not all he might have hoped for. Blake sat out with a neck strain, while Johnson failed to hit the score sheet in a 4-2 loss to Vancouver and was sent somersaulting from a hip check by Jan Bulis.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY: SUNDAY SHOOTOUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
