<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Composure and Whistles Keep U.C.L.A. at Bay</title>
    <meta content="01glier" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/sports/ncaabasketball/01glier.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837463"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Officiating (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">University of California</org>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Florida</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E3DC1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="697" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Composure and Whistles Keep U.C.L.A. at Bay</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Composure and Whistles Keep U.C.L.A. at Bay</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAY GLIER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glier, Ray</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, March 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is called blitzing the ball screen, and U.C.L.A. does it as well as any team in college basketball. The tactic works this way: An opponent tries to set a screen at the top of the key, and the Bruins immediately jump the ball handler with two players.</p>
        <p>U.C.L.A. defenders then keep their hands out, pretending not to foul, but they throw hips and body checks, and an opponent's offense breaks down under double-team pressure. It is why the Bruins held their first four N.C.A.A. tournament opponents, including high-scoring Kansas, to an average of 50.2 points a game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Florida would have none of U.C.L.A.’s aggressive, physical play, and neither would the three officials in the Gators’ victory Saturday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is called blitzing the ball screen, and U.C.L.A. does it as well as any team in college basketball. The tactic works this way: An opponent tries to set a screen at the top of the key, and the Bruins immediately jump the ball handler with two players.</p>
        <p>U.C.L.A. defenders then keep their hands out, pretending not to foul, but they throw hips and body checks, and an opponent's offense breaks down under double-team pressure. It is why the Bruins held their first four N.C.A.A. tournament opponents, including high-scoring Kansas, to an average of 50.2 points a game.</p>
        <p>But Florida would have none of that aggressive, physical play, and neither would the three officials in the Gators' 76-66 national semifinal victory against U.C.L.A. Saturday night.</p>
        <p>Florida's guards stayed poised in the first 10 minutes of the game under the pressure, stepping through the double-teams or keeping their dribbles alive. The Gators led by 29-23 at the half, but it could have been a larger margin if Florida had not missed at least a half-dozen open shots.</p>
        <p>''They try and be aggressive, they try and get the ball out of the guard's hands,'' said Taurean Green, the Florida point guard. ''You've got to be strong with the ball and make the easy play.''</p>
        <p>The Gators made 10 turnovers in the first half against the pressure, but they also managed to get any open shot they wanted.</p>
        <p>For their part, the officials did not let U.C.L.A. play too aggressively. The Bruins were whistled for five fouls in the first four minutes.</p>
        <p>Two of the fouls were called on guard Aaron Afflalo, the Bruins' leading scorer, who was forced to the bench and played only five minutes in the first half. The game was officiated much differently from the first national semifinal between Ohio State and Georgetown, a much more physical contest.</p>
        <p>''In a game like that, you'd think it should be physical,'' said Luc Richard Mbah a Moute, the U.C.L.A. forward. ''Both teams are very physical. They should let us play. But there's nothing we can do about it. A lot of guys got in foul trouble, and it really affected us.''</p>
        <p>U.C.L.A.'s game is defense. Once that is neutralized, the Bruins become more ordinary. They are not very deep and they are not particularly tall. Florida outrebounded the Bruins, 43-26.</p>
        <p>U.C.L.A. changed tactics in the second half and tried to double the low post after Green and Lee Humphrey, the Gators' guards, made only 2 of 7 3-point attempts in the first half.</p>
        <p>Florida's big men, Joakim Noah and Al Horford, simply kicked the ball out of the post after allowing the double team to get to them, and Humphrey, Green and Corey Brewer made their shots. They were 9 of 22 from behind the 3-point line.</p>
        <p>''The guards did a good job of getting to the open areas,'' Horford said. ''They hit some big shots and broke the game open.''</p>
        <p>U.C.L.A. Coach Ben Howland then put his team in a man-to-man defense, and the Gators shredded that, too, once with an over-the-shoulder pass from Green driving the lane to Humphrey curling to the high left wing. Humphrey made a 3-pointer.</p>
        <p>The scoreboard read 13 minutes 49 seconds, and Howland was out of timeouts. He was out of options, too.</p>
        <p>If it was a game spectators thought they had seen before, it was. Just as in 2006, when the Gators buried the Bruins with ball movement in the national championship game, Florida beat U.C.L.A. with passing and options.</p>
        <p>Brewer led the Gators with 19 points, Humphrey added 14, and Green contributed 10.</p>
        <p>The big difference was Chris Richard, the 6-foot-9 senior, who made all 7 of his shots from the field.</p>
        <p>Richard outscored the Bruins' reserves by himself, 16-12.</p>
        <p>Green said that the other significant factor was the early foul trouble of Afflalo, who did not make a field goal until 6:18 remained.</p>
        <p>Even then, he had to work for the points. The scoreboard operator gave the points to Florida before switching his 3-pointer back to U.C.L.A., but the Bruins were behind , 58-45, and could not rely on their defense to bail them out.</p>
        <p>N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
