<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Big Man, Big Trade</title>
    <meta content="01hoops" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/sports/basketball/01hoops.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837392"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="N.B.A."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Chicago Bulls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Cleveland Cavaliers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Chicago Bulls</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Curry, Eddy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Thomas, Isiah</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Paxson, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E0DE1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1373" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Big Man, Big Trade</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Deal for Curry Continues to Unfold for Knicks and Bulls</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eddy Curry, his jersey hanging loosely over his shorts as Knicks practice ended last Thursday, stood on the court laughing with his coach and advocate, Isiah Thomas.</p>
        <p>Powerfully peaceful at 7 feet and 300 pounds, Curry not only carries Thomas's legacy in his outstretched hands, but also still holds a link to the Bulls' future.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Since Chicago traded Eddy Curry to the Knicks in October 2005, he has grown to symbolize the divergent paths of two franchises, run by former opposing guards.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Eddy Curry, his jersey hanging loosely over his shorts as Knicks practice ended last Thursday, stood on the court laughing with his coach and advocate, Isiah Thomas.</p>
        <p>Powerfully peaceful at 7 feet and 300 pounds, Curry not only carries Thomas's legacy in his outstretched hands, but also still holds a link to the Bulls' future.</p>
        <p>Since Chicago traded Curry to the Knicks in October 2005, he has grown to symbolize the divergent paths of the two franchises, run by former opposing guards. Thomas, the Knicks' president, has constructed his team by taking risks and rehabilitating careers, while John Paxson, vice president of the Bulls, has taken a systematic and defense-oriented approach to reviving a team that had fallen off the N.B.A. map.</p>
        <p>''I just want to show the Knicks that they made the right decision by getting me over here,'' Curry said quietly Wednesday, after scoring 25 points to lift the Knicks to a desperate victory over Cleveland.</p>
        <p>He has had his breakout offensive games and his defensive breakdowns, too, averaging 19 points and 6.9 rebounds. He has become the Knicks' leading scorer, though not quite the leader of an injury-depleted team scrambling to stay in the Eastern Conference playoff race.</p>
        <p>The Bulls, meanwhile, clinched their third straight postseason berth Thursday.</p>
        <p>''They've moved on,'' Curry, 24, said, ''and so have I.''</p>
        <p>But the trade will continue to reverberate through June, when the draft completes the transaction.</p>
        <p>The Knicks gave up their first-round pick last year, No. 2 over all, which Chicago used to get the rangy power forward Tyrus Thomas of Louisiana State. They also gave the Bulls the chance to swap first-round picks in this June's draft.</p>
        <p>Bulls fans who were still recovering from post-Michael Jordan depression might have criticized Ben Wallace for not being the missing piece to fulfill mighty expectations of this young Chicago team. But they can now be distracted by another fantasy: claiming the Knicks' lottery number.</p>
        <p>''Bulls fans don't need a lot of added incentive to cheer against Isiah Thomas and the Knicks,'' said Carmen DeFalco, co-host of a radio talk show on ESPN 1000 in Chicago. ''But this has definitely added something extra to it. You can tell, people are seeing how the Knicks do down the stretch. You still get the, 'Let's hope the Knicks continue to lose.' ''</p>
        <p>But those who think the Bulls could land Greg Oden or Kevin Durant with the No. 1 pick would be mathematically challenged. The team that finishes with the worst record has a 25 percent chance of landing the top spot.</p>
        <p>By comparison, if the Knicks finish with the 10th-worst record in the league, for example, they have only a 1.1 percent chance of landing the No. 1 pick in the draft, according to the N.B.A.'s lottery calculations.</p>
        <p>''You can sit here and wish that you get a great pick, but we didn't do the deal thinking that,'' Paxson said. ''We did the deal hoping that we'd have a little better position in the draft.''</p>
        <p>Like many teams that stood pat at the trading deadline, the Bulls are waiting to find out their draft position. Then they could have a better chance to trade it, perhaps to get the low-post player they have lacked since Curry's departure. Paxson was unwilling to break up his young nucleus to acquire Pau Gasol from Memphis in February.</p>
        <p>The Bulls still need an elite offensive player who can consistently win games. Their perimeter players are the team's strength and as well as its weakness, while the Bulls' defense reflects the discipline of Coach Scott Skiles.</p>
        <p>Paxson built the team to suit Skiles, disposing of players he inherited upon becoming vice president in April 2003. (Thomas signed one of them, the quick shooter Jamal Crawford.) The Bulls' approach has been to bring in players from structured and successful college or international programs.</p>
        <p>Their regular starting lineup features an N.B.A. champion (Wallace, with Detroit), an N.C.A.A. champion (Ben Gordon, with Connecticut), a two-time Final Four participant (Kirk Hinrich, with Kansas) and an Olympic champion (Andrés Nocioni, with Argentina).</p>
        <p>Small forward Luol Deng went to the Final Four in his one season at Duke, and his background attracted the Bulls. Deng's father is an exiled Sudanese diplomat, and his family lived in Egypt and London. Then Deng went to a prep school in New Jersey, Blair Academy.</p>
        <p>''I feel like lucky to be doing what I'm doing,'' Deng said last week by telephone.</p>
        <p>Skiles runs a tight ship. His players must keep their shirts tucked in at all times, even during practice. That discipline makes the game easier for the Bulls, Deng said, ''because we play so hard against each other.''</p>
        <p>Paxson said, ''It takes a strong coach to understand, yes, it's about the present and the future as well.''</p>
        <p>The Bulls miss Nocioni, a power forward who has sat out all but one game since Feb. 5 because of plantar fasciitis in his right foot. His toughness and ability to pop off screens and hit long jumpers gave Chicago an edge that Tyrus Thomas lacks.</p>
        <p>''We all acknowledge that Tyrus doesn't have a lot of basketball experience,'' Paxson said. ''He is a player developing and growing, and the more minutes he plays only helps.''</p>
        <p>His tendency to get into foul trouble and his lack of strength may be liabilities now, but Skiles called Thomas's shot-blocking timing uncanny.</p>
        <p>The Knicks' own shot-blocking and rebounding talent, Renaldo Balkman, the 20th pick over all last June, has been an energetic addition. But several scouts and general managers contend that Tyrus Thomas had the greater upside.</p>
        <p>The Bulls and the Knicks are familiar with the downside. During their six playoffless years after Jordan retired, Chicago had a 119-341 record, the worst in the league. The Bulls won 47 games in 2005, but last season they had to win 10 of their last 11 games to finish with 41 victories and secure the final playoff spot.</p>
        <p>''I'm realistic,'' Paxson said. ''I know we're still far away from being a great team. But we feel like we're moving in a positive direction.''</p>
        <p>When asked about the Bulls' success, Isiah Thomas smiled.</p>
        <p>''They've done a nice job,'' he said. ''But when did Jordan leave? And they made the playoffs when? Well, it takes time.''</p>
        <p>As for Curry, Thomas said: ''I've always had a great belief in him. I really do think it's the tip of the iceberg.</p>
        <p>''One day he'll look up, and there'll be no more Shaq, there'll be no more Duncan. All those guys will be retired and it'll be him and these other guys.''</p>
        <p>Curry, who was drafted out of high school, underachieved with the Bulls. They became concerned that he could be predisposed to a heart ailment -- and Curry would not agree to a DNA test to confirm it. Thomas took the risk of signing him to a $56 million contract, with approval from the Knicks' doctors.</p>
        <p>''I can't ever repay him for the opportunity that he gave me, the way he let me really flourish as a player here,'' said Curry, who said he has had no problems with his heart.</p>
        <p>When Thomas was named coach in the wake of the failed Larry Brown tenure, he assumed responsibility for the roster he assembled. He received a long-term contract extension last month, before the team stumbled with injuries and Curry faded.</p>
        <p>''I'm not looking to accelerate; I'm looking to build it and do it right,'' Thomas said. ''I have the patience, persistence and stubbornness to do it. I'm confident enough in myself in basketball -- this I know. Give me a chemistry test and I may flunk that. I'm pretty confident about what I know and what I've done.''</p>
        <p>If the Knicks are living on visions of what could be, the Bulls are focusing on advancing to the second round of the playoffs for the first time in three seasons. Chicago (43-31) has the most victories in intraconference and divisional play and has played 26 times on national television, including NBA TV.</p>
        <p>''You got to get solid ground before you can take that next step,'' Skiles said. ''Yeah, maybe you get lucky and win a lottery. But right now we're on pretty solid ground.''</p>
        <p>N.B.A.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
