<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ex-Basketball Star Helps Rebuild His Hometown</title>
    <meta content="01njcolNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/01njcol.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837214"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="JERSEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jersey City (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Clippers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Coyne, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dehere, Terry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Clippers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906EFD91030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="864" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ex-Basketball Star Helps Rebuild His Hometown</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ex-Basketball Star Helps Rebuild His Hometown</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Kevin Coyne</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Coyne, Kevin</byline>
      <dateline>Jersey City</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kevin Coyne Jersey column on former Los Angeles Clippers basketball star Terry DeHere, who has returned to his hometown of Jersey City, NJ; DeHere is developing subsidized housing and planning to build luxury condos; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE first steps on the basketball journey that took Terry DeHere out of his hometown, then brought him back again, led down the scrubby hill from Randolph Avenue, along a sneaker-scuffed dirt path and through a chain-link gate onto the court that was known at the time simply as Garfield Park.</p>
        <p>''My mom could actually look out the window and see that I was fine,'' Mr. DeHere said as he stopped at the court on his rounds one recent day, pointing toward the house where he lived until his bull's-eye jump shot lifted him to Seton Hall and the National Basketball Association. The court was renamed for him after he turned pro and gave $75,000 to refurbish it. ''This is where I stayed 8, 10 hours a day, easy.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Terry DeHere, an N.B.A. grandee, chose to come back to his home city in the off-seasons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE first steps on the basketball journey that took Terry DeHere out of his hometown, then brought him back again, led down the scrubby hill from Randolph Avenue, along a sneaker-scuffed dirt path and through a chain-link gate onto the court that was known at the time simply as Garfield Park.</p>
        <p>''My mom could actually look out the window and see that I was fine,'' Mr. DeHere said as he stopped at the court on his rounds one recent day, pointing toward the house where he lived until his bull's-eye jump shot lifted him to Seton Hall and the National Basketball Association. The court was renamed for him after he turned pro and gave $75,000 to refurbish it. ''This is where I stayed 8, 10 hours a day, easy.''</p>
        <p>He started coming to this court when he was 9, and he owned it by the time he was in high school, the shooting guard for the St. Anthony's team that won 32 games without a single loss in his senior year. When he traveled around the city then, it was from court to court, looking for a game. When he travels it now, he's looking for something different.</p>
        <p>''This is my building here, this one that's boarded up,'' he said, pointing out a long-abandoned 12-unit apartment building on the corner of Bergen and Orient Avenues. ''We should be able to get working on this by the summer, rehabbing it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. DeHere scored 2,494 points at Seton Hall, still the school record. He was picked in the first round of the draft by the Los Angeles Clippers and spent six years earning the kind of paychecks that would have allowed him to live the manner of an N.B.A. grandee -- the suburban castle with an indoor court, a pool, a putting green. He chose instead to come back to his home city in the off-seasons.</p>
        <p>''Not too many players go back, but I never saw myself anyplace other than Jersey City,'' he said. He now lives in a brownstone downtown and owns a Journal Square restaurant, the Blue Ribbon Summit House, in a building that is among the city's oldest. ''Just because you have a certain amount of success, that doesn't mean it has to go somewhere else.''</p>
        <p>Driving up Bergen through the Greenville neighborhood, he touched the horn of his black Ford pickup at what seemed every other corner, returning the waves and shouted greetings of people who recognized him. ''This is an old toy factory here that we're turning into senior housing,'' he said, referring to his Jersey City Community Housing Corporation, a nonprofit organization. Then, on the next block, he pointed to a hole in the ground -- the foundation for 43 more units of senior housing. ''That's ours, too.''</p>
        <p>Mr. DeHere, 35, started investing in real estate while he was still in the N.B.A. and became a developer after he retired in 1999 -- starting not with golf-course condos or shopping malls or office buildings, but subsidized housing in the city he knew best. He has more than 100 units occupied or under construction, and he has ambitious plans for many more, spreading out from Jersey City to other urban neighborhoods in the state.</p>
        <p>''This is the big one,'' he said, stopping his truck in the Morris Canal section, near the light-rail station, where his real-estate development company Shining Star Productions is planning two 20-story towers of luxury condos with views of the Statue of Liberty and Manhattan. ''This is the league. This is the one that gets you in the show.''</p>
        <p>He turned his truck back toward his restaurant and passed too many young men hanging around on corners and stoops in the aimless way he never had time for himself when he was their age. ''If I could just talk to these kids and touch them somehow, let them know there's another way,'' he said, by way of explaining why he is also running for a seat on the city's Board of Education on April 17. (He ran unsuccessfully for City Council in 2001.) ''If you can organize 200 people to be affiliated in gang activity, it's the same power you need to have 200 people to do something positive.''</p>
        <p>The Blue Ribbon was busy with lunch when Mr. DeHere arrived, the televisions tuned to coverage of the N.C.A.A. tournament. The building's hand-hewn beams were salvaged 300 years ago from wrecked ships, the sandstone hauled in on oxcarts. Hanging on one of the walls was his Seton Hall jersey, No. 24. He is seeking permission from the city to have live music -- jazz performers, D.J.s for private parties -- but his application has been complicated by what he calls ''the incident.'' A few months after the restaurant opened in 2005, a late-night argument outside ended with gunfire and left an off-duty Hudson County corrections officer dead.</p>
        <p>Basketballs were bouncing all over the TV screens, but Mr. DeHere paid no attention. ''I might not watch 15 minutes today,'' he said of the tournament into which he once led Seton Hall three years in a row. He had too much else to do, and that was one place he had already been.</p>
        <p>JERSEY E-mail: jersey@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: jersey@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
