<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Toast of the Town</title>
    <meta content="04get.samurai.tst.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="T: Design Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="68" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Style; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/style/tmagazine/04get.samurai.tst.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837057"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Samurai Shopper"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Appliances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E0DA1230F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1046" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Toast of the Town</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Toast of the Town</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By S.S. Fair</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fair, S S</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The movies have given us many catchphrases that seem to seep into the cultural idiom overnight: ''Go ahead, make my day,'' for one; Arnold's ''I'll be back'' is another. ''Fasten your seat belts'' and ''What a dump'' are compliments of Bette Davis, and lest we forget: ''There's no place like home.'' You may not bless my all-time list of movie zingers, but frankly, my dear, I don't give a damn. The line that has me in thrall right now comes from Arthur Penn's ''Night Moves.'' ''I saw a Rohmer film once,'' muses Gene Hackman. ''It was kinda like watching paint dry.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Samurai’s referendum of intelligent design.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The movies have given us many catchphrases that seem to seep into the cultural idiom overnight: ''Go ahead, make my day,'' for one; Arnold's ''I'll be back'' is another. ''Fasten your seat belts'' and ''What a dump'' are compliments of Bette Davis, and lest we forget: ''There's no place like home.'' You may not bless my all-time list of movie zingers, but frankly, my dear, I don't give a damn. The line that has me in thrall right now comes from Arthur Penn's ''Night Moves.'' ''I saw a Rohmer film once,'' muses Gene Hackman. ''It was kinda like watching paint dry.''</p>
        <p>The Samurai Shopper can relate. For weeks I've been watching bread toast, meditating on the Maillard reaction, which happens when sugars and amino acids heat up and interact, like the Jets and the Sharks did in ''West Side Story.'' The reaction gives beer its color and self-tanners the means of making you fake brown; it also turns bread into toast via the miracle of a toaster. If you're curious as to how a toaster works, find a search engine and type in ''How a Toaster Works.'' I'm the Samurai Shopper, not Mr. Wizard.</p>
        <p>Besides, I'm watching bread toast as part of a national referendum -- which I just declared -- to explore the more rational and secular aspects of intelligent design. In this case, the design of a toaster, in order to purchase a kitchen-worthy one to feed my minions or be left standing on the sodden Atlanta earth, declaring, ''As God is my witness, I'll never be hungry again.'' The Samurai Shopper may not be Mr. Wizard, but she does a mean Scarlett O'Hara.</p>
        <p>I've stared down coils of wire glowing evenly inside sleek cages; watched grains and gluten tanning, blistering, scorching, rising from the deep like marine life piercing the glassy surface of the sea. I've got some toasters with tarted-up features and primeval noises, others as silent as Buster Keaton. In spite of these subtle variants, I can state unequivocally that watching paint dry is a Baz Luhrmann romp through ''Moulin Rouge'' compared with watching bread toast, which is more like a Yoko Ono movie where nothing happens except dust falls; eventually you want to rip your eyes out from the coruscating ennui.</p>
        <p>There may be a strict methodology to finding Oscar-winning toasters, but generally, there's no accounting for toast. (Heh-heh.) All appliances have their peccadilloes, and need to be treated gingerly. No wire hangers! as Mommie Dearest said. Some toasters will outlive you and become toys in the attic; others hog so much counter space that there's no room for much else. Then again, owning a single-task appliance in this era of multitasking means that greed is still good, or it's an omen that you've been cast in some B movie where the toaster will strangle you with its cord and devour you with fava beans and a nice Chianti.</p>
        <p>I rounded up the usual breakfast delectables: Trader Joe's Blueberry Waffles and bagels from the Bagel Store, 247 Bedford Avenue, Williamsburg. The bagels were cloud-shaped and megalithic, like the design for Frank Gehry's downtown Guggenheim museum. Their heft and density made toaster performance a true challenge. I'll spoil the ending right now and reveal that they were all brave little toasters, working mightily to produce edible treats.</p>
        <p>The worst of the lot was the new, retro-styled half-moon Heritage from Sunbeam, which made great toasters in the 1920s and '30s but now commits too many crimes and misdemeanors. The Alessi SG68 in stainless steel is a sleek vessel of majesty and style. But S.O.S.: the entire toaster becomes alarmingly hot when in use; burn, baby, burn.</p>
        <p>The Breville Ikon two-slicer is brushed stainless steel with a blue background LCD control center, smart chips and three settings. Once you ruin several breadstuffs tweaking your preferences, the rest is a piece of cake. The Krups two-slicer had a countdown timer, a three-position control lever for easy toast retrieval and a stop/eject button, gadgets almost as cool as Jason Statham's BMW 735i E38 in ''The Transporter.'' The Dualit Lite was done up in the ubiquitous Ikea cobalt blue. I dropped a sliced baguette into it one morning; the Dualit's slingshot mechanism catapulted the toast behind the stove. Houston, we had liftoff.</p>
        <p>Show me the money, you say? The Rowenta Morrison, designed by Jasper Morrison, is best in show: slim lines, quiet mechanism, sweet beeps when your toast's done, a purring beauty of grace and ability. In the bargain bin, a Back to Basics toaster and egg poacher combo was on sale at CVS for $2.99. When a small appliance costs you $2.99, you forfeit the right to whine about it. The Back to Basics poached my egg, toasted my toast, and the rest is silence.</p>
        <p>Still, nothing was superstar-like or singular in the design department. I wanted the Meryl Streep of toasters, a Hepburn; either would do. I found the classics at www.toastercentral.com. Michael Sheafe, who runs the Web site, has what must be the greatest assemblage of vintage toasters anywhere. He lives on the Upper East Side and sells his wares at the flea and green market on Columbus and 77th in the school cafeteria on most Sundays. Sheafe finds the toasters of yesteryear and refurbishes them till they're functional and sparkling. He's had prize Toast-O-Lators from the 1940s, 24-karat-gold-plated Toastmasters from the 1950s and Torrid Toasters with swinging doors and red feet. Some are nickel-plated over steel, others are engraved with scrollwork and fleurs-de-lis; some have Bakelite fittings, others have porcelain bases and carry handles. All would look at home in Fritz Lang's ''Metropolis,'' or in Radio City Music Hall. Bergdorf's once featured 100 of Michael's vintage toasters in its wintry windows, so you could keep toasty through the snow. If you want an A-list star perched on your counter, spring for one of Sheafe's early American models, designed to bring a slice of luxury into the kitchen.</p>
        <p>Sheafe says you can't beat Sunbeam's T-35 Radiant Control toaster, made around 1958, with its automatic levitations: the bread drops silently down and floats back up a perfect shade of brown. Watching bread toast in the T-35 was like watching an old-time movie. His toasters are still big, it's our designs that got small.</p>
        <p>Samurai Shopper</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
