<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Getting Serious About Sex Trafficking</title>
    <meta content="NYsextraffic" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/opinion/nyregionopinions/NYsextraffic.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837157"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="The City | Long Island | Westchester"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prostitution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spitzer, Eliot (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prostitution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Dinowitz, Jeffrey</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Spitzer, Eliot L</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E0D61330F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="468" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Getting Serious About Sex Trafficking</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Getting Serious About Sex Trafficking</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial holds New York State Legislature, with nudge from Gov Eliot Spitzer, should enact strong measure that contains tough penalties, provides social services and assists victims of sex- and labor-trafficking industries</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lawmakers in Albany have a bad habit of waiting until the chaotic closing days of the legislative session to focus on important legislation. A result is that useful measures that would benefit the citizens of New York often fall by the wayside.</p>
        <p>That, essentially, is what happened last year to a promising bill to crack down on sex and labor trafficking, offered by Assemblyman Jeffrey Dinowitz, a Democrat from the Bronx. The Assembly Codes Committee insisted on a much weaker version, and time ran out before there was a chance to undo the damage and hammer out a final bill with the Senate, which was promoting a weak version of its own.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The hard work of fashioning a solid, anti-trafficking package, and building support for it, must begin now  not in May or June when lawmakers are racing to adjourn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lawmakers in Albany have a bad habit of waiting until the chaotic closing days of the legislative session to focus on important legislation. A result is that useful measures that would benefit the citizens of New York often fall by the wayside.</p>
        <p>That, essentially, is what happened last year to a promising bill to crack down on sex and labor trafficking, offered by Assemblyman Jeffrey Dinowitz, a Democrat from the Bronx. The Assembly Codes Committee insisted on a much weaker version, and time ran out before there was a chance to undo the damage and hammer out a final bill with the Senate, which was promoting a weak version of its own.</p>
        <p>True to form, the Democratic Assembly showed its usual aversion to imposing stiff new criminal penalties, and the Republican Senate balked at providing services to victims and giving them a private right of action against the people who abused them.</p>
        <p>New York badly needs its own anti-trafficking law. Although human trafficking is already a federal crime, the Justice Department lacks the time and resources to prosecute smaller-scale operations, involving, say, a single pimp or victim. State laws covering crimes like rape and kidnapping are inadequate to address the range of coercive techniques traffickers use to enslave women, men and children in the sex industry or various forms of cheap labor. New York has many such victims.</p>
        <p>Even in this year of big, diverting battles over the state budget, it should be possible to enact a strong anti-trafficking measure that contains tough penalties, provides an array of social services to encourage victims to come forward and assists victims in escaping their horrific situations. But the hard work of fashioning a solid package, and building support for it, must begin now -- not in May or June when lawmakers are racing to adjourn.</p>
        <p>With encouragement from Gov. Eliot Spitzer, some of the outside advocacy groups pressing for anti-trafficking legislation have started meeting with the state district attorneys association, with the goal of finding common ground on thorny definitional issues and the different levels of punishment. In the Assembly, meanwhile, Mr. Dinowitz has rounded up more than 100 co-sponsors for the latest incarnation of his bill. These are encouraging developments. Ultimately, though, it will take Mr. Spitzer's firm leadership to sustain the momentum.</p>
        <p>Fortunately, Mr. Spitzer is no stranger to the issue, having seen the need for a strong state anti-trafficking law during his years as attorney general. Fortunately, too, this year's quest for comprehensive anti-trafficking legislation need not start from scratch. Mr. Dinowitz's current bill provides a good working draft, and the city's bar association has suggested a number of useful refinements.</p>
        <p>This is a matter lawmakers of both parties in both chambers of the Legislature should be able to agree upon, given a timely nudge from the governor.</p>
        <p>The City | Long Island | Westchester</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
