<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BASEBALL PREVIEW: A.L.</title>
    <meta content="01aleast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837434"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Baltimore Orioles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Devil Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Toronto Blue Jays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Minnesota Twins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago White Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cleveland Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Detroit Tigers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Kansas City Royals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Angels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Texas Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Seattle Mariners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Dodgers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E0DD1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="3105" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BASEBALL PREVIEW: A.L.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MURRAY CHASS examines the strengths and weaknesses of the American League.</p>
        <p>East</p>
        <p>PROJECTED FINISH  1. YANKEES  2. RED SOX  3. BLUE JAYS  4. ORIOLES  5. DEVIL RAYS</p>
        <p>The Toronto Blue Jays were the division's big spenders last year, and they were rewarded for their extravagance with a second-place finish that dumped the Boston Red Sox uncharacteristically into third. Stunned by their failure to make the playoffs, the Red Sox made sure that this time around they were the big spenders. And did they ever spend big.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MURRAY CHASS examines the strengths and weaknesses of the American League.</p>
        <p>East</p>
        <p>PROJECTED FINISH  1. YANKEES  2. RED SOX  3. BLUE JAYS  4. ORIOLES  5. DEVIL RAYS</p>
        <p>The Toronto Blue Jays were the division's big spenders last year, and they were rewarded for their extravagance with a second-place finish that dumped the Boston Red Sox uncharacteristically into third. Stunned by their failure to make the playoffs, the Red Sox made sure that this time around they were the big spenders. And did they ever spend big.</p>
        <p>Between their bid and the ensuing contract, they spent $103 million for Daisuke (pronounced Dice-K) Matsuzaka. J. D. Drew opted out of his Los Angeles Dodgers contract and signed a $70 million deal. Julio Lugo signed for $36 million and will be Boston's sixth shortstop in four years.</p>
        <p>Not that the Blue Jays were a financial shrinking violet. They tied up center fielder Vernon Wells with a $126 million contract. They retained catcher Gregg Zaun and added designated hitter Frank Thomas, shortstop Royce Clayton and starting pitchers John Thomson and Tomo Ohka.</p>
        <p>It seems that everyone was trying to beat the Yankees at their own game. Despite their intention to lower their payroll, the Yankees gave Andy Pettitte $16 million to return to their starting rotation after he spent three years in Houston; they retained Mike Mussina for $23 million; and they added their own Japanese pitcher, Kei Igawa, for $20 million and first baseman Doug Mientkiewicz for a pittance.</p>
        <p>Carl Pavano may as well be considered a newcomer because he has not pitched in a major league game since June 2005.</p>
        <p>The Yankees traded two of their starting pitchers, Randy Johnson and Jaret Wright, and one of their big hitters, Gary Sheffield. Their offense should not be hurt by Sheffield's departure; last year they led the majors in runs scored despite having Sheffield and Hideki Matsui for only a combined 90 games.</p>
        <p>They have pitching replacements, but they also have pitching ailments. Pettitte had back spasms late in spring training, and Chien-Ming Wang, their leading winner last year with 19 victories, will open the season on the disabled list with a strained hamstring instead of pitching the season opener.</p>
        <p>While pitching could make the Yankees vulnerable, the Boston Red Sox may not have as solid a rotation as they thought.</p>
        <p>Josh Beckett had a decent record last season, 16-11, but he also had a dangerously high earned run average, 5.01. Tim Wakefield is one of two 40-year-olds in the rotation (Curt Schilling is the other) and is coming off a losing season (7-11).</p>
        <p>Jonathan Papelbon was supposed to be a starter this season but has returned to his role as closer. He gained saves in his first 20 chances last season, but then had only 15 in his last 21 chances. Julián Tavárez, who had been a candidate for the closer job, now becomes a starter. He had a 3-0 record and 4.01 E.R.A. in six starts last season.</p>
        <p>One of the keys to the Red Sox' season could be the fragility of Drew, the right fielder, who last year drove in 100 runs for the first time in his eight-year career. Drew has never played in as many as 110 games in two consecutive seasons, and based on his career pattern, this would be the season for him to play in fewer games.</p>
        <p>The health of a pair of Toronto Blue Jays pitchers, A. J. Burnett and Gustavo Chacín, who combined for only 38 starts last year, will help determine how serious a contender the Blue Jays will be. Not much can turn Baltimore and Tampa Bay into contenders.</p>
        <p>The Baltimore Orioles have fortified their bullpen with the addition of Danys Báez, Jamie Walker, Chad Bradford and Scott Williamson, but the additions to their starting rotation are New York castoffs, Jaret Wright from the Yankees and Steve Trachsel from the Mets. Little wonder that the Orioles are headed for their 10th consecutive losing season, a period the franchise last experienced when it primarily played as the St. Louis Browns.</p>
        <p>Despite a change in ownership control and front-office operation, the Tampa Bay Devil Rays are the same franchise they were for the first nine years of their existence. The original owner, Vince Naimoli, dug them into such a deep hole that last season they endured their second-worst record (61-101). The Devil Rays made only one notable addition, third baseman Akinori Iwamura, but their brightest hope is right fielder Delmon Young, who batted .317 in 30 games last season.</p>
        <p>TAMPA BAY LIGHTNING</p>
        <p>Tampa Bay is counting on young players like CARL CRAWFORD, 25, who has led the American League in steals three of the past four seasons and in triples for the past three.</p>
        <p>YANKEES  2006: 97-65, first place</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Doug Mientkiewicz  2B Robinson Canó  SS Derek Jeter  3B Alex Rodriguez  LF Hideki Matsui  CF Johnny Damon  RF Bobby Abreu  C Jorge Posada  DH Jason Giambi  SP Chien-Ming Wang (d.l.)  Andy Pettitte  Mike Mussina  Carl Pavano  Kei Igawa*  Closer Mariano Rivera</p>
        <p>BOSTON RED SOX  2006: 86-76, third</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Kevin Youkilis  2B Dustin Pedroia*  SS Julio Lugo  3B Mike Lowell  LF Manny Ramírez  CF Coco Crisp  RF J. D. Drew  C Jason Varitek  DH David Ortiz  SP Curt Schilling  Josh Beckett  Daisuke Matsuzaka*  Tim Wakefield  Julián Tavárez  Closer Jonathan Papelbon</p>
        <p>TORONTO BLUE JAYS  2006: 87-75, second</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Lyle Overbay  2B Aaron Hill  SS Royce Clayton  3B Troy Glaus  LF Reed Johnson  CF Vernon Wells  RF Alex Rios  C Gregg Zaun  DH Frank Thomas  SP Roy Halladay  A. J. Burnett  Gustavo Chacín  John Thomson  Tomo Ohka  Closer B. J. Ryan</p>
        <p>BALTIMORE ORIOLES  2006: 70-92, fourth</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Kevin Millar  2B Brian Roberts  SS Miguel Tejada  3B Melvin Mora  LF Aubrey Huff  Jay Payton (d.l.)  CF Corey Patterson  RF Nick Markakis  C Ramón Hernández  DH Jay Gibbons  SP Erik Bedard  Daniel Cabrera  Jaret Wright  Adam Loewen  Steve Trachsel  Closer Chris Ray</p>
        <p>TAMPA BAY DEVIL RAYS  2006: 61-101, fifth</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Ty Wigginton  2B Jorge Cantú  SS Ben Zobrist  3B Akinori Iwamura*  LF Carl Crawford  CF Rocco Baldelli  RF Delmon Young*  C Dioner Navarro  DH Jonny Gomes  SP Scott Kazmir  James Shields  Jae Seo  Casey Fossum  Edwin Jackson  Closer Al Reyes</p>
        <p>*-Rookie</p>
        <p>Central</p>
        <p>PROJECTED FINISH  1. TIGERS  2. INDIANS  3. TWINS  4. WHITE SOX  5. ROYALS</p>
        <p>Unless the other teams employ a strict strategy that they should have picked up from last year's World Series, the Detroit Tigers should do this season what they failed to do by one day last year. That would be finish in first place.</p>
        <p>The Tigers were in first place last year from May 16 until the last day of the season, but the Minnesota Twins squeezed past them when Detroit lost a 12-inning game to Kansas City. The wild-card Tigers rallied, however, and went to the World Series, only to find a novel and quirky way to lose to St Louis.</p>
        <p>That is where the opposition strategy comes in. If the other teams were watching, they learned that the Tigers were vulnerable to ground balls hit back to their pitchers. Once in each of the five World Series games, a Detroit pitcher made a costly error, a feat never before performed in a World Series.</p>
        <p>Assuming the Tigers can find a way to foil that strategy, they will also have to overcome the loss of their No. 1 pitcher, Kenny Rogers, who had a blood clot removed from his left shoulder on Friday and will miss the first half of the season.</p>
        <p>With a journeyman right-hander, Chad Durbin (17-30), replacing Rogers, the Tigers could find it more difficult to prevail in what could be the majors' toughest division.</p>
        <p>Only the Kansas City Royals, losers of 100 games each of the past three years and four of the past five, do not have a chance. They may have the potential rookie of the year, third baseman Alex Gordon, who has pushed Mark Teahen to right field, but they definitely will not have the team of the year.</p>
        <p>The Tigers, on the other hand, could be the team of the year. They won 95 games last year after going through 12 consecutive losing seasons, and they could be even better this season. Mike Maroth, whose elbow operation limited him to nine starts last season, is back in the rotation, and the Tigers bolstered their lineup with Gary Sheffield, one of the fiercest hitters in the majors.</p>
        <p>The Tigers could also have the right side of their infield intact for the full season. First baseman Sean Casey joined the Tigers in a trade July 31, and second baseman Plácido Polanco separated his shoulder Aug. 15. Polanco returned in time to go 7 for 17 in the division series, 9 for 17 in the league championship series and 0 for 17 in the World Series.</p>
        <p>The Minnesota Twins, who became the first team to win a division title by being alone in first place for only one day, won with the help of a sensational pitching performance by Francisco Liriano (12-3, 2.16 E.R.A.). They did not begin last season with him in the rotation, and they will not this year either because he will miss the season after having elbow surgery.</p>
        <p>But the Twins have their Cy Young award winner, Johan Santana (19-6); their A.L. most valuable player, Justin Morneau (.321, 34 homers, 130 R.B.I.); and their league batting champion, catcher Joe Mauer (.347).</p>
        <p>A key to the Twins' participation in a possible four-way division race figures to be their starting pitching behind Santana. Brad Radke has retired, leaving Carlos Silva (11-15), the newcomer Ramón Ortiz (11-16 with Washington), Boof Bonser (7-6) and the retread Sidney Ponson.</p>
        <p>The 2005 champion Chicago White Sox have shuffled their pitching, trading Freddy García and Brandon McCarthy and acquiring the youngsters Gavin Floyd (4-3 with the Phillies) and John Danks. It remains to be seen if they gave up too much in swapping García for Floyd.</p>
        <p>The White Sox deepened their depth by adding the veterans Darin Erstad and Toby Hall.</p>
        <p>The Cleveland Indians are the team to watch in the division. They underachieved last season with their unexpectedly poor 78-84 record, so improvements by each player could make them a threat, maybe this year's Tigers.</p>
        <p>Two new outfielders, David Dellucci and Trot Nixon, along with the new second baseman Josh Barfield, could stir up a team that played lethargically at times last year. The Indians tried to get Sheffield from the Yankees but failed.</p>
        <p>Cliff Lee will open the season on the disabled list, giving Fausto Carmona a chance in the rotation. Key to the pitching, though, will be the journeyman closer Joe Borowski (36 saves with Florida).</p>
        <p>ONE MILLION PER VICTORY</p>
        <p>GIL MECHE, with a career record of 55-44 and a 4.65 earned run average, signed a $55 million deal with Kansas City. The Royals had the worst E.R.A. in the majors last season (5.65).</p>
        <p>DETROIT TIGERS  2006: 95-67, wild card</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Sean Casey  2B Plácido Polanco  SS Carlos Guillén  3B Brandon Inge  LF Craig Monroe  CF Curtis Granderson  RF Magglio Ordóñez  C Iván Rodríguez  DH Gary Sheffield  SP Jeremy Bonderman  Justin Verlander  Nate Robertson  Mike Maroth  Chad Durbin  Kenny Rogers (d.l.)  Closer Todd Jones</p>
        <p>CLEVELAND INDIANS  2006: 78-84, fourth</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Casey Blake  2B Josh Barfield  SS Jhonny Peralta  3B Andy Marte  LF David Dellucci  CF Grady Sizemore  RF Trot Nixon  C Víctor Martínez  DH Travis Hafner  SP C. C. Sabathia  Jake Westbrook  Jeremy Sowers  Paul Byrd  Fausto Carmona  Cliff Lee (d.l.)  Closer Joe Borowski</p>
        <p>MINNESOTA TWINS  2006: 96-66, first</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Justin Morneau  2B Luis Castillo  SS Jason Bartlett  3B Nick Punto  LF Rondell White  CF Torii Hunter  RF Michael Cuddyer  C Joe Mauer  DH Jason Kubel  SP Johan Santana  Boof Bonser  Carlos Silva  Ramón Ortiz  Sidney Ponson  Closer Joe Nathan</p>
        <p>CHICAGO WHITE SOX  2006: 90-72, third</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Paul Konerko  2B Tadahito Iguchi  SS Juan Uribe  3B Joe Crede  LF Scott Podsednik  CF Darin Erstad  RF Jermaine Dye  C Gregg Zaun  DH Jim Thome  SP José Contreras  Jon Garland  Mark Buerhle  Javier Vázquez  John Danks*  Closer Bobby Jenks</p>
        <p>KANSAS CITY ROYALS  2006: 62-100, fifth</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Ryan Shealy  2B Mark Grudzielanek  SS Tony Peña  3B Alex Gordon*  LF Emil Brown/Ross Gload  CF David DeJesus  RF Mark Teahen  C J. LaRue or J. Buck  DH Mike Sweeney  SP Gil Meche  Odalis Pérez  Luke Hudson  Jorge De La Rosa  Zack Grienke  Closer Octavio Dotel</p>
        <p>*-Rookie</p>
        <p>West</p>
        <p>PROJECTED FINISH  1. ATHLETICS  2. ANGELS  3. RANGERS  4. MARINERS</p>
        <p>This has become a division of haves and have-nots. The Athletics and the Angels have had success in recent years; the Rangers and the Mariners have not. There is little reason to think that will change this season.</p>
        <p>The Rangers and the Mariners keep trying; each increased its win total last year. But they still have work to do.</p>
        <p>For their effort, the Texas Rangers have gathered a curious collection of veteran players:</p>
        <p>Sammy Sosa is back in the game after a year's hiatus, seeking to enhance his home run total of 588, which is fifth on the career list, and his reputation, which has suffered from suspicions of steroid use.</p>
        <p>Eric Gagné, the once-brilliant closer for the Dodgers (161 saves, including 84 in a row, in 167 chances), is back after two injury-shattered seasons, though he will begin the season on the disabled list.</p>
        <p>Kenny Lofton is with his ninth team in eight seasons.</p>
        <p>The best the Seattle Mariners can do to match that collection is cite Miguel Batista, a new member of their rotation, who is the author of a novel, ''The Avenger of Blood.''</p>
        <p>Batista is one of three new Seattle starters in a renovated rotation. The Mariners have also added Horacio Ramirez, for whom they gave up reliever Rafael Soriano, and Jeff Weaver, whose strong eight-inning effort clinched the World Series for the Cardinals last October.</p>
        <p>For their lineup, the Mariners acquired two players who were with the Washington Nationals last season, José Vidro and José Guillén. It is questionable that they will add much punch to an offense that was one of the league's weakest last season. Only the Devil Rays scored fewer runs.</p>
        <p>When it came to offense, the Oakland Athletics did not have an explosive aggregation, but they won the division title because their pitchers did not give up a lot of runs. Only the Tigers and the Twins allowed fewer runs.</p>
        <p>Missing from that pitching corps, though, is Barry Zito, who went across the bay to San Francisco for the princely sum of $126 million. His flight completed the departure of the pitching triumvirate (Zito, Tim Hudson, Mark Mulder) upon whom the Athletics relied for two division titles and one other playoff foray.</p>
        <p>Now it is up to Rich Harden (4-0 in nine starts), Dan Haren (14-13) and Joe Blanton (16-12) to become the division-winning triumvirate. They will have three more seasons together before Harden can be a free agent.</p>
        <p>It is up to Mike Piazza to provide the offense that Frank Thomas supplied (39 homers, 114 R.B.I.) in his cameo appearance as the designated hitter last season. After catching with less than artistic success for 14 years, Piazza, 38, has been liberated and only has to hit.</p>
        <p>Although there had been some question about how many hits he had left in him, Piazza batted .283 and hit 22 home runs for the Padres last season. In eight games as a designated hitter, he batted .258 with one home run; in 99 games as a catcher, he batted .288.</p>
        <p>In Anaheim -- or is that Los Angeles? -- it is Casey at the bat but also Casey at first base for the Angels. That is Casey Kotchman, who was supposed to be their first baseman last year before mononucleosis reduced his season to 29 games, and three other players shared his position.</p>
        <p>Howie Kendrick was one of those players, and this year he is the second baseman. Robb Quinlan was another of those players, and he will start this season as the third baseman because Chone Figgins broke two fingers and is expected to miss the first month.</p>
        <p>Kendry Morales, a Cuban defector, started more games at first than anyone (49), but for now he is behind Kotchman. The Angels are also waiting for Dallas McPherson to be their third baseman. He missed half of last season with a bad back.</p>
        <p>More important, the Angels await the return from the disabled list of two pitchers, Bartolo Colón and Jered Weaver. Colón, the Cy Young award winner in 2005, made only 10 starts last season because of a torn rotator cuff. Weaver had a great rookie season (11-2, 2.56), so good that he forced the Angels to release his older brother, Jeff. But now he has biceps tendinitis.</p>
        <p>WAITING ON BELTRE</p>
        <p>Seattle is still waiting for ADRIÁN BELTRE to pay dividends on his $64 million contract. After hitting 48 homers for the Dodgers in 2004, he has had 44 in two seasons with the Mariners.</p>
        <p>OAKLAND ATHLETICS  2006: 93-69, first</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Erubiel Durazo  Dan Johnson (d.l.)  2B Mark Ellis  SS Bobby Crosby  3B Eric Chavez  LF Shannon Stewart  CF Milton Bradley  Mark Kotsay (d.l.)  RF Nick Swisher  C Jason Kendall  DH Mike Piazza  SP Dan Haren  Rich Harden  Joe Blanton  Esteban Loaiza  Joe Kennedy  Closer Huston Street</p>
        <p>LOS ANGELES ANGELS  2006: 89-73, second</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Casey Kotchman  2B Howie Kendrick  SS Orlando Cabrera  3B R. Quinlan/M. Izturis  Chone Figgins (d.l.)  LF Garret Anderson  CF Gary Matthews Jr.  RF Vladimir Guerrero  C Mike Napoli  DH Shea Hillenbrand  SP John Lackey  Ervin Santana  Kelvim Escobar  Joe Saunders  Dustin Moseley  Jered Weaver, B. Colón (d.l.)  Closer Francisco Rodríguez</p>
        <p>TEXAS RANGERS  2006: 80-82, third</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Mark Teixeira  2B Ian Kinsler  SS Michael Young  3B Hank Blalock  LF Brad Wilkerson/  Frank Catalanotto  CF Kenny Lofton  RF Nelson Cruz  C Gerald Laird  DH Sammy Sosa  SP Kevin Millwood  Vicente Padilla  Brandon McCarthy  Robinson Tejeda  Jamey Wright  Closer Akinori Otsuka  Eric Gagné (d.l.)</p>
        <p>SEATTLE MARINERS  2006: 78-84, fourth</p>
        <p>PROBABLE STARTERS  1B Richie Sexson  2B José López  SS Yuniesky Betancourt  3B Adrián Beltre  LF Raúl Ibáñez  CF Ichiro Suzuki  RF José Guillén  C Kenji Johjima  DH José Vidro  SP Félix Hernández  Jarrod Washburn  Jeff Weaver  Miguel Batista  Horacio Ramirez  Closer J. J. Putz</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
