<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Good Mother</title>
    <meta content="Nussbaum.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/books/review/Nussbaum.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837024"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Garrison, Deborah</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Second Child, The: Poems (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E6DB1530F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1007" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Good Mother</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Good Mother</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EMILY NUSSBAUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nussbaum, Emily</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE SECOND CHILD</p>
        <p>Poems.</p>
        <p>By Deborah Garrison.</p>
        <p>76 pp. Random House. $19.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Deborah Garrison’s new poems trace her shift from plucky Manhattanite to suburban mom.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE SECOND CHILD</p>
        <p>Poems.</p>
        <p>By Deborah Garrison.</p>
        <p>76 pp. Random House. $19.95.</p>
        <p>We are living in -- take your pick -- a glorious renaissance era of writing about parenthood or a bathetic swamp of diaper blogs. On the nonfiction shelves, polemicists spar over whether mothers should stay at home; chick-lit heroines strap on pink Baby Björns; and online, mothers and fathers document milestones with a fervor formerly reserved for fanatical birders. Meanwhile, anthologies of personal essays cover every subject from miscarriage to only children.</p>
        <p>Deborah Garrison's latest collection of poems is the highbrow analogue to this cultural boom. A former editor at The New Yorker and Knopf's poetry editor, Garrison won an appreciative audience for her first book, ''A Working Girl Can't Win,'' a collection that enjoyed its own bit of cultural kismet, as the highbrow analogue to ''Sex and the City.'' This is not an insult: I loved ''Sex and the City,'' and Garrison's portrayal of herself as a plucky Manhattanite won fans for good reason. She was witty, she was straightforward and she captured something lovely in the ambiguous self-knowledge of a young woman turning toward love.</p>
        <p>Now Garrison is back with this new subject, motherhood. Her once-freewheeling narrator has three children and lives on the other side of the Hudson. And she is astonished to find that she is no longer that high-heeled girl strutting down the street, full of ''self-ish pleasure''; instead, she has entered ''the shuttered room / where life is milk'' and when she walks in Midtown, she is merely headed home. But despite moments of nostalgia, this narrator loves her new life, where a child's clutching fingers remind her of a lever ''ringing in the first / jackpot of many, with coins / and cries, heavenly noise, / a crashing pile / of minor riches.''</p>
        <p>As the many fans of her first book would attest, the strength of Garrison's poems is their ordinariness, in both language and subject matter. They are not pretentious. They speak to the reader directly: this is a conversation with a likable next-door neighbor rather than a scary visitation from a bipolar goddess. But this ordinariness is also Garrison's weakness, and in ''The Second Child'' it can be glaring. Many of these poems are simply anecdotes of children being adorably profound: asking questions about death, struggling with the concept of infinity. Elsewhere, Garrison strives to celebrate domestic life but settles insead for cliché, as in one poem where she longs for more ''voices that pierce / my heart utterly.''</p>
        <p>There's nothing wrong with aiming at simplicity, of course. And occasionally, Garrison hits her mark, as in a lovely poem about her child's delight at discovering that her mother can make a cup of water with her hand. But even poems that seem clever the first time around dissolve, upon rereading, from simple to merely obvious. In ''Sestina for the Working Mother,'' she salutes her own busy day, layered with a brief, sentimental fantasy of what it would be like if she stayed home -- more NPR, more volunteerism. In ''A Midnight Bris,'' she recalls a beloved obstretician who had held ''my cervix, and me in thrall,'' and who gets teary during their final meeting. ''But you ... so many patients,'' she murmurs. '' 'They're not all the same,' he said. / We let that stand.'' Such moments feel too self-congratulatory by half.</p>
        <p>Garrison's poems about birth have some vivid images, as in her bawdy (and unprintable) description of labor in ''Birth Day Pun,'' which makes the most of the legendary ''ring of fire.'' And the liveliest poems here play to Garrison's strength, her rhymey wit, as in ''To the Man in a Loden Coat,'' a monologue directed at a guy blocking the escalator. In one of several poems that make reference to Sept. 11, she recounts her own perverse, relatable impulse that day, to get pregnant. ''The pushy, ennobling pulse / Of the ordinary won't halt / For good taste. Or knows nothing of tragedy. / Thus. Today I have a boy / A week old. Blessed surplus: / A third child.''</p>
        <p>But is it wrong to want more? Since female poets began bum-rushing the academy midcentury, claiming their right to discuss these formerly taboo subjects, there has been a flood of smart, morbid, searching, sometimes outrageous writing on maternity. The best such poems burn off the pink sentimentality of motherhood in favor of something wilder and more surprising. When Anne Sexton wrote her hilarious rant ''In Celebration of My Uterus,'' critics mocked her for considering such crassly female subject matter for poetry. But she and others -- Sharon Olds especially, who has built her career on a far more vivid and ambitious variant of what Garrison seems to be striving for -- have cleared a path for writing that does more than simply memorialize household happiness.</p>
        <p>To my mind, the great unsung poet of motherhood is Sylvia Plath. She may have a reputation as the ultimate misery chick, but in fact, her writing overflows with talk of birth, of breastfeeding and motherhood, much of it, despite sad undercurrents, loving and celebratory. In the gorgeous ''Nick and the Candlestick,'' for instance, Plath writes ''O love, how did you get here? / O embryo / Remembering, even in sleep, / Your crossed position. / The blood blooms clean / In you, ruby.'' The poem ends with one of her most moving images: ''You are the one / Solid the spaces lean on, envious. / You are the baby in the barn.'' In poems like this, and in her finest descriptions (as when a newborn's ''clear vowels rise like balloons''), Plath makes strange what should be familiar -- which is, after all, a central task of poetry.</p>
        <p>It's unfair, of course, to expect Garrison to be like Plath. She has her own gifts and an audience sure to appreciate them. In real life, I'd rather have a likable next-door neighbor than a bipolar goddess as a confidante. But in writing? Give me the strange mother over the sweet one any day.</p>
        <p>Emily Nussbaum is a contributing editor at New York magazine. She writes frequently about poetry.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Emily Nussbaum is a contributing editor at New York magazine. She writes frequently about poetry.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
