<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Genius of Grover's Corners</title>
    <meta content="McCarter.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/books/review/McCarter.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837020"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ESSAY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Wilder, Thornton</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE7DB1530F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1481" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Genius of Grover's Corners</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Genius of Grover’s Corners</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEREMY MCCARTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mccarter, Jeremy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mary McCarthy liked Thornton Wilder's ''Our Town'' more than she cared to admit. It was 1938, and the theater of social protest -- of Odets and Blitzstein -- was at its zenith: an inconvenient time for a politically minded critic to fall for this homespun tale of life in Grover's Corners. In enjoying this Broadway hit, she later remembered wondering, ''was I starting to sell out?''</p>
        <p>McCarthy was not the first, and very far from the last, to feel the strange queasiness that sometimes besets Wilder's admirers. With his slender output and whiff of Norman Rockwell wholesomeness, he can seem an odd figure alongside Eugene O'Neill, Arthur Miller and Tennessee Williams on the Rushmore of American drama -- if he's granted a place there at all. His new enshrinement in the Library of America, which has just published Wilder's Collected Plays &amp; Writings on Theater (Library of America, $40), may not convince everyone it's finally safe to love him. But this anthology of some of America's most bewitching theatrical writing offers the best chance yet to figure out how the man who might be our greatest playwright could also be our most misunderstood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Audiences familiar with “Our Town” may think of Thornton Wilder as a sentimentalist. But a new anthology shows he was one of our darkest playwrights  and one of our best.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mary McCarthy liked Thornton Wilder's ''Our Town'' more than she cared to admit. It was 1938, and the theater of social protest -- of Odets and Blitzstein -- was at its zenith: an inconvenient time for a politically minded critic to fall for this homespun tale of life in Grover's Corners. In enjoying this Broadway hit, she later remembered wondering, ''was I starting to sell out?''</p>
        <p>McCarthy was not the first, and very far from the last, to feel the strange queasiness that sometimes besets Wilder's admirers. With his slender output and whiff of Norman Rockwell wholesomeness, he can seem an odd figure alongside Eugene O'Neill, Arthur Miller and Tennessee Williams on the Rushmore of American drama -- if he's granted a place there at all. His new enshrinement in the Library of America, which has just published Wilder's Collected Plays &amp; Writings on Theater (Library of America, $40), may not convince everyone it's finally safe to love him. But this anthology of some of America's most bewitching theatrical writing offers the best chance yet to figure out how the man who might be our greatest playwright could also be our most misunderstood.</p>
        <p>Great reputations, we tend to think, should be held aloft by imposing columns of major works. But producing one magnum opus after another was never Wilder's style. Much of his energy went into writing one-acts, the kind of little pieces that many playwrights treat as fodder for the next company that asks for help with a fund-raiser. For Wilder, who disdained kitchen-sink drama in favor of the absolutes -- finding the universe in a grain of sand, then reversing the lens to view the whole cathedral of existence -- the short plays were as likely to be masterpieces as the long.</p>
        <p>Thus the one-act ''Pullman Car Hiawatha,'' the story of a sleeper car making an overnight trip to Chicago, features not just the petty concerns of the passengers but the voices of the planets and the hours: human mortality in its smallness and its largeness. ''The Long Christmas Dinner'' telescopes 90 years of a family's history into one never-ending holiday feast, and as generations appear, have children, wither and depart, only we in the audience appreciate what changes and what doesn't. ''Every least twig is wrapped around with ice. You almost never see that,'' young Genevieve marvels, not realizing that her mother has made this observation years earlier nor that her daughter-in-law will one day do the same. Wilder's tone is dry, fond; if God were to dabble in anthropology, and the recording angels to write with wry humor and infinite tolerance of human folly, this is how the holy books would read.</p>
        <p>These qualities find their fullest expression in ''Our Town,'' a show you might recall, if your high school had a drama club. For all the play's ubiquity, though, how well do we really understand it? Everyone remembers the folksy Stage Manager leading us through the story, as pretty Emily Webb grows up in picturesque Grover's Corners in Act I, marries the local baseball star George Gibbs in Act II, and is buried in Act III. You may remember, too, how she decides to relive one day of her life, and sums up the play's cosmic gospel as she returns to her grave: ''Oh earth, you're too wonderful for anybody to realize you.''</p>
        <p>Frequently lost in the sentimental haze that most revivals inflict upon the play is the contrary voice of Simon Stimson, the town drunk and suicide. ''That's what it was to be alive,'' he snarls. ''To move about in a cloud of ignorance; to go up and down trampling on the feelings of those ... of those about you.'' He makes a good point. Grover's Corners is, in retrospect, an unbearable place: quite content to be homogeneous, conformist, anti-intellectual and lacking ''any culture or love of beauty.'' When staged properly, the play doesn't let us to feel simple nostalgia. We ought to weep at Emily's famous line not because she finds earth wonderful, but because she was unable to find it so during her close-minded life in her close-minded town -- which is, of course, our town. Wilder makes a profound statement about the limits of human understanding here, one that requires delicacy and a little steel to convey. '' 'Our Town' is one of the toughest, saddest plays ever written,'' Edward Albee has said. ''Why is it always produced as hearts and flowers?''</p>
        <p>If Wilder had moped around in black, drunk himself into oblivion or -- if you're feeling romantic -- hanged himself like Simon Stimson, people might not have so much trouble finding that note of radical despair amid the bathos. But like Alfred Hitchcock (for whom he wrote the unmistakably Wilderian screenplay for ''Shadow of a Doubt''), he confounded the popular image of the genius as a tortured, self-destructive soul. Wilder cultivated a wide circle of friends and remained throughout his 78 years an enthusiastic teacher and lecturer. Though he had plenty of frustrations and some Broadway flops, he rewrote the highest-profile of these to create the hit farce ''The Matchmaker,'' then watched someone else rewrite his rewrite to create ''Hello, Dolly!'' It made him a fortune without his lifting a finger. With habitual modesty, he said he differed from his contemporaries in one respect: ''I give (don't I?) the impression of having enormously enjoyed it.''</p>
        <p>All this unfashionable contentment might make the creator of Grover's Corners sound like some dismissible hayseed. In fact, he was among the worldliest writers of his generation. Born in 1897 in Madison, Wis., Wilder -- the survivor of a pair of twin brothers -- followed his consul father to China and Hong Kong before settling with his highly cultured mother in Berkeley, Calif. After Yale, he began a lifelong circuit of the hubs of the intelligentsia (MacDowell, Harvard, the home of his close friend Gertrude Stein) with a year doing archaeology at the American Academy in Rome. He read voraciously in at least four languages, becoming so erudite it sometimes seemed to work against him: the fragments of his unfinished play ''The Emporium,'' included in the Library of America volume, are less captivating than the journal entries in which he wrestled with how to blend Kafka, Kierkegaard and Stein in a Philadelphia department store. Yet he remains the only writer to win a Pulitzer Prize for drama (twice) and for fiction (''The Bridge at San Luis Rey''). To really do him justice, the Library of America needs to publish volumes of both.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, J. D. McClatchy, the editor of this volume, has included many of Wilder's essays on theater, an inspired move that helps dispel the gravest misunderstanding of all. To audiences reared on the realistic dramas of O'Neill, Williams and Miller, Wilder's plays can seem overloaded with self-conscious trickery: the Stage Manager who guides the action, the imaginary props. His prefaces and other writings reveal these aren't mere flights of fancy: they're the essence of his art, his way of acting on an uncommonly sophisticated view of drama.</p>
        <p>For Wilder, theater's ability to present the universal and eternal made it ''the greatest of all the arts,'' but the 19th-century vogue for box sets and realistic props had reduced it to ''a minor art and an inconsequential diversion.'' He realized that for theater to regain its old pre-eminence, it would need to abandon naturalism and rediscover the tools of Shakespeare and the Greeks: stage conventions that convey -- a marvelous distinction -- ''not verisimilitude but reality.'' Thus Wilder's lack of scenery and other brazenly theatrical devices are all ways of escaping the literal and picayune, of stretching theater as far as an engaged audience's imagination can take it. The uncanny result is plays that pursue the emotional aims of Chekhov with the adventurous theatricality of Brecht.</p>
        <p>That doesn't necessarily make Wilder our greatest playwright, but if we really understand him, he seems by far the most essential: the homegrown writer who made the largest claims for the theater, who put its special capacities to better use than his contemporaries -- or his successors. While you can see hints of his influence in later playwrights -- John Guare and Lanford Wilson, for instance -- American theater today remains in thrall to the ''childish attempts to be 'real' '' that he decried. All the family-room dramas and stagy sitcoms that pour forth every season show he still represents a road largely not taken.</p>
        <p>Though this collection helps make sense of Wilder, what he really needs -- what our theater needs -- is producers willing to stage these plays, and directors sensitive to their fragile allure. In hands like those of the Keen Company, which staged an exquisite revival of ''Pullman Car Hiawatha'' three years ago, Wilder leaves you feeling that you haven't just watched a show. With the actors and other playgoers, you've tried to make a little better sense of the funny, scary, bewildering business of being alive.</p>
        <p>ESSAY Jeremy McCarter, the theater critic at New York magazine, is editing a collection of Henry Fairlie's writing.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jeremy McCarter, the theater critic at New York magazine, is editing a collection of Henry Fairlie's writing.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
