<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>STREETSCAPES/Readers' Questions; Where They Are Is Known; Why They Went, Isn't</title>
    <meta content="01scap" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837243"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Streetscapes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E3D81030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1023" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>STREETSCAPES/Readers' Questions; Where They Are Is Known; Why They Went, Isn't</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q. Do you know when and why the statues by J. Massey Rhind at the old Exchange Court building were taken down?  Randall Gabrielan, Middletown, N.J.</p>
        <p>A. In 1898, the investor William Waldorf Astor built the Exchange Court office building at the southeast corner of Broadway and Exchange Place. The shell is still there, but it was rebuilt in 1981 and is no longer recognizable. Clinton &amp; Russell, Astor's regular architects, designed a rich wedding cake of rusticated limestone, arranged in the shape of a C. The open court formed the entrance -- closed off at night by an elaborate bronze portcullis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q. Do you know when and why the statues by J. Massey Rhind at the old Exchange Court building were taken down?  Randall Gabrielan, Middletown, N.J.</p>
        <p>A. In 1898, the investor William Waldorf Astor built the Exchange Court office building at the southeast corner of Broadway and Exchange Place. The shell is still there, but it was rebuilt in 1981 and is no longer recognizable. Clinton &amp; Russell, Astor's regular architects, designed a rich wedding cake of rusticated limestone, arranged in the shape of a C. The open court formed the entrance -- closed off at night by an elaborate bronze portcullis.</p>
        <p>More bronze was arrayed across the Broadway facade at the third floor: 10-foot-tall statues of Henry Hudson; Peter Stuyvesant; George Clinton, the first governor of New York State; and James Wolfe, the British general. The last was a peculiar choice, although he was famous as the victor against the French in the battle for Quebec in 1759. J. Massey Rhind was the sculptor for all four.</p>
        <p>A good place to start with historical queries about classical architecture is Henry Hope Reed of the nonprofit Institute of Classical Architecture &amp; Classical America, which has its office in New York. He knew immediately where three of the statues were: in Kingston, N.Y., where they can be seen in Academy Green Park.</p>
        <p>And General Wolfe? ''Well, he's in Canada -- Alberta, I think,'' Mr. Reed said.</p>
        <p>The statues were removed sometime between 1945 and 1950, but why is an unanswered question. A letter to the editor of The New York Times in June 1945 noted that the statues were still in place, but a photograph published in The Times in August 1950 shows the building sculptureless.</p>
        <p>The photo was printed to mark Robert W. Dowling's sale of Exchange Court, and he presents interesting possibilities.</p>
        <p>In 1950, at 77th Street and Madison Avenue, he built the old Parke-Bernet Building, which is notable for its aluminum sculpture by Wheeler Williams. He also owned the Carlyle Hotel.</p>
        <p>''He was very interested in art and antiques,'' said his daughter Ruth Dowling Bruun. That an art lover should remove art from his own investment doesn't make obvious sense, but press accounts of the installation at the Kingston park in 1950 describe the statues as having come from a junkyard, suggesting that Mr. Dowling sold them for scrap, an act that seems out of character.</p>
        <p>The plot thickens slightly, because correspondence in the collection of the Glenbow Museum in Calgary, Alberta, indicates that no later than 1951, John J. Cunningham, educational director of the National Sculpture Society, wrote to a church in London about sending the Wolfe statue there. That effort was not successful. Mr. Cunningham may have stumbled across the same junkyard, but he might just as well have been involved with the removal of all four statues.</p>
        <p>In 1966, Mr. Cunningham offered to sell the Wolfe statue to Eric Harvie, a collector in Calgary, for $11,500. Mr. Harvie countered with $8,000, which was accepted.</p>
        <p>Walter Beretta, the monuments officer for the New York City Parks Department, arranged to have the statue cleaned before it was shipped. General Wolfe now stands in front of the Telus World of Science in Calgary. Mr. Beretta had not only studied under J. Massey Rhind but had also looked after New York City park monuments since the 1930s. He must have been keenly aware of his tutor's works at Exchange Court long before their removal.</p>
        <p>What's the History Of 29 East Ninth Street?</p>
        <p>Q. We've been told that our building, 29 East Ninth Street, was built in the late 20s as city ''bachelor'' residences for wealthy Wall Street types whose family homes were out of the city. Any truth to all this?  Arthur Cohen, Manhattan</p>
        <p>A. It looks doubtful. The plot your building occupies was part of the large land holding of the charity for retired seamen, Sailor's Snug Harbor. In the early 1920s, the charity began improving the area around this corner, and in 1922 the architectural firm of Helmle &amp; Corbett filed plans for 29 East Ninth Street, at the northeast corner of University Place.</p>
        <p>Finished in 1923, the building had 24 simplex and duplex apartments of three to seven rooms. Each had a large studio living room, with a ceiling half again as high as those in the rest of the apartment.</p>
        <p>On the facade, the architects used a tawny, lightly mottled brick, with spare decoration hinting at the Romanesque. The most prominent details on the facade are the high studio windows and step-out balconies.</p>
        <p>In 1924, Architecture magazine explained some of the thinking behind the project. New construction techniques permitted lower ceiling heights so that the ''modern apartment is a prison cell -- is it any wonder the restaurants and movies thrive?'' But at least, the magazine said, each apartment at 29 East Ninth Street had a large entertaining room as high as an ''old-fashioned city-house parlor, a fireplace that is real, including a chimney that really draws, and wall space large enough to hang a real tapestry if the tenant should be fortunate enough to possess one.''</p>
        <p>The 1930 census lists for 29 East Ninth show few bachelors and far more couples, often with children. One tenant was Evariste Orteig, who lived there with his family of four. He co-managed the family-run Lafayette Hotel on the southeast corner of East Ninth and University Place. His father, Raymond Orteig, had donated the $25,000 prize claimed by Charles Lindbergh after his trans-Atlantic flight in 1927.</p>
        <p>Another tenant was Robert Benepe, a 32-year-old linen importer, who lived with his wife, Marjorie, and sons Bruce, 8, and Barry, 1, along with a Portuguese-born butler.</p>
        <p>Barry Benepe became an architect, an activist and a founder of the Greenmarkets in New York City. (He is also the father of Adrian Benepe, the city's parks commissioner.)</p>
        <p>As for the rumor that the building was used as ''bachelor'' residences by men who had homes elsewhere, the elder Mr. Benepe said that his family did not have a weekend house until later. ''I spent summers with relatives in Maine,'' he said.</p>
        <p>E-mail: streetscapes@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: streetscapes@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
