<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Updated Italian Fare Fused With French</title>
    <meta content="01wedineWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/01wedine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837186"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/HARRISON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">A'Tavola Bistro 385 (Harrison, NY, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gabriel, Alice</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE3DC1030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="804" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Updated Italian Fare Fused With French</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Updated Italian Fare Fused With French</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALICE GABRIEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gabriel, Alice</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alice Gabriel reviews A'Tavola Bistro 385 restaurant in Harrison, NY; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OPEN since August 2006, A'Tavola Bistro 385 -- the name captures the menu's tilt toward a loose Italian-French fusion -- is ensconced in the Harrison Shopping Center, a stone's throw from the train station. Twin evergreens in black urns stand sentinel outside, where the freshly stained wooden facade and taut new awning signal a fresh start.</p>
        <p>''Neighborhood restaurant'' is sometimes used pejoratively, but A'Tavola, owned by Camille Branca and Paul Harrison (also the chef), is everything a neighborhood restaurant should be: comfortable, welcoming and consistently on its game when it comes to food. One measure of how good it is: on two visits, with the exception of a spoonful or two of sweet risotto pudding, we ate every morsel that came from the kitchen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A’Tavola Bistro 385 in Harrison is everything a neighborhood restaurant should be: comfortable, welcoming and consistently on its game when it comes to food.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OPEN since August 2006, A'Tavola Bistro 385 -- the name captures the menu's tilt toward a loose Italian-French fusion -- is ensconced in the Harrison Shopping Center, a stone's throw from the train station. Twin evergreens in black urns stand sentinel outside, where the freshly stained wooden facade and taut new awning signal a fresh start.</p>
        <p>''Neighborhood restaurant'' is sometimes used pejoratively, but A'Tavola, owned by Camille Branca and Paul Harrison (also the chef), is everything a neighborhood restaurant should be: comfortable, welcoming and consistently on its game when it comes to food. One measure of how good it is: on two visits, with the exception of a spoonful or two of sweet risotto pudding, we ate every morsel that came from the kitchen.</p>
        <p>The restaurant is really one big room, with a burnished wood bar lighted by diminutive Tiffany-style fixtures. Large framed mirrors give the illusion of a more expansive space. The big-screen TV and rhythm-and-blues soundtrack can dominate the stage, but once the food arrives, they fade into the wings. Friendly waiters, with names like Joe and Sal, wear French-blue shirts and baggy jeans, and they know to fill an empty water glass. My only real complaint: on a cold night, with the stone floor making it seem colder, the heat came on in big, intermittent blasts.</p>
        <p>A'Tavola's strong suit is updated Italian fare (the bistro part is a stretch -- even the menu, with misspellings like ''mescalin,'' ''frits'' and ''tartar,'' falls short in the French department). Good rustic starters included grilled polenta spread with melted Maytag blue cheese in a light marinara, and spiedini A'Tavola -- pan-fried bread sandwiched with oozy mozzarella -- in a tomato sauce darkened with anchovies. I loved the deep-fried zucchini ribbons garnished with shaved Parmesan, and the way-above-average fried calamari with a trio of sauces.</p>
        <p>On the lighter side, a salad of tiny arugula, beets, red onion and goat cheese with a lemon-thyme vinaigrette was properly chilled, pretty to look at and wonderful to eat. Fresh, thick slices of mozzarella were layered with roasted red peppers and drizzled with opal basil oil. Tahini ginger sauce pooled in the curved tails of pan-seared sesame shrimp, which were ringed by a bright caramelized mango salsa.</p>
        <p>Amid a sea of modern white porcelain, wild mushroom ravioli arrived on a charming plate with navy blue edges and hand-painted peaches. The dish seemed to capture A'Tavola's gift for the slightly unexpected, and somewhat elevated, presentation.</p>
        <p>We did not splurge on a chilled shellfish tower ($57 and $85) but instead ordered a half-dozen bluepoints, salty and fresh but less than firm. A good way to sample shellfish is by ordering the excellent zuppa di pesce, with its perfectly cooked lobster tail and supporting cast of clams, shrimp and scallops. .</p>
        <p>From a nice array of entrees, I especially liked the grilled wild salmon with horseradish cream sauce. Garlicky skirt steak, seasoned with extra-virgin olive oil and fresh basil, was fork tender and flavorful. Nicely cooked shrimp scampi arrived on a bed of buttery, al dente linguine.</p>
        <p>A few entrees lacked balance: diver scallops, rich by nature, became excessively so when combined with a black truffle demi-glace and dense, creamy risotto. Delicate poached halibut was overwhelmed by bitter broccoli rabe and heavily salted potato crisps.</p>
        <p>For dessert, try the delicious poached pear, or the coconut and raspberry sorbets. Chocolate lava cake, a special one night, was a model of what that overplayed dessert should be. Chocolate polenta cake, also a special, was more novel, and also very good.</p>
        <p>A'Tavola Bistro 385  385 Halstead Avenue  Harrison  (914) 381-6050</p>
        <p>VERY GOOD</p>
        <p>THE SPACE -- One big room, with stone floors and mustard walls, dominated by a wood bar. Bare tabletops, each set with a single votive candle and linen napkins. Patio dining in fair weather.</p>
        <p>THE CROWD -- Mostly adult (on two visits, I counted one infant and two teenagers). There is a children's menu. Dress is casual.</p>
        <p>THE BAR -- Look for novelty martinis and blueberry mojitos. The wine list is limited, with lamentably few affordable Italian selections. I enjoyed the crisp, tropical 2004 Te Awa New Zealand chardonnay ($45).</p>
        <p>THE BILL -- Dinner entrees, $12 to $27. Major credit cards accepted.</p>
        <p>WHAT WE LIKE -- Wild mushroom ravioli, zucchini ribbons, fried calamari, mozzarella spiedini, sesame shrimp, grilled polenta, zuppa di pesce, skirt steak, wild king salmon with horseradish cream sauce, shrimp scampi, poached pear, chocolate polenta cake (special), chocolate lava cake (special), coconut and raspberry sorbets.</p>
        <p>IF YOU GO -- Lunch: Monday to Saturday, 11 a.m. to 3 p.m. Dinner: Monday to Thursday, 5 to 10 p.m.; Friday and Saturday, 5 to 11 p.m.; Sunday, 4 to 9 p.m. Brunch: Sunday, 10:30 a.m. to 2:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>Reviewed April 1, 2007</p>
        <p>DINING/HARRISON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
