<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Sizzling Spring, Phelps Makes His Case to Start Opener Over Mientkiewicz</title>
    <meta content="01yankees-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837477"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E2DC1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="379" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Sizzling Spring, Phelps Makes His Case to Start Opener Over Mientkiewicz</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>TAMPA, Fla., March 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As a Kansas City Royal last season, Doug Mientkiewicz lobbied his manager to start on opening day against a left-handed pitcher.</p>
        <p>''I rewarded him by going out there and striking out twice,'' Mientkiewicz said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As a Kansas City Royal last season, Doug Mientkiewicz lobbied his manager to start on opening day against a left-handed pitcher.</p>
        <p>''I rewarded him by going out there and striking out twice,'' Mientkiewicz said.</p>
        <p>In their opening game Monday, the Yankees will face Scott Kazmir, the All-Star left-hander for the Tampa Bay Devil Rays. Manager Joe Torre seems inclined to start the right-handed-hitting Josh Phelps at first base, rewarding him for a sizzling spring that included another home run Saturday.</p>
        <p>''Josh came in here and set the world on fire, and he deserves it,'' Mientkiewicz said before the Yankees finished spring training with a 3-3 tie against the Detroit Tigers. ''Yes, it will hurt to not start on opening day, but then again, I've never been on a team this good, either.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees scored 930 runs last season, the most in the majors, despite playing for months without Hideki Matsui and Gary Sheffield. They replaced Sheffield with Bobby Abreu last July, and their lineup is so deep that the player Mientkiewicz considers the team's best hitter, Robinson Canó, will bat eighth.</p>
        <p>That is where Torre put Canó on Saturday, in a lineup that seemed to be a preview of what he may use Monday. Johnny Damon led off, followed by Derek Jeter, Abreu and Alex Rodriguez. Jason Giambi hit fifth, followed by Matsui, Jorge Posada, Canó and Phelps. In Phelps's first at-bat, against the left-hander Mike Maroth, he hit his fourth spring homer. Phelps beat out Andy Phillips for a roster spot by hitting .395.</p>
        <p>''I had to have the mind-set coming in that I knew I could make the club and I expected to make it,'' Phelps said.</p>
        <p>Torre would not say if Saturday's lineup was the one he will use Monday, but he called it a reasonable idea. The Yankees, who were 14-13-3 this spring, will work out at Yankee Stadium on Sunday, returning to a clubhouse where Mariano Rivera has taken over Bernie Williams's corner locker.</p>
        <p>The Yankees did not offer Williams a major league contract, and he turned down an invitation to spring training. He played 16 seasons for the Yankees and might have made the team had he been here.</p>
        <p>''We never will know what would have happened,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
