<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Suicidal Secrets</title>
    <meta content="01wwln-ethicist.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Education; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/magazine/01wwln-ethicist.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837043"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 4-01-07: THE ETHICIST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bedbugs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Randy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/The Ethicist</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beds and Bedding</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beds and Bedding</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E4DA1230F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="562" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Suicidal Secrets</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Suicidal Secrets</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Randy Cohen</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Randy Cohen Ethicist column on whether a therapist may inform school officials about suicidal thoughts a teacher experienced long ago if therapist learned about them from a patient, a student to whom teacher divulged this personal history in effort to give student hope that she would overcome her own suicidal thoughts; also comments on whether and how to inform friends that their guest bed is infested with bedbugs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I am a schoolteacher. A teenager told me about her thoughts of suicide. To offer her hope, I told her that I had contemplated suicide decades ago and survived with the support of friends and doctors. She told her therapist about this -- fine with me -- who told our school social worker, who criticized my conduct to our principal, perhaps endangering my job. I'm not the therapist's patient, but was it ethical of her to discuss me?</p>
        <p>name withheld, Conn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dilemmas involving therapy run amokand a run in with bedbugs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I am a schoolteacher. A teenager told me about her thoughts of suicide. To offer her hope, I told her that I had contemplated suicide decades ago and survived with the support of friends and doctors. She told her therapist about this -- fine with me -- who told our school social worker, who criticized my conduct to our principal, perhaps endangering my job. I'm not the therapist's patient, but was it ethical of her to discuss me?</p>
        <p>name withheld, Conn.</p>
        <p>There is plenty of blame to go around: everyone acted imperfectly.</p>
        <p>Although the therapist had no professional duty to you -- as you note, you are not her patient -- she erred by ordinary civilian standards when she chatted about you to the school social worker, passing along secondhand information that could be damaging.</p>
        <p>(Of course, ''therapist'' is an elastic designation. Some are highly trained practitioners bound by a professional code of conduct. Others are my imaginary Uncle Milt, who has no training whatever but who does have a nice couch in the garage. He is bound only by my equally imaginary Aunt Selma.)</p>
        <p>The therapist also ill served her patient by talking about her out of school (albeit in school). Howard Owens, a forensic psychiatrist, explains: ''It is a clinical error to report on the teacher because of the likely impact of doing so on the student and on the therapeutic relationship. How is the teenager likely to react when she finds out that she has gotten her teacher in trouble? Depressed people don't usually profit from being made to feel more guilty.''</p>
        <p>The social worker transgressed by running to the principal with this thirdhand story. The principal can be faulted if she allows this information to influence professional decisions about you. Even the student can be gently faulted for repeating your story without consent, although in her defense, she should have been able to rely on her therapist's discretion.</p>
        <p>You, too, could be chided, at least for your naïveté. You should have anticipated that a young person might repeat such an emotionally fraught story about a teacher. Also questionable was your attempt to engage in a quasi-therapeutic relationship with a student in so fragile an emotional state.</p>
        <p>The mitigating factor here: Everyone seems to have had benign motives. The adults were concerned with the student's well-being, and the student herself meant no harm.</p>
        <p>Last summer, I visited friends at their chateau in France -- good company, excellent food, but a lumpy mattress full of bedbugs. Badly bitten, I said nothing, but I know I'll be invited back. How can I politely tell them about their infestation? Or more politely, must I remain silent and simply decline the invitation?</p>
        <p>Joan Shore, Fort Lauderdale, Fla.</p>
        <p>You're waiting until now to tell them that their house is infested? What would you do if the chateau were on fire, mention it demurely in a few months? If this situation involved only your own comfort, you could keep silent, but because other people are at risk, you must speak up. Here's how you tell them: You tell them -- on the telephone, using a fake accent and a false name. No, no -- openly, honestly, calmly. I can understand your desire not to embarrass your friends or imperil your relationship, but I hope they will value your candor and realize that having bedbugs is not a moral failing.</p>
        <p>THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 4-01-07: THE ETHICIST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
