<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Castle's Colorful Story Gets a Heavy Rewrite</title>
    <meta content="01njtopicNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/01njtopic.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837211"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HISTORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fleming Castle (Flemington, NJ)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Flemington (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Berland, Dennis, Associates</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mallozzi, Vincent M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E0D91030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Castle's Colorful Story Gets a Heavy Rewrite</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Castle’s Colorful Story Gets a Heavy Rewrite</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VINCENT M. MALLOZZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mallozzi, Vincent M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Fleming Castle in Flemington, NJ, which tour guides for years have extolled as tavern visited by George Washington, stagecoach stop and post office; Dennis Berland Associates, historic preservation consultants, has debunked much of castle's traditional lore; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANYONE who has toured Fleming Castle might consider returning for another round of tales that may not be so tall.</p>
        <p>For years, tour guides have been regaling visitors -- whether Girl Scouts, business people or history buffs -- with sensational stories attached to the historic home on Bonnell Street in Flemington, which was believed to be a tavern visited by George Washington, a stagecoach stop and a post office.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANYONE who has toured Fleming Castle might consider returning for another round of tales that may not be so tall.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANYONE who has toured Fleming Castle might consider returning for another round of tales that may not be so tall.</p>
        <p>For years, tour guides have been regaling visitors -- whether Girl Scouts, business people or history buffs -- with sensational stories attached to the historic home on Bonnell Street in Flemington, which was believed to be a tavern visited by George Washington, a stagecoach stop and a post office.</p>
        <p>But Dennis Bertland Associates, historic preservation consultants based in Bloomsbury and hired by the borough of Flemington, has all but put an end to that romance, debunking much of Fleming Castle's traditional lore.</p>
        <p>''This is a case of history getting embellished'' by writers after an 1870 article in The Hunterdon Republican reported the bare bones of the story correctly, said Dennis Bertland, the principal at the firm. His historical analysis and summary of the 18th-century dwelling does not include a single mention of George Washington, the stagecoach stop or the post office. He also discovered through court documents that the tavern was actually situated elsewhere.</p>
        <p>''None of this research diminishes Fleming Castle in any way,'' he said. ''In fact, there is a new history that actually enriches the story.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bertland's report formed part of a historic preservation plan for Fleming Castle that was put together by Historic Building Architects of Trenton.</p>
        <p>Carmen Grimes, president of the Fleming Castle Board of Trustees, said she was ''surprised that there was such a difference between what we thought was, and what actually is, the history of Fleming Castle.''</p>
        <p>''Frankly, I still love the old stories,'' she said. ''I think the plan now is for our docents to combine some of the old stories with this new information.''</p>
        <p>Visitors to the castle -- tours are given every other Saturday -- will learn that in 1741, an Irishman named Samuel Fleming bought 210 acres from Thomas Penn, whose father, William, founded Pennsylvania. In 1746, according to court records Mr. Bertland unearthed, Mr. Fleming was granted a license to run a tavern, but it was issued 10 years before he is claimed to have built his so-called castle.</p>
        <p>''We know that Fleming's tavern and the castle were in two different places,'' Mr. Bertland said. ''We know this because court records show that property on which Fleming Castle stands was seized in a sheriff's sale in 1763 to settle judgments for debt and that the tavern was put up in a separate sheriff's sale three years later.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bertland could find no evidence that Mr. Fleming ever referred to his home as a castle. It is first described as a castle in the minutes of a 1906 meeting of the Colonel Lowrey Chapter of the Daughters of the American Revolution.</p>
        <p>The chapter, named for Thomas Lowrey, a militia colonel who married a daughter of Mr. Fleming, was organized in 1899. In 1927, the house was deeded to the chapter, which maintained it as its headquarters and museum until 2005, when the borough bought it for $138,000.</p>
        <p>''Fleming Castle emerged from my investigation as a significant early example of historic preservation,'' Mr. Bertland said. ''In 1906 it became the first property to be marked with a historic plaque in Hunterdon County, and in 1927-28 it became the first property to be acquired for restoration.''</p>
        <p>The history that Mr. Bertland found involves Mr. Lowrey and his son-in-law Thomas Skelton. In 1772 Mr. Skelton bought the plantation that Mr. Fleming had lost in 1763.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lowrey and Mr. Skelton had become business partners, but they pledged allegiance to different flags. While Mr. Lowrey stood for the colonies' independence, Mr. Skelton remained loyal to the British crown and fled to England. New Jersey confiscated his American property.</p>
        <p>Janice Armstrong, Fleming Castle's director of education, said she found Mr. Bertland's revelations ''kind of exciting in some ways.''</p>
        <p>She also noted that Fleming Castle's revised history had taught a valuable lesson to anyone associated with the house: ''Through all of this, we learned that just because someone told you something, it doesn't necessarily mean it's true.''</p>
        <p>HISTORY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
