<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Force in Touring Hits the End of the Road</title>
    <meta content="01robe" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/theater/01robe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837117"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Live Nation Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pace Theatrical Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Clear Channel Communications Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robertson, Campbell</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilkin, Miles</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zeiger, Scott</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rapino, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Clear Channel Communications Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Viertel, Thomas</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Seller, Jeffrey</person>
        <person class="online_producer">McCollum, Kevin</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE2DD1330F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1431" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Force in Touring Hits the End of the Road</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Force in Touring Hits the End of the Road</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAMPBELL ROBERTSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robertson, Campbell</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Live Nation will sell off its North American theatrical business assets, thus ending attempt to align Broadway and Wall Street; origins of Live Nation as Pace Theatrical, created by Miles Wilkin and Scott Zeiger, involvement of Clear Channel Communications, spin-off of Live Nation in 2005 and chief executive Michael Rapino's decision to end its theater business discussed; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE it was, the long-expected news.</p>
        <p>''As part of our strategy to focus on our core global music business,'' read Live Nation's quarterly statement last month, ''we have launched a process to divest the majority of our North American theatrical business assets.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The sale of Live Nation’s theater business illustrates the bizarreness of live entertainment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE it was, the long-expected news.</p>
        <p>''As part of our strategy to focus on our core global music business,'' read Live Nation's quarterly statement last month, ''we have launched a process to divest the majority of our North American theatrical business assets.''</p>
        <p>With that, the end was in sight of one of the most high-profile attempts to align Broadway and Wall Street.</p>
        <p>Live Nation's ''theatrical business assets'' have changed names more often than P. Diddy. They started 25 years ago as a division of a pioneering company called Pace Management, which was bought in 1997 by an aggressively acquisitive company called SFX Entertainment, which was in turn bought by the colossal public company Clear Channel, which then spun off all its live entertainment business as Live Nation, also a public company.</p>
        <p>What that company grew into over those 25 years -- and what is now on the auction block -- includes the country's largest subscription series for touring theatrical performances; 13 performing centers the company owns, operates or has an interest in, including theaters in Chicago, Boston, Washington and Philadelphia; and a majority investment in the Las Vegas production of ''The Phantom of the Opera.''</p>
        <p>The company also owns the Hilton Theater on Broadway, the Boston Opera House and a touring theater business in Britain, but will not be selling any of those holdings because of tax restrictions.</p>
        <p>When Live Nation was spun off in December 2005, Michael Rapino, who took over as chief executive, made clear (dismayingly clear to many theater professionals) that his priority was music. The shedding of the theater business was just part of his strategy, which is apparently working. The company's stock price doubled soon after it was spun off, though it has stayed at an even plateau for the last few months.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rapino and Live Nation declined to comment for this article.</p>
        <p>But the sale of Live Nation's theater business also illustrates the bizarreness of live entertainment, an industry in which family dynasties and go-it-alone entrepreneurs can thrive while multibillion-dollar corporations sometimes stumble.</p>
        <p>Only a few years ago independent theater producers around the country worried that the large conglomerates would march in, Wal-Mart-like, and put the locals out of business.</p>
        <p>Chief among the threats was Clear Channel, which, as a presenter, promoter, theater owner and producer, had the potential to eat up the whole industry. Within five years, though, its foray into live entertainment was a disappointment -- to shareholders in particular.</p>
        <p>Broadway touring can be a money-making business over the long haul, but the margins are thin and terribly capricious. There are good years and bad years; a lackluster season on Broadway can leave the road depressed, while a season with ''Wicked'' can mean Champagne all around.</p>
        <p>To achieve the consistent, and sizable, growth Wall Street demands, there are few options for a road promoter -- build more theaters, raise ticket prices or squeeze more money out of partners -- and all those options are restricted.</p>
        <p>''The theater business belongs in private hands because it can't grow with any consistency,'' said Tom Viertel, a producer who has worked with all the iterations of the company's theater division. ''The nature of the product flow is so unpredictable.''</p>
        <p>When Miles Wilkin helped create Pace Theatrical in Houston in 1982, the business of taking Broadway shows on the road looked nothing like the way it does now. But Mr. Wilkin and his partners, including Scott Zeiger, through smarts, savvy and ruthless negotiating, became enormously influential promoters. They built and renovated theaters, stabilized the business and brought Broadway shows to many cities that had never presented them before. The company also invested in and produced shows on Broadway, cementing relationships with producers whose shows Pace would later be booking.</p>
        <p>''The road as we know it today,'' said Albert Nocciolino, the president of NAC Entertainment, a Broadway tour producer in New York and Pennsylvania, ''has to give tremendous credit to Pace.''</p>
        <p>In 1997 Pace, which was partnered with a few dozen theaters in secondary touring cities, was bought by SFX Entertainment, a large but privately owned live-entertainment company. SFX was on an acquisition binge and spent millions to move into new and bigger areas like Boston, making it an obligatory business partner for any producer with a show on tour.</p>
        <p>Three years later Clear Channel Communications, the broadcast and outdoor advertising giant, bought the business for $3.3 billion. Though the cast did not change at the theatrical offices, a feeling began to sink in for many that something had been lost.</p>
        <p>''Everybody who was over there stopped having a good time,'' said the producer Jeffrey Seller, who also owns a booking company with his business partner, Kevin McCollum, and Live Nation.</p>
        <p>Clear Channel, which actually owned few theaters but had partnerships with dozens, made its touring series into a national brand, Broadway Across America. This was a mistake, several theater professionals say, in a business where taste varies so greatly from region to region.</p>
        <p>''One side of the company didn't know what the other was talking about,'' said Glenda Kennedy, the executive director of the Broadway series in Birmingham, Ala., which ended its partnership with Live Nation last year. ''When a decision needed to be made on booking a show, it would take months and months on what seemed to be a lot of red tape.''</p>
        <p>The live entertainment business turned out be, in some ways, a little hard to swallow. Though Clear Channel had some success producing on Broadway, with shows like ''The Producers'' and ''Movin' Out,'' it also invested heavily in several bombs (a tradition Live Nation continued; the company recently lost more than $1 million on ''High Fidelity'').</p>
        <p>The value of the division plummeted, and in 2005 Clear Channel spun it off as Live Nation. Mr. Wilkin, who had been leading the division for 23 years, left. Mr. Rapino took over.</p>
        <p>It was clear from the beginning that Mr. Rapino was a not a theater man. In the winter of 2006 he came to the Live Nation conference in Miami, where, according to several people who were there, he said that he would ensure the success of the theater business, but that theater was not a personal interest of his.</p>
        <p>''All of a sudden we were faced with an organization that didn't know the work and didn't love it,'' said Colleen Jennings-Roggensack, who, as the executive director of public events at Arizona State University, oversees a Broadway series that owes its existence to Pace. ''In a way it made us grow up a little more.''</p>
        <p>But for several theaters it was the last straw. The theater business is still dependent on handshakes and smiles. For years Mr. Wilkin and Mr. Zeiger kept their road empire intact not only through business ability but also through force of personality, several producers and regional theater operators said. The departure of Mr. Wilkin and, several months later, Mr. Zeiger left a few Live Nation partners wondering what was keeping them attached.</p>
        <p>''I had been working with certain people,'' said Judith Lisi, the president of the mammoth Tampa Bay Performing Arts Center, which announced the end of its partnership with Live Nation in March 2006. ''And I felt I didn't know who I was going to be doing business with.''</p>
        <p>So what now?</p>
        <p>In the gap left by Mr. Wilkin and Mr. Zeiger, a few entities have tried to move in and take their place, most notably the Independent Presenters Network, a coalition of 60 performing arts centers, promoters and theaters that formed as a counterweight to Clear Channel.</p>
        <p>But even though Live Nation's road business still represents about a third of the touring Broadway attendance, Mr. Nocciolino, the tour producer, said, the absence of Mr. Wilkin and Mr. Zeiger's muscle is noticed.</p>
        <p>The process of selling Live Nation's theater business is just beginning, but a few interested parties have been mentioned by theater professionals following the situation.</p>
        <p>Among them are the Nederlander Organization; John Gore, a British producer and investor; AEG, a Los Angeles-based sports and entertainment presenter; and David Ian, the current chairman of Live Nation's global theater operations (who is also a judge on the reality show '' 'Grease': You're the One That I Want'').</p>
        <p>Most intriguingly, both Mr. Zeiger and Mr. Wilkin have been mentioned, separately, as interested bidders. If one of them is successful, the company could end up coming within a few degrees of full circle.</p>
        <p>All these people and companies declined to comment, with some citing confidentiality agreements. But they all have one thing in common: None of them have to answer to Wall Street.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
