<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Going Up, Getting Grumpy</title>
    <meta content="01elev" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/thecity/01elev.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837294"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: UPPER EAST SIDE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elevators and Escalators</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Torgovnick, Kate</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elevators and Escalators</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Upper East Side (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E4DB1130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="468" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Going Up, Getting Grumpy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Going Up, Getting Grumpy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATE TORGOVNICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Torgovnick, Kate</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elevator in apartment house on Upper East Side has become bulletin board for complaints among neighbors and temporary forum for hot-button, buildingwide subjects; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The flier appeared on the elevator wall about a month ago. ''I cannot sleep with you listening to music and stomping back and forth all night,'' it read. ''Please be respectful or, at a minimum, buy a rug.'' The writer was not shy -- the apartment number was typed at the top in bold letters.</p>
        <p>Twenty minutes later, the flier was gone. Maybe the author had second thoughts, or maybe the message had reached its intended recipient.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The flier appeared on the elevator wall about a month ago. “I cannot sleep with you listening to music and stomping back and forth all night,” it read. “Please be respectful or, at a minimum, buy a rug.” The writer was not shy  the apartment number was typed at the top in bold letters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The flier appeared on the elevator wall about a month ago. ''I cannot sleep with you listening to music and stomping back and forth all night,'' it read. ''Please be respectful or, at a minimum, buy a rug.'' The writer was not shy -- the apartment number was typed at the top in bold letters.</p>
        <p>Twenty minutes later, the flier was gone. Maybe the author had second thoughts, or maybe the message had reached its intended recipient.</p>
        <p>The sleepless note writer is only one of the inhabitants of the six-story Upper East Side apartment house, where this reporter lives, who have used its faux-marble-paneled elevator as a grumpy public forum. Somehow, perhaps because it has a captive audience, the elevator has become a bulletin board for complaints.</p>
        <p>Some of the notes at the building, on 78th Street between First and York Avenues, are mild correctives, like the superintendent's reminders to tenants to tie their trash bags carefully and to clean their chimney flues to keep smoke from pervading the building. But others are angry, like the flier posted by Curvin O'Rielly, a freelance advertising creative director, about his mauled newspaper.</p>
        <p>''There's a 'crime wave' in the building,'' Mr. O'Rielly wrote, complaining that his paper ''arrives at my door rumpled and pawed over, frequently with multiple pages, even whole sections missing.'' The note continued: ''It's not a crime that the N.Y.P.D. will investigate. Nor is it a crime that will send the perpetrator to jail. Instead, it's sort of like shoplifting. A petty crime that's damn embarrassing if/when you're caught.''</p>
        <p>Speaking of his decision to go public on the elevator wall, Mr. O'Rielly said, ''It got to the point where I couldn't take it.'' He had ended his flier with an indignant ''If you live in this building, you can afford your own copy.''</p>
        <p>While elevators may not often be pressed into service for gripe work, sometimes they become temporary forums for hot-button, buildingwide subjects. Theo Gangi, a novelist, recalled full-out elevator hostilities a year ago in an apartment building on West 179th Street in Washington Heights. After the gas lines in the building were replaced, gas service for the entire building could not be restored until the lines in every apartment had been tested. The management company posted a polite memo in the elevator.</p>
        <p>''The fliers got increasingly nasty, really quickly,'' said Mr. Gangi, referring to the anger that developed as tenants waited for neighbors to comply so they could resume using their ovens. ''My apartment was on the market, and people were coming in and seeing this elevator where people were just firing bullets at each other.''</p>
        <p>But maybe the elevator strategy works. Back on 78th Street last Sunday, for the first time in a month, Mr. O'Rielly's newspaper arrived at his door untouched.</p>
        <p>KATE TORGOVNICK</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: UPPER EAST SIDE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
