<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CALENDAR</title>
    <meta content="01CTlistingsCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837174"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E4DC1030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2496" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CALENDAR</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Connecticut this week. Items for the guide should be sent at least three weeks in advance to ctcal@nytimes.com, or by mail to Connecticut Weekly, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036-3959.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Bridgeport ''Cabaret Songs: Songs From the Great American Rittbook,'' presented by Ritt Henn, bass, Joe Monnonna, keyboard, and others. Friday at 8 p.m. $15 to $20. Black Rock Art Center, 2838 Fairfield Avenue. (203) 367-7917.</p>
        <p>Bridgeport ''Swingtime!'' Presented by the Wayne Hiller Jazz Trio and others. April 7 at 7:30 p.m. $25. Playhouse on the Green, 177 State Street. (203) 333-6211.</p>
        <p>Greenwich The Chamber Players of the Greenwich Symphony; works by Telemann, Ravel and others. Monday at 8 p.m. $20; students, $5. Bruce Museum of Arts and Sciences, 1 Museum Drive. (203) 869-6468.</p>
        <p>Hartford Connecticut Trio Chamber Music, featuring Gerard Rose, Linda Laurent and others. Thursday at 7:30 p.m. $10 to $15. Old State House, 800 Main Street. (860) 522-6766.</p>
        <p>New Canaan ''Collegium Royale,'' music of Herbert Howells presented by the church choir. April 1 at 4 p.m. Donation: $12. First Presbyterian Church of New Canaan, 178 Oenoke Ridge. (203) 966-0002.</p>
        <p>New Haven Wallace Roney Sextet, jazz. Friday at 8:30 and 10 p.m. $10 and $15. Firehouse 12, 45 Crown Street. (203) 785-0468.</p>
        <p>Torrington Puccini's ''Madama Butterfly,'' presented by Teatro Lirico d'Europa. April 1 at 7:30 p.m. $19.50 to 59.50. Mannheim Steamroller, classical rock. April 7 at 8 p.m. $49.50 to $100. Warner Theater, 68 Main Street. (860) 489-7180.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>New Britain ''Wit,'' by Margaret Edison, directed by Warren Dutkiewicz. Through April 7. Donation: $15. Hole in the Wall Theater, 116 Main Street. (860) 229-3049.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''The Blue Album'' by David Cale and Dael Orlandersmith, directed by Gordon Edelstein. Through April 29. $41.25 to $61.25. Long Wharf Theater, 222 Sargent Drive. (203) 787-4282.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''The River Niger'' by Joseph A. Walker, directed by Malcolm K. Darrell. Thursday through April 7. $10 to $15. Yale Cabaret, 217 Park Street. (203) 432-1566.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Lulu'' by Frank Wedekind, directed by Mark Lamos. Through April 21. $22.50 to $55. Yale Repertory Theater, 1120 Chapel Street. (203) 432-1234.</p>
        <p>Oakville ''It Runs in the Family'' by Ray Cooney, directed by Harold J. Pantely. Through April 7. $16. Clockwork Repertory Theater, 133 Main Street. (860) 274-7247.</p>
        <p>Stamford ''Trying'' by Joanna McClelland Glass, directed by Steve Karp. Through April 1. $22 to $38. Stamford Theater Works, 200 Strawberry Hill Avenue. (203) 359-4414.</p>
        <p>Storrs ''North Shore Fish,'' by Israel Horovitz, presented by the Connecticut Repertory Theater. Through April 1. $15.50 to $26. Jorgensen Center for the Performing Arts, 2132 Hillside Road, University of Connecticut. (860) 486-4226.</p>
        <p>Waterbury ''Viagara Falls,'' comedy by Joao Machado and Lou Cutell, directed by Don Crichton. Through April 15. $27 to $45. Seven Angels Theater, Plank Road in Hamilton Park Pavilion. (203) 757-4676.</p>
        <p>Westport ''Born Yesterday'' by Garson Kanin, presented by the Westport Community Theater. Through April 15. $12 to $16. Westport Town Hall, 110 Myrtle Avenue. (203) 226-1983.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Beauty in Trouble,'' directed by Jan Hrebejk; in Czech with English subtitles. April 1 at 2 p.m. $3 to $8. ''Volver,'' directed by Pedro Almodóvar; in Spanish with English subtitles. Thursday and April 7 at 7:30 p.m.; April 8 at 2 p.m. $3 to $8. Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art, 600 Main Street. (860) 838-4058.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''The Skull,'' directed by Freddie Francis. April 7 at 2 p.m. Free. Yale Center for British Art, 1080 Chapel Street. (203) 432-2800.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>Hamden ''The Legacy of Eleanor Roosevelt,'' lecture by Anna Eleanor Roosevelt. Wednesday at 7 p.m. Free. Alumni Hall, Quinnipiac University. (203) 582-8425.</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Dish,'' discussion with various chefs about food, the restaurant business and dining out; moderated by Rand Richards Cooper, contributing editor of ''Bon Appétit.'' Monday at 7 p.m. Free. Real Art Ways, 56 Arbor Street. (860) 232-1006.</p>
        <p>Madison Giada De Laurentiis, author of the cookbook ''Everyday Italian.'' Tuesday at 1 p.m. Free with purchase of book. R. J. Julia Booksellers, 768 Boston Road. (203) 245-3959.</p>
        <p>New Haven Paul Mellon Lectures: ''The Rise of the Regional Museum in Victorian Britain, Parts I and II,'' lecture presented by Giles Waterfield, independent writer and curator. Tuesday and Wednesday at 4 p.m. ''Collecting for the People,'' lecture presented by Mr. Waterfield. Thursday at 5:30 p.m. Both free. Yale Center for British Art, 1080 Chapel Street. (203) 432-2800.</p>
        <p>Old Greenwich Patrick Carman, author of children's book ''Atherton: The House of Power.'' Tuesday at 3:30 p.m. Free. Arcadia Coffee Company, 20 Arcadia Road. (203) 637-8766.</p>
        <p>Stamford Big Read: Charles Shields, author of ''Mockingbird: A Portrait of Harper Lee.'' April 1 at 1 p.m. Free. Ferguson Library Main Branch, 1 Public Library Plaza. (203) 964-1000.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>Bridgeport ''Peter Rabbit,'' adapted from the book by Beatrix Potter. Through April 1. ''Beauty and the Beast.'' April 1 through May 20. Both: $13.50. Downtown Cabaret Theater, 263 Golden Hill Street. (203) 576-1636.</p>
        <p>Bridgeport ''Creativity Ignited!'' Interactive children's exhibition exploring the imagination. Through April 30. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. The Discovery Museum, 4450 Park Avenue. (203) 372-3521.</p>
        <p>Glastonbury ''Earthworms.'' Learn what worms eat and why they are important. Ages 3 to 5. Monday at 1 p.m. and Wednesday at 10 a.m. $13; members, $10; reservations required. The Connecticut Audubon Society Center at Glastonbury, 1361 Main Street. (860) 633-8402.</p>
        <p>Waterbury ''Great Expectations,'' adapted from the novel by Charles Dickens. Ages 12 to 18. Thursday at 9:30 and 11:30 a.m. $8. Palace Theater of Connecticut, 100 East Main Street. (203) 755-4700.</p>
        <p>Wilton ''Norwalk Symphony Family Program (Not) Just For Kids, Part 4.'' Play various brass instruments. Ages 3 to 10. April 7 at 2 p.m. Free; advance registration recommended. Wilton Library, 137 Old Ridgefield Road. (203) 762-3950.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>Brookfield ''Fiber Cartography: Mapping Imagination and Experience,'' works by 10 fiber artists. Through April 29. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Brookfield Craft Center, 286 Whisconier Road. (203) 775-4526.</p>
        <p>Greenwich ''Natural Elements,'' works by Bryan Nash Gill, Catherine Kernan and Eve Stockton. Through April 26. Hours: Mondays through Wednesdays and Fridays and Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Flinn Gallery, 101 West Putnam Avenue. (203) 622-7947.</p>
        <p>Guilford ''Exhibition of Miniatures,'' works by Tom Edwards, Gail Friedland and others. Through April 22. Guilford Art Center, 411 Church Street. (203) 453-5947.</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Soul Food: African American Cooking and Creativity,'' art and artifacts exploring Southern cooking and culture; presented by the Amistad Center for Art and Culture. Through April 22. ''Faith and Fortune: Five Centuries of European Masterworks,'' exhibition of European masterworks and sculpture from the museum's collection. Through Dec. 9. ''Picasso to Pop: Aspects of Modern Art,'' exhibition of the museum's holdings from many 20th-century genres. Through Nov. 18. $3 to $10; members and children 12 and under, free. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; first Thursdays of the month, 11 a.m. to 8 p.m. Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art, 600 Main Street. (860) 838-4058.</p>
        <p>Litchfield Works by Nancy Lasar and Amanda Branson. Through April 15. Hours: Thursdays through Mondays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. New Arts Gallery, 513 Maple Street. (860) 567-5015.</p>
        <p>Mashantucket ''Booming Out: Mohawk Ironworkers Build New York,'' photographs and sculpture documenting the Mohawk sky-walking construction tradition passed through six generations. Through May 27. $10 to $15; children under 6, free. Hours: Daily, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center, 110 Pequot Trail. (800) 411-9671.</p>
        <p>Middletown ''Etching Since 1950.'' Through April 8. ''A Newspaperman's Eye,'' American photographs from the collection of Russell G. D'Oench. Through May 27. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Davison Art Center, 301 High Street, Wesleyan University. (860) 685-2500.</p>
        <p>Middletown ''Brushwork by Kazuaki Tanahashi.'' Tuesday through May 6. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Mansfield Freeman Center for East Asian Studies Gallery, Wesleyan University, 343 Washington Terrace. (860) 685-2330.</p>
        <p>Milford ''Black and White,'' juried group exhibition. Through Thursday. Hours: Thursdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Firehouse Art Gallery, 81 Naugatuck. (203) 306-0016.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Random Access Memory,'' works dealing with memory by Liz Pagano and Colleen Tully. Through April 29. Free. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Arts + Literature Laboratory, 319 Peck Street. (203) 671-5175.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Women's Studies: New Works by Mary Lesser.'' Thursday through April 29. Reception: April 15, 3 to 6 p.m. Hours: Thursdays through Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. City Gallery, 994 State Street. (203) 782-2489.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Ceramic Abstraction: Exploration and Evidence,'' juried group exhibition. Through May 4. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Creative Arts Workshop, 80 Audubon Street. (203) 562-4927.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''New Haven's Garment Workers: An Elm City Story,'' photographs and artifacts documenting the 20th-century garment industry. Through May 4. Free. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to noon. Ethnic Heritage Center, 270 Fitch Street. (203) 392-6126.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Howard Hodgkin: Paintings 1992-2007.'' Through April 1. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Yale Center for British Art, 1080 Chapel Street. (203) 432-2800.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''UNStudio: Evolution of Space,'' exhibition of five projects by the Amsterdam-based firm. Through May 4. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Yale School of Architecture Gallery, 180 York Street. (203) 432-2889.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Jasper Johns: From Plate to Print.'' Through April 1. ''Making a Mark: Four Contemporary Artists in Print,'' prints by Enrique Chagoya, Carroll Dunham, Jane Hammond and Kiki Smith. Through April 1. ''Made for Love: Selections From the Jane Katcher Collection of Americana,'' 30 works of art that focus on the ways love and friendship are expressed through gift exchange. Through Aug. 26. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 6 p.m. Yale University Art Gallery. (203) 432-0600.</p>
        <p>New London ''Gas in Glass: The Light Sculptures of Mundy Hepburn.'' Through June 24. ''Expresiones/Expressions: Caribbean and Latin American Art From the Benjamin Ortiz Collection.'' Through June 24. $3 and $4; children 6 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Lyman Allyn Art Museum, 625 Williams Street. (860) 443-2545.</p>
        <p>New Milford ''Rural Wealth,'' photographs by Ray Kwiatkowski. Through May 5. Hours: Mondays, Thursdays and Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Tuesdays and Wednesdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 1 p.m. New Milford Public Library, 24 Main Street. (860) 355-1191.</p>
        <p>Old Lyme ''Shadows and Pulls: A Short History,'' photographs by Ellen Carey. April 1 through May 5. Reception: April 1, noon to 4 p.m. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Diane Birdsall Gallery, 68 Lyme Street. (860) 434-3209.</p>
        <p>Old Lyme ''The Freedom Business: Connecticut Landscapes Through the Eyes of Venture Smith,'' poems by Marilyn Nelson paired with paintings from the museum's collection. Through June 24. ''A Circle of Friends: The Artists of the Florence Griswold Museum.'' Through July 1. $4 to $8; under 6, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Florence Griswold Museum, 96 Lyme Street. (860) 434-5542.</p>
        <p>Ridgefield ''The Photograph as Canvas,'' works by artists who draw or paint on photographs. Through June 10. ''Tekrar,'' sound installation by David Abir. Through Aug. 12. ''W(E)AVE,'' sound and textile collaboration between Elana Herzog and Michael Schumacher. Through Aug. 12. ''Blow Ups: Spores, Pollen and Pollutants,'' works by Kysa Johnson. Through June 10. ''Castles, Dwarfs and Happychaps,'' work by Arturo Herrera created using the Renaissance technique of pouncing. Through Sept. 2. ''Chrysanthemum Anthems,'' sculpture by Dario Robleto based on American soldiers' experience of wars. Through June 17. $7; seniors and students, $4; members, K-12 teachers and children under 18, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Aldrich Contemporary Art Museum, 258 Main Street. (203) 438-4519.</p>
        <p>Stamford ''Great Dames Part Trois,'' works by female artists. Through April 10. Hours: Fridays and Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Loft Artist Gallery at Yale and Towne, 737 Canal Street. (203) 323-4153.</p>
        <p>Storrs ''Salvage Research Soul Training,'' installation by Nari Ward. Through April 13. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. Contemporary Art Galleries, 830 Bolton Road, University of Connecticut, Storrs Campus. (860) 486-1511.</p>
        <p>Storrs ''Intemperate Times: Kathe Kollwitz, 1918-1934.'' Through May 6. ''Tradition and Innovation: Latin American Art From the Benton Collection.'' Through June 17. ''Old Master Drawings and Prints,'' exhibition of 15 Italian and Dutch works dating from 1539 to 1690. Through May 6. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 4:30 p.m. William Benton Museum of Art, 245 Glenbrook Road. (860) 486-4520.</p>
        <p>Waterbury ''From Colonial Village to Country Retreat,'' exhibition exploring the architectural history of Middlebury. Through April 7. $4; children under 16, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Mattatuck Museum Arts and History Center, 144 West Main Street. (203) 753-0381.</p>
        <p>West Hartford Works by Paul Bowen and Pat de Groot. Through May 5. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Brick Walk Fine Art, 322 Park Road. (860) 233-1730.</p>
        <p>Westport Oil paintings by Yetvart Kaprielian. Through April 27. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Galerie Je Reviens, 991 Post Road East. (203) 227-7716.</p>
        <p>Westport ''States of Connecticut,'' juried exhibition with works by various artists. Through April 29. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Westport Arts Center, 51 Riverside Avenue. (203) 222-7070.</p>
        <p>Westport ''Art and the Good Earth: As Seen Through the Painter's Eye,'' works by 14 artists. Through May 11. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Westport Historical Society, 25 Avery Place. (203) 224-1424.</p>
        <p>Woodbury ''Pattern Play,'' paintings by Anne Hebebrand and sculpture by Diana Chamberlain. Through May 13. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Fenn Gallery, 345 Main Street South. (203) 263-3449.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Connecticut this week. Items for the guide should be sent at least three weeks in advance to ctcal@nytimes.com, or by mail to Connecticut Weekly, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036-3959.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Bridgeport ''Cabaret Songs: Songs From the Great American Rittbook,'' presented by Ritt Henn, bass, Joe Monnonna, keyboard, and others. Friday at 8 p.m. $15 to $20. Black Rock Art Center, 2838 Fairfield Avenue. (203) 367-7917.</p>
        <p>Bridgeport ''Swingtime!'' Presented by the Wayne Hiller Jazz Trio and others. April 7 at 7:30 p.m. $25. Playhouse on the Green, 177 State Street. (203) 333-6211.</p>
        <p>Greenwich The Chamber Players of the Greenwich Symphony; works by Telemann, Ravel and others. Monday at 8 p.m. $20; students, $5. Bruce Museum of Arts and Sciences, 1 Museum Drive. (203) 869-6468.</p>
        <p>Hartford Connecticut Trio Chamber Music, featuring Gerard Rose, Linda Laurent and others. Thursday at 7:30 p.m. $10 to $15. Old State House, 800 Main Street. (860) 522-6766.</p>
        <p>New Canaan ''Collegium Royale,'' music of Herbert Howells presented by the church choir. April 1 at 4 p.m. Donation: $12. First Presbyterian Church of New Canaan, 178 Oenoke Ridge. (203) 966-0002.</p>
        <p>New Haven Wallace Roney Sextet, jazz. Friday at 8:30 and 10 p.m. $10 and $15. Firehouse 12, 45 Crown Street. (203) 785-0468.</p>
        <p>Torrington Puccini's ''Madama Butterfly,'' presented by Teatro Lirico d'Europa. April 1 at 7:30 p.m. $19.50 to 59.50. Mannheim Steamroller, classical rock. April 7 at 8 p.m. $49.50 to $100. Warner Theater, 68 Main Street. (860) 489-7180.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>New Britain ''Wit,'' by Margaret Edison, directed by Warren Dutkiewicz. Through April 7. Donation: $15. Hole in the Wall Theater, 116 Main Street. (860) 229-3049.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''The Blue Album'' by David Cale and Dael Orlandersmith, directed by Gordon Edelstein. Through April 29. $41.25 to $61.25. Long Wharf Theater, 222 Sargent Drive. (203) 787-4282.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''The River Niger'' by Joseph A. Walker, directed by Malcolm K. Darrell. Thursday through April 7. $10 to $15. Yale Cabaret, 217 Park Street. (203) 432-1566.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Lulu'' by Frank Wedekind, directed by Mark Lamos. Through April 21. $22.50 to $55. Yale Repertory Theater, 1120 Chapel Street. (203) 432-1234.</p>
        <p>Oakville ''It Runs in the Family'' by Ray Cooney, directed by Harold J. Pantely. Through April 7. $16. Clockwork Repertory Theater, 133 Main Street. (860) 274-7247.</p>
        <p>Stamford ''Trying'' by Joanna McClelland Glass, directed by Steve Karp. Through April 1. $22 to $38. Stamford Theater Works, 200 Strawberry Hill Avenue. (203) 359-4414.</p>
        <p>Storrs ''North Shore Fish,'' by Israel Horovitz, presented by the Connecticut Repertory Theater. Through April 1. $15.50 to $26. Jorgensen Center for the Performing Arts, 2132 Hillside Road, University of Connecticut. (860) 486-4226.</p>
        <p>Waterbury ''Viagara Falls,'' comedy by Joao Machado and Lou Cutell, directed by Don Crichton. Through April 15. $27 to $45. Seven Angels Theater, Plank Road in Hamilton Park Pavilion. (203) 757-4676.</p>
        <p>Westport ''Born Yesterday'' by Garson Kanin, presented by the Westport Community Theater. Through April 15. $12 to $16. Westport Town Hall, 110 Myrtle Avenue. (203) 226-1983.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Beauty in Trouble,'' directed by Jan Hrebejk; in Czech with English subtitles. April 1 at 2 p.m. $3 to $8. ''Volver,'' directed by Pedro Almodóvar; in Spanish with English subtitles. Thursday and April 7 at 7:30 p.m.; April 8 at 2 p.m. $3 to $8. Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art, 600 Main Street. (860) 838-4058.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''The Skull,'' directed by Freddie Francis. April 7 at 2 p.m. Free. Yale Center for British Art, 1080 Chapel Street. (203) 432-2800.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>Hamden ''The Legacy of Eleanor Roosevelt,'' lecture by Anna Eleanor Roosevelt. Wednesday at 7 p.m. Free. Alumni Hall, Quinnipiac University. (203) 582-8425.</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Dish,'' discussion with various chefs about food, the restaurant business and dining out; moderated by Rand Richards Cooper, contributing editor of ''Bon Appétit.'' Monday at 7 p.m. Free. Real Art Ways, 56 Arbor Street. (860) 232-1006.</p>
        <p>Madison Giada De Laurentiis, author of the cookbook ''Everyday Italian.'' Tuesday at 1 p.m. Free with purchase of book. R. J. Julia Booksellers, 768 Boston Road. (203) 245-3959.</p>
        <p>New Haven Paul Mellon Lectures: ''The Rise of the Regional Museum in Victorian Britain, Parts I and II,'' lecture presented by Giles Waterfield, independent writer and curator. Tuesday and Wednesday at 4 p.m. ''Collecting for the People,'' lecture presented by Mr. Waterfield. Thursday at 5:30 p.m. Both free. Yale Center for British Art, 1080 Chapel Street. (203) 432-2800.</p>
        <p>Old Greenwich Patrick Carman, author of children's book ''Atherton: The House of Power.'' Tuesday at 3:30 p.m. Free. Arcadia Coffee Company, 20 Arcadia Road. (203) 637-8766.</p>
        <p>Stamford Big Read: Charles Shields, author of ''Mockingbird: A Portrait of Harper Lee.'' April 1 at 1 p.m. Free. Ferguson Library Main Branch, 1 Public Library Plaza. (203) 964-1000.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>Bridgeport ''Peter Rabbit,'' adapted from the book by Beatrix Potter. Through April 1. ''Beauty and the Beast.'' April 1 through May 20. Both: $13.50. Downtown Cabaret Theater, 263 Golden Hill Street. (203) 576-1636.</p>
        <p>Bridgeport ''Creativity Ignited!'' Interactive children's exhibition exploring the imagination. Through April 30. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. The Discovery Museum, 4450 Park Avenue. (203) 372-3521.</p>
        <p>Glastonbury ''Earthworms.'' Learn what worms eat and why they are important. Ages 3 to 5. Monday at 1 p.m. and Wednesday at 10 a.m. $13; members, $10; reservations required. The Connecticut Audubon Society Center at Glastonbury, 1361 Main Street. (860) 633-8402.</p>
        <p>Waterbury ''Great Expectations,'' adapted from the novel by Charles Dickens. Ages 12 to 18. Thursday at 9:30 and 11:30 a.m. $8. Palace Theater of Connecticut, 100 East Main Street. (203) 755-4700.</p>
        <p>Wilton ''Norwalk Symphony Family Program (Not) Just For Kids, Part 4.'' Play various brass instruments. Ages 3 to 10. April 7 at 2 p.m. Free; advance registration recommended. Wilton Library, 137 Old Ridgefield Road. (203) 762-3950.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>Brookfield ''Fiber Cartography: Mapping Imagination and Experience,'' works by 10 fiber artists. Through April 29. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Brookfield Craft Center, 286 Whisconier Road. (203) 775-4526.</p>
        <p>Greenwich ''Natural Elements,'' works by Bryan Nash Gill, Catherine Kernan and Eve Stockton. Through April 26. Hours: Mondays through Wednesdays and Fridays and Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Flinn Gallery, 101 West Putnam Avenue. (203) 622-7947.</p>
        <p>Guilford ''Exhibition of Miniatures,'' works by Tom Edwards, Gail Friedland and others. Through April 22. Guilford Art Center, 411 Church Street. (203) 453-5947.</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Soul Food: African American Cooking and Creativity,'' art and artifacts exploring Southern cooking and culture; presented by the Amistad Center for Art and Culture. Through April 22. ''Faith and Fortune: Five Centuries of European Masterworks,'' exhibition of European masterworks and sculpture from the museum's collection. Through Dec. 9. ''Picasso to Pop: Aspects of Modern Art,'' exhibition of the museum's holdings from many 20th-century genres. Through Nov. 18. $3 to $10; members and children 12 and under, free. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; first Thursdays of the month, 11 a.m. to 8 p.m. Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art, 600 Main Street. (860) 838-4058.</p>
        <p>Litchfield Works by Nancy Lasar and Amanda Branson. Through April 15. Hours: Thursdays through Mondays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. New Arts Gallery, 513 Maple Street. (860) 567-5015.</p>
        <p>Mashantucket ''Booming Out: Mohawk Ironworkers Build New York,'' photographs and sculpture documenting the Mohawk sky-walking construction tradition passed through six generations. Through May 27. $10 to $15; children under 6, free. Hours: Daily, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center, 110 Pequot Trail. (800) 411-9671.</p>
        <p>Middletown ''Etching Since 1950.'' Through April 8. ''A Newspaperman's Eye,'' American photographs from the collection of Russell G. D'Oench. Through May 27. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Davison Art Center, 301 High Street, Wesleyan University. (860) 685-2500.</p>
        <p>Middletown ''Brushwork by Kazuaki Tanahashi.'' Tuesday through May 6. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Mansfield Freeman Center for East Asian Studies Gallery, Wesleyan University, 343 Washington Terrace. (860) 685-2330.</p>
        <p>Milford ''Black and White,'' juried group exhibition. Through Thursday. Hours: Thursdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Firehouse Art Gallery, 81 Naugatuck. (203) 306-0016.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Random Access Memory,'' works dealing with memory by Liz Pagano and Colleen Tully. Through April 29. Free. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Arts + Literature Laboratory, 319 Peck Street. (203) 671-5175.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Women's Studies: New Works by Mary Lesser.'' Thursday through April 29. Reception: April 15, 3 to 6 p.m. Hours: Thursdays through Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. City Gallery, 994 State Street. (203) 782-2489.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Ceramic Abstraction: Exploration and Evidence,'' juried group exhibition. Through May 4. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Creative Arts Workshop, 80 Audubon Street. (203) 562-4927.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''New Haven's Garment Workers: An Elm City Story,'' photographs and artifacts documenting the 20th-century garment industry. Through May 4. Free. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to noon. Ethnic Heritage Center, 270 Fitch Street. (203) 392-6126.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Howard Hodgkin: Paintings 1992-2007.'' Through April 1. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Yale Center for British Art, 1080 Chapel Street. (203) 432-2800.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''UNStudio: Evolution of Space,'' exhibition of five projects by the Amsterdam-based firm. Through May 4. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Yale School of Architecture Gallery, 180 York Street. (203) 432-2889.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Jasper Johns: From Plate to Print.'' Through April 1. ''Making a Mark: Four Contemporary Artists in Print,'' prints by Enrique Chagoya, Carroll Dunham, Jane Hammond and Kiki Smith. Through April 1. ''Made for Love: Selections From the Jane Katcher Collection of Americana,'' 30 works of art that focus on the ways love and friendship are expressed through gift exchange. Through Aug. 26. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 6 p.m. Yale University Art Gallery. (203) 432-0600.</p>
        <p>New London ''Gas in Glass: The Light Sculptures of Mundy Hepburn.'' Through June 24. ''Expresiones/Expressions: Caribbean and Latin American Art From the Benjamin Ortiz Collection.'' Through June 24. $3 and $4; children 6 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Lyman Allyn Art Museum, 625 Williams Street. (860) 443-2545.</p>
        <p>New Milford ''Rural Wealth,'' photographs by Ray Kwiatkowski. Through May 5. Hours: Mondays, Thursdays and Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Tuesdays and Wednesdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 1 p.m. New Milford Public Library, 24 Main Street. (860) 355-1191.</p>
        <p>Old Lyme ''Shadows and Pulls: A Short History,'' photographs by Ellen Carey. April 1 through May 5. Reception: April 1, noon to 4 p.m. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Diane Birdsall Gallery, 68 Lyme Street. (860) 434-3209.</p>
        <p>Old Lyme ''The Freedom Business: Connecticut Landscapes Through the Eyes of Venture Smith,'' poems by Marilyn Nelson paired with paintings from the museum's collection. Through June 24. ''A Circle of Friends: The Artists of the Florence Griswold Museum.'' Through July 1. $4 to $8; under 6, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Florence Griswold Museum, 96 Lyme Street. (860) 434-5542.</p>
        <p>Ridgefield ''The Photograph as Canvas,'' works by artists who draw or paint on photographs. Through June 10. ''Tekrar,'' sound installation by David Abir. Through Aug. 12. ''W(E)AVE,'' sound and textile collaboration between Elana Herzog and Michael Schumacher. Through Aug. 12. ''Blow Ups: Spores, Pollen and Pollutants,'' works by Kysa Johnson. Through June 10. ''Castles, Dwarfs and Happychaps,'' work by Arturo Herrera created using the Renaissance technique of pouncing. Through Sept. 2. ''Chrysanthemum Anthems,'' sculpture by Dario Robleto based on American soldiers' experience of wars. Through June 17. $7; seniors and students, $4; members, K-12 teachers and children under 18, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Aldrich Contemporary Art Museum, 258 Main Street. (203) 438-4519.</p>
        <p>Stamford ''Great Dames Part Trois,'' works by female artists. Through April 10. Hours: Fridays and Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Loft Artist Gallery at Yale and Towne, 737 Canal Street. (203) 323-4153.</p>
        <p>Storrs ''Salvage Research Soul Training,'' installation by Nari Ward. Through April 13. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. Contemporary Art Galleries, 830 Bolton Road, University of Connecticut, Storrs Campus. (860) 486-1511.</p>
        <p>Storrs ''Intemperate Times: Kathe Kollwitz, 1918-1934.'' Through May 6. ''Tradition and Innovation: Latin American Art From the Benton Collection.'' Through June 17. ''Old Master Drawings and Prints,'' exhibition of 15 Italian and Dutch works dating from 1539 to 1690. Through May 6. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 4:30 p.m. William Benton Museum of Art, 245 Glenbrook Road. (860) 486-4520.</p>
        <p>Waterbury ''From Colonial Village to Country Retreat,'' exhibition exploring the architectural history of Middlebury. Through April 7. $4; children under 16, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Mattatuck Museum Arts and History Center, 144 West Main Street. (203) 753-0381.</p>
        <p>West Hartford Works by Paul Bowen and Pat de Groot. Through May 5. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Brick Walk Fine Art, 322 Park Road. (860) 233-1730.</p>
        <p>Westport Oil paintings by Yetvart Kaprielian. Through April 27. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Galerie Je Reviens, 991 Post Road East. (203) 227-7716.</p>
        <p>Westport ''States of Connecticut,'' juried exhibition with works by various artists. Through April 29. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Westport Arts Center, 51 Riverside Avenue. (203) 222-7070.</p>
        <p>Westport ''Art and the Good Earth: As Seen Through the Painter's Eye,'' works by 14 artists. Through May 11. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Westport Historical Society, 25 Avery Place. (203) 224-1424.</p>
        <p>Woodbury ''Pattern Play,'' paintings by Anne Hebebrand and sculpture by Diana Chamberlain. Through May 13. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Fenn Gallery, 345 Main Street South. (203) 263-3449.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
