<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beyond the Yankees and the Zoo</title>
    <meta content="01weekend" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/travel/01weekend.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837104"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEEKEND IN NEW YORK | THE BRONX"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bronx (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kugel, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Bronx (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E0D91230F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1103" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beyond the Yankees and the Zoo</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Beyond the Yankees and the Zoo</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH KUGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kugel, Seth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Seth Kugel Weekend in New York column on visit to the Bronx; list; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ARE you the kind of avant-garde tourist who lives to be the first outsider to find that charming little shop or try that new gem of a neighborhood bistro? If so, forget Manhattan. Unless you stumble across a place as the sign is going up, Google will show you that dozens of critics, bloggers and old-fashioned pundits have beaten you to it. That's the way things work on this overdocumented island.</p>
        <p>And that's a great reason to visit the Bronx, which by itself would be the seventh most populous city (1.4 million) in the United States, but is virtual terra incognita for tourists.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bronx, which by itself would be the seventh most populous city (1.4 million) in the United States, is virtual terra incognita for tourists.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ARE you the kind of avant-garde tourist who lives to be the first outsider to find that charming little shop or try that new gem of a neighborhood bistro? If so, forget Manhattan. Unless you stumble across a place as the sign is going up, Google will show you that dozens of critics, bloggers and old-fashioned pundits have beaten you to it. That's the way things work on this overdocumented island.</p>
        <p>And that's a great reason to visit the Bronx, which by itself would be the seventh most populous city (1.4 million) in the United States, but is virtual terra incognita for tourists.</p>
        <p>The Bronx accounts for about 7 pages of 472 in Lonely Planet's latest New York City guide and a whopping 1.2 percent of restaurants in the 2007 Zagat survey. Its citations on the food-obsessive Web site Chowhound.com are dwarfed by postings about spots in Brooklyn and Queens.</p>
        <p>Because of the media snubs, there are surprises at every turn in the Bronx: An exotic bird store near an antiques district near 19th-century brownstones near hole-in-the-wall Mexican restaurants. Or an African DVD shop where advice on Nigerian movie classics is free with directions to the best Ghanaian peanut soup and fufu in the neighborhood. Or a new espresso haven on Arthur Avenue.</p>
        <p>But isn't the Bronx dangerous?</p>
        <p>If you think so, stick your iceberg lettuce and Wonder Bread in the fridge and join the rest of us in 2007 to celebrate a few anniversaries. It was 30 years ago that Howard Cosell made his ''the Bronx is burning'' remark during the World Series at Yankee Stadium; and it was 20 years ago that ''Bonfire of the Vanities'' by Tom Wolfe painted a bleak picture of the South Bronx. A lot has changed.</p>
        <p>But isn't the Bronx too hard to get to?</p>
        <p>Starting today and every Saturday and Sunday through the spring and summer, you can take the free Bronx Trolley bus from the corner of Seventh Avenue and 53rd Street at 9:30 a.m. There are hop-on, hop-off stops at the Bronx Zoo, the New York Botanical Garden and Arthur Avenue in Little Italy. Otherwise, the subway and Metro-North make it easy to get there.</p>
        <p>The best way to explore the Bronx is to head to one of its well-known attractions, take it in, and then explore the neighborhoods that surround it.</p>
        <p>You can, for example, build a great day around a baseball game at Yankee Stadium. For a satisfying après-game stroll, go a few blocks up the Grand Concourse, with its Art Deco buildings, to the Bronx Museum of the Arts, which last year temporarily opened its sleek, expensive expansion by the firm Arquitectonica.</p>
        <p>The museum has been closed this year for final work but reopens today with an exhibition of video and more traditional art, ''Here and Elsewhere,'' featuring 36 artists from the New York region.</p>
        <p>Then explore one of the Bronx's flourishing West African neighborhoods, which happens to take up the blocks behind the museum.</p>
        <p>Although few people might have known about the Bronx's African immigrants before a fire killed 10 members of two Malian families last month, they have been here for years.</p>
        <p>You can check out the African Movie Mart and chat with the staff. At the tidy Papa Ye restaurant a few blocks down, you'll find an informal place (no menus) where you can order huge meals like peanut soup with goat and the porridge-like fufu for $8. Ghana is an English-speaking nation, so just ask what's for lunch.</p>
        <p>If you're taking the trolley, the day is almost designed for you. After a visit to the zoo or the garden, check out the Little Italy neighborhood around Arthur Avenue, where you can still unearth something new. Palombo Pastry Shop, which serves cannoli, pignoli, great espresso and much more, opened only seven months ago.</p>
        <p>And unless you despise delicious food for not much money, don't forget to stop off for 100 freshly made meat-and-spinach ravioli at Borgatti's Ravioli and Egg Noodles. The place has been around for a while, but at these prices ($11 per hundred), who needs discoveries?</p>
        <p>In the far southern Bronx, antiques lovers can build a jaunt around the shops on Alexander Avenue near Bruckner Boulevard and Alexander Avenue. While there, look for signs of the growing but still somewhat hidden artists' colony in the area, especially anyone coming out of the old Estey Piano Factory, which became a city landmark last year and is now a home to artists' lofts.</p>
        <p>There's nary a cafe in sight, though (perhaps meaning that the artists are not wasting their time sipping and gossiping), but there are burgers and salads served with darn good fries and local chatter at Bruckner Bar and Grill.</p>
        <p>You may also stop by 33rd and Bird, the bird shop that used to be on guess-what-street in Manhattan, but flew the high-rent coop last year. Or maybe you'll walk toward the Mott Haven Historic District a few blocks up Alexander Avenue, making a pit stop at one of 138th Street's Mexican restaurants before you check out the 19th-century row houses that are part of what used to be called Irish Fifth Avenue.</p>
        <p>Or, even better, just find your own Bronx treasures.</p>
        <p>(Coming next month: The Bronx by night.)</p>
        <p>A SURPRISE AT EVERY TURN</p>
        <p>The Bronx Trolley leaves from NYC &amp; Company at the corner of Seventh Avenue and 53rd Street in Midtown Saturday and Sunday starting today at 9:30 a.m., and leaves the Bronx at 5:30 p.m.; www.bronxtrolley.com.</p>
        <p>Bronx Zoo, 2300 Southern Boulevard, (718) 220-5100; www.bronxzoo.org. Take the No. 2 or No. 5 train to East Tremont Avenue/West Farms Square.</p>
        <p>New York Botanical Garden, Bronx River Parkway and Fordham Road, (718) 817-8700; www.nybg.org. Take Metro-North from Grand Central to the Botanical Garden stop.</p>
        <p>Yankee Stadium, 161st Street and River Avenue. Take the No. 4, B or D trains to 161st Street. (To go straight to the Bronx Museum, take the B or the D to 167th Street.) Baseball tickets at www.yankees.com.</p>
        <p>Antiques District: Take the No. 6 train to Third Avenue/138th Street.</p>
        <p>Palombo Pastry Shop, 2400 Arthur Avenue (East 187th Street), (718) 329-8800.</p>
        <p>Borgatti's Ravioli and Egg Noodles, 632 East 187th Street, (718) 367-3799.</p>
        <p>Bronx Museum of the Arts, 1040 Grand Concourse (East 165th Street), (718) 681-6000; www.bronxmuseum.org. ''Here and Elsewhere'' runs until Aug. 19.</p>
        <p>African Movie Mall, 179A East 165th Street (Grand Concourse and Sheridan Avenue), (718) 503-5040.</p>
        <p>Papa Ye Restaurant, 196 McClelland Street (Sheridan Avenue between 166th and 167th Streets), (718) 681-3240.</p>
        <p>Bruckner Bar &amp; Grill, 1 Bruckner Boulevard (almost under the Third Avenue Bridge), (718) 665-2100.</p>
        <p>WEEKEND IN NEW YORK | THE BRONX</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
