<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Once the Butcher for the World, Now a Quarter-Acre Lot</title>
    <meta content="01land" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/us/01land.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837397"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THIS LAND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Easter and Holy Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Passover</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chicago (Ill)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chiappetti Lamb and Veal Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barry, Dan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Columns/This Land</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois/Chicago</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Easter and Holy Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Passover</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Passover</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Easter and Holy Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Chicago (Ill)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0DE1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="962" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Once the Butcher for the World, Now a Quarter-Acre Lot</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Once the Butcher for the World, Now a Quarter-Acre Lot</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN BARRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barry, Dan</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dan Barry This Land column visits Chiapetti Lamb and Veal Co slaughterhouse in Chicago on edge of former Union Stock Yards; says family-run business will slaughter more than 7,000 lambs for Passover and Easter; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The time has come for that symbol of redemption, the lamb. And when the lamb's time has come, it might as well be here, on the South Side, in one of the last of the city's classic slaughterhouses.</p>
        <p>A few dozen yards from where new brick houses preen on old packinghouse property, hundreds of lambs nuzzle and nudge in a livestock pen as neat as a livestock pen can be. Their echoing bleats sound like puzzled responses to something unpleasant just realized:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At one of the last of Chicago’s classic slaughterhouses, Passover and Easter mean the lambs’ days are numbered.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The time has come for that symbol of redemption, the lamb. And when the lamb's time has come, it might as well be here, on the South Side, in one of the last of the city's classic slaughterhouses.</p>
        <p>A few dozen yards from where new brick houses preen on old packinghouse property, hundreds of lambs nuzzle and nudge in a livestock pen as neat as a livestock pen can be. Their echoing bleats sound like puzzled responses to something unpleasant just realized:</p>
        <p>Wha-a-a-a-t?</p>
        <p>Little lamb, I'll tell thee. It is nearly Passover; Jews use your shank to symbolize deliverance from ancient Egyptian oppressors. It is nearly Easter; Christians use your meat to commemorate the death and resurrection of Jesus. Little lamb, we slaughter thee.</p>
        <p>Soon a truck with aerated sides backs up to the pen, owned by the Chiappetti Lamb and Veal Company. Two men in white lab coats coax about 70 of the lambs into the truck's hold, the march of hooves upon the metal ramp sounding like pounding rain. Lambs who dodge this ferry have just bought themselves an hour.</p>
        <p>A rolling remnant of the city's stockyard days, the animal-laden truck makes three rights and lumbers onto South Halsted Street, passing near the developed land where the stockyards once sprawled. Two left turns and it is at the back of a brick building unremarkable but for being the Chiappetti slaughterhouse, and a link to what was.</p>
        <p>Some 60 years ago, a butcher named Fiore Chiappetti bought the building to accommodate his expanding trade. It sat on the lip of the storied Union Stock Yards, where millions of cattle, sheep and hogs came in by rail on hooves, and left by rail on hooks. This massive, squirming operation, breathtaking in so many ways, had helped to make Chicago.</p>
        <p>By then, the stockyard was already in ''a long and slow decline,'' says Dominic Pacyga, an urban historian at Columbia College in Chicago. And by the early 1970s it was gone, in part because refrigerated trucks and interstate highways had transformed the business of meat.</p>
        <p>Now it is so distant in memory that to invoke Carl Sandburg's familiar description of Chicago as ''Hog Butcher for the World'' is akin to calling New York a seaport.</p>
        <p>Through it all, the Chiappettis killed lamb, processed lamb, sold lamb. After Fiore came his son Mike, born with only partial use of his right arm, not that you'd notice, with the way he could wield a knife and carry a carcass on his back. He left school after the eighth grade to work, and he never stopped, not even when he needed an oxygen tank to breathe.</p>
        <p>Two of his sons, Dennis and Bryan, followed his path, driving trucks, washing away the blood on the kill floor; now they are co-owners. Back in July 1971, with the stockyard about to close, Dennis grabbed a movie camera and climbed onto the hood of an Oldsmobile 442. While his friend drove the car slowly through the yards, he filmed for posterity the downed signs, the deserted pens.</p>
        <p>''We were basically the last ones there,'' he says of his family's business.</p>
        <p>Several Chiappettis work in the business now, including Franco, 31, son of Dennis. While attending Carl Sandburg High School in Orland Park, a suburb to the southwest, he read the poet's words and felt the pull of the past. He got his start by chauffeuring his grandfather Mike around, and listening to stockyard stories featuring tough men who worked and lived hard.</p>
        <p>Franco Chiappetti considers the lamb-filled pen, a few yards from where he sits, a living part of the city's past. ''We have a very small quarter-acre of it,'' he says. ''But you won't find it anywhere else.''</p>
        <p>Things have changed. Many of the company's 130 workers are Mexican immigrants. Imports from New Zealand and Australia have tightened the market. Buyers want their loin chops vacuum packed. Old South Side packinghouses come down, and half-million-dollar houses go up. The Chiappettis look around and barely recognize the place.</p>
        <p>Maybe someday they will move out of their two buildings, if they can find a place in Chicago where they can consolidate their operation. At the moment, though, it is nearly Passover, nearly Easter, and they have more than 7,000 lambs to slaughter this week.</p>
        <p>Some of the lambs just trucked in stand in a small holding pen at the edge of the kill floor, a cold and bright place redolent of fresh meat. During what is called their ''waiting time,'' they have water to drink and an overhead fan to cool them, because ''humane handling is a must,'' says Roberto Bellavia, the company's quality assurance manager.</p>
        <p>One by one the lambs are lifted, turned upside down and attached by a back leg to an overhead rail that runs along an assembly line. The work to follow, no matter how technologically advanced, hinges still on a single motion with a knife by an employee, rabbinically supervised if the lamb is to be kosher. Slit, and done. The back wall is a Pollock-like study in scarlet.</p>
        <p>When the lamb stops quivering, it is pushed down the rail to be presented before people in white smocks, one after another, each one with a specific duty in the process, from head skinner to hide puller. Nearly everything is used: the intestines become casings, the hides become upholstery.</p>
        <p>At the end of the line, the swinging carcass, all red and white, looks nothing like the woolly creature it had been just moments ago. Before it is swung into the cooler, before it is quartered and converted into roasts and chops, another man in white sprays it with a citric-acid solution to reduce bacteria. Smiling, he says in Spanish, ''I am baptizing them.''</p>
        <p>THIS LAND</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
