<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Security Systems: Your Eyes and Ears</title>
    <meta content="01HOME" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/realestate/01HOME.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837244"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="YOUR HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romano, Jay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Your Home</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E3D81030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="592" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Security Systems: Your Eyes and Ears</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Security Systems: Your Eyes and Ears</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAY ROMANO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romano, Jay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Your Home column on professionally monitored home security systems; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MOST people have smoke alarms, many have carbon-monoxide detectors, and a good number even have devices that detect flooding or unexpected changes in temperature. But all of these alarms are useful only if someone is there to hear them.</p>
        <p>''The untold story of professionally monitored security systems is that people are using them for a variety of reasons beyond burglar protection,'' said Ann Lindstrom, a spokeswoman for ADT Security Services in Boca Raton, Fla. ''We are the eyes and ears for people when they can't be home.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Home monitoring systems are useful only if someone is there to hear them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MOST people have smoke alarms, many have carbon-monoxide detectors, and a good number even have devices that detect flooding or unexpected changes in temperature. But all of these alarms are useful only if someone is there to hear them.</p>
        <p>''The untold story of professionally monitored security systems is that people are using them for a variety of reasons beyond burglar protection,'' said Ann Lindstrom, a spokeswoman for ADT Security Services in Boca Raton, Fla. ''We are the eyes and ears for people when they can't be home.''</p>
        <p>Better systems are monitored around the clock by companies like ADT. When a customer's alarm system is triggered, Ms. Lindstrom said, the company will first call the house -- or any other numbers provided by the homeowner -- to make sure the alarm wasn't set off by accident. If there is no answer, or if the owner answers but is away from home, the company will call the police or fire department.</p>
        <p>The basic home security setup, Ms. Lindstrom said, includes sensors on the doors and windows that are connected to a main panel, where a keypad is used to arm or disarm the system. A more sophisticated system might include motion detectors and sensors that can detect glass being broken. Or it can monitor for fire, carbon monoxide, unexpected temperature changes, power failures and flooding and can even provide for video monitoring.</p>
        <p>Jill Steele, the director of marketing for Monitronics, a nationwide security monitoring company based in Dallas, says that a security system can be connected to the monitoring station either over the phone line or by a cellular connection. (Since a savvy crook might know enough to cut the phone lines, a cellular connection between the house and the monitoring station eliminates that weak link.)</p>
        <p>Ms. Steele said that while some parts of a security system are armed and disarmed by the resident, some are monitored by the company around the clock. Smoke detectors, carbon-monoxide detectors, flood and temperature alarms, for example, are monitored whether or not the homeowner has activated the system.</p>
        <p>Bruce Mungiguerra, the director of consumer sales for Monitronics, said that a basic home security system, with three door or window sensors, a motion sensor and an alarm panel, would cost about $100 installed. Adding a smoke detector, temperature sensor or other monitoring device would cost about $100 each. Monthly monitoring ranges from $29 to $39, depending on what equipment is installed.</p>
        <p>Ralph Winn, the vice president of the Home Security Store in Riverside, Calif., says his company caters to the do-it-yourself market.</p>
        <p>''The most popular systems we sell are wireless systems because of the ease of installation,'' he said. ''With wireless systems, there is no drilling holes or running wires.''</p>
        <p>The wireless detectors and the main alarm panel have a battery backup so that they will function even when the electricity is off. ''Most have a 24-hour backup battery,'' he said. ''And two hours before the battery dies, the system will call you and tell you it's running out of power.'' (He noted that many insurance companies will discount their premiums if the house has a properly installed and professionally monitored security system.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Winn said that while some security companies will provide services only to homes in which they have installed the detectors, there are others that will monitor self-installed systems. AlarmRelay, a San Diego security monitoring company, is one of them. It will provide monitoring services for $107.45 prepaid for the year (which comes to $8.95 a month), and it also offers technical support for homeowners.</p>
        <p>YOUR HOME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
