<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Day Care and a Child's Behavior</title>
    <meta content="l01daycare" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837342"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Day Care Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E2D81130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="843" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Day Care and a Child's Behavior</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Study Finds Rise in Behavior Problems After Significant Time in Day Care'' (news article, March 26):</p>
        <p>American day care is suffering, and it shouldn't take a $200 million study to see that.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Study Finds Rise in Behavior Problems After Significant Time in Day Care'' (news article, March 26):</p>
        <p>American day care is suffering, and it shouldn't take a $200 million study to see that.</p>
        <p>The argument between the pro-day-care and anti-day-care camps goes on fruitlessly while, like it or not, more and more children are being raised outside the home. We need a new dialogue, one that addresses the problem's roots rather than pontificating on its effects.</p>
        <p>We live in a country in which most women work outside the home and are also responsible for child rearing; ours is also one of the only developed countries with no national policy on maternity leave. It is no surprise, then, that we have no coherent philosophy for day care.</p>
        <p>As money is poured into studies, American day care continues to morph into an increasingly unstable structure, one with no real foundation or plan.</p>
        <p>Day care ought to be a nurturing and learning environment for children, one that simultaneously resembles an extended family, a neighborhood and a nursery school. In partnership with parents, day care providers are raising this next generation.</p>
        <p>Peggy J. Sradnick  John Okrent  New York, March 29, 2007</p>
        <p>The writers are director and a staff member at Basic Trust Day Care.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>If the upshot of the article was to increase emphasis on both quality of day care (including a teacher pay level to show we actually do care about our future generation) and, ideally, the kind of guidance in parenting needed in proportion to the stressfulness of the parents' lives, then fine.</p>
        <p>But as to the study's implied cause-and-effect: why isn't it likely that the kids who begin day care early and spend the most years in it are also those whose parents are the most stressed in their work lives and who continue to be the most stressed, up to and beyond their children's sixth-grade years?</p>
        <p>Then the real causal factor might not be number of years in day care but the stress levels (and untutored stressed-out-parenting skills) in the home. Johnny or Juan may get little quality or quantity time with parents, which can feed restless, disruptive behavior-- at least as much as the alleged day care peer group.</p>
        <p>Carolyn Taylor  Los Angeles, March 26, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As the article pointed out, the researchers who did the day care study ''could not randomly assign children to one kind of care or another; parents chose the kind of care that suited them.'' Because there was no control group, ''determining cause and effect was not possible.'' Yet the word ''effect'' was used in reporting the outcome.</p>
        <p>In fact, there is no good evidence of any ''effect.'' Parents not only chose the kind of care that suited them, they also chose the kind that suited their child. Parents are less likely to leave their child in a busy, noisy day care center if the child happens to be timid and quiet.</p>
        <p>The underrepresentation of such children in the day care center population means that this population is biased slightly toward children with a bold, outgoing temperament. This bias alone can account for the small day care ''effect'' reported by the researchers.</p>
        <p>Judith Rich Harris  Middleton, N.J., March 26, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is the author of two books about children's development.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Just what does it mean that more time in day care equates with poor behavior in public school?</p>
        <p>There's a huge difference between the two, and it's no accident that the activities encouraged of preschoolers will result in criticism when they reach school age.</p>
        <p>Often, children who have spent time in a friendly child-centered environment are slow to make the transition to the standardized public school classroom. It's not surprising that kids who are used to an open play space are unable to sit still in a classroom of 28 or 30 children, or that such kids are labeled disruptive.</p>
        <p>The answer is higher salaries and better training for teachers in day care and in public schools. The answer is not less day care -- it's smaller classrooms in public schools.</p>
        <p>Nancy M. Lederman  New York, March 27, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Perhaps parents of disruptive children are more likely to enroll their children in day care.</p>
        <p>It might be difficult for an elderly relative to care for high-energy children or children with behavioral issues.</p>
        <p>It might be harder for a parent to get anything done at home while caring for these children.</p>
        <p>Katharine London  Cambridge, Mass., March 27, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The discovery that time in day care leads children to be more disruptive in class should really lead to a follow-up question: What does disruptiveness in the first through fifth grades lead to in the future? Do disruptive kids make less productive and unsuccessful adults?</p>
        <p>Or are disruptive young children perhaps destined to become assertive and entrepreneurial members of society?</p>
        <p>Joshua Kulp  Modiin, Israel, March 27, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
