<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Five Centuries of Printmaking Packed Into One Museum</title>
    <meta content="01LIArtsLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/01LIArts.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837161"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nassau County Museum of Art</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Genocchio, Benjamin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Nassau County Museum of Art</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06EED61330F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="801" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Five Centuries of Printmaking Packed Into One Museum</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Five Centuries of Printmaking Packed Into One Museum</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BENJAMIN GENOCCHIO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genocchio, Benjamin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Benjamin Genocchio reviews exhibition of prints at Nassau County Museum of Art; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The beauty of printmaking is celebrated in ''Rembrandt to Rosenquist: Masters of Printmaking,'' the Nassau County Museum of Art's enormous spring show. Sweeping in scope, with an all-star cast, it fills the museum's first- and second-floor galleries with 150 examples of the medium. There is so much here that you will even find a Warhol silk-screen print of Mao Zedong tucked away in a corridor instead of in one of the main galleries.</p>
        <p>Among the show's many pleasures are examples of the work of the masters of European printmaking: Rembrandt, Goya and Dürer. This is to be applauded. But as with most exhibitions here, it also a bit of a mess; the selection is a hodgepodge, and an excessively broad one, ranging over five centuries. The curator, Franklin Hill Perrell, would have been wise to have narrowed his focus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the Nassau County Museum of Art, an exhibit offers a chronological overview of the practitioners and methods of the print.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The beauty of printmaking is celebrated in ''Rembrandt to Rosenquist: Masters of Printmaking,'' the Nassau County Museum of Art's enormous spring show. Sweeping in scope, with an all-star cast, it fills the museum's first- and second-floor galleries with 150 examples of the medium. There is so much here that you will even find a Warhol silk-screen print of Mao Zedong tucked away in a corridor instead of in one of the main galleries.</p>
        <p>Among the show's many pleasures are examples of the work of the masters of European printmaking: Rembrandt, Goya and Dürer. This is to be applauded. But as with most exhibitions here, it also a bit of a mess; the selection is a hodgepodge, and an excessively broad one, ranging over five centuries. The curator, Franklin Hill Perrell, would have been wise to have narrowed his focus.</p>
        <p>The show is displayed chronologically, but backward, beginning upstairs and then continuing downstairs toward the entrance. This is very confusing for visitors, though understandable. The museum's historic mansion is a charming setting for art, but its mix of different-size galleries presents difficulties for curators. Mr. Perrell has tried to install the prints where they look best, with sensitivity to their fragile condition; too much light damages prints, so the more valuable historic pieces need to be in darkened rooms.</p>
        <p>Somehow, none of this seems to matter, for this is among the liveliest and most pleasurable shows at the museum in recent memory. Color is everywhere, for starters, and a lovely, substantial presence of first-rate artwork keeps you thoroughly engaged. That is especially true of the downstairs sections devoted to postwar American prints.</p>
        <p>Few contemporary artists have explored the print medium with as much tenacity as Jim Dine, whose ''Viennese Hearts'' (1987-1990) kicks off the show. It is a messy, hand-colored screen print of a huge ruby-colored heart, wrinkled, past its prime and darkening with age. The rough-and-tumble expressionism of the artist's style avoids sentimentality, though the piece evokes empathy.</p>
        <p>Until recently, most prints were small, largely because of the limits of printing technology. But as the technology advanced, artists began to toy with scale and materials, often to exhilarating effect. The next downstairs room contains works by Robert Rauschenberg, among them signature prints from the 1970s, in which he printed on fabric, Plexiglas, mirrors and other materials. These are among the more innovative examples of modern printmaking.</p>
        <p>Rarities include a selection of seldom-seen prints by Jasper Johns, on loan from Barbara Bertozzi Castelli, the Italian art critic and wife of the late New York art dealer Leo Castelli. Oddities also abound, among them a selection of black-and-white screen prints of several of Jackson Pollock's paintings, printed posthumously in 1964, which I suspect the artist never would have countenanced were he alive at the time. Flat, boring and lifeless, they lack any sense of the dynamism and playfulness of the paintings.</p>
        <p>Printmaking, among the world's oldest art-making traditions, encompasses a great variety of processes and techniques. They can be divided roughly into four categories: relief methods, like woodcuts and linocuts; intaglio methods, like engraving, etching and drypoint; surface processes, chiefly lithography; and stencil methods, including silk-screens and serigraphs, which were popular with Pop artists like Warhol.</p>
        <p>Prints made using each of these graphic processes are represented in the exhibition. All have unique qualities by which they can be identified. A woodcut like Emil Nolde's ''Kerzentanzerinnen'' (1917) contains large blocky shapes and a stark contrast between the black printed areas and the white of the paper; in contrast, Rembrandt's etching and drypoint ''The Triumph of Mordecai'' (circa 1641) illustrates the subtlety of tone and fine line detail characteristic of this medium.</p>
        <p>''The Triumph of Mordecai'' is a masterpiece of printmaking for several reasons -- the complexity of the design, for one, a group scene with dozens of interlocking figures and animals. Then there is the casual-looking play of light and shadow, creating astonishingly subtle contrasts of tone. Finally there is the combination of various graphic methods (etching and drypoint) in a single print, a difficult though not uncommon practice suggesting that it is inappropriate to think of the graphic arts as separate processes.</p>
        <p>Other exhibits in the upstairs rooms include a delightful color lithograph of a young girl with a dog on a street by Pierre Bonnard, several exotic woodcuts by Paul Gauguin and a wide range of prints by Picasso. You'd have to hang around in these galleries for almost a day to see all the prints properly, which suggests that the exhibition is a bit too large. But it seems churlish to complain about a surfeit of quality. This show is gorgeous to look at.</p>
        <p>''Rembrandt to Rosenquist: Masters of Printmaking,'' Nassau County Museum of Art, 1 Museum Drive, Roslyn Harbor, through May 13. Information: (516) 484-9337 or www.nassaumuseum.com.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
