<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gentlemen of the Road: Chapter 10: On the Belated Repayment of the Gift of a Pear</title>
    <meta content="01funny--serial.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/magazine/01funnyserial.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837039"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE FUNNY PAGES: III: SUNDAY SERIAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chabon, Michael</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Gentlemen of the Road (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Chabon, Michael</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E5DA1230F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2667" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gentlemen of the Road: Chapter 10: On the Belated Repayment of the Gift of a Pear</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Gentlemen of the Road</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michael Chabon</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chabon, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chapter 10 of Michael Chabon's novel Gentlemen of the Road; drawing (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Zelikman has crossed paths with a group of Radanites who were able to give him news of his family in Regensburg, including his estranged and dying father. In an effort to reconcile the two, they invite Zelikman to accompany them home. He accepts their offer but disappears in the night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This week, Zelikman has crossed paths with a group of Radanites who were able to give him news of his family in Regensburg, including his estranged and dying father.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Zelikman has crossed paths with a group of Radanites who were able to give him news of his family in Regensburg, including his estranged and dying father. In an effort to reconcile the two, they invite Zelikman to accompany them home. He accepts their offer but disappears in the night.</p>
        <p>''I can only save them one at a time,'' Zelikman said.</p>
        <p>He sat cross-legged on a carpet that smelled like rutting sheep, in the cramped gloom of a circular dog tent constructed, as far as he could tell, from equal quantities of rancid felt, dung smoke and the acrid shadow cast by a naphtha lamp. He was working to get Amram to take him and his proposal seriously, a task impeded by the fact that he was still wearing the robes and head wrap with which the Radanites had generously if unwittingly supplied him, his patchy golden beard tied in trivial plaits and blackened with lamp soot.</p>
        <p>''I am not overly encumbered by principle, as you know,'' Zelikman continued. ''I am a gentleman of the road, an apostate from the faith of my fathers, a renegade, a brigand, a hired blade, a thief, but on this one small principle of economy, damn you, and damn that troublemaking little stripling, and damn every one of those men out there, living men, in full possession, for the most part, of all their limbs and humors, I have to hold firm: if we can only save them one at a time, then by God we must only kill them one at a time.''</p>
        <p>''I didn't get a word of that,'' Filaq said. Having declined to sit with the reunited partners, he leaned against the roof pole nearest the low door flap, hugging himself in the way of a youth trying to keep his temper, glowering at Zelikman from under his ruddy eyebrows. ''But if what this barber proposes is that, having mustered these men and promised them redress of their grievance and a fine fight, we now sneak into the city like cutpurses and strangle Buljan in his sleep with a silk girdle. ... ''</p>
        <p>''A scarf will do as well,'' Zelikman said.</p>
        <p>'' ... and send those good men home with a handclasp and our thanks for their trouble, then I suggest he wriggle on back to whatever reeking Western sump exuded him and leave us to settle this matter in the Khazar way. Openly. By fire and steel. And soon, Amram, today, now, before the main body of the army can return from the Crimea and surround us.''</p>
        <p>''We sent our demand for his surrender not two hours ago, boy!'' Amram said. Six lancers of the 15th Arsiyah, the best-attired, finest-armored troops in the Brotherhood, had been admitted under flag of truce into the city, bearing testimonials of the humble obeisance of the Little Elephant, Filaq, eternally loyal servant of the kagan in whose name all truces were held to be sanctified, and lenient terms of surrender to Buljan, who would be permitted to keep not only his household goods, camels and tents but -- over the objections of Filaq -- the eyes and tongue in his head.</p>
        <p>''And in any case, your 'good men' have no grievance with Buljan,'' Zelikman said, fighting the urge to make a trial of his skill at strangulation, by scarf or bare fingers, right there. ''Their quarrel is with the Rus. And the sooner and the easier you make yourself bek, and act to revoke the safe passage that Buljan granted to the Northmen, the sooner your men will be free to seek the redress they do want, and the more of them will live to get it. You are the one who has a grievance with Buljan, you arrogant little bastard.''</p>
        <p>''Not even in power yet and already thinking like a despot,'' Amram observed with a rueful smile, studying his shatranj board. ''Confusing your will with the will of the men you lord it over.'' Without looking up from the board he grabbed at the youth's left ankle and gave it a yank, sending Filaq tumbling onto the carpet. ''I swear, you are starting to worry me.''</p>
        <p>''And you are starting to worry me,'' Filaq said, scrambling to his feet, his cheeks and throat radiant with blood. ''You seem to have forgotten the purpose of that impressive ax you carry about so picturesquely. I thought you were a soldier. But I see that you are just a craven barber like your friend.''</p>
        <p>''I am a soldier,'' Amram said, looking up, no longer smiling.</p>
        <p>''Are you? Then fight like one. We should have attacked as soon as we arrived.''</p>
        <p>''The men were tired. It was dark. The city is well defended and prepared.''</p>
        <p>''Is that how they do it in the armies of Byzantium? Offer excuses in advance of the defeat, to save time later?''</p>
        <p>Zelikman was obliged to acknowledge that Filaq had a true gift for commanding soldiers, because Zelikman knew what the stripling had intuited, namely that Amram was vulnerable to a well-timed display of taunting. The African had served too long as a pit mastiff in the dogfights of empire not to respond to an artful application of the handler's goad, even when it was wielded by a beardless youth who could have no clear notion of the hard and harrowing work that soldiering entailed. Filaq stood there with his lip curled, his pretty eyes glinting with scorn, his soft, narrow fingers playing on the hilt of his untried sword, looking as certain of victory as only a green recruit would dare.</p>
        <p>''Let your spies within the walls do their work,'' Amram said. ''After you have news --''</p>
        <p>On hands and knees an Arsiyah trooper crawled in through the door flap, in a clatter of armor. He pressed his forehead to the blood-blue figured carpet and waited for Filaq to give him leave to speak.</p>
        <p>''Has he responded?'' Filaq said.</p>
        <p>''It is -- we were told that Buljan would be sending out an emissary, Bek, an old friend of yours -- but they have sent an elephant.''</p>
        <p>''An elephant?'' Filaq whispered.</p>
        <p>''A very old one. Thin and old and slow.''</p>
        <p>Filaq stood unmoving, shaking his head.</p>
        <p>''It has a spotted patch on its forehead, Bek. Hairless. Like a worn spot.''</p>
        <p>Filaq crawled past the guard, shoving him aside, and poked his head out of the door flap, looking toward the great gates of Atil. Whatever he saw when he looked out made him forget himself. He leapt up and ran, laughing, snuffling, tripping over his own feet.</p>
        <p>Amram and Zelikman went after him and arrived before the gates just in time to see Filaq encircle with his slender arms, in their baggy sleeves of borrowed quilt armor, the gnarled proboscis of a broken-down elephant. It loomed, skeletal and listing, its skin tuberous, lumpy, pocked with whitish scars and peeling away in strips of papery excelsior that snowed and blew in little drifts around its feet. A wagonload of ragged and mildew-blown blankets hastily arranged over the staved-in ruin of a barn. A steady rattle issued from the mysterious machinery of its interior like wind in the branches of a locust tree, over a deeper rumbling, an unmistakable continuo of pleasure as the stripling rubbed at the piebald patch between its phlegmatic little eyes, gummed with a milky effluence of tears.</p>
        <p>Filaq spoke to it, calling it his beauty and his little mother and his queen. At a slight distance from the stripling and the elephant, as if granting a measure of privacy to this reunion, the lancers of the 15th Arsiyah sat their horses, with four foot soldiers behind them bearing the flag of truce and the impromptu green bandon of the Brotherhood of the Elephant, the soldiers' faces expressionless and shaded by the brims of their round helmets.</p>
        <p>The elephant withdrew its burled trunk from Filaq's embrace and turned its slow head on the scraping millstones of its vertebrae, left, right, as if indicating the men around it, making a clucking sound with its lips or throat. It made a backward lurch toward the troopers, and one of the horses shied. The trooper riding it raised his lance and drove it deep into the flank of the elephant. Life blew in gusts from the hole in the side of the elephant with a rank smell and a comic flatulence. It sounded a few flat whuffling notes that seemed to raise a stirring echo from far away, and then it pitched forward, its massive skull dragging it down. The architecture of the head struck the ground with a formidable tolling, but the rest of it hit with the light snap of brushwood. Its fall kicked up a roil of dust and delicate falling flakes of scurf.</p>
        <p>''Damn me,'' Amram said, unslinging Defiler of All Mothers from his back. The impostors threw down the streaming banners to be trampled in the mud, unfurled the candelabrum flag of Khazaria and drew their swords. Amram reared up and began to uncoil the bite of his Viking ax, but before he had the chance to swing it, one of the impostors dragged Filaq off the body of the dead beast and, reaching for the collar of the stripling's tunic, ripped the front away, revealing a white belly with a soft prominence, a curve of hip and two yards of linen swaddling cloth wrapped tightly around a slender chest. Filaq struggled, growled, cursed and finally screamed as the soldier tore off the linen drawers, revealing a gonfalon of russet hair with nothing to inspire it but the breeze. With a flourish of his dagger -- one of those bold gestures so dear to emancipators -- the soldier slit the swaddling cloth, and it sprang from Filaq's body, baring the startled gaze of a pair of breasts shaped by the hand of nature to fit the cup of a lover's palm.</p>
        <p>On that plain of mud and grass and staring faces, along the battlements and bartizans of the walls of Atil barbed with pikemen and archers, from the Black Sea to the Sea of Khazar, from the Urals to the Caucasus, there was no sound but the wind in the grass, the clop of a sidestepping horse, the broken breathing of the Little Elephant, Filaq, with whom they had marched and slept and shivered, the son, the prince they had raised up on their shoulders to rule them as their bek, the revenger of the rape of their sisters and the burning of their houses and the pillage of their goods. All Zelikman's disdain, all his resentment toward the foulmouthed spoiled stripling who had plagued him since the rescue at the caravansary vanished with the double shock of the elephant's slaughter and the revelation, and in its place he felt only pity for a white thing flecked with mud, a motherless girl, drooping in the grip of the soldier like a captured flag.</p>
        <p>Before Amram could recover, the mounted impostors had him at the point of their lances. He studied the angles and distances, the lean faces under the helmets, the wonder of the girl, the glinting steel tips of the lances. He threw down his ax. They bound his arms behind him, and with the girl they drove him toward the gates of the city. Zelikman reached for Lancet, but as if he had heard the snick of the blade Amram whipped his head around, seeking among the baffled faces of the Brotherhood for his old friend's, and in his own impassive mien there was neither a warning against hasty action nor the fatalism of defeat but a hint of amusement more useful and wise. Can you top this? And Zelikman recollected his own intelligence, forgot his outrage, resisted the urge to act in panic and left his blade where, for now, it belonged.</p>
        <p>Like apes on a rock at sunset, like crows in the trees, like the bells in the watchtowers of a city under attack, the men of the Brotherhood fell to talking all at once, as those nearest the gates and those at the extremes of the encampment sought to reconcile the stark prodigies of observation with the grandiose inventions of rumor.</p>
        <p>''Master?'' Hanukkah said, approaching Zelikman warily, one hand extended like a man searching out a stairhead in the dark. He wore a mail shirt and one boot and no pants, with his arm in a sling and a bruise on his cheek, a hangover folded about him like a cloak, listing, squinting, a loop of his woolen bedroll caught in a link of his mail so that the blanket dragged along behind him in the mud. ''Is that you?''</p>
        <p>And he reached out, his pudgy cheeks slack, his bright little eyes drained by surprise of any visible emotion, to tug at one of the braids of Zelikman's beard. But the day was not yet replete with wonders, because before Zelikman could reply there were shouts from the rear and then the blatting tantara of an inhuman horn. A fissure opened in the mass of soldiers, and like a dike giving way before the ransacking arm of a flood they fell back or ran to get out of the path of Cunegunde, the elephant, who came shambling toward the gates of Atil, her hide scrubbed, oiled and glistening in the sun, caparisoned in purple silk and cloth of gold, the tips of her tusks capped with gilded leather sheaths. On her back in a large rush basket jostled the nephew of Joseph Hirkanos with three or four of his uncles, clutching the sides of the basket. The effect of the fine silk robes they wore, like that of the bright ribbon braiding their beards and moustaches, was spoiled to a degree by the expressions of terror on their faces.</p>
        <p>Cunegunde stopped beside the body of the dead elephant, staring at it with an unreadable expression. She snuffled, and rumbled, and investigated its sounds and the pocks and scars of its hide. She redistributed her weight impatiently among the pillars of her frame, and some fundamental injustice or harsh fact about the world seemed to confront her afresh, with no gain in meaning or message. The dead animal was a distant cousin to her at best, Zelikman supposed, no nearer kin than Amram was to him.</p>
        <p>Zelikman clapped Hanukkah on the shoulder and then ran toward the elephant. The Radanites riding in the howdah, not yet fully recovered from their jaunt, appeared taken aback by the sudden appearance amid the legs of their merchandise of one of their own guild. Even Joseph cried out in alarm as Zelikman grabbed hold of one of the gilt-embroidered purple strips that fluttered from the withers of the elephant and used it as a rope to pull himself up to the shoulders of the beast, whom his disguise neither alarmed nor, apparently, deceived. Twenty years earlier, at the St. John's Fair at Mainz, a Jewish boy sneaked into the stall where the elephant was kept for the night and fed her a ripe pear, and patted her flank, and spoke a kind word in the holy tongue, which he believed at the time to have been the original language of elephants and men, and now, when that boy, grown to a man, lost his footing on the elephant's flank and began to slide down the silken panel to the ground, Cunegunde reached back and, with the tip of her trunk against the seat of his breeches, held him steady until he could regain his purchase.</p>
        <p>''The offer to join us was a simple one, really,'' Joseph Hirkanos said when Zelikman joined them in the basket, looking him up and down from the tips of his curled slippers to his blackened hedgehog of a plaited beard to the clumsy windings of his head wrap. ''But I divine that you find a way to complicate everything.''</p>
        <p>Next week: Buljan exhibits rather unsportsmanlike behavior after being beaten at shatranj.</p>
        <p>THE FUNNY PAGES: III: SUNDAY SERIAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
