<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To Tighten Drug Tests, Teams Are Secretly Monitoring Players</title>
    <meta content="01testing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/sports/baseball/01testing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837461"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Major League Baseball</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">World Anti-Doping Agency</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE4DC1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2186" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To Tighten Drug Tests, Teams Are Secretly Monitoring Players</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">To Tighten Drug Tests, Baseball Teams Secretly Monitor Players</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY; Judy Battista and Juliet Macur contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Yankees' pitchers and catchers arrived for spring training in mid-February, they saw signs taped up in the clubhouse bathroom reminding them that they would be tested for drugs. They knew the drill: They would have to lower their pants and lift their shirts to prove they were not hiding tampering devices, then give their urine samples with the collector in front of them.</p>
        <p>What few, if any, of them reporting to their training camp in Tampa knew was that the Yankees -- and every other major league team -- had assigned someone in the organization to monitor them discreetly from the time they were notified of a test until they produced a urine sample, sometimes hours later. This behind-the-scenes procedure is not listed in Major League Baseball's Joint Drug Prevention and Treatment Program. It was quietly put in place in July 2005, during the season that baseball was embarrassed by Rafael Palmeiro, who tested positive for a steroid after declaring to Congress that he had never used such drugs. The policy was introduced because top baseball officials perceived that some players had too much freedom on testing days.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Every major league team assigns someone in the organization to monitor their players discreetly from the time they are notified of a drug test until they produce a urine sample.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Yankees' pitchers and catchers arrived for spring training in mid-February, they saw signs taped up in the clubhouse bathroom reminding them that they would be tested for drugs. They knew the drill: They would have to lower their pants and lift their shirts to prove they were not hiding tampering devices, then give their urine samples with the collector in front of them.</p>
        <p>What few, if any, of them reporting to their training camp in Tampa knew was that the Yankees -- and every other major league team -- had assigned someone in the organization to monitor them discreetly from the time they were notified of a test until they produced a urine sample, sometimes hours later. This behind-the-scenes procedure is not listed in Major League Baseball's Joint Drug Prevention and Treatment Program. It was quietly put in place in July 2005, during the season that baseball was embarrassed by Rafael Palmeiro, who tested positive for a steroid after declaring to Congress that he had never used such drugs. The policy was introduced because top baseball officials perceived that some players had too much freedom on testing days.</p>
        <p>It is with this revised system that all 1,200 players on the 30 major league rosters were tested for performance-enhancing drugs within five days of arriving at spring training.</p>
        <p>From baseball's perspective, the overall effort is working, with only 14 major leaguers testing positive since the existing drug program was installed in 2005. Commissioner Bud Selig cited the banning of amphetamines in 2006 in calling his drug policy ''the toughest in American sports.''</p>
        <p>But to antidoping experts, the fact that baseball must rely on club officials to watch over players is evidence of a flawed system. They question why players are not more closely chaperoned when they are to be tested and why, in some cases, they are given so much time to provide a sample. And they say that far more random tests should be conducted.</p>
        <p>Selig said that monitoring was needed because Rob Manfred, baseball's senior vice president for labor relations, and other officials had told him there was ''a problem,'' that some players were not being watched closely enough.</p>
        <p>Now, ''players may not be aware they're under observation, but we're watching,'' Manfred said in a recent interview. ''It doesn't mean we tell them we're watching.''</p>
        <p>Baseball tests the 40-man rosters of all teams once in spring training and at least once more during the season, including the playoffs. Another 600 tests are randomly conducted, as many as 60 of them during the off-season.</p>
        <p>That is hardly an imposing number, say antidoping experts, who also question why baseball does not have an independent oversight committee and why it does not have more substances on its banned list. Some of the sharpest criticism, however, is reserved for the testing process, which began anew this year as players reported to training camps in Florida and Arizona.</p>
        <p>In interviews, more than a dozen players explained what happened on the day that they showed up at the ballpark to find a urine collector waiting for them. Under the testing program, negotiated by the players union and Major League Baseball, which has been toughened twice in recent years, a player has leeway when he is being tested. If he cannot quickly produce a urine sample, he has up to an hour to participate in baseball activities before returning to the collector. If he is still unable to give a sample, he can wait up to an hour after that day's game ends.</p>
        <p>''If a guy can't do it, he comes back in an hour?'' said Dr. Gary I. Wadler, an associate professor of medicine at New York University and a member of the World Anti-Doping Agency. ''Comes back in an hour? Give me a break. They should say that he will be chaperoned from the moment of notification. It shouldn't even be 30 seconds later.''</p>
        <p>During any time that players are not chaperoned, antidoping experts said, they could drink a lot of water to try to dilute their urine, use masking agents or use devices that allow them to fill their bladders with someone else's drug-free urine.</p>
        <p>One general manager said recently that he saw some loopholes last season in the way the tests were conducted.</p>
        <p>''That is an area that needs to be monitored better,'' he said. ''Not that it's lax, but I have seen times where there's a little more trust given to a player than there should be.''</p>
        <p>The general manager, who was granted anonymity to discuss the testing procedure, said that during the season the collectors routinely showed up four and a half hours before a night game -- about 2:30 p.m. in most cities.</p>
        <p>After a player spotted the collector, the general manager said, he could alert teammates who had not yet arrived at the ballpark that testing was taking place that day. If a player planned to use amphetamines, the general manager said, he would know not to do so until he found out if he was going to be tested that day.</p>
        <p>''They should vary when the tester shows up,'' he said. ''Make it 3:30 or 4 one time. You're looking for deterrents.''</p>
        <p>When Yankees pitcher Mike Mussina was to be tested last off-season, he said, he was called and told roughly what time the next day the collector would arrive. Mussina said he considered off-season testing a legitimate effort to deter the use of performance enhancers.</p>
        <p>Wadler said that giving athletes notice was ''100 percent unacceptable'' because some could be tempted to use that window of time for various ''evasive techniques.''</p>
        <p>''In my view, that represents a very significant flaw'' in baseball's testing program, he said.</p>
        <p>In out-of-competition testing in the Olympics, an antidoping collector shows up unannounced at athletes' houses or training sites or anywhere else the athletes have told the agency they may be. If the athlete who is to be tested is not at those locations, the representative calls to notify him or her about the test. The athlete then has a two-hour window to report and provide a sample.</p>
        <p>Like baseball players, National Football League players are notified on the day of their tests. If a player cannot produce a sample, he is free to work out or attend meetings without being chaperoned. But he must remain at the team facility.</p>
        <p>Three of the 30 baseball player monitors are general managers, 18 are assistant general managers, 4 are vice presidents, 4 are directors of baseball operations and the title of the other one was not disclosed.</p>
        <p>If a monitor is unable to observe a player or players, a preapproved designee can take over, a fairly common occurrence. Still, the general manager who spoke of the loopholes said, some teams consider it more of the collector's responsibility to watch the players than it is the club's.</p>
        <p>Before the policy spurred by Palmeiro's test, observation was supposed to be the collector's responsibility.</p>
        <p>When Palmeiro was interviewed by congressional investigators in an inquiry into whether he had lied under oath about steroid use, he said he found out when he arrived at the stadium on May 4, 2005, that he would be tested.</p>
        <p>Palmeiro, who was playing for the Baltimore Orioles, said he did his pregame preparation and supplied the sample about half an hour before the first pitch. He said he was not supervised by drug-testing officials from the time he was alerted to the test until the time he provided the specimen.</p>
        <p>How much has that changed under the new policy?</p>
        <p>Mike Myers, a Yankees reliever, initially said in an interview in February that a player would have to leave a stadium to have a chance to beat a test. Then he reconsidered.</p>
        <p>Myers said: ''I'm sure if you studied that real hard and you figured out a way to empty out your bladder and go back and fill it up with something else and come back in and take the test, then possibly. There's got to be a way to combat it.''</p>
        <p>Mussina dismissed that notion.</p>
        <p>''We're not leaving the building and coming back four hours later,'' he said. ''Where are we going to go? This is our job. We can't just up and leave. I don't understand, on short notice, what anyone is going to do to circumvent the test anyway.''</p>
        <p>Chris Capuano, a pitcher for the Milwaukee Brewers, said that players were asked to produce a sample as soon as they arrived and that he had never encountered a problem doing so. Capuano added: ''Some guys take their time, get changed, whatever. There's not someone with you the whole time, certainly.''</p>
        <p>But Gene Orza, the chief operating officer of the players union, insisted that players were chaperoned.</p>
        <p>''There is absolutely no evidence that a player scheduled for a test is left unattended for a period of time that permits him to defeat the purposes of the test,'' Orza said in an e-mail message. ''Absolutely none. From the moment the player is designated for a test, he is under observation by the team coordinator.''</p>
        <p>Miguel Batista, a pitcher for the Seattle Mariners, said players who had nothing to hide should not care who monitored them anyway. ''If you are concerned about people watching you,'' Batista said, ''you are in the wrong sport.''</p>
        <p>Some antidoping experts said baseball's policy would be stronger if it called for more than 600 random tests. Wadler scoffed at that total, saying that adding more tests would indeed be another form of deterrence.</p>
        <p>Manfred said he was content with the number because ''a player is never certain he's completed his testing for the season.'' But he added that an increase in random testing could be discussed at a future collective bargaining session with the union.</p>
        <p>In the N.F.L., players are tested at least once a year, usually at the beginning of training camp or when they report for physicals. Last year, the N.F.L. increased the maximum number of times a player could be randomly tested in the off-season to six times from two.</p>
        <p>Beyond the questions about supervision, baseball's policy -- like those in other sports -- still has a notable blemish because it does not test for human growth hormone, even though it is banned. Players realize that, for now, human growth hormone use will go undetected.</p>
        <p>As he reviewed baseball's list of prohibited substances, Wadler said he wondered why it did not use the World Anti-Doping Agency's more wide-ranging list. That list includes substances like the blood booster erythropoietin, or EPO, and the hormone 1GF-1, which, Wadler said, ''pretty much does what'' human growth hormone does.</p>
        <p>Manfred said baseball would prefer to use the agency's list but that it did not achieve that goal in the give-and-take of collective bargaining.</p>
        <p>Orza said the union and Major League Baseball ''didn't trade one substance for another.'' He said the longer agency list of banned substances included some found in over-the-counter drugs, like cold medications. It would be unfair, he said, for a player to be suspended for 50 games, the punishment for a first-time offense, for using a product that anyone could legally buy.</p>
        <p>Wadler said the international agency's code included provisions for reducing sanctions if an athlete used a generally available substance that was not meant as a performance enhancer.</p>
        <p>''They keep incrementally moving toward where they need to get,'' Wadler said of Major League Baseball. ''They're just not there yet. There is a gold standard. When are they going to adopt the gold standard?''</p>
        <p>Dr. Christiane Ayotte, the director of the antidoping agency's laboratory in Montreal, which handles baseball's testing, said she would not have agreed to work with baseball if she felt the testing was insufficient.</p>
        <p>''For the moment, I'd say it's good enough,'' Ayotte said. ''They test for stimulants and performance-enhancing drugs. I'd say it's good enough.''</p>
        <p>Manfred and Orza are on baseball's four-member Health Policy Advisory Committee, which oversees the testing regimen. It has two representatives from management and two from the union.</p>
        <p>Wadler questioned the committee's effectiveness, saying he doubted it could act as an independent group like WADA or the United States Anti-Doping Agency. Because the committee has a financial interest in the sport's success, he said, there are potential conflicts of interest.</p>
        <p>''The real question is, why the reluctance to farm it out to an independent, transparent and accountable agency and get out of the business in which you don't belong?'' he said.</p>
        <p>Manfred strenuously maintained that the baseball panel had an independent administrator, Dr. Bryan Smith. Smith is paid by baseball, but another entity would also have to be paid.</p>
        <p>The United States Anti-Doping Agency ''doesn't do things for free, either,'' Manfred said.</p>
        <p>So, for now, baseball presses on with testing in its current form.</p>
        <p>Selig acknowledged that there was more to do, with a nationwide investigation into illegal online sales of performance enhancers under way and with some antidoping experts criticizing the policy.</p>
        <p>''I'm very pleased by what we've done,'' he said. ''Does that mean we've solved the problem? No, it doesn't, and I wouldn't suggest that.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
