<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unsporting News</title>
    <meta content="Bouton.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/books/review/Bouton.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837012"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Cheater's Guide to Baseball, The (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E7DB1530F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1184" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unsporting News</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Unsporting News</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM BOUTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bouton, Jim</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE CHEATER'S GUIDE TO BASEBALL</p>
        <p>By Derek Zumsteg.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 265 pp. Houghton Mifflin Company.</p>
        <p>Paper, $13.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you ever wanted to throw a spitball or cork a bat, Derek Zumsteg can tell you how.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE CHEATER'S GUIDE TO BASEBALL</p>
        <p>By Derek Zumsteg.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 265 pp. Houghton Mifflin Company.</p>
        <p>Paper, $13.95.</p>
        <p>I can just imagine the marketing meeting for this book:</p>
        <p>''Why do we need another baseball book?''</p>
        <p>''No matter how bad they are, we always recoup our costs.''</p>
        <p>''What's the title?''</p>
        <p>''We've got two good words so far: 'baseball' and 'cheating.' ''</p>
        <p>''Hmm. It needs an angle.''</p>
        <p>''How-to books always sell.''</p>
        <p>''That's it! A book about how to cheat.''</p>
        <p>'' 'The Cheater's Guide to Baseball.' Three good words!''</p>
        <p>Thus we have the baseball equivalent of ''How to Build an Atomic Bomb.'' Or, more precisely, ''How to Build an Entire Munitions Dump'' -- ''dump'' being a good word to describe the book's bulletin-board style.</p>
        <p>Sandwiched between a chapter entitled ''The Exotic Bird of Cheating: The Hidden Ball Trick'' (not actually cheating, but close enough to qualify as filler) and a chapter about heckling and riots (a form of fan cheating) is a chapter on Billy Martin (''a cheater's cheater''), which includes ''Billy Martin's all-time all-horrible team.'' This appears in a box that features Benito Mussolini (P), Adolf Hitler (LF) and Emperor Hirohito (CF), among others, with the players and positions selected by the author, Derek Zumsteg. Why he has Mussolini on the mound, as opposed to Genghis Khan (SS), say, or Pol Pot (C), may be a good subject for blogging, another hobby of Zumsteg's.</p>
        <p>For the purposes of this book, almost anything qualifies as cheating.</p>
        <p>In a section called ''Cheating for Beginners,'' Zumsteg, a co-author of five editions of Baseball Prospectus, shows how even fans can affect the outcome of games. Rather than ''yelling at people randomly,'' he explains, they should obey the ''rooting rules'' of Pete Adelis (the Iron Lung of Shibe Park, whom the Yankees once brought to New York, all expenses paid, to holler at the Cleveland Indians). Players have heard obscene chants for years, Zumsteg writes, referring to rooting rule No. 4: Know your players. ''You've got to work on new material. ... Play on their fears ... that's especially effective for marginal players. Know the name of the farm team.''</p>
        <p>Other ways fans can have a negative impact on the visiting team? If an opposing player reaches into the stands to catch a ball, ''getting in the fielder's way isn't just allowed,'' Zumsteg insists, referring to the rule regarding fan interference, ''it's your obligation as an intelligent fan. And don't be afraid to knock it out of his glove. ... If he can't control it, it's not a catch. Really.''</p>
        <p>Zumsteg does draw the line, however, at throwing certain things onto the field. ''If a fan could smuggle in the transmission from a 1984 Pontiac Fiero and then take out the left fielder with it, and every other fan followed suit, it'd only be a couple of games before everyone would be watching Triple-A talent from their jail cells. No one wants that.''</p>
        <p>You'll be relieved to know that Zumsteg is also against full-scale riots. ''I'm sure the novelty would wear off after the first week,'' he writes, ''and then there'd be the consequences: no one would be able to buy beer.'' The magnitude of such a tragedy becomes clear in the acknowledgments, where a number of brewing companies are thanked for their ''unintentional contributions.''</p>
        <p>This is a very thorough book, which is what's required to take it beyond 60 pages. No detail is spared. Not only do you get the complete history of -- and instructions for -- bat corking, you get a step-by-step recipe for how to tamper with an aluminum bat: (1) Buy an industrial aluminum forge plant. (2) Hire new workers, as needed. (3) Retool plant. (4) Take existing bat to plant. (5) Melt bat down. Etc.</p>
        <p>By this time you realize the book is less an examination of cheating and more a glimpse into the mind of a particular kind of sports addict. The kind who, when he's not at a ballgame with his buddies, sits in front of the TV with the remote, checking the scores to see how much money he's won or lost.</p>
        <p>''Fans are itching for a way to liven up baseball with a little friendly betting action,'' Zumsteg writes in a chapter called ''Gambling and Game-Fixing: The Good Old Days,'' and ''I'm here to scratchy, scratchy that itch.''</p>
        <p>In ''Scratchy, Scratchy, Picky Picky,'' another space-filling digression, he writes: ''Every bettor picks a player standing against the dugout rail, watching the game. The bettor then makes money on the actions of this player. The player scratches or otherwise reaches down to adjust his crotch ... the owning bettor wins $1 from all other bettors. Picking the nose is worth $2 (maximum, one payout per minute), but if it's followed by booger-eating it's worth $10.'' There must be a lot of money changing hands in the stadium section where Zumsteg sits.</p>
        <p>Other betting games include: the odds that an inspirational video will be played before the ninth inning; which ball girl is likely to boot one; and an over/under on the 90-second prescribed time for the singing (or playing) of the national anthem. Zumsteg's tip: ''Always bet the over on longhaired saxophonists and anyone described as a 'local recording artist.' '' This is where I thought it might be fun to go to a ballgame with Zumsteg. One game, anyway.</p>
        <p>In ''The Worst Thing Ever to Happen to Baseball,'' Zumsteg discusses the Black Sox scandal, a story more fully recounted elsewhere in real books. But none of those other authors wrote a two-act play with imagined dialogue between gamblers and fixers, or included instructions in the event that, ''for whatever reason, you want to throw a World Series.''</p>
        <p>And then the book gets wacky.</p>
        <p>In the last chapter, in a relative handful of pages, Zumsteg finally addresses steroids. And what does he have to say about the drug that's had a more adverse effect on the integrity of the game than all the other cheating combined? ''Steroids themselves aren't evil,'' he writes. ''They don't load themselves up into syringes in excessive doses and inject themselves into someone's innocent butt.'' I wonder if he owns a gun.</p>
        <p>''Statistics aren't tainted,'' Zumsteg continues; ''they just require us to remember their context.'' He then argues that Babe Ruth never had to face black pitchers and that early fielders had poor equipment. But that's not analogous because whatever the conditions at the time, they were the same for everyone. Steroids, on the other hand, give users an unfair, superhuman advantage over nonusers.</p>
        <p>''Baseball without cheating would be a terrible sport,'' Zumsteg concludes, in a sweeping statement intended to justify the existence of his book, but which more tellingly reveals his view of the game as a vehicle for his obsessions.</p>
        <p>How does a book like this occur to someone in the first place? Once again, a clue can be found in the acknowledgments. ''Thanks are due,'' Zumsteg writes, ''to my agent, Sydelle Kramer, who was willing to help me figure out which book idea I could do well with, whip up a good proposal and find it a home.''</p>
        <p>Jim Bouton is the author of ''Ball Four'' and, more recently, ''Foul Ball: My Life and Hard Times Trying to Save an Old Ballpark, Plus Part II.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jim Bouton is the author of ''Ball Four'' and, more recently, ''Foul Ball: My Life and Hard Times Trying to Save an Old Ballpark, Plus Part II.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
