<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Women's War</title>
    <meta content="01letters.t-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837143"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corbett, Sara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lemelin, Carol A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">anderson, karin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">bassano, marilyn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">hurwitz, alan j (dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mosley, Stephen T</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00EED91330F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="515" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Women's War</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>March 18 article on women who served with US military in Iraq prompts letters from Carol A Lemelin, Karin Anderson, Marilyn Bassano, Dr Alan J Hurwitz and Stephen T Moseley; photo</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I was heartsick when I finished Sara Corbett's article (March 18). These women soldiers who served their country were treated with the utmost contempt by their own. Gen. Peter Pace, who is so worried about the effect of homosexual soldiers on the service, ought to look closely at what the heterosexual soldier is doing to his fellow soldiers. Officers using their rank to degrade, at the least, and rape, at the worst, bring all under suspicion. One hundred percent intolerance for such behavior is called for. Instead, the victim is afraid to ask for help. Always a supporter of women in the military, I now wonder if those who oppose them are right, that it is too dangerous, sadly not just on the battlefield but also in the barracks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I was heartsick when I finished Sara Corbett's article (March 18). These women soldiers who served their country were treated with the utmost contempt by their own. Gen. Peter Pace, who is so worried about the effect of homosexual soldiers on the service, ought to look closely at what the heterosexual soldier is doing to his fellow soldiers. Officers using their rank to degrade, at the least, and rape, at the worst, bring all under suspicion. One hundred percent intolerance for such behavior is called for. Instead, the victim is afraid to ask for help. Always a supporter of women in the military, I now wonder if those who oppose them are right, that it is too dangerous, sadly not just on the battlefield but also in the barracks.</p>
        <p>Carol A. Lemelin</p>
        <p>Saint Clair Shores, Mich.</p>
        <p>The military cannot expect its sensitivity workshops to effectively prevent sexual assault and harassment when its core values undermine the workshops' goals. The military must cultivate in its troops an excessive amount of adrenaline and anger in order to turn otherwise compassionate, rational individuals into soldiers capable of the violence that war requires. Combine this with America's mainstream culture (one that continues to glorify women as sexual objects), and you can arrive only at a formula for rape.</p>
        <p>Karin Anderson</p>
        <p>Volunteer Rape Crisis Advocate</p>
        <p>St. Luke's-Roosevelt</p>
        <p>Hospital Center</p>
        <p>Crime Victims Treatment Center</p>
        <p>New York</p>
        <p>What a powerful article. It really opened my eyes. Whenever I hear anyone talk about soldiers and their service to our country, I will be thinking of this special class of women, who received a ''double whammy'' of suffering not only through the horrors of war but also through the horrors of sexual abuse, verbal or physical, by their fellow mates and officers as part of their ''service to our country.''</p>
        <p>Marilyn Bassano</p>
        <p>Wayne, N.J.</p>
        <p>As a psychiatrist who treated many Vietnam veterans with post-traumatic stress disorder earlier in my career, I was saddened but not surprised by Corbett's article. In the last three years, we have seen a very significant increase in the number of individuals accepted into the military with so-called ''moral waivers.'' Rather than merely being ''under 25, and often developmentally adolescent'' (as Corbett quotes Tina Lee, a psychiatrist with the V.A. in Palo Alto), we are talking about an increase in the number of enlistees with criminal records -- including crimes like vehicular manslaughter, robbery and aggravated assault.</p>
        <p>Alan J. Hurwitz, M.D.</p>
        <p>Houston</p>
        <p>Corbett's article about the difficulties experienced by military women in Iraq reminded me of a saying about Ginger Rogers: she had to do everything Fred Astaire did, only backward and in high heels. How tragic that the horrors of war are compounded by the threat of sexual harassment and rape by our own men. The stories of these courageous women reveal the need for the establishment of female ombudsmen to whom women in the military can turn for issues that soldiers and military leaders, both male and female, have demonstrably failed to handle.</p>
        <p>Stephen T. Mosley</p>
        <p>Newtown, Pa.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
