<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bringing Back the Sunday Dinner</title>
    <meta content="01RdinnerLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837152"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Italian-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Haven (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bittman, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut/New Haven</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E1D61330F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2629" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bringing Back the Sunday Dinner</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK BITTMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bittman, Mark</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on traditional Sunday dinners in suburban New York metropolitan area, which may be ripe for revival; describes dinner with Italian-American family in New Haven, Conn; recipes; photos; drawing (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is no surprise that Sunday has become the new Saturday, a day of errands and chores, of tidying up odds and ends of work or sitting at the desk for hours at a time, with maybe a little exercise and television thrown in. I am surprised, though, that this bothers me. Like many baby boomers, I have spent a great deal of energy cultivating an unsentimental and even antitraditional attitude. But I just can't seem to shake my fond memories of a quiet day in Queens, with few cars on the streets, everything except maybe a drugstore and a restaurant or two closed, and three generations of my family laughing over the remains of a Sunday dinner cooked by my grandmother.</p>
        <p>Though Sunday may no longer be a day of rest, Sunday dinner can often define the rest of the day. And for many families -- unable to bring everyone to the table during the rest of the week because of soccer practices and music lessons, after-school programs and long workdays -- it is the only time to gather as one.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is no surprise that Sunday has become the new Saturday, a day of errands and chores, of tidying up odds and ends of work or sitting at the desk for hours at a time, with maybe a little exercise and television thrown in. I am surprised, though, that this bothers me. Like many baby boomers, I have spent a great deal of energy cultivating an unsentimental and even antitraditional attitude. But I just can't seem to shake my fond memories of a quiet day in Queens, with few cars on the streets, everything except maybe a drugstore and a restaurant or two closed, and three generations of my family laughing over the remains of a Sunday dinner cooked by my grandmother.</p>
        <p>Though Sunday may no longer be a day of rest, Sunday dinner can often define the rest of the day. And for many families -- unable to bring everyone to the table during the rest of the week because of soccer practices and music lessons, after-school programs and long workdays -- it is the only time to gather as one.</p>
        <p>It may not be as strong as it was, but this tradition, as old as churchgoing and a part of the secular American landscape as well, seems ripe for revival. Whether the setting is a formal dining room or a breakfast nook, whether the food is prime rib or eggplant Parmesan, it is the presence of loved ones in a drawn-out, laid-back, barrier-breaking atmosphere that really counts.</p>
        <p>It took a visit to a family of Italian descent in New Haven to bring it all home to me. It was a miserable day, cold and raining in sheets. I was the odd man in, and knew only one of the 20 or so people there. Yet I was never a stranger; rather, I was ignored in a way that felt familial, treated as if I belonged and was nothing special.</p>
        <p>The dinner was a panoply of Italian-American classics: a hunk of pecorino, some spicy marinated olives that I suspect came from Stop &amp; Shop, a tureen of pasta e fagioli, a pan of lasagna that clearly was central and much beloved, a plate of pan-fried veal in case there wasn't enough food, some very retro garlic bread, overcooked broccoli with olive oil, an uninspired salad made with Wishbone or the equivalent, and, to finish, fresh and dried fruit, nuts in their shells and cannoli from a good local bakery. On the table were Coke and rough red wine, both in big bottles.</p>
        <p>The event began in the kitchen, moved to the dining room, ended in the living room. I could barely follow the conversation while we were actually eating, but I felt right at home: it was intensely personal and as argumentative as a scene from an early Woody Allen movie.</p>
        <p>Later, things calmed down radically. One of the older members of the third generation, a young woman of about 20, was asking her grandfather how he met her grandmother; I helped clean up and tried to figure out the provenance of the lasagna.</p>
        <p>A football game was on (the Giants were losing), and a couple of the younger men and boys were watching it. I wanted a nap, but fought through it. A languorous atmosphere of chatting and really personal conversation developed; I was asked about my family, and found myself speaking fondly of similar Sundays, remembering the war stories, the talk of the old country, and how so-and-so's son had gotten into medical school.</p>
        <p>Though not everyone participated -- some appeared to be in a stupor, and a couple of the children were getting hyper -- people began looking at photos, and they weren't digital. Eventually, the TV was turned off; some people left, others stayed. There was more coffee, and a little snacking on the lasagna.</p>
        <p>It sounds like Thanksgiving, and felt like it too. But this scene is repeated every week, throughout the metropolitan area, throughout the country, throughout the world. Last spring, I was invited to a Sunday dinner in Catalonia, two hours from Barcelona, almost in the Pyrenees. Despite the differences in time, space and culture, the two experiences had far more in common than not -- the distracted and occasionally loving children; the revered elders; the young adults and middle-aged people engaged in sometimes calm, sometimes animated conversations; the food that everyone knew and loved; and most of all the long, drawn-out, leisurely afternoon.</p>
        <p>The food varies, in type and quality; it is, most commonly, a meal in which the cooking is almost determined by genetics. When I make meals like this I serve the same food my grandmother did -- roast chicken, potato pancakes, chopped liver and the like -- with barely a variation, though it is never as delicious as in my memories.</p>
        <p>Is the food the point? Not entirely. We all have 10 times as many food options as we did 20 or 30 years ago, and most of us have eaten better-tasting lasagna or meatloaf or fried chicken or ribs or pot roast than that made by our parents or grandparents.</p>
        <p>Rather, the meal is the excuse. It's the attraction, and it's the glue. No one is going to go to your house on a Sunday afternoon without expecting food, and there's no way they will stay past ''How are you? What's new?'' without a leisurely meal to slow them down. And since Sunday dinners are often late-afternoon affairs, there is plenty of time to linger over dessert and reminisce about the Fillmore East or antiwar rallies or the old Pontiac that broke down in Missouri on that long-ago road trip.</p>
        <p>One of the terrific things about Sunday dinners is that few people have ultra-high expectations of the food, though they do expect enough of it. This doesn't mean the food shouldn't be good, but the quantity gives you an excuse to produce a big stew or even a crockpot of chili; a lasagna or other huge pasta dish; a classic rib or pork roast; or a nice big bird (fortunately, unlike Thanksgiving, this bird doesn't have to be a turkey).</p>
        <p>I'm offering a few recipes here (the lasagna, by the way, is vegetarian, an increasingly important consideration few of our grandparents were ever forced to take into account), but there are infinite possibilities for the center of your Sunday table.</p>
        <p>All of these recipes are easy to double, but these days it makes more sense to think about adding side dishes, and they all need not be cooked by you. Store-bought olives (if you marinate them overnight in a little olive oil, garlic and rosemary, so much the better), baked goods and prewashed salad greens can all serve as major components of a meal, with little sacrifice in quality. Cheese, nuts and fresh and dried fruit are all options.</p>
        <p>This leaves you with the main dish, a cooked vegetable or two, maybe some salad dressing (a two-minute operation) and enough time to sit back and enjoy your family in a less frantic, more Sunday sort of way.</p>
        <p>The Less Fuss, the Better</p>
        <p>WITH the exception of dishes like lasagna, main courses for Sunday dinners tend to be extremely simple; the labor involved is more in the shopping (and expense) than it is in the actual cooking, as you can see from the recipes here.</p>
        <p>To complement the centerpiece, you have two basic options: more shopping or more cooking (preceded by shopping, of course). A combination of both is most effective, but you can really go one way or the other.</p>
        <p>For me, there is something about roast chicken that begs for good, crusty bread, and a large, round peasant-style loaf has a celebratory look about it that makes it perfectly appropriate. Mashed potatoes -- sweet, white or a combination -- is another well-loved option. You can boil the potatoes a little in advance, then mash with butter and milk, or olive oil and a hint of garlic, and reheat at the last minute. Creamy polenta, which cannot be made in advance, is another possibility. Any kind of steamed vegetable -- especially those with color, like broccoli, spinach or carrots -- is obviously a good idea. (Poach or steam the vegetable in advance, then drain it and reheat it in olive oil or butter at the last minute.)</p>
        <p>As simplistic as it sounds, prime rib demands baked potatoes, at least traditionally. (These should not be baked in foil, but roasted at 400 degrees or higher until soft inside, then kept in an oven set at 250 degrees for at least a half-hour.) A potato gratin is even nicer, if you have the energy. My steamed vegetable recommendations would be about the same, but a chopped or green salad would lighten things up a bit, not a bad idea with a huge hunk of meat sitting on the table.</p>
        <p>The vegetable lasagna here is as close to a one-pot (or one-pan) dish as you can come for a feast. It is also the one main course here that is actually some work to put together, but the benefit comes with the sides, which can be very simple. Think about marinated olives, a green salad, a good bread -- you don't need much more.</p>
        <p>I don't like to fuss about wine, but there are some differences among these dishes, so pairing requires at least a little thought. Chicken with onions and parsley is not a classic roast chicken, and needs something lighter than the usual; a nearly chillable red, like gamay Beaujolais or a light pinot noir or zinfandel, or a sprightly white with character -- maybe sémillon or albariño. Rib roast traditionally takes the best red you can find (and afford), specifically Burgundy or Bordeaux, but that doesn't rule out a Barolo, the great wines of the south of France, or a soft but complex Rioja. The vegetable lasagna is a wine-killer, so you don't want anything too fancy -- Chianti, and not a great one, or a rough zinfandel or southern French wine.</p>
        <p>MARK BITTMAN</p>
        <p>ROAST CHICKEN WITH ONIONS AND PARSLEY  Time: 11/2 hours</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons freshly squeezed lemon juice  2 cups chopped fresh parsley or chervil leaves  1 teaspoon chopped garlic  Salt and freshly ground black pepper  1 large chicken or capon, about 6 pounds, trimmed of excess fat  3 tablespoons butter or extra virgin olive oil  3 cups thinly sliced onions  1 cup chicken or vegetable stock or water.</p>
        <p>1. Heat the oven to 500 degrees. Combine the lemon juice, 1/2 cup parsley, garlic and some salt and pepper, and rub this mixture all over the chicken. Put the chicken, breast side down, on a rack in a roasting pan and put the pan in the oven.  2. While it's roasting, melt the butter or heat the olive oil in a medium skillet or saucepan over medium heat, then add the onions; cook, stirring occasionally, until softened, 10 to 15 minutes. Stir in the remaining parsley and the stock.  3. After the chicken has roasted for about 20 minutes, spoon some of the onion mixture over it, then turn the bird breast side up. Top with more of the onion mixture, leaving some in the saucepan. Baste again after 10 minutes; at this point the breast should be beginning to brown (if it isn't, roast a few more minutes). Turn the heat down to 325 degrees, baste again, and roast until an instant-read thermometer inserted into the thickest part of the thigh reads 155 to 165 degrees. Total roasting time will be about an hour and a half.  4. Remove the chicken from the oven and let it rest for about 5 minutes. Meanwhile, pour some or all of the pan juices into the saucepan with the remaining onion mixture and bring to a boil; reduce slightly if the mixture is thin. Carve the chicken and serve with the sauce.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 servings or more.</p>
        <p>CLASSIC PRIME RIB FOR A SMALL CROWD  Time: About 11/2 hours, largely unattended</p>
        <p>1 (3-rib) roast, about 5 pounds, trimmed of excess but not all fat  Salt and freshly ground black pepper to taste  1 or 2 cloves garlic (optional)  1 cup red wine, stock, or water.</p>
        <p>1. Bring the meat to room temperature by removing it from the refrigerator at least an hour before cooking, preferably two. (For a larger roast, make it three.) Preheat the oven to 450 degrees.  2. Place the meat, bone side down, in a large roasting pan. Season it with salt and pepper. If you like garlic, peel the cloves and cut them into tiny slivers; use a boning or paring knife to poke small holes in the meat and insert the garlic into them.  3. Place the roast in the oven and cook for 15 minutes, undisturbed. Turn the heat down to 350 degrees and continue to roast about 1 hour; check in several places with a meat thermometer. When no spot registers under 125 degrees (120 degrees if you like your meat really rare and your guests are of the same preference), the meat is rare; cook another 5 or 10 minutes if you like it more well done, then check again, but in no case should you let the temperature of the meat go above 155 degrees.  4. Remove the meat from the oven. Pour off all but a few tablespoons of the fat, and place the roasting pan over a burner set to high. Add the liquid and cook, stirring and scraping up any brown bits, until it is reduced by half. Slice and serve the roast, splashing a little of the sauce on the meat platter and passing the rest at the table.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 servings or more.</p>
        <p>SPINACH LASAGNA  Time: 1 hour, with prepared pasta and sauce</p>
        <p>12 to 16 dried or fresh lasagna noodles  3 to 4 cups tomato sauce  2 tablespoons extra virgin olive oil  3 cups cooked spinach, squeezed dry and chopped  11/2 cups ricotta  11/2 cups coarsely grated mozzarella  2 cups grated Parmesan  Salt and freshly ground black pepper.</p>
        <p>1. If you're using dried pasta, bring a large pot of salted water to a boil. If you're using fresh pasta sheets, cut them into long wide noodles approximately 3 inches by 13 inches, or a size that will fit into your lasagna dish. Cook the noodles (6 at a time for dried noodles) until they are tender but still underdone (they will finish cooking as the lasagna bakes); fresh pasta will take only a minute. Drain and then lay the noodles flat on a towel so they won't stick.  2. Heat the oven to 400 degrees. Grease a rectangular baking dish with the olive oil, add a large dollop of tomato sauce and spread it around. Put a layer of noodles (use four) in the dish, trimming any overhanging edges; top with a layer of tomato sauce, one-third of the spinach, and one-fourth of the ricotta (use your fingers to spread it evenly) , the mozzarella and the Parmesan. Sprinkle some salt and pepper between the layers of tomato sauce and spinach if desired.  3. Repeat the layers twice, and top with the remaining noodles, tomato sauce, ricotta, mozzarella and Parmesan; the top should be covered with cheese; add more ricotta and Parmesan as needed. (The lasagna may be made ahead to this point, wrapped tightly and refrigerated for up to a day or frozen. Bring to room temperature before proceeding.)  4. Bake until the lasagna is bubbling and the cheese is melted and lightly browned on top, about 30 minutes. Remove from the oven and let rest a few minutes before serving, or cool completely, cover well, and refrigerate for up to 3 days, or freeze.  Yield: 6 servings or more.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
