<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Who Should Pay for a Broken Skylight?</title>
    <meta content="01qa" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837235"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Q &amp; A"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Q and A</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE6D81030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="480" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Who Should Pay for a Broken Skylight?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAY ROMANO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q. After a recent storm, a huge chunk of ice fell off the roof of a commercial building that is next to mine and overlooks my deck and skylight. The ice broke the skylight. My co-op lease says that the windows are my responsibility. The owners of the building next door say they are not responsible. Is that true?</p>
        <p>A. Steve Troup, a Manhattan real estate lawyer, said a property owner in New York has an obligation to keep his building free from dangerous conditions, including a buildup of ice and snow, that he knows about or should know about.</p>
        <p>Mr. Troup said a number of factors would go into determining whether the owner knew or should have known about the ice and whether there was a reasonable opportunity to correct the problem.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q. After a recent storm, a huge chunk of ice fell off the roof of a commercial building that is next to mine and overlooks my deck and skylight. The ice broke the skylight. My co-op lease says that the windows are my responsibility. The owners of the building next door say they are not responsible. Is that true?</p>
        <p>A. Steve Troup, a Manhattan real estate lawyer, said a property owner in New York has an obligation to keep his building free from dangerous conditions, including a buildup of ice and snow, that he knows about or should know about.</p>
        <p>Mr. Troup said a number of factors would go into determining whether the owner knew or should have known about the ice and whether there was a reasonable opportunity to correct the problem.</p>
        <p>''Some things the courts consider are how long the condition had existed, when the snow had stopped falling, from where the chunk of ice fell, whether it was visible from the street, whether the property owner took steps to clear the ice and whether there were prior similar occurrences,'' he said.</p>
        <p>So if the letter writer can demonstrate that the property owner knew or should have known about the dangerous condition, and had sufficient opportunity to correct it, a judge or a jury could then decide that the owner was negligent and thus liable to pay for repairing the skylight.</p>
        <p>''The writer should also contact her homeowner's insurance company to see if this is a covered claim,'' Mr. Troup said.</p>
        <p>Replacing Windows In a Condominium</p>
        <p>Q. Our condo has old windows that leak, making it difficult, expensive and wasteful to heat and air-condition. The windows cannot be repaired, and the board voted down the costly window replacement project that some owners had requested. Can the board deny us the ability to remedy the problem and force us to spend money on energy instead of replacement?</p>
        <p>A. Arthur I. Weinstein, a Manhattan lawyer and a vice president of the Council of New York Cooperatives and Condominiums, said that if the board weighed the benefits of replacing all windows in the building against the cost of doing so and then made a good-faith decision against buildingwide replacement, its decision would be protected by the ''business judgment rule'' and would not be subject to second-guessing by unit owners or the courts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Weinstein noted, however, that the board would probably allow individual unit owners to replace their windows at their own expense. Typically, he said, permission would be granted as long as the new windows do not change the appearance or character of the building.</p>
        <p>An alternative might be for a shareholder to install storm windows on the inside of the apartment. Some of these windows are made of lightweight plexiglass and mount on or over existing sashes.</p>
        <p>JAY ROMANO</p>
        <p>Q &amp; A</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
