<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GLOVES WITHOUT NAMES</title>
    <meta content="01glove" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/sports/baseball/01glove.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837437"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL PREVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sporting Goods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Modell's Sporting Goods</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EFDD1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="848" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GLOVES WITHOUT NAMES</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Autograph Is No Longer What Makes a Mitt Most Valuable</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL S. SCHMIDT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schmidt, Michael S</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a warm March afternoon at a Modell's Sporting Goods store on Manhattan's Upper East Side, 39-year-old Angel Valez was, appropriately enough, in a baseball frame of mind.</p>
        <p>He scanned the aisles of the store, looking for the perfect size and color for the glove he planned on purchasing for himself so he could play catch with his 10-year-old son. But as he tested various gloves, and pounded his fist into any number of leather pockets, he did not notice that something from his childhood was missing -- the player autograph, ingrained in the glove's leather palm, that used to romantically announce that the mitt was a major league model.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Baseball mitts used to come with an ingrained autograph in the glove’s leather palm to romantically announce that it was a major league model. That trend is over due to changing tastes and economics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a warm March afternoon at a Modell's Sporting Goods store on Manhattan's Upper East Side, 39-year-old Angel Valez was, appropriately enough, in a baseball frame of mind.</p>
        <p>He scanned the aisles of the store, looking for the perfect size and color for the glove he planned on purchasing for himself so he could play catch with his 10-year-old son. But as he tested various gloves, and pounded his fist into any number of leather pockets, he did not notice that something from his childhood was missing -- the player autograph, ingrained in the glove's leather palm, that used to romantically announce that the mitt was a major league model.</p>
        <p>These days, most of those autographs are gone, a reflection of changing tastes and economics.</p>
        <p>When Valez was growing old enough to own a glove in the late 1970s, about 70 percent of the gloves on the market came with a major league player's autograph, said Joe Phillips, the editor of The Glove Collector, an online (www.glovecollector.com) and printed newsletter.</p>
        <p>Now, he said, about 80 percent of the gloves on the market lack the signature of a Jim Edmonds or a Derek Jeter. Only lower-end gloves intended for use by younger children still have autographs. For the most part, all people are on their own, free to pick a glove because they like it and not, perhaps, because of the name written on it. Autographs first appeared on gloves when Babe Ruth and Ty Cobb signed their first endorsement deals roughly 90 years ago and had remained a fairly consistent marketing tool through the early 1980s, Phillips said.</p>
        <p>But at that point, he said, the licensing fees for a player's autograph became prohibitively expensive and the number of gloves with autographs dropped to a little more than 50 percent through the mid-1990s.</p>
        <p>And in the last decade, he said, the percentage has continued to decline.</p>
        <p>Denny Whiteside, a project engineer in research and development at the St. Louis headquarters of Rawlings, the sporting goods manufacturer, said that market research in recent years indicated that autographs had little impact on why a person would buy a glove, and could actually hurt sales. The consumer wanted the best-quality glove, not a signature.</p>
        <p>''As kids got older they wanted a glove that looked just like Derek Jeter's glove, but didn't want anyone's name on it,'' Whiteside said. ''Autographs began to be looked at as a negative, not a positive.''</p>
        <p>Trying to follow demand, Rawlings and other glove manufacturers began to design more and more gloves for teenagers and adults that were without signatures. The one exception, Whiteside said, were the gloves for children under 12, for whom a glove autographed by Jeter still might mean something.</p>
        <p>''It used to mean something to me,'' said Adam Copeland, a 15-year-old high school baseball player from the Upper East Side, who was shopping in the Modell's store. ''I used to think they were real autographs. Now it is about the feel and the material.''</p>
        <p>Copeland does not have a player autograph on his glove and said only a handful of his teammates at the Trinity School still did. Those that do are not teased, Copeland said, but they are not envied, either.</p>
        <p>In any case, it is not only the changing tastes of customers that have diminished an old baseball staple. The expansion of regional sporting good stores, like Modell's, has also had an impact.</p>
        <p>Tom DeSimone is a baseball buyer for Modell's, which until the late 1990s was primarily based in the New York area. He said he currently buys gloves for stores from New Hampshire to Virginia and finds it too difficult to match specific players to specific markets.</p>
        <p>''It's easiest to just have a few low-end gloves with a couple of stamped autographs and call it a day because we have so many more stores nationally now,'' DeSimone said. An Alex Rodriguez autograph on a high-quality glove ''only gives a kid in New England more of an excuse not to buy the glove,'' he added.</p>
        <p>''Why am I going to worry about all these different signatures on gloves?'' he said. ''They don't add anything, they don't help sell more gloves, and they cost more.''</p>
        <p>Although DeSimone said that there were indeed fewer and fewer gloves for sale with major league signatures, his best-selling glove is actually a relatively inexpensive $29.99 Derek Jeter model intended for children under 12.</p>
        <p>Those are the people, young as they are, who still seem drawn to the old-fashioned autograph. After all, they are the ones who are most at liberty to make believe, to stand on the field and look at the signature in their glove, and to then imagine they are a major leaguer. And years from now, they will probably remember that signature, just as Valez did on that warm day in Modell's.</p>
        <p>Asked about his first glove as a child, Valez recalled that it carried the autograph of Don Gullett, then with the Yankees. ''He was my favorite because of that,'' Valez said. ''When I lost it, I was devastated.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL PREVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
