<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What's In Store</title>
    <meta content="04talk.moroso.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="T: Design Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="86" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Style; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/style/tmagazine/04talk.moroso.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837079"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="The Talk"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Textiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Textiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Furniture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EEDA1230F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="556" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What's In Store</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">What’s in Store</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Melissa Feldman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Feldman, Melissa</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the design world's more glamorous partnerships will make its debut next month when Moroso at Moss opens its doors at 146 Greene Street. Moroso is a cutting-edge Italian furniture label, and Moss, of course, is New York's design mecca. The 3,800-square-foot store, which was designed by the Spanish-born architect Patricia Urquiola, will take over Murray Moss's original space, which opened in 1994 and subsequently expanded northward to two additional storefronts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Melissa Feldman tracks New York’s newest retail collaboration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of the design world's more glamorous partnerships will make its debut next month when Moroso at Moss opens its doors at 146 Greene Street. Moroso is a cutting-edge Italian furniture label, and Moss, of course, is New York's design mecca. The 3,800-square-foot store, which was designed by the Spanish-born architect Patricia Urquiola, will take over Murray Moss's original space, which opened in 1994 and subsequently expanded northward to two additional storefronts.</p>
        <p>The new store will be Moroso's premier retail outlet, showcasing the company's designs to the public and offering a to-the-trade component. It will also sell the entire line of Maharam, the inventive New York textile manufacturer.</p>
        <p>The letter ''M'' isn't the only link these three collaborators share. Over a succession of meetings and meals in New York and Milan, Murray Moss, his partner, Franklin Getchell, and Patrizia Moroso, the creative director of Moroso, agreed that they wanted to expand their businesses in an unorthodox partnership. After 13 years, Moss wanted to create a dialogue with like-minded people in the design world. Moroso fit the bill -- ''Patrizia Moroso is fearless,'' he says, and ''treats the company like a laboratory, with no agenda'' -- and so did Maharam.</p>
        <p>Both brands are idiosyncratic, entrepreneurial and family-owned. Under the direction of Patrizia Moroso, the daughter of the couple who founded the company in 1952, Moroso has become a style arbiter, corralling international design innovators like Urquiola, Ron Arad and Tord Boontje. (This month in Milan, the manufacturer will showcase Bent, a collection of brightly colored geometric outdoor furniture by Christophe de la Fontaine and Stefan Diez, as well as a daybed covered in hand embroidery from India by the design duo Doshi Levien.)</p>
        <p>Maharam, whose fabrics will adorn walls as well as cover Moroso furnishings in the new store, is now run by its founding family's fourth generation. It is known for its technical innovation and its unexpected collaborations -- the illustrator and author Maira Kalman and the fashion designer Paul Smith have both worked with Maharam, as have companies like Nike and Design Within Reach. Plans are also in the works for a new luxury line of fabrics for the home, and the Maharam+ accessories line, which will be available in August, will include items by design stars like Jasper Morrison, Konstantin Grcic, Hella Jongerius and Luisa Cevese.</p>
        <p>Urquiola, who has been a Moroso collaborator and muse for the last seven years, working on product display and furniture design, faces the challenge of satisfying several design masters at once in the new space, her first retail project in the United States. Of the store, she says, ''It is not my intention to make a box that overshadows the product,'' and describes her design as linear, with platforms and walls covered in mirrored and transparent glass surfaces. She speaks about Moss as the ''genius loci'' of the place. ''The frame is Moss, the content is Moroso, and Maharam will complement the presentation, as part of the skin,'' she explains.</p>
        <p>Urquiola is gifted in the art of collaboration. She has worked with both the legendary Vico Magistretti and Achille Castiglioni, installing an exhibition at the renowned Milan furniture store De Padova. Urquiola recalled an expression that Castiglioni used: ''Creativity is like jam, and the industry is like bread. You get the best taste out of the two together.''</p>
        <p>The Talk</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
