<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Invasor Wins in Dubai at Site of Only Loss</title>
    <meta content="01dubai" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/sports/othersports/01dubai.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837431"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/United Arab Emirates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/United Arab Emirates/Dubai</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Dubai</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Drape, Joe</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E1DD1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="690" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Invasor Wins in Dubai at Site of Only Loss</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Invasor Wins in Dubai on Site of His Only Loss</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>DUBAI, United Arab Emirates, March 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The world's richest race was supposed to be a showdown between brothers on their home racetrack Saturday. Sheik Mohammed bin Rashid al-Maktoum, the ruler of Dubai, had the undefeated Discreet Cat while Sheik Hamdan had America's 2006 Horse of the Year, Invasor.</p>
        <p>The brothers showed up, but only one of their horses did. While Discreet Cat broke last and stayed there for most of the mile-and-a-quarter route, Invasor proved that he was the most dominant horse on the planet with a two-length victory in the $6 million Dubai World Cup that was as emphatic as it appeared effortless.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Invasor proved that he was the most dominant horse on the planet with a two-length victory in the $6 million Dubai World Cup that was as emphatic as it appeared effortless.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The world's richest race was supposed to be a showdown between brothers on their home racetrack Saturday. Sheik Mohammed bin Rashid al-Maktoum, the ruler of Dubai, had the undefeated Discreet Cat while Sheik Hamdan had America's 2006 Horse of the Year, Invasor.</p>
        <p>The brothers showed up, but only one of their horses did. While Discreet Cat broke last and stayed there for most of the mile-and-a-quarter route, Invasor proved that he was the most dominant horse on the planet with a two-length victory in the $6 million Dubai World Cup that was as emphatic as it appeared effortless.</p>
        <p>It capped a colorful evening of world-class racing here at Nad Al Sheba, and a tremendous year for Invasor and his New York-based jockey and trainer, Fernando Jara and Kiaran McLaughlin.</p>
        <p>Exactly 360 days ago on this racetrack, Invasor lost his only race in 11 starts to Discreet Cat in the U.A.E. Derby. Invasor, the son of Candy Stripes, responded by running off with five consecutive Grade I victories, including the Breeders' Cup Classic.</p>
        <p>For McLaughlin, Invasor's victory meant more than the $3.6 million first-place check. It was a way to pay back Sheik Hamdan. They met in the mid-1990s when McLaughlin came here as a young trainer looking for a break.</p>
        <p>''What do you give a man who has everything?'' McLaughlin said Sheik Hamdan, who inhabits palaces and breeding farms from England to Kentucky. ''You give him this. I spent 10 great years here, and the whole family were great people and great sportsmen.''</p>
        <p>While the outcome of the race was not really in doubt, a horse owned by another family of Arab royalty, Premium Tap, forced Jara and Invasor to run every step of the way. King Abdullah of Saudi Arabia bought the son of Pleasant Tap last fall, after he finished third behind Invasor in the Breeders' Cup Classic.</p>
        <p>Then, the king's goals were to capture the Custodian of the Two Holy Mosques Cup, or King's Cup, in his home country. Last night, Kent Desormeaux and Premium Tap tried valiantly to steal the Dubai World Cup.</p>
        <p>Premium Tap, a big bay horse, broke sharply from the gate, and Desormeaux sat icily aboard as he skimmed him along the rail and to a relaxed lead. Behind them, Jara found an easy stride and loomed in third place, and much farther behind him, Discreet Cat spun his wheels.</p>
        <p>His jockey, Frankie Dettori, could not get Discreet Cat into the easy rhythm that had vanquished Invasor here last year and gave him three subsequent victories in New York. When Dettori tried to hustle Discreet Cat as they headed into the final bend here, the colt made a halfhearted burst and then gave up.</p>
        <p>''He didn't stay the distance,'' said the colt's trainer, Saeed bin Suroor. ''We're going to give him a break and cut him back to a mile.''</p>
        <p>When Premium Tap squared his shoulders for the final stretch run, Jara had Invasor ready to uncork a big run. McLaughlin was already heading to the winners' circle.</p>
        <p>''I saw how easy Fernando had him moving at the three-eighths pole and I knew we had plenty of left,'' McLaughlin said.</p>
        <p>Still, Premium Tap refused to crumble. When Invasor drew eyeball to eyeball with his rival, Premium Tap found another gear. They matched strides for about 200 yards before Invasor finally kicked past.</p>
        <p>''We had to fight at the end,'' Jara said. ''But I had too much horse.''</p>
        <p>Before the race, Sheik Mohammed conceded that he wanted very much for Discreet Cat to upset Invasor. He also promised, however, that he would be happy if his brother won the race. Afterward, he was true to his word and presented the World Cup to Sheik Hamdan with a smile.</p>
        <p>They walked off hand-in-hand. Sheik Hamdan did not try to contain his elation. He made it clear that there was no place like home.</p>
        <p>''I am over the moon,'' he said. ''I've had a lot of good horses, but Invasor's one of the top horses that I've owned ever. It was great how he won in America. It's best when he wins here.''</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
