<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Music and Dance</title>
    <meta content="weber.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/books/review/nfweber.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070422T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837009"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Chance and Circumstance: Twenty Years With Cage and Cunningham (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0DD1F31F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1215" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Music and Dance</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Music and Dance</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS FOX WEBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weber, Nicholas Fox</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHANCE AND CIRCUMSTANCE</p>
        <p>Twenty Years With Cage and Cunningham.</p>
        <p>By Carolyn Brown.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 645 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $37.50.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Carolyn Brown offers an insider’s view of the modernist pioneers John Cage and Merce Cunningham.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CHANCE AND CIRCUMSTANCE</p>
        <p>Twenty Years With Cage and Cunningham.</p>
        <p>By Carolyn Brown.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 645 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $37.50.</p>
        <p>CAROLYN BROWN'S rich account of 20 years of dancing with Merce Cunningham and John Cage, ''Chance and Circumstance,'' provides an insider's portrait of two pioneering modernists who ventured into uncharted territory in the realm of dance and music. Brown vividly evokes the thrills and struggles inherent to true liberation, and describes the courage requisite to artistic inventiveness. She is a rare memoirist who focuses on her mentors' physical and spiritual leaps rather than on herself; her guileless revelations illuminate what went right and wrong in Cunningham and Cage's personal dealings, as well as in their fight for survival.</p>
        <p>Brown first saw Cunningham dance when she took a master class with him in 1951 :</p>
        <p>''He was slender and tall, with a long spine, long neck and sloping shoulders; a bit pigeon breasted. There was a lightness of the upper body which contrasted with the solid legs, so beautifully shaped, and the heavy, massive feet.  I remember Merce most clearly demonstrating a fall that began with him rising onto three-quarter point in parallel position, swiftly arching back like a bow as he raised his left arm overhead and sinking quietly to the floor on his left hand, curving his body over his knees, rising on his knees to fall flat out like a priest at the foot of the cross, rolling over quickly and arriving on his feet again in parallel position -- all done with such speed and elegance, suppressed passion and catlike stealth that my imitative dancer's mind was caught short. I could not repeat it. I could only marvel at what I hadn't really seen. His dancing was airborne.  Merce Cunningham had an appetite for dancing that seemed to me then, as it does today, to be his sole reason for living.  He was a strange, disturbing mixture of Greek god, panther and madman.''</p>
        <p>Only another dancer could capture Cunningham's extraordinary physical prowess, dexterity and deliberate emotional abandon. And only someone with Brown's intrinsic personal modesty and generous spirit could be so trenchant about the man who has enchanted but plagued her from then until now.</p>
        <p>The book follows Cunningham's company from its formative years in squalid conditions to glamorous world tours. Unwilling to settle for clichés, Brown questions the notion that Cunningham got his ideas for dance movements by watching people on the street from a high window . She maintains that Cunningham's work has more meaning, and depends less on chance, than he often admitted . Similarly, she does not hesitate to claim that George Balanchine resorted to ''daisy-chain contortionist acrobatics'' and ''girlie-show kitsch'' when choreographing to modern composers like Schoenberg and Ives, teetering on ''the Mickey Mouse-'Fantasia' aesthetic'' in what the public perceives as undisputed masterworks. Right or wrong, Brown writes with the courage and conviction of a true devotee.</p>
        <p>She rounds out the portraits of her characters by depicting them as the children of their parents. John Cage's taste for the unconventional was in his genes. The year Cage was born, 1912 , his father invented a submarine run by a gasoline engine (worthless to the government, since enemy ships could detect its location from the bubbles produced) ; John Milton Cage Sr. also devised an alcohol-based panacea for all woes and patented a wall-size television projection system . However creative Cage Sr. was, though, when his son's ''Suite by Chance'' was first performed in the 1950s , he and Carolyn Brown's father said ''they both made better music in the 'water closet.' '' Cage's and Brown's mothers were offended by electronic blasts that they felt deliberately imitated human wind during a plié; in fact, Brown says, ''the flatulent sound  occurred completely by chance and took Merce (and the composer!) by surprise.'' Brown's parents wept after seeing the large Robert Rauschenberg painting for which her husband had paid $26, believing their son-in-law might be mentally ill . Cunningham's mother, Mayne , appears when the company spends a Thanksgiving holiday in the choreographer's hometown, Centralia, Wash. Mayne brings out Wilhelmina, a floppy lifesize ''girl-doll'' whose shoes are still attached to the larger shoes that young Merce wore when doing a ballroom act with her.</p>
        <p>Brown is on surer ground discussing dance -- her métier -- than painting, where she is an outsider attracted to apparent novelty and too readily prizes theory over craft. She knowingly positions Cunningham in relation to Martha Graham and Antony Tudor , but when she writes about Jasper Johns and Rauschenberg she lacks equivalent perspective, neglecting the pivotal role of Kurt Schwitters and Hans Arp and other predecessors of these American artists who have enjoyed such disproportionate celebrity and absurdly high market values . Brown would have done better to exercise the independence with which she evaluates the big names of dance.</p>
        <p>BUT with her own profession, she provides rare perspective. Brown is forthright about the agony of injuries -- including, in her case, grueling physical pain after a rehearsal in which Cunningham dropped her on her hip, an act she imagined might have been intentional . She also candidly reveals the reality of performing during a heavy menstrual period , needing to wear ''rubber-lined underpants'' for an acrobatic duet and, when they leaked, changing into black practice clothes because their color would not visibly change . If the book provides too many details about flight delays and other transportation problems , its good-heartedness and plethora of interesting information compensate.</p>
        <p>And if you want to learn about the era before name-brand recognition ruled the art world, when creativity was burgeoning and money was incidental, ''Chance and Circumstance''</p>
        <p>is a splendid guide. Existence was precarious, conflicts inevitable, but the pleasures and achievements were sumptuous. In the mid-1960s , when the Cunningham dancers were invited to numerous theaters and festivals in Europe, they could not afford to go, a paltry $5,000 having been their total award from the new National Council on the Arts . Then Joan Miró donated a painting to finance the trip, with the painter Jean-Paul Riopelle also giving a canvas so the dancers could afford to head to France as well as Spain. After Miró's contribution, Clive Barnes wrote in The New York Times, ''Lucky old State Department -- being subsidized by European painters.''</p>
        <p>Miró's and Riopelle's generosity enabled Cunningham's troupe to perform at the Fondation Maeght in southern France . They warmed up in a storage room alongside Calder mobiles and paintings by Léger, Miró and Kandinsky , and danced at midnight in a rain that grew consistently heavier until the lights burst, shattering glass on the stage, and the black floor paint ran in a dance of its own . Meanwhile, ''a galaxy of art-world luminaries'' -- Miró, Riopelle, Max Ernst, Dorothea Tanning, José Luis Sert -- watched enraptured as Cunningham and Brown exploded the boundaries of dance. Cunningham later performed ''Place'' at the Maeght . In this ''primitive incantation,'' he danced a tender duet with Brown, strutted, flailed, leapt, stood rigid, crashed to the floor , and finally thrashed and kicked inside a plastic bag in a finale that was, in the words of the choreographer Kenneth King , ''archly existential, also profoundly and magically mysterious.'' This is the real thing.</p>
        <p>Nicholas Fox Weber's latest book, ''The Clarks of Cooperstown,'' will be published in May.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 22, 2007, Sunday  A review on April 1 about ''Chance and Circumstance: Twenty Years With Cage and Cunningham,'' by Carolyn Brown, misstated the composer of the music for ''Suite by Chance,'' a 1953 Merce Cunningham Dance Company piece. It was Christian Wolff, not John Cage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 22, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>A review on April 1 about ''Chance and Circumstance: Twenty Years With Cage and Cunningham,'' by Carolyn Brown, misstated the composer of the music for ''Suite by Chance,'' a 1953 Merce Cunningham Dance Company piece. It was Christian Wolff, not John Cage.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Nicholas Fox Weber's latest book, ''The Clarks of Cooperstown,'' will be published in May.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
