<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Week Ahead: April 1 - 7</title>
    <meta content="01weekahead" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="0" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/arts/01weekahead.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837479"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E4D61E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2280" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Week Ahead: April 1 - 7</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Week Ahead: April 1 - 7</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FILM  A. O. Scott</p>
        <p>When RAINER WERNER FASSBINDER died of a drug overdose in 1982, he had just turned 37 -- which still seems astonishing a quarter-century later. Part of the shock is the thought of what he might have gone on to accomplish as he matured alongside his baby-boomer colleagues in West Germany and beyond. His generational cohort included Steven Spielberg and Martin Scorsese as well as Werner Herzog and Wim Wenders; if any of their careers had ended when Fassbinder's did, the loss to cinema would have been grievous indeed.</p>
        <p>Even more stunning, though, is just how much he accomplished in so short a time. When it came to writing and directing, he was prolific, even compulsive, as if he knew his time was short. And perhaps for this reason his work has an urgency that has hardly diminished over time. His exhumations of German history -- a politically charged project in the 1960s and '70s -- have a ferocity rarely seen in costume drama, and his inquiries into sex and power are capable of delivering a jolt of discomfort even to jaded eyes that think they've seen it all before.</p>
        <p>An excellent and eclectic sampling of his films will be presented at the Museum of Modern Art starting Monday. Among the highlights are "Lili Marleen" and "Veronika Voss," but the program, called "Fassbinder in the Collection," represents the full range of his films. It also offers audiences a chance to rediscover the enigmatic, occasionally frightening charms of Hanna Schygulla, the great German actress who was Fassbinder's muse, alter ego and fetish object. (212) 708-9400, moma.org.</p>
        <p>THEATER  Ben Brantley</p>
        <p>In the library of bad jokes, there are plenty of responses to the immortal question "How many actors does it take to screw in a light bulb?" (My personal favorite: Five -- one to screw in the bulb and four to say, "I could have done that better.")</p>
        <p>The issue of just how many actors it takes to make a successful play has no comparably snappy answer. But New York audiences will have the chance this week to evaluate the relative merits of double- and single-digit ensembles with the opening of productions from creators famous for bringing bracing new perspectives to their genres: the South African playwright ATHOL FUGARD and the French composers ALAIN BOUBLIL and CLAUDE- MICHEL SCHÖNBERG.</p>
        <p>Mr. Boublil and Mr. Schönberg are the fellows who gave the world a strapping new breed of megamusical -- of epic sweep and steamroller score -- in the 1980s with "Les Misérables" and "Miss Saigon." Two decades later they are hoping to re-establish themselves as the biggest and splashiest on the block with "THE PIRATE QUEEN," a swaggering tale of love, rivalry and stage-sized boats in the 16th century, written in collaboration with Richard Maltby Jr. Frank Galati ("The Grapes of Wrath") oversees a cast of 42 -- count 'em, 42. Hilton Theater, 213 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4100; $51.25 to $111.25.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fugard has always worked on a canvas that seems diminutive by comparison. But his plays, among the first to deal with the moral consequences of apartheid, have consistently shown that big explosions can come in small packages. His greatest works, including "Boseman and Lena," "The Island" and "Blood Knot," have kept the dramatis personae to a potently bare minimum. His new two-character drama, "EXITS AND ENTRANCES," inspired by his relationship with the South African actor Andre Huguenet, opens Wednesday. Stephen Sachs directs Morlan Higgins and William Dennis Hurley in the roles of actor and playwright. 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200, ticketcentral.com; $60.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION  Mike Hale</p>
        <p>Back when it was one of the most overhyped new shows of the season, "30 ROCK" wasn't quite as good as people said it was. The strain of trying to be an alt-sitcom and still attract an audience was too apparent. But as the season went on, and Tina Fey grew more comfortable playing herself, and Alec Baldwin and Jane Krakowski were reliably funny as the preening network executive and the neurotic star, and Jack McBrayer made something brilliant out of the fey NBC page Kenneth, the show got better and better -- and the talk gradually subsided. Then it went away for a few weeks. It returns to the schedule on Thursday (NBC, 8:40 p.m.), and while the writers'-room high jinks are still dull, the plot involving Jack (Mr. Baldwin) using Kenneth as his Mata Hari in a battle with a gay network rival (Will Arnett) is the show at its giggly best.</p>
        <p>Andy Baldwin is a ruggedly handsome Navy lieutenant. He's a doctor (Duke undergrad; University of California, San Francisco, medical school). He's stationed in Honolulu. He's a triathlete. And to make it all just a teensy bit better, the award he won from an endurance-sports group wasn't for his athletic prowess; it was humanitarian of the year. But there's one less-than-perfect thing about this paragon: He's also a reality-TV star. Lieutenant Baldwin wields the roses in "THE BACHELOR: OFFICER AND A GENTLEMAN," which begins Monday (ABC, 9:45 p.m.) with the traditional gathering of the 25 highly made-up bachelorettes, including the de rigueur drunken bachelorette falling down. Best pre-rose-ceremony moment: when one of the women sings the national anthem to the lieutenant. And damned if he doesn't tear up.</p>
        <p>DANCE  Jennifer Dunning</p>
        <p>All dance is influenced to some extent by the artists who perform it. That makes for difficulties in restaging pieces with different dancers, and even calls authorship into question occasionally. (Did George Balanchine really create the unnerving solo that ends his "Episodes," or did Paul Taylor, the man who danced it?) JOHN JASPERSE, a modern-dance choreographer with a gift for poetic insights and visual effects, cuts to the chase in a new piece, "BECKY, JODI AND JOHN," which opens Wednesday at Dance Theater Workshop. It celebrates Becky Hilton, Jodi Melnick and Mr. Jasperse. The three, who will perform the piece, met nearly two decades ago and have remained friends. Mr. Jasperse explores the constancy of their personalities, and the role of dancing, in making their friendship possible. 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077, dtw.org; $25.</p>
        <p>NORA CHIPAUMIRE is a relatively new modern-dance choreographer. Whatever else her new "DARK SWAN" may be, it will be performed by the powerful Ms. Chipaumire on Thursday at the BRICstudio in Brooklyn. Sadly, its theme is more pertinent than ever today. Born in wartime Zimbabwe, Ms. Chipaumire traces the journey of a woman as she loses her country, her family and even her bearings, in a solo inspired by the ballet classic "The Dying Swan" and set to its score, by Saint-Saëns. The performance is part of 651 Arts's "Choreography in Development" series. 57 Rockwell Place, next to the BAM Harvey Theater, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4181, 651arts.org; $5.</p>
        <p>And for bittersweet laughter, there is LARRY KEIGWIN at Symphony Space. Mr. Keigwin and his company will explore the ways gender can be "bent, stretched, inverted, converted and manipulated" to enhance self-scrutiny, with humor. Thursday through Saturday, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, larrykeigwin.com;$21, $25 on the day of the show.</p>
        <p>CLASSICAL  Anne Midgette</p>
        <p>The METROPOLITAN OPERA will celebrate its 40th anniversary at Lincoln Center with ANNA NETREBKO and ROLANDO VILLAZÓN, the so-called love couple (at least onstage), who will appear in a gala of fully staged acts from "La Bohème," "Manon" and "L'Elisir d'Amore," along with the veteran bass Samuel Ramey and the rising baritone Mariusz Kwiecien. And there are still tickets available, from $250 to $1,250. Tuesday at 7 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org.</p>
        <p>Across the plaza City Opera is preparing a treat: a reprise of its 2003 production of Handel's "FLAVIO" by Chas Rader-Shieber. It's a bright, antic production that brings a delightful touch of zaniness to an opera that is by turns madcap and sober. It is also the company debut of Gerald Thompson, a countertenor who has been garnering rave reviews and who will go over to the Met at month's end to make his debut there in "Giulio Cesare." Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., Friday at 8 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nycopera.com; $25 to $125.</p>
        <p>Hugo Wolf's songs are often found in small dollops on recital programs, but there are not many chances to hear his "Spanisches Liederbuch" in its entirety. To conclude the Austrian Cultural Forum's "WOLFIADE," a three-part concert series with the baritone Wolfgang Holzmair, Susanna Phillips (a soprano) and Hermine Haselböck (a mezzo) will join the bill for a free concert at Weill Recital Hall on Thursday. This one should be well worth hearing. Mr. Holzmair has also led six selected singers through a set of master classes focused on Wolf; the results can be heard in a recital on Wednesday at the Austrian Cultural Forum itself. Master class, Wednesday at 8 p.m., Austrian Cultural Forum, 11 East 52nd Street, Manhattan; recital, Thursday at 8 p.m., Weill Recital Hall, Carnegie Hall. Free, but reservations are required: (212) 319-5300, acfny.org.</p>
        <p>Finally, one of the week's most interesting and wacky recitals takes place on Sunday night at Zankel Hall, where Pierre-Laurent Aimard, the ever more respected pianist, conducts a personal tour of the history of his instrument in a dazzling array of short pieces by 29 composers, from Scarlatti and Bach through Carter and Kurtag. Don't miss it. At 7:30 p.m., Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $40 to $48.</p>
        <p>POP  Jon Pareles</p>
        <p>KOKO TAYLOR, who comes to the B. B. King Blues Club on Friday, has always been a strong woman, the Chicago blues belter who treated the battle of the sexes like an all-out brawl. She has the classic blues pedigree: Born in 1935 near Memphis, she grew up working on a sharecropper's farm before heading for Chicago as a teenager and making her name in the blues. With her gutsy, leathery voice Ms. Taylor turned macho men's songs like "Wang Dang Doodle" into her own rough and ready testimonies, and she answered boasts like Muddy Waters's "Mannish Boy" with her own "I'm a Woman," vowing, "I'm an earthshaker." No one denied it.</p>
        <p>In 2003 Ms. Taylor had a medical crisis. After emergency surgery for gastrointestinal bleeding, she wound up unable to breathe, on a ventilator in intensive care. For some time it was uncertain whether she would sing again. But she pulled through, and her first new album since 2000, "Old School" (Alligator), tears into its blues with a vengeance. The album includes five new songs of her own -- more than she has written for any of her other albums -- and revives hardheaded lesser-known songs from Willie Dixon, Magic Sam, Memphis Minnie and others. "You don't want to tangle with me," Ms. Taylor sings in "You Ain't Worth a Good Woman."</p>
        <p>Through the years Ms. Taylor has sometimes simply blustered through songs. On "Old School" she's more nuanced and strategic, working her way up before unleashing a rasp. It's a lean, straightforward production -- guitar, piano, bass, drums and an occasional harmonica -- that deliberately looks back to the sound of 1950s and 1960s Chicago blues. Ms. Taylor sounds like she still knows exactly what she wants. Friday, B. B. King Blues Club and Grill, 243 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144. 8 p.m.; $33 in advance, $38 Friday.</p>
        <p>ART  Randy Kennedy</p>
        <p>Just as the little green buds emerge in the spring, so do the AUDUBONS at the NEW-YORK HISTORICAL SOCIETY, which has the world's largest collection of that artist's work. For the third year now the society is making a rite of displaying a selection of 40 fragile watercolors from the 435 that Audubon used for his masterwork volumes, "The Birds of America."</p>
        <p>The newest batch, which went on view Friday, have been taken from protective storage, where they are kept away from light for years at a time. Alongside the watercolors, the society will also display documents and other historical materials. (Previous exhibitions have included stuffed birds and even Audubon's muzzle-loading shotgun, which he used to ensure that many of his elusive subjects stayed quite still while he was painting them.) The museum's Web site, nyhistory.org, offers a helpful list of birds that migrate through the New York area, including the red-tailed hawk, the great egret and even the turkey vulture, circling high over Manhattan in search of a free lunch. Through May 20, 170 Central Park West, (212) 873-3400.</p>
        <p>The historical society will also dig into its vaults to pull out portraits, landscapes, drawings and prints from its huge collections of work by Asher B. Durand, the Hudson River School master, to complement a major Durand show opening Friday at the Brooklyn Museum. "The World of Asher B. Durand: The Artist in Antebellum New York," April 13 through Sept. 30.</p>
        <p>With landscapes in mind the work of a radically different sort of landscape artist are going on display Saturday in Manhattan, at two locations of the Gagosian Gallery. Works from the mid-1980s by WALTER DE MARIA -- probably best known for "Lightning Field," his solemn grid of steel poles arranged on a remote New Mexico mesquite prairie -- are on display through May 5. "A Computer Which Will Solve Every Problem in the World/3-12 Polygon," a stark, rhythmic floor arrangement of 75 polygonal bars, is at 522 West 21st Street, and "13, 14, 15 Meter Rows," a similar meditation on matter and mathematical progression, is at 555 West 24th Street. The work of Mr. De Maria, who has spoken of the "strangeness of the meaning of geometry," brings to mind natural mysticism in the mold of Pythagoras and numerology. But he cautions against easy interpretation: "Every good work should have at least 10 meanings."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FILM  A. O. Scott</p>
        <p>When RAINER WERNER FASSBINDER died of a drug overdose in 1982, he had just turned 37 -- which still seems astonishing a quarter-century later. Part of the shock is the thought of what he might have gone on to accomplish as he matured alongside his baby-boomer colleagues in West Germany and beyond. His generational cohort included Steven Spielberg and Martin Scorsese as well as Werner Herzog and Wim Wenders; if any of their careers had ended when Fassbinder's did, the loss to cinema would have been grievous indeed.</p>
        <p>Even more stunning, though, is just how much he accomplished in so short a time. When it came to writing and directing, he was prolific, even compulsive, as if he knew his time was short. And perhaps for this reason his work has an urgency that has hardly diminished over time. His exhumations of German history -- a politically charged project in the 1960s and '70s -- have a ferocity rarely seen in costume drama, and his inquiries into sex and power are capable of delivering a jolt of discomfort even to jaded eyes that think they've seen it all before.</p>
        <p>An excellent and eclectic sampling of his films will be presented at the Museum of Modern Art starting Monday. Among the highlights are "Lili Marleen" and "Veronika Voss," but the program, called "Fassbinder in the Collection," represents the full range of his films. It also offers audiences a chance to rediscover the enigmatic, occasionally frightening charms of Hanna Schygulla, the great German actress who was Fassbinder's muse, alter ego and fetish object. (212) 708-9400, moma.org.</p>
        <p>THEATER  Ben Brantley</p>
        <p>In the library of bad jokes, there are plenty of responses to the immortal question "How many actors does it take to screw in a light bulb?" (My personal favorite: Five -- one to screw in the bulb and four to say, "I could have done that better.")</p>
        <p>The issue of just how many actors it takes to make a successful play has no comparably snappy answer. But New York audiences will have the chance this week to evaluate the relative merits of double- and single-digit ensembles with the opening of productions from creators famous for bringing bracing new perspectives to their genres: the South African playwright ATHOL FUGARD and the French composers ALAIN BOUBLIL and CLAUDE- MICHEL SCHÖNBERG.</p>
        <p>Mr. Boublil and Mr. Schönberg are the fellows who gave the world a strapping new breed of megamusical -- of epic sweep and steamroller score -- in the 1980s with "Les Misérables" and "Miss Saigon." Two decades later they are hoping to re-establish themselves as the biggest and splashiest on the block with "THE PIRATE QUEEN," a swaggering tale of love, rivalry and stage-sized boats in the 16th century, written in collaboration with Richard Maltby Jr. Frank Galati ("The Grapes of Wrath") oversees a cast of 42 -- count 'em, 42. Hilton Theater, 213 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4100; $51.25 to $111.25.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fugard has always worked on a canvas that seems diminutive by comparison. But his plays, among the first to deal with the moral consequences of apartheid, have consistently shown that big explosions can come in small packages. His greatest works, including "Boseman and Lena," "The Island" and "Blood Knot," have kept the dramatis personae to a potently bare minimum. His new two-character drama, "EXITS AND ENTRANCES," inspired by his relationship with the South African actor Andre Huguenet, opens Wednesday. Stephen Sachs directs Morlan Higgins and William Dennis Hurley in the roles of actor and playwright. 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200, ticketcentral.com; $60.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION  Mike Hale</p>
        <p>Back when it was one of the most overhyped new shows of the season, "30 ROCK" wasn't quite as good as people said it was. The strain of trying to be an alt-sitcom and still attract an audience was too apparent. But as the season went on, and Tina Fey grew more comfortable playing herself, and Alec Baldwin and Jane Krakowski were reliably funny as the preening network executive and the neurotic star, and Jack McBrayer made something brilliant out of the fey NBC page Kenneth, the show got better and better -- and the talk gradually subsided. Then it went away for a few weeks. It returns to the schedule on Thursday (NBC, 8:40 p.m.), and while the writers'-room high jinks are still dull, the plot involving Jack (Mr. Baldwin) using Kenneth as his Mata Hari in a battle with a gay network rival (Will Arnett) is the show at its giggly best.</p>
        <p>Andy Baldwin is a ruggedly handsome Navy lieutenant. He's a doctor (Duke undergrad; University of California, San Francisco, medical school). He's stationed in Honolulu. He's a triathlete. And to make it all just a teensy bit better, the award he won from an endurance-sports group wasn't for his athletic prowess; it was humanitarian of the year. But there's one less-than-perfect thing about this paragon: He's also a reality-TV star. Lieutenant Baldwin wields the roses in "THE BACHELOR: OFFICER AND A GENTLEMAN," which begins Monday (ABC, 9:45 p.m.) with the traditional gathering of the 25 highly made-up bachelorettes, including the de rigueur drunken bachelorette falling down. Best pre-rose-ceremony moment: when one of the women sings the national anthem to the lieutenant. And damned if he doesn't tear up.</p>
        <p>DANCE  Jennifer Dunning</p>
        <p>All dance is influenced to some extent by the artists who perform it. That makes for difficulties in restaging pieces with different dancers, and even calls authorship into question occasionally. (Did George Balanchine really create the unnerving solo that ends his "Episodes," or did Paul Taylor, the man who danced it?) JOHN JASPERSE, a modern-dance choreographer with a gift for poetic insights and visual effects, cuts to the chase in a new piece, "BECKY, JODI AND JOHN," which opens Wednesday at Dance Theater Workshop. It celebrates Becky Hilton, Jodi Melnick and Mr. Jasperse. The three, who will perform the piece, met nearly two decades ago and have remained friends. Mr. Jasperse explores the constancy of their personalities, and the role of dancing, in making their friendship possible. 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077, dtw.org; $25.</p>
        <p>NORA CHIPAUMIRE is a relatively new modern-dance choreographer. Whatever else her new "DARK SWAN" may be, it will be performed by the powerful Ms. Chipaumire on Thursday at the BRICstudio in Brooklyn. Sadly, its theme is more pertinent than ever today. Born in wartime Zimbabwe, Ms. Chipaumire traces the journey of a woman as she loses her country, her family and even her bearings, in a solo inspired by the ballet classic "The Dying Swan" and set to its score, by Saint-Saëns. The performance is part of 651 Arts's "Choreography in Development" series. 57 Rockwell Place, next to the BAM Harvey Theater, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4181, 651arts.org; $5.</p>
        <p>And for bittersweet laughter, there is LARRY KEIGWIN at Symphony Space. Mr. Keigwin and his company will explore the ways gender can be "bent, stretched, inverted, converted and manipulated" to enhance self-scrutiny, with humor. Thursday through Saturday, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, larrykeigwin.com;$21, $25 on the day of the show.</p>
        <p>CLASSICAL  Anne Midgette</p>
        <p>The METROPOLITAN OPERA will celebrate its 40th anniversary at Lincoln Center with ANNA NETREBKO and ROLANDO VILLAZÓN, the so-called love couple (at least onstage), who will appear in a gala of fully staged acts from "La Bohème," "Manon" and "L'Elisir d'Amore," along with the veteran bass Samuel Ramey and the rising baritone Mariusz Kwiecien. And there are still tickets available, from $250 to $1,250. Tuesday at 7 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org.</p>
        <p>Across the plaza City Opera is preparing a treat: a reprise of its 2003 production of Handel's "FLAVIO" by Chas Rader-Shieber. It's a bright, antic production that brings a delightful touch of zaniness to an opera that is by turns madcap and sober. It is also the company debut of Gerald Thompson, a countertenor who has been garnering rave reviews and who will go over to the Met at month's end to make his debut there in "Giulio Cesare." Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., Friday at 8 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nycopera.com; $25 to $125.</p>
        <p>Hugo Wolf's songs are often found in small dollops on recital programs, but there are not many chances to hear his "Spanisches Liederbuch" in its entirety. To conclude the Austrian Cultural Forum's "WOLFIADE," a three-part concert series with the baritone Wolfgang Holzmair, Susanna Phillips (a soprano) and Hermine Haselböck (a mezzo) will join the bill for a free concert at Weill Recital Hall on Thursday. This one should be well worth hearing. Mr. Holzmair has also led six selected singers through a set of master classes focused on Wolf; the results can be heard in a recital on Wednesday at the Austrian Cultural Forum itself. Master class, Wednesday at 8 p.m., Austrian Cultural Forum, 11 East 52nd Street, Manhattan; recital, Thursday at 8 p.m., Weill Recital Hall, Carnegie Hall. Free, but reservations are required: (212) 319-5300, acfny.org.</p>
        <p>Finally, one of the week's most interesting and wacky recitals takes place on Sunday night at Zankel Hall, where Pierre-Laurent Aimard, the ever more respected pianist, conducts a personal tour of the history of his instrument in a dazzling array of short pieces by 29 composers, from Scarlatti and Bach through Carter and Kurtag. Don't miss it. At 7:30 p.m., Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $40 to $48.</p>
        <p>POP  Jon Pareles</p>
        <p>KOKO TAYLOR, who comes to the B. B. King Blues Club on Friday, has always been a strong woman, the Chicago blues belter who treated the battle of the sexes like an all-out brawl. She has the classic blues pedigree: Born in 1935 near Memphis, she grew up working on a sharecropper's farm before heading for Chicago as a teenager and making her name in the blues. With her gutsy, leathery voice Ms. Taylor turned macho men's songs like "Wang Dang Doodle" into her own rough and ready testimonies, and she answered boasts like Muddy Waters's "Mannish Boy" with her own "I'm a Woman," vowing, "I'm an earthshaker." No one denied it.</p>
        <p>In 2003 Ms. Taylor had a medical crisis. After emergency surgery for gastrointestinal bleeding, she wound up unable to breathe, on a ventilator in intensive care. For some time it was uncertain whether she would sing again. But she pulled through, and her first new album since 2000, "Old School" (Alligator), tears into its blues with a vengeance. The album includes five new songs of her own -- more than she has written for any of her other albums -- and revives hardheaded lesser-known songs from Willie Dixon, Magic Sam, Memphis Minnie and others. "You don't want to tangle with me," Ms. Taylor sings in "You Ain't Worth a Good Woman."</p>
        <p>Through the years Ms. Taylor has sometimes simply blustered through songs. On "Old School" she's more nuanced and strategic, working her way up before unleashing a rasp. It's a lean, straightforward production -- guitar, piano, bass, drums and an occasional harmonica -- that deliberately looks back to the sound of 1950s and 1960s Chicago blues. Ms. Taylor sounds like she still knows exactly what she wants. Friday, B. B. King Blues Club and Grill, 243 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144. 8 p.m.; $33 in advance, $38 Friday.</p>
        <p>ART  Randy Kennedy</p>
        <p>Just as the little green buds emerge in the spring, so do the AUDUBONS at the NEW-YORK HISTORICAL SOCIETY, which has the world's largest collection of that artist's work. For the third year now the society is making a rite of displaying a selection of 40 fragile watercolors from the 435 that Audubon used for his masterwork volumes, "The Birds of America."</p>
        <p>The newest batch, which went on view Friday, have been taken from protective storage, where they are kept away from light for years at a time. Alongside the watercolors, the society will also display documents and other historical materials. (Previous exhibitions have included stuffed birds and even Audubon's muzzle-loading shotgun, which he used to ensure that many of his elusive subjects stayed quite still while he was painting them.) The museum's Web site, nyhistory.org, offers a helpful list of birds that migrate through the New York area, including the red-tailed hawk, the great egret and even the turkey vulture, circling high over Manhattan in search of a free lunch. Through May 20, 170 Central Park West, (212) 873-3400.</p>
        <p>The historical society will also dig into its vaults to pull out portraits, landscapes, drawings and prints from its huge collections of work by Asher B. Durand, the Hudson River School master, to complement a major Durand show opening Friday at the Brooklyn Museum. "The World of Asher B. Durand: The Artist in Antebellum New York," April 13 through Sept. 30.</p>
        <p>With landscapes in mind the work of a radically different sort of landscape artist are going on display Saturday in Manhattan, at two locations of the Gagosian Gallery. Works from the mid-1980s by WALTER DE MARIA -- probably best known for "Lightning Field," his solemn grid of steel poles arranged on a remote New Mexico mesquite prairie -- are on display through May 5. "A Computer Which Will Solve Every Problem in the World/3-12 Polygon," a stark, rhythmic floor arrangement of 75 polygonal bars, is at 522 West 21st Street, and "13, 14, 15 Meter Rows," a similar meditation on matter and mathematical progression, is at 555 West 24th Street. The work of Mr. De Maria, who has spoken of the "strangeness of the meaning of geometry," brings to mind natural mysticism in the mold of Pythagoras and numerology. But he cautions against easy interpretation: "Every good work should have at least 10 meanings."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
