<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Growing Pains</title>
    <meta content="04talk.brubach.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="T: Design Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="98" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Style; Magazine; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/style/tmagazine/04talk.brubach.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837077"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Biblio File"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EEDA1230F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1444" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Growing Pains</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Growing Pains</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Holly Brubach</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brubach, Holly</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Do you live in a concrete jungle and dream of an Eden of your own making, which you will tend in your spare time on sunny weekends? Do you keep a potted basil plant on the kitchen windowsill and wish that you could grow the lettuce that's on your plate? Do you picture yourself at some time in the distant future lovingly pruning antique rose bushes in riotous bloom or picking peaches from a tree in the backyard of a house that exists only in your dreams? If you answered yes to any of these questions, you may be at risk for Obsessive Gardening Syndrome, a disorder that claims the lives of innumerable Americans each year. Though there is no known cure, prevention is highly effective. Ask your bookseller for a copy of 'The $64 Tomato: How One Man Nearly Lost His Sanity, Spent a Fortune and Endured an Existential Crisis in the Quest for the Perfect Garden'' (Algonquin Books of Chapel Hill), in which William Alexander documents his own worsening symptoms in hilarious detail.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For some people, gardening is no bed of roses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Do you live in a concrete jungle and dream of an Eden of your own making, which you will tend in your spare time on sunny weekends? Do you keep a potted basil plant on the kitchen windowsill and wish that you could grow the lettuce that's on your plate? Do you picture yourself at some time in the distant future lovingly pruning antique rose bushes in riotous bloom or picking peaches from a tree in the backyard of a house that exists only in your dreams? If you answered yes to any of these questions, you may be at risk for Obsessive Gardening Syndrome, a disorder that claims the lives of innumerable Americans each year. Though there is no known cure, prevention is highly effective. Ask your bookseller for a copy of 'The $64 Tomato: How One Man Nearly Lost His Sanity, Spent a Fortune and Endured an Existential Crisis in the Quest for the Perfect Garden'' (Algonquin Books of Chapel Hill), in which William Alexander documents his own worsening symptoms in hilarious detail.</p>
        <p>His ambitions at the outset seem modest enough: a kitchen garden that would yield fresh food for his family and cut flowers throughout the house. But in the course of taming his small plot of earth in the Hudson Valley, Alexander finds himself going mano a mano with Mother Nature, winning the occasional battle in an ultimately futile war. Purslane, quack grass and other weeds proliferate beyond his control and seize more territory with each passing year. A plague of sod webworms picks off his cornstalks, one by one, like an invisible marksman. Japanese beetles attack the roses. Maggots and caterpillars devour the apple harvest.</p>
        <p>And then there's the pesky fauna. ''Never in the history of the North American continent has the deck been more stacked in favor of the beasts,'' he laments. ''Here in the Northeast, as in many parts of the country, herds of deer roam through neighborhoods unmolested, while the kids who used to roam through the neighborhood now sail through cyberspace. Groundhogs build underground networks that put the New York subway system to shame. And just when you've finally secured the perimeter, birds swoop down from the skies.''</p>
        <p>Self-deprecating, remarkably devoid of vanity, Alexander willingly sacrifices our admiration and earns our affection in the bargain. He flaunts the sentimental streak that prompts him to select one variety of apple because it was first discovered ''just miles from our home'' and because it is reputed to have been the favorite apple of his boyhood hero, Thomas Jefferson. He admits to a certain foppish enjoyment of working with his hoe, which makes him feel ''connected not only to the land but also to some of my favorite painters, such as Millet, Seurat and Brueghel.'' He violates his own resolve to raise his apples organically and wrestles with his conscience. He lets his wife have the last word and the last laugh.</p>
        <p>His timing and his delivery are flawless. Introducing an account of his efforts to repel ''Bambi and family'' -- efforts that revolve around an electric fence he writes, ''Before discussing the sometimes grisly details of this battle, I should point out, in the spirit of full disclosure, that I have historically had a poor rapport with animals, all animals: domesticated, wild, just about any kind but grilled.''</p>
        <p>With the wry voice of a narrator who knows better, Alexander paints a comic portrait of himself as a hapless protagonist, going to expensive, labor-intensive extremes in his quixotic pursuit of a hobby that soon overruns his thoughts and his time, and in the end it is this perspective that redeems him -- both in his own life and in the eyes of the reader. In the final chapter, he tallies the cost of growing the heirloom tomato he is eating: $64.</p>
        <p>Alexander's book, as I can attest, is highly effective as a cure for Obsessive Gardening Syndrome, provided that you catch it early, in the fantasy stages. Once land is involved, and after the purchase of equipment, baskets, goatskin gloves and charming little trowels, the disease becomes more pernicious and tenacious. The blissful victims Aurelia C. Scott depicts in ''Otherwise Normal People: Inside the Obsessive and Thorny World of Competitive Rose Gardening' (Algonquin Books of Chapel Hill) are, to put it bluntly, goners. There is no helping the patient who constructs an elaborate carrying case lined with dense foam and wooden racks for transporting roses to conventions, or builds his own power sprayer, or amasses a collection of Waterford crystal trophies.</p>
        <p>Scott interweaves her character sketches with history and statistics, and although this material is interesting enough, one gathers that there's more to the industry's development than her straightforward version acknowledges. It would take an aggressive journalist to get to the bottom of the factions she alludes to only in passing, and Scott seems too well behaved a guest and too polite a listener to embark on an investigation of the Jackson &amp; Perkins hegemony.</p>
        <p>Of the most commercially successful roses, ''Knockout,'' a shrub, is the world's best seller, primarily because it's so easy to grow. ''You don't have to do anything but stick it in the ground and water it,'' one American Rose Society veteran tells Scott. But like most of the members quoted, he disdains anything so low-maintenance and trouble-free.</p>
        <p>The focus is on hybrid teas, which are the only roses eligible to win the top prizes: Queen, King, Princess and Best of Show. It isn't until late in the book that Scott finally gets around to so-called old roses, the kind that William Alexander planted and fell so effusively in love with. ''They are incredibly, almost indescribably, beautiful, a so-beautiful-it-hurts kind of beautiful,'' Alexander writes. ''The roses I'm talking about -- real roses -- are sexy, powerful aphrodisiacs with pink and peach and pale yellow petals that suggest blushing Victorian maidens and sex in the bushes.'' These heirloom roses have retained their pungent fragrance, their blowsy demeanor, their limber stems, while hybrid teas have been manipulated over generations in order to make them tall and ramrod straight, with restrained blooms; most have lost their scent in the process. The ''old rose activists,'' Scott discovers, turn out to be no less passionate than the hybrid-tea zealots; each camp has its own network and its own conventions. The hybrid-tea types, however, seem to be wound a little tighter, with their zero tolerance for happenstance and the idiosyncrasies of nature.</p>
        <p>Because, it seems, just coaxing a spectacular rose out of the ground is not enough. It's when Scott describes the grooming process that the reader begins to realize just how bizarre a subculture this is. ''Grooming roses is more interesting for me than growing roses,'' says John Mattia, a frequent winner and a judge. ''See, I've always loved symmetry. That's what you're looking for when you groom a rose. You move petals to fill in the voids and to make the roses symmetrical.'' Scott inventories the contents of Mattia's kit, among them: a turkey baster for topping off the vases with water, nail scissors to trim uneven petals, small green foam wedges used to hold floppy stems upright in vases, deckle-edged shears to trim leaves whose edges are brown, a shoe mitt to buff the leaves, nail clippers to remove thorns, cosmetic brushes for arranging petals in the required spiral, Q-Tips for inserting between tight petals, to ease them apart. Scott takes us to the San Diego convention center, where the nervous exhibitors set up their presentations, primping the blooms they have gingerly transported, fussing over the placement of the vases, sniping at rivals' entries, and we feel a Christopher Guest movie coming on.</p>
        <p>But what accounts for these advanced cases of obsessive gardening? ''Fulfilling each challenge class requirement offers a chance to display proficiency,'' Scott hypothesizes. ''In lives that are rife with situations beyond our control, such as missing a child's soccer practice owing to an intransigent boss, it's satisfying to get all the steps right.'' Well, maybe. But still. Lots of people miss their kids' soccer practice and manage to take it in stride without planting a few hundred roses, hauling them to far-flung competitions and prizing the petals apart with a Q-Tip. I tend to think that Clarence Rhodes, a longtime champion and one of Scott's main characters, comes closer when he says, ''Everybody has to do something.'' It's just that not everybody has to do something to this extent. If, 20 years from now, I'm not pruning my own antique roses and baking a cobbler with peaches from my own tree, what will I do with all that free time? I'll read books about gardening.</p>
        <p>Biblio File</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
