<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rutgers's Prince Learns Her Share Of Hard Lessons</title>
    <meta content="01araton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/sports/ncaabasketball/01araton.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837430"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Prince, Epiphanny</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Araton, Harvey</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Stringer, C Vivian</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E1DD1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="985" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rutgers's Prince Learns Her Share Of Hard Lessons</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rutgers’s Prince Learns Her Share Of Hard Lessons</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
      <dateline>Cleveland</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>How did it feel, Epiphanny Prince was asked, to make what was essentially the most important stop of the season for a basketball team known as Defend U.?</p>
        <p>She was squeezed into the corner of the Rutgers locker room yesterday, flanked on one side by the showers and the other by a male chaperon from the university's sports information department.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>From scholastic exhibitionist to a participant on the most prestigious stage in American women’s team sports, does the learning curve bend any better than that for Rutgers’ Epiphanny Prince?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>How did it feel, Epiphanny Prince was asked, to make what was essentially the most important stop of the season for a basketball team known as Defend U.?</p>
        <p>She was squeezed into the corner of the Rutgers locker room yesterday, flanked on one side by the showers and the other by a male chaperon from the university's sports information department.</p>
        <p>Actually, Prince acknowledged, her strip of Duke's Wanisha Smith, which precipitated her coast-to-coast dash for the winning basket in Rutgers's Round of 16 takedown of the top-ranked Blue Devils eight days ago, was the result of a blown assignment on defense.</p>
        <p>''I didn't box out, and she got the rebound,'' she said, her awareness and honesty one more example of the compulsory evolutionary process she has undergone in less than one year's time.</p>
        <p>From 113-point wonder to would-be defensive warrior, from scholastic exhibitionist to a participant on the most prestigious stage in American women's team sports. Does the learning curve bend any better than that?</p>
        <p>Tonight at Quicken Loans Arena, the epiphany continues for Epiphanny with Rutgers's national semifinal against Louisiana State , the reward for choosing and eventually embracing the curriculum in Basketball 101 as administered by Coach C. Vivian Stringer.</p>
        <p>''I've had to learn what the game is really about,'' said Prince, a 5-foot-9 guard who arrived at Rutgers this season with a reputation as a scorer and a fighter but not necessarily in the positive sense.</p>
        <p>As her defenders tell it, Prince was, as a high school sophomore at Murry Bergtraum High School in Manhattan, only a bystander to a fight that left a 13-year-old girl with a broken leg and Prince with a court-ordered 15 days of community service. As fair-minded critics judge it, Prince was hardly the most culpable party when she scored 113 points in a 105-point Bergtraum victory against Louis Brandeis last season.</p>
        <p>It was a sustained exercise in chucking and basket hanging that rightfully set off sports ethicists everywhere and left the Bergtraum coach, Ed Grezinsky, to explain what the point of all the points was.</p>
        <p>A year later, back in the spotlight, it shouldn't be Prince's sole responsibility to rationalize why her former coach and would-be teacher failed her so spectacularly. It was inevitable that she would be asked.</p>
        <p>''I don't talk about that,'' she said. ''It's a rule.''</p>
        <p>Then she gave the chaperon -- who, at the moment, was not paying attention, perhaps dreaming of the university's first N.C.A.A. championship in any sport since 1949 (Rutgers's women did win the basketball title in the old Association of Intercollegiate Athletics for Women in 1982) -- a light slap on the knee.</p>
        <p>''One person asked me about the arrest and two about the 113-point game,'' she complained.</p>
        <p>Was Prince listening carefully enough the night before she committed to Rutgers and was advised by Stringer, of all people, not to sign unless she was ready to pay the price?</p>
        <p>It wasn't the arrest or the 113 points -- which Stringer knew reflected more on the coach than the player -- that made her suspicious of Prince. Nor was it that she feared she would be getting a bad person.</p>
        <p>Stringer has been around long enough to make her own judgments. Her take on Prince was, as she said yesterday, ''Very shy, pitifully shy, and just a wonderful, wonderful young lady.''</p>
        <p>One whose experience to that point made her define basketball as a game, as Prince acknowledged yesterday, ''where you just try to outscore your opponent.''</p>
        <p>That may be the case in the often lopsided world of high school ball, but not in Stringer's gymnasium. ''I just want hard-nosed basketball players,'' Stringer said. ''We are blue-collar workers, not silk-suit people. I just didn't know that she was going to be tough enough.''</p>
        <p>It would be a stretch to say that the Scarlet Knights' 2-4 start, which made them an afterthought until they stunned Connecticut in the Big East tournament final, was Prince's fault. Their best player, the junior Matee Ajavon, was rounding into shape after she had a titanium rod inserted to stabilize her left shin. Kia Vaughn, the 6-4 sophomore center, was still in the process of running off enough weight to make her a force and a legitimate threat tonight to L.S.U.'s 6-6 dynamo, Sylvia Fowles.</p>
        <p>Let's just say that Prince's early adjustments were part and parcel to a larger problem that begot a volcanic Stringer eruption, in which the coach said she would no longer wear team colors out of embarrassment, evicted her players from the comforts of their locker room and made them do their own laundry for the better part of a month.</p>
        <p>It was up to the veterans, Ajavon and especially Essence Carson, to make Prince and the younger players understand what the running in practice was for, what the defensive mind-set might eventually yield.</p>
        <p>About Prince in particular, Carson said: ''You don't want to step away just because you think that she may think that she is better than every other player on the team. You communicate and let her know that she is going to have to try to go through some things.''</p>
        <p>Read between the lines, and there is little doubt that some dirty laundry was aired as well as washed, inside the locker room and out. Prince, for her part, said she dutifully handled her load, separating light and colored clothing, the way her mother did it back home, and learning to distinguish between street ball and Stringer ball.</p>
        <p>At Rutgers, she has learned that basketball is not about basket hanging or setting scoring records. She recalled a January game when the opponent, South Florida, was held to 36 points and ''it was like we decided, O.K., we'll do it'' Stringer's way.</p>
        <p>Down and dirty got Rutgers past Duke, out of the Greensboro Regional, and all the way to Cleveland, two victories from cleaning up with its first N.C.A.A. crown.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
