<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Get: In-Store; Picky, Picky</title>
    <meta content="04get.instore.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="T: Design Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="60" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Style; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837054"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E0DA1230F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="593" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Get: In-Store; Picky, Picky</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sandra Ballentine</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From flashlights to egg cups, it's all in the edit at Turpan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From flashlights to egg cups, it's all in the edit at Turpan.</p>
        <p>1. Greg Turpan has more firsts in his files than a patent office. He introduced New Yorkers to Garland ranges, Alessi teapots and Metro shelving in the early 1980s via Turpan Sanders, the SoHo store he owned with David Sanders. In 1993, he created the Calvin Klein Home collection. Eight years later, he and his wife, Katherine, opened Turpan at 55 Main Street in East Hampton, N.Y. The tiny shop was also something of a first, since it showcased contemporary design in a hamlet more associated with timeworn tradition. The Turpans have a new, larger location in Los Angeles, but the original space best reflects their personal approach. You won't find glass cases here. ''We want people -- adults and kids -- to touch things and engage in the experience of the products,'' Turpan says. ''And we make it impossible to have a bad experience.''</p>
        <p>2. A good husband as well as a prescient retailer, Turpan loves shopping for Katherine and often buys her jewelry by David Rees and Ron Andersen of Tenthousandthings. ''Their work isn't only about style, it's about substance,'' he says. ''The manipulation of materials is what great modernism is all about.'' This 18-karat gold and coral necklace is $2,100 at Tenthousandthings, 423 West 14th Street.</p>
        <p>3. The East Hampton shop stocks a smattering of wearable design, including graphic tees by the New York-based designer Rogan Gregory. This one's $62.</p>
        <p>4. Judging by how many hospital flashlights ($15) the store sells each month, there's hardly a local beach house without one.</p>
        <p>5. Alice's looking glass was never as chic as this nickel-plated purse mirror ($115) from the France-based company Arpin. ''It's made with the finest glass available and magnifies seven times with very little distortion.''</p>
        <p>6. Turpan lets function take a back seat to form with a miniature car from Playsam ($45), a modernist toy company based in Sweden. ''Most toys aren't sensitively designed, but this is something a child will love and a design-conscious adult can appreciate.''</p>
        <p>7. The retailer knows that self-respecting eggheads prefer their soft-boiled eggs in a proper vessel, like Holmegaard's heavy glass cup ($24). ''It's all about the ritual,'' he says.</p>
        <p>8. Hamptonites snap up these feather-light Nepalese cashmere scarves ($475) by the Los Angeles-based designer Denis Colomb faster than shingle-style second homes south of the highway.</p>
        <p>9. Turpan takes as much care selecting cotton dish towels for the store as he does cashmere. His favorites come from Bragard, the venerable French chef's uniform maker. ''We like things that cross contexts,'' Turpan says. ''These $12 towels also work well as potholders.''</p>
        <p>10. An architect friend brought him a bundle of Ito-ya pencils ($24 for 12) from Japan, and he was ''mesmerized by their perfection.'' He adds, ''Things you use every day can give so much pleasure; the experience of a pencil can be the same as that of a Porsche.''</p>
        <p>11. Pencil paradigms need model sharpeners, like this Faber-Castell $20 UFO version. ''It feels like you're holding a polished stone. This is really important to me, as I think the way things feel is often overlooked in design.''</p>
        <p>12. At just under 500 square feet, the shop doesn't have a lot of room for furniture. Hans Wegner's steel and rope Flag Halyard chair, from 1950 ($8,500; add $600 for the sheepskin), is one of the few pieces to make the cut. ''It's so different from any other chair,'' Turpan says. ''You lie back in it, and it literally forces you to relax.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
