<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Going Out With a Flurry</title>
    <meta content="01NJArtsNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/01NJArts.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837215"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">James, Randy, Dance Works</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Randy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">La Gorce, Tammy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DEFD91030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="722" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Going Out With a Flurry</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Going Out With a Flurry</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TAMMY LA GORCE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">La Gorce, Tammy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on choreographer Randy James, New Jersey native who started his own Highland Park-based dance troupe, Randy James Dance Works, in 1993; James, who is also university professor, plans to put company on hold after four remaining dates; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INSTEAD of dwelling on his impressive résumé as a choreographer, Randy James likes to talk about his stint dancing onstage in Atlantic City in the 1980s, recalling a sailor-type move called the ''bell kick'' that he worked into productions of ''The Wiz'' and ''Pinocchio.''</p>
        <p>Later Mr. James, a New Jersey native who grew up in New Brunswick, spent eight years as principal dancer with Dan Wagoner's Manhattan-based troupe. Then, in 1993, he started his own company, Randy James Dance Works, based in his home in Highland Park. The group has performed its original repertory in 15 states and overseas, winning choreography fellowships from the New Jersey State Council on the Arts (in 1994 and 2004) and the New Jersey Governor's Award in Arts Education (in 2002).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The choreographer Randy James is putting at least a temporary halt to his company after a series of New Jersey shows.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INSTEAD of dwelling on his impressive résumé as a choreographer, Randy James likes to talk about his stint dancing onstage in Atlantic City in the 1980s, recalling a sailor-type move called the ''bell kick'' that he worked into productions of ''The Wiz'' and ''Pinocchio.''</p>
        <p>Later Mr. James, a New Jersey native who grew up in New Brunswick, spent eight years as principal dancer with Dan Wagoner's Manhattan-based troupe. Then, in 1993, he started his own company, Randy James Dance Works, based in his home in Highland Park. The group has performed its original repertory in 15 states and overseas, winning choreography fellowships from the New Jersey State Council on the Arts (in 1994 and 2004) and the New Jersey Governor's Award in Arts Education (in 2002).</p>
        <p>Now Mr. James plans to put the company on hold, taking what may or may not be a permanent break after four remaining dates -- an April 1 matinee at the Community Theater in Morristown, an April 28 show at Raritan Valley Community College and June 2 and 3 performances at the Two River Theater Company in Red Bank.</p>
        <p>He admits to being a bit burned out. ''I really need a vacation, some time to do nothing if I feel like it,'' he said. ''I haven't had that in 14 years.''</p>
        <p>Mr. James is also a tenured professor of choreography and technique at the Mason Gross School of the Arts at Rutgers University, and he has come to feel that he is stretching himself too thin. ''It's like breaking up with someone,'' he said during a recent rehearsal in New York for the Community Theater date. ''Not that this has been a bad relationship. But everyone needs a break sometimes. Sometimes there's a right time to do it. That doesn't mean it's forever.</p>
        <p>''Some will see this as a door closing, but I see it as many doors opening,'' he said. ''In my nine years at Rutgers, I've never choreographed an original piece on our students. I'd like to do that. I also have deep roots in entertainment dance -- I might return to where I came from and try to choreograph a Broadway musical.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the lean and personable 49-year-old will do his best to communicate something about modern dance.</p>
        <p>At the Raritan Valley Community College and Two River Theater Company shows, his 11-member troupe will present premieres of two still-untitled works -- one at each site. Live music will accompany the Raritan Valley piece, which Mr. James characterized as ''upbeat, lush and full.'' The Two River Theater premiere will be a duet on June 2, followed on June 3 by a performance of ''The Lion, the Witch and the Wardrobe,'' a lively hourlong dance from 1998 that is a popular part of his company's repertory.</p>
        <p>At the all-ages matinee in Morristown, the company will perform three pieces, all rooted in some aspect of Mr. James's idiosyncratic personality.</p>
        <p>''I love dark films with subtitles, but I also love 'Terminator 2.' I love hot dogs, but I was a vegetarian for 22 years,'' he said, in one of many verbal riffs. ''For me, a dance can be about anything, as long as it's very human.''</p>
        <p>The troupe first presented ''Unknown Horizon,'' one of the pieces to be performed in Morristown, in the Cayman Islands in 2002. Mr. James described it as a jazzy, celebratory piece that involves some artful floor-rolling.</p>
        <p>Also on the bill will be ''Blue Waters,'' first performed last fall in Manhattan, which uses music by the Icelandic rock band Sigur Rós to reflect on relationships. And Mr. James calls the Morristown concert-closer ''Susie and Swoozie's Soiree,'' from the company's first season, ''a lively, funny piece based on characters from my life.''</p>
        <p>A lot of those characters probably feel the same way about Mr. James's decision to discontinue his company that Sarah Bumgarner, a 25-year-old troupe member at the rehearsal, does.</p>
        <p>''I'm so sad,'' she said during a break. ''I hope he changes his mind.''</p>
        <p>Randy James Dance Works is scheduled to perform on April 1 at 3 p.m. at the Community Theater in Morristown, April 28 at 8 p.m. at Raritan Valley Community College in North Branch, and June 2 at 7 p.m. and June 3 at 3 p.m. at the Two River Theater Company in Red Bank. Information: www.rjdw.org.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
