<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Reason to Use a Designated Hitter Who Doesn't Hit</title>
    <meta content="01score" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837395"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="KEEPING SCORE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E0DE1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="815" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Reason to Use a Designated Hitter Who Doesn't Hit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN ROSENHECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenheck, Dan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Moneyball'' was supposed to have taught baseball a lesson.</p>
        <p>A 2003 best seller by Michael Lewis, the book recounted how Billy Beane, the general manager of the low-budget Oakland Athletics, won a string of division titles by assembling a roster of inexpensive, unathletic players whose ability to get on base was being undervalued by the market. Although the book riled many baseball traditionalists, it was also considered a watershed, one that would force even the most intransigent franchises to rely on statistical analysis if they hoped to remain competitive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Moneyball'' was supposed to have taught baseball a lesson.</p>
        <p>A 2003 best seller by Michael Lewis, the book recounted how Billy Beane, the general manager of the low-budget Oakland Athletics, won a string of division titles by assembling a roster of inexpensive, unathletic players whose ability to get on base was being undervalued by the market. Although the book riled many baseball traditionalists, it was also considered a watershed, one that would force even the most intransigent franchises to rely on statistical analysis if they hoped to remain competitive.</p>
        <p>But a cursory look around the American League suggests that four years later, not much has changed since the pre-''Moneyball'' era -- at least when it comes to finding a designated hitter.</p>
        <p>Since D.H.s do not have to play the field, in theory they should easily outhit players at every other position. But the production of A.L. first basemen is notably superior on average, and right fielders hit just as well as D.H.s. Some teams use the slot to provide players with partial days off when they are tired, or when they have minor injuries that do not prevent them from hitting, accounting for some of this relative underperformance.</p>
        <p>But a number of teams simply fill the D.H. slot with established veterans who can no longer play the field, calling them ''professional hitters'' even though they can no longer hit professionally.</p>
        <p>Take the Minnesota Twins. Last year they handed 196 D.H. at-bats to 34-year-old Rondell White, who responded with a .194 batting average, a .215 on-base percentage and a .276 slugging percentage. ''What would it have taken to get Rondell White out of the lineup?'' Christina Kahrl of Baseball Prospectus asked.</p>
        <p>This season is likely to offer its own disappointments. The Texas Rangers plan to try out 38-year-old Sammy Sosa as their designated hitter. Sosa took last year off after hitting .221 with a .295 on-base percentage and a .376 slugging percentage in 2005.</p>
        <p>''The Sosa experiment will be fun to watch -- as long as it isn't happening to your team,'' Kahrl said.</p>
        <p>It is one thing to get that type of offense from a shortstop, but quite another from a D.H., with productive options freely available. Scouts and managers are turned off by strikeout-prone, streaky hitters with poor batting averages and gloves of stone, even those whose power and patience make them valuable offensive players.</p>
        <p>An example is the Padres' 31-year-old Russell Branyan, a 6-foot-3 left-hander. In a full season's worth of at-bats -- spread out in part-time roles over the past three seasons -- he has hit 41 home runs and drawn 93 walks. Even though he struck out a stunning 237 times in that span, which would easily set a single-season record, his production was about as valuable as the 2006 hitting of leadoff men such as the Yankees' Johnny Damon or the Mets' José Reyes.</p>
        <p>Players who were productive minor league power hitters like the Pirates' Brad Eldred, the Brewers' Ryan Braun and the Padres' Jack Cust would also probably be above-average major league hitters if given playing time.</p>
        <p>The potential benefits of acquiring such players -- and, conversely, the cost of shunning them -- is substantial. For example, the Seattle Mariners traded a well-regarded prospect to the Washington Nationals this off-season in exchange for the washed-up former second baseman José Vidro, whom they plan to use at D.H. Had they instead acquired Branyan, whom San Diego got last season for two unsung minor leaguers, they probably would have added enough offense to win two or three more games this season, and saved $6.5 million.</p>
        <p>By contrast, the best D.H. signing before last season was, predictably, Beane's. He signed Frank Thomas, a future Hall of Famer recovering from two injury-riddled seasons, to a bargain-basement deal. Thomas delivered with a tremendous season, hitting 39 home runs and driving in 114 runs. He finished fourth in voting for the A.L. most valuable player, and cashed in on his success by signing a two-year, $18 million deal with the Toronto Blue Jays.</p>
        <p>Knowing Beane, one might have expected him to pluck another low-cost slugger off another team's bench or a Class AAA roster for the D.H. role. Instead, he laid out a hefty $8.5 million -- 12 percent of his team's payroll -- for the veteran Mike Piazza. Admittedly, Piazza had an excellent 2006. But his skills have declined much more than Thomas's, and at 38, Piazza is unlikely to provide much more than league-average offense at this stage.</p>
        <p>It is possible Beane sees something in Piazza that most statistical analysts do not. But perhaps even Beane, the hero of ''Moneyball,'' can lose by betting on a ''proven veteran.''</p>
        <p>Boston's David Ortiz and Cleveland's Travis Hafner, two of the most dangerous hitters in the A.L., were picked up off the scrap heap by savvy general managers. Will a new Billy Beane arise to free the likes of Russell Branyan?</p>
        <p>KEEPING SCORE E-mail: keepingscore@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: keepingscore@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
