<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Obama's Online Strategy Seeks Big Bonus From Small Turnout</title>
    <meta content="01obama" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/us/politics/01obama.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837418"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CAMPAIGN '08"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kantor, Jodi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Obama, Barack (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Obama, Barack</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E3DD1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="749" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Obama's Online Strategy Seeks Big Bonus From Small Turnout</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Obama’s Online Strategy Seeks Big Bonus From Small Turnout</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JODI KANTOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kantor, Jodi</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Democratic presidential candidate Barack Obama has promised to run uniquely decentralized campaign using Internet to connect supporters and win new ones; campaign says March 31 'community kickoff' event saw more than 5,000 gatherings of supporters, but campaign's numbers suggest most events suffered from low turnout; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Justin Neely is a dream of a supporter, so committed to Senator Barack Obama's presidential bid that he stayed up until 2 a.m. using the campaign's social networking site the night it went online.</p>
        <p>''I was Customer No. 62 in the Obama store,'' Mr. Neely, a freelance writer in Brooklyn, said proudly as he pointed to the Obama '08 placards and decals piled amid the DVD's, seltzer bottles and fake gorilla head in his apartment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator Barack Obama has promised to run a uniquely decentralized campaign, using the Internet to connect supporters and win new ones.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Justin Neely is a dream of a supporter, so committed to Senator Barack Obama's presidential bid that he stayed up until 2 a.m. using the campaign's social networking site the night it went online.</p>
        <p>''I was Customer No. 62 in the Obama store,'' Mr. Neely, a freelance writer in Brooklyn, said proudly as he pointed to the Obama '08 placards and decals piled amid the DVD's, seltzer bottles and fake gorilla head in his apartment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Neely used that Web site, my.barackobama.com, to invite strangers into his home yesterday for the campaign's nationwide ''community kickoff'' event. He and many others who did so had a lonelier afternoon than they had hoped.</p>
        <p>His first visitors were three video bloggers from brooklynforbarack.org, winding their way on bicycles to all eight house parties scheduled in the borough as part of the event. Two of the visitors videotaped Mr. Neely while a third turned his camera on the first two taping Mr. Neely. But there were no other guests, so the bloggers soon continued on their way.</p>
        <p>Mr. Obama, the Democrat of Illinois who is seeking his party's presidential nomination in 2008, has promised to run a uniquely decentralized campaign, using the Internet to connect supporters and win new ones.</p>
        <p>The gathering at Mr. Neely's apartment was one of the first tests of that ambition, as thousands of supporters simultaneously threw open their doors to strangers they had met through his Web site, along with friends and relatives, to watch Mr. Obama in a live Webcast from Iowa. The event was planned as a final push before yesterday's fund-raising deadline, the first of the presidential race. The campaign Web site reported last night that more than 82,000 individuals had contributed so far.</p>
        <p>''This campaign reflects Senator Obama's experience as a community organizer,'' Bill Burton, a campaign spokesman, said on Friday. ''He shares the belief that change comes by getting people together.''</p>
        <p>By the campaign's count, yesterday's experiment yielded more than 5,000 events like Mr. Neely's open house, with a total turnout of guests in the ''tens of thousands,'' Mr. Burton said. There is no way to know exactly how many people showed up, but the campaign's numbers suggest an average of just a few people per event. As of Friday night, according to my.barackobama.com, many events had not received any RSVP's at all.</p>
        <p>On Friday, the campaign sent event hosts a message from Mr. Obama, asking those with low turnouts not to be discouraged.</p>
        <p>''We couldn't be asking more'' of supporters, Chris Hughes said. Mr. Hughes, 22, is one of the founders of the networking site Facebook.com; he has taken a hiatus from the company to work on my.barackobama.com. ''It's opening up your living room to people you don't know,'' Mr. Hughes said. ''If we had a thousand of these things, we would be in great shape. It turns out we have a lot more than that.''</p>
        <p>By Friday, nearly 200 had signed up for a gathering in Dupont Circle in Washington, while more than 60 had said they would attend one on New York's Lower East Side. Many of the events with strong projected turnouts were to be held in public venues, suggesting that participants might have been more willing to gather in public spots than at the homes of strangers.</p>
        <p>On Friday, Olivia Walker, a Web designer in Atlanta, was expecting more than 100 people at a party that she was holding at a museum. "I wouldn't feel comfortable going to a stranger's house,'' she said, ''and I wouldn't feel comfortable hosting and having people in my home."</p>
        <p>''Size, for what it's worth, is not a good measure of the quality of an event,'' said Zephyr Teachout, who served as director of online organizing for Howard Dean's presidential bid. She said she would rather have many small groups than a few big ones, because in small groups everyone meets each other but at larger events participants can be passive.</p>
        <p>Back at Mr. Neely's apartment in Brooklyn, three guests had arrived by the time the three-inch-high image of the senator appeared on Mr. Neely's laptop screen. Soon the image and sound froze, sending Mr. Neely dashing across the room to cue up another stream. That worked for a while, and then it cut off abruptly. Then the image on the laptop came back to life, but in a segment that had been shown earlier in the hour.</p>
        <p>''That concludes the streaming media portion,'' Mr. Neely said with a shrug.</p>
        <p>CAMPAIGN '08</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
