<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Islanders, With New Goalie, Are Unable to Stop Senators</title>
    <meta content="01isles" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837444"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="N.H.L. ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Ottawa Senators</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6DC1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="832" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Islanders, With New Goalie, Are Unable to Stop Senators</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONDALE, N.Y., March 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Goaltender Rick DiPietro missed his third consecutive game because of a concussion, and the flailing Islanders lost their third in a row, lamely falling to the Ottawa Senators, 5-2, Saturday night at Nassau Coliseum.</p>
        <p>Coach Ted Nolan said that the loss might have been just as bad if DiPietro, who is out indefinitely, was in goal instead of Wade Dubielewicz, who has spent most of the season with the Islanders' farm team in Bridgeport, Conn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Goaltender Rick DiPietro missed his third consecutive game because of a concussion, and the flailing Islanders lost their third in a row, lamely falling to the Ottawa Senators, 5-2, Saturday night at Nassau Coliseum.</p>
        <p>Coach Ted Nolan said that the loss might have been just as bad if DiPietro, who is out indefinitely, was in goal instead of Wade Dubielewicz, who has spent most of the season with the Islanders' farm team in Bridgeport, Conn.</p>
        <p>Ottawa finished with 47 shots in a game the Islanders (36-30-12) had to win to keep pace in the race for the eighth and final playoff spot in the Eastern Conference. The Montreal Canadiens(41-32-6), the eighth-place team, defeated the Buffalo Sabres on Saturday, to move 4 points ahead of the Islanders.</p>
        <p>''Whether Ricky's in or not, that's not the factor right now,'' Nolan said of the loss.</p>
        <p>The factor, he said, was the team's absence of desire. No one can figure out why a team that has won games with guile and hustle suddenly seems unable to muster much of either quality.</p>
        <p>Nolan said of Dubielewicz, ''He was probably the only one who gave us an opportunity.''</p>
        <p>The Senators (47-24-8) defeated the Islanders for the fourth time in four meetings this season by racing past them and pelting Dubielewicz with shots.</p>
        <p>Although he is with the Islanders only because DiPietro is hurt and got the start Saturday because Mike Dunham, DiPietro's backup, gave up five goals in a loss Friday to Buffalo, Dubielewicz said he was disappointed with himself.</p>
        <p>''A guy like me doesn't get too many second chances,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The rest of the Islanders said they did not give Dubielewicz much of a chance. The Senators, chasing home ice for the first round of the playoffs, had the Islanders retreating for most of the night.</p>
        <p>''If you don't play good defense, you're going to hang those guys out to dry,'' Islanders center Mike Sillinger said, nodding to the corner of the locker room where the goaltenders dress.</p>
        <p>The Islanders have four games to play, the first on Tuesday at home against the Rangers. DiPietro, who was injured March 13 in the second period against Montreal, is not certain to play in any of them.</p>
        <p>''It shouldn't matter who's in net,'' Islanders defenseman Brendan Witt said. ''I just don't think we're playing well in this situation.''</p>
        <p>The Islanders failed to score on a four-minute power play early in the first period after Dany Heatley received a double high-sticking penalty. Late in the period, Sillinger received a roughing penalty a minute into an Islanders power play.</p>
        <p>The Islanders charged up the ice but were caught with only one defenseman, Tom Poti, playing back. Ottawa's Jason Spezza started a 2-on-1 rush that ended with defenseman Christoph Schubert scoring his eighth goal, with 20 seconds left in the period.</p>
        <p>The Islanders tied the score, 1-1, at 11 minutes 11 seconds of the second period when Viktor Kozlov slapped in a rebound for his 25th goal. But the tie lasted for only 28 seconds, because the Islanders again became lax on defense.</p>
        <p>Ottawa left wing Peter Schaefer pushed a loose puck out of the Senators' zone to Mike Comrie. Only defenseman Deron Quint was back to cover him, and Comrie danced around him and beat Dubielewicz for his 18th goal.</p>
        <p>Quint was not even supposed to be playing. The Islanders had signed defenseman Todd Simpson on Thursday, but the National Hockey League announced Saturday that it would respect the International Ice Hockey Federation's request that it enforce the German Ice Hockey League's indefinite suspension of Simpson.</p>
        <p>While playing with the Hannover Scorpions, Simpson was penalized for abusing an official in the team's last playoff game. The German League will hold a hearing about the incident Monday, and the N.H.L. will then determine Simpson's status.</p>
        <p>''We've got to work with what we've got,'' Nolan said. ''We've got to have some heart and desire to play this game.''</p>
        <p>CANADIENS 4, SABRES 3 Saku Koivu scored his 20th goal early in the third period, and Michael Ryder got his team-leading 27th in the first as host Montreal hung on to the eighth playoff spot in the Eastern Conference. (AP)</p>
        <p>THRASHERS 3, BRUINS 2 Keith Tkachuk scored the winner with 18.6 seconds left and Kari Lehtonen stopped 25 shots for visiting Atlanta, which can clinch a playoff berth with a victory in any of its last three games. (AP)</p>
        <p>LIGHTNING 5, CAPITALS 2 Vincent Lecavalier scored his 51st goal and had two assists to lead host Tampa Bay, which remained 3 points behind first-place Atlanta in the Southeast Division. Tampa Bay also stayed in sixth place in the Eastern Conference, 1 point ahead of the Rangers. (AP)</p>
        <p>MAPLE LEAFS 5, PENGUINS 4 Tomas Kaberle scored his second goal of the game at 3:55 of overtime and host Toronto stayed in ninth place in the East, a point and a place below Montreal and the playoff cutoff. (AP)</p>
        <p>N.H.L. ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
