<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>She Has a Vision for Montclair State. But Is It the Right One?</title>
    <meta content="01njpeopleNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/01njpeople.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837227"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="EDUCATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Montclair State University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cole, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">holmberg, david</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Montclair State University</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E7D81030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="763" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>She Has a Vision for Montclair State. But Is It the Right One?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">She Has a Vision for Montclair State. But Is It the Right One?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID HOLMBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">holmberg, david</byline>
      <dateline>MONTCLAIR</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Susan Cole, president of Montclair State University, whose ambitious $250 million construction program has been criticized; some faculty members say Cole has emphasized new buildings and research to detriment of 100-year-old university's traditional teaching function; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SUSAN A. COLE, the supercharged president of Montclair State University, took a visitor on a campus tour recently to show off some of the fresh, gleaming buildings constructed during her eight and a half years running New Jersey's second-largest university.</p>
        <p>She pointed out several buildings with a visionary's pride, saying, ''I built that.'' Then she led the way to the top floor of the elegant University Hall, a year-old, seven-story academic building that is the centerpiece of her $250 million construction program.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>MONTCLAIR.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SUSAN A. COLE, the supercharged president of Montclair State University, took a visitor on a campus tour recently to show off some of the fresh, gleaming buildings constructed during her eight and a half years running New Jersey's second-largest university.</p>
        <p>She pointed out several buildings with a visionary's pride, saying, ''I built that.'' Then she led the way to the top floor of the elegant University Hall, a year-old, seven-story academic building that is the centerpiece of her $250 million construction program.</p>
        <p>Through the wraparound windows of a conference room, the skylines of New York and Newark were distant images. Close in was a clear view of the fast-growing north end of the 246-acre campus.</p>
        <p>Dr. Cole pointed out several more landmarks, including a student housing complex at the largely commuter university, a nearly completed recreation center, a New Jersey-type diner and a train station with service to Manhattan.</p>
        <p>In the foreground were two undistinguished buildings that she singled out playfully. ''One of my predecessors had his picture taken in front of one of those ugly buildings,'' Dr. Cole said.</p>
        <p>Montclair State celebrates its 100th anniversary next year, and she is its eighth president. But Dr. Cole -- who is in her 60s but declined to reveal her age -- does not intend to step down any time soon, saying she is a confirmed workaholic, so the word ''retirement'' does not compute.</p>
        <p>Dr. Cole is ''brilliantly opportunistic'' and a ''populist educator with an intense social mission,'' said one of her supporters, Patterson Sims, director of the Montclair Art Museum.</p>
        <p>That description may pass muster with her faculty detractors. They concede her accomplishments while calling her an authoritarian micromanager who has emphasized new buildings and research to the detriment of the university's traditional teaching function.</p>
        <p>Richard Wolfson, a longtime faculty member in the College of Education and Human Services, acknowledged Dr. Cole's ambitious and partly completed agenda, which also includes hiring new faculty members on what one administrator described as ''an aging campus.''</p>
        <p>But Dr. Wolfson, a former president of the University Senate and a leader of the faculty union, said, ''The problem is that I think we've lost our soul along the way.''</p>
        <p>''We've gone from a comprehensive teaching university to a data-driven university,'' Dr. Wolfson said, adding that Montclair State had fallen under the spell of ''the corporatization of American universities.''</p>
        <p>Another critic, Larry Schwartz, who has taught English since 1970 and is a former department chairman, said the Cole administration did not listen to faculty members.</p>
        <p>Dr. Cole, a Brooklyn native but now a self-proclaimed Jersey girl, graduated from Barnard College in 1962 and considered a career in theater. But a professor suggested that she pursue her doctorate, and in 1972 she received her Ph.D in English and American literature from Brandeis University.</p>
        <p>She taught for nine years at the City University of New York before going into administration. Dr. Cole served for 11 years as a vice president for administration at Rutgers University, and after the death of a beloved president and mentor there, she decided her own university presidency could be in the cards.</p>
        <p>In 1993 Dr. Cole became president of Metropolitan State University in Minneapolis-St. Paul, where she said cautious Minnesotans sometimes told her, ''Stop pushing, Susan.''</p>
        <p>Then in 1998 she took the Montclair State job. Her husband, David, a visual artist, died in 2000; her son, Simon, 39, is a professor of criminology and her daughter, Alexa, 35, is a lawyer.</p>
        <p>''I've spent my life trying to provide higher education to people who for most of the country's history did not have access to it,'' Dr. Cole said.</p>
        <p>She said she always envisioned that Montclair State would flourish under her, and enrollment has grown to 16,000 from 13,500. ''The reason I came here was because of the potential,'' she said. ''I didn't come here to take care of a good university but to lead the development of a better one.''</p>
        <p>Responding to Dr. Wolfson and other critics on the corporatization claim, Dr. Cole said that ''their sense of the situation is dead wrong.''</p>
        <p>''This is a teaching university,'' she said, ''and we have not at all moved away from our central mission to be a teaching university.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Cole also rejects the vision of herself as authoritarian. ''I don't view my role as telling everyone what to do,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''I work; that's what I do,'' she said, summing up her high-energy tenure at Montclair State. ''Everything I've done here is for the institution and the faculty. I'm not here for myself, but for the institution.''</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
