<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Contributors</title>
    <meta content="04contributors.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="T: Design Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Style; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837050"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E1DA1230F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="621" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Contributors</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JULIUS SHULMAN</p>
        <p>Born in 1910, Julius Shulman can honestly say that he has seen it all when it comes to 20th-century design. The architecture photographer, who reminisces in this issue about Arne Jacobsen's famous Egg chair (''The Egg and I,'' Page 162), is at work on a three-volume addendum to his 2000 book ''Modernism Rediscovered'' (Taschen), which he will promote with a tour around the world. Shulman shot to fame 60 years ago, photographing the work of mid-century architectural giants like Richard Neutra and Pierre Koenig (center), but he remembers Jacobsen with particular fondness. ''He was special because despite his great talent, he never promoted himself or openly sought attention,'' Shulman says. ''That makes him a true icon.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JULIUS SHULMAN</p>
        <p>Born in 1910, Julius Shulman can honestly say that he has seen it all when it comes to 20th-century design. The architecture photographer, who reminisces in this issue about Arne Jacobsen's famous Egg chair (''The Egg and I,'' Page 162), is at work on a three-volume addendum to his 2000 book ''Modernism Rediscovered'' (Taschen), which he will promote with a tour around the world. Shulman shot to fame 60 years ago, photographing the work of mid-century architectural giants like Richard Neutra and Pierre Koenig (center), but he remembers Jacobsen with particular fondness. ''He was special because despite his great talent, he never promoted himself or openly sought attention,'' Shulman says. ''That makes him a true icon.''</p>
        <p>PATRICK LI</p>
        <p>''More is more, even when you're making something that's simple and subtle,'' says the creative director Patrick Li, who designed this issue's voluminous T (Page 121). ''I wanted to work with an all-white palette, but still give the letter lots of definition.'' Li is the New York editor of Self Service Magazine and a partner in the New York- and Paris-based advertising design studio Work in Progress, which counts among its clients fashion and art heavyweights like Chloé, Barneys and Dia Art Foundation. To keep his ideas bank fresh, Li is constantly restocking his extensive book collection; among his current obsessions are the Japanese illustrator Tadanori Yokoo, the visual artist Eiko Ishioka, the architect Rem Koolhaas (far left) and the German painter Christian Schad (center).</p>
        <p>MONICA KHEMSUROV</p>
        <p>While surveying the Victoria and Albert Museum's ''Surreal Things: Surrealism and Design'' exhibition in London, Monica Khemsurov discovered that fur teacups may not be ideal for everyday use, but they certainly have a place of honor in the history of the decorative arts. ''Nowadays, most environments are calm and minimalist,'' says the I.D. Magazine senior associate editor, who wrote ''Surreality Check'' (Page 74). ''It would be interesting to see more whimsy, done in a modern way.'' Khemsurov is certainly doing her part to banish the mundane: her home décor includes large-scale photographs of industrial machines (far right) and an armless, hairless mannequin of a kneeling girl. ''My current aesthetic is 1960s institutional environments mixed with girly touches,'' she says.</p>
        <p>CHEE PEARLMAN</p>
        <p>''Bertjan Pot has the ability to think with his hands,'' says Chee Pearlman, who profiled the Dutch wunderkind in ''Popular Mechanics'' (Page 142). ''He works on objects over long periods of time, until they are perfect.'' When she's not writing, Pearlman, who was the editor in chief of I.D. Magazine for eight years, curates design exhibitions like ''The Voting Booth Project'' (center) at Manhattan's Parsons the New School for Design and plans conferences like ''Radical Craft'' at Art Center College of Design in Pasadena, Calif. ''I'm very excited by the state of craft now,'' says Pearlman, who counts among her prized possessions a Marcel Wanders hand-painted lamp. ''Especially in Europe, people are using craft in conjunction with high-tech materials and processes.'</p>
        <p>STEFAN BECKMAN</p>
        <p>Creating the '70s-inspired backdrops for this issue's cover story (''Neo Geo,'' Page 136) came naturally to the set designer Stefan Beckman, whose favorite objet is an Ettore Sottsass lamp (far right). ''I was born in the late '60s, so it is an era that I remember from my childhood,'' he says. Beckman worked for a film agent and producer in Los Angeles before moving to New York, where he has created the mise-en-scÃ</p>
        <p>nes for ad campaigns by Prada, Tiffany &amp; Company and Banana Republic, as well as for Marc Jacobs's recent fashion shows (center). But returning to his cinematic roots may be in the cards: Beckman was responsible for the sets in the photographer Carter Smith's short film ''Bugcrush,'' which won a Jury Prize at last year's Sundance Film Festival.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
