<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>IN THE REGION/Westchester; Trying to Preserve an Aging Relic</title>
    <meta content="01wczo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/realestate/01wczo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837425"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="In the Region | Connecticut"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Garages and Service Stations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westport (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Prevost, Lisa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ronemus, Kim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ronemus, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E2DD1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1035" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>IN THE REGION/Westchester; Trying to Preserve an Aging Relic</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Trying to Preserve an Aging Relic</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA PREVOST</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Prevost, Lisa</byline>
      <dateline>WESTPORT</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kim Ronemus and husband Michael have spent last year fighting for approval to restore Westport, Conn, gas station that was built around 1910; couple was backed by local historic preservationists who say Westport is rapidly 'digesting itself' at rate of some 100 tear-downs each year; Kim Ronemus says ultimate victory in long, very expensive battle is that their case has spurred zoning amendments that would make Westport more amenable to historic preservation; photo (In the Region/Connecticut) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE inside of the old filling station at 113 Cross Highway is about as utilitarian as it gets. The cracked concrete floors in the two auto bays, the antiquated furnace shoved into one corner, the office area's blackened work bench fronted by deep metal drawers -- the only adornment in here is dust.</p>
        <p>Yet it's this property's purely functional past that appeals to Kim Ronemus, a graphic designer who lives up the street. This was Westport's first gas station, beginning around 1910, and though autos continued to pull in as late as the 1980s, the 700-square-foot wooden building remained much the same.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A plan to restore an ancient gas station meets resistance in Westport, Conn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE inside of the old filling station at 113 Cross Highway is about as utilitarian as it gets. The cracked concrete floors in the two auto bays, the antiquated furnace shoved into one corner, the office area's blackened work bench fronted by deep metal drawers -- the only adornment in here is dust.</p>
        <p>Yet it's this property's purely functional past that appeals to Kim Ronemus, a graphic designer who lives up the street. This was Westport's first gas station, beginning around 1910, and though autos continued to pull in as late as the 1980s, the 700-square-foot wooden building remained much the same.</p>
        <p>Standing inside, Ms. Ronemus points with delight to the mismatched handles on the drawers, and a mysterious metal pole on the ceiling held in place by what could very well be a twisted coat hanger.</p>
        <p>It's real, a true relic, and, for Ms. Ronemus and her husband, Michael, a worthy investment.</p>
        <p>Ignoring nearly every piece of advice from real estate agents, builders and architects, the couple bought the property a year ago with ambitious plans to restore not only the filling station but also the modest 1820 colonial in front of it, and a surrounding menagerie of six dilapidated outbuildings, including a chicken coop.</p>
        <p>''You just see this property decaying before your eyes, and it's just so sad,'' Ms. Ronemus said, explaining their rationale. As developers began eyeing the 1.7-acre lot, she said, ''finally, I said to my husband, you know, maybe we do have to buy this property.''</p>
        <p>Yet winning approvals for their preservation plan has been an arduous process, as the couple have run up against zoning regulations unadapted to modern development pressures.</p>
        <p>The Ronemuses almost gave up, at one point even applying for demolition permits. But last Tuesday, after turning down their original plans for restoring the property, the Zoning Board of Appeals signed off on a final effort to make the project feasible.</p>
        <p>The ordeal prompted the chairman of the town's Historic District Commission, Morley Boyd, to propose zoning amendments that would make Westport more amenable to historic preservation. If owners as dedicated as the Ronemuses can barely make it through the process, he reasoned, it's time to make a change.</p>
        <p>''Who else would do this?'' Mr. Boyd said. ''Statistically speaking, no one would do what they did. They are a couple who fell passionately in love with the property.''</p>
        <p>Some might say the Ronemuses were crazy to have taken on the project. After paying $965,000 for the property, they had to remove 100 tons of soil contaminated by PCBs.</p>
        <p>In a town that is rapidly ''digesting itself'' at the rate of some 100 teardowns a year, however, saving old properties located outside of protected historic zones is rarely a rational process, Mr. Boyd said. Over the past year, local historic preservationists have tried and failed to save a 150-year-old home up the road known as the Meeker house, and a Modernist house on Minute Man Hill Road designed by the renowned architect Paul Rudolph. Both properties were purchased by builders.</p>
        <p>The situation is so ''desperate,'' Mr. Boyd said, that he, as part of a subcommittee of the Planning and Zoning Commission, is working on new zoning regulations that would grant property owners relief from setback, lot coverage and use restrictions for the purpose of historic or architectural preservation.</p>
        <p>While still a rarity in surrounding suburban communities, regulations that offer similar incentives for historic preservation have been adopted in Wilton and New Canaan and are being considered in Ridgefield, Mr. Boyd said.</p>
        <p>They have been used successfully for years in the city of Stamford, according to Richard Redniss, a land use consultant who helped write the regulations. ''Every community should have these -- they're relatively simple and rarely controversial,'' Mr. Redniss said.</p>
        <p>The Ronemuses knew from the start that their plans for 113 Cross Highway would require several variances from town zoning regulations. Yet after securing support from dozens of neighbors, and encountering no opposition, they figured their chances were good. They worked closely with the Historic District Commission to designate the site as a historic district, with hopes of giving their plans more credibility with the zoning board.</p>
        <p>Their architect, Michael Glynn, drew up plans to convert the gas station into an office for Ms. Ronemus with a small bathroom addition, and to make a 300-square-foot shed into a guest bedroom.</p>
        <p>The 1,800-square-foot main house, which had lost much of its historic detailing during an addition in the 1980s, would be restored and given an L-shaped addition in back.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to restore all of the outbuildings -- all we wanted was permission to use two of them,'' Mr. Glynn said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ronemus said, ''It's the least invasive use of the landscape that I could possibly imagine.''</p>
        <p>In February, however, the Zoning Board of Appeals denied the Ronemuses' request, saying they had failed to show a hardship that warranted expansion of an outbuilding beyond the size allowed by current zoning. Ms. Ronemus could put a desk in the gas station, but any expansion, they said, would have to be done in the form of a basement.</p>
        <p>The couple considered the decision a death knell for their project. Digging a basement could add another $250,000 to an already expensive proposition, Mr. Glynn said, and would require moving a very shaky structure.</p>
        <p>After being assured by the Historic District Commission that, as a result of the zoning board decision, they could make the property more tempting to a possible buyer by tearing down the outbuildings, the Ronemuses applied for demolition permits. They would sell the whole thing.</p>
        <p>Persuaded by Mr. Boyd to give it one more try, however, the couple hired a land-use consultant and followed his advice: they proposed building a separate 300-square-foot structure for the station's bathroom, and connecting it by a breezeway to the filling station. The plan was approved.</p>
        <p>The compromise -- connecting the bathroom by breezeway -- seems ''kind of silly,'' Ms. Ronemus said. But she takes comfort in knowing that their very expensive effort may yield a greater benefit in the form of zoning reform, and hopes the changes come soon rather than later.</p>
        <p>''There isn't much left'' to protect, she said. ''The end is here.''</p>
        <p>In the Region | Connecticut</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
