<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Despite Spitzer's Election Mandate, First Budget Proves a Humbling One</title>
    <meta content="01spitzer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/01spitzer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837459"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEWS ANALYSIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spitzer, Eliot (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Albany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Albany (NY)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Spitzer, Eliot L</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E4DC1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1193" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Despite Spitzer's Election Mandate, First Budget Proves a Humbling One</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Despite Spitzer’s Election Mandate, First Budget Proves a Humbling One</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, Sunday, April 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>News Analysis of concessions Gov Eliot Spitzer had to make to New York State Legislature in order to have budget adopted by April 1 deadline; Legislature added more than $700 million in new spending and put back some of health care spending that Spitzer had fought to cut; Spitzer, who frequently spoke of need to rein in spending during campaign, acknowledges that his first budget is bigger than he would have liked, but says it achieves all three of his main objectives: creating new school aid formula, curbing growth of Medicaid and making sure that more than $1 billion in property tax relief is focused on middle class; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>During his campaign for governor, Eliot Spitzer spoke frequently about the need to rein in state spending and to change the way New York's government works. ''Day 1, Everything Changes'' was his oft-repeated slogan.</p>
        <p>In the last few days, as the poetry of campaigning gave way to the prose of getting a budget passed, Mr. Spitzer, who won his election in a landslide, invoked another phrase: ''Rome wasn't built in a day.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer adopted a new tone after making concessions to get the State Legislature to adopt his budget by the April 1 deadline.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>During his campaign for governor, Eliot Spitzer spoke frequently about the need to rein in state spending and to change the way New York's government works. ''Day 1, Everything Changes'' was his oft-repeated slogan.</p>
        <p>In the last few days, as the poetry of campaigning gave way to the prose of getting a budget passed, Mr. Spitzer, who won his election in a landslide, invoked another phrase: ''Rome wasn't built in a day.''</p>
        <p>The new governor adopted his newly humble tone after he made a number of concessions to get the State Legislature to adopt his budget by the April 1 deadline. Lawmakers returned to the Capitol on Saturday and began passing the $120.9 billion budget -- but last-minute negotiations and delays meant that some of the bills could not be passed until Sunday morning.</p>
        <p>But the spending plan they began passing differed in key respects from the proposal Mr. Spitzer presented made in January.</p>
        <p>The Legislature added more than $700 million in new spending to the governor's proposal, which had already increased spending by more than twice the rate of inflation.</p>
        <p>Lawmakers put back some of the health care spending he had fought to cut. They also blunted some of the impact of his plan to direct most new education spending to New York City and other so-called high-needs districts when they added money for schools on Long Island and in other well-off districts.</p>
        <p>Governor Spitzer acknowledged that his first budget was bigger than he would have liked. But he said that the budget achieves all three of his main objectives: creating a school aid formula that would direct most of a record spending increase to high-needs districts; curbing the growth of Medicaid by nearly $1 billion and directing spending toward patients, not institutions; and making sure that more than $1 billion in property tax relief was focused on the middle class.</p>
        <p>On top of that, the governor won some thorny political battles, including approval of a measure that will double the number of charter schools. Mr. Spitzer said that he would be in a better position to curb spending next year. But if recent history is any guide, the power of governors and mayors to curb spending and push through big changes diminishes after their first year in office.</p>
        <p>When Gov. George E. Pataki took office in 1995, after a close election that no one mistook for a mandate, he faced a $5 billion budget gap. He managed to close the deficit, push through a big income tax cut and actually freeze state spending in his first budget. It was in his later years that Mr. Pataki let budgets balloon.</p>
        <p>Governor Spitzer, by contrast, took office with nearly 70 percent of the vote, a mandate of historic proportions. His main opponents in this year's budget battle, the Senate Republicans, were weakened politically by having lost several seats in recent elections, and by the news that their majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, was being investigated by the Federal Bureau of Investigation over his business dealings.</p>
        <p>It was a dynamic that led lawmakers in both parties, and some political analysts, to say that they had expected Governor Spitzer's first budget to shake things up more.</p>
        <p>''Walking in with a 70 percent majority, it seems like an awful lot of mandate produced a mouse,'' said Douglas A. Muzzio, a professor of public affairs at Baruch College.</p>
        <p>The Legislature, which has grown more powerful than ever in recent years, showed that it was not about to roll over for a new governor, mandate or no.</p>
        <p>Lawmakers even rejected some of Governor Spitzer's pet projects. They gutted a proposal, which he had campaigned on, to make high-speed Internet access available across the state. They rejected his call to require a deposit on cans and bottles of noncarbonated drinks. They blocked his plan to create a commission to study whether some of New York's prisons should close, now that there are fewer inmates.</p>
        <p>During much of the session, Democrats tried to divide or conquer the Republican majority in the State Senate. Mr. Spitzer campaigned heavily in a special Senate election on Long Island that cost the Republicans a seat. Democrats then spoke about trying to get a couple of Republicans to switch parties, which would have given them control. When that failed, there was talk that some individual Republicans might break ranks on the budget vote.</p>
        <p>It did not happen. As a result, the Republicans were able to address many of their concerns, from sending more school aid to Long Island to altering Mr. Spitzer's middle-class property tax break so that some wealthier homeowners could qualify.</p>
        <p>The experience left the Republicans feeling a little cocky.</p>
        <p>After Mr. Bruno was asked on Friday what he had learned about the new governor from their first budget negotiation together, he smiled broadly. ''What have I learned?'' he asked. ''The question is, 'What has he learned?' ''</p>
        <p>Senator Dean G. Skelos, a Nassau County Republican, joined the conversation. ''Didn't a very famous president once say, 'I forgive his youth and inexperience'? '' he said, paraphrasing President Ronald Reagan's quip during a debate with Walter F. Mondale.</p>
        <p>The governor was clearly stung by the criticisms, and particularly by comparisons with his predecessor's first budget.</p>
        <p>At a briefing with reporters on Friday, Mr. Spitzer said that he had been able to enact 73 percent of the Medicaid spending reductions -- nearly a billion dollars -- that he had called for this year. In 1995, he said, Mr. Pataki had been able to get only 17 percent of the Medicaid cuts he called for, or $211 million. (Of course, Mr. Pataki's budget froze spending overall.)</p>
        <p>As the Legislature began approving the first budget bills late Saturday, Governor Spitzer proclaimed victory. His first budget, he noted, would provide heath insurance for the state's 400,000 uninsured children.</p>
        <p>It contains agreements on issues that have eluded Albany's leaders for years: it provides money for stem cell research, doubles the number of charter schools in the state, and includes a new law that will provide financial incentives for whistleblowers to report Medicaid fraud.</p>
        <p>''We're getting the sorts of reforms that had long been thought impossible,'' the governor said.</p>
        <p>Still, a $120.9 billion spending plan is a big budget for someone who campaigned for fiscal austerity and who complained as a candidate that last year's budget -- about $113.5 billion -- was ''faith-based'' because it counted on revenues that might not come in.</p>
        <p>And after spending months talking about changing paradigms in Albany and pushing through new laws that had been tough to negotiate, Mr. Spitzer may have raised expectations for his first budget that were hard to meet.</p>
        <p>But the governor said he was more than satisfied.</p>
        <p>''I understand the Legislature is going to say, we got A, B and C,'' the governor said. ''Some of what they got, they got because they made powerful arguments, some of it is because compromise was the essence of dealings between a legislature and an executive branch.</p>
        <p>''We compromised no more than we thought was right or appropriate,'' he said, ''to accomplish the twin objectives of both timeliness and the policy pursuits we sought.''</p>
        <p>NEWS ANALYSIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
