<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Seven Years of Disputation, A Map Makes Its Debut</title>
    <meta content="01jewi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/thecity/01jewi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070408T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837282"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK UP CLOSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Maps</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lando, Michal</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Maps</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E5DB1130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="632" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Seven Years of Disputation, A Map Makes Its Debut</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After Seven Years of Disputation, a Map Makes Its Debut</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAL LANDO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lando, Michal</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jewish New York: A History and Heritage Map, after years of debate over who and what to include, will be published in May in conjunction with national Jewish Heritage Month; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Until the very last second, it was unclear whether Nathan's Famous, the legendary Coney Island hot dog stand opened by Nathan Handwerker in 1916, would make the cut, and whether Sarah Jessica Parker, who played a racy sex columnist in the television series ''Sex and the City,'' should be included alongside the likes of Woody Allen and Rabbi Menachem Mendel Schneerson. Nathan's isn't kosher, and Ms. Parker is the daughter of a mixed marriage.</p>
        <p>These were some of the issues debated in true Talmudic style by the makers of a forthcoming map detailing the Jewish history and heritage of New York. It was in part because these and similar questions proved so knotty that it took years for the creators of ''Jewish New York: A History and Heritage Map'' to make their publication a reality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It took years for the creators of “Jewish New York: A History and Heritage Map” to make their publication a reality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Until the very last second, it was unclear whether Nathan's Famous, the legendary Coney Island hot dog stand opened by Nathan Handwerker in 1916, would make the cut, and whether Sarah Jessica Parker, who played a racy sex columnist in the television series ''Sex and the City,'' should be included alongside the likes of Woody Allen and Rabbi Menachem Mendel Schneerson. Nathan's isn't kosher, and Ms. Parker is the daughter of a mixed marriage.</p>
        <p>These were some of the issues debated in true Talmudic style by the makers of a forthcoming map detailing the Jewish history and heritage of New York. It was in part because these and similar questions proved so knotty that it took years for the creators of ''Jewish New York: A History and Heritage Map'' to make their publication a reality.</p>
        <p>The map, to be published next month in conjunction with National Jewish Heritage Month, includes about 75 illustrated sites and individuals from all five boroughs, including synagogues, cemeteries, movie stars and magicians. The goal was to create the first map that would serve both students and tourists.</p>
        <p>Since dreaming up the idea seven years ago, a New York lawyer named Howard Teich, who has an interest in Jewish heritage, has been brainstorming with Jeff Gottlieb, president of the Queens Jewish Historical Society; Marc Miller, a mapmaker who founded the Ephemera Press; and Rabbi Joseph Potasnik, executive vice president of the New York Board of Rabbis.</p>
        <p>But their work was painfully slow. Citywide celebrations of the 350th anniversary of the arrival of Jews in New York came and went in 2004, but the map was far from being ready to make its debut.</p>
        <p>Mr. Teich and his collaborators grappled with philosophical questions that have plagued Jews for millenniums. What does it really mean to be Jewish? How kosher is kosher enough? Is a self-hating Jew still a Jew? Is Sarah Jessica Parker a member of the tribe?</p>
        <p>Early in the process it became clear that the collaborators would be unable to satisfy the city's one million Jews. The map had to be ''kosher'' enough for some, and ''secular'' enough for others.</p>
        <p>''We recognize we can't be all things to all people,'' Rabbi Potasnik said, ''but given the choice of having a diverse picture, or not, we opted for diversity. The mentality was, leave your denomination at the door, and let's look at us as a whole, not as individuals.''</p>
        <p>Over the last few years, like a group of rabbis weighing in on a religious text, Mr. Teich and his colleagues pored over a list of relevant sites and figures, deciding how and what to eliminate. Experts were consulted, choices examined, judgments tallied.</p>
        <p>Controversial figures like Allen Ginsberg and Emma Goldman were rejected outright. In one instance, the collaborators worried that a drawing of a religious man pushing a baby carriage might be inaccurate or even offensive. (It was subsequently determined that ultra-Orthodox men do indeed push baby carriages.)</p>
        <p>According to Lloyd Ultan, the Bronx historian, his borough had been shortchanged; in response, he wrote a five-page e-mail message with suggestions of what to add. Because so many Jews have come from the Bronx, some notable Jewish figures from the borough, like the actress-director Penny Marshall and the ventriloquist Shari Lewis, stood no chance. By contrast, in Staten Island, a borough with relatively few Jews, the threshold was much lower, making room for figures like the publisher Samuel I. Newhouse.</p>
        <p>In the end, Ms. Parker was deemed the perfect figure to represent contemporary Jews, many of whom are the product of mixed marriages. Nathan's sneaked in on the back of the map, with a disclaimer noting that the restaurant isn't kosher.</p>
        <p>''There is no perfect map,'' Rabbi Potasnik said. ''But some are more perfect than others.''</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK UP CLOSE</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 8, 2007, Sunday  An article last Sunday about a new map depicting the city's Jewish heritage erroneously included an actress-director among Jewish figures from the Bronx. Penny Marshall is not Jewish.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 8, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about a new map depicting the city's Jewish heritage erroneously included an actress-director among Jewish figures from the Bronx. Penny Marshall is not Jewish.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
