<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sweet Spot</title>
    <meta content="01wwln-safire.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/magazine/01wwln-safire.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837044"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 4-01-07: ON LANGUAGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safire, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/On Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E4DA1230F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="967" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sweet Spot</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sweet Spot</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Safire</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Safire, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Safire column on the phrases 'sweet spot' and 'fall guy' (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stop searching for the sweet spot in today's world of cliché; you found it here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stop searching for the sweet spot in today’s world of cliché; you found it here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stop searching for the sweet spot in today's world of cliché; you found it here.</p>
        <p>''Midcap Stocks May Be Market's Next 'Sweet Spot,' '' headlines The Wall Street Journal.</p>
        <p>''Consumers develop a sweet spot for even bigger TVs,'' reports The Times.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for the Alliance of Automobile Manufacturers has called upon highway safety officials ''to crunch the numbers and come up with a sweet spot between [sic] affordability, safety concerns, jobs and technology.''</p>
        <p>Richard Weiner, the alert media- and showbiz-lingo maven, sends in this item from a newsletter touting ''search engine optimization,'' which can be subverted into a way of marketing by fooling Google: ''What is your company's 'keyword sweet spot?' ''</p>
        <p>Political observers have already turned the delicious noun phrase into a verb. Amy Walter, on CNN, notes how candidates are trying to position themselves for primaries driven by partisans 10 months from now without offending the centrist voters in a general election late next year: ''Finding the way to . . . sweet spot here on this issue becomes very, very important.''</p>
        <p>I ran this rampant usage past Joe Pickett, executive editor of American Heritage Dictionaries, who agreed that ''sweet spots are proliferating and refer to an area of range surrounded by or lying between less favorable conditions. In baseball, the sweet spot is the area on the barrel (the thickest part) of the bat that provides the most power on contact with the ball. Of course, the collocation sweet spot, meaning 'a pleasant or favorable place,' existed long before this.'' (A collocation is the placement of words next to each other to form a familiar phrase, like baseball's heavy hitter or golf's maddening duffer. Lexicographers use the word a lot; our most valuable element in evaluating the worth of a noun phrase is collocation, collocation, collocation.)</p>
        <p>In the ''Council of War'' chapter of Robert Louis Stevenson's 1883 ''Treasure Island,'' Long John Silver, the fearsome pirate, tells the narrator, ''Ah . . . this here is a sweet spot, this island -- a sweet spot for a lad to get ashore on. You'll bathe, and you'll climb trees, and you'll hunt goats. . . . Why, it makes me young again.'' The same idyllic early sense is intended by the real estate company pushing the resort of GrandDunes, fashionably squeezing together the two words of its name, in advertising ''Carolina's Coastal Sweet Spot.''</p>
        <p>The sense newer than that, however, is not just a place that is lovely. It is a more exhilarating version of the happy medium. Remember the tale of ''Goldilocks and the Three Bears''? She faced three bowls of the bears' cereal, tasted one and exclaimed, ''This porridge is too hot!'' The next was too cold, but the third caused her to purr, ''Ahhh, this porridge is just right,'' and ''she ate it all up,'' to the consternation of the returning three bears. Economists wondering whether the economy is overheating or cooling hope we are in ''the Goldilocks economy'' -- just right -- and those who are bearish or bullish today may soon wonder whatever happened to today's sweet spot.</p>
        <p>Other senses of this collocation -- See? You'll never forget that word now -- exist. It is used as an alternative to ''soft spot'' in ''I have a sweet spot in my heart for him/her/it''; it is also mistakenly used in lieu of G-spot, supposedly an erogenous zone.</p>
        <p>A word of etymological caution: Golfers may lay claim to the origin. ''Trigonometry Finds 'Sweet Spot' for the Golf Club to Meet the Ball'' was a headline in The New York Times of March 16, 1957. Members of the oil industry may also cite early uses of the term: in a Times review of the 1941 novel by Hartzell Spence, ''Radio City,'' about that then-hot medium, the protagonist is an advertising man who had a client named Sweetspot Oil; it may be that oilmen spoke of a field of sweet spots where wells were not dry holes. (Joe Pickett directed me to these on the amazing Times Archive; it goes back so far that it even has some of my early pooh-poohing of Watergate as a minor-league scandal.)</p>
        <p>Most phrasedicks, however, would say that the origin of the metaphor is the thickest part of a baseball bat. That may not be subtle enough; more precisely, it is the place somewhere on the ''meat end'' of the bat that the batter believes gives him the most power and control of placement. Or it is the place on the ball, just below the center of the sphere, that -- when hit squarely to generate the proper amount of backspin -- leads to the longest high drive.</p>
        <p>The Fall Guy</p>
        <p>What's the derivation of the fall guy?</p>
        <p>Senator Charles Schumer, the New York Democrat, said after the conviction of Lewis (Scooter) Libby, the novelist, that he had been made ''the fall guy'' for others; one juror in the trial used the same expression about the defendant. Soon afterward, the Republican congressman Bill Young said of Maj. Gen. George Weightman, who assumed command at Walter Reed Army Medical Center six months before The Washington Post exposed substandard outpatient facilities there, that ''I don't know him. But I know he's the fall guy.''</p>
        <p>J. E. Lighter's great Historical Dictionary of American Slang, with an array of citations dating to 1904, presents the two senses of the phrase: ''a person who is easily duped'' and today's more common meaning, ''scapegoat.'' But a mystery remains: What was the original fall? A prizefighter ''taking a fall''? Lucifer's ''fall'' from paradise? A lover ''falling for'' a mate? In other words, who was the original guy?</p>
        <p>A fishhook in this space recently landed the origin and coiner of ''the third rail of politics (touch Social Security and you're dead).'' Shall we try again? Address at left.</p>
        <p>THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 4-01-07: ON LANGUAGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
