<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Thomas Vents After Tough Loss for Marbury and Knicks</title>
    <meta content="01knicks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/sports/basketball/01knicks.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837466"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Orleans Hornets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New Orleans Hornets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Thomas, Isiah</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Marbury, Stephon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E3DC1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="811" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Thomas Vents After Tough Loss for Marbury and Knicks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Thomas Vents After Tough Loss for Marbury and Knicks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beck, Howard</byline>
      <dateline>OKLAHOMA CITY, March 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Isiah Thomas wore a look of despair but spoke in tones of defiance late Saturday evening. Redemption, in the form of a playoff berth, seems certain to elude the Knicks this spring. But Thomas, the coach and team president, sounded like he was laying groundwork for next fall.</p>
        <p>Twenty-four hours after a heart-breaking loss in Dallas, the Knicks repeated all the same themes -- they showed resilience and grit right down to the final minutes and lost anyway. The night ended with a 103-94 overtime loss to the Hornets that might have killed the Knicks' already faint playoff hopes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Twenty-four hours after a heart-breaking loss in Dallas, the Knicks repeated all the same themes  they showed resilience and grit right down to the final minutes and lost anyway.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Isiah Thomas wore a look of despair but spoke in tones of defiance late Saturday evening. Redemption, in the form of a playoff berth, seems certain to elude the Knicks this spring. But Thomas, the coach and team president, sounded like he was laying groundwork for next fall.</p>
        <p>Twenty-four hours after a heart-breaking loss in Dallas, the Knicks repeated all the same themes -- they showed resilience and grit right down to the final minutes and lost anyway. The night ended with a 103-94 overtime loss to the Hornets that might have killed the Knicks' already faint playoff hopes.</p>
        <p>With nine games left, the Knicks (31-42) are three games behind Orlando and the Nets (both 34-39) for the final playoff spot in the Eastern Conference. The loss dropped the Knicks a season-high 11 games under .500 and ensured them of their sixth consecutive losing season.</p>
        <p>As he groped for answers afterward, Thomas directed his frustration at the referees -- not Saturday's crew in particular, but all of them -- for not giving enough respect to Stephon Marbury, the Knicks' star guard.</p>
        <p>Marbury was incensed when no foul was called as he got the ball stripped in the final seconds of regulation. A night earlier, Marbury was angry over a noncall when he drove for a potential game-tying layup in Dallas.</p>
        <p>Without being asked, Thomas went on a two-minute filibuster about the refereeing of Marbury.</p>
        <p>''I've never said this, and I've never done this for a player before, but I think there's a point that seriously needs to be made how Marbury is being treated by the officials now,'' Thomas said. ''I don't understand why a guy who, for all his career, is a guy that drives to the basket -- and I see a lot of other players drive to the basket and get fouled and go to the foul line -- and I don't understand what he's done to receive the kind of treatment that he's getting and the lack of respect that he's getting from the officials.</p>
        <p>''That's not why we lost the game,'' Thomas added. ''We did a lot of things to lose the game. But moving forward, I would hope that he would be treated just like other star players are treated when they get fouled.''</p>
        <p>The speech did not end there, and Thomas, perhaps risking a fine from the commissioner's office, made an open plea to the league.</p>
        <p>''I would hope by me saying this that maybe that will change for him one day, because this year's been difficult for him and myself and all of us watching the way the noncalls happen for him,'' he said.</p>
        <p>It was indeed a tough night for Marbury, who seemed to have little left after a season-high 43-point game on Friday. He shot poorly all night, going 6 for 20 from the field and finishing with 16 points. He was awarded just three free throws, but he also spent a lot of time at the 3-point arc, going 2 for 11.</p>
        <p>Marbury hit a pull-up 3-pointer as the Knicks erased an 11-point deficit late in the fourth quarter. The Knicks were within 1 point when Marbury drove into the lane and had the ball stripped by Jannero Pargo. Marbury, his hands out, turned to the referee Derek Richardson and said, incredulously, ''Nothing?''</p>
        <p>Nate Robinson hit a 3-pointer with 10 seconds left to force overtime, where the Knicks came apart. The Hornets scored the first 5 points, on a Desmond Mason layup and a Chris Paul 3-pointer, and the Knicks never threatened again. Robinson missed two 3-pointers, and Marbury missed a driving layup. The Knicks also made the curious decision not to foul quickly when they were behind by 7 points with 36 seconds left.</p>
        <p>Now, only a collapse by the Nets or the Magic will get the Knicks back in the playoff hunt.</p>
        <p>''We can't let this kill us, kill our spirits,'' said Eddy Curry, who led the Knicks with 34 points and 13 rebounds despite dislocating two fingers in the first half.</p>
        <p>Marbury assessed his team's playoff chances this way: ''Stranger things have happened.''</p>
        <p>As for getting more whistles when he drives the lane, Marbury seemed just as doubtful.</p>
        <p>''I'm not getting any calls,'' he said, adding, ''This is how it's been'' throughout his career.</p>
        <p>At the moment, it is two noncalls in particular that have Marbury and Thomas perturbed.</p>
        <p>''It happened, it's something that we got to deal with, and that's it,'' Marbury said. ''There's nothing really more to say about it.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>The Knicks legend Willis Reed, a Hornets vice president who is retiring at the end of the season, was honored at halftime. ''It was a great run,'' said Reed, whose Hall of Fame career began with the Knicks in 1964 and included championships in 1970 and 1973. He has worked for the Hornets since 2004.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
