<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What Consultants May Not Know About Leadership</title>
    <meta content="01shelf" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/business/yourmoney/01shelf.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837319"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OFF THE SHELF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Off the Shelf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Leaders and Leadership</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leaders and Leadership</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">George, Bill</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04EFDB1130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1204" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What Consultants May Not Know About Leadership</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">What Consultants May Not Know About Leadership</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. HOLSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holstein, William J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR many years, choruses of management coaches, consultants and business school professors have proclaimed that they can teach executives how to become leaders. The avalanche of words spilled on the subject -- many of them simplistic and repetitive -- would fill many libraries.</p>
        <p>Now comes a truly worthwhile look at leadership, ''True North: Discover Your Authentic Leadership,'' by Bill George with Peter Sims (Jossey-Bass, $27.95).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>One view that emerges in Bill George’s book, “True North: Discover Your Authentic Leadership,” is that the soul of leadership cannot be taught.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR many years, choruses of management coaches, consultants and business school professors have proclaimed that they can teach executives how to become leaders. The avalanche of words spilled on the subject -- many of them simplistic and repetitive -- would fill many libraries.</p>
        <p>Now comes a truly worthwhile look at leadership, ''True North: Discover Your Authentic Leadership,'' by Bill George with Peter Sims (Jossey-Bass, $27.95).</p>
        <p>Mr. George was chief executive of Medtronic for 10 years and is currently on the boards of Exxon Mobil, Goldman Sachs and Novartis. He also teaches at Harvard Business School. The book is based on interviews with 125 other leaders.</p>
        <p>One view that emerges is that the soul of leadership cannot be taught. Instead, leaders are shaped by personal crises or other life experiences -- often early in life but also in the middle stages of life -- that give them a burning sense of mission. If Mr. George is correct, much of the money spent on leadership development has been wasted.</p>
        <p>Howard Schultz, the chairman of Starbucks, describes his key experience as occurring in the winter of 1961 when he was 7 and throwing snowballs with friends outside the Bayview Housing Projects in Brooklyn. His mother shouted to him to come inside. There, he discovered that his father had had an accident. While working as a delivery driver, he had fallen on ice and broken his ankle.</p>
        <p>The father lost his job and benefits, and soon began arguing with his wife at the dinner table over how much money the family needed to borrow. ''I was surrounded by people who were working hand-to-mouth trying to pay the bills, who felt like there was no hope,'' Mr. Schultz is quoted as saying. ''That's something that never leaves you -- never.''</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Schultz, the stigma of his family's experience equipped him with an ambition to succeed and helped spur him to build Starbucks into what it is today. It also drove him to pay more than the minimum wage, offer substantial health benefits and grant stock options to all his workers.</p>
        <p>Then there is Daniel Vasella, chief executive of the Swiss company Novartis. He suffered from asthma, tuberculosis and meningitis as a child in Switzerland and had to spend long periods away from his family. A sister died of cancer and his father died in surgery.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vasella initially decided to become a doctor so that he could help ease the type of suffering that he and his family endured, but he then was drawn to the pharmaceutical field.</p>
        <p>In his role at Novartis, he has driven his scientists to come up with live-saving drugs quickly because he has an emotional connection with patients. ''As C.E.O., I have the leverage to impact the lives of many more people,'' Mr. Vasella says.</p>
        <p>That's a common thread in the strongest leaders, Mr. George argues: they have a deep desire to serve a greater goal beyond simply making money.</p>
        <p>In general, the book paints a portrait that clashes with the image of isolated and greedy C.E.O.'s that appears in the popular press. Those certainly exist, Mr. George says, but he argues that many of them are impostors certain to fail. The best leaders are those who have values, or a ''true north,'' that other people in their organizations come to appreciate, he said.</p>
        <p>''Leaders whose goal is the quest for power over others, maximizing wealth or becoming famous tend to look to other people for satisfaction and acknowledgment of their status,'' Mr. George writes. ''In public and in private, they display a high degree of narcissism.''</p>
        <p>''True North'' also reflects a clear change in ideas on leadership , a moving away from command-and-control figures like Maurice R. Greenberg, former chief executive of the American International Group, and toward more collaborative management styles.</p>
        <p>Increasingly, the key is to realize that the game isn't about ''I,'' meaning the C.E.O., but rather about ''we,'' meaning the team. ''The role of leaders is not to get other people to follow them, but to empower others to lead,'' Mr. George writes. ''They cannot elicit the best performance from their teams if they are in the game primarily for themselves.''</p>
        <p>Several other insights in the book help put the issue of corporate leadership in a new light. One is that a leader can, in fact, display certain vulnerabilities to others. A leader does not have to pretend to have all the answers all the time.</p>
        <p>Anne M. Mulcahy, chief executive of Xerox, faced the possibility of a company bankruptcy filing in 2001 and described how she felt: ''Around 8:30 p.m. on my way home, I pulled over to the side of the Merritt Parkway and said to myself, 'I don't know where to go. I don't want to go home. There's just no place to go.' ''</p>
        <p>Her display of personal vulnerability -- combined with a determination to succeed -- helped Ms. Mulcahy rally her team and cut billions of dollars in expenses and reduce debt by 60 percent, saving the company. In the final analysis, leadership is personality-based.</p>
        <p>It is perhaps surprising how much time Mr. George spends talking about the work-life balance that the best leaders must have. That is certainly at odds with the stereotype of business leaders who put in monster 16- and 18-hour days and never see their families.</p>
        <p>Mr. George tells the story of John Donahoe, who was on the fast track at Bain &amp; Company, the consulting firm. As Mr. Donahoe moved up the ranks, he repeatedly wrestled with work-life issues. At one point, his wife, Eileen, received a job offer that required her to be at work at 7:30 a.m. That raised the question of who would take their two children to school every day. Mr. Donahoe went to his boss and said he had to quit so that he could do it. But his boss and his clients both agreed to allow him to start work at 10 a.m. Mr. Donahoe, now a top executive at eBay, actually became more effective as a leader, Mr. George concludes.</p>
        <p>''Integrating their lives is one of the greatest challenges leaders face,'' Mr. George writes. ''To lead an integrated life, you need to bring together the major elements of your personal life and professional life, including work, family, community and friends, so that you can be the same person in each environment.'' Leaders who are well grounded in this way avoid the trap of isolation and arrogance.</p>
        <p>THE best leaders are also capable of developing a virtuous, or reinforcing, cycle of leadership, Mr. George explains. They are driven people with moving personal stories and they empower the people around them. That leads to business success, and attracts even more ideas and people.</p>
        <p>Not everything about ''True North'' is compelling. The analysis sometimes seems wooden and repetitive; at other times, it veers into inspirational mode. The do-it-yourself leadership exercises at the back of the book (''What are your strongest capabilities or talents?'') are irritatingly sophomoric.</p>
        <p>Even so, this is one of the most important books on leadership to come along in years, because it is based on so much up-close-and-personal observation. It is far more reality-based than the theories peddled by the bulk of management pundits.</p>
        <p>OFF THE SHELF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
