<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nitzan Pelman and Joseph Braude</title>
    <meta content="01vows" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/fashion/weddings/01vows.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837253"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS: VOWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pelman, Nitzan (Nitzan Braude)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Braude, Joseph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Columns/Vows</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EEDE1130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="695" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nitzan Pelman and Joseph Braude</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nitzan Pelman and Joseph Braude</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SANDEE BRAWARSKY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN a New York taxi, Joseph Braude can eavesdrop on an Arabic-speaking driver's phone conversation and name his place of birth. He's fluent not only in Arabic but also in Hebrew and Farsi. But when he met Nitzan Pelman in August 2004, it was his native English that caught her attention and her heart.</p>
        <p>''There was just a serenity and calmness in his voice, with a lot of sophistication and confidence,'' she said. ''It was a love-at-first-sight moment.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The couple met in the federal courthouse in Brooklyn, where Mr. Braude was on trial for theft of Iraqi antiquities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN a New York taxi, Joseph Braude can eavesdrop on an Arabic-speaking driver's phone conversation and name his place of birth. He's fluent not only in Arabic but also in Hebrew and Farsi. But when he met Nitzan Pelman in August 2004, it was his native English that caught her attention and her heart.</p>
        <p>''There was just a serenity and calmness in his voice, with a lot of sophistication and confidence,'' she said. ''It was a love-at-first-sight moment.''</p>
        <p>The setting was the hallway of the federal courthouse in Brooklyn, where Mr. Braude was on trial for theft of Iraqi antiquities. Ms. Pelman had been invited there by her childhood friend Zachary Shrier, who roomed with Mr. Braude's brother at Harvard.</p>
        <p>The previous summer, Mr. Braude, the author of ''The New Iraq: Rebuilding the Country for Its People, the Middle East and the World,'' was in Baghdad doing research for the book's paperback edition and meeting with Pentagon officials about job prospects there. (Through his years at Yale and Princeton, he had been a consultant to federal authorities, sometimes doing Arabic translations and analysis.)</p>
        <p>On his return, customs officials at Kennedy Airport discovered three 4,000-year-old stone seals in his luggage. He said that he hadn't known the value of these relics, which were offered to him on the street, and that he planned to turn them over to his government contacts.</p>
        <p>When the trial adjourned for lunch, Ms. Pelman joined Mr. Braude and his supporters at a diner, where, she said, ''we were flirting across the table.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Braude said, ''Despite the intensity of the environment, sparks were flying.''</p>
        <p>After lunch she went back to work, and he pleaded guilty. The charges carried a maximum sentence of 16 months in prison. That night, Ms. Pelman said to Mr. Shrier, ''I know this is crazy, but did he ask about me?'' ''Yes,'' Mr. Shrier recalled telling her.</p>
        <p>''Nitzan is highly inquisitive and intellectually engaging, of Joe's caliber,'' he reflected. Still, Mr. Shrier added, ''I never imagined they would go on a date that week.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Braude came in from his family's home in Providence, R.I., and met Ms. Pelman for lunch in New York. Soon after, they broke off the relationships they were in.</p>
        <p>With his sentencing coming up on Nov. 20, they spoke on the phone every night and saw each other frequently. Mr. Braude, 32, remarked, ''When you meet the woman of your dreams, there's really no time like the present.''</p>
        <p>The night before sentencing, Ms. Pelman, 30, an associate director of the accountability office at the New York City Education Department, said she was bursting with mixed emotions. She knew she had met the man she wanted to marry and felt confident in his character, yet feared he could be sent away.</p>
        <p>Judge Allyne R. Ross of Federal District Court took the unusual step in her comments of pointing out Mr. Braude's exemplary achievements and service. She sentenced him to six months of home confinement.</p>
        <p>The couple embarked on a domestic courtship. Every weekend, Ms. Pelman visited Providence, where he was serving his sentence, and enjoyed watching movies and talking. Ms. Pelman, a child of an Eastern European family, who grew up in Los Angeles, learned about the Middle East, and together they learned Iraqi cooking from his mother, who left Baghdad when she was 5.</p>
        <p>Mr. Braude listened as Ms. Pelman, a Yeshiva University graduate with a master's in public policy from New York University, spoke passionately about public education and her wish to level the achievement gap.</p>
        <p>Soon after he completed his sentence, he moved to Brooklyn to be with her.</p>
        <p>On March 25, Ms. Pelman, and Mr. Braude were married by Rabbi Saul J. Berman at the Wilshire Grand Hotel in West Orange, N.J. The music at the reception was a lively mixture of the Middle East and Eastern European klezmer.</p>
        <p>''It's a textbook case of divine intervention,'' declared Mr. Braude, whose father is a Reform rabbi and whose maternal great-great-grandfather was a rabbi in Baghdad. ''If I had not sought to recover these antiquities, I would have been working in Baghdad for as long as I lived.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS: VOWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
