<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>April Madness: My College Outrecycles Yours!</title>
    <meta content="01RrecycleCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837178"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spiegel, Jan Ellen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E4DC1030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1271" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>April Madness: My College Outrecycles Yours!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAN ELLEN SPIEGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Spiegel, Jan Ellen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Recyclemania, 10-week national competition that began in 2001 as friendly wager between recycling directors, now involves 201 colleges and universities and is in its final week; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>C. J. MAY is not happy.</p>
        <p>''My boss and others want to know if Harvard is doing better than Yale, and they want to know why,'' moaned Mr. May, 44, a Yale graduate turned Yale employee.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>C. J. MAY is not happy.</p>
        <p>''My boss and others want to know if Harvard is doing better than Yale, and they want to know why,'' moaned Mr. May, 44, a Yale graduate turned Yale employee.</p>
        <p>The news is bad. Harvard is beating Yale. That the competition is in recycling does not diminish the angst. ''It is personally troubling to me,'' said Mr. May, who has been Yale's recycling coordinator for 17 years. ''I've been working very hard to make Yale recycle. I know we can do better.''</p>
        <p>It's now or never for Mr. May and his fellow Elis, as the 10-week national competition known as Recyclemania enters its final week. The contest ends April 7.</p>
        <p>Begun in 2001 as a friendly wager between the recycling directors at Ohio and Miami Universities, the contest this year involves 201 colleges and universities, more than double the number from last year, including 12 from New York State, 8 from New Jersey and 3 from Connecticut. (There are none from New York City.)</p>
        <p>The campuses compete -- for bragging rights only since there is no monetary prize -- in several categories, most of which use a formula to tally the amount each student, teacher and staff member recycles, so large and small schools can compete more equitably.</p>
        <p>While winning is fun, the real goal, campus recycling coordinators and experts say, is actually getting young people, living on their own, to pay attention to where they throw their trash.</p>
        <p>''We have, in the United States, been establishing a recycling infrastructure for three decades, but when we look at rates, we are not improving,'' said Kate M. Krebs, executive director of the National Recycling Coalition, a nonprofit trade organization in Washington that runs the contest with the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>National data shows that recycling over all is flat, Ms. Krebs said, but it is especially poor among college-age people, even though they grew up with recycling as a widespread practice. ''When you look at demographics, the 18- to 24-year-old sector makes little if any effort to recycle,'' she said. ''It is heartbreaking for those of us who have been in the field for a long time.''</p>
        <p>College recycling directors say the competition helps shine a light on their efforts, which generally have been in place for years but are often ignored.</p>
        <p>''If you don't make it absolutely convenient -- you walk out your door and there it is -- they don't want to walk to the end of the hall,'' said Kevin Lyons, director of purchasing at Rutgers University and a professor of environmental management.</p>
        <p>Mark Smith, a sophomore at Princeton and Recyclemania coordinator, agreed. ''There are kids that don't want to recycle -- aren't going to do it no matter what,'' he said. ''There are kids who carry around a bottle all day until they find a receptacle for it. And then there are the kids who would do it if it was convenient. That's who we want to get.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lyons has run the recycling effort at Rutgers for 19 of its 20 years. He prides himself on a recycling rate that approaches 60 percent and includes 20 different items, from the usual paper, bottles, cans and cardboard to fluorescent bulbs, electronic waste (like inkjet and toner cartridges) and food.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Lyons admitted, Rutgers ''didn't do so hot'' last year in its first Recyclemania. But this year, as of Week 7, it was close to being tied for the lead with California State University at San Marcos, a two-time winner. (Standings can be found at recyclemaniacs.org.) Rutgers was also leading or contending in per capita recycling and three other categories: bottles, cans and corrugated cardboard; food service; and ''gorilla,'' which measures gross tonnage.</p>
        <p>To improve student participation, Mr. Lyons's office ran a two-week shredding effort (which collected 75,000 pounds of paper and 4,700 pounds of cardboard), dormitory competitions and a sculpture contest using items that otherwise would have been thrown away.</p>
        <p>All great for promoting recycling, but he would also like to beat Princeton. ''We would have a parade on Nassau Street,'' Mr. Lyons said, referring to the main road adjacent to that campus.</p>
        <p>Princeton, however, is intent on topping the other four Ivy League participants (Brown and Dartmouth are competing, too), despite an audit that showed that 35 percent of the contents of dormitory trash cans were filled with recyclables.</p>
        <p>Which is why Princeton's building services director, Jonathan Baer, says Recyclemania is a plus -- win, lose or draw. ''I think it's a good time, once per year, in an increased way, to focus on recycling that's not punitive or paternal,'' he said. ''It's a time to reinforce our focus with some renewed energy.''</p>
        <p>Michael Youdelman, Stony Brook University's recycling and resource management director, said he figured the best way to get students to recycle was to take the bins to them. So over Christmas break, some 3,500 mixed-paper recycling bins were put in every dorm room. People ''caught green-handed'' -- doing something environmentally desirable -- are entered in a drawing for a green iPod. Jennifer Myatt, a graduate student and outreach coordinator, runs a recycling information table offering pencils recycled from used currency and old jeans.</p>
        <p>''Education, that's pretty much the hardest thing -- just educating people and getting them in the habit of recycling,'' Ms. Myatt said. ''We don't even think about taking out our trash. We can do the same with recycling.''</p>
        <p>The Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory of Columbia University, a small graduate research school in Palisades, N.Y., with fewer than 600 students, discovered that all it needed to do well was to do what it had always done: generate research proposals, which typically use huge amounts of paper. In its first year of competition, the college is sitting atop the recycled paper category.</p>
        <p>''The next step is to figure out how to generate less of it,'' said Mary Reagan, who heads Lamont-Doherty's Recyclemania effort. But the contest, she said, had given her ''cold hard numbers'' for the first time confirming that recycling works.</p>
        <p>Amy Cabaniss, environmental coordinator at Connecticut College in New London, drew the same conclusion after finishing in the top five in four categories last year, including second in food service -- a result of the college's long-standing practice of sending food waste to a pig farm. (Princeton has a similar arrangement; at Rutgers, food waste is pulped and dried, and what is left is sold to a cattle farm .)</p>
        <p>This year, a student at Connecticut College mapped outdoor pedestrian patterns so recycling and trash bins could be placed more strategically, Ms. Cabaniss said. As of Week 7, Connecticut was in the top five in bottles and cans and fourth in food service, and ahead of in-state rivals Wesleyan and Yale, but just behind another small college in the area, Bard College, in Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Bard's environmental resources auditor, Laurie Husted, said that despite offering prizes donated by local businesses, student participation had not been as strong as she had hoped. Still, Recyclemania was ''stirring the pot -- I'm seeing the effects in other ways,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Which is what brings Mr. May at Yale, ever the optimist, back to Recyclemania for the fourth time. He may never be able to overcome the inherent problem of Yale's historic buildings, which have no halls, so recycling bins are in the basement, requiring a lot of student motivation. But he hopes a new plan to pick up paper directly from desks will help. ''Our goal is to try to get up to 40 percent recycling in the next few years,'' Mr. May said.</p>
        <p>''If we can beat Harvard in the process, all the better.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
