<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The New Owners Get the Once-Over</title>
    <meta content="01livi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/realestate/01livi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837234"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="LIVING IN: STUYVESANT TOWN AND PETER COOPER VILLAGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stuyvesant Town (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Peter Cooper Village (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vandam, Jeff</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Living In</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Peter Cooper Village (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stuyvesant Town (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E6D81030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2236" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The New Owners Get the Once-Over</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The New Owners Get the Once-Over</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF VANDAM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vandam, Jeff</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Living In article on Stuyvesant Town and Peter Cooper Village in Manhattan; maps; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF you're thinking of living in Stuyvesant Town or Peter Cooper Village, those immense, green-windowpaned collections of 1940s brick apartment towers near the East River, known for their neighborliness and affordability -- well, just because they recently changed hands in a $5.4 billion transaction doesn't mean they are changing at heart. At least, not very rapidly.</p>
        <p>Residents have been concerned since late last year about the possibility of radical change. The neighborhood, with its 12,000 or so rental apartments in 110 buildings, was sold by MetLife, the builder, to Tishman Speyer Properties, in the largest residential deal in real estate history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just because Stuyvesant Town or Peter Cooper Village in Manhattan recently changed hands in a $5.4 billion transaction, it doesn’t mean they are changing at heart.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF you're thinking of living in Stuyvesant Town or Peter Cooper Village, those immense, green-windowpaned collections of 1940s brick apartment towers near the East River, known for their neighborliness and affordability -- well, just because they recently changed hands in a $5.4 billion transaction doesn't mean they are changing at heart. At least, not very rapidly.</p>
        <p>Residents have been concerned since late last year about the possibility of radical change. The neighborhood, with its 12,000 or so rental apartments in 110 buildings, was sold by MetLife, the builder, to Tishman Speyer Properties, in the largest residential deal in real estate history.</p>
        <p>''Right now, there's a lot of anxiety that there's a way of life that's about to change,'' said Jack Lester, who since 1990 has been the lawyer for the local tenants' association.</p>
        <p>With the 18-block complex of buildings starting its seventh decade of occupancy, it is a way of life that has had time to mature. Among the 25,000 residents there are still old-timers with roomy rent-stabilized aeries and river views. There are also holdovers, and their relatives, from the complex's birth as a residence for World War II veterans.</p>
        <p>Tishman Speyer is not articulating its long-term vision for the complex. Robert Lawson, a spokesman, said recently in an e-mail message that there were no plans to convert it to condominiums (although there has been speculation that Peter Cooper Village, with its larger units, might lend itself to a conversion). Rather, industry experts see the developer as likely to be aggressive about freeing units from rent stabilization.</p>
        <p>''I think anybody would be surprised if they were to keep the status quo, based on the purchase price,'' said Jonathan J. Miller, president of the appraisal firm Miller Samuel. ''It's a big number.''</p>
        <p>As for the developer's approach, he added: ''I would think that it's going to be a combination of political sensibilities and maximizing their investment. I think they go hand in hand.''</p>
        <p>Political sensibilities already seem to be front and center. Tishman Speyer says it will introduce an array of services, including a fitness center that is to be installed on 20th Street; it is also finishing a deal to bring in a greenmarket on Thursdays and Fridays, said Steven Rubenstein, a spokesman for the developer.</p>
        <p>Even before the sale, however, an influx of younger residents -- the 27 percent already unprotected by rent stabilization -- began the process of bringing the neighborhood into a new era. As Mr. Lester put it, ''You're getting a high degree of people coming in for a short term and leaving.''</p>
        <p>The experiences of one couple who settled into a market-rate apartment at Peter Cooper Village in 2003 may explain the reason for this new pattern of turnover.</p>
        <p>The couple, Vincent FitzPatrick and Katie Kurtz, rent a bright and roomy 14th-floor two-bedroom unit with views of Midtown Manhattan. Since arriving, they have marveled at the spacious grounds; a paddle tennis court is right outside their building, and their son, Jack, 9 months old and nearly walking, has a fine time in the large playgrounds.</p>
        <p>People even greet one another on the wide pathways between buildings, something most likely rare to both Ms. Kurtz and Mr. FitzPatrck as they grew up elsewhere in Manhattan.''It's a community feeling that I feel like you don't get in other neighborhoods,'' said Mr. FitzPatrick, 34, a lawyer. ''It's sort of a throwback.''</p>
        <p>Yet while pleased with their apartment, the grounds and the helpful maintenance workers, they feel the opposite about their rent. When they arrived three and a half years ago and signed a two-year lease, the monthly rate was $3,175. Now, Mr. FitzPatrick said, it is around $4,100, an amount they had 30 days to accept when they signed their latest lease. (''I think that is a gun-to-the-head approach,'' Mr. FitzPatrick said.)</p>
        <p>He explained that the potential condo or co-op conversion of Peter Cooper Village had been a factor when he and his wife decided to rent there, because they knew ''MetLife didn't want to be in the real estate game anymore.''</p>
        <p>''I would love it,'' he added. ''It would be a great opportunity -- provided that there would be some sort of insider price offered.''</p>
        <p>In the meantime, however, as the couple more closely examine their aging building and the days and hours they've waited for maintenance problems to be addressed, they are torn between the features they love and the fact that, for the rent they're paying, they could afford -- and might be better off in -- a full-service luxury doorman building elsewhere in the city.</p>
        <p>''It's no longer a no-brainer,'' Mr. FitzPatrick said. ''But, yes, take away all of that other stuff, and there's a reason why we keep re-signing our lease. We still think it's a good size. The other rents out there are still ridiculous.''</p>
        <p>What You'll Pay</p>
        <p>State law dictates that an apartment can be removed from rent control after its tenants move out and it is renovated, or if the rent (which, though stabilized, is allowed to increase to keep up with inflation) reaches $2,000 a month and the tenants' income surpasses $175,000 for two years in a row.</p>
        <p>In comparison with the rates paid by rent-stabilized tenants like Alvin Doyle, president of the tenants' association, and his wife, Patricia Sallin -- around $1,300 for a two-bedroom they first rented in 1979 -- market-rate prices for new residents at Stuyvesant Town are more in line with luxury rental prices elsewhere in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>A one-bedroom, with 755 square feet, now starts at $2,800 a month, with two-bedrooms of 943 square feet starting at $3,500 a month. There are no four- or five-bedroom units currently available, but a three-bedroom with 1,161 square feet can be had for $4,600 a month or more.</p>
        <p>Across 20th Street in Peter Cooper Village, rents are higher, with a 1,223-square-foot two-bedroom starting at $4,250, just over what Ms. Kurtz and Mr. FitzPatrick pay for their unit. Rents for one-bedrooms with 947 square feet are $3,075.</p>
        <p>For market-rate tenants, increases can come each year, and amounts can vary; at times, the increase persuades families who had just been getting settled to leave.</p>
        <p>''When people can't predict what their rent is going to be, it shakes them up,'' said City Councilman Daniel R. Garodnick, who pays market rate in Peter Cooper Village. ''In many cases, it requires families to uproot themselves and take kids out of school and move elsewhere.''</p>
        <p>On top of the monthly rent, Mr. Doyle of the tenants' association said, over the last several years there have been increases small and large for major capital improvements, like new electrical wiring and elevators. There may be more to come, said John Marsh, a Peter Cooper resident who is also a tenants' association member, as the pipes in the buildings are quite old and occasionally spurt brown water.</p>
        <p>''I've noticed a lot of people have been getting Poland Spring deliveries,'' he said.</p>
        <p>What You'll Find</p>
        <p>To enter either of the complexes on a pleasant spring day is to stroll into a seemingly calm, controlled urban utopia. Grass is clipped and land maintained by helpful workers. Neighbors -- elderly, young and in between -- play shuffleboard, sit on benches or stop to chat. Sports courts and wide patches of grass are everywhere, and the atmosphere of small-town-within-city, of nature within an urban morass, is striking.</p>
        <p>''The squirrels are certainly a distinguishing feature,'' said Mr. Garodnick, who grew up in both Stuyvesant Town and Peter Cooper Village. ''They'll come right up to you now and ask you for a walnut.''</p>
        <p>Geographically, the two developments fit snugly into a curve of Manhattan once known as the Gashouse District, between 14th and 23rd Streets, from First Avenue to Avenue C and the Franklin D. Roosevelt Drive. The dividing line between the complexes is 20th Street, and though conditions may appear similar in both, there are differences.</p>
        <p>Units in Peter Cooper Village are larger and more expensive; the two-bedroom units, for instance, have a second bathroom. Also, buildings in Peter Cooper Village are taller, going to the 14th floor as in Mr. FitzPatrick's apartment, and affording views sometimes lacking in Stuyvesant Town, with its 11-story buildings. ''My grandmother was in Stuyvesant Town, and I'd go over and visit her there,'' recalled Mr. Marsh, who grew up in Peter Cooper Village and lives there today. ''I could always feel the difference.''</p>
        <p>Another fact of life -- unwelcome to some -- is the permanent presence of hundreds of students, for whom New York University has rented 175 Stuyvesant Town apartments as student housing. According to Mr. Garodnick, the students can sometimes create a ''dormlike atmosphere.'' At present, said Kelly Franklin, an N.Y.U. spokeswoman, 175 apartments are occupied by 315 students, all of them graduate level and a majority pursuing doctorates. The university has housed students there for six years, she said.</p>
        <p>Before the sale, tenants certainly had their disputes with MetLife, but that hasn't made them any less cautious toward the new regime. On the one hand, there is an acknowledgment of the professional way the new owner takes care of its property; on the other, the rent increases that started under MetLife are persisting, along with a perceived eagerness to shuffle out rent-stabilized tenants.</p>
        <p>''Some people have very positive feelings'' about Tishman Speyer, said Mr. Doyle, who has lived in Stuyvesant Town since his birth in 1952. One move that engendered good will over the winter was the complexwide installation of holiday decorations. ''I've met some of them, and they're very courteous and nice,'' Mr. Doyle added of the new maintenance team. In addition to the fitness center and greenmarket, Mr. Rubenstein said, Tishman Speyer has encouraged a concierge service called the Villager to offer a trolley service to Wall Street and the No. 6 station on 23rd Street. The trolleys were never given the go-ahead by MetLife, said Bill Seidler, the Villager's president.</p>
        <p>Offering further evidence of that difference -- or perhaps merely evidence of complaints -- Tishman is also planning to dispatch ''property ambassadors'' to various buildings.</p>
        <p>''They seem to be paying more attention to details,'' Mr. Marsh said. ''They're doing nice things like retiling the compactor chutes.''</p>
        <p>What to Do</p>
        <p>Ms. Kurtz and Mr. FitzPatrick, the young couple from Peter Cooper Village, can't get enough of Petite Abeille and Vamos, restaurants at 20th Street and First Avenue that are welcoming to families. For those without children or with a baby sitter, the culinary and nightlife scenes of the East Village beckon to the south, as does the Gramercy area to the west. Of course, some find fun within the complex, which has 15 recreation areas, and offers courts for bocce, basketball and volleyball.</p>
        <p>The Commute</p>
        <p>From Stuyvesant Town, the L train stops at the corner of First Avenue and 14th Street, a few minutes by subway from the lines that run to Midtown and the Financial District from Union Square. Still, residents on the Avenue C side have a half-mile walk to that stop; alternatives include the M14D and the M21 buses.</p>
        <p>On the Peter Cooper Village side, residents face a long walk along 23rd Street to the No. 6 train at Park Avenue South, or a ride down 23rd Street on the M23 bus, which arrives every five to eight minutes during the day. There are also the new trolleys.</p>
        <p>The Schools</p>
        <p>Outside the perimeter of the complex are several strong public schools -- among them, on East 19th Street, Public School 40, where 88.3 percent of students met standards on state and city math tests in 2004-05, and 89.1 percent met English standards. The citywide averages that year were 65.1 and 60.9 percent.</p>
        <p>That year at Middle School 255, at the same address, 86 percent met standards in English, 86.4 in math, versus 43.3 and 40.8 percent citywide.</p>
        <p>One of the few public high schools close by, on East 15th Street, is the Institute for Collaborative Education, where students averaged 493 on the verbal section of the SAT in 2004-05 and 451 in math, compared with 497 and 511 statewide.</p>
        <p>One nearby private option is the United Nations International School, which teaches Grades 9 through 12 on a campus north of Peter Cooper Village along F.D.R. Drive. In 2007-8, annual tuition ranged from $22,000 to $22,500.</p>
        <p>The History</p>
        <p>In the 19th century, before Town and Village arrived, the chunk of Manhattan they now occupy was in the Gashouse District, a slum filled with odoriferous gas tanks and tenement residents, including the Gashouse Gang, a group of misfits whose name was later adopted by a less objectionable club called the St. Louis Cardinals.</p>
        <p>Nearly 200 years before the Gashouse tenements were erected, the land was farmed by Peter Stuyvesant, the final director-general of the New Amsterdam settlement before it was taken over by the British.</p>
        <p>In 1943, the city and MetLife cleared away most tenements to build housing, in large part for veterans returning from World War II.</p>
        <p>Going Forward</p>
        <p>In the short term, residents say, more grocery stores are needed in the area, as a D'Agostino on the grounds of Stuyvesant Town closed and Gristedes, also, will soon close two local stores.</p>
        <p>And looking ahead, the sheer size of the complex makes it unlikely that market-rate prices can be imposed, across the board, very quickly. As Mr. Miller of Miller Samuel put it, ''It would take past our lifetime with the number of units they have.''</p>
        <p>LIVING IN: STUYVESANT TOWN AND PETER COOPER VILLAGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
