<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gators Top Bruins in Rematch And Earn Right to Play in Another</title>
    <meta content="01gators" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/sports/ncaabasketball/01gators.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837460"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Florida</org>
        <org class="online_producer">University of California</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Noah, Joakim</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E4DC1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="773" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gators Top Bruins in Rematch And Earn Right to Play in Another</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Gators Top Bruins in Rematch and Earn Right to Another</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEE JENKINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jenkins, Lee</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, March 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three Florida underclassmen bypassed the N.B.A. draft and put millions of dollars on hold so they might get a chance to play one college basketball game.</p>
        <p>It will be Monday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After drubbing the Bruins in the national championship game 362 days ago, Florida beat them again Saturday night in the national semifinal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three Florida underclassmen bypassed the N.B.A. draft and put millions of dollars on hold so they might get a chance to play one college basketball game.</p>
        <p>It will be Monday night.</p>
        <p>Joakim Noah, Al Horford and Corey Brewer, all of whom could have left Florida and been first-round draft choices last spring, will get what they came back for -- a chance to win a second consecutive national championship.</p>
        <p>The Gators were better than U.C.L.A. last season and they are still better. After drubbing the Bruins in the national championship game 362 days ago, Florida beat them again Saturday night in a 2007 national semifinal, 76-66.</p>
        <p>The matchup was not much more competitive this time around. With all of Florida's slam dunks and 3-point shots and chest-thumping celebrations, the game looked almost like an old replay left over from last April.</p>
        <p>The Gators' victory sets up a national championship game against Ohio State on Monday night at the Georgia Dome, and another kind of rematch.</p>
        <p>The Florida basketball team beat Ohio State by 26 points in December and the Florida football team beat Ohio State by 27 points for the national championship in January. The Gators are going for their third straight national title in a major sport.</p>
        <p>''We're back in the championship game,'' Brewer said. ''You can't ask for anything else.''</p>
        <p>During this season, and even in this N.C.A.A. tournament, Florida sputtered through some extended lapses. But U.C.L.A. seems to bring out the best in this team. The Gators found another gear Saturday night, showing off their championship form.</p>
        <p>As far as Florida's place in history, the Gators may have just passed the great Nevada-Las Vegas teams of the early 1990s. U.N.L.V. blew out Duke in the 1990 championship game, but fell to the Blue Devils in the semifinals the following year.</p>
        <p>Florida did not succumb to the same fate. And now, the Gators could become the first repeat champions since Duke in 1992 and only the second since U.C.L.A. in 1973.</p>
        <p>For the second year in a row, the Bruins' season ended with a loss to Florida. Arron Afflalo, U.C.L.A's all-American guard, had three fouls by the midpoint of the first half and did not score until there was less than seven minutes left in the game.</p>
        <p>''The disappointing thing is that I couldn't be on the floor to help my teammates,'' Afflalo said. ''I really wanted to be there for them and be that aggressive leader for them.''</p>
        <p>With Afflalo on the court, U.C.L.A. is an inconsistent offensive team. Without him, the Bruins can barely score.</p>
        <p>Florida, on the other hand, has about six players who can fill up the stat sheet. Brewer dominated the first half and Lee Humphrey took over in the second, as the two guards combined for 33 points and 8 3-pointers.</p>
        <p>Noah and Horford, perhaps the best N.B.A. prospects on the Florida roster, were content to play complementary roles. They passed quickly out of double teams, pulled down a combined 28 rebounds, and deferred to Chris Richard, a backup forward who came off the bench and made all seven of his field goal attempts.</p>
        <p>There was no good reason to think the Bruins could win Saturday night. They lost by 16 points in last year's national championship game and then lost their starting point guard, Jordan Farmar, to the Los Angeles Lakers.</p>
        <p>The Gators, meanwhile, brought back every one of their decorated starters. They got to return to the Georgia Dome, where they won the Southeastern Conference tournament this season. They even enjoyed the majority of the crowd support.</p>
        <p>For a little while, Florida fans and players were unnerved by U.C.L.A.'s vaunted defense. The Gators did not make a field goal for the first seven and a half minutes of the game. Midway through the first half, they led by 9-6.</p>
        <p>Florida is unaccustomed to such low numbers, but the Gators still looked comfortable. Humphrey, who missed his first three 3-pointers, made his next three. Horford crashed the boards. Noah started the celebration.</p>
        <p>''This has been our main focus all year,'' Humphrey said. ''This is a new season and an opportunity for a new championship.''</p>
        <p>As difficult as it may be for a college basketball team to repeat, the task is more daunting if that team has to win this kind of rematch. But the stakes were too high for Florida to let down Saturday. Everyone had come too far.</p>
        <p>Humphrey and Richard are seniors. Noah, Horford and Brewer could soon declare for the N.B.A. draft. This group of Gators will play its last game together Monday.</p>
        <p>Florida has reached the finish line.</p>
        <p>N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
