<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Homeowners Seek Safer Alternatives to Pesticides</title>
    <meta content="01wemainWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/01wemain.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837192"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ENVIRONMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lawns</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gruen, Abby</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Organic Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organic Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Landscaping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E0DA1030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Homeowners Seek Safer Alternatives to Pesticides</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Homeowners Seek Safer Alternatives to Pesticides</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY GRUEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gruen, Abby</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Growing number of homeowners in Westchester County, NY, concerned about exposure to pesticides, are moving toward natural lawn care; professional landscapers tell customers to adjust their expectations when they make change because lawns need several years to build up resistance to bugs and weeds; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN it comes to feeding her family, Liz Kaplan buys organic products because, like many consumers, she says she believes that food grown without chemicals is healthier. She takes the same approach to her gardening and lawn care, and in the six years she has lived in her house in Sleepy Hollow, she has never used pesticides on her property. ''It feels wrong to have any extra chemicals around,'' Ms. Kaplan, 45, said.</p>
        <p>On a recent spring day, Ms. Kaplan bought compost at the Stone Barns Center for Food and Agriculture in Pocantico Hills to use in an organic greenhouse project at the Washington Irving School in Tarrytown. ''We're trying to get the kids to grow produce,'' she said. ''We hope they will feel more connected to where their food comes from.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN it comes to feeding her family, Liz Kaplan buys organic products because, like many consumers, she says she believes that food grown without chemicals is healthier. She takes the same approach to her gardening and lawn care, and in the six years she has lived in her house in Sleepy Hollow, she has never used pesticides on her property. “It feels wrong to have any extra chemicals around,” Ms. Kaplan, 45, said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN it comes to feeding her family, Liz Kaplan buys organic products because, like many consumers, she says she believes that food grown without chemicals is healthier. She takes the same approach to her gardening and lawn care, and in the six years she has lived in her house in Sleepy Hollow, she has never used pesticides on her property. ''It feels wrong to have any extra chemicals around,'' Ms. Kaplan, 45, said.</p>
        <p>On a recent spring day, Ms. Kaplan bought compost at the Stone Barns Center for Food and Agriculture in Pocantico Hills to use in an organic greenhouse project at the Washington Irving School in Tarrytown. ''We're trying to get the kids to grow produce,'' she said. ''We hope they will feel more connected to where their food comes from.''</p>
        <p>There is growing concern around the country about the risks of exposure to synthetic pesticides in the food and the environment. Westchester County, which is one of the largest pesticide users in New York, according to the State Department of Environmental Conservation, is trying to reduce that dependence. In the last few years, the county, which maintains 18,000 acres, has effectively eliminated the use of pesticides in its parks and greatly reduced its use on golf courses.</p>
        <p>The county has also become partners with the Grassroots Environmental Education Program, which has trained hundreds of private landscapers in nonchemical methods, and the insurance company Swiss Re's United States headquarters in Armonk joined the program this month, eliminating pesticide use on its 127-acre corporate campus.</p>
        <p>''We are blessed with great water here,'' said the county executive, Andrew J. Spano in an interview last week. ''There aren't many places in the world that have such good water, so for us to contaminate it is really criminal. These pesticides get into the water, and they are unhealthy for people and animals.''</p>
        <p>Most homeowners, however, have not given up on chemicals. Cosimo Ferraro, 53, a landscaper in Mamaroneck who has been in business for 29 years, said his average customer gets five applications a year. ''Only one of my customers has ever asked me to cut down on chemicals,'' he said. ''Her children play on the lawn, so she asked me to stop.''</p>
        <p>The theory behind pesticide-free lawn care is that when properly managed, natural biological systems in soil can support healthy turf grass that is dense and strong enough to withstand damaging pests and weeds. But giving up pesticides is difficult for many homeowners -- their lawns can look worse because the chemicals sustain a population of plants that become dependent on them, said Frank S. Rossi, a professor of turf science at Cornell University.</p>
        <p>Professional landscapers say they tell their customers to adjust their expectations when they change to natural lawn care.</p>
        <p>''Most of the time, organics don't give the results chemicals do -- you need several years to try to build up your lawn to resist the bugs and the weeds,'' said Joseph Tinelli, president of the New York State Turf and Landscape Association. ''After that, it will be just about as good. There is a lot of trial and error involved. You don't get overnight results.''</p>
        <p>Patricia J. Wood, founder and executive director of Grassroots Environmental Education, a nonprofit group based in Scarsdale and Port Washington, on Long Island, that tries to educate the public about the links between environmental toxins and health, says she believes that the ultimate motivation for homeowners to make the change to natural lawn care is concern about chemical exposure.</p>
        <p>''We're trying to change people's thinking from having a weed-free lawn to having a worry-free lawn,'' Mrs. Wood said.</p>
        <p>Over the last four years, about 400 landscapers in Westchester and on Long Island have taken the 16-hour Grassroots course and certification program. This year, the group is expanding its outreach to include corporate headquarters like Swiss Re's. There are 5,000 acres in the county under corporate stewardship, according to a county spokesman.</p>
        <p>The Grassroots Healthy Lawn Program begins with soil testing to determine how to balance the soil and make it more hospitable so organisms like microbes and earthworms can thrive. Other aspects include: letting the grass grow longer to retain moisture; leaving the grass clippings on the lawn to provide extra nitrogen; and over-seeding. ''We always say, 'Our best weed control is a bucket of grass seed,' '' Mrs. Wood said.</p>
        <p>On a mild spring day last week, Jay Archer, president of John Jay Landscape Development in Katonah, went to inspect the quality of the compost at Hudson Pines Farms, a privately owned Sleepy Hollow cattle farm that abuts the nonprofit Stone Barns Center's property and is managed cooperatively by the two facilities.</p>
        <p>Mr. Archer, whose company maintains the grounds of hundreds of private residences, schools and commercial buildings in Connecticut and New York, says high-quality compost is an essential part of his springtime program, especially for the 40 percent of his customers who are almost pesticide free.</p>
        <p>Grabbing a handful of the finished compost from below a silver tarp, he ran the coarse, dark, soil-like grains through his fingers, gauging the feel of the organic material it contains, specifically the healthy bacteria and fungus that will promote plant growth.</p>
        <p>''Compost also adds water-holding capacity, so you can water less,'' Mr. Archer said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Archer, 50, who also lectures on ecosystems and habitat restoration at the New York Botanical Garden, said he believed that ''healthy landscapes equal healthy people.'' He worries that the suburban standard of chemically enhanced lawns means people are losing touch with nature.</p>
        <p>''I travel all over Westchester, and I see very few children playing on these toxic lawns,'' he said. ''People avoid their landscapes because they are intuitively aware of what makes them look that way. They are missing the birds and the butterflies and the vibrancy that nature is full of.''</p>
        <p>ENVIRONMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
