<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Social Engineer</title>
    <meta content="04well.mendes.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="T: Design Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="128" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Style; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/style/tmagazine/04well.mendes.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837087"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E7D91230F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2011" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Social Engineer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Social Engineer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Herbert Muschamp</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Muschamp, Herbert</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>São Paulo lives in the clouds. All those ranks of skyscrapers march unstoppably toward the horizon, and the visitor is struck by the relative scarcity of inviting public spaces on the ground. This imbalance is accentuated by the helicopter pads, some of them flamboyantly cantilevered, that adorn many of the city's tallest buildings. As you drive along the street, even riding in the back of a snazzy black sedan driven by a handsome, armed chauffeur dressed in an Armani suit, you're aware of being consigned to an inferior form of transportation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Paulo Mendes Da Rocha has spent his life thinking about public and private space, designing monumental buildings for the masses and houses for those who admire his intellectual poetry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>São Paulo lives in the clouds. All those ranks of skyscrapers march unstoppably toward the horizon, and the visitor is struck by the relative scarcity of inviting public spaces on the ground. This imbalance is accentuated by the helicopter pads, some of them flamboyantly cantilevered, that adorn many of the city's tallest buildings. As you drive along the street, even riding in the back of a snazzy black sedan driven by a handsome, armed chauffeur dressed in an Armani suit, you're aware of being consigned to an inferior form of transportation.</p>
        <p>What's an old Marxist architect to do in such advanced capitalist circumstances? Become a philosopher, I would say, based on a few days spent looking at the work of Paulo Mendes da Rocha, the most highly respected architect in a city that has come to symbolize the hyper-consumerist ethos of contemporary Brazil. An hour's conversation with Mendes da Rocha, the winner of last year's Pritzker Architecture Prize, did not suffice to clarify whether the dream of a worldwide worker's utopia is part of his global outlook. Yet I suspect that, as was the case with many 20th-century intellectuals, Mendes da Rocha understood Marxism to be chiefly a framework for conversation about the difference between life as it is and life as it should be.</p>
        <p>That can mean having a conversation about concrete, for example. Concrete is this old Marxist's material of choice. It is stone for the masses and a symbol of the worker's fortitude. Mendes da Rocha describes this material as ''liquid stone,'' which is both literally true and a clue to the architect's symbolic way of thinking. In Mendes da Rocha's eyes, concrete seems to retain something of its liquid state, even after it has hardened into solid structure. Not that this perception seems so outlandish in a land where no mere manufactured substance looks capable of long withstanding the tropical humidity. In short order, Mendes da Rocha's concrete buildings may liquefy once again.</p>
        <p>Doesn't everything in Brazil? Isn't the prospect of imminent meltdown what we love most about this country of rippling pavements, fluid movements, musical wave after wave?</p>
        <p>As it happens, the surfaces of some of Mendes da Rocha's concrete walls are already damp enough to support mosses and other miniature flora. Architects often refer to the ''bloom'' on concrete, the blotchy texture and coloration that at times attains the effect of abstract painting. In Mendes da Rocha's case, the bloom is literal. Tropical organisms give his concrete the image of a garden, blurring the separation between the building and the landscape in which it is set: clay.</p>
        <p>The image is reinforced by one of Mendes da Rocha's recurring architectural motifs: the roofs of his buildings are often covered with shallow pools of water. The thin aquatic layer performs a thermal function and makes a nice rooftop getaway. Square paving stones make it possible to walk, or sit, on these meditative surfaces.</p>
        <p>But the pools also serve the poetic function of knitting together the sky above and the earth below. Clouds are reflected in the rainwater that steams the sultry atmosphere, a device far more elegant than a helicopter for projecting yourself into São Paulo's frequently overcast skies.</p>
        <p>At 78 years old, Mendes da Rocha is a quarter century younger than Oscar Niemeyer, the Brazilian architect whose name is most familiar to North Americans. That's too young to have framed modern architecture's belief in a utopian society but old enough to have worked alongside those who believed with Le Corbusier that architecture is a progressive force with the power to neutralize the need for violent revolution. And he was old enough to suffer for such beliefs during the military dictatorship that ruled Brazil from 1964 to 1985.</p>
        <p>The generals had techniques other than architecture for stifling revolution as well as more peaceful progressive causes. Censorship, surveillance and the banning of opposition political parties were among their routine tactics. Not that I want to give anyone up north ideas, but there were mikes under the tables in popular restaurants.</p>
        <p>Unlike Niemeyer, who exiled himself to France during this period, Mendes da Rocha remained in Brazil to face the harsh martial music.</p>
        <p>He was not entirely without work in those years. A soccer stadium in 1973 and the Brazil Pavilion at the 1970 Osaka World's Fair are among the most important projects of his career. But his practice did not flourish again until the country's democratic institutions were restored.</p>
        <p>Speaking with him now, I have the impression that he does not regret one moment of his personal and professional struggles. He chose to meet me at the most decrepit of the three offices he currently maintains. It is housed in a building that was designed in 1947 as the headquarters of the Institute of Brazilian Architects. The building will soon be restored to its pristine modern lines, but its downtown neighborhood is seedy -- the striptease dive next door wouldn't rank as top-flight night life -- and I doubt very much that the restoration will penetrate Mendes da Rocha's modest space. It is his palace of memory.</p>
        <p>The cold-water sink and the peeling walls bear witness to the rise and fall of optimism in 20th-century architecture as well as to the persistence and fragile renewal of that spirit into the 21st. A naked light bulb with a tin shade dangles from the ceiling. Mendes da Rocha is and is not joking when he points out its resemblance to the bulb that blazes in Picasso's ''Guernica.''</p>
        <p>It was Anthony Blunt, the art historian and Soviet spy, who attacked Picasso for attempting to reckon with social injustice in painting ''Guernica.'' ''There is something pathetic in the sight of a talented artist struggling to cope with a problem entirely outside his powers,'' Blunt wrote in 1937. Blunt lived to recant that view, among others. But some today may feel similarly vexed by Mendes da Rocha's residential designs for private clients. Communist houses for rich people? Didn't we have our fill of that in the postwar United States suburbs? This is nonetheless the type of building I've traveled here to see.</p>
        <p>Mendes da Rocha says he will accept commissions for houses only from friends. Isabella Prata and her husband, Idel Arcuschin, are fortunate enough to be among the chosen. Prata is one of Brazil's most prominent collectors of contemporary art -- or was. She says living in the house enabled her to shift her course from consuming culture to producing it. Last year, she opened Escola São Paulo, an art school with a progressive sense of mission. The seed for this project was planted by the cursory air Mendes da Rocha took toward her treasures when the two were talking about how her valuable collection should be displayed in the new house. His suggestion: ''Why don't you keep it in some drawers?''</p>
        <p>The clients had one overarching requirement. The couple wanted a house where they and their two teenage children could live both separately and together. The result is a three-story Brazilian family sandwich. The kids can occupy living areas on the ground story, while adults hang out one floor above; bedrooms for all are on three. An elevator lets the young folk bypass the old folk on their way to bed.</p>
        <p>This social and spatial intersection reflects Mendes da Rocha's creative approach as well as his clients' wishes. Many of his projects establish a similarly interlocked relationship between differentiated space. On the second floor of this house, for example, the living area runs parallel to an outdoor terrace of identical width. The arrangement creates an inside, an outside and a double-size space, with its own character, that is made from the two combined. The same floor design covers both areas, a unifying element that emphasizes the continuity between opposites.</p>
        <p>Stairs are a big deal in Mendes da Rocha's buildings. Ramps, too. In contrast to the raw concrete of the walls, these transitional spaces are articulated with sculptural refinement.</p>
        <p>The effect is to intensify the fleeting sensation of being on two levels at once. The stairwell in the Prata-Arcuschin house compresses the kinetic energy that flows more freely throughout the house. ''You will know that the house is successful,'' Mendes da Rocha told Prata, ''if you get up one morning and find yourself dancing barefoot through it.''</p>
        <p>But watch out for loose chairs! There are, by my count, five separate seating areas on the house's second floor, including a long dining table that is the preferred informal gathering spot during the day. Scanning the living room is like taking in a panorama of remembered conversations and those yet to occur, and it is easy to imagine how Prata's idea for an art school might have taken shape here. The school's improvisational program sets the discussion of art and ideas on a par with the production of aesthetic objects. In much the same way that public lectures have surged in popularity in New York and other North American cities, the school reflects an increasing awareness of the audience as a force for cultural change.</p>
        <p>The terrace outside, by contrast, is unencumbered by furniture. It's a platform, an empty stage, my favorite type of urban space. Visually enclosed at one end, like a plaza, by the tall buildings across the street, the terrace might be a metaphor for the plateau on which São Paulo itself is built and will go on being built and unbuilt, in waves of hysteria or conviction that rise and crash with the years.</p>
        <p>I am trailed around São Paulo by an idea that Mendes da Rocha offered to Annette Spiro in an interview included in her beautiful 2002 monograph of his work. ''Essentially, there is no private space,'' he said. ''There are only varying degrees of publicness.'' I love being in a city where an architect can say such a thing, as I marvel at a city where people are not afraid to put helicopter pads on the tops of buildings, even if the reason is that they're too scared by street crime to come down.</p>
        <p>Some might interpret Mendes da Rocha's remark as an old socialist worker's refrain about the inferiority of the individual to the group. But I chose to hear it as the view of an artist for whom the realm of individual fantasy is so private as to be essentially unknowable. This realm can scarcely even be talked about, much less represented in architectural space. It can be sensed only indirectly in the interaction between a self and the society it inhabits.</p>
        <p>Mendes da Rocha has dramatized that interaction in spatial counterpoint. Point: He persuaded Prata to buy only one of the two plots next door and not to put a pool in it. Then he prevailed on her to turn the wooded lot into a garden. The client becomes, in effect, the groundskeeper for the future.</p>
        <p>Counterpoint: At the far end of the living area on the second floor, the space makes a bend on the way to the kitchen. Here Mendes da Rocha has planted a single easy chair in glorious isolation. It faces a wall of glass. Through it, the solitary sitter can gaze out at the terrace below and the cityscape beyond. The tops of the park's trees beckon in the middle distance. After dark, reflected in the glass, this crystal cell of selfhood hovers over a tropical city of night. It is a setting for the thinker as a triple agent: a figure loyal to self and to the world of others but above all to the art of revealing the inherent dignity of their complex transactions.</p>
        <p>But let the architect complete the picture. In his interview with Spiro, Mendes da Rocha continued: ''One could say that even a human being who is apparently alone -- sitting at three o'clock in the morning in a small room, in a cell, before the light of a single burning candle, writing a poem with a goose feather -- is basically a public human being; for his poem may perhaps be read for centuries thereafter.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
