<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For 'Blue-Collar' Musicians, A 'Factory' All Their Own</title>
    <meta content="01NJFactoryNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/01NJFactory.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837216"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arts Factory Theater (Bayonne, NJ)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theaters (Buildings)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bayonne (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hughes, Jennifer V</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CEFD91030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="654" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For 'Blue-Collar' Musicians, A 'Factory' All Their Own</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For ‘Blue-Collar’ Musicians, a ‘Factory’ All Their Own</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER V. HUGHES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hughes, Jennifer V</byline>
      <dateline>BAYONNE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Arts Factory Theater, new performance space in Bayonne, NJ, that reflects its neighborhood's blue-collar industrial presence; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GRADIE STONE has been performing professionally for 30 years, but she still describes herself as a ''blue-collar musician.'' So although she has played established jazz clubs like Trumpets in Montclair, she was happy to bring her cabaret act recently to the Arts Factory Theater, a new performance space on the edge of a modest residential neighborhood here.</p>
        <p>''To be honest, there are not a lot of gigs out there for working-class musicians,'' said Ms. Stone, who lives in Paterson.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>BAYONNE.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GRADIE STONE has been performing professionally for 30 years, but she still describes herself as a ''blue-collar musician.'' So although she has played established jazz clubs like Trumpets in Montclair, she was happy to bring her cabaret act recently to the Arts Factory Theater, a new performance space on the edge of a modest residential neighborhood here.</p>
        <p>''To be honest, there are not a lot of gigs out there for working-class musicians,'' said Ms. Stone, who lives in Paterson.</p>
        <p>Her attitude made her a good fit for the Arts Factory Theater.</p>
        <p>''The idea for the space is to reflect the blue-collar industrial presence that Bayonne was and, to some extent, still is,'' said Dennis Argul, a city native who books acts for the center. ''We want to mass-produce art -- that's what the idea of this space is.''</p>
        <p>The upstairs hall, seating up to 250, is now used for comedy nights and other larger-scale acts, but eventually the owners intend to stage musicals and other plays there. The 150-seat downstairs cabaret features an oval-shaped bar and cafe tables. Tickets for upstairs events range from $15 to $30, and the cabaret has no cover or drink minimum.</p>
        <p>The Arts Factory Theater has been in the works for about five years, according to Carl Gonzalez, a playwright, teacher and lifelong city resident who is one of the two co-owners. For a location they leased 280 Avenue E, which had been the home of the Ukrainian National Home, a civic center. Mr. Gonzalez and his friend Greg Bukshowany, a videographer, then spent $200,000 renovating the space, ripping out floor-to-ceiling wood paneling in the cabaret and installing more than $8,000 worth of lights and sound equipment in the main hall.</p>
        <p>The space, if nondescript-looking, has been active since its opening; on some weeks there is entertainment on five nights. Mr. Argul, a teacher and trombonist -- he plays bass trombone with Diane Moser's Composers Big Band -- has been keeping the calendar full.</p>
        <p>Gerry Niewood, the multi-instrumentalist who played for years with Chuck Mangione, is appearing in the cabaret on Friday and Saturday. A Cinco de Mayo festival on May 5 will include salsa and merengue music and dancing, as well as Latin cuisine.</p>
        <p>As Ms. Stone sang ''I Thought About You'' to about 20 people in the cabaret, Peter Urciuoli of Bayonne and Michael Italiano of Jersey City sipped cocktails and tapped their hands on the bar in time to the music.</p>
        <p>''This is the first time we've been here, but it won't be the last,'' Mr. Urciuoli said. Mr. Italiano compared Ms. Stone to Peggy Lee, and the men reminisced about the days when Bayonne had big-band dance halls. The friends sometimes go into New York for shows, but they dislike the drive and the expense.</p>
        <p>''If this catches on, we'll have our own little 'Village' right here,'' Mr. Urciuoli said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gonzalez said the Arts Factory is hoping eventually to receive city and state financing and corporate sponsorship.</p>
        <p>At the same time that Ms. Stone was working through her collection of jazz standards, upstairs the husband-and-wife comic team Jeff Norris and Renee DeLorenzo performed for about 75 people. Mr. Norris riffed on timeless Jersey themes, like road rage and high tolls.</p>
        <p>''I paid 35 cents to back out of my driveway,'' said Mr. Norris, who appears weekly on the ''Jersey Guys'' radio show on 101.5 FM. After their set was over, the couple said they enjoyed playing emerging places like the Arts Factory Theater.</p>
        <p>''It's really nice to be a part of a production that is bringing the arts and entertainment to a community that doesn't have it,'' Ms. DeLorenzo said. Perhaps unable to resist one last joke, she added, ''I think the biggest hangout now is the T.G.I. Friday's.''</p>
        <p>Information about coming programs at the Arts Factory Theater, 280 Avenue E, Bayonne, is available by calling (201) 436-6700 or online at www.baypac.org.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
