<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HABITATS/Riverside Drive; Sometimes, Shopping Can Be Therapeutic</title>
    <meta content="01habi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/realestate/01habi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837238"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Habitats | Riverside Drive"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Psychology and Psychologists</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shaw, Dan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Benson, April Lane</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Habitats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Psychology and Psychologists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Psychology and Psychologists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Charivari</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE5D81030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1156" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HABITATS/Riverside Drive; Sometimes, Shopping Can Be Therapeutic</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sometimes, Shopping Can Be Therapeutic</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN SHAW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shaw, Dan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Habitats column on April Lane Benson, who chose co-op apartment on Riverside Drive in Manhattan 20 years ago because it was two blocks from favorite clothing boutique; Benson has remained in apartment, turning one bedroom into office for her work as psychotherapist, ironically specializing in shopping addiction; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN April Lane Benson's older son, Eric, went off to the University of Chicago four years ago, she made his bedroom, with its windows overlooking Riverside Park, into her office. ''I do all my writing here,'' said Dr. Benson, a psychotherapist who culled and edited the essays for ''I Shop Therefore I Am: Compulsive Buying and the Search for Self'' (Jason Aronson, 2000).</p>
        <p>The boxes under Eric's bed contain the components for Dr. Benson's new Stopping Overshopping self-help kit, which includes a workbook, CD and shopping diary for organizing one's thoughts when the urge to shop strikes. ''We're still in the mom-and-pop stage,'' she said. ''I have an intern who puts them together and sends them out.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>April Lane Benson chose her apartment 20 years ago for its proximity to Charivari, the West Side’s first high-fashion store.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN April Lane Benson's older son, Eric, went off to the University of Chicago four years ago, she made his bedroom, with its windows overlooking Riverside Park, into her office. ''I do all my writing here,'' said Dr. Benson, a psychotherapist who culled and edited the essays for ''I Shop Therefore I Am: Compulsive Buying and the Search for Self'' (Jason Aronson, 2000).</p>
        <p>The boxes under Eric's bed contain the components for Dr. Benson's new Stopping Overshopping self-help kit, which includes a workbook, CD and shopping diary for organizing one's thoughts when the urge to shop strikes. ''We're still in the mom-and-pop stage,'' she said. ''I have an intern who puts them together and sends them out.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Benson's interest in shopping is both personal and professional.</p>
        <p>When she and her husband, Jim, a lawyer who reverse-commutes to New Jersey, were looking for family-size apartments 20 years ago, one of the selling points of this three-bedroom co-op on Riverside Drive with seven windows facing the Hudson was that it was two blocks from her favorite boutique, which had become a mainstay of her life.</p>
        <p>''Somehow, my unconscious selected this store, Charivari, which was right here on Broadway between 83rd and 84th Street,'' she said wistfully. Charivari, which filed for bankruptcy in 1997, was the first high-fashion store on the Upper West Side. From the mid-1970s to the mid-1990s, it was the city's most avant-garde retailer, introducing New Yorkers to innovative designers from Belgium and Japan.</p>
        <p>For Dr. Benson, shopping at Charivari was not recreational. It was therapeutic. During her childhood on Long Island, shopping trips with her mother had been power struggles, and Dr. Benson said that she came to feel that she did not deserve nice things. She thought all mother-daughter relationships were similarly fraught until a wealthy family from Manhattan moved in next door.</p>
        <p>The mother and daughter next door had fun buying clothes, and they became her role models. ''They used to talk about this store, Hirshleifer's,'' she recalled. ''They would talk about going there as if they were visiting a friend. The store would serve them coffee and rugelach. Hirshey's, as they called it, would order things for them if they didn't have their color or size.'' (Hirshleifer's was then in Forest Hills, Queens, but has now moved to Long Island, to the Americana Manhasset.)</p>
        <p>When Dr. Benson discovered Charivari in the 1970s, she decided to make it her Hirshleifer's. ''This was something I wanted in my life,'' she said. ''I wanted to take better care of myself in this way. I got to experience myself as worthy, that it was O.K. to like clothes. That it was O.K. to go to a place that charged full price. That it was O.K. to go to a place that was a little bit out of the ordinary. Over the years, I made friends with the people who worked at the store. It was very healing.''</p>
        <p>She was such a good customer that when Mr. Benson walked by the plate-glass windows on Broadway, the sales staff would often come out to greet him. ''I thought it was a stitch,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Shortly after moving into the Riverside Drive apartment, the Bensons made an astonishing discovery. The mother from next door on Long Island had grown up in this same Riverside Drive building, in the same ''B'' apartment line but on a different floor.</p>
        <p>''It was one of those 'six degrees of separation' moments,'' Mr. Benson said. For Dr. Benson, it was validation: ''It was like karma. I felt I was where I was supposed to be.''</p>
        <p>Her relationship with Charivari led her to create a workshop called ''When Shopping Heals,'' because ''shopping can be a real source of self-definition,'' she said. ''You look in the mirror and ask, 'Is this me?' ''</p>
        <p>As she began to study the scholarly literature on shopping, she realized that it was women who found shopping too easy who needed help. (According to a study published last year in The American Journal of Psychiatry, 5.8 percent of Americans are compulsive shoppers.)</p>
        <p>''Shopping and dieting are the two main ways that contemporary women handle the ups and downs of life,'' said Dr. Benson, who is a founder of the Center for Anorexia and Bulimia. ''Overshopping is the smiled-upon addiction.''</p>
        <p>Her ability to deliver sound bites is why she is one of the talking heads in a new documentary, ''What Would Jesus Buy?'' which was produced by Morgan Spurlock, whose movie ''Super Size Me'' lambasted McDonald's. She hopes the film will raise awareness about compulsive shopping. ''This is really a problem people want to deny,'' she said. ''They feel ashamed because it is not yet legitimized as a bona fide psychological problem.''</p>
        <p>She admits that sometimes she herself bought more than she needed. ''But I never overshopped so much that it was a financial problem,'' she said, explaining that other programs like Debtors Anonymous are as focused on underearners as on overspenders. ''I think there were times when my husband wasn't so happy with how much I was spending.''</p>
        <p>Her modest walk-in closet seems proof that she is a controlled shopper. The top shelves are not crammed with handbags but photo albums. The clothes are not crowded together, and each piece is given special treatment. She pulls out an elaborate blouse from Anne Fontaine and a hand-knit sweater from Julie Artisans' Gallery on Madison Avenue. ''It was my 50th birthday present,'' she said, a gift she chose to be a present from her husband.</p>
        <p>But there are numerous bracelets. ''That used to be my trademark, a bracelet made of buttons,'' she said. ''They were all made just for me. Some of the buttons were from my mother's button box and some came from the dressmaker at Charivari.''</p>
        <p>Her interest in craftsmanship extends beyond fashion to the design of her apartment, which features several murals by different artisans. In the foyer, there is a bucolic river scene that echoes the one from her windows. ''It could be the Hudson up north where it gets narrow,'' she said.</p>
        <p>By the kitchen table, there is a mural of a formal Italianate garden. ''I often think that one day Jim and I may spend time in Tuscany and learn Italian,'' she said, ''so I had the painter do this view.''</p>
        <p>The framed artworks in the hallway connecting the bedrooms were all done by Eric or his brother, Corey, when they were little. (Eric is now 22 and will graduate from the University of Chicago this year; Corey is 18 and will graduate from the Dalton School.)</p>
        <p>As Dr. Benson reminisces about their taking Friday night ''sketch and lecture'' classes at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, she suddenly remembers that her older son is coming home for the weekend.</p>
        <p>''I have to move all my stuff out of his room,'' she said. ''I don't mind because I love to have him at home.''</p>
        <p>Habitats | Riverside Drive</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
