<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Shore Dimly Seen</title>
    <meta content="01Lives.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="64" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/magazine/01Lives.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837041"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Lives"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Memory</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tumors</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chaffin, Tom</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Tumors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tumors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tumors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Memory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Emory University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Whitman, Walt</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Stevens, Wallace</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Dylan, Bob</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Porter, Cole</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E5DA1230F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="797" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Shore Dimly Seen</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Shore Dimly Seen</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Tom Chaffin</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chaffin, Tom</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tom Chaffin article on comfort and encouragement he derived in being able to recall scraps of poetry and song lyrics during his recovery from surgery to remove benign brain tumor (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One Saturday morning last summer, I was lingering in bed, listening to NPR and reaching for my first sip of coffee, when an overwhelming, shaking sensation on a tectonic scale rumbled through my skull and entire body -- an experience not unlike being dragged by wild horses down a darkened gravel road. I came to in a hospital, surrounded by equipment and strangers. An attending doctor told me that I'd had a seizure caused by a brain tumor -- a benign tumor of a type called meningioma. I was headed for brain surgery.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Making your way back to yourself, with the help of Whitman, Dylan and Cole Porter  after brain surgery.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One Saturday morning last summer, I was lingering in bed, listening to NPR and reaching for my first sip of coffee, when an overwhelming, shaking sensation on a tectonic scale rumbled through my skull and entire body -- an experience not unlike being dragged by wild horses down a darkened gravel road. I came to in a hospital, surrounded by equipment and strangers. An attending doctor told me that I'd had a seizure caused by a brain tumor -- a benign tumor of a type called meningioma. I was headed for brain surgery.</p>
        <p>After the operation, during my first moments of renewed consciousness, I realized I was not the same. The right side of my body was numb. My right leg, arm, fingers and toes all refused orders, ignoring synaptic cues from my brain. The tumor had been on my brain's left side, which contains the motor nerves that control the body's right side. Then a physician approached. ''Name for me,'' he said, ''all the animals you can think of.''</p>
        <p>''Dog . . . ,'' I began. ''Cat. . . . '' I think I managed four. Beyond that, I was in excruciating pain. I was given morphine.</p>
        <p>Two days after the operation, according to a notebook my wife, Meta, kept, a speech therapist asked me a series of simple questions. ''Do you peel a banana before eating it?'' she asked. ''After,'' I answered. About a week later, Meta tells me, I managed my first complete sentence: ''I miss . . . my dog.'' Attempting one afternoon to ask about the status of a request I'd made for Tylenol, I could only say, ''What? . . . ''</p>
        <p>Then about a day or so later, while working with a speech therapist, I found that I could recall the first dozen or so lines of a favorite poem, Walt Whitman's ''Song of the Open Road'':</p>
        <p>''Afoot and light-hearted, I take to the open road,</p>
        <p>Healthy, free, the world before me,</p>
        <p>The long brown path before me, leading wherever I choose.''</p>
        <p>I soon discovered that I could repeat -- and find solace in -- other bits of cherished poetry and song lyrics long committed to memory: shards of Whitman, Wallace Stevens, Bob Dylan, Cole Porter and others.</p>
        <p>Otherwise, despite the gifted and empathetic medical professionals, there wasn't much progress. My days became an exasperating game of charades. My interior thoughts remained fluid, but the words to express them had vanished into some neurological Bermuda Triangle.</p>
        <p>I was in the hospital for a week, stayed in a rehab center for two weeks and pursued outpatient speech and physical therapy for another two months. During the entire ordeal, I stayed on a Hunter Thompson-worthy regimen of medications, from morphine to steroids. And each pill offered its own unique side effects. The steroids, for instance, which combated postoperative brain swelling, guaranteed that I slept for no more than three or four hours during most 24-hour periods.</p>
        <p>After I came home, as I wandered, doped up, through my cloud banks of aphasia, I felt oddly estranged from my past. A phrase I recalled from Jean-Paul Sartre, about foundering on ''the reef of solipsism,'' haunted me. I found myself organizing my papers and other worldly possessions into the wee hours of the morning. I devoted all-night sessions to the compulsive sorting of books, papers, CDs and anything else that could be alphabetized. I gathered photos and other souvenirs and ultimately had a friend frame and hang them in my study. (I was too weak for the job.) They included snapshots of me taken over the years in fondly recalled places -- China, the French Alps, Cuba, Gramercy Park, Paris, Walden Pond, South Dakota and other locales. At the center of the collection, I placed a framed cartoon clipped years ago, in which two men are seated at a bar and one is proposing a Whitmanesque toast: ''I celebrate myself.''</p>
        <p>Eventually, slowly, I came back. I recovered the use of my body's right side, as well as my verbal abilities. And the day came when a psychologist asked me again to name as many animals as I could think of. This time -- feeling cocky and drawing on years of bird-watching -- I tore into a litany of avian species: the Carolina chickadee, the yellow-rumped warbler, the belted kingfisher and on and on.</p>
        <p>I've since learned that an ability to repeat memorized passages from poems and the like is a common trait among expressive aphasia patients. Even so, I can't help thinking of those words and images of my interior life as essential landmarks in finding my way back to the outside world. Those lines that came back to me, when all other words failed, provided me with a geography of hope, like some distant but clearly visible shoreline.</p>
        <p>Lives Tom Chaffin, a visiting scholar at Emory University, is the author of ''Sea of Gray: The Around-the-World Odyssey of the Confederate Raider Shenandoah.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Tom Chaffin, a visiting scholar at Emory University, is the author of ''Sea of Gray: The Around-the-World Odyssey of the Confederate Raider Shenandoah.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
