<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rangers Hold Their Ground in a Tight Playoff Race</title>
    <meta content="01rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/sports/hockey/01rangers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837445"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Philadelphia Flyers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Jagr, Jaromir</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E5DC1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="808" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rangers Hold Their Ground in a Tight Playoff Race</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rangers Hold Their Ground in a Tight Playoff Race</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinser, Lynn</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, March 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Rangers stood or sat in clusters around televisions in the visiting locker room at Wachovia Center on Saturday night. The matter of their 6-4 victory against the Flyers had been settled, but they watched one of their playoff pursuers, Toronto, Sunday's opponent, intently on the screens above them.</p>
        <p>When Toronto defeated Pittsburgh in overtime, a few Rangers muttered, but mostly they went back to the routine of their playoff chase. The Rangers had another victory in hand, but they played sloppily against a bad Flyers team and that, along with Toronto's victory, made Sunday's game at Madison Square Garden loom even larger.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Rangers and the Flyers interrupted their hard-hitting season series with a goal-scoring show Saturday night at, with the Rangers getting two goals from Jaromir Jagr.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Rangers stood or sat in clusters around televisions in the visiting locker room at Wachovia Center on Saturday night. The matter of their 6-4 victory against the Flyers had been settled, but they watched one of their playoff pursuers, Toronto, Sunday's opponent, intently on the screens above them.</p>
        <p>When Toronto defeated Pittsburgh in overtime, a few Rangers muttered, but mostly they went back to the routine of their playoff chase. The Rangers had another victory in hand, but they played sloppily against a bad Flyers team and that, along with Toronto's victory, made Sunday's game at Madison Square Garden loom even larger.</p>
        <p>''We knew we had to win this game,'' Jaromir Jagr said right before he took a spot on a table as overtime started in the Toronto game. ''We play tomorrow, probably the most important game of the season. With a two-goal lead, you want to play smart, save some energy for tomorrow, but you can't play that way. You let them back in the game.''</p>
        <p>Jagr scored twice -- only his fourth two-goal game this season, giving him a total of 28 goals -- to help keep the Flyers from interfering with the Rangers' playoff plans. The Rangers left the ice with 89 points and another night to enjoy sitting in the seventh of eight playoff spots. They are a point behind sixth-place Tampa Bay, but have only a 1-point edge on eighth-place Montreal. Toronto sits another point back in ninth.</p>
        <p>But the Rangers also know if they play their final four games the way they played Saturday, and the way they did in Tuesday's 6-4 loss at Montreal, they could lose their hold on a playoff berth.</p>
        <p>When his postgame news conference opened with a question about the Rangers' hot offense, Rangers Coach Tom Renney stopped and laughed. He seemed far more concerned about the suddenly shaky defense.</p>
        <p>''I'm not sure I'd use the word alarmed, but it certainly has my attention,'' Renney said. ''We're giving up free ice. We're giving up free pucks. We're giving up free opportunities for the opponent to score from pretty prime areas. We have to tidy up our game.''</p>
        <p>Before the loss to Montreal, the Rangers had given up two or fewer goals in 10 of 12 games. They were keeping the opponents' scoring chances low and making goaltender Henrik Lundqvist's job relatively routine.</p>
        <p>In contrast, the past two games have been free-for-alls. Lundqvist gave up four goals to Montreal before being pulled, and he gave up another four, two to the light-scoring forward Ben Eager, against the Flyers.</p>
        <p>''I don't think we played our best tonight,'' Lundqvist said. ''We battled, but we have to manage the puck better. The last four games, we've allowed a lot of chances against us.''</p>
        <p>Renney was quick to say the fault was not Lundqvist's.</p>
        <p>''If we keep the chances to 10 or 12, Henrik's great,'' Renney said. ''The fact of the matter is, he's a victim of a sloppy team in front of him.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers let down a bit Saturday because they went ahead by 3-1 in the first period on goals by defenseman Thomas Pock, forward Ryan Callahan and Jagr.</p>
        <p>Jagr's first goal was perhaps the prettiest of his season. He took a pass from Michael Nylander inside the blue line, stick-handled around forward R. J. Umberger, slid between defenseman Derian Hatcher and Braydon Coburn and fired a shot inside the left post and the stick of goalie Martin Biron.</p>
        <p>''He is one of the best players in the world and he just needs a little space and he can do things like that to hurt you,'' Eager said.</p>
        <p>Jagr scored again in the second, beating Biron with another wrist shot, as did Martin Straka and Petr Prucha, to keep the Flyers from making the game closer.</p>
        <p>But it was still too close for the Rangers' tastes.</p>
        <p>''I think we know we didn't play great,'' Rangers forward Sean Avery said. ''It's imperative that we stay positive. I think tomorrow is exactly what we need, coming back to M.S.G. and playing a big game against Toronto. I think we need a little kick in the butt because I don't think we've been great the last four or five days.''</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>For a change in this bitter series, the Rangers and Flyers did not fight. In their last meeting, 10 days ago at Madison Square Garden, Rangers forward Colton Orr knocked out Flyers forward Todd Fedoruk with a punch.  Rangers defenseman Fedor Tyutin, who had hoped to return from his knee injury this weekend, is now more likely to return for Tuesday's game against the Islanders. ''He's absolutely pain free,'' Tom Renney said. ''It's a matter of making sure he can sustain shifts over 60 minutes.'' Tyutin has missed 13 games with a sprained medial collateral ligament.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
