<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Phelps's Shot at 8 Golds Ends on Relay Team's Miscue</title>
    <meta content="01swimming" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/sports/othersports/01swimming.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837456"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SWIMMING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Testosterone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Testosterone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Testosterone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hormones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">FINA</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Phelps, Michael</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Thorpe, Ian</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E4DC1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1187" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Phelps's Shot at 8 Golds Ends on Relay Team's Miscue</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Phelps’s Shot at 8 Golds Ends on Relay Team’s Miscue</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clarey, Christopher</byline>
      <dateline>MELBOURNE, Australia, Sunday, April 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As it turned out, the only thing that could stop Michael Phelps from winning eight gold medals at these world championships was someone else's mistake.</p>
        <p>It came in the final heat of the men's medley relay Sunday morning, just when it seemed likely that Phelps would establish a new gold standard for a major swim meet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the day that Michael Phelps matched Ian Thorpe’s record of six gold medals, a French newspaper reported that a drug test Thorpe underwent last May has produced curious results.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As it turned out, the only thing that could stop Michael Phelps from winning eight gold medals at these world championships was someone else's mistake.</p>
        <p>It came in the final heat of the men's medley relay Sunday morning, just when it seemed likely that Phelps would establish a new gold standard for a major swim meet.</p>
        <p>Phelps had already qualified for the final in his last individual event by recording the fastest time in the heats of the 400 individual medley Sunday, the last day of the championships. He then took a rest as his American teammates -- Ryan Lochte, Scott Usher, Ian Crocker and Neil Walker -- tried to qualify the American team for the final of the medley relay.</p>
        <p>It should have been a lock, but instead it turned into a shock, as Crocker left the starting block one hundredth of a second too early when Usher reached the wall at the end of the second leg.</p>
        <p>The American team was disqualified after the race, even though their time would have been the fastest overall by more than two seconds.</p>
        <p>The United States assistant Eddie Reese said that American coaches examined the footage of the takeoffs and declined to protest, and now Phelps will have to wait until next year's Olympics in Beijing for another chance to win eight gold medals in the same major meet.</p>
        <p>He can still set a championships record with seven gold medals if he wins the 400 individual medley, an event in which he holds the world record. Seven has been swimming's iconic number since Mark Spitz won seven times at the 1972 Summer Olympics.</p>
        <p>Crocker, who had lost to Phelps in a tight 100 butterfly final on Saturday night, declined comment after the relay. Reese, who is also Crocker's personal coach, said he had never seen him start too soon.</p>
        <p>Instead, Walker was left to search for explanations in public.</p>
        <p>''Ian had an exciting race last night; to get up for the morning relay is tough,'' Walker said.</p>
        <p>And what about Phelps? ''Michael was doing something nobody has ever done before,'' Walker said. ''I think everybody will be disappointed, Michael included. But he'll see this is what happens sometimes.''</p>
        <p>Swimming's rules allow a relay swimmer the leeway to start three hundredths of a second early. Crocker left four hundredths of a second early. ''That's just incomprehensible, that amount of time,'' Walker said.</p>
        <p>It was the latest strange twist during the final weekend here. On Saturday, when Phelps matched Ian Thorpe's record of six gold medals in a world championships, Thorpe's legacy was called into question when the French sports newspaper L'Équipe reported that a drug test he had last May was being challenged by swimming's world governing body, FINA.</p>
        <p>Although the organizers of the championships have been unable to fill all the seats in Rod Laver Arena for any of the swimming sessions, there was not an empty seat in the sometimes testy news conference in which FINA confirmed that it had filed an appeal to the Court of Arbitration for Sport. FINA is seeking clarification of the results of a drug test performed on an Australian swimmer by the Australian Sports Anti-Doping Authority.</p>
        <p>Neither FINA officials nor the antidoping officials would confirm whether the swimmer in question was Thorpe, who retired in November at 24, citing burnout.</p>
        <p>According to the report, the test in May 2006 showed that Thorpe had an unusually high ratio of testosterone to epitestosterone and also showed abnormally high levels of luteinizing hormone, a substance produced naturally by the pituitary gland that aids in testosterone production.</p>
        <p>Richard Ings, the chairman of the Australian antidoping authority, confirmed that those were the substances in question, but he said his group's inquiry into the test results, which he cautioned should not be considered a positive test, was still continuing despite FINA's appeal.</p>
        <p>''There is no suggestion that an athlete has committed an antidoping violation,'' Ings said. ''Media reports that an athlete has failed a drug test are simply incorrect.''</p>
        <p>Ings also said that the athlete in question was to have been notified by the antidoping agency next week, but was informed Saturday because of the news media speculation.</p>
        <p>Swimming Australia's chief executive, Glenn Tasker, said that the Australian team coach, Alan Thompson, informed Thorpe about the report in L'Équipe on Saturday.</p>
        <p>''I know Ian is vehemently opposed to any sort of performance-enhancing drug,'' Tasker said.</p>
        <p>Tasker was not concerned only for Thorpe. He was also concerned for the story's impact on the championships. ''I think it would be a real pity if this was to overshadow what Michael Phelps is doing here,'' Tasker said. ''It would be a travesty of justice because we are seeing something that no one's ever done before.''</p>
        <p>That is not quite true, at least not yet. Phelps has broken four world records here and won six gold medals in six events, matching what Thorpe did in 2001 in Fukuoka, Japan.</p>
        <p>Phelps played down the numbers, saying that until Saturday he was unaware that Thorpe's six gold medals was a record.</p>
        <p>''Honestly, the biggest thing about this week is trying to get through it and trying to compete at this level and try to swim as many events as I'm doing and be able to do them good,'' Phelps said.</p>
        <p>Even without Phelps, this would have been a remarkable meet for the Americans, who have won 17 gold medals, three short of their best total for a world championships, established in 1978.</p>
        <p>Saturday continued the trend. The Stanford University swim captain Benjamin Wildman-Tobriner sprang a surprise to win the 50 freestyle in 21.88 seconds. Margaret Hoelzer set an American record of 2 minutes 7.16 seconds in the 200 backstroke, and Kate Ziegler completed her long-distance double by winning the 800 freestyle.</p>
        <p>The 100 butterfly was considered Phelps's toughest race here.</p>
        <p>Crocker set the world record in 2005 by overwhelming Phelps in the world championships in Montreal, and Crocker led the way in the preliminaries, which explains why he was in Lane 4 for the final and Phelps was in Lane 6.</p>
        <p>Crocker was still ahead at the turn, but the 21-year-old Phelps had enough energy to catch him late in the final lap and lunge past him at the wall.</p>
        <p>''Honestly, I thought I botched the finish,'' Phelps said. ''I honestly thought I got touched out because of the finish, and it ended up being the other way around.''</p>
        <p>Phelps's time of 50.77 seconds was the third fastest ever and a personal best; Crocker finished in 50.82.</p>
        <p>When the race was over, Crocker swam over his lane line toward Phelps, shook his hand and congratulated him on his phenomenal meet. But Crocker looked particularly pensive on the medal stand.</p>
        <p>''It's hard to get up and slay the dragon every time,'' Crocker said.</p>
        <p>But Crocker still managed to keep Phelps from winning a gold medal here, and from the look on his face as he shuffled away from the relay gone bad Sunday, there was no joy in it.</p>
        <p>''Ian is very, very sensitive,'' Reese said, ''and this is real tough for him.''</p>
        <p>SWIMMING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
