<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amid Theft Charges, the Struggle to Lure Volunteers</title>
    <meta content="01limainLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/01limain.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837150"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC PROTECTION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Embezzlement</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Volunteers</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Selden (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rather, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embezzlement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volunteers</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE2D61330F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1043" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amid Theft Charges, the Struggle to Lure Volunteers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Amid Theft Charges, the Struggle to Lure Volunteers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rather, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on problems many volunteer fire departments across Long Island face as membership continues to drop and corruption allegations come to light; seven former and current fire officials, including five from Selden, have been accused of stealing taxpayers' money for personal expenses; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HAD they been pictures in a children's book, they would have been confounding: See the firefighters marching in the parade with their shiny trucks, cheered as heroes. See the firefighters marched into court wearing shiny manacles, charged as thieves.</p>
        <p>Within the last month, both scenes unfolded in Suffolk County. As firefighters were appearing in one local St. Patrick's Day parade after another, seven former and current fire officials were accused of stealing public money for private use. The corruption allegations are coming at a difficult time across Long Island for many volunteer fire departments, which are struggling to recruit new members to help fill their thinning ranks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>HAD they been pictures in a children’s book, they would have been confounding: See the firefighters marching in the parade with their shiny trucks, cheered as heroes. See the firefighters marched into court wearing shiny manacles, charged as thieves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HAD they been pictures in a children's book, they would have been confounding: See the firefighters marching in the parade with their shiny trucks, cheered as heroes. See the firefighters marched into court wearing shiny manacles, charged as thieves.</p>
        <p>Within the last month, both scenes unfolded in Suffolk County. As firefighters were appearing in one local St. Patrick's Day parade after another, seven former and current fire officials were accused of stealing public money for private use. The corruption allegations are coming at a difficult time across Long Island for many volunteer fire departments, which are struggling to recruit new members to help fill their thinning ranks.</p>
        <p>''Ideally, we'd like to be at about 200 members,'' said William M. Winning, a New York City police detective who is chief of the Brentwood Fire Department, which now counts 160 members. ''Of course, anything over that would be fantastic.''</p>
        <p>Nassau County, which has 31 fire districts and 71 departments, has about 9,000 volunteer firefighters, said Carey A. Welt, a division supervisor in the Nassau County fire marshal's office and a fire commissioner in East Meadow. Suffolk County, with 94 districts and 109 departments, has 10,000 to 10,500 firefighters, said Warren Horst, the county's chief fire marshal.</p>
        <p>Each district is supervised by an elected board of fire commissioners, who oversee the budget and levy property taxes. Some fire and government officials estimate that over all, the number of firefighters is down roughly 30 to 35 percent from its peak in the 1970s.</p>
        <p>Still, while the current number of firefighters is slightly above the pre-9/11 level on Long Island -- where there were about 18,600, according to Nassau and Suffolk fire officials at the time -- it has been on a downward trend since the 1970s, Mr. Welt and Mr. Horst said. And fire calls are markedly up.</p>
        <p>The New York State Office of Fire Prevention and Control said that fire, ambulance and other emergency calls in Nassau increased about 12 percent from 2001 to 2005, to 32,987 from 29,473. In Suffolk, calls were up even more -- from 2004 to 2005, the number rose to 51,099 from 39,534 -- reflecting broader service, like responding to calls reporting carbon monoxide alarms.</p>
        <p>In Brentwood, the Fire Department has launched an aggressive recruiting drive, with an emphasis on community service, firehouse camaraderie, pension benefits and the tax savings supporters say volunteers provide their communities when compared with a paid force.</p>
        <p>A study by the National Volunteer Fire Council estimated those annual tax savings at $2.8 billion for all of New York. In a calculation based on the study, the Brentwood department said its volunteers saved about $29 million for the 100,000 or so residents in the district.</p>
        <p>The Brentwood recruiting drive highlights perks that include pensions ($30 a month for each year of service, with eligibility beginning after five years); a 10 percent reduction in property taxes; education scholarships; and life and disability insurance. Such benefits make firefighters in Brentwood and other Long Island communities not quite uncompensated volunteers and also involve public expense.</p>
        <p>Even with the incentives, many young potential volunteers, even some whose families have a three- or four-generation tradition of firefighting, say they do not have the time to train, attend meetings and come running when the siren wails.</p>
        <p>According to Brentwood's Chief Winning, the announcement of the corruption accusations did not help. ''The timing was kind of rough,'' he said, noting that the arrests, on March 20, came just one day after the Suffolk County executive, Steve Levy, had joined department chiefs and firefighters at a news conference to kick off their recruiting drive.</p>
        <p>Thomas J. Spota, the Suffolk County district attorney, said that those arrested included seven former and current members of fire districts or departments and one current member of an ambulance company. Five were current or former Selden Fire District commissioners accused of stealing taxpayers' money for personal expenses. Mr. Spota's office is seeking restitution of $52,600 that he said the five men from Selden charged to the district for travel and lodging in connection with district junkets. All five pleaded not guilty.</p>
        <p>The largest theft, the district attorney's office said, occurred in the Montauk Fire District. Its former secretary-treasurer was charged with stealing more than $500,000 to pay for gambling, meals, clothes, travel and private school for her son.</p>
        <p>In another charge, a Terryville Fire Department member was accused of pocketing more than $5,000 while heading the department's carnival committee in 2005. Another defendant, the president of East Moriches Community Ambulance, is accused of altering receipts for about $6,500 in personal purchases.</p>
        <p>Chief Winning said he hoped that prospective recruits would differentiate between the department, which responds to fires and other emergencies, and its board, which holds the purse strings.</p>
        <p>Most of the commissioners in Long Island's 125 fire districts rose through the ranks of volunteers and won election in light voter turnouts. In Selden, the district said that combined, the five current and former commissioners accused of stealing public money had more than 100 years of experience as firefighters.</p>
        <p>A lawyer for the district, Raymond G. Perini, said the charges against the five men largely had to do with meals for their wives that they charged to the district while at conferences and meetings. Any mistakes they may have made, he said, should not overshadow ''the fact that these men have dedicated themselves to the fire services in Selden.''</p>
        <p>Asked whether the commissioners had known that it was illegal to use district money to pay for family members' meals, Mr. Perini declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Fire districts in New York manage more than $1 billion in taxpayer money, the state comptroller's office said. In announcing new regulations for fire district officials in February, the comptroller, Thomas P. DiNapoli, said that auditors ''have uncovered a number of troubling details over the years regarding unchecked spending and other financial oversight problems at fire districts.''</p>
        <p>Legislation enacted last year requires fire districts with more than $200,000 in revenues to undergo an independent audit every year. The districts are chartered by the state, and thus are beyond the jurisdiction of county comptrollers.</p>
        <p>A new law also requires districts to hold annual budget hearings, adopt a code of ethics and set rules for travel and travel expenses.</p>
        <p>PUBLIC PROTECTION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
