<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Turkish Delights, With Appetizers the Best</title>
    <meta content="01njdineNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/01njdine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837226"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/PATERSON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kafe Teria (Paterson, NJ, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corcoran, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E7D81030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="850" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Turkish Delights, With Appetizers the Best</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Turkish Delights, With Appetizers the Best</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CORCORAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Corcoran, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Corcoran reviews Kafe Teria restaurant in Paterson, NJ; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW JERSEY has a few urban neighborhoods so transformed and enlivened by immigrant cultures that entering them is like going abroad. Drive down Bergenline Avenue in Union City or into the Ironbound in Newark, and you may be tempted to reach for your passport. A different language appears in the windows, the energy level kicks up a notch, and even the weather seems to change.</p>
        <p>Main Street in Paterson is like that. In recent years its lower end, near the Clifton border, has become a souk, a bustling, thriving Middle Eastern market. Taking a bus north on Main on a recent evening, I began scrawling names of food establishments in my notebook: Al-Aqsa Supermarket, Al Khayam Restaurant, Al Basha, Alnakheel  and that was just the A's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Beyond its appearance, Kafe Teria in Paterson has two things that set it apart: its parentage and its commendable effort to reach a wider audience.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW JERSEY has a few urban neighborhoods so transformed and enlivened by immigrant cultures that entering them is like going abroad. Drive down Bergenline Avenue in Union City or into the Ironbound in Newark, and you may be tempted to reach for your passport. A different language appears in the windows, the energy level kicks up a notch, and even the weather seems to change.</p>
        <p>Main Street in Paterson is like that. In recent years its lower end, near the Clifton border, has become a souk, a bustling, thriving Middle Eastern market. Taking a bus north on Main on a recent evening, I began scrawling names of food establishments in my notebook: Al-Aqsa Supermarket, Al Khayam Restaurant, Al Basha, Alnakheel  and that was just the A's.</p>
        <p>For the most part these places looked small, homey and dim. Then there was Kafe Teria. On a timeworn and shabby block, it jumped out like an architect's rendering -- sleek and bright, all windows, sharp angles and vibrant pastels. Like many of its neighbors, this 11-month-old restaurant is Turkish (the name is a play on cafeteria), and the menu offers few surprises. Beyond its appearance, Kafe Teria has two things that set it apart: its parentage and its commendable effort to reach a wider audience.</p>
        <p>For both of these qualities you can thank its owners, the husband-and-wife team of Sait Esen and Sabrina Cagar. Mr. Esen, 40, emigrated from eastern Turkey in 1992, planning a career as a mechanical engineer. Instead, he fell in with his uncle Yahya Bicaksiz, owner of Beyti Kebab in Union City, one of the region's best-known Turkish restaurants. Mr. Esen still manages Beyti Kebab, and a bakery, Beyti Sweet Shop, in Clifton.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cagar, 34, grew up in Paterson, a few blocks from the old drugstore that is now the site of Kafe Teria. Her first career was marketing, and it shows in the restaurant's elegance, down to the crisp graphics of its bilingual menu.</p>
        <p>The best single item at Kafe Teria, however, doesn't appear on the menu. It is the bread, baked in the restaurant's own pizza ovens. (Pizza? More about that in a moment.) Slightly dense and redolent of yeast and fresh-baked wheat, it comes in long, flattish loaves that are scored like dinner rolls for easy tearing. It makes an ideal delivery vehicle for the best things that are on the menu: mezeler, or appetizers.</p>
        <p>The roll call is familiar to anyone who has ever tried and failed to save room for a Turkish entree. In particular, acili ezme, or spicy vegetable spread, stands out: a bright-red blend of chopped tomatoes, bell and hot peppers, walnuts, olive oil and lemon juice, it is particularly radiant in Kafe Teria's fluorescent ambience.</p>
        <p>At the same high level are lebni, the lustrous dip of yogurt, dill, cucumbers and walnuts; hummus, the chickpea-and-sesame spread; patlican salata, the smoky, garlic-laden eggplant salad; and sigara boregi, fried cigar-shaped wrappers filled with feta cheese. It would be easy to make a meal of a few of these appetizers and any of eight Turkish pizzettes, or little pizzas, especially lahmajun, a thin eight-inch disk of tender dough painted with spicy ground meat. It's all of $2.50; thicker and more substantial oblongs with toppings like kashari cheese, garlicky sausage, chopped meat or Turkish pastrami (or all four) are $8 to $12.</p>
        <p>There's no harm in filling up on the preliminaries, because the main courses are pretty ordinary. Thanks to chunks of veal, stewed okra had a pleasing depth of flavor, but was seriously overcooked. Chicken kebabs were dry and short on flavor. Two kinds of fried fish -- whiting and tilapia -- were disagreeably salty. Thin but tasty lamb chops and broiled lamb patties filled with cheese were the best entrees; each had a bracing lamb flavor.</p>
        <p>Flaky phyllo pastries from the Beyti Sweet Shop, heavy with honey and nuts, make a perfect finish, along with a demitasse of smoky, sludgy Turkish coffee or a clear-glass beaker of head-clearing tea. Then it's back out to the souk, where Kafe Teria lights up the block, a welcome ambassador from Turkey by way of Union City.</p>
        <p>Kafe Teria  939 Main Street  Paterson  (973) 977-3934</p>
        <p>GOOD</p>
        <p>THE SPACE A bright, comfortable, thoroughly modern corner storefront in the heart of Paterson's Middle Eastern district. Midsize, with 64 seats. Wheelchair accessible.  THE CROWD Casual couples and families, mainly from the neighborhood.  THE STAFF Warm and accommodating.  THE BAR Bring your own wine or beer; Turkish wines and after-dinner drinks can be bought at several nearby shops.  THE BILL Breakfast, $7; lunch (appetizer, entree and drink), $9; dinner entrees, $9 to $16. Visa and MasterCard only.  WHAT WE LIKE Bread; hummus, lebni (yogurt dip), patlican salata (roasted eggplant salad), acili ezme (spicy vegetable spread), sigara boregi (feta-filled wrappers); lamb chops, grilled lamb patties; Turkish pastries.  IF YOU GO Open daily. Breakfast: 10 a.m. to noon. Lunch: noon to 2 p.m. Dinner: 2 to 10 p.m. Reservations recommended for groups. Parking is available on the street or behind the restaurant.  Reviewed April 1, 2007</p>
        <p>DINING/PATERSON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
