<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Expanded Health Program For Children Causes Clash</title>
    <meta content="01health" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/washington/01health.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837375"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pediatrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">House of Representatives</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E4D61130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="869" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Expanded Health Program For Children Causes Clash</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Expanded Health Program for Children Causes Clash</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bush administration says it will resist Democratic plans for threefold expansion of Children's Health Insurance Program; is concerned that program will replace private insurance and involve sharp increase in coverage of children from families with higher income levels; Bush wants to increase allotments to states to provide nearly $30 billion over next five years; Democrats seek total of $75 billion; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bush administration says it will strenuously resist Democratic plans for a threefold expansion of the Children's Health Insurance Program, ensuring a clash with Congress over the most important health care legislation being considered this year.</p>
        <p>Administration officials said that much of the new government coverage proposed by Democrats would simply replace private insurance, and they expressed concern about a sharp increase in the proportion of children covered by public programs in the last decade.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bush administration says it will strenuously resist Democratic plans for an expansion of the Children’s Health Insurance Program.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Bush administration says it will strenuously resist Democratic plans for a threefold expansion of the Children's Health Insurance Program, ensuring a clash with Congress over the most important health care legislation being considered this year.</p>
        <p>Administration officials said that much of the new government coverage proposed by Democrats would simply replace private insurance, and they expressed concern about a sharp increase in the proportion of children covered by public programs in the last decade.</p>
        <p>Dennis G. Smith, the federal official in charge of Medicaid and the Children's Health Insurance Program, said 45 percent of all children were now covered by the two programs, up from 28 percent in 1998.</p>
        <p>''The original intent of the Children's Health Insurance Program was to cover low-income children who were uninsured,'' Mr. Smith said in an interview. Democratic proposals to cover millions of additional children ''would change the complexion of the program and take it away from its original intent,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''At higher income levels,'' Mr. Smith said, ''families are more likely to have private health insurance. If they become eligible for the Children's Health Insurance Program, you are more likely to be substituting public for private coverage. You could add billions of dollars to the program without insuring many new kids.''</p>
        <p>The administration says that 36 million children were enrolled in the programs last year -- 29.4 million in Medicaid and 6.6 million in the Children's Health Insurance Program. More than eight million children remain uninsured.</p>
        <p>Democrats want to expand the children's health program as a first step to universal coverage, a goal endorsed by all the party's major candidates for president.</p>
        <p>But Michael O. Leavitt, the secretary of health and human services, said the program ''should not be the vehicle by which we insure every adult and every child in America.''</p>
        <p>The federal government has spent $25 billion on the children's health program in the last five years. President Bush wants to increase allotments to the states by $4.8 billion, providing a total of nearly $30 billion over the next five years.</p>
        <p>Democrats want to triple spending on the program, by adding $50 billion, for a total of $75 billion over the next five years.</p>
        <p>Representative John D. Dingell, Democrat of Michigan, who is leading House efforts to expand the program, said he was aware that Medicaid and the children's insurance program covered nearly half of all children.</p>
        <p>''It's a great investment,'' Mr. Dingell said in an interview. ''One of my problems with this administration is that there are people who know the cost of everything and the value of nothing.''</p>
        <p>If the White House resists Democratic plans for a major expansion of the popular program, Mr. Dingell said, ''that's a ground on which I will be very happy to fight.''</p>
        <p>The Bush administration says it wants to ''refocus the program on low-income uninsured children.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has proposed reducing federal payments to the states for coverage of children with family incomes exceeding twice the poverty level. At least 17 states already cover children above that level, and governors in several other states are trying to expand eligibility by raising the income limit.</p>
        <p>A family of four is considered poor if its annual income is less than $20,650. Mr. Dingell and Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton, Democrat of New York, recently introduced bills that would encourage states to cover children up to four times the poverty level -- up to $82,600 for a family of four.</p>
        <p>While opposing any major expansion of the program, Mr. Bush has proposed a new tax deduction to help people buy private health insurance. In the past, he proposed tax credits.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dingell scoffed at the idea. ''To rely on a bunch of good-hearted insurance companies whose purpose is, quite frankly, to make money -- to expect them to go into the charitable business of taking care of a lot of hungry and impoverished kids -- strikes me as the height of folly,'' Mr. Dingell said.</p>
        <p>Congress faces a deadline for action on the Children's Health Insurance Program. Legal authority for the program expires on Sept. 30, and 14 states expect to run out of money before then.</p>
        <p>The House and Senate have voted to provide about $750 million to help those states get through the next six months. But the money is included in a war spending bill that Mr. Bush has threatened to veto because it sets a timetable for gradually withdrawing most American troops from Iraq. So the future of the child health program is unclear.</p>
        <p>Representative Jack Kingston, Republican of Georgia, said he was distressed to see Democrats pursuing what he called ''a huge expansion of government-sponsored health care.''</p>
        <p>''The Children's Health Insurance Program has given Democrats a wide-open door for socialized medicine,'' Mr. Kingston said in an interview. But he added, ''The door was left open by Republicans, who were in the majority when we passed the original legislation in 1997.''</p>
        <p>Republicans senators like Orrin G. Hatch of Utah and John H. Chafee of Rhode Island helped create the program. Some Republicans, like Senators Olympia J. Snowe of Maine and Gordon H. Smith of Oregon, are working with Democrats to expand the program, a goal supported by many governors of both parties.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
