<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In This Final Four, Powerhouses Loom Large</title>
    <meta content="01george" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/sports/ncaabasketball/01george.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837410"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">George Mason University</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Ohio State University</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Georgetown University</org>
        <org class="online_producer">University of California</org>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Florida</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Donovan, Billy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Larranaga, Jim</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Boeheim, Jim</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E4DD1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="879" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In This Final Four, Powerhouses Loom Large</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">It’s Hard Getting to the Final Four, Even if You’re Supposed To</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
      <dateline>Atlanta</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Greg Oden may only be passing through, on his way to becoming somebody's work in progress in the N.B.A. The truth is, right now Oden is Ohio State's work in progress, a raw talent learning not to do impetuous things.</p>
        <p>In the only Final Four this 7-foot center may ever be part of, Oden was the extra factor last night as Ohio State held off Georgetown, 67-60. Oden scored all 13 of his points and grabbed all 9 of his rebounds in the second half, to back up all the marvelous talent that Ohio State has accumulated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There was no George Mason this year, which raises the question of whether any of us truly appreciated what George Mason accomplished last year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Greg Oden may only be passing through, on his way to becoming somebody's work in progress in the N.B.A. The truth is, right now Oden is Ohio State's work in progress, a raw talent learning not to do impetuous things.</p>
        <p>In the only Final Four this 7-foot center may ever be part of, Oden was the extra factor last night as Ohio State held off Georgetown, 67-60. Oden scored all 13 of his points and grabbed all 9 of his rebounds in the second half, to back up all the marvelous talent that Ohio State has accumulated.</p>
        <p>Now Ohio State will play another powerhouse, the defending champion from Florida, which dominated U.C.L.A., 76-66, later last night, as this Final Four comes down to a couple of top-seeded teams.</p>
        <p>No team at the Georgia Dome last night vaguely resembled George Mason, the 11th-seeded midmajor team that hustled its way into the Final Four last year. This raises the question of whether any of us truly appreciated what Coach Jim Larranaga accomplished last year. For that matter, there was no upstart like fourth-seeded Louisiana State, which reached the semifinals last year.</p>
        <p>Florida Coach Billy Donovan has said the teams in this Final Four comprise ''probably the toughest field I think we can all remember in a long time.'' Ohio State and Florida were seeded first in their original groups of 16, and Georgetown and U.C.L.A. were seeded second. These are the kinds of teams that can stock up on the best players in the country, load up their bench with players who could start almost anywhere else. Woe to the midlevel colleges that think that they can emulate them.</p>
        <p>''I think there's unrealistic expectations when you have teams -- when George Mason does what they do,'' Syracuse Coach Jim Boeheim said Thursday in a news conference. Boeheim added that powers at many colleges think, ''If they can do it, we can do it,'' and added, ''That type of mentality exists.''</p>
        <p>Ohio State's Thad Matta was able to persuade the towering Oden to spend at least one year of college in Columbus. And Georgetown, rebuilding under John Thompson III, has kept Craig Esherick's recruit Roy Hibbert, all 7 feet 2 inches of him, around for three years.</p>
        <p>Last night, Oden and Hibbert collided. Quite literally. These kind of bodies do not materialize easily in the midmajor Round of 16 kind of universities, bless their hearts. Yet the duel between giants fizzled quickly as Oden picked up two offensive fouls in the first 2 minutes 41 seconds.</p>
        <p>''It was just me being out there and being excited,'' he said later. ''I mean, I can't lower my shoulder. I can't move setting ball screens.''</p>
        <p>Rather than be out there playing timidly, Oden went to the bench with zero points and zero rebounds. And he sat, and he sat, and he sat, right through the first half.</p>
        <p>Frankly, Ohio State looked better without him. Matta has loaded up with talented players who can move and shoot and think. And to be fair, Oden missed the first month of the season because of a wrist operation and ever since has been discovering his inner ambidextrous self under national scrutiny.</p>
        <p>''I hated the fact we played the first seven games without Greg,'' Matta said after the game. ''But today is another example where it probably helped us because those guys never skipped a beat. They just came in and got the job done.''</p>
        <p>He wasn't about to try it for a second half, if he could help it. ''I told Greg at halftime, he should be well rested,'' Matta said dryly.</p>
        <p>Asked how he felt at halftime, Oden said: ''I was out for 17 minutes. I wanted to get in there and just tear the rim down, you know.''</p>
        <p>He came close, throwing his large body around early in the second half, blasting a few dunks over and through Georgetown. In foul trouble himself, Hibbert finished with 19 points but only 6 rebounds, not quite enough.</p>
        <p>Ohio State and Georgetown had survived questionable calls by the referees earlier in the tournament, supporting the somewhat fatalistic view of Donovan that all four teams here, including his Gators, should consider themselves fortunate to have survived.</p>
        <p>''I don't know if people truly understand how hard it is,'' Donovan had said, talking about reaching the Final Four.</p>
        <p>Because of George Mason's spurt last year, many colleges have had grandiose dreams. Coaches have been dismissed or forced out after failing to reach goals, realistic or otherwise. Lives have been disrupted. Yet Donovan has suggested that any team needs to be a little lucky.</p>
        <p>''I think if you would start this tournament all over again, there would maybe be four different teams sitting up here right now,'' Donovan said Friday. ''That's not taking away from what anybody's done up to this point in time.''</p>
        <p>Some colleges will be spending extravagantly to try to be the next George Mason, but that is not Ohio State's issue. The Buckeyes look smooth and versatile without Oden but at times they are intimidating with him. Now Oden will play at least one more college game against a Florida team so deep and so talented that it doesn't even have a work in progress like Oden.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
