<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For a Melting Pot, Scoops of Coconut Ice</title>
    <meta content="01ices" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/01ices.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837390"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice Cream</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vendors, Street</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Delicioso Coco Helado</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ramirez, Anthony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ice Cream</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice Cream</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Serrano, Jose E</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE1DE1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="682" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For a Melting Pot, Scoops of Coconut Ice</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For a Melting Pot, Scoops of Coconut Ice</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY RAMIREZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ramirez, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York street vendors begin annual warm-weather offerings of Caribbean gelato known as Delicioso Coco Helado; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was a special kind of opening day yesterday. But there was no Carl Pavano, no Tom Glavine, no peanuts, no Cracker Jack, no opening pitch.</p>
        <p>There was, instead, an opening-day scoop of a Caribbean gelato known as Delicioso Coco Helado, or in English, Delicious Coconut Ice Cream.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Carts selling Caribbean gelato have become as much a part of warm-weather New York as sidewalk ice chests and boys jimmying open fire hydrants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was a special kind of opening day yesterday. But there was no Carl Pavano, no Tom Glavine, no peanuts, no Cracker Jack, no opening pitch.</p>
        <p>There was, instead, an opening-day scoop of a Caribbean gelato known as Delicioso Coco Helado, or in English, Delicious Coconut Ice Cream.</p>
        <p>With little advertising, the carts selling the ice cream, commonly called ''coquito,'' have become as much a part of warm-weather New York as sidewalk ice chests of beer and barefoot boys prying open fire hydrants.</p>
        <p>The annual city permits for the Delicioso street vendors went into effect yesterday, but before the vendors pushed off from the company's factory in the Morrisania section of the Bronx, there was coffee and pastries and Representative José E. Serrano, who congratulated Alfredo Thiebaud, the company's founder, and made a tart comment about immigration.</p>
        <p>Finally, Mr. Serrano scooped -- a little inexpertly (someone kept yelling, ''press down, press down!'') -- some coconut ice cream into a paper cup for a little girl whose nose barely edged above the cart.</p>
        <p>Then Mr. Serrano said, in Spanish, ''May this be filled with something sweet for immigrants.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Thiebaud's business, which he began almost 30 years ago, has grown to 200 carts. Some carts are transported by truck, but most are pushed by vendors, with frequent interruptions from walk-up customers, to spots in the Bronx and Upper Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''They push and they sell, they push and they sell,'' Mr. Thiebaud said.</p>
        <p>Besides coconut, Mr. Thiebaud (pronounced TEE-bo) makes 14 other flavors like mango and pineapple. ''And we make it with passion!'' he exclaimed, holding his thumbs to his forefingers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thiebaud was born near San Pedro Sula, Honduras, one of 13 children of an executive with the United Fruit Company. At 20, he moved to New York to live with an uncle.</p>
        <p>''Everybody's dream then was to come to the United States,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In the Bronx, he worked as a general helper making $1 an hour at a window-making factory. He later became a carpenter, a welder and then a union construction worker.</p>
        <p>With the money he saved working in construction, he founded Delicioso in 1978 and slowly prospered, using his welding experience to design the carts. But in the late 1990s, his company, along with other street vendors, almost foundered when city officials threatened to ban or sharply limit sidewalk businesses.</p>
        <p>The vendors are independent contractors; they typically buy four quarts of ice cream from Mr. Thiebaud's company and net $100 or more a day. The vendors can charge any price, but depending on the neighborhood, a scoop can be as little as 50 cents or as much as $1.50. The permits run until Oct. 31.</p>
        <p>Most, if not all, of the vendors are immigrants. And most are from Mexico, El Salvador, the Dominican Republic and Honduras, a note Mr. Serrano seemed to strike when he said yesterday, ''This country was made by illegal immigrants because the pilgrims didn't ask permission of the Indians to come to this country when they created America.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Thiebaud has had difficulty expanding. He has long wanted to sell his dessert to the Pentagon, especially to troops in Afghanistan and Iraq, because many children from Bronx families are serving in the military. ''It's very hard,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He hopes to have a concession in the new Yankee stadium, but it is also difficult.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Thiebaud is content to be a local hero, posing for photos and listening as children sang ''O, I love my coquito'' to the tune of ''Take Me Out to the Ball Game'' before the official start of business.</p>
        <p>One of his vendors barely got around the block before he was stopped by Sharon Williams, 30, and her son Zhyion Cogle-Williams, 7.</p>
        <p>''Gracias, papí,'' Ms. Williams said, using a Spanish term of affection as the vendor gave her a napkin.</p>
        <p>''Not everyone speaks English and it makes them more comfortable.'' She added, ''I've eaten these since I was a little girl.''</p>
        <p>Zhyion listened to his mother and licked a mango ice cream. Finally, he said, ''It tastes like juice!''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
