<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Director Leaps From Shorts To Longing</title>
    <meta content="01wint" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/movies/01wint.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837115"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cannes International Film Festival</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Scotland</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Winters, Laura</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arnold, Andrea</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Red Road (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals/Cannes International Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/Scotland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cannes International Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">New Directors-New Films (Festival)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cannes International Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cannes International Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E2DD1330F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1562" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Director Leaps From Shorts To Longing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Director Leaps From Shorts to Longing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURA WINTERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Winters, Laura</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes Scottish director Andrea Arnold's first feature film Red Road, which won jury prize at Cannes; film is part of Scottish-Danish initiative called Advance Party, an offshoot of Dogma 95; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANDREA ARNOLD'S first feature film, ''Red Road,'' begins with the haunting image of a young woman sitting hunched in front of a bank of computer consoles, her face lighted by flickering, grainy images. The woman, Jackie, works as a closed-circuit-television surveillance operative, watching for signs of crime in a rundown area of Glasgow.</p>
        <p>Jackie wears a wedding ring but lives alone; she appears troubled by something though we don't know what. One day she sees a man in one of her cameras and recoils, though the man, named Clyde, doesn't recognize her when their paths cross later. Jackie (played by Kate Dickie) begins to track Clyde's whereabouts and gradually insinuates herself into his life, forcing a confrontation that will change them both forever.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The cinematic puzzle "Red Road" is Andrea Arnold's first feature and the first installment in a Scottish trilogy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANDREA ARNOLD'S first feature film, ''Red Road,'' begins with the haunting image of a young woman sitting hunched in front of a bank of computer consoles, her face lighted by flickering, grainy images. The woman, Jackie, works as a closed-circuit-television surveillance operative, watching for signs of crime in a rundown area of Glasgow.</p>
        <p>Jackie wears a wedding ring but lives alone; she appears troubled by something though we don't know what. One day she sees a man in one of her cameras and recoils, though the man, named Clyde, doesn't recognize her when their paths cross later. Jackie (played by Kate Dickie) begins to track Clyde's whereabouts and gradually insinuates herself into his life, forcing a confrontation that will change them both forever.</p>
        <p>Part thriller, part meditation on love and loss, ''Red Road'' galvanized audiences at the Cannes Film Festival last year with its suspense and its wrenching emotional payoff. As in cinematic puzzles like Atom Egoyan's ''Exotica'' and Michael Haneke's ''Hidden,'' we have no idea until quite late in the game why Jackie is doing what she is or what will happen next.</p>
        <p>Ms. Arnold walked off with the jury prize at Cannes and has since won an award at the BAFTAs -- the British equivalent of the Oscars -- for special achievement in a first feature. ''Red Road'' played recently at the New Directors/New Films series and will open in New York on April 13.</p>
        <p>The 45-year-old Ms. Arnold is not a total newcomer; her film ''Wasp'' won an Oscar for best live-action short film in 2005. But being called a major new talent (joining a small band of female directors in Britain that includes Lynne Ramsay and Gurinder Chadha) is a big change for the strong-willed and intensely private Ms. Arnold.</p>
        <p>During a conversation at the Toronto International Film Festival last fall she was by turns warm and guarded and looked like a grown-up Alice in Wonderland, with her long strawberry blond hair held back by a headband. ''I've talked to so many people about 'Red Road,' and everyone has all these ideas about it,'' she said. ''It can be bewildering because I don't want to be that self-conscious about what I do. I want to try and be instinctive as a writer and director.''</p>
        <p>Though Ms. Arnold wrote her own screenplay, she was given all of her major characters beforehand. ''Red Road'' is part of a Scottish-Danish initiative called Advance Party, which is an offshoot of Dogma 95, the film movement started by Lars von Trier and three other Danish directors as an attempt to restore authenticity to filmmaking by establishing rules for directors to follow.</p>
        <p>Gillian Berrie, a Scottish producer who helped found Advance Party, said, ''We decided that we'd like to do a low-budget scheme in Scotland for first-time directors that would use all of the elements of Dogma that worked and eliminate those that didn't.''</p>
        <p>According to Ms. Berrie and her Danish counterparts at Mr. von Trier's company, Zentropa, what worked best in Dogma was its spirit of community. So they decided that Advance Party would consist of three low-budget films by three novice directors, each one shot digitally in Scotland in six weeks. The catch? All three films would feature the same group of characters (provided to the directors in a bare-bones outline) and be played by the same actors. Each director would then create a story, and the characters would change and be fleshed out from film to film.</p>
        <p>Was it difficult to work within these constraints? ''No, it was exciting,'' Ms. Arnold said. ''The trick was to try to make these characters my own. So I went off and wrote a lot of my own things about them, filling in gaps about who I thought they were.'' For instance, Jackie, who was described in the outline as ''a bit aloof and cool,'' has to be aloof and cool in all three films, but it was Ms. Arnold's decision to make her a closed-circuit television operator, and this occupation can change in the next two films.</p>
        <p>The producers of Advance Party chose Ms. Arnold after viewing her short films. The other two Advance Party directors are Morag McKinnon, whose film will likely be shot later this year, and Mikkel Norgaard, whose film is still in development. Ms. Arnold wanted to be first out of the gate and was immediately drawn to Ms. Dickie -- who had done theater and television but no feature film work -- for the role of Jackie. ''There's a kind of mystery about Kate, a sense of something more going on beneath the surface,'' Ms. Arnold said. ''I thought that you would know when you saw her that something had happened to her.''</p>
        <p>With her gaunt face and expressive eyes, Ms. Dickie gives an emotionally and physically daring performance (including an explicit love scene). Speaking by telephone from Glasgow, she recalled growing ''really obsessed'' with the character. ''I guess I am attracted to damaged souls and to people who have been through a lot,'' she said. ''I didn't want to impose myself on Jackie. I wanted to become her.'' She said Ms. Arnold encouraged naturalistic performances: ''Andrea would say: 'Less acting, less acting. What would Jackie do? Where would she stand?' Rather than telling me what she wanted, she would allow me to get there by myself.''</p>
        <p>The filming took place in 2005, during a rainy Glasgow November. The main location was the high-rise complex called Red Road, a notorious and derelict housing complex. As she has in her short films, Ms. Arnold cast several local residents as extras. ''One day a police car pulled up,'' recalled Tony Curran, who plays Clyde, ''and we saw one of our extras being taken out in handcuffs by two policemen. He was shouting: 'Hey, you can't keep me! I'm in the film!' ''</p>
        <p>Ms. Arnold deals in dark realism, but there is a compassionate, redemptive quality to her work. ''I always think that if you look at anyone in detail, you will have empathy for them because you recognize them as a human being, no matter what they've done,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But the moments she spotlights are gritty, telling ones: people drinking whiskey out of mugs, a waiflike girl pouring a can of dog food on the floor to feed the dog. ''I grew up in a working-class family, so I guess you could say I write from what I know.''</p>
        <p>She was born and raised in Dartford, a drab community southeast of London, ''full of sprawly, terraced houses with small gardens,'' she said. The eldest of four children, she was born when her mother was 16 and her father was 17. Her parents separated when she was a child, leaving her mother to raise four children alone.</p>
        <p>At 18 Ms. Arnold left for London, where she got a job working as a host and actress for a children's television show called ''No. 73.'' She worked in television for the next decade. ''But I was always writing things on the side,'' she said, ''and when I got to my late 20s I suddenly felt that maybe I could make these stories into films.''</p>
        <p>She spent a year studying at the American Film Institute in Los Angeles, an experience that she describes as a creative watershed. After that she went back to England, had a daughter with her longtime boyfriend, a software engineer, and then started making short films and natural history programs for television.</p>
        <p>Ms. Arnold got a break when her first short film, ''Milk,'' was selected for the International Critics' Week section at Cannes in 1998. Another tersely titled short film, ''Dog,'' followed, and then she shot ''Wasp,'' which is about a young single mother in Dartford trying desperately to balance the demands of four children with her wish to have a romance.</p>
        <p>Ms. Arnold, who makes it a point now not to talk about her private life, winces when asked whether ''Wasp'' is modeled on her mother. ''If it was just down to me, I would talk about anything,'' she explained, ''but I'm protective of my family, who after I got the Oscar were inundated with the press tracking them down.''</p>
        <p>She continued: '' 'Wasp' is informed by things that I know, but the character that Natalie Press plays in the film is not my mom. People ask, 'Are your things autobiographical?,' and I think, no, they're not autobiographical directly, but of course my life has informed my work. You could tell me to go away and write 'Die Hard 10,' and I'd end up making my version of 'Die Hard 10' informed by me and my life.''</p>
        <p>There's no danger, though, that Ms. Arnold will film ''Die Hard 10'' any time soon. In the wake of ''Red Road'' she has been getting film offers, but said she intended to continue making her own films on terrain where she can be both at home and daring.</p>
        <p>''I'm very driven to write my own things, for better or worse,'' she said. ''To me that's the biggest effort and the biggest risk. Risk is the place where you really discover things. I'm still a novice, and I want to be discovering and learning and making mistakes and exploring. For me that's the most exciting place, and I don't want to give that up.'' She smiled. ''Why would anyone want to give that up?''</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
