<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cuba and Venezuela, the Odd Couple</title>
    <meta content="01romero" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/weekinreview/01romero.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837357"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="The World"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Electric Light Bulbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light Bulbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lighting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Cuba</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Venezuela</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Chavez, Hugo</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Castro, Fidel</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404EED81130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="888" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cuba and Venezuela, the Odd Couple</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cuba and Venezuela, the Odd Couple</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SIMON ROMERO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romero, Simon</byline>
      <dateline>CARACAS, Venezuela</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONCE night falls in this city, its vast hillside slums acquire a blue hue. The color is from new fluorescent lighting in the cinderblock hovels, which just a few weeks ago emanated an incandescent yellow. That was before thousands of Cubans fanned out across this oil-rich country to teach Venezuelans a thing or two about conserving energy.</p>
        <p>The campaign, to install efficient light bulbs free in millions of households, is the latest product of President Hugo Chávez's enduring embrace of Cuba and its revolutionary patriarch, Fidel Castro. But it also reveals how mismatched this oil-glutted country may be as a revolutionary partner for the much poorer society Castro transformed 50 years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hugo Chávez and Fidel Castro may be bosom buddies, but a close look at their respective nations reveals some gaping disparities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONCE night falls in this city, its vast hillside slums acquire a blue hue. The color is from new fluorescent lighting in the cinderblock hovels, which just a few weeks ago emanated an incandescent yellow. That was before thousands of Cubans fanned out across this oil-rich country to teach Venezuelans a thing or two about conserving energy.</p>
        <p>The campaign, to install efficient light bulbs free in millions of households, is the latest product of President Hugo Chávez's enduring embrace of Cuba and its revolutionary patriarch, Fidel Castro. But it also reveals how mismatched this oil-glutted country may be as a revolutionary partner for the much poorer society Castro transformed 50 years ago.</p>
        <p>Venezuela has oil to spare and sends Cuba almost 100,000 subsidized barrels of it a day. It also plans to send 100,000 poor Venezuelans to Cuba on all-expense-paid vacations.</p>
        <p>But what can Cubans do for Hugo Chávez?</p>
        <p>Clearly, they can serve as revolutionary models, but not in the heroic way they did back in the 1960s, when Venezuela had the kind of moderate democracy that Cuban guerrillas tried secretly to help overthrow.</p>
        <p>These days, with Mr. Chávez a much-valued ally, the Cubans are left to helping in matters of military advice, offering lessons in how to run a socialist-inspired educational curriculum -- and conducting projects that promote human interchange, like installing a few million light bulbs and offering medical assistance in Caracas slums.</p>
        <p>One problem, though, is that the interchange is sometimes too revealing. A few weeks ago, three Cubans lugging bags of light bulbs showed up at this reporter's home here, and the more they spoke about their experiences in Venezuela, the more it became apparent how different the two countries were.</p>
        <p>A third-year psychology student named Yunia Hernández Suárez, from the central Cuban city of Camaguey, told of venturing into poor urban neighborhoods in Venezuela.</p>
        <p>In the coastal city of Puerto La Cruz, she complained, armed thieves robbed her and her colleagues of their cash, watches, light bulbs, everything.</p>
        <p>''I cried that day,'' she said. ''The violence here makes me so afraid.''</p>
        <p>Such violent crime is less frequent under the tight grip of the Castro regime. Venezuela, by contrast, has one of the world's highest rates of firearm deaths, and this remains a taboo subject, rarely spoken about in public by senior officials in Mr. Chávez's government. (He made an exception during last year's presidential campaign when he condemned the murder of a Cuban doctor, one of thousands of medical workers sent to Venezuela by Mr. Castro in exchange for oil.)</p>
        <p>And violence may not be the biggest challenge the Cubans face. However many poor there are in the slums of Caracas, Venezuela remains a resource-rich country where rich and poor both still draw cultural inspiration more from Miami than Havana.</p>
        <p>Energy saving is one of the furthest things from their minds.</p>
        <p>Venezuela's gasoline prices, in fact, are among the world's lowest, at about 12 cents a gallon, as a result of a subsidy for car owners that is estimated to cost the state $9 billion a year.</p>
        <p>It would be hard for Mr. Chávez to chip away at this largesse. Few Venezuelans were shocked last month when a key ally of his, Gov. Luís Acosta Carlez, of Carabobo State, publicly defended the right of Venezuelan ''revolutionaries'' to own a Hummer, an increasingly popular vehicle in an economy that has been growing 10 percent a year as a result of high international oil prices.</p>
        <p>''If we earn money, we can do it,'' Mr. Acosta said.</p>
        <p>Additional subsidies of natural gas and electricity effectively encourage consumption, allowing Venezuela easily to outpace other major Latin American countries like Brazil and Argentina in per capita energy usage.</p>
        <p>Perhaps that explains why it was thousands of Cubans, not Venezuelans, who enlisted to install new bulbs across the country. Or perhaps it was that the bulbs themselves carried a revolutionary cachet. Venezuelan manufacturers, who have been stymied by price and currency controls, did not supply them. Vietnam did.</p>
        <p>Vietnam, on the other hand, is no longer the Communist model it once was; in recent years, it has adopted economic policies that welcome foreign investment, in contrast with Mr. Chávez's growing control over the economy. And such ironies are not lost on some political scientists here who say that if you examine them closely, Mr. Chávez's policies actually owe little to Mr. Castro.</p>
        <p>Instead, they say, his brand of militaristic populism more closely resembles the leftist military government of Gen. Juan Velasco, a career soldier and fiery orator who ruled Peru in the 1970's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chávez, 52, traveled to Peru as a young soldier and greatly admired General Velasco's experiment, a top-down government that nationalized cattle haciendas, banks and oil fields. The policies initially won popular support, but ultimately left Peru with high inflation and a scarcity of basic products. A bloodless coup toppled the general in 1975, and he was left an obscure figure, at best, in the annals of populism.</p>
        <p>So there are no murals in Caracas depicting General Velasco today. Instead, images of Che Guevara and Mr. Castro are what one sees alongside those of Mr. Chávez on the city's walls -- illuminated, these nights, in the odd blue glare of revolutionary energy-saving lights from Vietnam and the headlamps of gas-guzzlers imported from the United States.</p>
        <p>The World</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
