<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Generation Whatever in Tales From the : ( Side</title>
    <meta content="01books" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/fashion/01books.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837287"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF STYLE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E5DB1130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="840" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Generation Whatever in Tales From the : ( Side</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Generation Whatever in Tales From the : ( Side</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIESL SCHILLINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schillinger, Liesl</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANT FARM: AND OTHER DESPERATE SITUATIONS.  By Simon Rich.  160 pp. Random House. $12.95.</p>
        <p>BOOMSDAY: A NOVEL  By Christopher Buckley.  336 pp. Twelve (Hachette Book Group USA). $24.99.</p>
        <p>CONSIDER two savagely funny propositions.</p>
        <p>Here's the first: A comely young wonk named Cass Devine wants baby boomers to commit suicide at 70, to relieve the younger generation of paying for their elders' Social Security. She calls it Voluntary Transitioning and declares, ''They want to live forever -- we're saying, let them pay for it.'' Her plan electrifies American youths, who drop their iPods and Red Bulls and begin storming gated communities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANT FARM: AND OTHER DESPERATE SITUATIONS.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANT FARM: AND OTHER DESPERATE SITUATIONS.  By Simon Rich.  160 pp. Random House. $12.95.</p>
        <p>BOOMSDAY: A NOVEL  By Christopher Buckley.  336 pp. Twelve (Hachette Book Group USA). $24.99.</p>
        <p>CONSIDER two savagely funny propositions.</p>
        <p>Here's the first: A comely young wonk named Cass Devine wants baby boomers to commit suicide at 70, to relieve the younger generation of paying for their elders' Social Security. She calls it Voluntary Transitioning and declares, ''They want to live forever -- we're saying, let them pay for it.'' Her plan electrifies American youths, who drop their iPods and Red Bulls and begin storming gated communities.</p>
        <p>As Cass makes a speech at the Washington Mall, the police move to arrest her, and 75,000 of her followers, members of ''the most cynical generation in American history'' (also known as Generation Whatever) flood the stage to defend her. The Washington Post later calls the surge a ''Banana Republic tsunami.''</p>
        <p>Here's the second proposition: Abraham, coming down from the mountaintop, not having slit his son Isaac's throat after all, tries to restore father-son rapport and cajole Isaac into not telling his mother about what nearly went down. ''How about some ice cream, Isaac?'' Abraham asks. He changes the subject. ''Let me explain something to you. Sometimes, grown-ups have to do grown-up stuff that children don't understand,'' he says. ''Like what happened on top of the mountain? Do you remember? Of course you  of course. Anyway, that was a thing for grown-ups. How about some Rocky Road? Chocolate?''</p>
        <p>Guess which passage is the maiden effort of a 22-year-old Harvard senior and which appears in the 12th book by a 54-year-old Yale alumnus? The first comes from ''Boomsday,'' Christopher Buckley's youthquake of a black comedy. Mr. Buckley, the Yalie, proves there's no upper limit for precocity: a writer could live to be 100 without producing anything this wickedly entertaining.</p>
        <p>The second comes from ''Ant Farm,'' a collection of short comic essays by Simon Rich, whose high-spirited schadenfreude can work its magic in a page or two. In one story, a ''typical teenage girl'' recounts her fatal case of hepatitis C via text messaging: ''All I can do now is w8 4 death, : ( '' she bleakly confides.</p>
        <p>In ''The Dog X-Files,'' the eerie television series is reimagined, cast with dog players, whose daily mysteries defy canine understanding: a suddenly electrified living room; a magic collar that dispels fleas; a dog named Boomer who awakes to discover he's been rendered unmale. ''This is the fifth case this month,'' Dog Scully marvels.</p>
        <p>Many of Mr. Rich's shorts appeared first in The Harvard Lampoon (he was a former president), and three of them were published in the March 26 New Yorker. Not a bad debut for a kid who has yet to claim his sheepskin.</p>
        <p>Both writers have well-known fathers: in one case, the conservative guru William F. Buckley Jr. and in the other, the New York Times columnist Frank Rich. But neither their parentage nor their second-generation Ivy pedigrees had anything to do with the interest their writing provokes. April fool!</p>
        <p>Of course, there cannot help being heightened curiosity about men so fortunately connected. But their work is its own legacy, a prolific one in Mr. Buckley's case. And they don't inherit their laughs; they earn them. Both books poke merciless good-natured fun at the older generation (even if Mr. Buckley is technically one of Cass's loathed boomers). In ''Boomsday,'' Cass's father squanders her Yale tuition on an Internet start-up, then shunts her into the Army for her education.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Mr. Rich still keenly remembers the us-versus-them dynamic that prevails at kids' tables and in classrooms everywhere, which gives his stories the mutinous brio of Underdog in flight.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Buckley's tone has a quasi-British feel, Mr. Rich's idiom is all-American. It could be Steve Martin or Woody Allen speaking. Actually, the jacket of ''Ant Farm'' -- it shows a man's shoe poised to squash an ant -- recalls an early Woody Allen routine, ''Pets'' (which appears on the CD ''Standup Comic''), in which the comedian explains that when he was a child his parents were too poor to get him a dog. ''They got me an ant,'' he tells an audience. ''And I didn't know any better, you know. I thought it was a dog. I was a dumb kid. I called it Spot.'' When he sicced Spot on a bully named Sheldon, Mr. Allen says, ''Sheldon stepped on my dog.''</p>
        <p>The title story in ''Ant Farm'' describes the futile efforts of a team of ants trapped in a box of sand, who refuse to give up hope as they try for the umpteenth time to tunnel through the glass. ''You want to know something?'' the ant commander tells his men, ''I've got a good feeling about this one. A really good feeling.''</p>
        <p>In ''Boomsday,'' Cass turns that same doomed energy toward the goal of saving Social Security  and leading her generation out of an ''endless swamp of debt and misery.''</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF STYLE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
