<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Star Tech</title>
    <meta content="04talk.waldemeyer.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="T: Design Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="80" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Arts; Style; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/style/tmagazine/04talk.waldemeyer.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837084"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="The Talk"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Engineering and Engineers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7D91230F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="963" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Star Tech</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Star Tech</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Armand Limnander</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Limnander, Armand</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Moritz Waldemeyer is doing his best to counter the stereotype of the socially inept techno-wizard nerd in Coke-bottle glasses. He zips around London in a bright-yellow 1979 MG; with his shaggy hair and gangly good looks, he could easily be mistaken for the lead singer in an English guitar band. Over the past few years, Waldemeyer has become the go-to guy for cutting-edge gadgetry: Zaha Hadid, Ron Arad and Hussein Chalayan have all availed themselves of his services. Needless to say, he does not wear a plastic pocket protector.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Moritz Waldemeyer’s electronic gizmos are revolutionizing the design world. Armand Limnander plugs in.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Moritz Waldemeyer is doing his best to counter the stereotype of the socially inept techno-wizard nerd in Coke-bottle glasses. He zips around London in a bright-yellow 1979 MG; with his shaggy hair and gangly good looks, he could easily be mistaken for the lead singer in an English guitar band. Over the past few years, Waldemeyer has become the go-to guy for cutting-edge gadgetry: Zaha Hadid, Ron Arad and Hussein Chalayan have all availed themselves of his services. Needless to say, he does not wear a plastic pocket protector.</p>
        <p>Waldemeyer, 33, is at the forefront of mechatronics, a rapidly growing engineering field that creates design innovations for concept cars, smart weapons and space shuttles -- as well as for somewhat less glamorous subspecialties, like photocopiers. ''Mechatronics is simply a combination of mechanics and electronics,'' he explains. ''It's a relatively new discipline, but almost everything we use nowadays -- a washing machine, the electric windows in a car--is automated in one way or another.''</p>
        <p>What sets Waldemeyer apart from most gearheads is his eagerness to apply his technological know-how to whimsically creative endeavors. His career got a jump-start in 2004 with a cold call to Arad, who gave him his first commission, a drumstick that lit up to create words in midair as it swung back and forth. Waldemeyer went on to help Arad with large-scale projects like the Miss Haze and Lolita chandeliers; the latter features more than 1,000 light-emitting diodes that display scrolling text messages on shimmering Swarovski crystals.</p>
        <p>A collaboration with Hadid followed; Waldemeyer designed interactive, touch-sensitive control panels on the tabletop of her futuristic Z. Island kitchen for DuPont Corian. He also worked on Yves Béhar's Voyage, a blue, wavelike chandelier for Swarovski that is the size of a small car; and he helped perfect the infrastructure for the silhouette-shifting mechanical dresses that Chalayan showed on the runway last fall and for the recent frocks that can go from garden party to disco by lighting up and flashing.</p>
        <p>''Many designers are moving away from the quest to constantly reinvent shapes,'' Waldemeyer says. ''You can only make a chair in so many ways before you start repeating yourself. What I find exciting is how technology is becoming a design medium in itself. For example, the switches that we use in everyday life to turn lights on and off or to call an elevator could be made to disappear when they are not in use, and everything around us would look cleaner. That's why the upcoming Apple iPhone is revolutionary -- when you need to type an e-mail, the keys show up on the screen; otherwise, you don't see them at all.''</p>
        <p>Waldemeyer grew up in Halle, a small city in Soviet-era East Germany where the symbiosis between technology and aesthetics didn't hold much currency. Still, he was surrounded by creativity. ''Both my grandparents were artists, my aunt is a sculptor, and my uncle is a designer,'' he says. As a teenager, Waldemeyer attended a math school for gifted students. ''It was a very geeky place,'' he remembers. ''Kids would joke about pi and program software that caused computer monitors to self-destruct.''</p>
        <p>At 21 he moved to London to study business administration, but discovered robotics during an internship at Bosch. He switched to mechatronics and landed a research and development job at Philips. ''We did some things that were considered pretty crazy at the time,'' he says. ''Like a bra for female athletes embedded with sensors to monitor their heart rate, and a home entertainment system that altered the lighting in the room according to the scenes in a film. If you were watching a horror movie, everything would go dark during the scariest moments.''</p>
        <p>These days, Waldemeyer is happy splitting his time between collaborations and the pursuit of his own quirky ideas. His version of a postmodern mirror, for example, is a white Corian slab equipped with a miniature camera that transmits what it captures onto minuscule lights embedded in its surface. His Pong table is clean and spare -- until it's turned on and digital lights appear on its top, enabling you to play the classic video game. Another table lights up and becomes a roulette station; once bets are placed, the numbers flash until only one randomly selected winner remains illuminated.</p>
        <p>''Working with Moritz is always amazing,'' says Nadja Swarovski, who counts on him to make Swarovski's lighting fantasies a reality. ''He has the most up-to-date technology but also understands the aesthetics of design, and that is something one doesn't encounter every day.'' The design for their newest flight of fancy, a FredriksonStallard chandelier, incorporates motion. ''I don't mean that it swings,'' Swarovski says. ''It's made up of various layers that move up and down individually. The effect is truly mind-boggling.''</p>
        <p>Waldemeyer has plenty of other work lined up: he has been in talks about possible projects with Philippe Starck and Thomas Heatherwick, and he also teaches a weekly class in the design products department at the Royal College of Art. As for his spare time, it's spent either tinkering with his MG or dreaming up even more esoteric inventions. Case in point: his obsession with intrusive insects.</p>
        <p>''I find it incredibly annoying when I'm sitting next to the garden window and bugs come in and buzz all around the flat,'' he says. ''I want to develop a system with three or four sensors attached to the windowsill to determine if a fly has come in and triangulate its exact location. It would be linked to a really high-pressure water gun inside the room to shoot the fly back out into the garden. I'd have to work with really complicated math, but it's an elegant idea, and it really could work.''</p>
        <p>Now, about that pocket protector. . . .</p>
        <p>The Talk</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
