<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NAMES WITHOUT GLOVES</title>
    <meta content="01hands" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/sports/baseball/01hands.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837438"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL PREVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Protective Clothing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Protective Clothing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Posada, Jorge</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mientkiewicz, Doug</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EFDD1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="996" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NAMES WITHOUT GLOVES</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Some Hitters Feel Their Bare Hands Are Enough</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NOAH LIBERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Liberman, Noah</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Considering everything major leaguers can wear at the plate -- uniform, helmet, spikes, protective armor, sunglasses, wristbands, jewelry, ego -- it is intriguing that a handful walk up there naked, without batting gloves.</p>
        <p>Jorge Posada, Doug Mientkiewicz, Moises Alou, Vladimir Guerrero, Doug Mirabelli and a few others may be baseball's great individualists, because they have stepped away from a 40-year tradition of putting a little leather between the bat and their hands.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some in baseball have stepped away from a 40-year tradition of putting a little leather between the bat and their hands.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Considering everything major leaguers can wear at the plate -- uniform, helmet, spikes, protective armor, sunglasses, wristbands, jewelry, ego -- it is intriguing that a handful walk up there naked, without batting gloves.</p>
        <p>Jorge Posada, Doug Mientkiewicz, Moises Alou, Vladimir Guerrero, Doug Mirabelli and a few others may be baseball's great individualists, because they have stepped away from a 40-year tradition of putting a little leather between the bat and their hands.</p>
        <p>''It's just about feel,'' said Posada, the Yankees' catcher. ''The way the bat feels in my hands; I like to feel the pine tar, I like to feel the dirt, I like to feel the tape I put on the bat, and I like to feel the wood on the bat.''</p>
        <p>Alou, the Mets' left fielder, says it forces him to concentrate on hitting the ball square, because his bare hands feel the sting of a mis-hit more sharply. Blisters? They are not a problem after a few weeks of spring training, he said.</p>
        <p>Mientkiewicz, the Yankees' first baseman, echoes Posada on feel.</p>
        <p>''I feel I have better bat-head awareness without it,'' he said of a batting glove. ''I just feel I have better bat control.''</p>
        <p>Curiously, players who do wear batting gloves say the same thing -- starting with Ken Harrelson, who is considered the first to have worn one in an official game, roughly four decades ago.</p>
        <p>''The bat felt better in my hands than it did with the gloves off,'' said Harrelson, 65, who hit 131 home runs for four American League teams over nine seasons. ''The bat felt better, stronger, and anytime the bat feels better, you're going to feel stronger. I felt like I could do just about anything I wanted to do.''</p>
        <p>Never mind that Harrelson, now a Chicago White Sox television announcer, was a .239 career hitter; his description syncs with theories of how the hand, mind and body work together. Scientists believe that when early humans began walking upright, their hands and mind became free to collaborate in an evolutionary journey that explains why chimps play in trees and humans play, well, baseball.</p>
        <p>One milestone in this evolution is the uniquely human oblique squeeze grip, by which we hold hammers, baseball bats, golf clubs and a million other objects only humans can use with precision.</p>
        <p>''The baseball player, like the golfer, is putting his hand in a configuration that stands at the center of the march of human evolution,'' said the retired Stanford University neurologist Frank R. Wilson, author of the book ''The Hand: How Its Use Shapes the Brain, Language and Human Culture.''</p>
        <p>''So this is not tiddlywinks. This is who we are.''</p>
        <p>This grip makes the object an extension of the hand and arm. It also gives carpenters and marksmen the accuracy they need, and batters a swing with power and precision. Truly, if Babe Ruth had been a chimp, there would have been no Called Shot.</p>
        <p>Nor would there be batting gloves. Wilson explains that part of this evolution is our deep sensitivity to what scientists call ''slip'' -- instant awareness of any movement of an object held in the hand. Wilson guesses that gloves may help some batters by giving a more secure feel to the grip early in the swing -- that is when aiming counts because once the swing is under way, it is too late to fine-tune the bat's trajectory.</p>
        <p>Thus, it is batting gloves for 98 percent or 99 percent of major leaguers and bare hands for a few others, seemingly all of whom -- gloved or gloveless -- say their method gives them a better feel and a stronger grip.</p>
        <p>But is there a more precise explanation for the players who do not use gloves? Many of them -- Alou, Posada and Milwaukee Brewers infielder Craig Counsell, and, before he retired, the former first baseman Mark Grace -- hold the bat less in their palm and more in their fingers, which are quite sensitive to touch but absorb painful vibrations better, according to Posada.</p>
        <p>Wilson offers a different hypothesis he says can be tested. ''You might discover that these guys could all pass lie-detector tests because their hands don't sweat -- maybe it's as simple as that,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''I was a sweat horse,'' Harrelson, the glove pioneer, admitted.</p>
        <p>Regardless, if batting gloves are illustrative of human evolution, they are also a window into the behavior of the human male. Harrelson solves a minor historical debate -- was his first official use of a batting glove in 1964 or 1968? -- when he pinpoints the game as one against the Yankees in which he hit two home runs for the Kansas City Athletics. The records show it was Sept. 4, 1964, in Kansas City.</p>
        <p>Whitey Ford was the Yankees' surprise starter -- prompting the A's to counter with Harrelson, a platoon player. Trouble was, Harrelson had played 36 holes of golf that morning, and he had a blister. So he pulled a red golf glove from his jeans, he said, and his first home run traveled 450 feet. He never went without a glove -- or, later, a glove on each hand -- again.</p>
        <p>The next day, Harrelson said, the Yankees ran out for warm-ups wearing red golf gloves. Mickey Mantle had had the clubhouse man buy 20 pairs so they could razz the young Harrelson.</p>
        <p>''They were calling me 'Mrs. Harrelson' and 'Sweetness' and 'Sweetheart'; 'Don't let your skirt get dirty,' '' Harrelson said. But he is certain that within two years, most players were wearing gloves to bat, and before long, equipment makers had batting gloves in their catalogs.</p>
        <p>And now, you are the odd man out if you do not wear them. Which creates a brotherhood among those who go without. Mientkiewicz, formerly with the Minnesota Twins, describes a cold day against the Yankees when he chose to wear batting gloves. As he settled into the batter's box, he heard the usually quiet Posada giving him grief.</p>
        <p>''I thought you were one of us,'' Posada said.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL PREVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
