<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beyond Airbrushing</title>
    <meta content="01weartsWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837185"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Aldrich Museum of Contemporary Art (Ridgefield, Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Genocchio, Benjamin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3DC1030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="768" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beyond Airbrushing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BENJAMIN GENOCCHIO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genocchio, Benjamin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Benjamin Genocchio reviews exhibition of painted photographs on view at Aldrich Contemporary Art Museum in Ridgefield, Conn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rarely is the hand or touch of the artist visible in photography, in which mechanical reproduction is the norm. But an exhibition at the Aldrich Contemporary Art Museum in Ridgefield, Conn., suggests that this may be a thing of the past.</p>
        <p>''The Photograph as Canvas'' is organized by Stephen Maine, a Hartford-born artist, curator and critic who has lived in Brooklyn for many years. It evolved from a 2005 article that Mr. Maine wrote for the magazine Art on Paper, surveying the increasing trend among artists to paint and draw on photographs. The exhibition consists of two dozen works by 10 American and international artists.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rarely is the hand or touch of the artist visible in photography, in which mechanical reproduction is the norm. But an exhibition at the Aldrich Contemporary Art Museum in Ridgefield, Conn., suggests that this may be a thing of the past.</p>
        <p>''The Photograph as Canvas'' is organized by Stephen Maine, a Hartford-born artist, curator and critic who has lived in Brooklyn for many years. It evolved from a 2005 article that Mr. Maine wrote for the magazine Art on Paper, surveying the increasing trend among artists to paint and draw on photographs. The exhibition consists of two dozen works by 10 American and international artists.</p>
        <p>The show presents several different kinds of painted photographs. The most common are everyday, realistic snapshots enhanced with the addition of painterly details. Some of this enhancement is dramatic, as in Rob Fischer's addition of little ashy-gray clouds of smoke and intense yellow-orange flames to photographs of a mobile home parked on the edge of a field in Minnesota. The enhancements, in acrylic paint, completely alter the meaning of the original image.</p>
        <p>At other times the enhancement is more playful, even improvisational, and less concerned with conveying a meaning or message. Saul Leiter paints over old black-and-white prints of a standing female nude using gouache and watercolor, the light rinse of color partially obscuring the figure and the background. It is hard to read the artist's intentions here, though the washy surface and blurriness of the painted image remind you of a naked form seen through a shower curtain.</p>
        <p>At 83, Mr. Leiter is the oldest artist represented in the exhibition. Hanging near his work are paintings by Sebastiaan Bremer, who at 36 is among the youngest. Both artists have a love of visual obfuscation. Mr. Bremer obsessively overlays large, darkened photographs of what look like classic Dutch still-life paintings with elaborate, decorative constellations of imagery made with fine white dots. The results are marvelous to look at and dramatically intriguing.</p>
        <p>The inclusion of the performance artist Kim Jones's sprightly revisions of documentary photographs of his performances is especially pertinent, reminding us that the painted photograph is not an entirely recent phenomenon. From the mid-1960s, the Viennese artist Arnulf Rainer obscured photographs of himself and others with expressive finger painting. And the German painters Anselm Kiefer and Gerhard Richter painted and defaced photographic images as art.</p>
        <p>American conceptual artists also experimented with painted photography. In the 1970s, John Baldessari routinely altered photographs with pen and paint, and variations on this theme can be found in the work of Lucas Samaras and Ellsworth Kelly. Even the cartoonist Saul Steinberg has painted and drawn on photographs. Then there is the work of a generation of 1980s postmodern appropriation artists, among them the collage photographs of Richard Prince.</p>
        <p>Though acknowledging these historical precedents in his essay in the exhibition catalog, Mr. Maine argues that there has been an escalation of painted photographic work in the last few years. Digital computer imaging technology is partly responsible, he believes, for it has created a culture of photographic image manipulation and enhancement -- almost every advertising image is now digitally altered in some way. Painted photographs are an extension of this.</p>
        <p>But unlike the digital manipulation of imagery for advertising, painted photography is not always about image enhancement or improvement. Eugenie Tung paints over the people and elements of human habitation -- furniture, appliances, housewares -- in photographs of domestic interiors, usually apartments in which she has lived. The faint, blurry outlines of these painted-out elements are often visible, giving them an apparitional quality, like ghosts of some past presence.</p>
        <p>Similarly, Jim Dingilian makes new and startlingly intimate images by eliminating elements of the original. He carefully bleaches out portions of vintage photographs in various decorative patterns. The new artwork looks like psychedelic drawings; it is not until you get up close to them that you begin to see that they are photographs.</p>
        <p>Prolonged viewing of the examples of his work here only increases one's desire to see more. Mr. Dingilian is an artist to watch.</p>
        <p>Other artists choose to bury the photographic imagery under many layers of paint, often resulting in abstract or expressionist paintings. One of them, James Hyde, even paints on photographic enlargements of details from paintings by European and American master artists -- Francisco Goya, Stuart Davis, Theodore Rousseau -- a technique that brings the idea behind this exhibition full circle. We are only at the beginning of the story of the painted photograph.</p>
        <p>''The Photograph as Canvas,'' Aldrich Contemporary Art Museum, 258 Main Street, Ridgefield, Conn., through June 10. Information: (203) 438-4519 or www.aldrichart.org.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
