<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ellen Cowen, Andrew Meltzer</title>
    <meta content="01cowen" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/fashion/weddings/01cowen.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837269"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowen, Dr. Ellen Brooke (Dr. Ellen Brooke Meltzer)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Meltzer, Dr. Andrew Jason</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE7DB1130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="406" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ellen Cowen, Andrew Meltzer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ellen Cowen, Andrew Meltzer</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dr. Ellen Brooke Cowen, the daughter of Gloria Perlo Cowen and Philip R. Cowen of New York, was married last evening to Dr. Andrew Jason Meltzer, the son of Evelyn S. Meltzer and Richard M. Meltzer of Bala Cynwyd, Pa. Rabbi Peter J. Rubinstein performed the ceremony at Central Synagogue in New York, with Cantor Richard Botton taking part.</p>
        <p>The bride and bridegroom met at Jefferson Medical College in Philadelphia, from which both graduated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dr. Ellen Brooke Cowen, the daughter of Gloria Perlo Cowen and Philip R. Cowen of New York, was married last evening to Dr. Andrew Jason Meltzer, the son of Evelyn S. Meltzer and Richard M. Meltzer of Bala Cynwyd, Pa. Rabbi Peter J. Rubinstein performed the ceremony at Central Synagogue in New York, with Cantor Richard Botton taking part.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dr. Ellen Brooke Cowen, the daughter of Gloria Perlo Cowen and Philip R. Cowen of New York, was married last evening to Dr. Andrew Jason Meltzer, the son of Evelyn S. Meltzer and Richard M. Meltzer of Bala Cynwyd, Pa. Rabbi Peter J. Rubinstein performed the ceremony at Central Synagogue in New York, with Cantor Richard Botton taking part.</p>
        <p>The bride and bridegroom met at Jefferson Medical College in Philadelphia, from which both graduated.</p>
        <p>The bride, 32, is a senior resident at Boston Medical Center, where she is to begin a fellowship in July in general internal medicine and preventive medicine. She graduated from Bowdoin College.</p>
        <p>Her father is the chairman of Decatur Capital Corporation, a New York investment company, where her mother is vice chairwoman. The bride's father is also the chairman of Insultab, a maker of plastic tubing products in Woburn, Mass.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom, 29, is a general surgery resident at Massachusetts General Hospital in Boston. He graduated from Yale. His father is a lawyer in Philadelphia. His mother is a personnel consultant for information technology companies in Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>Dr. Cowen and Dr. Meltzer met in September 1999, when they worked together in a class on interviewing patients. They quickly became friends and after final exams that year had a date. But they were better at seeing patients than seeing each other.</p>
        <p>''Dating was just overshadowed by the academic rigors of medical school,'' Dr. Cowen said.</p>
        <p>Still, they met occasionally for coffee or dinner. When Dr. Meltzer left Philadelphia for Boston in 2003 to begin his internship, they guessed their paths wouldn't cross again.</p>
        <p>The following year the National Residency Matching Program, a computerized service, sent Dr. Cowen to a residency at Boston Medical Center.</p>
        <p>''My mother was very exited about the prospect of the two of us being in the same city again,'' she recalled. ''My parents always thought that Andrew was a very appropriate person.''</p>
        <p>At first they were dating others, but resumed meeting for coffee.</p>
        <p>By October 2005, they were meeting with greater frequency. She asked him out for a second date, a dinner in Boston, where her parents came to celebrate her birthday. At the end of the night Dr. Meltzer teased Dr. Cowen, telling her he had received her father's blessing to marry.</p>
        <p>Though he was only joking, marriage was becoming a serious subject.</p>
        <p>The following July he proposed at the bride's family vacation home in Santa Fe, N.M.</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
