<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jobs at Risk After Scandal at Juvenile Facility</title>
    <meta content="01texas" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/us/01texas.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837369"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pyote (Tex)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Monahans (Tex)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">West Texas State School (Pyote, Tex)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Novovitch, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Texas</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EED71130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="743" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jobs at Risk After Scandal at Juvenile Facility</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Jobs at Risk After Scandal at Juvenile Facility</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA NOVOVITCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Novovitch, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>PYOTE, Tex., March 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>About 200 people gather outside county courthouse in Monahans, Tex, to oppose state auditor's recommendation that West Texas State School be closed following sex abuse scandal that has shaken Texas's juvenile detention system; see school as badly needed source of jobs for neighboring communities; school employs 228 people; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To most Texans, the West Texas State School here is the troubled institution at the center of a sexual abuse scandal that has shaken the state's juvenile detention system.</p>
        <p>But to the residents of this town of 129 and the neighboring communities, it is a source of badly needed jobs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Residents of a town in western Texas have protested the proposed closing of a detention facility where allegations of abuse surfaced in February.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To most Texans, the West Texas State School here is the troubled institution at the center of a sexual abuse scandal that has shaken the state's juvenile detention system.</p>
        <p>But to the residents of this town of 129 and the neighboring communities, it is a source of badly needed jobs.</p>
        <p>That is why about 200 people gathered outside the county courthouse in Monahans on Tuesday to oppose a state auditor's recommendation to close the school, and why nine residents made the 750-mile round trip drive to Austin this week to address legislators on the matter.</p>
        <p>''This facility has been a part of the community since 1965,'' said Donna Garcia, community relations coordinator at the school. ''It feels like a personal vendetta against this community. We feel like the Legislature needs somebody to blame this on.''</p>
        <p>In February, news accounts reported that from 2003 to 2005 two officials at West Texas State had had late-night sexual encounters with incarcerated boys and then were allowed to resign without facing criminal charges. Responding to the disclosure, and to pressure from the Legislature, Gov. Rick Perry forced the resignation of the Texas Youth Commission board and ordered a review of all of its facilities.</p>
        <p>The agency is currently investigating 1,200 complaints against juvenile facilities around the state.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, we're outraged at the kind of things that are alleged,'' Judge Greg Holly of the Ward County Court said Thursday, after returning from Austin, where he addressed a legislative hearing. ''Obviously the folks accused are not Ward County people. It sickens us, it bothers us -- but local folks ought not to be punished.''</p>
        <p>The schools superintendent of Monahans, Keith Richardson, said closing West Texas State, which employs 228 people, could mean the loss of 60 students in Monahans schools because their parents would have to move if they lost their jobs there.</p>
        <p>Mayor David Cutbirth of Monahans said the job loss would damage the area's economic diversity, which is tied to oil and gas production.</p>
        <p>''Drilling jobs can pay up to $28 per hour, but they're mostly for men,'' he said. West Texas State offers jobs for clerical workers, teachers, counselors and men ''with special training.''</p>
        <p>Pyote now houses 238 offenders ages 12 to 20, with most ages 15 to 17, said a Texas Youth Commission spokesman, Jim Hurley.</p>
        <p>When a reporter visited the facility, groups of young men clad in orange or blue marched in drill formation from the cafeteria to classrooms. The youngsters wear uniforms to signify their phase of ''resocialization,'' Mr. Hurley said. He said the youngsters' days were structured: ''They go to school, to therapy groups, behavior groups, meals, exercise and recreation, physical training, and a hour of free time in the evenings. They are up at 5 a.m. and in bed at 9 p.m.''</p>
        <p>Nearly 4,000 youthful offenders are being held in 36 Texas Youth Commission facilities.</p>
        <p>A Ward County grand jury will meet on April 10 to consider the accusations against the former officials of West Texas State who, according to a Texas Ranger investigation, ''engaged in sexual contact with several students.''</p>
        <p>In recommending the closing of West Texas State, the auditor cited Pyote's remote location, its sparse labor force and its distance from medical facilities.</p>
        <p>Judge Holly said he understood that all but 10 percent of the jobs at the Pyote facility were filled, ''while some other Texas Youth Commission facilities have 20 to 30 percent openings.'' He pointed out that Odessa, with several hospitals, is just 40 miles away on Interstate 20. ''In time, that's as close as any metropolitan area prisons,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Sixty percent of West Texas State counselors and teachers drive the 15 miles from Monahans (population 6,700 with an additional 2,000 outside city limits), and 40 percent from Pecos (population 9,000), 26 miles to the west, Mayor Cutbirth said.</p>
        <p>Bob Siekman, a former teacher and a retired contractor, said that he lived next door to West Texas State and that he considered the detention center a good neighbor. Mr. Siekman blamed ''the muckety-mucks, the higher-ups'' for any misconduct there.</p>
        <p>But he was more interested in pointing out that Pyote has a museum, open on weekends, devoted to the town's earlier fame as the World War II ''Rattlesnake Bomber'' Air Force base, which in 1952 was temporarily home to the B-29 Enola Gay, which had dropped the atomic bomb on Hiroshima.</p>
        <p>''I climbed all over the Enola Gay when I was a kid,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
