<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Up Front</title>
    <meta content="Conant.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/books/review/Calhoun.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837014"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Breast</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Breast</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Stacked: A 32DDD Reports From the Front (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7DB1530F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="506" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Up Front</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Up Front</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADA CALHOUN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Calhoun, Ada</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>STACKED</p>
        <p>A 32DDD Reports From the Front.</p>
        <p>By Susan Seligson.</p>
        <p>229 pp. Bloomsbury. $23.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The book is a celebration, neither prudish nor depraved, of “female orbs” in all their hypnotic glory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>STACKED</p>
        <p>A 32DDD Reports From the Front.</p>
        <p>By Susan Seligson.</p>
        <p>229 pp. Bloomsbury. $23.95.</p>
        <p>When I think about breasts -- and as a DD-endowed editor of sex and parenting magazines currently breast-feeding a baby, that's quite often -- I think about ''lactivist'' organizations like La Leche League, dopey enterprises like ''Girls Gone Wild,'' sublime celebrities like Dolly Parton and the blog-traffic-boosting potential of the red-carpet ''nip slip.'' When Susan Seligson thinks about breasts -- and, since she's a DDD-endowed (touché) middle-aged woman who's been groped and catcalled her whole life, that's often, too -- she thinks about ... her own DDDs.</p>
        <p>''Stacked,'' a good-natured examination of the breast question, is more memoir than dispatch. Seligson, a journalist, repeatedly interrupts her research to bring us updates on her ''good old girls,'' her ''fleshy torpedoes,'' her ''Tetons'': ''As I massage them with coconut oil after my bath,'' she writes in one of many pseudo-autoerotic passages, ''I find myself less and less averse to my breasts' imposing fleshy contours.''</p>
        <p>It's not that Seligson doesn't get out of the house. She goes to conclaves sponsored by Exotic Dancer magazine in Las Vegas, where she stalks Maxi Mounds, wielder of 156MMMs. Seligson hangs out with breast-enhancement patients before, after and, remarkably, during surgery. She talks to the former editor of Busty Beauties magazine, who appears to be suffering from some form of post-traumatic stress disorder (he's haunted by ''memories, wistful and bitter, of ghosts of paramours past''). She criticizes the fashion sense of top-freedom crusaders (shirtless activists who are ''as sexually provocative as a bowl of muesli'').</p>
        <p>Seligson trips lightly over potential signs of the apocalypse like surgery safaris, deconstructed by Alex Kuczynski in the recent ''Beauty Junkies.'' While a dazzlingly good sport, Seligson breaks no new ground in her research on America's breast fixation. The book is full of lists and long quotations, at times yielding the impression that the author just left the tape recorder running while she looked down her own shirt. She evades even her own questions. (Wondering whether her participation in a topless photo shoot was life-changing, she concludes, ''I'm not sure yet.'') After one interview, Seligson gets in her car and ''absent-mindedly'' cups her breasts: ''For the zillionth time I marvel at how these sacks of flesh can be the objects of such deep, persistent longing.''</p>
        <p>She behaves rather like a besotted schoolboy, making naughty puns and going to second base with her interview subjects. At times, her giddiness seems a little unbecoming in a mature woman. She's essentially banking on the idea of sexy without really delivering. There are, alas, no photos of Maxi, no before-and-afters, no ''here are my good old girls in a bikini.''</p>
        <p>Ultimately, ''Stacked'' is on the side of right -- a celebration, neither prudish nor depraved, of ''female orbs'' in all their hypnotic glory. Seligson is likable, if for no other reason than that she's absolutely dizzy with admiration for her assets. The book's superficiality actually makes her point well: it's not just construction workers who are distracted by large breasts.</p>
        <p>Ada Calhoun is the editor in chief of Babble.com and a frequent contributor to the Book Review.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Ada Calhoun is the editor in chief of Babble.com and a frequent contributor to the Book Review.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
