<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Why REIT Shoppers Are Heading to the Malls</title>
    <meta content="01sqft" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/realestate/commercial/01sqft.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837307"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SQUARE FEET: VENTURES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E1DB1130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1301" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Why REIT Shoppers Are Heading to the Malls</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Why REIT Shoppers Are Heading to the Malls</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIVIAN MARINO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marino, Vivian</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INVESTORS shopping for loftier returns may want to peruse the regional malls and the shopping centers -- or at least the real estate investment trusts that own them.</p>
        <p>These types of properties offer among the highest returns of all REIT categories, yet they are still considered by some people to be generally undervalued. And many industry analysts predict that they will outpace the market this year, even as the growth of REITs over all is expected to decelerate after a seven-year run.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Analysts say that space is tightest in the regional malls, which generally contain 400,000 to 800,000 square feet of enclosed real estate for department stores, specialty shops and, often, a food court.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INVESTORS shopping for loftier returns may want to peruse the regional malls and the shopping centers -- or at least the real estate investment trusts that own them.</p>
        <p>These types of properties offer among the highest returns of all REIT categories, yet they are still considered by some people to be generally undervalued. And many industry analysts predict that they will outpace the market this year, even as the growth of REITs over all is expected to decelerate after a seven-year run.</p>
        <p>From the beginning of the year through last Thursday, REITs owning regional malls and shopping centers returned 11.98 percent and 5.23 percent, respectively, and REITs owning free-standing stores, another subsector, were up 1.34 percent, according to the National Association of Real Estate Investment Trusts. The retail REIT sector as a whole was up 8.31 percent.</p>
        <p>By contrast, equity REITs over all -- dividend-paying companies with portfolios of property of any sort -- returned 2.14 percent, the association said, while the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index, was nearly flat.</p>
        <p>''There is still a good deal of interest in real estate, although that will begin to attenuate at some point,'' said John J. Kriz, the managing director of real estate finance for Moody's Investors Service. But, he added, ''retail space, especially the higher-end regional mall, is one of the more stable real estate types.''</p>
        <p>Free-spending consumers and a steady economy can be thanked. Spending growth averaged 3.3 percent annually from 1990 through 2000, according to the Bureau of Labor Statistics, and was expected to grow 3.6 percent annually from 2000 through 2010.</p>
        <p>''A pretty large segment of consumers are doing well -- unemployment is low, jobs are being created -- and they like to go out and shop, whether it's for daily necessities or luxury items,'' said Ralph L. Block, the author of ''Investing in REITs'' (Bloomberg Press, 2006) and the publisher of The Essential REIT, a newsletter. ''You can't buy everything online,'' he added.</p>
        <p>At the same time, developments can't seem to be built fast enough, as more retailers look to expand into new spaces to raise revenue.</p>
        <p>''Demand for space is outstripping supply,'' said David M. Fick, a managing director at Stifel Nicolaus. He noted that rent spreads, or the difference between what tenants pay for new leases and expiring leases, are increasing steadily as a result. ''There has been 20 percent average rent spreads on the higher-quality mall portfolios,'' he said, ''and on the more average-quality portfolios, high single digits.''</p>
        <p>Analysts say that space is tightest in the regional malls, which generally contain 400,000 to 800,000 square feet of enclosed real estate for department stores, specialty shops and, often, a food court.</p>
        <p>''They're just not building many regional malls; they're very expensive and very difficult to get approval for,'' explained Richard C. Moore, a managing director at RBC Capital Markets. ''Communities like going to them once they're in place, but they don't like them coming to their own towns, taking up enormous amounts of space and tying up traffic.''</p>
        <p>As a result, mall occupancy rates are high -- 93 percent, on average, not including seasonal vendors, according to Mr. Block. A decade ago, he said, the rate averaged 87 percent, he said.</p>
        <p>Shopping-center REITs, which generally own open-air complexes that include community centers anchored with supermarkets or big-box retailers, have occupancy rates closer to 95 percent, on average, he said. Local approval for them, though, is generally easier to obtain.</p>
        <p>The Simon Property Group, the largest retail REIT, expects to spend more than $5 billion over the next four years developing retail projects, and not one will be an enclosed mall, said Stephen E. Sterrett, the chief financial officer.</p>
        <p>Instead, the company, like its competitors, has been developing more so-called lifestyle centers, which are upscale shopping complexes that mimic urban streetscapes, and adding mixed-use projects.</p>
        <p>Last month, Simon opened the Domain in Austin, Tex.; it combines 700,000 square feet of retail and restaurant space with 75,000 square feet of office space and 390 residential apartments. Just north of Austin, the Round Rock Premium Outlets complex, developed through the Chelsea Property Group subsidiary that Simon acquired in 2004, was designed like a village with pedestrian courtyards and fountains. It opened last summer.</p>
        <p>''We are busier today than at any other time in our company's history at building retail projects in the United States,'' Mr. Sterrett said. ''Some of them are new; some of them are expansions of existing projects.''</p>
        <p>Many industry analysts give Simon high marks. ''They have a very good development pipeline, with opportunities overseas,'' Mr. Moore said, ''and a great balance sheet.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fick agreed, adding that ''owning Chelsea will generate a significant amount of earnings growth not currently reflected in anyone's estimates.''</p>
        <p>He likes some of the smaller retail REITs as well, like Kite Realty and Cedar Shopping Centers, each of which focuses on neighborhood and community shopping centers, because of their development projects. And he is bullish on the retail REIT sector in general. ''The group over all will continue to beat all the major markets,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Maserich Company is also on Mr. Moore's list of favored companies, because of what he called its ''very high quality portfolio.'' The company recently acquired 11 stores owned by Federated Department Stores that are in Maserich malls. And he likes the Kimco Realty Corporation, the Developers Diversified Realty Corporation and Weingarten Realty Investors -- shopping center owners that, he says, have ''good development pipelines and joint-venture relations'' with institutions like pension and endowment funds.</p>
        <p>Analysts find other retail REITs attractive because of what they consider relatively low valuations, based on recent earnings reports and capitalization rates, or initial rates of return.</p>
        <p>Though they have been declining, ''cap rates in retail haven't really come down to the extent that they have in other sectors,'' Mr. Block said, noting that retail REIT cap rates average about 6 percent, versus just below 5 percent for offices and around 5 percent for apartments.</p>
        <p>Ross Nussbaum, a senior equity analyst at Bank of America, says regional malls, in terms of market valuations, are among ''the cheapest in the REIT sector.''</p>
        <p>But retail REITs could eventually suffer from an overbuilding of shopping centers. A downturn in the economy and higher interest rates could hurt as well. ''Retail REITs still have a fair amount of debt on their balance sheets,'' Mr. Kriz said, adding that consumers struggling with debt could also curb their spending.</p>
        <p>Most analysts, however, say they think that fundamentals will remain strong for the retail sector. Some say that there may be further consolidation within the retail REIT area, which could push up share prices as investors speculate about which company will be the next takeover candidate.</p>
        <p>''We think there are a number of retail REITs that are fairly good takeover targets in the next 24 months,'' Mr. Fick said.</p>
        <p>This past winter was an especially busy time for mergers and acquisitions. The Centro Properties Group, an Australian REIT, agreed to buy New Plan Excel Realty Trust, an operator of shopping centers, for about $3.4 billion in cash. In addition, Simon, along with the hedge fund Farallon Capital Management, agreed to acquire the Mills Corporation, a retail REIT, in a cash offer of $1.64 billion. Including assumed debt and preferred stock, the deal was valued at $7.9 billion.</p>
        <p>Mills had been struggling financially in recent years. Its biggest drain was the Meadowlands Xanadu, a 2.2-million-square-foot shopping-and-entertainment center planned on 104 leased acres surrounding the Continental Arena in northern New Jersey. Mills has since transferred control over that project to a joint venture led by Colony Capital, a private investment firm based in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>The acquisition of Mills, which was seen as dragging down the retail REIT sector with its poor returns, is considered by some analysts as yet another positive for the industry.</p>
        <p>SQUARE FEET: VENTURES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
