<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Map for the Maze Of Federal Contracts</title>
    <meta content="01home" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/business/yourmoney/01home.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837326"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OFFICE SPACE: HOME FRONT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Small Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Small Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">General Services Administration</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE3D91130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="880" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Map for the Maze Of Federal Contracts</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Map for the Maze of Federal Contracts</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH P. FRIED</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fried, Joseph P</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CARL R. BONITZ is co-owner of a small business, and he wants a piece of the federal contracting pie.</p>
        <p>So one morning last month, he and about 70 others attended a workshop in Manhattan for operators of small companies seeking to sell their goods or services to the federal government.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many small-business owners find the process of securing a federal supply contract frustrating.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CARL R. BONITZ is co-owner of a small business, and he wants a piece of the federal contracting pie.</p>
        <p>So one morning last month, he and about 70 others attended a workshop in Manhattan for operators of small companies seeking to sell their goods or services to the federal government.</p>
        <p>Federal agencies spend more than $300 billion a year buying items from paper clips to fighter jets, and services from office cleaning to information technology management. Obtaining a federal supply contract can help a thriving business expand or help a sinking one stay afloat.</p>
        <p>But many small-business owners find the process of securing such contracts frustrating. To help them, the government sponsors sessions like the recent one in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Each person at the workshop received a 21-page list of thousands of products and services arranged under more than 60 categories -- ''schedules,'' as the government calls them. As a vital first step, small-business owners must determine which schedule applies to them.</p>
        <p>That is easier said than done. Consider Mr. Bonitz, an owner of Black Hawk Telecom, a year-old company that recruits and supplies crews for projects involving engineering, construction or installation of cellular, satellite and telecom equipment.</p>
        <p>The company, which has 10 full-time employees and is based in Bloomingburg, N.Y., in Sullivan County, has contracts with 10 corporate clients, Mr. Bonitz said; he hopes to add federal agencies to the list. Before the session, he said, he tried to determine the schedule that applied to the company.</p>
        <p>''I communicated with many people in different agencies, and they bounced me around and gave me unsure information,'' he said. At the session, he was told that his staffing services fell under Schedule 70, ''general purpose commercial information technology equipment, software and services,'' and not, as he had previously been told, Schedule 736, ''temporary administrative and professional staffing services.''</p>
        <p>The session was held by the General Services Administration, which issues its own contracts as the manager of federal buildings, and serves as a centralized procurement unit for many other federal agencies. Those agencies can choose suppliers from the G.S.A.'s multiple award schedules, which are lists of vetted companies that provide a particular item or service.</p>
        <p>Agencies are required to solicit at least three companies when making a purchase, and they choose the one offering the most favorable terms. Being on a multiple award schedule increases the chances that a business will be approached.</p>
        <p>But getting onto a schedule can be time-consuming, confusing and cumbersome. To help ease the way, small-business operators can attend sessions called ''schedules contract training,'' which are listed in the events section of www.gsa.gov.</p>
        <p>The G.S.A. events, and others held by the Small Business Administration, are intended to help achieve a Congressionally mandated goal that 23 percent of federal contracting dollars each year go to small businesses.</p>
        <p>The S.B.A.'s definition of small varies by industry; for most retail and service industries, the business must have no more than $6.5 million in annual revenues; for most manufacturing industries, it must have no more than 500 employees. (The agency says businesses with fewer than 500 workers provide about half the jobs in the country.)</p>
        <p>Whether the 23 percent goal is being met is in dispute. In its latest report, the S.B.A. said that in fiscal 2005, federal agencies surpassed the goal for the third consecutive year, awarding small businesses $79.6 billion out of a total $314 billion worth of prime contracts, or 25.4 percent.</p>
        <p>But Democrats on the House Small Business Committee maintained last year that the goal had not been met for the sixth consecutive year, saying that nearly $12 billion of the claimed $79.6 billion had actually gone to large businesses, making the small-business share 21.6 percent.</p>
        <p>Most people interviewed at the workshop in Manhattan were unaware of the dispute, but they were very much aware of how important federal contracts can be to a small business.</p>
        <p>''That's the big money,'' said Rodney Evans, who owns Skyline Connections of Manhattan. The company, which has 25 employees, provides video and other electronic security systems and computer hardware to private-sector customers and state and local agencies.</p>
        <p>''But the federal system is new to us,'' he said. Though the G.S.A. speakers at the workshop said that hiring a private consultant to help get onto a schedule was unnecessary, Mr. Evans said he had hired one because ''it's time-consuming to put all the information into the application.''</p>
        <p>He was at the workshop, he said, because once on the list, ''I'll have to bid and deal with the contracting people,'' and he wanted to learn which of them handled video security systems and how to contact them.</p>
        <p>SOME people, like Howard Epstein, left the session feeling that despite all the information they had received, obtaining federal contracts still seemed like having to scale a Himalayan peak.</p>
        <p>Mr. Epstein is executive vice president of Sandra Hartog &amp; Associates, a management consulting business in Brooklyn that has 9 full-time employees and 35 consultants and specializes in helping corporations with employee assessment issues. His company would like to expand by doing the same for federal agencies, he said. ''I wished I had walked away with a sense that it was a much less daunting task,'' he said, ''but it continues to be a daunting task.''</p>
        <p>OFFICE SPACE: HOME FRONT E-mail: homefront@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: homefront@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
