<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>STREET LEVEL/Bay Ridge; The Little Church That Couldn't</title>
    <meta content="01stre" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/thecity/01stre.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837305"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Street Level | Bay Ridge"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Methodist Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bay Ridge United Methodist Church (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bay Ridge (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Consolidated Edison Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gentile, Vincent (Councilman)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Brooklyn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Luxury and Vacations/Active Adult</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Construction and Maintenance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Methodist Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E2DB1130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>STREET LEVEL/Bay Ridge; The Little Church That Couldn't</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Little Church That Couldn’t</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAKE MOONEY</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Street Level column on unusual disagreement over fate of Bay Ridge United Methodist Church in Brooklyn; members have put church, whose stone walls need at least $3 million in repair work, up for sale for $12 million; City Councilman Vincent Gentile is leading push to preserve church by having Con Edison build senior housing next door, which would generate about $315,000 a year for church and avoid prospect of large apartment tower on site; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Bay Ridge United Methodist Church has stood on a leafy Brooklyn corner since 1900, and somewhere along the way it picked up a nickname, the Green Church, a reference to the tint of the stone on its walls and its signature clock tower. These days, that stone can also be found, in large chunks and fine powder, scattered on the ground outside, near fences and scaffolding that have been erected to protect people walking in the front door.</p>
        <p>The old church is in rough shape, and has been for at least a decade. But this year a disagreement over the building's future has taken a turn unusual for church preservation struggles. The impetus toward saving the building has come from outside the congregation, while church members say it is time to move on.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This year a disagreement over the future of the Green Church has taken a turn unusual for church preservation struggles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Bay Ridge United Methodist Church has stood on a leafy Brooklyn corner since 1900, and somewhere along the way it picked up a nickname, the Green Church, a reference to the tint of the stone on its walls and its signature clock tower. These days, that stone can also be found, in large chunks and fine powder, scattered on the ground outside, near fences and scaffolding that have been erected to protect people walking in the front door.</p>
        <p>The old church is in rough shape, and has been for at least a decade. But this year a disagreement over the building's future has taken a turn unusual for church preservation struggles. The impetus toward saving the building has come from outside the congregation, while church members say it is time to move on.</p>
        <p>''It breaks our hearts to give up this building; we love it, and it wasn't easy to make that decision,'' said John Donlon, a retired firefighter who is chairman of the church's board of trustees. In recent years, Mr. Donlon said last week, church members have held two fund-raising drives, raising tens of thousands of dollars, which barely had an effect. The last estimate was that repairs to all the church's stone would cost at least $3 million. That, he said, does not include needed work to the building's windows, plumbing and electricity.</p>
        <p>So now, the members have put the church on the market; it is listed at $12 million, and the assumption is that whoever buys it will tear it down and build a tall residential building.</p>
        <p>The church's pastor, the Rev. Robert Emerick, believes that moving into a smaller space in whatever new building is built on the site is an opportunity for the congregation, which has shrunk in recent years to 40 worshipers for Sunday Mass, to pursue its mission of community service -- helping the needy and even donating to charities -- without being saddled with repair bills.</p>
        <p>''This group has had time to realize what the situation is in terms of building, and they've had time to reflect on it morally, spiritually, theologically,'' he said. ''This is me, the minister, talking, but I see the hand of God here.''</p>
        <p>But City Councilman Vincent Gentile, who has been leading a push to preserve the church, says the church members have not sufficiently considered a plan he developed in which Con Edison would build housing for senior citizens next to the church, which is on Fourth and Ovington Avenues, and sell it at below-market rates. The deal would generate about $315,000 a year for the church while avoiding the prospect of a large apartment tower on the site.</p>
        <p>''I'm not commenting on their Christian mission,'' Mr. Gentile said. ''I'm commenting on their ability to save the church as a community structure, and being able to answer a dire community need, the ability to put affordable senior housing on that site. I'm trying to get them to see their responsibility to the rest of the community.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gentile said that short of having the church declared a landmark against its members' will, no one can force them to save the building, but he continues to hope the two sides can negotiate.</p>
        <p>At a contentious neighborhood meeting last month organized by his office, and in interviews, congregants scoffed at Mr. Gentile's plan, saying the money it would generate is barely enough to maintain the church's three buildings, let alone repair them.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Emerick, the pastor, bristled at the idea of preserving the church on aesthetic grounds. ''We answer to God in the person of Jesus Christ, and there's nothing in Jesus' sayings or actions about providing comforting buildings for communities to gaze upon,'' he said. ''No one has enough money to save this building. I don't think that Councilman Gentile understands that.''</p>
        <p>Still, congregation members who favor letting the church go are not happy about it. Many of them just see it as sadly inevitable.</p>
        <p>''It's been a long and tortuous road,'' said Lois Habenicht, a church trustee and its financial secretary. ''I can't get up there and ask widows on fixed incomes to give money, I can't get up there and ask young people with children to send to college to give more money. Everybody's already doing what they can -- there just aren't enough people.''</p>
        <p>Street Level | Bay Ridge E-mail: streetlevel@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: streetlevel@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
