<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trying to Get a Handle On the Car of Tomorrow</title>
    <meta content="01nascar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/sports/othersports/01nascar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837383"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn of Stock Car Auto Racing</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Labonte, Bobby</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Busch, Kyle</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E4DE1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trying to Get a Handle On the Car of Tomorrow</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Trying to Get a Handle On the Car of Tomorrow</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Starting with quarter-midget racecars during his childhood in Texas, Bobby Labonte has raced a lot of different vehicles. He says Nascar's Car of Tomorrow is nothing like any of them, including the other kind of stock cars he is driving this year.</p>
        <p>Labonte, who turns 43 next month, will be in the 43-car field for a Nextel Cup race today at Martinsville, Va., on a relatively flat, half-mile track with two 800-foot straightaways and two grinding turns. The Car of Tomorrow will be used again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is plenty of complaining from drivers, most notably Bobby Labonte, about how the Car of Tomorrow is a chore to drive, let alone race.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Starting with quarter-midget racecars during his childhood in Texas, Bobby Labonte has raced a lot of different vehicles. He says Nascar's Car of Tomorrow is nothing like any of them, including the other kind of stock cars he is driving this year.</p>
        <p>Labonte, who turns 43 next month, will be in the 43-car field for a Nextel Cup race today at Martinsville, Va., on a relatively flat, half-mile track with two 800-foot straightaways and two grinding turns. The Car of Tomorrow will be used again.</p>
        <p>Martinsville is not Bristol, the site of the first Car of Tomorrow race, won last Sunday by Kyle Busch. The track at Bristol, Tenn., is only about 37 feet longer than Martinsville, but Bristol has higher banking, wider turns and shorter straightaways.</p>
        <p>In other words, Bristol is more like a speed bowl than Martinsville, and there was plenty of complaining after the race from drivers -- most notably, Busch -- about how the Car of Tomorrow was such a chore to drive, let alone race.</p>
        <p>''If your car doesn't handle good, then you're not going to want to race anybody,'' Labonte said in a telephone interview Thursday.</p>
        <p>Labonte, who finished 22nd at Bristol in a Dodge, said he had spent most of the race trying to hold onto his spot until the race was over, so he could return it in one piece to the hauler. There was little side-by-side racing.</p>
        <p>''I didn't really feel comfortable doing it,'' said Labonte, who is to start 31st in today's race. ''There was less charging. A few cars handled good, but a lot of them didn't handle good.''</p>
        <p>He included his car in the latter category. Labonte was not necessarily grumbling about it -- every driver gets a poor-handling car from time to time -- and he seemed to be willing to give the Car of Tomorrow another chance, or two.</p>
        <p>He remembered wrestling with his brother Terry's car during a test drive in 1989, two years before Bobby joined the Winston Cup series. Bobby Labonte won the Winston Cup in 2000. He learned about stock cars before, and he figures he can learn again.</p>
        <p>Labonte's 29th Cup race at Martinsville (he won a race there in 2002) promises to be different from the first 28. The Car of Tomorrow was built for safety. The car is boxier, or more square, Labonte said, than the stock cars that have been used in the series.</p>
        <p>The Car of Tomorrow, he said, is also engineered to turn left on ovals, but the Car of Tomorrow has a higher center of gravity. As a result, he said, the car feels top-heavy heading into corners, as if it were not leaning into the curves. There is less weight on the left sides of the cars.</p>
        <p>''It is a little more difficult to turn left than it was before,'' Labonte said.</p>
        <p>To protect drivers better, the steering wheel has been moved closer to the center of the car, and the windshield is more upright, making Labonte feel as if he were sitting higher in the car. It takes getting used to.</p>
        <p>''I think the cars handled bad enough Sunday where there wasn't too much side-by-side racing,'' Labonte said.</p>
        <p>Nascar officials say the Car of Tomorrow is by no means a finished product. John Darby, the series director, and Robin Pemberton, the vice president for competition, said at a news conference Friday at Martinsville that some issues needed to be addressed. Most notably, too many exhaust systems failed in the new cars at Bristol.</p>
        <p>Darby said the new cars were generally reliable, durable and mechanically sound. The height of the front and back bumpers now match, lessening the chance of a car hitting another from behind, lifting it and sending it out of control.</p>
        <p>''Most of the drivers we've talked to don't particularly like the way it drives compared to what they've been used to for a decade or more with the aero matched templates and all those things,'' Pemberton said at the news conference. ''But at the end of the day, they're coming to us with reasons that this is a good idea.''</p>
        <p>Drivers like to grumble. Bristol has always been a tough track, Labonte said, and it will probably be tough 20 years from now. Progress at Martinsville has always been measured in how many feet are gained on the driver in front in one lap.</p>
        <p>''This is a harder car to drive, and to steer, than what we've had, and it's less aerodynamic,'' Labonte said. ''In anything you do, you're going to take one step forward, two steps back. I guess it's just one of those deals where if the racing is no good, they'll refine things to make it better.''</p>
        <p>The Car of Tomorrow will be used in 14 more races this year after Martinsville, the next time in two weeks at Phoenix. Labonte said he would find a way to handle the car. Coping has always been a part of racing, since his quarter-midget days.</p>
        <p>''We've just had an old pair of shoes, and we've got a new pair to break in,'' he said, laughing.</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
