<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Heart, Williams Wins in 3 Sets</title>
    <meta content="01tennis" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/sports/tennis/01tennis.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837404"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Williams, Serena</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Henin-Hardenne, Justine</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802EEDE1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Heart, Williams Wins in 3 Sets</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With Heart, Williams Wins in 3 Sets</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crouse, Karen</byline>
      <dateline>KEY BISCAYNE, Fla., March 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Serena Williams's physical strength is there for everybody to see -- the muscles in her arms and legs about as subtle as an overhead smash. While the eye is drawn to Williams's brawn, her greatest asset goes largely unnoticed.</p>
        <p>A rare opponent can push Williams to the point where it becomes obvious that her strongest muscle is her heart. Justine Henin was that formidable foil Saturday in the final of the Sony Ericsson Open, with their riveting two-and-a-half hour match turning on Williams's fearlessness in the face of adversity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Serena Williams, the reigning Australian Open champion, staved off two championship points against Justine Henin in the second set on her way to a 0-6, 7-5, 6-3 victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Serena Williams's physical strength is there for everybody to see -- the muscles in her arms and legs about as subtle as an overhead smash. While the eye is drawn to Williams's brawn, her greatest asset goes largely unnoticed.</p>
        <p>A rare opponent can push Williams to the point where it becomes obvious that her strongest muscle is her heart. Justine Henin was that formidable foil Saturday in the final of the Sony Ericsson Open, with their riveting two-and-a-half hour match turning on Williams's fearlessness in the face of adversity.</p>
        <p>Williams, a former No. 1 player and the reigning Australian Open champion, lost the first set in 27 minutes and staved off two match points in the second before roaring back to win her fourth title here, 0-6, 7-5, 6-3.</p>
        <p>With the victory against Henin, the new world No. 1, Williams will ascend to No. 11 in the rankings to be released Monday. After playing in only four events in 2006 because of injuries and burnout, the 25-year-old Williams started the year ranked No. 81.</p>
        <p>''I kept fighting,'' Williams said. ''Even though I was down, I never was out.''</p>
        <p>Henin, whose career, like Williams's, has progressed in fits and starts because of injuries and illness, took a break at the start of this year to deal with the dissolution of her 4-year marriage. Henin, a 24-year-old Belgian, is considered a heavy-mettle player. But on this day, she was the one who blinked first.</p>
        <p>After committing five unforced errors in the first set, Henin made 12 in the third as she wilted under the pressure that Williams applied.</p>
        <p>''I felt I had the match under control and then the match turned over,'' Henin said. ''She played better than me on the important points. It's tough to close the matches against her because she goes for it.''</p>
        <p>What the match did not have in drama in the beginning it more than made up for in the final set and a half, which was characterized by high-level tennis.</p>
        <p>The match was a study in contrasts, pitting players with a combined 13 Grand Slam championships who have different body types, games and temperaments.</p>
        <p>Williams is 5 feet 9 inches, with the curves of a muscle car. At 5-6 and 126 pounds, Henin is as compact as the Mini Cooper she drives.</p>
        <p>''I'm very proud of not so tall, not so strong, and I compete,'' Henin said, adding, ''I can be powerful when I want with my technique and everything.''</p>
        <p>Williams overpowers opponents. Henin lures them into submission with patience, quickness and a fine array of shots.</p>
        <p>But Saturday, Williams showed plenty of finesse, winning more points at the net than Henin, and Henin displayed impressive power, finishing with more aces (five to Williams's three).</p>
        <p>Henin kept Williams off balance in the first set with her impressive serves and the depth and breadth of her shotmaking. Williams had a hard time keeping the ball in play, with the backhand she sent wide on set point epitomizing her early troubles. Williams had 14 unforced errors in the first set to Henin's 5.</p>
        <p>The match turned in the 10th game of the second set, when Henin had two championship points on her serve, at 40-15 and 40-30. She knew better than to count out a cornered opponent, having herself come back from a 5-1 deficit in the third set of her third-round match against Virginie Razzano to prevail in a tie breaker.</p>
        <p>Williams had spoken earlier in the week of Henin's returning to the Tour after a self-imposed absence and catching ''that Serena flame,'' adding, ''I'm trying to catch it, too.''</p>
        <p>She did in the nick of time, staving off both championship points with big forehands and beautifully constructed points. Williams broke Henin, and won the next five games as well.</p>
        <p>In that stretch, Henin twice hurt her knees lunging for shots. Whether it was a muscle strain or the mental strain of trying to close out Williams, Henin did not cover the court with the same fluidity in the third set that she had exhibited in the first.</p>
        <p>''The only thing I can have regrets about is that for a few games I wasn't really focused on every point,'' Henin said, ''and I lost a couple of games in a row because I was maybe still focused on these match points and these opportunities that I missed.''</p>
        <p>Henin fought back to tie the third set at 3-3. Williams, serving at 40-0 in the next game, hit a cotton ball of a drop shot that Henin returned, and then passed her with a backhand for one of her 10 winners in the set (she had four in the first).</p>
        <p>''I feel like when I get down,'' Williams said, ''a part of me just plays better.''</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
