<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Get: Mucho Gusto; Style Map | Mexico City</title>
    <meta content="04get.map.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="T: Design Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="66" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Style; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837055"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E0DA1230F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="579" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Get: Mucho Gusto; Style Map | Mexico City</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Armand Limnander</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mexico City has long been dismissed as either a pit stop on the way to a beach resort or a megalopolis too vast and chaotic to tackle. But in recent years, the D.F. (Distrito Federal), as locals refer to Mexico's capital, has been exerting a cultural influence to match its size. It offers world-class shopping, jalapeno-hot night life and increasingly influential art and design movements that combine avant-garde influences with the traditions of one of the oldest civilizations in the world.</p>
        <p>Armand Limnander</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mexico City has long been dismissed as either a pit stop on the way to a beach resort or a megalopolis too vast and chaotic to tackle. But in recent years, the D.F. (Distrito Federal), as locals refer to Mexico's capital, has been exerting a cultural influence to match its size. It offers world-class shopping, jalapeno-hot night life and increasingly influential art and design movements that combine avant-garde influences with the traditions of one of the oldest civilizations in the world.</p>
        <p>Armand Limnander</p>
        <p>1. Galeria Mexicana de Diseno</p>
        <p>A mecca for international and local furniture design, this vast emporium includes a well-curated book selection, pieces by Established &amp; Sons, and updated interpretations of Mexican classics like the diva-ish Acapulco chair (best suited for poolside use, margarita firmly in hand). Don't miss out on the cheeky artist tees (left) and specially commissioned wallpapers as well as the collection of Corian and steel jewelry by Iker Ortiz. Anatole France 13; 011-52-55-5280-0080.</p>
        <p>2. La Primavera Vidrio Soplado</p>
        <p>Baccarat this is not, but the affordable and sturdy offerings here have a rustic charm all their own. Glass spheres share shelf space with tinted wine and water glasses, hefty ashtrays and oversize vases. Favorites are the mirrored bowls in all sizes and hues like emerald green, crimson and silver. Colima 264; 011-52-55-5207-1159.</p>
        <p>3. Esrawe Diseno</p>
        <p>Héctor Esrawe designs interiors and creates objects and furniture under his label. He is also a partner at NEL, a collective known for things like expanded polystyrene furnishings decorated with cats and waves. See his own work and NEL's more whimsical creations at his showroom. Alfonso Reyes 58; 011-52-55-5553-9611.</p>
        <p>4. Condesa df and the Hippodrome Hotel</p>
        <p>The city's most fashionable district is anchored by the Condesa df (left), a belle époque building turned hotel with a rooftop bar, a basement club and India Mahdavi interiors. A close second is the Hippodrome Hotel and its Hip Kitchen restaurant. Condesa df: Avenida Veracruz 102; 011-52-55-5241-2600. The Hippodrome Hotel: Avenida México 188; 646-862-5158.</p>
        <p>5. La Bipolar</p>
        <p>Holes in the wall and street carts with tostadas and tacos are hard to miss. But La Bipolar, co-owned by the actor Diego Luna, has made these dishes and a few health-conscious ones cool and delicious. The joint uses butcher blocks as stools, and menus look like vintage posters. Malitzin 155; 011-52-55-5484-8066.</p>
        <p>6. Chic by Accident and Sexe by Accident</p>
        <p>Emmanuel Picault has a trove of 20th-century furnishings that has included late-'70s Murano baubles, a Saarinen chair and a ''de-tropicalized'' table from Michoacan treated with black lacquer. A few feet away, his haute-sex emporium has naughty mezcal bottles from Oaxaca and an 18th-century Sevres bowl modeled after a breast (originally produced for Marie Antoinette's dairy). Chic by Accident: Colima 180; 011-52-55-5514-5723. Sexe by Accident: Colima 212: 011-52-55-5207-9282.</p>
        <p>7. Proyectos Monclova and OMR</p>
        <p>The city's burgeoning contemporary art scene continues to grow as independent-minded galleries like Proyectos Monclova and OMR (left) promote the next generation of Gabriel Orozcos. Proyectos Monclova: Colima 244; 011-52-1-55-1800-4150. OMR: Plaza RÃo de Janeiro 54; 011-52-55-5207-1080.</p>
        <p>8. Cibeles</p>
        <p>The chicest place for a drink or 12 is Cibeles, which caters with equal ease to a first-date couple or a raucous fashion party. Conceived as a series of open yet distinct spaces, it has a mismatched décor that marries rustic farm-style tables with Philippe Starck lamps and mod mirrors; well-worn chesterfield sofas look at home next to wicker peacock chairs worthy of the Miss Mexico pageant. Plaza Villa de Madrid 17; 011-52-55-5208-1456.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
