<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>EVERYBODY LOVES DAVID</title>
    <meta content="01mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/sports/baseball/01mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837441"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL PREVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">All Star Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wright, David</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04EEDD1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1627" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>EVERYBODY LOVES DAVID</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Baseball Actively Promotes Him, Advertisers Eagerly Chase After Him</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shpigel, Ben</byline>
      <dateline>PORT ST. LUCIE, Fla.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At age 24, David Wright has an easy smile and brown eyes that have already appeared on the covers of ESPN's magazine, Men's Health, Player and The Sporting News, and inside the pages of Cosmopolitan, GQ, Sports Illustrated and People. He has swapped baseball stories over dinner with President Bush and charmed David Letterman on late-night television. He has established a charitable foundation, and Delta Airlines put his name and number on one of its shuttles.</p>
        <p>Last year, there was no other professional athlete in New York whose name sold as much merchandise as Wright's did. Not Tiki Barber, not Wright's teammate Pedro Martínez, not even Derek Jeter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Mets third baseman David Wright enters his third full season in the major leagues, his profile is increasing at a rate not often seen in baseball.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At age 24, David Wright has an easy smile and brown eyes that have already appeared on the covers of ESPN's magazine, Men's Health, Player and The Sporting News, and inside the pages of Cosmopolitan, GQ, Sports Illustrated and People. He has swapped baseball stories over dinner with President Bush and charmed David Letterman on late-night television. He has established a charitable foundation, and Delta Airlines put his name and number on one of its shuttles.</p>
        <p>Last year, there was no other professional athlete in New York whose name sold as much merchandise as Wright's did. Not Tiki Barber, not Wright's teammate Pedro Martínez, not even Derek Jeter.</p>
        <p>As Wright, the Mets' third baseman, enters his third full season in the major leagues, his profile is increasing at a rate not often seen in the sport. Major League Baseball is promoting him as one of its best assets, putting him on the cover of a 2007 video game and in All-Star Game commercials. Madison Avenue swoons over his blend of athleticism, charisma and humility. Men want to be him. Women want to marry him. As major league rosters become increasingly international, Wright is emerging as an intriguing counterpoint.</p>
        <p>''You're looking at one of those rare times in baseball history where you've got this incredible kid and all the stars have aligned perfectly,'' Howard Smith, baseball's senior vice president for licensing, said in explaining the Wright phenomenon.</p>
        <p>And yet, as appealing and likable as he is, Wright is hardly perfect. He has steadily improved since joining the Mets in the 2004 season, but his power plummeted in the second half of last season and he hit .216 in his first encounter with postseason baseball. There is always the risk that the hype will get too far ahead of his achievements, that he will become too big, too soon, and that the grumbling will begin in New York, where few athletes are awarded unlimited sympathy and where the highly paid Alex Rodriguez has been belittled in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>Perhaps mindful of those risks, the Mets are being careful not to single out Wright in boldface type. Thankful as they are to have him signed for the next six seasons, they prefer to market him within the mosaic of the other All-Star players who dot their roster and, particularly, in tandem with shortstop José Reyes, who has blossomed alongside Wright on the left side of the infield. The Mets' stance is reflected by the cover of the team's 2007 media guide, which features Manager Willie Randolph and five other players in addition to Wright and Reyes.</p>
        <p>''One thing we have to be careful about is overexposing David, going to him too often,'' said Dave Howard, the Mets' executive vice president for business operations. ''Not only is he attractive in the business community, but he hardly ever says no. We have to remind ourselves that we're a team that has a number of attractive, very marketable, players.''</p>
        <p>It is within that group that Wright's role may be changing this season, with Randolph leaning toward moving him from fifth to second in the batting order. It is a position that often puts less emphasis on hitting home runs and more on the less glamorous tasks of working the count and getting on base and sometimes hitting behind runners. It is, of course, the spot in the order in which Jeter helped the Yankees capture four World Series championships and defined himself as the ultimate winner.</p>
        <p>If Wright does bat second, he will probably find himself in a new equation, being compared more to Jeter than to Rodriguez, with whom, after all, Wright shares a position. And if, like Jeter, Wright can become the glue of a team that wins championships the way the Yankees did in the 1990s, then Wright will become an enormous star, as big as Jeter ever was.</p>
        <p>This is all heady stuff for the Mets, and for Wright, who has made a rapid ascent within New York's baseball and social circles, quickly transforming himself from a fresh-faced youngster from Virginia who carted around Cliff Floyd's luggage into a high-profile bachelor with a newly purchased multimillion dollar loft in the Flatiron district of Manhattan. His charity, the David Wright Foundation, is already two years old, with Wright starting it at the same age that Jeter began his Turn 2 foundation. Meanwhile, the endorsement opportunities keep pouring in, with Wright trying to keep a sense of perspective, and even honor, about it all.</p>
        <p>''If I were to do all the things that come in by the boatload, I feel like I'd be distracted from what the main goal is, and that's baseball,'' Wright said. ''I understand if I stop performing on the field and if this team doesn't win, then those things go away.''</p>
        <p>''I'm not doing this to be a billboard,'' added Wright, whose affiliations include brands like Wilson, vitaminwater and Hickey Freeman. ''I don't want to be a Nascar car that has 100 different stickers on it. I'm only going to put my name on something that I believe in and something that I would use even if I don't have an endorsement.''</p>
        <p>How Wright's soaring marketability is perceived within the Mets' diverse clubhouse, where his still-emerging career is overshadowed by the achievements of veterans like Tom Glavine, Carlos Delgado, Carlos Beltrán and Moises Alou, is a relevant issue, although any sign of resentment would be hard to find.</p>
        <p>In the clubhouse, Wright fits in easily among his teammates, giving pep talks to Chan Ho Park, teasing Glavine's young sons, pulling practical jokes on Paul Lo Duca. One of his closest friends on the team is none other than Dave Racaniello, the bullpen catcher. Teammates have observed how easily Wright balances his responsibilities to the news media -- he nearly missed a meeting last week because he was finishing an interview with a reporter -- with those to the club.</p>
        <p>And they notice, too, how graciously he interacts with fans. Before a game in Lakeland, Fla., earlier in spring training, people standing by the visiting dugout besieged him with autograph requests, and he signed and posed for photographs until the crowd dissipated. The same scene transpired in every spring training ballpark.</p>
        <p>''David's a kid that looks like he belongs in New York,'' said Billy Wagner, another Mets veteran with a résumé longer than Wright's. ''He's well mannered, he's well liked, he's well disciplined and he's well rounded.''</p>
        <p>Delgado said: ''He has a great head on his shoulders. I think he just gets it, and some people don't get it until much, much later.''</p>
        <p>Wright fast-forwarded his way through the Mets' system, spending hardly any time at Class AA and AAA before he reached the major leagues in July 2004. That was a few months before General Manager Omar Minaya was hired and, together with Randolph, rejuvenated a moribund franchise. Wright's emergence coincided with the Mets' upswing in 2005, and last year, when the team won 97 games and a division title, Wright made several game-saving defensive plays and displayed a Jeter-esque knack for delivering big hits.</p>
        <p>One such hit -- a go-ahead three-run homer in the Mets' final game before the All-Star Game break -- immediately preceded a three-day span when Wright vaulted into the national spotlight. On Monday, July 10, Wright reached the finals of the nationally televised home run derby before losing to Philadelphia's Ryan Howard. The next night, in his first All-Star Game at-bat, he slammed a homer off Detroit's Kenny Rogers. After the game, he flew to New York from Pittsburgh to prepare for his appearance on Letterman's show. Then the came the flood of inquiries.</p>
        <p>''Every different kind of company, from banks to ice cream bars, wanted a piece of him,'' said Keith Miller, a former Met who is one of Wright's agents. ''The number of inquiries we were getting doubled at least. Probably tripled.''</p>
        <p>Wright keeps in close contact with Miller as he steers his way through stardom. In the off-season, when Wright has more free time, they speak several times a day to make sure he is not being overextended. Wright even maintains a schedule on his cellphone, so he knows exactly when he has to be in Oregon (to develop his shoe at Nike headquarters) or San Diego (to be digitized for Sony's MLB 07 The Show video game) or New York (for the winter gala at the Hickey Freeman store that benefited his foundation). Over the coming months, vitaminwater will start a campaign featuring Wright on a national level, and Topps has put Wright on the box of a set of trading cards.</p>
        <p>It is part of Wright's charm that he seems to treat these companies like teammates. He promises that he has never owned a pair of baseball shoes that were not made by Nike. His first baseball glove was made by Wilson, and here he is with the company now. In his first minor league season, he started drinking vitaminwater because, according to the label, it was a low-sugar alternative to other sports drinks. Only when he arrived in New York and discovered that the company was based in Whitestone, Queens, a few miles from Shea Stadium, did he pursue a relationship.</p>
        <p>''When we have dinner, I ask him baseball questions, and he asks me business questions,'' Mike Repole, the president of vitaminwater, said.</p>
        <p>For the time being, Wright will put aside those questions. A new season is about to begin, with Wright's teammates looking to him, baseball's hierarchy rooting for him and opposing teams watching him, looking for signs of weakness. No problem: All Wright has to do is hit .300 and win a championship. Then he can navigate his way through a new army of advertisers.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL PREVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
