<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Dry Saloon, the Dissected Violin, the Dreamer of Sleepy Hollow</title>
    <meta content="01read" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/thecity/01read.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837306"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: READING NEW YORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Sam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marchese, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lerner, Michael A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burstein, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yamashita, Michael</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Violin Maker, The (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Dry Manhattan: Prohibition in New York City (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Original Knickerbocker, The (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Facing Fascism: New York and the Spanish Civil War (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">New York Flying High (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E1DB1130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1105" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Dry Saloon, the Dissected Violin, the Dreamer of Sleepy Hollow</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Dry Saloon, the Dissected Violin, the Dreamer of Sleepy Hollow</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Sam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sam Roberts reviews some new books about or set in New York City; list of other recently published books relating to New York; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the spirit of James Barron's book ''Piano,'' which chronicled the birth of a Steinway concert grand in a Queens factory, John Marchese now offers up ''The Violin Maker: Finding a Centuries-Old Tradition in a Brooklyn Workshop'' (HarperCollins, $24.95).</p>
        <p>''The Violin Maker'' is an impassioned account of the collaboration between Eugene Drucker, a West Side violinist, and Sam Zygmuntowicz, a son of Polish concentration camp survivors, whose studio on Dean Street in Downtown Brooklyn shows what magic is secretly practiced behind many of New York's nondescript doors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“The Violin Maker” is an impassioned account of the collaboration between a West Side violinist and a son of Polish concentration camp survivors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the spirit of James Barron's book ''Piano,'' which chronicled the birth of a Steinway concert grand in a Queens factory, John Marchese now offers up ''The Violin Maker: Finding a Centuries-Old Tradition in a Brooklyn Workshop'' (HarperCollins, $24.95).</p>
        <p>''The Violin Maker'' is an impassioned account of the collaboration between Eugene Drucker, a West Side violinist, and Sam Zygmuntowicz, a son of Polish concentration camp survivors, whose studio on Dean Street in Downtown Brooklyn shows what magic is secretly practiced behind many of New York's nondescript doors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zygmuntowicz is a luthier. The occupational classification system of the federal Bureau of Labor Statistics does not define his rarefied profession separately, but Mr. Marchese does, and enchantingly. The really good luthier, he writes, is ''at once a woodworker, an engineer, an historian, a mechanic and a shaman.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Marchese, a practiced trumpet player, was inspired to write the book after hearing a high school violinist's rendition of ''How Deep Is the Ocean.'' He infuses his graceful dissection of the instrument with a special appreciation of sound and of history in explaining how 70 or so components unite to create the violin's unique anatomy.</p>
        <p>''How is it that this hunk of wood with the funny shape can express so perfectly the deepest and most profound human emotions?'' Mr. Marchese asks. ''The Violin Maker'' provides some inviting answers.</p>
        <p>Before the bans on smoking and on cooking with trans fats, there was Prohibition. Whatever the theoretical merits of banning the sale of liquor back then, a case could be made that unlike recent decrees by the health police, Prohibition unfairly -- and intentionally -- singled out Catholics, Jews, immigrants and New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>In ''Dry Manhattan: Prohibition in New York City'' (Harvard University Press, $28.95), Michael A. Lerner, associate dean of studies at Bard High School Early College in Manhattan, convincingly makes that case.</p>
        <p>Perhaps he sometimes overstates New York's role as the ''foremost battleground'' over Prohibition, and the extent to which the temperance movement spawned a local backlash that helped elevate Alfred E. Smith and Franklin D. Roosevelt into national politics. And ''Dry Manhattan'' can be occasionally just a tad too dry, even for a book published by an academic press.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Lerner exhaustively and effectively illuminates some of the relatively obscure or forgotten sidelights of America's so-called ''noble experiment,'' among them: ''curiously insular'' New Yorkers' arrogant miscalculation of the clout of the Anti-Saloon League; the dimensions of the return of some immigrants to Europe, where they could drink again unmolested; and the reasons Tammany Hall was so dependent for its survival on the local tavern.</p>
        <p>He also profiles some of the largely unsung protagonists of the era, including Pauline Sabin, a Morton Salt heiress who reversed herself and supported repeal, and William H. Anderson, the hero of Prohibitionists, against whom Tammany had the last laugh -- he was later convicted of forgery and sent to Sing Sing.</p>
        <p>In 1848, Washington Irving was the executor of John Jacob Astor's estate. Imagine how this literary figure who wrote about history as burlesque would have covered the melodrama involving Astor's heirs today.</p>
        <p>Andrew Burstein's engaging biography is titled ''The Original Knickerbocker'' (Basic Books, $27.50), and to aid readers who might mistake his subject for a pair of short pants or a brand of beer, he serves up three subtitles: ''The Life of Washington Irving,'' ''Ambassador, Biographer, New York Politico and Acclaimed American Storyteller'' and ''How the Legendary Author of 'Sleepy Hollow' Shaped a Nation.''</p>
        <p>There! Must be something worth reading about. And so there is.</p>
        <p>Professor Burstein, a native New Yorker and a history professor at the University of Tulsa, artfully weaves together Irving's many vocations in a book that reads much more smoothly than some of Irving's own.</p>
        <p>Irving was a biographer of Washington and Columbus and the man who conjured up his caricature of Colonial Dutch aristocracy, the legendary New York raconteur and historian Diedrich Knickerbocker of the family from Scaghtikoke, ''where the folk lay stones upon the houses in windy weather, lest they should be blown away.''</p>
        <p>Irving also helped popularize Santa Claus and, of course, his special version of Rip Van Winkle. ''We are all curious to know how life will go on without us,'' Professor Burstein writes. ''Rip found out.''</p>
        <p>Don't look for excessive evenhandedness in ''Facing Fascism: New York and the Spanish Civil War'' (N.Y.U. Press, $27.95), a collection of largely nostalgic essays by writers and academics. The evocative photographs in this book are black and white. In retrospect, at least, the war, fought by, among others, surrogates for Hitler and Stalin, seems more defined by shades of gray.</p>
        <p>But readers don't necessarily have to agree totally with all the premises in this book -- including E. L. Doctorow's, that the war ''was essentially a clear contest between an elected government trying to extricate its people from a feudal social system, and a privileged class intent on preserving it'' -- to revel in an era 70 years ago when global politics seemed much simpler.</p>
        <p>''That the war was pervasive in the city's consciousness I know,'' Mr. Doctorow writes, ''because as a 5-year-old, I had more than once answered the doorbell to find someone collecting money for 'Spanish War Relief.' ''</p>
        <p>This collection of essays is being published in conjunction with an exhibition through Aug. 12 at the Museum of the City of New York (and in collaboration with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives and the Instituto Cervantes).</p>
        <p>Michael Yamashita's ''New York Flying High'' (White Star, $24.95) is like soaring over the city on a perfectly clear day. Even better. In the photographer's lavishly illustrated book, you can linger, enjoying the vista without vertigo, and view rare close-ups of aeries like rooftop water tanks atop tall buildings, and the Statue of Liberty's crown.</p>
        <p>''From above, Manhattan makes sense,'' Elizabeth Bibb, a former magazine editor and Mr. Yamashita's wife, writes in the accompanying text, ''its over 50 unique neighborhoods, from SoHo to Harlem, follow a logical schematic plan, like Mondrian's 'Boogie on Broadway' come to life.''</p>
        <p>Recently Published</p>
        <p>THE BIRTHDAY PARTY  A Memoir of Survival  By Stanley N. Alpert  (Putnam, $24.95)</p>
        <p>THE BLACKEST BIRD  By Joel Rose  (W. W. Norton &amp; Company, $24.95)</p>
        <p>A GREAT TEAMMATE  The Legend of Mickey Mantle  By Randall Swearingen  (Sports Publishing L.L.C., $16.95)</p>
        <p>HEYDAY  By Kurt Andersen  (Random House, $26.95)</p>
        <p>THE LABEL  The Story of Columbia Records  By Gary Marmorstein  (Thunder's Mouth Press, $29.95)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK FASHION  By Sonnet Stanfill  (V &amp; A Publications, $55)</p>
        <p>THE WORLD IN MY KITCHEN  The Adventures of a (Mostly) French Woman in America  By Colette Rossant  (Atria Books, $22)</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: READING NEW YORK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
