<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Chatting Face to Face, Webcams With a Clearer View</title>
    <meta content="01novel" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/business/yourmoney/01novel.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837323"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NOVELTIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cameras</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cameras</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Logitech International SA</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Microsoft Corp</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906EEDB1130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1048" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Chatting Face to Face, Webcams With a Clearer View</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Chatting Face to Face, Webcams With a Clearer View</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE EISENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eisenberg, Anne</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SEEING people on screen while talking with them by phone has its advantages, but consumers have been slow to take to the video technology and its often grainy images. Now, better cameras and video services may change all that.</p>
        <p>Companies that once offered only instant messaging services have been adding and improving video messaging programs that allow subscribers to see and talk to one another, too, with tolerable sound and image quality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>To tap the potential world of video buddies, manufacturers are offering high-quality portable Web cameras.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SEEING people on screen while talking with them by phone has its advantages, but consumers have been slow to take to the video technology and its often grainy images. Now, better cameras and video services may change all that.</p>
        <p>Companies that once offered only instant messaging services have been adding and improving video messaging programs that allow subscribers to see and talk to one another, too, with tolerable sound and image quality.</p>
        <p>To tap this potential world of video buddies, manufacturers are offering high-quality portable Web cameras that clip neatly onto laptops, or pack up in small containers to be taken along on business trips.</p>
        <p>The cameras are about the size of a lipstick and plug directly into the U.S.B. port on a computer. They have built-in microphones and wide-angle lenses. Because they can be mounted securely to the top of the monitor, they will not wobble or produce unflattering, under-the-chin views of faces, as desktop Webcams are prone to do when perched on the arm of a chair or hitched temporarily to a laptop.</p>
        <p>The Webcams may have particular appeal for people who want to try video chatting but don't want to buy a new laptop with an embedded Webcam solely for the camera.</p>
        <p>The better portable Webcams typically cost at least $60 because of the quality of components like lenses. But the overall price of video chatting is modest because the major players in the industry, like Windows Live Messenger and other video message services, are free, supported in part by advertising.</p>
        <p>So if you are already paying for a broadband connection like D.S.L. or cable, which are essential for video streaming, a clip-on Webcam may yield the benefits of face-to-face conversations with business contacts, friends or far-away relatives, at no additional cost beyond the camera.</p>
        <p>To test how well the portable Webcams worked, I tried two models and asked several neighbors to experiment with them, too. We tested the Microsoft LifeCam NX-6000 ($75 to $100 on the Web), and the QuickCam for Notebooks Pro ($66 to $90), from Logitech. Our consensus is that both cameras do the job -- and are easy to set up and use.</p>
        <p>Be aware, though, that the images in live video chatting will not be as crisp as, say, still photographs taken by the same Webcams. Sending highly defined images and refreshing them many times a second requires more available bits per second than instant messaging services can usually provide.</p>
        <p>But the quality of the images transmitted by the two cameras was surprisingly good, and after an initial investment of an hour or so to set up the software and hardware, you can talk for as long as you want with no worry about the phone bill.</p>
        <p>A neighbor of mine, Li Wah Lai, a graphic designer at Standard &amp; Poor's, agreed to try both cameras with her laptop. Ms. Lai is an old hand at using Webcams: at Christmas her two sons, then planning an extended trip to China, bought her a desktop Webcam so that the family could stay in touch. The boys have Webcams that are built into their laptops -- one a Mac, the other a PC.</p>
        <p>Both sons are now in China, and Ms. Lai often has video chats with them when she is home in New York City. But she also travels a lot, and wants to keep in touch with her family at those times, too. After plugging in the new Webcams and testing them for a week, Ms. Lai decided that buying a portable camera would be a great help. ''I'm getting one,'' she said.</p>
        <p>She said that both Webcams worked well, but that she preferred the Microsoft model for several reasons, including its lens, which is retractable. It sits within the camera when you're traveling and then, with a push, pops out.</p>
        <p>A number of instant messaging programs support video chatting, including those from AOL, Skype, Yahoo and Microsoft. Ms. Lai and her sons, Mickey, 20, who is studying in Shanghai, and Ming, 22, teaching English in Qingdao, all use Skype.</p>
        <p>I decided to try the cameras with a different system, Windows Live Messenger, and the e-mail service with which it is paired, Hotmail. First, I signed up for both and installed the camera software, which comes on a CD and offers special features like on-screen controls that let you zoom in, pan and tilt. That took about 10 minutes.</p>
        <p>Once the software was installed and the screen gave the go-ahead, I plugged the camera into a U.S.B. port. I read a bit of text into the microphone in a normal voice and adjusted the controls. Then I started getting used to the sight of myself on the screen. All of that took another 10 minutes.</p>
        <p>Finally, after clicking on the name and e-mail address of a friend I had persuaded to sign up, I pressed the Live Call button, and we were in business.</p>
        <p>We talked and typed, sending still pictures with one click and short videos with another. I had expected the video to have some distortion, but on screen my chat buddy sounded and looked very close to his in-person self.</p>
        <p>I tried out the Logitech camera with Skype Video Messaging. The Logitech Webcam has a slightly snugger fit on the screen lid than the Microsoft version, and is a bit more compact. It compensates well for dim lighting. The sensor on its camera has 1.3 megapixels, versus 2 megapixels for the Microsoft version.</p>
        <p>But I saw no difference in the instant-messaging video images of the two cameras; both were diminished by the transmission process, which typically reduces the 30 frames a second the cameras can produce to 15.</p>
        <p>''We can do 1.3 megapixels at 30 frames a second,'' Andrew Heymann, senior global product manager at Logitech, said of its Webcam. But the instant messaging services ask for far fewer megapixels at 15 frames a second, ''so we compress the data off the camera,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Despite the imperfect images that result primarily from data compression on the messaging services, Ms. Lai is highly pleased with the images of her sons when she talks with them.</p>
        <p>''It makes me feel good just to see their faces,'' she said. ''With the camera, it's like they are next door.''</p>
        <p>NOVELTIES E-mail: novelties@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: novelties@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
