<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Awaited Matchup Between Oden and Hibbert Has Little Chance to Materialize</title>
    <meta content="01lapointe" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/sports/ncaabasketball/01lapointe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837452"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Ohio State University</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Georgetown University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Oden, Greg</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E5DC1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="703" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Awaited Matchup Between Oden and Hibbert Has Little Chance to Materialize</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Matchup of Big Men, Ohio State’s Oden Comes Out the Ultimate Winner</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, March 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some day, perhaps in the N.B.A., fans will be able to see and enjoy the much-anticipated one-on-one matchup between Greg Oden and Roy Hibbert, two 7-foot centers. Might it be like the legendary battles between Bill Russell and Wilt Chamberlain, or something different?</p>
        <p>A national television audience and a throng at the Georgia Dome wanted to see the matchup Saturday night when Oden's Ohio State Buckeyes defeated Hibbert's Georgetown Hoyas by 67-60 in the semifinals of the N.C.A.A. tournament.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Statistically, Georgetown’s Roy Hibbert did better than Ohio State’s Greg Oden on Saturday. But Oden’s Buckeyes are the ones who will be playing for a national championship.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Some day, perhaps in the N.B.A., fans will be able to see and enjoy the much-anticipated one-on-one matchup between Greg Oden and Roy Hibbert, two 7-foot centers. Might it be like the legendary battles between Bill Russell and Wilt Chamberlain, or something different?</p>
        <p>A national television audience and a throng at the Georgia Dome wanted to see the matchup Saturday night when Oden's Ohio State Buckeyes defeated Hibbert's Georgetown Hoyas by 67-60 in the semifinals of the N.C.A.A. tournament.</p>
        <p>But foul trouble prevented both men from being on the floor together for 25 of the first 33 minutes of a 40-minute game. By the time they returned to play at the same time, the Buckeyes were ahead and on their way to the title game Monday night against Florida.</p>
        <p>Oden is a freshman and soon could be on the way to the pros. Hibbert is a junior and also might leave college this spring. But for a brief moment outside the locker room Saturday night, Hibbert smiled and thought about another go-round.</p>
        <p>''I'd like to see him back next year and we could do it again,'' Hibbert said. ''It was a good matchup. He's a good kid and he's going to do great things. It was a good battle. I would have liked to have seen more of it.''</p>
        <p>Statistically, Hibbert did better. In 24 minutes, he scored 19 points and had 6 rebounds. Oden, in 20 minutes, had 13 points and 9 rebounds. Both players had four fouls. Would Oden liked to have faced Hibbert for more minutes, man to man?</p>
        <p>''Not really,'' Oden said. ''I mean, he shot over me a bunch of times, so you see what he can do. All I care about is we won.''</p>
        <p>One of Oden's most impressive moments came with 6 minutes 37 seconds left in the game, Hibbert on the bench and Oden leading the rally that would turn a 44-44 tie into a 7-point Buckeyes lead. After starting a fast break with a rebound and a pass, Oden got the ball back at the other end.</p>
        <p>He tried for a leaping slam dunk that seemed to begin in the upper deck of the dome and ended up with him sprawled on the floor when he was fouled by Jeff Green of the Hoyas. Even though Oden missed the shot, leading to two free throws, the fans gasped and chattered about the scene.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to get in there and just tear the rim down,'' Oden said.</p>
        <p>When they were playing at the same time, Hibbert scored the first points, with a sweeping hook in the first minute. Oden picked up his second foul in the third minute and sat down for the rest of the half.</p>
        <p>''What happened?'' Oden said. ''The ref blew the whistle. I can't lower my shoulder. I can't move setting ball screens.''</p>
        <p>Hibbert started the second half with a two-handed dunk and blocked a follow shot by Oden a couple of minutes later, but he sat down with his third foul when he made contact with Ivan Harris on Harris's put-back attempt. Hibbert came to the bench shaking his head.</p>
        <p>''Wrong place at the wrong time,'' Hibbert said. ''I just needed to make smarter decisions out there.'' On the postgame dais, Hibbert seemed depressed as he sat next to his coach, John Thompson III, and a few teammates.</p>
        <p>Hibbert leaned back, then leaned forward and put his right hand -- clenched into a fist -- over his mouth. He then raised his gaze to the ceiling and rolled his eyes. When it was over, he sighed loudly and walked slowly toward a golf cart that took him back to the locker room.</p>
        <p>But, outside the door, he held in his hand the statistical sheet for the game as well as the placard bearing his name from the interview room that had rested in front of him; souvenirs from a major night in his young life.</p>
        <p>Hibbert seemed to perk up in later discussions with members of the news media, smiling and patiently answering the same questions many times. When someone again wanted to know about the battle against Oden, Hibbert smiled, shrugged and said, ''I guess he won.''</p>
        <p>N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
