<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Stay-at-Home Mom Who'd (Maybe) Rather Not</title>
    <meta content="01RgenWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837191"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GENERATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sender, Lori</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E1DC1030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1012" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Stay-at-Home Mom Who'd (Maybe) Rather Not</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LORI SENDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sender, Lori</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lori Sender Generations essay on ambivalence she feels as she considers returning to work now that her son is 7; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MY 7-year-old son, Ben, appears to have found his first, true, best friend. I can hear them one room over -- they sound as if they could hang out all day, deeply talking. ''Do you like the smell of wine?'' Joshua asks my son. Oh great, I think, soon they'll be going out drinking. ''Did you know Listerine can make bombs?'' he adds. I listen more closely.</p>
        <p>Later on they're playing ''restaurant management,'' and our kitchen counter is littered with pantry stock. I have the role of fussy patron, and as much as I'm trying to stay in character, I keep fast-forwarding to the final scene of me as busboy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MY 7-year-old son, Ben, appears to have found his first, true, best friend. I can hear them one room over -- they sound as if they could hang out all day, deeply talking. ''Do you like the smell of wine?'' Joshua asks my son. Oh great, I think, soon they'll be going out drinking. ''Did you know Listerine can make bombs?'' he adds. I listen more closely.</p>
        <p>Later on they're playing ''restaurant management,'' and our kitchen counter is littered with pantry stock. I have the role of fussy patron, and as much as I'm trying to stay in character, I keep fast-forwarding to the final scene of me as busboy.</p>
        <p>This is the story of a mother with too much time on her hands, one who should probably have a job, but instead is stuck in the house in her son's play-date face. One by one, the neighborhood moms have gone off to work. I'm the lone wolf now, surveying the suburban landscape, watching out for any fenced dogs gone astray (so far two), car thefts (one), the last vestige of midafternoon door opener for the PSE&amp;G man.</p>
        <p>Now the boys are in my jewelry box looking for bracelets. ''Punch me in the head,'' my son says, laughing, from my bedroom. The sirens of working women are calling to me: paycheck, solitude of train to Manhattan, lunches with women. Soon I will follow their call. But I'm ambivalent. I'm still important here in my son's life -- not to mention in the lives of all his friends I've managed to steal from after-school programs. I know any day now Ben will join them, and maybe should. Lately I can feel the shift of power. Pretty soon he and his friends will be grabbing their own snacks from the pantry, and then I will be nearly obsolete. As it is, when I say only two cookies, they look at me as if they could really take me on.</p>
        <p>I didn't have Ben until I was 42. When he turned 3, I realized that the chances of a sister or brother were nearly nil, and that I'd be wearing the hat of mother, friend and sibling. But then he went and turned 7 and fun mom turned 50 and Monopoly on the rug demanded contortions of the hip. I have my days -- like my last-minute stab at a winter vacation, when I grabbed another family and drove to Montreal to go tubing down Mount Royal -- but let's face it, I'm more fun now for dinner conversation and a cuddly movie.</p>
        <p>The two boys are now online sledding with penguin children on clubpenguin.com. They're squealing with delight, and I find myself dropping the kitchen sponge and climbing upstairs to see what all the commotion is about. I watch from behind as they race other penguins down the mountain, flying over tree trunks, jumping moguls, colliding with one another. They decide to meet later that night at the Web site's arcade and nightclub. I'm guessing there will be girl penguins there, and then I see some of the sledders' names --Princessax, ButEful, Glamcutie.</p>
        <p>I notice that my neighborhood friend, the latest to embark into the work world, looks harried. I watch her rushing off each morning, her makeup getting less and less pronounced, her hair no longer blown dry. At night I see her headlights pull in late, and I want to throw a big warm blanket around her and hand her a roasted chicken. We used to talk each morning at the bus stop -- through wind, snow, it didn't matter, just reveling in our gossip with our rain-stained coffee. Now I no longer see her. That kind of stress could easily cause my undoing.</p>
        <p>Part-time work, I'm thinking. I mention this to my husband, who winces back at me. Full-time pay would be better, he mumbles.</p>
        <p>I've been going over my options. There's that dusty old pharmacy degree from the '80s -- maybe turning that into two days a week at some slow-paced chain store. Or writing -- that literature professor on the bus in Boston actually remembered my work all those years later. And what about the classical piano lessons I had growing up. Just recently I saw some guy performing at schools as Mozart. Surely there's room for Clara Schumann, 19th-century virtuoso.</p>
        <p>I'm panicking, but just a little. I know I can figure this out; I just need more time.</p>
        <p>''I need more time,'' I say to my husband, who smiles weakly.</p>
        <p>It's a week later, a Friday, and I gather a giddy Ben and Joshua off the bus. Their plan is to make a short snowman from last night's minimal snowfall. ''See the sun?'' I say, pointing upward. ''There's no more snow left.'' Not to be deterred, they collect pinches of snow off the driveways on our block, and I take a picture of them holding a six-inch mud-packed figure with a carrot-grate nub. ''Snowball fight,'' my son declares, and the boys quickly disassemble him for new purposes. And then it's back to their computer penguins.</p>
        <p>Ben shouts down to me, ''Mom, I just bought a puffle!'' He shows me his pet puffle and the flooring he has chosen for his loft-size igloo. As I leave the room I hear them discussing rugs, window treatments and couch colors, and I feel the tug of his ever-so-slight growing-up.</p>
        <p>I'm starting to formulate a plan for Ben and me. I figure next year, when he's in third grade, a couple of days each week in the after-school program wouldn't be terribly traumatic for either of us.</p>
        <p>I think back to when he was 18 months old, the only time I put him in day care. We both lasted one day. When I picked him up I found him in a highchair facing the front door, crying at the sight of me. The caretaker said he had cried throughout the day and would stop only if she had him facing the door. I know those days are over for him; it's me I'm still concerned about.</p>
        <p>GENERATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
