<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Flashing A Subtler Side Instead Of Underpants</title>
    <meta content="01lidz" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/movies/01lidz.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837118"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lidz, Franz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shannon, Molly</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Year of the Dog (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Saturday Night Live (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Actors and Actresses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Actors and Actresses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Shannon, Molly</person>
        <person class="online_producer">White, Mike</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Year of the Dog (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DD1330F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1295" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Flashing A Subtler Side Instead Of Underpants</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Flashing a Subtler Side Instead of Underpants</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANZ LIDZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lidz, Franz</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles actress Molly Shannon, known for nuttiness on Saturday Night Live, who appears in more subtle role in new film Year Of The Dog; life and career described; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE last time Molly Shannon put on a show that wasn't for laughs was when, on a dare from her father, she stowed away on a People Express flight to New York City from Cleveland. She was 12.</p>
        <p>Just before takeoff, Ms. Shannon and her best friend from Shaker Heights, Ohio, dashed aboard wearing pink leotards and tights, assuring a stewardess that they were just saying goodbye to their sister. ''I tried my best to come off as sweet and innocent,'' she said. ''But my heart was pounding so loud I could hardly hear.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The new film “Year of the Dog” gives Molly Shannon the opportunity to tap into her personal pain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE last time Molly Shannon put on a show that wasn't for laughs was when, on a dare from her father, she stowed away on a People Express flight to New York City from Cleveland. She was 12.</p>
        <p>Just before takeoff, Ms. Shannon and her best friend from Shaker Heights, Ohio, dashed aboard wearing pink leotards and tights, assuring a stewardess that they were just saying goodbye to their sister. ''I tried my best to come off as sweet and innocent,'' she said. ''But my heart was pounding so loud I could hardly hear.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Shannon and her pal ducked into a seat. Waved off the plane on arrival, they took a subway to Rockefeller Center, where Ms. Shannon would one day make her name as a geek goddess on ''Saturday Night Live.''</p>
        <p>''If my friend and I hadn't sneaked on that plane, we had a fallback plan,'' she said. ''We would have hopped on a bus and gone to ballet practice.''</p>
        <p>Thirty years later Ms. Shannon is about to play it almost straight again in ''Year of the Dog,'' a film that Mike White, its writer and a first-time director, describes as ''a comedy that's not very funny.'' In ''Year of the Dog,'' which opens Friday, she plays a shy, chirpy secretary named Peggy who literally goes to the dogs when her beloved beagle, Pencil, dies.</p>
        <p>The aggrieved Peggy renounces humanity, adopts every condemned pooch at the pound and becomes such a militant animal-rights advocate that she drowns her sister-in-law's furs in a bathtub.</p>
        <p>Watching Ms. Shannon in ''Year of the Dog'' may be unsettling for viewers who know her as Mary Katherine Gallagher, the most popular of the manic misfits she created during her six seasons on ''SNL.'' Under duress Ms. Shannon's hapless Catholic school girl -- the epitome of excruciating adolescence -- would hook her fingers under her armpits, then sniff them.</p>
        <p>Mary Katherine reached the height of her white cotton Carter's underpants-flashing fame in ''Superstar'' (1999), another ''SNL'' skit turned into a toothless feature-length film, in which she French-kissed a tree. Of her budding breasts, she observes in the movie: ''This one is bigger than this one 'cause this is the mommy and that's the baby. And this one is very nice to this one, and they hold hands because they're friends.''</p>
        <p>The pratfall-heavy ''Superstar'' and nearly every other movie Ms. Shannon has made since graduating from New York University in 1987 have showcased her exuberance and gift for physical mayhem. She has been a homeless woman (''Lawnmower Man 2: Beyond Cyberspace''), a Who (''How the Grinch Stole Christmas'') and a lusty drunk (''Talladega Nights: The Ballad of Ricky Bobby'').</p>
        <p>Nothing about Ms. Shannon's previous film work hinted that she could handle Peggy's neediness and lunging desperation.</p>
        <p>''The comedy, I was expecting,'' one of her co-stars, Josh Pais, said in a recent telephone interview. ''What I didn't anticipate was the level of pain Molly brought to the role. She perfectly captures a woman who has lost everything she identifies with and is left with nothing. You feel her misery, but it never becomes melodramatic or squashes the comedy.''</p>
        <p>John C. Reilly, who plays Peggy's trigger-happy neighbor, says Ms. Shannon brings the same intensity and chaotic commitment to drama that she does to slapstick. ''As funny as Molly is,'' Mr. Reilly said, ''she has the heart of a real actor.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly previously worked with Ms. Shannon in ''Never Been Kissed'' (1999) and ''Talladega Nights'' (2006). ''She doesn't just joke it the way most comedians do,'' he said. ''I haven't met another actress who can be broad and clownish and yet is so unafraid to be deadly serious.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pais said that whenever Ms. Shannon was asked to give an alternate take of an anguished scene, she would say, ''Just give me a minute,'' and then step away from the camera. ''Molly's face would crinkle like balled-up paper,'' he said. ''As she took a breath, you could almost see her draw from some dark well of emotion from her past.''</p>
        <p>It's a deep well. ''I can relate to the part of Peggy that doesn't want to feel her devastation,'' Ms. Shannon offered. She was saying this in a restaurant near the meatpacking district loft she shares with her two toddlers and husband, the photorealist painter Fritz Chesnut. While lunching on sausage and eggs -- a dish the vegan Peggy wouldn't touch with a 10-foot fork -- she projected a childlike excitement that verged on giddiness.</p>
        <p>''I like the fact that Peggy struggles through something to get to a better place,'' Ms. Shannon said.</p>
        <p>She did. Her childhood sounds like a cross between ''Ponette'' and ''Ferris Bueller's Day Off.'' At 4 she was in a car crash that killed her mother, a cousin and her younger sister. Though Ms. Shannon was unharmed, her father was maimed. ''His legs were crushed,'' she said. ''He wore a brace for the rest of his life.''</p>
        <p>While her father, James, was laid up in intensive care, Ms. Shannon and her older sister, Mary, stayed with their Aunt Bernie in Cleveland Heights. ''I'd ask where my dad was, and no one would tell me,'' she said. ''For a long time after that I had trouble trusting people.'' She later incorporated her anxiety about life into Mary Katherine and other uneasy characters.</p>
        <p>After the accident Mr. Shannon quit his job as a sales manager and stayed home to raise Molly and Mary. ''My dad was a bohemian who hated rules,'' Ms. Shannon recalled. He encouraged her after-school high jinks -- crashing around candy stores as if she were blind, undressing department store mannequins and posing them suggestively. ''He liked wild and crazy stuff,'' Ms. Shannon said.</p>
        <p>The wildest and craziest was her stowaway stunt. Ms. Shannon waited until she and her friend got to Manhattan before phoning her father. ''He was really excited to hear that we'd succeeded,'' she said.</p>
        <p>When Ms. Shannon asked what they should do for an encore, Mr. Shannon suggested stowing their way back. After they tried and failed, he arranged for two return tickets. The stowaways paid him back from baby-sitting. ''Years of baby-sitting,'' Ms. Shannon allowed.</p>
        <p>A gig singing telegrams at stag parties was followed by drama school at New York University, an improv comedy show in Los Angeles and, in 1995, ''Saturday Night Live.'' Nine years later she was cast in Mr. White's Fox sitcom ''Cracking Up.'' Ms. Shannon described her character as a ''typical alcoholic, bipolar, self-involved, pill-popping Beverly Hills housewife.''</p>
        <p>''Cracking Up'' was canceled after only a handful of episodes. ''Fighting the network every step of the way was a terrible experience,'' said Mr. White, whose screenwriting credits include ''School of Rock,'' ''Nacho Libre'' and ''The Good Girl.'' ''But Molly was terrific and, as a personal creative exorcism, I decided to write a movie for her.''</p>
        <p>That movie turned out to be ''Year of the Dog.'' If it should turn out to be the dog of the year, Ms. Shannon has a couple of fallbacks. Next month she'll be seen in ''Sing Now or Forever Hold Your Peace,'' Bruce Leddy's low-budget manifesto about a singing group that reunites at a wedding. This summer she'll pop up as a real estate agent in ''Evan Almighty,'' the sequel to the 2003 hit ''Bruce Almighty.'' And Ms. Shannon just completed the pilot for ''The Mastersons of Manhattan,'' a comic soap opera in which she and Natasha Richardson play socialite sisters.</p>
        <p>Pet grooming is apparently not a career option. During a preproduction photo shoot for Ms. Shannon's new film, a canine co-star licked her cheeks, causing them to erupt in red welts. ''I was horrified,'' Mr. White said. ''Molly looked like a Chernobyl victim.''</p>
        <p>It was only then that Ms. Shannon admitted she's allergic to dogs.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
