<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A 5-Foot-6 Bruiser's Journey From East Meadow to a Title Bout</title>
    <meta content="01LIPeopleLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/01LIPeople.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837160"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MIXED MARTIAL ARTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Martial Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Serra, Matt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischler, Marcelle S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Martial Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Martial Arts</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EED61330F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="867" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A 5-Foot-6 Bruiser's Journey From East Meadow to a Title Bout</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A 5-Foot-6 Bruiser’s Journey From East Meadow to a Title Bout</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCELLE S. FISCHLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fischler, Marcelle S</byline>
      <dateline>HUNTINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of and interview with Matt Serra, owner of Brazilian jiujitsu school in Huntington, NY, who will be competing for welterweight title of Ultimate Fighting Championship at Toyota Center in Houston, Tex; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>USING a choke hold or an arm lock, Matt Serra can make almost anyone cry uncle.</p>
        <p>''It's all leverage and technique more than size and strength,'' said Mr. Serra, who describes himself as ''5-foot-6 dynamite'' and weighs 174 pounds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Huntington.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>USING a choke hold or an arm lock, Matt Serra can make almost anyone cry uncle.</p>
        <p>''It's all leverage and technique more than size and strength,'' said Mr. Serra, who describes himself as ''5-foot-6 dynamite'' and weighs 174 pounds.</p>
        <p>The owner of a Brazilian jiujitsu school here that bears his name, Mr. Serra demonstrated his technique on a recent afternoon to an intermediate adult class. He used his hand to grab his opponent behind the bend of one knee and wedged his opposite foot on the student's instep, tumbling them both to the ground. From underneath, he tightly crunched his legs around his opponent's body and clamped his armpits on his toes and feet.</p>
        <p>In addition to holding a black belt in Brazilian jiujitsu, which focuses on grappling and ground fighting, Mr. Serra, 32, competes in mixed martial arts, a sport that includes not only jiujitsu but also karate, boxing, kickboxing, wrestling and other forms of fighting. Matches often take place in an eight-sided cage called the octagon.</p>
        <p>As Matt (the Terror) Serra, he will be competing for the welterweight title of the Ultimate Fighting Championship -- what he calls ''the Super Bowl of mixed martial arts.'' The match, at the Toyota Center in Houston, is to be broadcast live at 10 p.m. on April 7 on pay-per-view.</p>
        <p>''I am an expert on the floor and I am dangerous in all areas, not to toot my own horn,'' Mr. Serra boasted. ''They go to kick me or punch me and I usually just get them down. From there that's where I own them.''</p>
        <p>He got his crack at the top spot after winning the championship in a 13-week competition last fall against 16 mixed martial artists on the Spike TV reality show ''The Ultimate Fighter 4: The Comeback.'' Some of his $100,000 winnings from the show went toward a new home in Massapequa.</p>
        <p>Mr. Serra fights barefoot. Size doesn't hold him back; his last three opponents, he says, were taller, lankier and stronger. ''When we hit the floor, we are the same size,'' he said. ''It doesn't matter anymore. Those long limbs are going to be not to his benefit anymore.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Serra fights by the rules, such as they are, in this brutal-looking contact sport. (It is sanctioned in many states, but not in New York.) No eye gouging. No kicking an opponent in the head. One moment he looks like he is hugging his challenger; the next he flips the rival over his back onto the floor.</p>
        <p>''I am getting him down any way I can without using strength,'' Mr. Serra said, citing his use of submission holds or armlocks or choke holds to make an opponent give up.</p>
        <p>Growing up in East Meadow, Mr. Serra got into his share of scraps.</p>
        <p>''My teachers used to point to the jail across the street and say that's where my fists would land me,'' said Mr. Serra, who graduated from East Meadow High School in 1992. His father, Ralph, a New York City police officer and lifelong martial artist, showed him a videotape about the fighting Gracie family from Brazil. Mr. Serra was intrigued and started training at Renzo Gracie Jiu Jitsu Academy in Manhattan. After a while he was hired and began moving up the ranks in the fighting sport.</p>
        <p>''Finding the Brazilian jiujitsu and the mixed martial arts, I turned it into a positive outlet and took a turn for the better,'' Mr. Serra said.</p>
        <p>He opened a school in East Meadow in 2002 and a larger one in Huntington the following year. Mr. Serra and his brother Nick, who is also a black belt, have close to 400 students, from 8 to 59 years old, including a few women.</p>
        <p>''I get to help a lot of teenagers and kids that were maybe like me when they were younger,'' Mr. Serra said. ''Now they have the jiujitsu so they can compete and be tough guys that way.''</p>
        <p>In 1999, Mr. Serra won the Pan American Games in Brazilian jiujitsu in Miami. That same year he won gold in the World Championships in Brazil. At a grappling tournament in Abu Dhabi in 2001, he caught the attention of the Ultimate Fighting Championship, a Las Vegas-based mixed martial arts organization.</p>
        <p>These days Mr. Serra's bare-chested image is on a billboard in Times Square promoting his coming match. Besides training four to five hours a day, he has made the round of talk shows, from ''The Dr. Keith Ablow Show'' to ''Fox &amp; Friends.''</p>
        <p>People have started to notice. ''It is not overwhelming, like you are George Clooney, but at the Starbucks, at the 7-Eleven or walking around Manhattan or the Roosevelt Field Mall, I do get recognized,'' Mr. Serra said. ''It's nice.''</p>
        <p>Comparing himself to Rocky Balboa, Mr. Serra said he is ready for his fight against the welterweight titleholder, Georges St.-Pierre, a Canadian.</p>
        <p>''He is chiseled, bigger, strong, a little younger,'' Mr. Serra said of his opponent. But Mr. Serra is not worried.</p>
        <p>''I have a lot of experience and I have got my own skills,'' he said. ''I am training hard, and I am getting ready to shock a lot of people.''</p>
        <p>MIXED MARTIAL ARTS E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
