<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kermit the Frog Turned Me Into a Puppeteer</title>
    <meta content="01ctpeopleCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/01ctpeople.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837173"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BEHIND THE SCENES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Puppets</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Osbahr, Carmen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Henson, Jim (1936-90)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gerstenzang, Peter</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Johnny and the Sprites (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Puppets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Toys</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E5DC1030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="740" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kermit the Frog Turned Me Into a Puppeteer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Kermit the Frog Turned Me Into a Puppeteer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER GERSTENZANG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gerstenzang, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of and interview with Carmen Osbahr of Fairfield, Conn, who comments on her mentor, Jim Henson, her work on Sesame Street and her new stint as puppeteer on television series Johnny and the Sprites; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVEN though Carmen Osbahr likes to quip that she wasn't born with a puppet in her hand, children who know her as Lily, the water sprite, on Disney's ''Johnny and the Sprites'' may be inclined to disagree.</p>
        <p>''I really grew up with no specific ideas of what I wanted to be,'' said Ms. Osbahr, who is originally from Mexico City but now lives in Fairfield. ''In 1969, though, I had an epiphany when I was watching 'Sesame Street.' I saw Elmo and Big Bird and I was blown away. I wondered: 'Who is making these puppets move? Who is Jim Henson?' From there, I was hooked.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Carmen Osbahr likes to quip that she wasn’t born with a puppet in her hand.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVEN though Carmen Osbahr likes to quip that she wasn't born with a puppet in her hand, children who know her as Lily, the water sprite, on Disney's ''Johnny and the Sprites'' may be inclined to disagree.</p>
        <p>''I really grew up with no specific ideas of what I wanted to be,'' said Ms. Osbahr, who is originally from Mexico City but now lives in Fairfield. ''In 1969, though, I had an epiphany when I was watching 'Sesame Street.' I saw Elmo and Big Bird and I was blown away. I wondered: 'Who is making these puppets move? Who is Jim Henson?' From there, I was hooked.</p>
        <p>''I took journalism in college, but when I was hired in 1981 to work on Televisa Mexico and began doing puppetry on a show called 'Xe-Tu,' everything changed for me. Jim Henson's people eventually saw my work, and in 1988 they asked me if I wanted to be on 'Sesame Street.' ''</p>
        <p>Ms. Osbahr glows when speaking of the late puppeteer. ''Jim was not only brilliantly talented,'' she said, ''but very kind and protective of me. When I first met him, I was shy and my English was not very good. But he said to me in his voice -- which was exactly like Kermit the Frog's -- 'Carmen, would you like to be part of my family?' How could anyone resist that?''</p>
        <p>Ms. Osbahr, whose other alter ego, Rosita, can still be seen on ''Sesame Street,'' also credits Mr. Henson for showing her that puppets, and children's shows in general, don't have to be sweet or simple-minded to appeal to youngsters.</p>
        <p>''One of the things I love about 'Johnny and the Sprites,' that I think Jim really pioneered,'' she said, ''is that puppets can look strange and the stories they tell can be dark at times and kids will still take to them.''</p>
        <p>That is certainly true of ''Johnny,'' which is about a singer-songwriter who lives near a magical world filled with sprites. In a recent episode Johnny becomes obsessed with video games and ends up dreaming that he is an old man, having been blinded to the passage of time by his obsession. The puppets, too, like Ms. Osbahr's character, are also strange-looking, with antennae and bulging eyes.</p>
        <p>Jim Henson may have changed children's shows from soothing to thought-provoking, but what hasn't changed, Ms. Osbahr said, is the amount of physical strain shows like ''Johnny'' put on the puppeteers.</p>
        <p>''We're basically on the floor all day, sitting in things called 'rollies,' that get us and our characters around,'' Ms. Osbahr said. ''We also have our arms above our heads for hours at a time. Add to this different hands, sometimes using rods, that get the puppets to talk, move and make realistic eye contact. It's physically demanding. Early in my career, my body would be in a knot after a day of filming. Now, I'm pretty much use to all the contortions.''</p>
        <p>John Tartaglia, who stars in and co-created ''Johnny,'' first met Ms. Osbahr in the 1980s, when he was 16 and working on ''Sesame Street.'' ''I was the new kid and felt very much like an outsider,'' Mr. Tartaglia said. ''Carmen, though, took me under her wing and made me feel at home. It was sheer coincidence when she came in to audition for my show years later. But a lucky one. Carmen made Lily much more dramatic, funny and artistic than we envisioned her. Also, we never wanted the show to talk down to kids. She understood that immediately.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Osbahr's talent was apparent from the start. ''We tried to be fair and saw lots of puppeteers for the part, but no one else showed the same creativity and energy as Carmen,'' said Paula Rosenthal, vice president of original programming for Playhouse Disney. ''She also fit in seamlessly with the other people we had cast. Watching them all work together now is like seeing a great symphony. Carmen was the instrument we were missing.''</p>
        <p>If Ms. Osbahr has any regrets about her success, it's that with ''Johnny'' already renewed for next year, she won't have much time this summer to spend with her husband and 6-year-old son.</p>
        <p>''We don't live far from the beach, but I don't think I will be seeing much of it, what with our filming schedule,'' she said. ''Still, when you're in show business, being that busy is not the worst problem you can have.''</p>
        <p>BEHIND THE SCENES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
