<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bloomberg at a Checkpoint: 1,000 Days Left on the Job</title>
    <meta content="01legacy" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/01legacy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837391"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Watches and Clocks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bloomberg, Michael R (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Sam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Watches and Clocks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <org class="online_producer">City Hall</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bloomberg, Michael R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E0DE1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1055" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bloomberg at a Checkpoint: 1,000 Days Left on the Job</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">1,000 Days Left for Bloomberg, All of Them on His Own Terms</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Sam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mayor Michael R Bloomberg keeps red digital clock in bullpen at City Hall that ticks off days, minutes and seconds remaining in his second term; as 1,000-day mark approaches, Bloomberg believes it is not time to slown down but time to speed up in order to leave stable and enduring legacy; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''The Hundred Days is indelibly associated with Franklin D. Roosevelt, and the Thousand Days with John F. Kennedy,'' the historian Arthur M. Schlesinger Jr. wrote last year -- neat time frames that defined the breathtaking debut of the New Deal and, as it turned out, just about the entire tenure of the New Frontier.</p>
        <p>In 2002, Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg approached his first such benchmark rather modestly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York City Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg has embraced an audacious managerial strategy in an effort to expand and preserve his legacy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''The Hundred Days is indelibly associated with Franklin D. Roosevelt, and the Thousand Days with John F. Kennedy,'' the historian Arthur M. Schlesinger Jr. wrote last year -- neat time frames that defined the breathtaking debut of the New Deal and, as it turned out, just about the entire tenure of the New Frontier.</p>
        <p>In 2002, Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg approached his first such benchmark rather modestly.</p>
        <p>''What did I do in the first 100 days?'' he asked rhetorically at the time. ''I think the answer is I got ready for the next 1,000.'' Then he went on to award his administration ''an A-plus for the things that matter: Set the tone and pick the team.''</p>
        <p>Five years later, with much of the same team still in place, but the tone considerably more self-confident and accomplished, the mayor has embraced an audacious managerial strategy in an effort to expand and preserve his legacy.</p>
        <p>In a prominent corner (near the pantry) of the second-floor bullpen at City Hall where he and his inner circle work, a red digital clock beneath a sign that urges ''Make Every Day Count'' ticks off the days, minutes and seconds remaining in Mr. Bloomberg's second term.</p>
        <p>This week, the countdown clock will signal a milestone: The beginning of the final 1,000 days of the Bloomberg administration. ''We have a lot to do, and the countdown clock is a very real reminder,'' Stu Loeser, the mayor's spokesman, said. ''The mayor believes it's not time to slow down. It's time to speed up.''</p>
        <p>By this point in his second term, a mayor -- particularly one barred by term limits from seeking re-election -- might well be thinking ahead to his next job or retirement and contemplating which sinecures to reserve for his cronies.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bloomberg, who successfully challenged political precedent in the first place by winning the mayoralty without having held another elective office, is intent on leaving City Hall on his own terms.</p>
        <p>He has arguably preserved, or even enhanced, his power by refusing to flatly rule out the possibility of a 2008 presidential run. But because higher elective office remains unlikely, he is not hobbled by the inevitable competition between governing and pursuing a political agenda.</p>
        <p>''He's not spending the time running for the next office, which is often what influences a second term,'' said Steve Malanga, a senior fellow at the Manhattan Institute, a conservative research group.</p>
        <p>The mayor has said he intends to disburse a billion dollars or more through a personal foundation, which means he will remain a presence to be courted and reckoned with in New York and beyond.</p>
        <p>Just last week, in collaboration with Christine C. Quinn, the City Council speaker -- herself term-limited and hoping for the mayor's endorsement to succeed him -- Mr. Bloomberg signed a bill requiring that any future benefits for married people working for the city also be granted to domestic partners and that businesses that use bicycle delivery workers provide them with helmets.</p>
        <p>''They're doing a lot of this stuff statutorily so it is more difficult to undo,'' said Douglas A. Muzzio, a professor of public affairs at Baruch College.</p>
        <p>The mayor also began an incentive program to reduce poverty by paying poor families up to $5,000 a year to meet goals like attending parent-teacher conferences, going for a medical checkup or holding down a full-time job. The idea is just an experiment for now, using private donations (including his own), though the mayor hopes to attract public money if it proves effective. His administration also is taking steps to blunt opposition when mayoral control of the school system comes up for legislative renewal in 2009.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bloomberg has embraced the strategic economic development agenda advanced by Daniel L. Doctoroff, the deputy mayor for economic development, including his ambitious campaign to prepare now for a bigger, older and environmentally more unpredictable city in 2030.</p>
        <p>''I don't remember a mayor as focused on the long term as Bloomberg is,'' Professor Muzzio said.</p>
        <p>The administration's unfinished agenda includes mass transit construction, including the extension of the Flushing line to the Far West Side; creating or preserving (or at least financing and finding sites for) 125,000 more homes and tens of thousands of classrooms, improving the power supply, reclaiming underused contaminated land, opening the waterfront and harbor to recreation, rezoning for housing and commercial development in Manhattan, Queens and Brooklyn, enacting a new building code and advancing projects like Brooklyn Bridge Park, a recreation area at the former Fresh Kills landfill and development of the Atlantic Yards in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>When he first took office, Mr. Bloomberg embraced much of the agenda of his predecessor, Rudolph W. Giuliani, but did not follow it in lockstep. He returned power to business improvement districts, undid stadium deals with the Yankees and Mets, restored the city bar association's role in recommending judges for reappointment and symbolically designated the Tweed Courthouse, behind City Hall, as a school and the headquarters of his new Department of Education, rather than as a home for the Museum of the City of New York.</p>
        <p>About that time, Fred Siegel, a history professor at Cooper Union, forecast that the endurance of Mr. Giuliani's legacy would depend on whether he had fundamentally transformed what New Yorkers expect from city government. Five years later, Professor Siegel says he is comfortable that the Giuliani administration's changes in welfare and policing will, indeed, endure.</p>
        <p>Similarly, he predicted, ''the sense that New York is not an ungovernable city will endure after Bloomberg.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Quinn, the Council speaker, said she was unconcerned that Mr. Bloomberg's successor would find his, or her, hands tied.</p>
        <p>''I don't know that you can ever assure that a successor will follow in the same footsteps, but if you leave a city better than you found it, what mayor isn't going to want to go in that direction,'' she said. ''You can de facto assure your legacy will continue because what mayor would get rid of what New Yorkers like and works well?''</p>
        <p>She contrasted New York today with the more fragile city that Mr. Bloomberg inherited after 2001. ''If you're lucky enough to not start in a place like that, it's really a gift,'' Ms. Quinn said. ''It's a sense of stability from which you can continue your predecessor's work and implement your own vision.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
