<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>3 Originals From a Busy Decade</title>
    <meta content="01tomm" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/arts/music/01tomm.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837134"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pacifica Quartet</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tommasini, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hindemith, Paul (1895-1963)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Janacek, Leos (1854-1928)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seeger, Ruth Crawford (D1953)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Pacifica Quartet</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EFDD1330F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="498" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>3 Originals From a Busy Decade</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">3 Originals From a Busy Decade</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Tommasini reviews new Pacific Quartet CD containing works by Paul Hindemith, Leos Janacek and Ruth Crawford Seeger (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVEN contemporary-music buffs can sometimes be overwhelmed by the profusion of styles among composers today, ranging from John Adams to John Zorn. But many periods of music history gave rise to wildly diverse styles simultaneously.</p>
        <p>This point is made vividly in a recent recording by the brilliant Pacifica Quartet, ''Declarations: Music Between the Wars.'' The program, from Cedille Records, offers three works composed within a nine-year span: Paul Hindemith's String Quartet No. 4 (1922), Leos Janacek's String Quartet No. 2 (''Intimate Letters,'' 1928) and Ruth Crawford Seeger's String Quartet (1931). In some ways these works could not be more different. Yet heard in succession, they come across as powerfully original products of a teeming musical decade.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A recent recording by the brilliant Pacifica Quartet offers three works that present themselves as powerfully original products composed within a nine-year span.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVEN contemporary-music buffs can sometimes be overwhelmed by the profusion of styles among composers today, ranging from John Adams to John Zorn. But many periods of music history gave rise to wildly diverse styles simultaneously.</p>
        <p>This point is made vividly in a recent recording by the brilliant Pacifica Quartet, ''Declarations: Music Between the Wars.'' The program, from Cedille Records, offers three works composed within a nine-year span: Paul Hindemith's String Quartet No. 4 (1922), Leos Janacek's String Quartet No. 2 (''Intimate Letters,'' 1928) and Ruth Crawford Seeger's String Quartet (1931). In some ways these works could not be more different. Yet heard in succession, they come across as powerfully original products of a teeming musical decade.</p>
        <p>Janacek was in his 70s when he composed ''Intimate Letters,'' inspired by his deep love for a woman 38 years his junior, Kamila Stosslova, the wife of a Bohemian merchant. She never left her husband, nor did Janacek leave his wife, and the extent of their relationship remains shrouded. In one of many letters to Mrs. Stosslova, Janacek revealed that the four movements of this quartet depict, in turn, their first meeting, a summer sojourn at a spa, his vision of his beloved's image and finally ''a fear'' of her that eventually ''sounds not as fear but as longing and fulfillment.''</p>
        <p>Though Janacek's language is steeped in late Romantic expressivity and rich chromatic harmony, the violent shifts make this fitful music seem boldly modern. The Pacifica players wring every bit of intensity from the score in their dynamic and visceral performance.</p>
        <p>Seeger emerges here as the most modernistic of the three composers. Her quartet's four movements are derived from fragments of jagged atonal motifs that leap fearlessly from high to low. Moods shift without warning. Frenzy gives way to eerily pensive stretches. But there is no padding in this strong and compact work of less than 12 minutes.</p>
        <p>You could say that Hindemith's quartet finds this German composer midway on the path from his early years as an unabashed rebel to his later period as a rigorous Neo-Classicist. The five-movement work begins with a self-contained fugato that keeps threatening to burst free, then segues into a percussive, grating second movement that could be mistaken for Bartok. Even the final short rondo, marked Gemächlich und mit Grazie (Leisurely and With Grace), abounds with such piercing contrapuntal writing that you do not trust its genial surface character, especially in this incisive and austere performance.</p>
        <p>Three members of the Pacifica Quartet -- Simin Ganatra and Sibbi Bernhardsson, the violinists, and Brandon Vamos, the cellist -- first met and worked together as teenagers in Southern California. Masumi Per Rostad, the violist, was the last to join the ensemble, officially founded in 1994. My introduction to these intrepid young musicians came in 2002 when they played all five of Elliott Carter's daunting string quartets in a single program at the Miller Theater in New York, an awesome feat. The excellence of this recording was no surprise.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
