<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>25 Years After War, Wealth Transforms Falklands</title>
    <meta content="01falklands" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/world/americas/01falklands.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837398"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Falkland Islands</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Argentina</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohter, Larry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Falkland Islands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Falkland Islands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Falkland Islands</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07EFDE1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1454" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>25 Years After War, Wealth Transforms Falklands</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">25 Years After War, Wealth Changes Falklands</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY ROHTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohter, Larry</byline>
      <dateline>STANLEY, Falkland Islands</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Falkland Islands face challenge of influx of outsiders brought on by prosperity resulting from changes Britain introduced after defeating 1982 Argentine invasion; newfound affluence and increased contact with outside world are forcing islanders to try to balance inevitable tensions between natives and newcomers; Argentina has not relinquished its claims to islands, but Britain maintains strong military presence on East Falkland Island; photos; map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Twenty-five years ago, Argentina invaded this wind-swept cluster of British-controlled islands in the remote South Atlantic. After 11 weeks of combat that claimed nearly 1,000 lives, British troops drove off the occupiers, allowing the islanders to continue with their eminently British way of life.</p>
        <p>Today, the 2,955 people living here face a very different challenge: an influx of outsiders, brought on by the prosperity that has resulted from changes the British introduced in this overseas territory after their 1982 triumph.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The British-controlled islands in the South Atlantic are facing an influx of outsiders attracted by new prosperity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Twenty-five years ago, Argentina invaded this wind-swept cluster of British-controlled islands in the remote South Atlantic. After 11 weeks of combat that claimed nearly 1,000 lives, British troops drove off the occupiers, allowing the islanders to continue with their eminently British way of life.</p>
        <p>Today, the 2,955 people living here face a very different challenge: an influx of outsiders, brought on by the prosperity that has resulted from changes the British introduced in this overseas territory after their 1982 triumph.</p>
        <p>Jobs like sheep-shearing and nursing are now filled by Chileans, while mixed-race people from the island of St. Helena, which lies some 2,500 miles to the northeast, take service jobs as waiters and store clerks. Just offshore, Korean, Taiwanese, Russian and Spanish ships with Indonesian, Filipino and Bangladeshi crews scoop up tons of squids, which have replaced wool and mutton as the territory's principal export.</p>
        <p>''There are just not enough of us to do all the work that has to be done,'' said Mike Summers, a member of the Falklands' legislative council. As a result of affluence and increased contact with the outside world, there is now a growing need ''to balance the inevitable tensions you find between belongers and newcomers in any small island,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''There was a time when all of us were small rural farmers,'' Mr. Summers added. ''Now we're not. We're something else, still Falkland Islanders, but we need to determine what that means.''</p>
        <p>Before the war, the islands were little more than a giant sheep farm, dominated for more than a century by the Falkland Islands Company. People who lived in ''the Camp,'' the local term for the rolling treeless expanses of pasture and peat bogs that make up most of this Connecticut-sized territory, were tenants, not landowners, and depended on the company for everything.</p>
        <p>The Argentine invasion on April 2, 1982, changed all that. First came the trauma of combat, which included not only some of the most extensive naval battles since World War II but also aerial bombardments and shelling here in the islands' only significant population center that made residents' homes targets and drove them into makeshift bunkers.</p>
        <p>''This was not a war waged at a distance,'' said John Smith, a former Royal Navy sailor whose diary of the Argentine occupation, ''74 Days,'' was published in 2002. ''Sometimes there was fighting in your own garden.''</p>
        <p>In the end, though, the war proved beneficial for the island's residents, most of whom are of English or Scottish descent and are sometimes known as ''kelpers,'' after a type of seaweed found here. ''The Conflict,'' as it is known here, forced Britain to re-examine its relationship with the Falklands and led, for example, to full British citizenship for islanders.</p>
        <p>But the biggest changes have been economic, the result of Britain's decision to allow the Falklands government to declare a 200-mile economic zone that gives islanders jurisdiction over the icy but fish-rich waters around them. Islanders had pushed for such a measure long before the war, but Britain had always refused for fear of provoking Argentina.</p>
        <p>''The war was a catalyst for change, but it was the fishing zone that really kick-started everything,'' said Andrea Clausen, a legislative council member who oversees fishing matters. ''On the backs of sacrifice and suffering, we've been able to build our economy and society and catch up with the rest of the world.''</p>
        <p>Today, fishing activities bring in about $88 million a year overall, with fishing licenses and taxes providing more than two-thirds of the government's $66 million in annual revenues. As a result, the Falklands have some of the highest per capita incomes in the world, about $50,000 a year, as well as bank reserves of $360 million.</p>
        <p>Argentina, however, has never relinquished its claim to the Falklands -- which it calls the Malvinas -- and the surrounding waters, and relations have recently worsened as a result of the fisheries boom. Even before the government here decided in 2005 to grant 25-year fishing contracts as a way to encourage foreign companies to invest, Argentina had withdrawn permission for flights over its territory, with the exception of one weekly flight from Chile.</p>
        <p>With Argentina facing an election in October and British forces stretched thin in Iraq and Afghanistan, President Néstor Kirchner has recently ratcheted up the nationalist talk over the islands. The Argentine government has promised to use only diplomacy in its effort to regain control of them, but that pledge offers islanders little solace.</p>
        <p>''We still have their claim hanging over our heads,'' said Leona Roberts, the curator of the local museum. ''As long as that is the case, it is hard to feel anything but anger and bitterness.''</p>
        <p>Argentine visitors occasionally make their way to the museum here, and when they leave, they sign the guest book with patriotic messages in Spanish that are full of irredentist sentiment. ''Always ours,'' reads one, while another proclaims, ''Little lost sisters, you are Argentine in spite of everything.''</p>
        <p>There is also an Argentine cemetery, nearly out of sight on a hillside overlooking Darwin and Goose Green, where the Argentine forces suffered the first of their military reversals after holding 114 people hostage in a community center for a month. Islanders agreed to allow the invaders to maintain a cemetery, but say they did not want to have to see it constantly and be reminded of the occupation they endured.</p>
        <p>Nearly half the 230 graves have headstones that say simply, ''An Argentine soldier known only to God.'' Some of the families of the other soldiers buried there have declined to repatriate the bodies to Argentina because they consider the Falklands to be their soil and thus a worthy resting place.</p>
        <p>But the most concrete reminder of Argentina's 74-day occupation is the presence of more than 18,000 mines. The minefields are clearly marked but have reduced beach areas, depriving islanders of some grazing land for their flocks, and Argentina, which laid the mines in hopes of deterring a British landing, is still dickering with Britain over payments to help clear them.</p>
        <p>Just in case Argentina is tempted to attack again, Great Britain maintains a heavy military presence at the Mount Pleasant complex on East Falkland Island. The cost is some $150 million a year, or about one quarter of 1 percent of Britain's defense budget, and includes about 1,200 soldiers, sailors and airmen, plus weaponry ranging from Tornado jet fighters to howitzers and naval patrol craft.</p>
        <p>Exploratory drilling for oil and gas is under way offshore, and initial results are promising. Many islanders, however, are less than excited, fearing that big finds could lead both to new tensions with Argentina and another influx of newcomers in numbers that would be difficult to absorb.</p>
        <p>''As it is, we have changed so much because of the wealth that came here that I worry we are losing our identity,'' said Robin Goodwin, a former sheep shearer and peat cutter who now works as a carpenter and is a sixth-generation kelper. ''I think that oil will destroy this place and cause horrendous frictions.''</p>
        <p>In Argentina, the war's 25th anniversary is also being noted, though with a very different tone and focus. Responding to Mr. Kirchner's campaign to hold accountable those who committed human rights violations during the military dictatorship, veterans' groups have been denouncing abuses of often-conscripted soldiers by their commanders.</p>
        <p>''It is as if we were caught between two enemies, the British and an officer corps that had been indoctrinated with the ideology of state terrorism and torture,'' Ernesto Alonso, a leader of a conscripts' group, said in an interview in Buenos Aires. ''We were undersupplied, underfed and in some cases deliberately subjected to inhuman conditions and beaten to force our compliance, and those responsible should be in jail, not receiving pensions.''</p>
        <p>A handful of Argentine veterans have also returned to visit the site of their country's humiliating defeat, which led to the collapse of the military dictatorship. They have mingled peacefully with British combatants who are also drifting back to see the islands in peacetime, but seem of two minds about what happened.</p>
        <p>Guillermo Diaz, for example, spent his 20th birthday in the trenches here, wondering if he would survive, and now works as a mental health counselor for fellow veterans outside Buenos Aires. He came back in late March with a jacket that read, ''We fought with honor and we shall return.''</p>
        <p>But he also left this inscription in the guest book at the British cemetery at San Carlos, where the British task force first came ashore: ''Life forced us into confrontation. No one desired the death of the other. For a message of peace forever, for our future generations. May God hold them in his glory.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
