<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Legislators Miss Deadline But Begin Passing Budget, Tax Rebates Included</title>
    <meta content="01budget" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/01budget.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837448"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rebates</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Charter Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spitzer, Eliot (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Albany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rebates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Charter Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Albany (NY)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Spitzer, Eliot L</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E5DC1E30F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1635" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Legislators Miss Deadline But Begin Passing Budget, Tax Rebates Included</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Legislators Miss Deadline but Begin Passing Budget, Tax Rebates Included</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, Sunday, April 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York state lawmakers begin voting on estimated $120.9 billion budget that will extend health coverage to state's 400,000 uninsured children, cut more than $1 billion worth of Medicaid spending and send out $1.3 billion worth of property tax rebate checks this year; it is first budget under Gov Eliot Spitzer; lawmakers agree to double number of charter schools in New York City to 200; vote misses March 31 deadline but will not affect state operations; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lawmakers began voting Saturday night on an estimated $120.9 billion budget that would extend health coverage to the state's 400,000 uninsured children, cut more than $1 billion worth of Medicaid spending and send out $1.3 billion worth of property tax rebate checks this year.</p>
        <p>Much of the budget had not been passed by the state's midnight deadline, although lawmakers expected to finish the voting by Sunday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first state budget under Gov. Eliot Spitzer was expected to fall short of what the brash former attorney general had hoped for.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lawmakers began voting Saturday night on an estimated $120.9 billion budget that would extend health coverage to the state's 400,000 uninsured children, cut more than $1 billion worth of Medicaid spending and send out $1.3 billion worth of property tax rebate checks this year.</p>
        <p>Much of the budget had not been passed by the state's midnight deadline, although lawmakers expected to finish the voting by Sunday.</p>
        <p>The budget, the first under Gov. Eliot Spitzer, but one that fell short of what the brash former attorney general had hoped for, as Senate Republicans appeared to outmaneuver him in some areas.</p>
        <p>It also would increase state spending by more than three times the rate of inflation, making it one of the most expensive budgets in decades.</p>
        <p>The process was held up Saturday as the governor and legislative leaders continued to haggle over last-minute details, particularly involving the education proposals. But because the majority leaders of both houses appeared to be in agreement Saturday night, the budget was expected to pass. If it passed on Sunday, the missed deadline would be largely symbolic and would not affect state operations.</p>
        <p>But some lawmakers were dismayed that they would be asked to vote on thousands of pages of legislation that they could not possibly have time to read, with Republicans on the Assembly floor loudly objecting to the process Saturday night.</p>
        <p>Governor Spitzer did prevail on several key policy objectives. Lawmakers agreed to expand Child Health Plus, a state-financed insurance program for children, to families earning 400 percent of the federal poverty level. The change would make the aid available to virtually all of the 400,000 uninsured children in the state, lawmakers said. They also took steps to simplify bureaucratic hurdles to make it easier for parents and guardians to enroll children and keep them covered.</p>
        <p>Senate Republicans dropped their opposition to a state false claims act that would provide substantial financial incentives to state or local government workers, or other citizens, who blow the whistle on government fraud. Democrats portrayed the act as a critical tool in reining in fraud in the state's sprawling Medicaid plan. The Senate Republicans had said it would lead to too many lawsuits.</p>
        <p>Legislators were also expected to approve a $600 million fund for stem cell research, a high priority of the governor.</p>
        <p>Governor Spitzer also kept in place nearly $1 billion worth of proposed Medicaid cuts. He relented, however, on $356 million more in cuts, mostly to hospitals and nursing homes, after a fierce fight with the health care lobby, which engaged him in a bruising media and advertising campaign. The sides continued to dispute who won and who lost.</p>
        <p>''We've covered enormous ground, in terms of policy,'' the governor said late Saturday. ''We are getting every kid insured -- health insurance. We're getting stem cell research. We're getting a false claims act. We're getting charter schools. We're getting the sorts of reforms that had been long thought impossible.''</p>
        <p>The agreements reached in the past week were hammered out almost entirely behind closed doors by the governor and leaders of the Legislature. As a result, many of the details will not be clear to rank-and-file lawmakers until well after the budget is passed, and at least some of the dollar numbers could shift.</p>
        <p>A couple of Mr. Spitzer's proposals were rejected in late negotiations on Saturday, including judicial pay increases and $1,000 tax credits for parochial school tuition. Talks also stalled on a proposal favored by Assembly Democrats to require that New York City use a certain amount of its new school aid to reduce class sizes. The measure was opposed by Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg, and it appeared to be moderated into something closer to a suggestion instead of a requirement, people with knowledge of the negotiations said.</p>
        <p>Lawmakers did agree to double the number of charter schools to 200, with up to half of the new ones to be created in New York City.</p>
        <p>The governor also compromised on his plan to halt $328 million of unrestricted municipal aid payments to New York City, agreeing instead to restore $20 million in the fiscal year that begins on Sunday and the full amount in the following year.</p>
        <p>The state will spend on the order of $1.8 billion more on education aid this year, a significant increase. The governor had proposed to send substantially more aid to New York City schools to resolve a lengthy legal battle that the Campaign for Fiscal Equity, an education advocacy group, fought with the state.</p>
        <p>But the governor's plan to wipe out the complicated and politically fraught education aid formula, by which ''shares'' of aid have been distributed around the state, met with fierce resistance from Long Island Republicans in the Senate.</p>
        <p>The deputy majority leader, Senator Dean G. Skelos of Nassau County, said the new proposal would lead to a sharp reduction in aid to his constituents.</p>
        <p>In the end, the governor agreed to add roughly $400 million to his original proposal.</p>
        <p>''The people on the Island are going to benefit, when they were disenfranchised in the original proposal,'' said the Senate majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, the state's top Republican. ''That's thanks to the Republican majority, Senator Skelos and the others, and no one else, and that's a fact.''</p>
        <p>The governor and the legislative leaders also agreed to send $1.3 billion worth of property tax rebate checks to homeowners next year, in addition to an existing $3.6 billion the state sends to local governments to reduce property tax bills.</p>
        <p>The governor won on one of his major priorities, to direct that aid to the middle class, but the Senate forced him to include a wealthier mix of people. The total amount of relief also was less than either side had initially proposed.</p>
        <p>The largest rebate checks are intended for homeowners with incomes of up to $120,000 downstate and up to $90,000 upstate. New York City residents also are to receive a modestly increased credit on their city income taxes, which are the main source of school financing in the city.</p>
        <p>The overall budget weighed in at $120.9 billion, including federal funds, according to the latest estimate, though the numbers tend to be re-estimated daily late in budget negotiations.</p>
        <p>Though that number grew only slightly from Mr. Spitzer's $120.6 billion executive budget, the Legislature added more than $1 billion worth of new state spending, which was offset by shrinking federal aid.</p>
        <p>State spending is projected to rise to $84 billion from $77.3 billion, an increase of 8.7 percent. That is well beyond a 2.6 percent inflation rate projected for the state.</p>
        <p>The final package will use up additional tax revenue that the state was expecting as a result of a relatively prosperous economy; the governor had hoped to set aside more of that money for reserves.</p>
        <p>''I think that there is going to be a lot of heavy lifting to do next year,'' said Elizabeth Lynam, deputy research director of the Citizens Budget Commission, an independent watchdog group.</p>
        <p>''They achieved some cost control in Medicaid, although not enough, and in school aid, they managed to shake up the dialogue about shares and move off the shares concept to some degree, but there are still issues with the formulas that will need to be tackled,'' she said.</p>
        <p>She and other analysts have also been concerned about the property tax rebate checks, which will greatly expand a system that has not appeared to accomplish the desired effect: keeping soaring property taxes in check.</p>
        <p>''They are building on a broken foundation,'' Ms. Lynam said.</p>
        <p>Some of the governor's initiatives were taken off the table by legislative leaders, including his proposal to expand nickel deposits to bottles of water, iced tea and sports drinks and to raise $100 million by keeping unclaimed deposits. Currently, grocers and bottlers keep unclaimed deposits. A number of observers were troubled by the lack of transparency in the budget process this year, even by the standards of Albany, which is known for secretive deals. This year, public budget negotiating sessions in the Legislature were largely relegated to rubber-stamping agreements behind closed doors.</p>
        <p>''I hope that as we go forward there will be a process that will be more open,'' Governor Spitzer said. ''We all want that.''</p>
        <p>The governor waived the required three-day waiting period between printing bills and voting on them. That meant that lawmakers would not have time to read the stacks of budget bills before voting on them.</p>
        <p>''Whatever bad things the Legislature wants to do probably would not withstand the light of day, but there is no light of day,'' said Edmund J. McMahon, director of the Empire Center for New York State Policy, a conservative policy group.</p>
        <p>The Assembly minority leader, James N. Tedisco, a Republican, said Saturday night that ''it won't be a reality budget because nobody's going to be able to read it,'' adding that he planned to vote against most of the budget.</p>
        <p>Mr. McMahon and other observers said they were puzzled that Governor Spitzer seemed willing to cut deals to get a budget approved on time, instead of holding out for broader reforms.</p>
        <p>''He backed off the brink there and I'm not quite sure why,'' Mr. McMahon said. ''Basically, he leaves a lot of unfinished business. He talked about turning around a battleship; I think the battleship is wedged in dry dock.''</p>
        <p>The governor, for his part, cited the quick transition required in New York, where new governors must submit their first budget at the end of their first month in office. He said that such a brief period did not permit time for the sort of analysis his office would be able to do next time.</p>
        <p>''I believe if you look at the time frame we had,'' Mr. Spitzer said, ''we did very well.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
