<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Little Lords Of the Ring</title>
    <meta content="01boxe" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/thecity/01boxe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070408T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837293"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="URBAN TACTICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golden Gloves (Boxing)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Police Athletic League</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Daily News</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dworin, Caroline H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E4DB1130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1228" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Little Lords Of the Ring</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Little Lords of the Ring</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROLINE H. DWORIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dworin, Caroline H</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on scene at Webster Police Athletic League in Tremont section of Bronx, which played host to first night of Golden Gloves boxing semi-finals; tournament, sponsored in New York by Daily News, is celebrating its 80th anniversary; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TUCKED behind a neutral corner near the press barricade sits Al Roth, an older gentleman, attentive to each bout, but with no fierce allegiance to any one matchup. Not an ex-fighter himself, Mr. Roth is a boxing fan of more than 40 years. White-haired, he wears a red vest and saggy green corduroys, the nap worn off across the thighs where he rests his arms. Leaning forward, he clasps a newspaper rolled up in one fist, like a man on his way from the bookie to the track. He travels into the city for the Golden Gloves tournament each year from Mamaroneck, and sits way up front.</p>
        <p>''There's nothing like a live sporting event,'' said Mr. Roth, a part-time medical courier who drives specimens to hospitals. ''These kids fight with their hearts. They have such raw energy. The professionals, they have to make a living.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Golden Gloves, New York’s premier amateur boxing event, bobs and weaves into its ninth decade.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TUCKED behind a neutral corner near the press barricade sits Al Roth, an older gentleman, attentive to each bout, but with no fierce allegiance to any one matchup. Not an ex-fighter himself, Mr. Roth is a boxing fan of more than 40 years. White-haired, he wears a red vest and saggy green corduroys, the nap worn off across the thighs where he rests his arms. Leaning forward, he clasps a newspaper rolled up in one fist, like a man on his way from the bookie to the track. He travels into the city for the Golden Gloves tournament each year from Mamaroneck, and sits way up front.</p>
        <p>''There's nothing like a live sporting event,'' said Mr. Roth, a part-time medical courier who drives specimens to hospitals. ''These kids fight with their hearts. They have such raw energy. The professionals, they have to make a living.''</p>
        <p>Tarps laid out on the floor, and basketball hoops hung out of the way, the evening is a slapdash carnival of an event. Children sell piles of hot dogs from polystyrene trays and sodas from a bucket.</p>
        <p>And while some of the fighters in the citywide amateur competition look like men, many look like boys, sweat-drenched, with concave chests, small arms and wild eyes. They are dwarfed by their trainers. One young man bounces on the balls of his feet and crosses himself awkwardly with gloved hand. And then, the bell.</p>
        <p>The Webster Police Athletic League in the Tremont section of the Bronx played host to the first night of the Golden Gloves semifinals on March 23. The tournament, sponsored in New York by The Daily News, is now celebrating its 80th anniversary.</p>
        <p>Event locations stretch from the toughest neighborhoods (where they most often find their home) to the most chic, and reach out into Long Island, Staten Island, southern Westchester County. Held in high school gyms, recreation centers and hotels, they begin at the Copacabana, the legendary nightclub in Midtown, and end with the finals at Madison Square Garden on April 19 and 20.</p>
        <p>The first fighters duck and crouch, avoiding tight, lean-limbed jabs, their deltoids rising like clamshells beneath the flesh; the smaller the fighter, often the greater the technique. ''Let's go Mexico! Mexico!'' shout a trio of fans. ''O.K., baby, O.K.!'' They cringe at a hit. ''I want to see someone get knocked the hell out!'' says a man in his 20s, mashing his fist in his palm.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roth, who is 76, remembers when pro fight results were common water-cooler chatter, the best bouts not relegated to pay-per-view. ''I watched since back when it was on TV on Friday nights. People don't have TV, they would go to the bar,'' he says with a shrug.</p>
        <p>Amateur boxing is a tight-knit community, with allegiances to a network of gyms speckled about the city. Much of the crowd is intimately invested in the outcome in the ring; many have their hearts in there, if not a spouse or child. And while the Golden Gloves has endured for the better part of a century, these days it runs a quieter parallel to basketball's March Madness.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roth, however, does not feel much of a change in the sport.</p>
        <p>''De La Hoya, the pretty boy, promised millions for a fight. There's still big money in this. And Tyson, as bad as he is, he still draws a crowd,'' Mr. Roth says. ''And the racial thing, too. The Mexican guys, they have their flag, the Irish they have theirs.''</p>
        <p>A group of young Middle Eastern men have a man up, Sadam Ali, in the third bout. Bright eyed they stand together against the back wall, hands cupped to mouths crying, ''Ali, Ali, Ali!'' A little boy in their midst wearing a Spider-Man hood chants along. More men lend a voice.</p>
        <p>''Bend your knees, baby! Uppercut!''</p>
        <p>When a man goes down, people leap out of their seats as if connected to him by the end of a rope, hands thrashing the air, shadowboxing in exuberance. And a beat after the bell, dance music, mostly hip-hop with the occasional salsa song, blasts through large speakers. The D.J. gives a shout out to ''Betty the Body'' (you'll know her when you see her, he says), and the ''Rocky'' anthem blares like a rallying cry.</p>
        <p>A fighter must be 16 or older and clean-shaven, and must possess a license from the USA Boxing Metropolitan Association, which regulates amateur boxing in the area. Fighters must provide their own fitted mouthpiece, trunks and socks. These are amateurs, many of them too young to buy a cigarette or a drink. They fight with protective headgear, and usually fight one- or two-minute rounds.</p>
        <p>Vonda Tariq, a woman in her 40s wearing lacquered bangs, a pink Lycra shirt and tight jeans, watches with her boyfriend, Greg Powell. Her son, Saqib, was supposed to fight on this night, but his opponent didn't show. He will fight instead at the Garden. ''I guess the guy must have chickened out,'' Mr. Powell says.</p>
        <p>Of her son's upcoming bout, Ms. Tariq says, ''This is the best thing that's ever happened to him, but I'm a little nervous about it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Roth nods at a great swath of seats flanking the ring. ''They're all here for Tierney,'' he says.</p>
        <p>The Irish contingent, clusters of fans with their children, from Throgs Neck, Yonkers and Riverdale, sit patiently, waiting for Daniel Tierney's bout. Many have sons who play Gaelic football, which has rules similar to those of soccer, with the young fighter, a student at Fordham Prep in the Bronx. ''He's probably the one of the best Irish-Americans to play the game,'' says one of the men.</p>
        <p>Of the 22 contenders on the bout sheet, Tierney is probably the one with the most fans. Their reactions to the other bouts are restrained, most waiting for their man.</p>
        <p>''I guess he's the closest to a hometown boy for me, being from Westchester,'' says Mr. Roth, who stopped by one day at the Dragone Boxing School in Yonkers, where he first saw Tierney train. ''He had style, he had charm,'' says Mr. Roth. ''That's why I like him.''</p>
        <p>Tierney is 16 and 132 pounds, dark-haired and fresh-faced, with just a shadow of chest hair above his tank top. He has a firm handshake. His mother, Maggie, wears blue nursing scrubs and talks quickly. Her son is fighting in the last bout, which, in terms of public devotion, is the main event.</p>
        <p>''They've got a great big picture of him in the window of the gym in Yonkers,'' says Mr. Roth.</p>
        <p>When Tierney climbs through the ropes, the crowd goes crazy. But on this day he is off. Just a fraction of a second off. He is unbalanced, slower than his opponent, Vasiliy Zherebnenko. Zherebnenko, 18, moves with confidence, and when Tierney, his head low, takes a hard jab, the crowd leaps out of the seats.</p>
        <p>Zherebnenko gets him against the ropes, and the noise is deafening. Tierney stumbles more than once, loses balance, gets back to his feet quickly. The referee shakes him out. He continues to move, but he makes little good contact. It is clear that the fight is Zherebnenko's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roth is still clutching his newspaper.</p>
        <p>''It's tough,'' he says, ''but somebody got to win, somebody got to lose. The turnout's pretty much the same.''</p>
        <p>URBAN TACTICS</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 8, 2007, Sunday  An article last Sunday about the annual Golden Gloves amateur boxing competition misstated the length of the rounds. Each round is two minutes -- not one or two minutes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 8, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about the annual Golden Gloves amateur boxing competition misstated the length of the rounds. Each round is two minutes -- not one or two minutes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
