<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Not All About the Process</title>
    <meta content="01boss" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/business/yourmoney/01boss.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837308"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OFFICE SPACE: THE BOSS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/The Boss</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Careers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Human Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE1DB1130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="770" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Not All About the Process</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">It’s Not All About the Process</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW PROZES; As told to Eve Tahmincioglu.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tahmincioglu, Eve; Prozes, Andrew</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE of my wife's very close childhood friends is Bo Jones, publisher of The Washington Post. I recently found myself at dinner with him, Ben Bradlee, Sally Quinn and Jim Lehrer at a restaurant in Biarritz, France. Jim Lehrer asked us all a monumental question. He asked us what we missed most from our childhood. Everyone went through their story of how they missed something. I ended up being the last one to say something. The reality was I didn't have anything I missed from my childhood. We were pretty poor. We didn't even have inside plumbing until I was 17. That pretty much shut up everyone who was around the table.</p>
        <p>My parents fled Estonia right before the Russians came in 1945. Everybody in Europe knew how the Communists ruled, which was without regard to personal liberties and rule of law.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“I got a heightened sense at a young age of what is right and what it is wrong,” said Andrew Prozes, chief executive, LexisNexis Group.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE of my wife's very close childhood friends is Bo Jones, publisher of The Washington Post. I recently found myself at dinner with him, Ben Bradlee, Sally Quinn and Jim Lehrer at a restaurant in Biarritz, France. Jim Lehrer asked us all a monumental question. He asked us what we missed most from our childhood. Everyone went through their story of how they missed something. I ended up being the last one to say something. The reality was I didn't have anything I missed from my childhood. We were pretty poor. We didn't even have inside plumbing until I was 17. That pretty much shut up everyone who was around the table.</p>
        <p>My parents fled Estonia right before the Russians came in 1945. Everybody in Europe knew how the Communists ruled, which was without regard to personal liberties and rule of law.</p>
        <p>My parents got on a boat and ended up in a camp for displaced people in Germany, where I was born . The lucky ones ended up on a boat to Sweden. It was pretty gruesome for my parents. They were forced into labor at a factory next to a former concentration camp. My parents received a check just a few years ago from the German government for the forced labor.</p>
        <p>When I was 2 years old, all the countries that agreed to take displaced people from Estonia came to our camp and set up booths. The line at the United States booth was a mile long, so my dad went to the Canadian booth. We ended up living in a small town called Campden in Ontario; the nearest town with a restaurant was five miles away.</p>
        <p>My parents came from a country that was overrun by invaders, and the invaders used illegal procedures. My father -- he was a very strong person, to say the least -- would sit in the kitchen and bang on the table. I listened for 40 years to my father's Sunday night diatribes. He'd say, ''Those damn Commies, what they did to us.'' And he probably increased the velocity when he was drinking.</p>
        <p>I got a heightened sense at a young age of what is right and what it is wrong. I got a heightened respect and caution about authority.</p>
        <p>I genuinely think I have learned more from my mistakes than I learned from my successes.</p>
        <p>I've had the good fortune of being tapped on the shoulder early in my career to take on big projects. I was asked to be a manager for a large mutual fund project when I worked for a computer services company in Canada. I was around 25 at the time.</p>
        <p>My job was to convert the mutual funds' punch card system to an automated system. At that age I thought it was all about the process, all about having meetings, checking off items, but it turned out to be a horrible disaster.</p>
        <p>When you go from a paper-based system to an automated system, it's an extremely complex conversion. You have to make sure everything in the paper system is properly transferred. But the conversion process wasn't accurate, and the electronic system did not duplicate what the paper-based system had done.</p>
        <p>I didn't realize part of what I had to do was ensure that adequate checks and balances were built into the system. I also didn't get close enough to the action to totally understand what was going on.</p>
        <p>I suffered internally and I suffered at the company because I was moved from being a potential star to being a question mark.</p>
        <p>The lesson I took away was that it's absolutely critical that when working on any project you develop relationships with the people so you can hear what it is that they're really thinking. That means getting to know them. Get them sufficiently comfortable so you know what's going on.</p>
        <p>I got a lot of help in completing that project. It took much much longer than expected: instead of two months it took two years. At that point, I just basically put my head down and worked my way through it. My boss had to step in and save the day. He was a wonderful individual with a big heart. I kept my job. I reclaimed myself.</p>
        <p>ANDREW PROZES  Chief executive, LexisNexis Group</p>
        <p>BIRTH DATE  Jan. 21, 1946</p>
        <p>BIRTHPLACE  Geislingen, Germany</p>
        <p>FAVORITE BOOK  'Tinker, Tailor, Soldier, Spy' by John le Carré</p>
        <p>WORST HABIT  Sleeping in on weekends</p>
        <p>DREAM JOB (OTHER THAN HIS OWN)  Hockey player</p>
        <p>THING HE FEARS MOST  Continued extinction of wildlife</p>
        <p>OFFICE SPACE: THE BOSS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
