<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Leaps and Bounds In Stoudemire's Knowledge</title>
    <meta content="01glass" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/sports/basketball/01glass.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837366"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="N.B.A.: OFF THE GLASS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Phoenix Suns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Stoudemire, Amare</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E0D71130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="418" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Leaps and Bounds In Stoudemire's Knowledge</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Leaps and Bounds in Stoudemire’s Knowledge</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Amare Stoudemire accompanied 12 students from his foundation's learning center in Phoenix to the Arizona Science Museum last month for the popular touring anatomical exhibit on bodies, they all saw the sinews, bones and muscles that troubled him.</p>
        <p>Stoudemire, who owns a poster of the human muscular structure, has learned to master his body from the inside out since returning from microfracture surgery on his left knee in October 2005 and arthroscopic surgery on his right knee last April.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Amare Stoudemire has learned to master his body from the inside out since returning from microfracture surgery on his left knee in October 2005 and arthroscopic surgery on his right knee last April.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Amare Stoudemire accompanied 12 students from his foundation's learning center in Phoenix to the Arizona Science Museum last month for the popular touring anatomical exhibit on bodies, they all saw the sinews, bones and muscles that troubled him.</p>
        <p>Stoudemire, who owns a poster of the human muscular structure, has learned to master his body from the inside out since returning from microfracture surgery on his left knee in October 2005 and arthroscopic surgery on his right knee last April.</p>
        <p>Now Stoudemire, the Suns' 6-foot-11 forward, has become an exhibit of recovery from the dreaded bone-drilling microfracture surgery, which has felled more than a few N.B.A. stars -- Jamal Mashburn, Allan Houston, Penny Hardaway among them, and for a time, Chris Webber.</p>
        <p>After playing in only three games last season and missing the Suns' run to the Western Conference finals, he has quietly played in all 72 of their games this season.</p>
        <p>''It was definitely a goal of mine to play all 82 games,'' Stoudemire said Thursday in a telephone interview. ''I'm just trying to prove I'm healthy. I don't want to jinx myself.''</p>
        <p>But Stoudemire, 24, made a proclamation that could reverberate in the playoffs. ''I think I'm better than what I was two years ago,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Opponents have seen the evidence. After Stoudemire scored 41 points in the Suns' double-overtime victory over Dallas on March 14, the Mavericks' Dirk Nowitzki reluctantly said Stoudemire was ''back to his old self.''</p>
        <p>Dallas has not lost in the nine games since, but Stoudemire, like his team, has gone 4-4. The Suns and the Mavs meet today in Phoenix, and another Phoenix victory to even the season series would ''probably be a great psychological lift,'' Stoudemire said.</p>
        <p>He has drawn his own lift from each game, averaging 20.7 points and 9.9 rebounds through Friday while dunking and driving with abandon again.</p>
        <p>''We worked with a lot of microfractures, and unfortunately a lot don't come back,'' said Mike Clark, the Suns' physical therapist, who is chief executive of the National Academy of Sports Medicine. ''The No. 1 reason for him has been his desire in getting himself back to that elite level.''</p>
        <p>Clark said that rehabilitation had corrected the cause of the injury. Before games, Stoudemire continues to work on strengthening the muscles around his knees.</p>
        <p>Like the students from his learning center, he is eager to learn.</p>
        <p>''He's always asking questions about how his muscles work,'' Clark said. ''That's one of the things that made him unique.''</p>
        <p>N.B.A.: OFF THE GLASS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
