<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plea to a Group Home: Another Backyard, Please</title>
    <meta content="01wetopicWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/01wetopic.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837194"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOUSING THE DISABLED"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Retardation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mount Vernon (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Westchester Arc (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murphy, Tim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Retardation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Retardation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E0DA1030F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="643" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plea to a Group Home: Another Backyard, Please</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Plea to a Group Home: Another Backyard, Please</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM MURPHY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Murphy, Tim</byline>
      <dateline>MOUNT VERNON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>City officials and some residents oppose plan by Westchester Arc to open home for eight adults with developmental disabilities in Elmsmere section of Mount Vernon, NY; residents worry that home would increase traffic and drive down property values; officials say city is already oversaturated with such residences; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SHARON JAMES said she has nothing against people with disabilities. Her 10-year-old daughter, Shylah, has cerebral palsy and uses a walker. But she is still opposed to having a home for eight adults with developmental disabilities move to her street, Del Rey Drive, in the Elmsmere section of the city.</p>
        <p>''I'm not against group homes,'' she said, ''but this is a residential area, and I think they need to be in more of a commercial area.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mount Vernon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SHARON JAMES said she has nothing against people with disabilities. Her 10-year-old daughter, Shylah, has cerebral palsy and uses a walker. But she is still opposed to having a home for eight adults with developmental disabilities move to her street, Del Rey Drive, in the Elmsmere section of the city.</p>
        <p>''I'm not against group homes,'' she said, ''but this is a residential area, and I think they need to be in more of a commercial area.''</p>
        <p>She said she worried that the proposed group home would bring too much traffic to the street because of employees and drive down property values.</p>
        <p>City officials in Mount Vernon said that they also object to the home because they argue that the city is already oversaturated with such residences. The home's operator, Westchester Arc, said Ms. James and her neighbors have nothing to fear, since it has run 45 such residences in Westchester for decades without incident.</p>
        <p>The nonprofit group's executive director, Ric Swierat, said that it wants to open the Mount Vernon group home to move eight aging residents from a longstanding home in Bronxville, the only such site there. The group rents the Bronxville house, whereas it is aiming to buy the Mount Vernon home.</p>
        <p>The commissioner for the State Office of Mental Retardation and Developmental Disabilities, which oversees such homes and initially greenlighted the Mount Vernon site, is expected to rule within the month.</p>
        <p>The city contends that it bears an unfair burden of such residences, as well as of homes and facilities serving juvenile delinquents and people with drug addictions, compared with smaller, more affluent communities nearby, like Bronxville and Scarsdale. (Each of those villages has only one or two such sites, according to officials there.)</p>
        <p>''Mount Vernon feels it's being taken advantage of,'' said John P. DiBlasi, chief of staff to Mayor Ernest D. Davis.</p>
        <p>Mount Vernon has an ally in State Senator Jeff Klein, a Democrat who represents parts of the Bronx and Westchester, and who released a study this month showing that when the number of day facilities were added to the number of group homes of all sorts, Mount Vernon had 40 sites serving the mentally disabled, juvenile-delinquent or chemically dependent in its four square miles.</p>
        <p>''You're not doing anyone any justice by having so many of these facilities in one specific area,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Klein said he was working on legislation that would prohibit such facilities from being situated within a half-mile of one another. The current law applies only to homes for the developmentally disabled and sets no hard limits on proximity.</p>
        <p>Westchester Arc opposes the legislation. Mr. Swierat said the organization's other homes have never created problems. ''We have a house in one of the most prestigious areas of Scarsdale,'' he said. ''The neighbors have learned to love us and come in for Friday movie nights.''</p>
        <p>Another of the organization's homes, on the Yonkers-Scarsdale border, so divided the neighborhood association before its arrival 12 years ago that the group disbanded, according to Lee Smith, who lives across from the home. He said the residence has never caused problems. ''They're good neighbors,'' he said. ''In some respects, because there's always somebody on duty there, they enhance the security of the area.''</p>
        <p>Christ Church in Bronxville owns Arc's building, and the rector there, the Rev. Michael A. Bird, said the home had never made trouble. ''It was their decision to leave,'' he said, ''not ours.''</p>
        <p>Deborah Sturm Rausch, a representative for the State Office of Mental Retardation, said that in such disputes, the agency usually rules in favor of the group home. If that were to happen, Mount Vernon would appeal the case to the State Supreme Court, Mr. DiBlasi said.</p>
        <p>Westchester Arc will not do that if it loses, Mr. Swierat said. Instead, it will seek a new site for the home.</p>
        <p>HOUSING THE DISABLED</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
