<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Looking For Signs Of Stability In Job Tally</title>
    <meta content="01mark" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/business/yourmoney/01mark.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837312"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Reserve System</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E0DB1130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="515" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Looking For Signs Of Stability In Job Tally</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Looking for Signs of Stability in Job Tally</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONRAD DE AENLLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">De Aenlle, Conrad</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE softening economy is hitting us where we live, but so far there has been little discernible impact on where we work.</p>
        <p>Employment has proved far more resilient than the housing market, and one strategist expects the new batch of data this week on job creation to show continued stability.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The softening economy is hitting us where we live, but so far there has been little discernible impact on where we work.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE softening economy is hitting us where we live, but so far there has been little discernible impact on where we work.</p>
        <p>Employment has proved far more resilient than the housing market, and one strategist expects the new batch of data this week on job creation to show continued stability.</p>
        <p>Brett Hammond, chief investment strategist at TIAA-CREF, the fund manager in New York, estimates that the economy added 115,000 jobs in March, less than the 130,000 forecast in a Bloomberg News poll of economists.</p>
        <p>A figure of 115,000 on Friday would fit in with Mr. Hammond's view that economic activity is likely to remain sluggish. He expects the G.D.P. to rise only about 2 percent this year -- compared with a 2.5 percent annual rate in the fourth quarter of last year.</p>
        <p>Still, he said, that should be enough growth to keep the job market in balance.</p>
        <p>Current job seekers, he said, include homeowners looking to extricate themselves from trouble as mortgage rates rise and home prices appear vulnerable to a decline.</p>
        <p>''In an odd way, we may be seeing people taking second jobs to make ends meet on the housing side,'' Mr. Hammond said. ''I can't prove it from the macroeconomic data, but I'm pretty sure it's happening. We might be seeing overemployment from people trying to cope.''</p>
        <p>The stock market, he said, should be able to cope better with a job number that exceeds forecasts rather than one that misses the mark.</p>
        <p>While Ben S. Bernanke, the chairman of the Federal Reserve, told Congress last week that inflation remained the Fed's chief concern, he also signaled an intention by the central bank to be more flexible in its credit policy. That means that a strong report may allow investors to reap the gain without feeling too much pain, Mr. Hammond said.</p>
        <p>''If you had an indication that the economy was going to start improving fairly significantly,'' Mr. Hammond said, ''the market might be quite happy because the Fed has indicated that it has changed its stance and is leaning more toward easing.''</p>
        <p>Investors faced with strong job data ''won't believe that the Fed is going to tighten, and it may ease sometime later this year,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Using the same logic, he cautioned that stocks could fall ''if we get terrific disappointment in the job number, combined with a downward revision'' in job creation reported for February.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hammond stressed that he expects numbers that are not a lot higher or lower than the consensus. After the recent losses and volatility in the stock market, he added, a lack of extremes would be quite positive.''I'm maintaining a neutral stance,'' he said, ''but that's better than things have been for the last couple of weeks.''</p>
        <p>DATA WATCH -- Activity in the nation's factories is predicted to have edged closer to the middle of the road in March. The Bloomberg poll forecasts a reading of 51.1 in the Institute for Supply Management's manufacturing survey, down from 52.3 in February.</p>
        <p>A reading of 50 indicates that manufacturing is neither expanding nor contracting.</p>
        <p>MARKET WEEK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
