<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Part Tux, Part Pajamas</title>
    <meta content="01shake" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/01/fashion/01shake.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837266"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SHAKEN AND STIRRED"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Columns/Shaken and Stirred</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E6DD1130F932A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="491" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Part Tux, Part Pajamas</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Part Tux, Part Pajamas</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN MILES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Miles, Jonathan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IDEALLY, a cocktail consumed at 4 a.m. should be transitional. It should serve as a bridge between the night that was and the morning to come, equally adept at picking you up and winding you down. It should gently prepare you for the startling pastel rays of dawn -- since the sunrise, when you've been out all night, always seems to come as a surprise, like a pursuer you thought you had eluded. A drink at that hour should usher in thoughts of, say, pancakes.</p>
        <p>Ladies and gentlemen, crawlers of the urban predawn, I give you that cocktail.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the InnLW12, a gastropub in the meatpacking district, a cocktail for the crawlers of the urban predawn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IDEALLY, a cocktail consumed at 4 a.m. should be transitional. It should serve as a bridge between the night that was and the morning to come, equally adept at picking you up and winding you down. It should gently prepare you for the startling pastel rays of dawn -- since the sunrise, when you've been out all night, always seems to come as a surprise, like a pursuer you thought you had eluded. A drink at that hour should usher in thoughts of, say, pancakes.</p>
        <p>Ladies and gentlemen, crawlers of the urban predawn, I give you that cocktail.</p>
        <p>It goes by the name of the Maple Leaf, and its combination of whiskey (which bids you good night) and maple syrup (which says good morning), balanced with a bracing splash of lemon juice, is the star of the cocktail menu at the InnLW12, a gastropub in the meatpacking district that opened three weeks ago and that features a last call at 4 a.m.</p>
        <p>The Maple Leaf is more refreshing than its autumnal, smoky-sweet ingredients might suggest. The taste evokes a crisp spring morning in Canada, befitting the InnLW12's Canadian motif.</p>
        <p>Two of the owners, Jeffrey Jah (whose credits include the meatpacking spots Lotus and Double Seven) and Lyman Carter, are Canadian. Poutine, a Québécois comfort dish of French fries topped with cheese curds and gravy, anchors the late-night menu. Snowshoes festoon the restroom door, photos of the Far North adorn the walls, and every possible surface is paneled with lustrous wood.</p>
        <p>''It was the same thing with the cocktails,'' said Monika Chiang, an owner with Mr. Jah of Double Seven, which is relocating a few blocks south, and who, as a consultant and manager at the InnLW12, designed the drinks list. Of course, given the theme, she had to have a Maple Leaf. The Northern woods are full of chill-chasers called Maple Leafs.</p>
        <p>For her version, Ms. Chiang took a Double Seven stalwart -- the Gold Rush, a whiskey sour variation in which bourbon, lemon juice and honey syrup are shaken together -- and refitted it, via the maple syrup, with a Canadian passport.</p>
        <p>The Maple Leaf, however, evokes something besides Canada for Ms. Chiang. ''I did this Master Cleanse a while ago,'' she said, referring to an allegedly detoxifying diet with a regimen of saltwater, maple syrup, lemon juice and cayenne pepper, ''and a friend said to me, 'You should do a Master Cleanse cocktail.' It occurred to me after I'd made the Maple Leaf that I'd almost done just that.''</p>
        <p>''It's supposed to cure all that ails you,'' she added. Which is precisely what you want from a 4 a.m. cocktail.</p>
        <p>Maple Leaf  Adapted from the InnLW12</p>
        <p>1 1/2 ounces Canadian Club whiskey</p>
        <p>1/2 ounce freshly squeezed lemon juice</p>
        <p>1/2 ounce maple syrup  Lemon twist, for garnish.</p>
        <p>Shake liquid ingredients with ice and pour into a rocks glass. Garnish with the lemon and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 1 serving</p>
        <p>SHAKEN AND STIRRED</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
