<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seaports May Provide Blueprint for Leasing Toll Roads</title>
    <meta content="06privatize" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/nyregion/06privatize.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838391"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEWS ANALYSIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tolls</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey Turnpike</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Garden State Parkway</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Port Authority of New York and New Jersey</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belson, Ken</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tolls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tolls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Port Authority of New York and New Jersey</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DB173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="887" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seaports May Provide Blueprint for Leasing Toll Roads</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Seaports May Provide Blueprint for Leasing Toll Roads</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEN BELSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Belson, Ken</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Model for privatizing New Jersey's largest toll roads may be found in ship terminals owned by Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, the leases on which are being sold by companies with strong track records in shipping industry to investment companies and other financial firms; opponents of 'monetizing' toll roads fear investors will sharply raise tolls to maximize their profits, but firms taking over terminal leases say that would be bad business; these firms also believe that reinvesting in terminals will increase value of their assets (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Resistance to the possibility that New Jersey will lease its largest toll roads to big financial firms is based largely on the fear that those investors would sharply raise prices to maximize their profits.</p>
        <p>While those concerns are worth considering, opponents of privatizing -- or ''monetizing,'' as Gov. Jon S. Corzine puts it -- the New Jersey Turnpike and the Garden State Parkway would do well to look at the ports in Newark and Elizabeth and on Staten Island for a glimpse at how public agencies have learned to work with such firms.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New Jersey Turnpike and the Garden State Parkway would do well to look at nearby ports for a glimpse at how public agencies have learned to work with private firms.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Resistance to the possibility that New Jersey will lease its largest toll roads to big financial firms is based largely on the fear that those investors would sharply raise prices to maximize their profits.</p>
        <p>While those concerns are worth considering, opponents of privatizing -- or ''monetizing,'' as Gov. Jon S. Corzine puts it -- the New Jersey Turnpike and the Garden State Parkway would do well to look at the ports in Newark and Elizabeth and on Staten Island for a glimpse at how public agencies have learned to work with such firms.</p>
        <p>In the past year, investment companies and other financial firms have taken over or hope to take over the leases on three of the five ship terminals owned by the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey. In all three cases, companies with long track records in the shipping industry have been the sellers.</p>
        <p>The shift in ownership from traditional shipping companies to financial firms -- pure investors -- at the ports is emblematic of Wall Street's broad interest in big public assets, including airports, lotteries and toll roads.</p>
        <p>Ports, like toll roads, are viewed as comparatively stable investments. In addition, competition is limited and revenue often grows steadily over many years. And current interest rates are relatively low, making it easier to finance such purchases, which can run into billions of dollars.</p>
        <p>''It's all tied together,'' said Cherian George, chief of the transportation group at Fitch Ratings, a bond-rating agency. ''The value of these long-term assets and leases is that there is limited acreage at all these ports and the growth is significant,'' propelled by technology advances, while ''building new ports is difficult.''</p>
        <p>In February, A.I.G. Global Investment Group, an arm of the insurance giant A.I.G., which has never run a port terminal, bought leases to the Port of Newark terminal. The Ontario Teachers Pension Plan Board is awaiting approval to take over the lease to operate a terminal at Howland Hook, on Staten Island, from Orient Overseas International Limited, a shipping conglomerate.</p>
        <p>And last month, a division of Deutsche Bank, Germany's largest bank, agreed to buy Maher Terminals, which runs the operations at the Port of Elizabeth in New Jersey and the Port of Prince Rupert in British Columbia.</p>
        <p>A.I.G. and other financial firms that are getting into the port business dismiss claims that they will simply raise prices to maximize their profits. After all, they say, that would be bad for business. They also say that they plan to reinvest in their businesses for the same reason -- to increase the value of their assets.</p>
        <p>Still, the Port Authority, which owns the ports in New York and New Jersey, is taking steps to guarantee such reinvestment.</p>
        <p>In return for its approval of A.I.G.'s purchase, from DP World, one of the largest port operators, the authority negotiated a $10 million payment from A.I.G. to help recoup the cost of an overpass it built from the port to a nearby train depot. A.I.G. also agreed to spend more than $40 million to improve operations at its Port of Newark terminal.</p>
        <p>Similarly, the Port Authority is asking for $54 million in commitments before it will agree to Orient Overseas International Limited's sale to the Ontario pension fund.</p>
        <p>The Port Authority views these payments as a way to ensure that the new owners continue to reinvest in their terminals and do not resell the leases in a few years for a quick profit.</p>
        <p>''We think good things will come out of having deep-pocketed investors'' operate the terminals, said Anthony Coscia, chairman of the Port Authority. ''But we have just spent billions of dollars to create common infrastructure, like dredging the harbor. To protect what we believe to be the public interest, we have to be certain that they make us comfortable in terms of operations and security, and they have robust capital plans.''</p>
        <p>Though leasing toll roads is common in Europe and Asia, only a handful of lease deals have been signed in the United States, most notably in Chicago and Indiana. But ports authorities have worked with a small group of private operators for decades. That is one reason it has been easier for financial firms to enter this industry.</p>
        <p>''Out of all the public infrastructure assets, the ports is already the most private,'' said Jeffrey D. Holt, vice president for public sector and infrastructure banking of Goldman Sachs.</p>
        <p>Since leasing toll roads is a relatively new concept in the United States, New Jersey, assuming it decides to do so, is likely to seek to protect drivers, truckers and toll collectors. It may, for instance, cap toll increases by linking them to the rate of inflation or another economic indicator. It may also require the buyers to agree to certain levels of service, like plowing the roads every hour during a snowstorm.</p>
        <p>With such promises, the state can help guarantee that drivers barely notice the change in ownership.</p>
        <p>In some cases, service at the ports may hardly change, either. The division of Deutsche Bank that plans to buy Maher Terminals will retain Maher to continue running the Port of Elizabeth operation.</p>
        <p>''From a user's standpoint, it makes very little difference who operates the facility,'' said Kurt Forsgren, director of public finance ratings at Standard &amp; Poor's. ''The question is how well they can be operated.''</p>
        <p>NEWS ANALYSIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
