<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Rumors Fly, Traffic Stalls, and Sharpshooters Roam the Golf Course</title>
    <meta content="06scene" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/nyregion/06scene.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838381"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AN AGENT FALLS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bank Robberies</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Readington Township (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Branchburg (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pnc Bank</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelley, Tina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Jonathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herrera-Genao, Francisco J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, Barry Lee</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cruz, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berrios, Wilfredo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE0DC173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="704" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Rumors Fly, Traffic Stalls, and Sharpshooters Roam the Golf Course</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Where Rumors Fly, Traffic Stalls, and Sharpshooters Roam the Golf Course</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TINA KELLEY and JONATHAN MILLER; Tina Kelley reported from Branchburg Township and Jonathan Miller from Readington Township. Ronald Smothers contributed reporting from Readington.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kelley, Tina; Miller, Jonathan</byline>
      <dateline>BRANCHBURG TOWNSHIP, N.J., April 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hundreds of officers fan out across Branchburg and Readington Townships in New Jersey in search of bank robbery suspect; schools are put in lockdown; troopers patrol train depot and golf course; roads are closed, forcing detours and creating confusion; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Hawkins, who lives by the third fairway of the Fox Hollow golf course here, is used to the occasional errant golf ball rolling onto his property.</p>
        <p>But he does not usually see police cars swarming the golf cart paths, or uniformed officers striding about brandishing weapons, as he did on Thursday after an F.B.I. agent was gunned down during a confrontation outside a nearby bank.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>BRANCHBURG TOWNSHIP, N.J., April 5  John Hawkins, who lives by the third fairway of the Fox Hollow golf course here, is used to the occasional errant golf ball rolling onto his property.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John Hawkins, who lives by the third fairway of the Fox Hollow golf course here, is used to the occasional errant golf ball rolling onto his property.</p>
        <p>But he does not usually see police cars swarming the golf cart paths, or uniformed officers striding about brandishing weapons, as he did on Thursday after an F.B.I. agent was gunned down during a confrontation outside a nearby bank.</p>
        <p>''I've seen sharpshooters on the fairway here most of the afternoon,'' Mr. Hawkins said.</p>
        <p>Scenes like that played out all afternoon in Mr. Hawkins's neighborhood and others in Branchburg Township and neighboring Readington Township, as hundreds of officers fanned out in search of a bank robbery suspect. Two other armed suspects were captured in the morning.</p>
        <p>In this part of central New Jersey about 50 miles from Manhattan, where McMansions meet trailer parks, exurban developments meet horse farms and sprawling campuses for drug companies dot the wooded landscape, life became very strange Thursday afternoon.</p>
        <p>Schools were put in lockdown, and students sent home early. Raritan Valley Community College also closed early. Troopers patrolled the train depot in Whitehouse Station all day, toting rifles and searching trains going in and out. Drivers were pulled over and questioned. Roads were closed, creating confusion and forcing detours down narrow lanes.</p>
        <p>After the shooting, an exit off Interstate 78, a major east-west route, was shut down, creating four-mile backups heading west. A stretch of Route 22 was also closed between Ridge and County Line Roads. State and local police officers and federal agents seemed to be everywhere.</p>
        <p>Many onlookers were astonished. ''This is a very sleepy hollow,'' said Rocco Romeo, 56, an environmental consultant in Readington, watching the dozens of news trucks at the Wal-Mart parking lot. ''The biggest crime here is a mailbox knocked over by an A.T.V. or someone's window is shot out by a BB gun.''</p>
        <p>A neighbor of Mr. Hawkins's at the golf course, John Luyben, said: ''It's very strange to look across at your neighbor's yard and see two state troopers with automatic rifles just marching through.''</p>
        <p>Jane Parsonnet, 68, of nearby Oldwick, was out at King's grocery store, about a mile from the shooting. As she loaded groceries into her black Audi in the afternoon, she said she had been relatively unaffected by the hubbub. ''What I figured was, by the time I got here, it'd be out of this area,'' she said. ''It's surprising for this area. There's so little crime around here, minor things. It's a little unnerving, too, to be honest.''</p>
        <p>Rumors flew. Many had heard that there had been a hostage-taking at a nearby convenience store, but those reports proved to be false. At Darrow's Sporting Edge, two employees, Larry Hansen, 56, and Nicole Ericson, 21, were talking about what they had heard. Mr. Hansen said the owner of Darrow's had called up, saying he had been at a gun store in nearby Flemington when he saw town police officers saying that they needed an assault rifle -- and fast.</p>
        <p>Just down Route 22 at the Siesta Motel, Sandeep Mishra stood behind the register. At 11:15 Thursday morning, he saw something strange: three cars, lined up next to each other, men inside, just sitting there for about 15 minutes. Another car was stopped just across Route 22. It was unusual, and he called the police. But by the time officers showed up, the cars were gone. At noon came the shooting of the F.B.I. agent just a few hundred feet down the road.</p>
        <p>Others commented on how things had changed of late, and not for the better. Pete Nicoletti, 47, the owner of Pete's White House Valero, a gas station in Readington, has lived in town since 1969. ''It used to be real quiet,'' he said. ''We have had house invasions around here, the population has been growing and you get many more riffraff coming off of I-78.'' Added Mr. Hansen: ''Kind of makes a quiet little town maybe wake up a little bit. If you live in a quaint little place, make sure you keep those doors locked.''</p>
        <p>AN AGENT FALLS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
