<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pettitte's Return Is Lost Amid Sloppy Fielding And a Stalled Rallly</title>
    <meta content="06yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/sports/baseball/06yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838415"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Devil Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Tampa Bay Devil Rays</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pettitte, Andy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rodriguez, Alex</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE3DB173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="927" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pettitte's Return Is Lost Amid Sloppy Fielding And a Stalled Rallly</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pettitte’s Return Lost Amid Sloppy Play</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was as if a glass bubble covered Yankee Stadium in the eighth inning last night, the way the snow flurries swirled against the black sky. A disjointed game was reaching its peak and the ballpark was all shook up.</p>
        <p>Then, suddenly, the snow was gone, and so was the Yankees' budding rally. Alex Rodriguez popped out to second against the Tampa Bay Devil Rays' Brian Stokes, ending the eighth inning with the bases loaded and the Yankees behind by a run. Rodriguez slammed his bat to the ground and kicked the bag when he crossed first.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was a forgettable return for Andy Pettitte, who was lifted in the fifth, and the Devil Rays capitalized on the Yankees' mistakes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was as if a glass bubble covered Yankee Stadium in the eighth inning last night, the way the snow flurries swirled against the black sky. A disjointed game was reaching its peak and the ballpark was all shook up.</p>
        <p>Then, suddenly, the snow was gone, and so was the Yankees' budding rally. Alex Rodriguez popped out to second against the Tampa Bay Devil Rays' Brian Stokes, ending the eighth inning with the bases loaded and the Yankees behind by a run. Rodriguez slammed his bat to the ground and kicked the bag when he crossed first.</p>
        <p>''A base hit right there, and we possibly win the game,'' Rodriguez said. ''I just didn't get it done.''</p>
        <p>The Devil Rays won, 7-6, spoiling Andy Pettitte's return by capitalizing on three Yankees errors, three wild pitches and a passed ball. The Yankees survived three errors in their opener Monday, but not so last night.</p>
        <p>''We played sloppy,'' said Derek Jeter, who made his second and third errors. ''I don't care who you play, you're not going to win too many games when you're playing sloppy.''</p>
        <p>Appropriately, the go-ahead run scored on a wild pitch in the eighth by Luis Vizcaíno, who said he could not get enough moisture on his fingers and let his slider get away. Akinori Iwamura, the Devil Rays' rookie third baseman from Japan, scored after leading off with a double.</p>
        <p>It was a forgettable return for Pettitte, who was lifted after 83 pitches with two on and no outs in the fifth. Pettitte allowed four runs (two earned) on six hits and three walks. When he came to the mound to pat Pettitte on the back, a chilly Joe Torre wore batting gloves.</p>
        <p>Because of Tuesday's day off and Wednesday's rainout, the teams had gone nearly 75 hours between games. It was 38 degrees at game time, and some of the Devil Rays wore skullcaps that covered their ears, mouths and cheeks. Infielders blew on their hands, and the wind whipped hot dog wrappers around the field.</p>
        <p>Back spasms had limited Pettitte late in spring training, and he pitched only four innings in his final spring game. Torre said before the game that he hoped Pettitte could go five innings, but that turned out to be too optimistic.</p>
        <p>''It was definitely not what you wanted to get out of your first outing,'' Pettitte said. ''We lost the game, that's the biggest disappointment. But I'm extremely disappointed only sticking around for four innings.''</p>
        <p>The Devil Rays did not hit Pettitte hard; he broke some bats, and three of their six hits never left the infield. But they made him work, drawing three walks and deploying their usual aggressive style on the bases.</p>
        <p>Pettitte said that he was especially bothered by a two-out walk to the left-handed Iwamura in the second inning. He needed 62 pitches to get through the first three innings, and it was clear by then that he would not last long. He trailed at that point, 2-1, but it could have been worse.</p>
        <p>After Josh Paul's two-out single drove in a run in the second, Pettitte walked Carl Crawford to load the bases. His 2-2 pitch to Ben Zobrist bounced away from Jorge Posada, and B. J. Upton charged in from third as Pettitte sprang off the mound. Posada scooped a throw to Pettitte, who slapped a tag on Upton's left elbow right before his hand crossed the plate. The inning was over, and Pettitte punched the air with his glove and then with his hand.</p>
        <p>But the good vibes did not last. Jeter began the third inning by botching Zobrist's grounder for an error, and a passed ball by Posada moved Zobrist into scoring position. Zobrist broke for third during Pettitte's pickoff move, stealing the base when Pettitte threw behind the runner. He scored on Delmon Young's single to give Tampa Bay a 2-1 lead.</p>
        <p>Pettitte acknowledged he was having trouble communicating with Posada, who applied Wite-Out to his fingernails to give Pettitte a better view of the signals.</p>
        <p>''We didn't get a chance to work together a whole lot in spring training, and it's been a while since he's caught me,'' Pettitte said. ''We had a little bit of a miscommunication, but we talked between innings, just like we did last time.''</p>
        <p>With a 4-2 lead, Pettitte faced two batters in the fifth and allowed two infield singles. The second was a bunt by Zobrist, which Pettitte fielded and flipped hastily to first, where Doug Mientkiewicz mishandled it as Zobrist raced by.</p>
        <p>Scott Proctor relieved Pettitte, and both runners scored to tie the score, 4-4. Elijah Dukes (two major league games, two home runs) scorched a liner into the left-field seats to lead off the sixth, and four batters later, Crawford singled against Mike Myers to make the score 6-4.</p>
        <p>The Yankees tied the score in the seventh when Hideki Matsui singled to drive in Jeter and Bobby Abreu.</p>
        <p>After Tampa Bay went ahead in the eighth, Abreu bounced back to Stokes with one out and the bases full in the bottom of the inning. Stokes went home for the force, then retired Rodriguez.</p>
        <p>The fans had stood and cheered Rodriguez before the at-bat. After the out, some of them booed. Rodriguez said he did not pay attention.</p>
        <p>''I don't get into that,'' he said. ''I'm enjoying playing the game. I've got a lot of work to do on the field.''</p>
        <p>So do the rest of his teammates, who are 1-1 with a lot of room for improvement.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
