<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Zell Gets Veto Power At Tribune</title>
    <meta content="06tribune" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/business/media/06tribune.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838372"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tribune Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zell, Samuel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Floyd Norris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Tribune Company</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Zell, Samuel</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E1DC173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Zell Gets Veto Power At Tribune</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Zell Gets Veto Power at Tribune</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tribune Co discloses new details of its plan to go private in complex deal engineered by real estate tycoon Samuel Zell, including provisions that will give Zell broad authority over corporate activities; reports that although Zell will control only minority of board, he will have right to veto any major transactions; employees, who will get company shares but who will no longer get 401(k) contributions from Tribune, will have far less control; top Tribune managers will be given 'phantom stock' in new company; top managers will be allowed to cash in that stock before ordinary employees will be able to withdraw money from employee stock ownership plan, or ESOP, that is to control company; ESOP will own company when deal is completed, with existing shareholders receiving $34 per share (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Tribune Company last night disclosed new details of its plan to go private in a complex deal engineered by the real estate tycoon Samuel Zell, including provisions that will give Mr. Zell broad authority over corporate activities.</p>
        <p>The company reported that although Mr. Zell will control only a minority of the board, he will have the right to veto any major transactions. The employees, who will get company shares but who will no longer get 401(k) contributions from Tribune, will have far less control.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although Samuel Zell will control a minority of the Tribune Company board, he will have the right to veto any major transactions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Tribune Company last night disclosed new details of its plan to go private in a complex deal engineered by the real estate tycoon Samuel Zell, including provisions that will give Mr. Zell broad authority over corporate activities.</p>
        <p>The company reported that although Mr. Zell will control only a minority of the board, he will have the right to veto any major transactions. The employees, who will get company shares but who will no longer get 401(k) contributions from Tribune, will have far less control.</p>
        <p>In a filing yesterday with the Securities and Exchange Commission, the company also disclosed that top managers of Tribune, which owns leading newspapers like The Los Angeles Times and The Chicago Tribune, would be given ''phantom stock'' in the new company.</p>
        <p>The top managers will be allowed to cash in that stock before ordinary employees will be able to withdraw money from the employee stock ownership plan, or ESOP, that is to control the company.</p>
        <p>Tribune disclosed plans for the deal this week, saying that it would sell the Chicago Cubs baseball team after the current season ended. It did not disclose any plans to sell other assets, but it did not rule out such sales.</p>
        <p>David Geffen, the entertainment mogul who has continued to say that he is interested in buying The Los Angeles Times, is set to have dinner tonight with Mr. Zell. The pair had scheduled the dinner at least a week ago, according to a person involved in arranging the meeting.</p>
        <p>The ESOP will own the company when the deal is completed, with existing shareholders receiving $34 a share. But Mr. Zell will have a warrant to purchase a 40 percent stake, and will select two of the six directors. Any transaction valued at more than $250 million would need the approval of at least one of his directors, giving Mr. Zell a veto over all major corporate moves.</p>
        <p>The company said managers and other ''key employees'' would be allocated an 8 percent stake in the company, via phantom stock, leaving the ESOP with an effective 52 percent ownership. The managers will also receive $6.8 million in bonuses when the deal is completed, which the company hopes will be this year.</p>
        <p>Employees will be allocated shares from the ESOP each year, the filing said, in proportion to their annual pay. But in most cases they will not be able to cash in any of their stake for at least a decade, and then only if they are retired or are over 55 and have worked for Tribune for at least 10 years.</p>
        <p>At that point, they will be able to ''diversify'' part of their investment out of Tribune.</p>
        <p>According to the filing, the company's board has set aside the $6.8 million to compensate 38 executives for ''overseeing the completion'' of the deal with Mr. Zell. The largest payout disclosed, $600,000, would go to the company's chief financial officer, Donald C. Grenesko.</p>
        <p>Tribune's chief executive, Dennis J. FitzSimons, chose not to take any of that bonus, the company said.</p>
        <p>At Tribune's flagship paper, The Los Angeles Times, the mood after the deal announcement was a mixture of fatigue and black humor.</p>
        <p>''It's like a bad divorce that's gone on too long,'' said a newsroom employee at The Times, who was granted anonymity because he, like many employees, fears for his job.</p>
        <p>Some employees were greeting each other as ''co-owner,'' he said, but added: ''There's a worry that Zell is betting the employees' retirement.''</p>
        <p>Most Tribune employees now have 401(k) defined-contribution benefit plans, to which the company contributes at least 6 percent of an employee's pay, and as much as 9 percent, depending on corporate profitability, according to a company spokesman, Gary Weitman.</p>
        <p>Under the new plan, however, the company will no longer contribute to the 401(k), although employees will be free to do so. Instead, it will establish a cash-balance pension plan, which will accrue interest, and be funded with an amount equal to 3 percent of an employee's base pay.</p>
        <p>In addition, each employee in the ESOP is to have shares allocated to his or her account, in an amount initially equal to 5 percent of salary.</p>
        <p>Managers and ''other key employees,'' as well as sharing in the ESOP, will receive the phantom stock units, amounting to 8 percent of the company. Most of those -- a 5 percent stake -- can be cashed in after five years. The first 1 percent stake can be cashed in on the fourth anniversary of the completion of the deal, and similar amounts can be cashed in after six years and eight years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zell is to invest $315 million in the company. He will end up with a $225 million note, earning interest, and a warrant to buy 40 percent of the company. To exercise the warrant, he would have to pay $500 million if he does so in the first year after the deal closes, with the exercise price rising $10 million a year until it reaches $600 million.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
