<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Way-Back Machine With Black Vinyl Wings</title>
    <meta content="06Ritual" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/travel/escapes/06Ritual.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838259"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="RITUALS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jukeboxes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mallozzi, Vincent</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07EED6163FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1044" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Way-Back Machine With Black Vinyl Wings</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Jukebox Is a Way-Back Machine With Black Vinyl Wings</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VINCENT M. MALLOZZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mallozzi, Vincent</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vincent Mallozzi Rituals column on his 1976 AMI Rowe jukebox, which he bought nine years ago, and what he did when machine went on fritz and stopped playing his favorite oldies; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON a rainy Saturday three summers ago, I turned on the jukebox in my New Jersey home and selected song No. 140. I was expecting to Rock Around the Clock with Bill Haley and the Comets, but got an earful of exit strategies from Paul Simon, whose ''50 Ways to Leave Your Lover'' happens to be selection 138.</p>
        <p>I soon realized that there was something wrong with the big wheel that spins the old 45's inside my jukebox, a malfunction that threatened my weekend travel plans. The big old box, you see, is my own personal time machine, providing mental getaways to whatever place and time any of its 200 selections will take me.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“The big old box, you see, is my own personal time machine, providing mental getaways to whatever place and time any of its 200 selections will take me.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON a rainy Saturday three summers ago, I turned on the jukebox in my New Jersey home and selected song No. 140. I was expecting to Rock Around the Clock with Bill Haley and the Comets, but got an earful of exit strategies from Paul Simon, whose ''50 Ways to Leave Your Lover'' happens to be selection 138.</p>
        <p>I soon realized that there was something wrong with the big wheel that spins the old 45's inside my jukebox, a malfunction that threatened my weekend travel plans. The big old box, you see, is my own personal time machine, providing mental getaways to whatever place and time any of its 200 selections will take me.</p>
        <p>Select 117 for ''Rock the Boat'' and I'm 10 again, swinging and singing to that Hues Corporation hit along with a dozen grammar school buddies on a creaky wooden drawbridge in a playground in East Harlem, where I grew up.</p>
        <p>Select 136 for ''We Are the Champions,'' and I'm back in 1982, listening as that Queen song, already a classic, is pumped out of a boom box at the Regis High School gymnasium in Manhattan, where me and my St. Agnes teammates upset a bunch of budding Bill Bradleys to win a Catholic High School Athletic Association basketball championship.</p>
        <p>Select 198 for Sinatra, and there we are, all summer long, singing a song, and strolling on golden sand, two sweethearts -- and the Summer Wind.</p>
        <p>Select 158 and I have just become a new daddy, singing and dancing with my first son, Christopher, to ''Heaven Must Be Missing an Angel,'' by Tavares.</p>
        <p>Select 178, and I'm crying over my own daddy as I listen to Luther Vandross's ''Dance With My Father.''</p>
        <p>But now, the big wheel was stopping two numeric spaces before the tune I was actually requesting, turning my weekend retreats into a series of musical mishaps.</p>
        <p>I tried to Boogie Oogie Oogie with A Taste of Honey (160), but my jukebox chose instead to have me Drift Away with Dobie Gray (158). When I did feel like drifting, into a New York State of Mind (190), I wound up 3,000 miles away, listening to Tony Bennett croon about leaving his heart in San Francisco (188). I'd heard of records skipping, but over an entire song? Where was Billy Joel?</p>
        <p>Nine years ago, I purchased my jukebox -- a 1976 AMI Rowe -- for a song and a dance from some guy in New Brunswick, N.J., who was singing the blues about getting older, about the kids being all grown up and out on their own, about having little use for a monstrous relic made of wood, glass and chrome that glowed in the dark, fed on vinyl and quarters and took up too much space in the basement.</p>
        <p>Almost every weekend since, I have found time to play my magical time machine, which is now electronically rigged to avoid having to pay for my favorite songs. It holds 10 selections at a time, creating roughly 30-minute jet sets back to somewhere special. When it went on the fritz, it was as if the doorway to the happy days of my youth got slammed shut.</p>
        <p>I needed to get back there, so I searched desperately for a jukebox repairman, which these days is like trying to find a record-playing needle in a haystack.</p>
        <p>It took a while, but I found one. He was a golden oldie who arrived last Christmas season, bringing with him the gift of gab.</p>
        <p>He asked me what kind of music I enjoyed, and I told him that I was an oldies, Top 40 kind of guy but that I wasn't shy about spreading the dial around the radio.</p>
        <p>''Do you own an iPod?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>''Nope,'' I replied.</p>
        <p>''Do you burn CD's?''</p>
        <p>''Nope,'' I said again, sounding like a broken record.</p>
        <p>''Old school, like me, huh?''</p>
        <p>''Yep,'' I answered. ''Who has time to figure out all that new technology?''</p>
        <p>I told him that along with a huge record collection -- which I often rotate in and out of the jukebox -- I own a mountain of cassette tapes that are also on the brink of extinction. I realized that after purchasing a new truck two years ago that came with a CD player -- and no cassette deck.</p>
        <p>I told him that other than the jukebox, which holds 100 singles (the 200 selections include flip sides), my records have no home. I told him that the wife said she would walk, not dance, if I cranked up the old stereo.</p>
        <p>The jukebox guy finally closed his mouth and opened the belly of the box. He flipped a few switches and pressed a few buttons that made the big wheel spin. He took the wheel off of its track and put it back on -- or so he thought.</p>
        <p>He pressed another button, but this time the wheel slipped off its track. Several records fell out of their metal slots and the wheel rolled clockwise. Three of my favorites got caught under the rolling wheel and cracked. Say goodbye to ''Brandy (You're a Fine Girl),'' by Looking Glass; ''Times of Your Life,'' by Paul Anka; and ''Knock Three Times,'' by Tony Orlando and Dawn.</p>
        <p>I put the old jukebox guy out of service, but I refused to pull the plug on the old jukebox.</p>
        <p>Then one morning, I awoke with the most brilliant idea. Why not take all 100 records out of their slots and move each of them down two places? I did just that, leaving the information labels (song, selection number, artist) in their original places.</p>
        <p>SO now, when I want to hear ''I Love You,'' by the Climax Blues Band, I select song No. 118, the original and proper corresponding number. The jukebox, of course, thinks it is really selecting No. 116, ''I'm Stone in Love With You,'' by the Stylistics. But I've done such a masterly job at playing musical chairs with my records that no one hears ''I'm Stone in Love With You,'' unless of course, they actually pressed 116, which is now the new 114.</p>
        <p>I'm still turning on my old jukebox, and it is still returning the favor.</p>
        <p>And I still do not own an iPod.</p>
        <p>Who needs all the confusion?</p>
        <p>RITUALS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
