<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Summary</title>
    <meta content="06forsumms" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838389"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E6DB173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="986" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Summary</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-12</p>
        <p>Dutch Soldiers Stress Restraint in Afghanistan  In Uruzgan Province, Afghanistan, where the Taliban operate openly, a Dutch-led task force of about 2,000 soldiers has mostly shunned combat. Its counterinsurgency tactics emphasize efforts to improve Afghan living conditions and self-governance, rather than hunting the Taliban's fighters. American military officials have expressed unease about the Dutch method. A1</p>
        <p>10 Soldiers Dead in Iraq  Six American and four British soldiers were killed in separate attacks around Iraq, coalition officials said, and an American helicopter crashed south of Baghdad, wounding four soldiers. Four of the Americans died Wednesday and four were wounded when their vehicles were hit by roadside bombs in southern Baghdad and north of the city, the American military command said.  A12</p>
        <p>War Crimes Inquest in Somalia  European diplomats said that they were investigating whether Ethiopian and Somali government forces committed war crimes during heavy fighting in Somalia's capital. The fighting, some of the bloodiest in 15 years, killed more than 300 civilians and reduced blocks of buildings to rubble.  A8</p>
        <p>French Candidate Skips Visit  Nicolas Sarkozy, the conservative French presidential candidate, abruptly canceled a campaign visit to a Lyon neighborhood as demonstrators gathered, holding signs and chanting that he was not welcome. A6</p>
        <p>Detained Britons Arrive Home  The 15 British marines and sailors held captive in Iran for nearly two weeks arrived back home. But Britain's relief at their safe return was accompanied by questions about how they behaved during their detention and why they had been captured in the first place.  A10</p>
        <p>The British official in charge of reaching out to disaffected Muslims indicated in a speech that the government intended to take some steps to regulate and try to influence the affairs of Muslim religious institutions and mosques. A10</p>
        <p>British authorities charged three Muslim men with conspiring to help with reconnaissance and planning for the attack on the London transit system in July 2005 that killed 52 people. The charges were the first brought in the attack, which was carried out by four British suicide bombers of Pakistani origin. A10</p>
        <p>Pakistani Rival Gains on Unrest  As the Pakistani president, Gen. Pervez Musharraf, wrestles with swelling public disaffection over his rule, one of his key political rivals, Benazir Bhutto, above, has embarked on an international campaign to revive her political standing.  A3</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A14-17</p>
        <p>S O S for 911 Systems In the Age of Cellphones  In many areas of the country, more 911 calls come from cellphones than land lines. But 40 percent of the nation's counties cannot yet pinpoint the location of cellphone callers, though the technology has been available for at least five years.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Felons Regain Voting Rights  Gov. Charlie Crist persuaded Florida's clemency board to let most felons easily regain their voting rights after prison, saying it was time to leave the ''offensive minority'' of states that uniformly deny ex-offenders such rights.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Panel Seeks Gonzales Account  The chairman of the Senate Judiciary Committee asked Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales to provide the panel with a written account of his role in the dismissals of eight United States attorneys at least two days before his scheduled April 17 testimony.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Giuliani Rules Out Abortion Ban  Rudolph W. Giuliani, campaigning in South Carolina, firmly stated that as president he would not seek to make abortion illegal.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>Pet Food Recall Widens  A recall of pet food tainted with melamine, a chemical used to make plastic products, has been widened to include 22 types of dog biscuits, the F.D.A. said.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>New Links to Loan Companies  A senior official at the federal Education Department who oversees lenders in the federal student loan program held and sold shares in a student loan company for more than $100,000 at a time when he was helping regulate the industry.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION B1-6</p>
        <p>F.B.I. Agent Fatally Shot Outside New Jersey Bank  A veteran F.B.I. agent on a bank robbery stakeout was fatally wounded, apparently in an accidental shooting by another agent, during a confrontation with three gunmen outside a bank in a quiet town in north-central New Jersey, the authorities said.  A1</p>
        <p>2nd Chance for Development?  David Bistricer, whose initial attempt to buy the Starrett City housing complex in Brooklyn was rejected by federal regulators, now has a well-regarded architect, powerful lobbyists and something he was missing from his first go-round: potential backing from two politically influential black ministers.  B1</p>
        <p>Golf Outing Ends in Plane Crash  The three men who died when a twin-engine plane that took off from the Westchester County Airport crashed in Maryland were inseparable golf buddies headed for a few days of golf in North Carolina with the fourth member of their usual foursome, who waited in vain for their plane to arrive. B1</p>
        <p>ESCAPES F1-10</p>
        <p>Aging With the Like-Minded  For some Americans approaching their golden years, choosing the right place to grow old is less about golf and weather than about finding neighbors who share their attitudes and interests. Developments that cater to specific populations have popped up around the country. F1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES C9</p>
        <p>Darryl Stingley  A receiver for the New England Patriots who became a quadriplegic after an intentionally violent hit in a 1978 game, he was 55. C9</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY C1-10</p>
        <p>A $4.5 Billion Bid for Chrysler  Kirk Kerkorian's investment arm, Tracinda Corporation, made a $4.5 billion offer for the Chrysler Group that hinges on winning the exclusive right to negotiate with DaimlerChrysler and a deal with the United Automobile Workers union that could mean concessions.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest C2</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL A18-19</p>
        <p>Editorials: Guantánamo follies; no recess from bad appointments; not just New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Columns: Paul Krugman, Thomas L. Friedman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E36  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E29  Weather</p>
        <p>D6</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-12</p>
        <p>Dutch Soldiers Stress Restraint in Afghanistan  In Uruzgan Province, Afghanistan, where the Taliban operate openly, a Dutch-led task force of about 2,000 soldiers has mostly shunned combat. Its counterinsurgency tactics emphasize efforts to improve Afghan living conditions and self-governance, rather than hunting the Taliban's fighters. American military officials have expressed unease about the Dutch method. A1</p>
        <p>10 Soldiers Dead in Iraq  Six American and four British soldiers were killed in separate attacks around Iraq, coalition officials said, and an American helicopter crashed south of Baghdad, wounding four soldiers. Four of the Americans died Wednesday and four were wounded when their vehicles were hit by roadside bombs in southern Baghdad and north of the city, the American military command said.  A12</p>
        <p>War Crimes Inquest in Somalia  European diplomats said that they were investigating whether Ethiopian and Somali government forces committed war crimes during heavy fighting in Somalia's capital. The fighting, some of the bloodiest in 15 years, killed more than 300 civilians and reduced blocks of buildings to rubble.  A8</p>
        <p>French Candidate Skips Visit  Nicolas Sarkozy, the conservative French presidential candidate, abruptly canceled a campaign visit to a Lyon neighborhood as demonstrators gathered, holding signs and chanting that he was not welcome. A6</p>
        <p>Detained Britons Arrive Home  The 15 British marines and sailors held captive in Iran for nearly two weeks arrived back home. But Britain's relief at their safe return was accompanied by questions about how they behaved during their detention and why they had been captured in the first place.  A10</p>
        <p>The British official in charge of reaching out to disaffected Muslims indicated in a speech that the government intended to take some steps to regulate and try to influence the affairs of Muslim religious institutions and mosques. A10</p>
        <p>British authorities charged three Muslim men with conspiring to help with reconnaissance and planning for the attack on the London transit system in July 2005 that killed 52 people. The charges were the first brought in the attack, which was carried out by four British suicide bombers of Pakistani origin. A10</p>
        <p>Pakistani Rival Gains on Unrest  As the Pakistani president, Gen. Pervez Musharraf, wrestles with swelling public disaffection over his rule, one of his key political rivals, Benazir Bhutto, above, has embarked on an international campaign to revive her political standing.  A3</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A14-17</p>
        <p>S O S for 911 Systems In the Age of Cellphones  In many areas of the country, more 911 calls come from cellphones than land lines. But 40 percent of the nation's counties cannot yet pinpoint the location of cellphone callers, though the technology has been available for at least five years.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Felons Regain Voting Rights  Gov. Charlie Crist persuaded Florida's clemency board to let most felons easily regain their voting rights after prison, saying it was time to leave the ''offensive minority'' of states that uniformly deny ex-offenders such rights.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Panel Seeks Gonzales Account  The chairman of the Senate Judiciary Committee asked Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales to provide the panel with a written account of his role in the dismissals of eight United States attorneys at least two days before his scheduled April 17 testimony.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Giuliani Rules Out Abortion Ban  Rudolph W. Giuliani, campaigning in South Carolina, firmly stated that as president he would not seek to make abortion illegal.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>Pet Food Recall Widens  A recall of pet food tainted with melamine, a chemical used to make plastic products, has been widened to include 22 types of dog biscuits, the F.D.A. said.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>New Links to Loan Companies  A senior official at the federal Education Department who oversees lenders in the federal student loan program held and sold shares in a student loan company for more than $100,000 at a time when he was helping regulate the industry.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION B1-6</p>
        <p>F.B.I. Agent Fatally Shot Outside New Jersey Bank  A veteran F.B.I. agent on a bank robbery stakeout was fatally wounded, apparently in an accidental shooting by another agent, during a confrontation with three gunmen outside a bank in a quiet town in north-central New Jersey, the authorities said.  A1</p>
        <p>2nd Chance for Development?  David Bistricer, whose initial attempt to buy the Starrett City housing complex in Brooklyn was rejected by federal regulators, now has a well-regarded architect, powerful lobbyists and something he was missing from his first go-round: potential backing from two politically influential black ministers.  B1</p>
        <p>Golf Outing Ends in Plane Crash  The three men who died when a twin-engine plane that took off from the Westchester County Airport crashed in Maryland were inseparable golf buddies headed for a few days of golf in North Carolina with the fourth member of their usual foursome, who waited in vain for their plane to arrive. B1</p>
        <p>ESCAPES F1-10</p>
        <p>Aging With the Like-Minded  For some Americans approaching their golden years, choosing the right place to grow old is less about golf and weather than about finding neighbors who share their attitudes and interests. Developments that cater to specific populations have popped up around the country. F1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES C9</p>
        <p>Darryl Stingley  A receiver for the New England Patriots who became a quadriplegic after an intentionally violent hit in a 1978 game, he was 55. C9</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY C1-10</p>
        <p>A $4.5 Billion Bid for Chrysler  Kirk Kerkorian's investment arm, Tracinda Corporation, made a $4.5 billion offer for the Chrysler Group that hinges on winning the exclusive right to negotiate with DaimlerChrysler and a deal with the United Automobile Workers union that could mean concessions.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest C2</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL A18-19</p>
        <p>Editorials: Guantánamo follies; no recess from bad appointments; not just New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Columns: Paul Krugman, Thomas L. Friedman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E36  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E29  Weather</p>
        <p>D6</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
