<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Goldberg' Variations Galore By New Music's Torchbearer</title>
    <meta content="06mcmi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/arts/music/06mcmi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838274"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Columbia University</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E5DF173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="543" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Goldberg' Variations Galore By New Music's Torchbearer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">‘Goldberg’ Variations Galore by New Music’s Torchbearer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The pianist Blair McMillen can play composers like Liszt, Debussy and Scriabin with flair, intelligence and Juilliard-honed virtuosity, as his self-produced 2004 recording ''Soundings'' makes abundantly clear. But what most excites this 36-year-old North Carolina native is contemporary music. He is best known as a mainstay of several contemporary music ensembles in New York.</p>
        <p>Yet even for a musician who champions new works, Mr. McMillen, in his recital on Wednesday night at Casa Italiana at Columbia University, was adventurous. As part of a series, ''Music for the New Century,'' sponsored by the university's Italian Academy for Advanced Studies in America, Mr. McMillen played an entire program of works composed since 2000. Well, to be precise, Marco Stroppa's ''Passacaglia Canonica,'' a study in staggered motion and multifaceted harmony, was written in 1991, then revised in 2002. Otherwise, the works by Steven Stucky, Barbara White, Joan Tower and others dated from the 21st century.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mr. McMillen was especially adventurous in his recital on Wednesday at Columbia University, featuring works by Steven Stucky, Barbara White and Joan Tower.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The pianist Blair McMillen can play composers like Liszt, Debussy and Scriabin with flair, intelligence and Juilliard-honed virtuosity, as his self-produced 2004 recording ''Soundings'' makes abundantly clear. But what most excites this 36-year-old North Carolina native is contemporary music. He is best known as a mainstay of several contemporary music ensembles in New York.</p>
        <p>Yet even for a musician who champions new works, Mr. McMillen, in his recital on Wednesday night at Casa Italiana at Columbia University, was adventurous. As part of a series, ''Music for the New Century,'' sponsored by the university's Italian Academy for Advanced Studies in America, Mr. McMillen played an entire program of works composed since 2000. Well, to be precise, Marco Stroppa's ''Passacaglia Canonica,'' a study in staggered motion and multifaceted harmony, was written in 1991, then revised in 2002. Otherwise, the works by Steven Stucky, Barbara White, Joan Tower and others dated from the 21st century.</p>
        <p>Mainstream concertgoers who assume that a recital of recent works must be a daunting listening experience should have been there. The Casa Italiana, an ornately decorated salon that can comfortably accommodate an audience of a couple of hundred, is an ideally intimate hall. Wearing an informal shirt and plain slacks, the youthful and somewhat shy Mr. McMillen set a pensive mood for his 70-minute program by opening with Mr. Stucky's ''Album Leaves,'' a 10-minute suite of four movements.</p>
        <p>''Contemplativo,'' the first, played with delicate colorings and rhapsodic expressivity, sounds like Ravel, ingeniously updated -- a succession of rolled chords with pungent out-of-focus harmonies. A melodic line pierces the milky textures but keeps getting stuck in place. The second movement is abuzz with swirling cyclic riffs. The crystalline Messiaen-like colors of the third movement lead to the finale, in which brutal chords are contained within a scampering Presto, dispatched with crackling vigor and crunchy tone by Mr. McMillen.</p>
        <p>He was equally commanding in three excerpts from Ms. White's engaging ''Reliquary.'' The first one played, ''Sin,'' could have been the fractured shards of a stride piano piece. ''Mirage'' was an overt homage to Ravel's ''Oiseaux tristes,'' all the more entrancing because the composer dares to be so close to her source, rightly confident that her ear is strong enough to make the piece original.</p>
        <p>Mr. McMillen's elegant performance of the theme of Bach's ''Goldberg'' Variations made you want to hear him play the entire work. Here the theme introduced four pieces from ''13 Ways of Looking at the Goldberg,'' a collective work in which a dozen composers wrote new variations on Bach's iconic theme. Though Stanley Walden's ''Fantasy Variation,'' Fred Hersch's ''Melancholy Minuet'' and Mischa Zupko's ''Ghost Variation'' were inventive in various ways, I especially enjoyed Derek Bermel's ''Kontraphunktus,'' in which one small embellished segment of Bach's theme is spun into a meter-smashing, obsessive musical reflection.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tower's two-part piece ''Vast Antique Cubes/Throbbing Still'' plays with whole tone scales, neo-primitive riffs, Stravinsky-like percussive rhythms and oscillating, arm-blurring chord passages. Though dramatic, volatile and virtuosic, the music seemed a little transparent. Still, when played by the formidable Mr. McMillen, any piece sounds terrific.</p>
        <p>The ''Music for the New Century'' series concludes on May 2 at Casa Italiana with a program by the pianist Kathleen Supove and the violinist Jennifer Choi.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
