<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Museum and Gallery Listings</title>
    <meta content="06wart" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/arts/design/06wart.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838422"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E1DB173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="5499" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Museum and Gallery Listings</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Museum and Gallery Listings</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THE NEW YORK TIMES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ART</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Selective listings from art critics of The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ART</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>'THOMAS STRUTH: MAKING TIME' Through the 1990s the German photographer Thomas Struth became an art-world celebrity for his outsize, absorbing portraits of crowds interacting with artwork in the world's great museums. As a follow-up, he is presenting the American premiere of two new series of pictures of audiences beholding single masterpieces in the Museo Nacional del Prado in Madrid and the State Hermitage Museum in St. Petersburg, Russia. The show, at Marian Goodman Gallery in Midtown, is one of the most visually sumptuous and thought-provoking in the city. Both series of photographs are from 2005, though they are completely different in style, tone, spirit and intent. The pictures of students and tourists at the Prado (above), milling about and chatting in front of various paintings of great attention, fame and devotion, contrive to get us thinking about a cocktail of cultural concerns -- the aura of masterpieces, museums as promenades, art tourism -- to which he adds a touch of farce. Almost nobody in the pictures is looking at the paintings. By contrast, the pictures of crowds pressed in close around Leonardo da Vinci's ''Litta Madonna'' and ''Benois Madonna'' at the Hermitage are deviously direct, the artist zooming in his lens on the facial expressions of the crowd to the exclusion of the paintings. These pictures are a sort of guilty pleasure, owing almost entirely to the cleverness of the artist, who allows us safely to look at others looking at art. You only hope that he is not lurking around the gallery here somewhere with a camera at the ready. (Through April 28, Marian Goodman Gallery, 24 West 57th Street, Manhattan, 212-977-7160, mariangoodman.com.) BENJAMIN GENOCCHIO</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>AMERICAN FOLK ART MUSEUM: MARTíN RAMíREZ, through May 13. Ramírez, a Mexican peasant who immigrated to Northern California and died there at 68 in 1963, spent the last 32 years of his life in a mental hospital, making some of the greatest art of the last century. He had his own way with materials and color, and an unforgettable cast of characters (most notably, a mounted caballero and a levitating Madonna crowned like the Statue of Liberty). But most of all, Ramírez had his own brand of pictorial space, established by rhythmic systems of parallel lines, both curved and straight, whose mesmerizing expansions and contractions simultaneously cosset and isolate his figures. In addition to being one of the season's best exhibitions and the first of his work in a New York museum, this show should render null and void the distinction between insider and outsider art. 45 West 53rd Street, (212) 265-1040, folkartmuseum.org. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY: 'GOLD,' through Aug. 19. Having delved into pearls, diamonds and amber, the museum applies its time-tested show-and-tell formula to the premier precious natural material, gold. This astounding array of art, artifacts and natural samples -- larded with fascinating facts and tales -- ranges from prehistoric times to the present. Stops along the way include pre-Columbian empires, sunken treasure, Bangladesh dowry rituals and the moon landing. It turns out that gold comes from the earth in forms as beautiful as anything man has thought to do with it, but that gold ingots have a brute force all their own. You are certain to emerge with mind boggled and eyes dazzled. Central Park West and 79th Street, (212) 769-5100, amnh.org.</p>
        <p>(Smith)</p>
        <p>ASIA SOCIETY: GLASS, GILDING, AND GRAND DESIGN: ART OF SASANIAN IRAN (224-642 A.D.), through May 20. This glinting, glowing show is a reduction of a much larger Paris exhibition that included material from Iranian museums impossible to bring to the United States. With some 70 examples of silver, glass and silk textile fragments, many from European museums, this is still substantial and the first major exhibition of its kind in this part of the world for more than 30 years. For about four centuries, the Sasanians ruled territory stretching from present-day Iran and Iraq to North Africa. Their only rivals were Rome, Byzantium and, at the very end, the early Islamic dynasties. Much of their surviving art is a sterling example of empire in action. 725 Park Avenue, at 70th Street, (212) 288-6400, asiasociety.org. (Holland Cotter) BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'GLOBAL FEMINISMS,' through July 1. Too much of the work in this sprawling, international assembly of recent pieces by nearly 90 women from nearly 50 countries is body-oriented and doesn't venture far beyond the essentialism of Judy Chicago's indomitable 1975-79 installation opus, ''The Dinner Party,'' whose enshrinement in the new Elizabeth A. Sackler Center for Feminist Art this exhibition celebrates. Thoroughly dominated by photography and video, with a documentary slant to many of its better moments, the show is more about information, politics and the struggle for equality than it is about art in any very concentrated or satisfying sense. That doesn't keep parts of it from being energetic and illuminating, especially as a record of the way that feminism has gripped and jump-started the imaginations of women around the world. 200 Eastern Parkway, Brooklyn, (718) 638-5000, brooklynmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'KINDRED SPIRITS: ASHER B. DURAND AND THE AMERICAN LANDSCAPE,' through July 29. This show of about 60 works by one of the greats of 19th-century American landscape painting has as its centerpiece ''Kindred Spirits'' (1849), a tribute to the landscapist Thomas Cole and his friend the poet-journalist William Cullen Bryant. A founder of the Hudson River School but one of its less dramatic painters, Durand (1796-1886) favored the realistic approach to landscape advocated by the English critic John Ruskin, rather than the metaphorical view held by Cole and other Hudson River artists that its representation ought to express God's sublimity. Obeying Ruskin's call for truth to nature, Durand explored forest interiors with close attention to the ways of trees, foliage, rocks and ground cover in smaller works, while his larger and more elaborate exhibition pictures, influenced by European masters, are Arcadian visions suffused with light, color and atmospheric perspective. If the show reveals some of Durand's weaknesses -- repetitive themes and borrowings from other artists -- it also reveals his strong sense of artistic mission and his potent role in shaping the aesthetic of 19th-century America. (See above.) (Grace Glueck).</p>
        <p>CHELSEA ART MUSEUM: 'DANGEROUS BEAUTY,' through April 21. A somewhat timely update of a well-worn idea, this show of contemporary works in a variety of mediums by 18 artists examines the beauty myth in art, advertising and the fashion industry. Eloquent but blunt imagery of anorexic girls, chiseled male beefcake and close-ups of surgically deformed faces predominates, reminding us of the violent extremes to which some people will go in pursuit of society's ideal of beauty and a designer body. The rest of the show -- often pointing an accusatory finger at skinny models, cosmetic labels and the mass media -- feels familiar in its critique, but the basic premise about the ideology of beauty in our culture is beyond argument. 556 West 22nd Street, (212) 255-0719, chelseaartmuseum.org. (Benjamin Genocchio)COOPER-HEWITT NATIONAL DESIGN MUSEUM: 'DESIGN LIFE NOW: NATIONAL DESIGN TRIENNIAL 2006,' through July 29. Like its two predecessors this ambitious show illuminates the volatile, contradictory and ever-expanding field of design, but fails to call it to order. The inclusions range from genius to schlock, delightful to dispiriting. They cover medical innovation, military hardware, completely frivolous reiterations of received ideas (far too many of which trace to Surrealism), sundry Web sites and magazines, haute couture, architecture and recycling -- more varieties of recycling than you can easily count. The show coalesces into deliberately orchestrated skirmishes between conflicting principles and entities: corporate and private, decorative and essential. 2 East 91st Street, (212) 849-8400, ndm.si.edu. (Smith) FRICK COLLECTION: 'GEORGE STUBBS (1724-1806): A CELEBRATION,' through May 27. One of the finest horse painters ever, Stubbs knew his subjects from head to hoof and skin to bones. He painted other mammals too: dogs, lions, tigers, oxen, monkeys and humans. This intimate show of 17 Stubbs paintings from English collections reveals his admirable range, although the people he portrayed in two large, late canvases have the stiffness of figures on a candy box. His horses are his true monuments. 1 East 70th Street, Manhattan, (212) 288-0700, frick.org. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'FAMILY PICTURES,' through April 16. This show sounds ripe with possibilities. The results, however, are more mixed. The exhibition is drawn from the museum's collection, which explains some of its exclusions and limitations. Many artists you associate with contemporary photography and the family are not in attendance: Richard Bellingham, Tina Barney, Malerie Marder. There is also a sense of false advertising in the exhibition's title. The museum's news release extends the exhibition's exploration into ''representation of families and children in contemporary art and video.'' Images of children, you quickly realize, can operate as a completely different genre. Rineke Dijkstra's ''Beach Portraits'' of adolescents awkwardly posing against stark seascape horizons are isolated (and isolating) images of children on the threshold of adulthood. You don't think about family when gazing at these photographs. Sally Mann is perhaps the best-known contemporary photographer of children, specifically her own. Ms. Mann, represented here by black-and-white photographs from the late 1980s and early 1990s of her ethereally gorgeous children, has been accused of everything from neglect to child abuse. The questions raised by her dual role as artist and mother, simultaneous protector and potential exploiter of the family, remain vitally interesting. 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3500, guggenheim.org. (Martha Schwendener)</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL CENTER OF PHOTOGRAPHY: 'HENRI CARTIER-BRESSON'S SCRAPBOOK: PHOTOGRAPHS, 1932-46,' through April 29. Arrived by way of the Fondation Henri Cartier-Bresson in Paris, this show has more than 300 of the prints the photographer glued into an album and toted to New York for curators at the Museum of Modern Art to cull. Captured by the Nazis, he had been presumed dead when the Modern planned his retrospective. Then he turned up alive -- the ''posthumous'' exhibition opened, with him in attendance, in 1947. The current exhibition reconstructs as best as possible the layout of the scrapbook as Cartier-Bresson originally organized the pictures. It surveys the revolutionary work he shot in Spain, Italy, Mexico, Britain and France. Here are the familiar and, more interestingly, some less familiar, shots of crowds in Hyde Park in London at George VI's coronation, of picnickers on the banks of the Marne in France and whores in Valencia, Spain. His taste for uncanny detail linked him to Surrealism and Surrealist wit, but unlike many Surrealists, he remained committed to human values. Boys mug at his camera. Prostitutes swan. Their gazes equalize them with us. 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000, icp.org. (Michael Kimmelman)INTERNATIONAL CENTER OF PHOTOGRAPHY: 'MARTIN MUNKACSI: THINK WHILE YOU SHOOT!' through April 29. Munkacsi, who inspired Cartier-Bresson, was, by contrast, self-taught, a creature of his own devising. This is the most complete retrospective, with a thick catalog (not too well researched) and dozens of vintage prints from the 1920s through the early '60s. He favored scenes of daily life, absorbing avant-garde ideas about odd angles and abstract compositions. His sports photographs epitomized his special gift for action and movement: capturing a soccer ball just as it neared a goalie's outstretched hands or a motorcyclist at the instant he splashed through a pool of water. In 1928 he moved to Berlin, where the opportunities were better, and traveled the world on assignment to Brazil, Algeria and Egypt. Munkacsi was a stylist, and he made catchy images the only way he knew how, in a modernist mode, which, being an opportunistic form, could serve any master. He became a celebrity in America. He photographed Fred Astaire dancing and Joan Crawford poolside. In the breezy layouts of Harper's Bazaar, the work looked brilliant. (See above.) (Kimmelman)THE METROPOLITAN MUSEUM OF ART: 'COAXING THE SPIRITS TO DANCE,' through Dec. 2. How the Papuans practiced their beliefs on the remote Pacific island of New Guinea in the late 19th and early 20th centuries, when they still had little contact with the West, is the complex and fascinating story told in this exhibition of some 60 objects and 30 rare photographs of the works on site or in actual use. The carved and painted ''spirit boards'' made throughout the gulf region, on the south coast of present-day Papua New Guinea, are probably the most easily recognized of the area's traditional artworks. Their central designs, passed down from fathers to sons and through marriages, typically represent a bush or river spirit, with a heavily stylized face and perhaps a small body, surrounded by various totemic symbols. More daring in concept are the masks used in ritual dances. Papuan art may not be as varied or exciting as that of many African or Amerind peoples, but it records a vibrant community. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* THE MET: 'VENICE AND THE ISLAMIC WORLD, 828-1797,' through July 8. At its peak in the Renaissance, Venice, the Most Serene, was a giant, clamorous Costco-on-the-Rialto. All the necessities, and most of the luxuries, of life flowed into and through it, with many items arriving from Islamic Africa and the Near East. With classic Met largesse, this exhibition suggests the spectacle of two different cultures meeting in one fantastic city, in which commerce and love of beauty, those great levelers, unite them in a fruitful bond. (See above.) (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* THE MET: 'INCISIVE IMAGES: IVORY AND BOXWOOD CARVINGS,' through Nov. 25. This extraordinary show, drawn almost entirely from the Met's vaults, presents an array of nearly 100 carved figures, crucifixes, reliefs, containers, hand-held weapons and the occasional piece of furniture. It is an engrossing hive of religious fervor, Classical erudition (and occasional naughtiness), style shifts and multicultural cross-currents. And among the many feats of drop-dead artistic skill are several of traffic-stopping caliber. Don't miss it. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (See above.) (Smith)</p>
        <p>THE MET: 'LOUIS COMFORT TIFFANY AND LAURELTON HALL -- AN ARTIST'S COUNTRY ESTATE,' through May 20. Laurelton Hall may have burned to the ground in 1957, but this exhibition does an excellent job of reassembling what remains of this extraordinary house- museum and its gardens, which Tiffany created for himself in the early 1900s. The Gilded Age opulence of the place, which occupied 580 acres overlooking Long Island Sound, is conveyed most blatantly by the Temple-of-Dendur-size Daffodil Terrace, in wood, marble and glass. The main events are the glass windows, vases and lamps, where Tiffany's genius for color, love of the exotic and reverence for nature coalesce into an unforgettable mystical materialism. (See above.) (Smith) * THE MET: 'ONE OF A KIND: THE STUDIO CRAFT MOVEMENT,' through Sept. 3. Focusing on the postwar development of artist-craftsmen who not only conceive and design their own objects but have a direct hand in making them, this display of furniture, glass, ceramics, metalwork, jewelry and fiber includes funny, quirky, provocative and sometimes gorgeous things. Among its stars are a witty bust by the California funk ceramicist Robert Arneson (1920-92), portraying the mother of the 16th-century painter and printmaker Albrecht Dürer; John Cederquist's elegant cabinet concealed behind a trompe l'oeil door painted and veneered to look like a battered wooden packing case with a rowdy wave tearing through it; and Bonnie Seeman's fetching ceramic coffeepot and tray, whose mock cabbage leaves and rhubarb stalks evoke the genteel tradition of 18th-century British and continental china, but can also be read as human rather than vegetative tissue. Traditionalists, too, have their place in this show, with the wood workers Wharton Esherick and Sam Maloof represented by elegantly simple renditions in the furniture line; respectively, a music stand and a Shaker-like settee. (See above.) (Glueck)MORGAN LIBRARY &amp; MUSEUM: 'APOCALYPSE THEN: MEDIEVAL ILLUMINATIONS FROM THE MORGAN,' through June 17. Even in the contemporary art world the symbolism of the Book of Revelation, with its demons and lakes of fire, has a subversive appeal. This new exhibition at the Morgan Library celebrates a facsimile of ''Las Huelgas Apocalypse'' (1220), the largest surviving Spanish illuminated commentary on the Apocalypse. The show, which includes 50 leaves from the original text, unbound and installed around the gallery's perimeter, offers a walking tour of the medieval imagination. 225 Madison Avenue, at 36th Street, (212) 685-0008, morganlibrary.org. (Andrea K. Scott)</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'ARTISTIC COLLABORATIONS: 50 YEARS OF UNIVERSAL LIMITED ART EDITIONS,' through May 21. This exhibition observes the half-century milestone for Universal Limited Art Editions in West Islip, N.Y., and its association with the Museum of Modern Art. The museum has acquired one print from every edition made at Universal, more than 1,200 works by nearly 50 artists. Prints by 12 artists are in this show. Among them are lithographs by Jasper Johns, mostly from the 1960s, with his signature maps and flags. Robert Rauschenberg is represented primarily by lithographs from the 1960s that combine found images of figures like John F. Kennedy and Lyndon B. Johnson with the freehand scrawling associated with Abstract Expressionism. It's hard to fault an exhibition that features prints by masters like Mr. Johns and Mr. Rauschenberg and Kiki Smith. But given the somewhat precarious position of prints in the contemporary art world, and with many artists opting to go digital, the inclusion of younger artists would make a good argument that traditional printmaking is still relevant and holds possibilities for this generation. (212) 708-9400, moma.org. (Schwendener)</p>
        <p>MOMA: 'COMIC ABSTRACTION: IMAGE-BREAKING, IMAGE-MAKING,' through June 11. This unimaginative and uniformed treatment of a big idea -- the healthy and essential contamination of Modernist abstraction by popular culture -- should be seen if only because it is such a dispiriting symptom of the Modern's paralysis where contemporary art is concerned. Although it promises work that addresses ''perplexing questions,'' nearly everything here is perfectly pleasant and innocuous. The exceptions are provided by Gary Simmons, Ellen Gallagher and Sue Williams. (212) 708-9400, moma.org. (See above.) (Smith)</p>
        <p>MOMA: ARMANDO REVERÓN, through April 16. Unless you spotted his single smoke-puff of a painting at MoMA months ago, Armando Reverón probably means nothing to you. Why should he? The artist, who died in 1954, spent most of his life in a shack by the sea in his native Venezuela. Many of his contemporaries dismissed him as nuts. His white-on-white pictures are practically unphotographable. But chances are that if you visit this retrospective, you'll find yourself thinking about him a lot. His art and his story are like few others, and so is the museum's inspired installation: a single, long corridor with cabinetlike rooms of paintings on either side and, at the very end, against a sea-green wall, a life-size doll with giant bat wings floating overhead. (See above.) (Cotter)</p>
        <p>MOMA: JEFF WALL, through May 14. This majestic show makes a great case for Mr. Wall as the most complete, if traditional, of the untraditional artists who emerged from the turmoil of Conceptual Art. His often immense color transparencies mounted on light boxes are enthralling vehicles, intent on giving pleasure while making a point or two about society, art, history, visual perception, the human animal or all of the above. An imposing blend of painting, street photography and movies, they blur reality and artifice, narrative and form, detail and the big statement. You can't stop looking at them. (See above.) (Smith)</p>
        <p>NATIONAL ACADEMY MUSEUM: HIGH TIMES, HARD TIMES: NEW YORK PAINTING, 1967-1975, through April 22. Organized under the auspices of International Curators Incorporated, this brave if confused exhibition is the first to tackle a neglected subject: New York painting during the period it was supposed to be dead. The show's 42 works by 37 artists reveal that, far from dead, painting was in fact in an uproar that was commensurate with the artistic, social and political turbulence of the times. The alternation between artists who remained loyal in their way to stretched canvas and those who abandoned it, which makes for clear installation, also tidies up history. The main problem is that the exhibition sticks too purposefully to the margins, mixing generations and levels of achievement and continuing the neglect of the main story. Too much of this work is as derivative now as it was then, and functions more as artifact than art. 1083 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 369-4880, nationalacademy.org. (Smith)NEUBERGER MUSEUM OF ART: FUGITIVE ARTIST: THE EARLY WORK OF RICHARD PRINCE, 1974-77, through June 24. Mr. Prince is one of the most elusive, perverse and sardonic of all of the important appropriation artists to emerge in the early 1980s, so perhaps it is not surprising that he has boycotted this exhibition of little-known early work, all from public and private collections. But that doesn't stop the 50 pieces on view from revealing his roots in 1970s Conceptual Art; his progress from generic to original and radical; or the depth and duration of his fascination with language, photography, printmaking, the more banal forms of urban postwar Americana and a disconnected, decidedly male blankness. If anything, it increases his stature. Purchase College, State University of New York, 735 Anderson Hill Road, Purchase, N.Y., (914) 251-6100, neuberger.org. (Smith) NEUE GALERIE: 'VAN GOGH AND EXPRESSIONISM,' through July 2. The Neue has, as usual, gathered a stellar roundup of Expressionist art. In one of the show's most exciting rooms, a third-floor gallery devoted mostly to self-portraits, two extraordinary van Goghs hang at opposite ends: ''Self-Portrait With Straw Hat'' (1887-88), from the Metropolitan Museum's collection, filled with energetic, radiating brushstrokes, and the National Gallery's vibrant self-portrait of the artist holding a palette and brushes, painted about a year later. The most compelling pairing in this room, though, is van Gogh's ''Bedroom'' from 1889, the second of three versions he painted of his room in Arles, with Egon Schiele's obvious homage, ''The Artist's Bedroom in Neulengbach,'' painted in 1911, in a darker palette and with a perspective tipped precariously toward the viewer. 1048 Fifth Avenue, at 86th Street, (212) 628-6200, neuegalerie.org. (Schwendener)NEW-YORK HISTORICAL SOCIETY: 'NEW YORK DIVIDED: SLAVERY AND THE CIVIL WAR,' through Sept. 3. New York has a cosmopolitan pride in itself, but as this exhibition shows, it is not always well deserved. Even after slavery belatedly came to an end in New York State in 1827, New York City was a ''hotbed of pro-slavery politics,'' inspired by close commercial links with the South and the international cotton trade. For every instance of abolitionist activity, there is another in which slavery is defended or supported. This powerful exhibition, focused on the years between Emancipation and Reconstruction, and featuring documents, videos, audio dramatizations, books, cartoons and historic objects, shows how divided the city was, even during the years of the Civil War. But it also draws attention to the importance of black abolitionists and to the forces that countered slavery's horrific heritage. It brings to a close the Historical Society's multiyear exploration of slavery in New York. 170 Central Park West, (212) 873-3400. (Edward Rothstein)</p>
        <p>ONASSIS CULTURAL CENTER: 'ATHENS-SPARTA,' through May 12. Painted vases, pottery, sculptured steles, tiny carved figures, writings inscribed on stone and a selection of coins are among the nearly 300 objects in this show, whose first section begins with pieces from both cities during the Geometric Period (1050-700 B.C.). Two other sections deal with the on-again, off-again relationship between the cities in the fifth century B.C., Greece's glory years, and with the wars they fought: the Persian Wars (about 500 to 449 B.C.) and the Peloponnesian War (431 to 404 B.C.), in which Sparta defeated Athens, only to fade not long after. As society evolved from tribal to civil and felt the first stirrings of democracy during the Archaic Period (650-480 B.C.), rigid geometrical motifs were succeeded by more human forms, like the kouroi and korai, the stone or bronze statues, sometimes life-size, representing young men and women and symbolizing a new emphasis on the individual. Usually they bore relief images of the deceased and were set on graves as markers and memorials. On view from the sixth century B.C. are two small Attic representations of korai, dressed statues of maidens, said to represent the Athenian aristocracy in rites celebrating the goddess Athena. Carved in stone, with long, braided hair (one is headless, but her braids are visible) and beautifully articulated drapery that clings to their bodies, they disappeared as a type after the Persian wars. 645 Fifth Avenue, near 52nd Street, (212) 486-4448. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>P.S. 1 CONTEMPORARY ART CENTER: 'KATRIN SIGURDARDOTTIR: HIGH PLANE V,' through May 7. Cut into a space between two levels of P.S. 1 is the Icelandic artist Katrin Sigurdardottir's ''High Plane V,'' a miniature artificial landscape of glacial mountains arranged in a naturalistic, faux-snow-covered setting against a painted white background. Visitors climb ladders and peer into one of two holes in the ceiling to view the work. The installation works best when two people mount the ladders and poke their heads in at the same time: then they can both see a disembodied head floating in the middle of the icy landscape. 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Street, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 784-2084, ps1.org. (Genocchio) UKRAINIAN MUSEUM: 'CROSSROADS: MODERNISM IN UKRAINE, 1910-1930,' through April 29. Some of the great names in Modernist Russian art -- Malevich, El Lissitsky, Rodchenko, Archipenko and Exter -- were actually born, or identified themselves as, Ukrainian. And this show of more than 70 works by 21 artists, including many interesting lesser-knowns, informs us that their Ukrainian-ness made an impact on their contributions to the Modernist movements of the 20th century. The entirely nonobjective Suprematist work of Kasimir Malevich, for instance, was based in part on Ukrainian folk motifs, and the exuberant Cubist-Futurist theater designs and paintings by Alexandra Exter relate to icons and patterns from village embroideries and weavings and bright peasant costumes. Discoveries in the show include Vsevolod Maksymovych, a painter drawing on Symbolist sources, heavily influenced by classical themes and the campy erotica of the British graphic artist Aubrey Beardsley; and Anatol Petrytsky, a painter and creator of lighthearted, collagelike sketches for classical and avant-garde opera and ballet. Stressing as it does the importance of Ukrainian participation in Modernist art, the show is equally significant in its exposure to Americans of lively talents, largely unknown. 222 East Sixth Street, East Village, (212) 228-0110, ukrainianmuseum.org. (Glueck)WADSWORTH ATHENEUM MUSEUM OF ART: 'FAITH AND FORTUNE: FIVE CENTURIES OF EUROPEAN MASTERWORKS,' through Dec. 9. Celebrating the return of its famous Renaissance, Baroque and Rococo paintings and objects of art from a three-year national tour, the Wadsworth has arranged a feast of a show. One of the most appealing things about this gathering of some 400 treasures is the mix, with knockout paintings keeping company with small sculptures, elaborate table furnishings, decorative platters, Meissen knockoffs of Chinese pottery, a porcelain birdcage and vases and such. Strolling through the galleries, you'll find treasures like ''Saint Francis of Assisi in Ecstasy'' (about 1594-95), said to be the first authentic Caravaggio in an American museum; Fra Angelico's poignant, poetic fragment ''Head of an Angel'' (about 1455-50); and Francisco de Zurbarán's fearsome portrayal of a dead martyr, ''Saint Serapion'' (1628). But the pièce de résistance is an entire gallery made into an art and curio cabinet, with a planned clutter of brilliant objects that play to a viewer's inner acquisitor: exotic shells mounted in gold; an extraordinary Baroque ivory carving (presumed to be before 1650) of Adam and Eve; an automatic tabletop clock (about 1619) with a standing lion that could roll its eyes, open its jaws and stick out its tongue when the hours struck. Dazzlement prevails. 600 Main Street, Hartford, (860) 278-2670, wadsworthatheneum.org (Glueck)</p>
        <p>WHITNEY MUSEUM OF AMERICAN ART: 'GORDON MATTA-CLARK RETROSPECTIVE,' through June 3. I have no doubt that Matta-Clark is now being turned into a hot commodity, but at least at the Whitney you can see what he aspired to be. He came up with various wonderfully harebrained ideas. Literally, in one case: after letting his hair grow for a year, he cut it off as a kind of performance and phrenological gag. The preserved hair, dutifully tagged piece by piece, opens the show like a holy relic. He also sautéed a Polaroid of a Christmas tree in grease. The copy he sent to Robert Smithson, golden brown on the outside, is here too, and none too appetizing, I might add. At the center of the exhibition is ''Splitting.'' To a plain single-family suburban frame house in Englewood, N.J., he made a cut straight down the middle, bisecting the building, then severing the four corners of the roof. The retrospective consists of films, drawings, photographs and some of the architectural pieces he cut out of buildings. The drawings are casual and not too interesting, but the luxurious black-and-white photographs from Paris speak more to Matta-Clark's formal elegance. The big message was: Life as art, and art as life, a philosophy dependent on our being properly attuned and keen to the moment. (212) 570-3676, whitney.org. (Kimmelman) WHITNEY MUSEUM OF AMERICAN ART: 'LORNA SIMPSON,' through May 6. This tight, refined and impassioned survey covers more than 20 years of Lorna Simpson's career, from her photo-and-text meditations on race and sexism in the 1980s, to her more recent short films, which unite American history and personal history in forceful and lyrical ways. It would be easy to put some of this work on a shelf as ''identity art,'' but with an African-American woman holding one of the highest offices in the United States government, an African-American man running for president, and the nation embroiled in what some people view as an ethnic war, this art is entirely of the moment. (See above.) (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>JEAN SHIN: KEY PROMISES The idea is obvious, if you're as keen as this artist on recycling everyday objects: an installation using the word commands of countless computer keyboards to orchestrate a flow of suggested actions, desires and emotional states across four walls of a smallgallery. From esc and shift to return and home. Art lite, perhaps, but expertly done. Frederieke Taylor Gallery, 535 West 22nd Street, (646) 230-0992, frederieketaylorgallery.com, through tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Other</p>
        <p>'GIFTS OF THE FOREST: NATIVE TRADITIONS IN WOOD AND BARK' Drawn from the collections of the Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center in Connecticut, this show celebrates the trees of the rich forests that once covered the Northeast, yielding essential materials to the Pequot and other Eastern Woodland cultures. The objects run from ancient woodworking tools to contemporary objects that carry on tribal traditions, like the simple and beautiful wooden flute made in 1999 by Hawk Henires (Nipmuc) and adorned with an elegantly carved bird motif. Many things here were made in the 19th and 20th centuries: handsome woven baskets, carved bowls and spoons, decorated cradle boards for carrying babies, birch bark canoe models, an elegant birch-bark hamper whose sides bear a stylized tree motif. UBS Art Gallery, 1285 Avenue of the Americas, between 51st and 52nd Streets, (212) 713-2885, through April 27. (Glueck) 'EARLY CHINESE BUDDHIST SCULPTURE,' Asia Week is over, but its essence lingers on in this exhibition of beautiful carved stone figures of Buddhas and bodhisattvas dating from the Northern Wei to Tang periods in China. This is the type of work that elicited rapturous responses when shown in London and Washington a few seasons back. Throckmorton Fine Art, 145 East 57th Street, third floor, (212) 223-1059, through April 14. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>MORGAN LIBRARY &amp; MUSEUM: 'PRIVATE TREASURES: FOUR CENTURIES OF EUROPEAN MASTER DRAWINGS,' through Sunday. This show is drawn entirely from an anonymous private collection. Despite the veil of secrecy, a couple of things are obvious: the collector had significant capital for investing in old masters and either an exceptional eye or a good adviser (or both). The works span more than 400 years, from the 16th to the early 20th centuries, and include drawings in ink and pencil, watercolor, chalk and gouache. The strongest concentration is in Italian drawings. The earliest works come from a period when drawing wasn't an autonomous practice but was used as a form of exercise, to apply one's craft, to experiment and to make preliminary sketches for larger works. The best example -- and the most historically significant work here -- is a black chalk drawing, ''The Dead Christ'' (1529-35), by Agnolo Bronzino. With more than 90 drawings in the show, being a diligent observer quickly becomes exhausting. In which case, put down the guide, find a few drawings you like, and enjoy them while you can. After all, you don't know where they came from, where they're going, or when you'll see them again. (See above.) (Schwendener)</p>
        <p>* JOHANNES VANDERBEEK The debut solo show of this young artist at Feuer is a poetic, storybook tableau with a full-scale sculpture of a medieval knight reclining on his tomb and a walled-up archway set in the gallery wall. Both are made entirely of papier-mâché made from old copies of Time and National Geographic. The beautiful little tree that stands between them is also of paper and paste. And check out the time-and-space-warped sleepers in the back room. Zach Feuer Gallery, 530 West 24th Street, Chelsea, (212) 989-7700; closes tomorrow. (Cotter)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
