<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Newark on Time on Budget, But a Fiscal Crisis Looms</title>
    <meta content="06budget" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/nyregion/06budget.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838390"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Newark (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Sharpe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Booker, Cory A (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jacobs, Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Newark (NJ)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE6DB173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1019" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Newark on Time on Budget, But a Fiscal Crisis Looms</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Newark on Time on Budget, but a Fiscal Crisis Looms</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW JACOBS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jacobs, Andrew</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, April 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Newark faces fiscal crisis unseen since 1970s, even though it has managed to complete work on $720 million budget for 2007 on time and without tax increase; officials must find way to fill $180 million shortfall in 2008 budget and are making presentations on problem with corporate executives and economists in region and residents; Mayor Cory A Booker blames administration of Sharpe James for problems (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Municipal Council approves the 2007 budget later this month, there is sure to be a burst of mutual acclaim among council members and the mayor for putting together a $720 million spending plan that was passed on time and without a tax increase.</p>
        <p>This is, after all, a city that usually passes its budgets after the fiscal year has expired and the money has been spent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEWARK, April 5  When the Municipal Council approves the 2007 budget later this month, there is sure to be a burst of mutual acclaim among council members and the mayor for putting together a $720 million spending plan that was passed on time and without a tax increase.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Municipal Council approves the 2007 budget later this month, there is sure to be a burst of mutual acclaim among council members and the mayor for putting together a $720 million spending plan that was passed on time and without a tax increase.</p>
        <p>This is, after all, a city that usually passes its budgets after the fiscal year has expired and the money has been spent.</p>
        <p>''I think we deserve a lot of credit considering the trickery and gimmickry and smoke and mirrors of the past,'' said Ronald C. Rice, a councilman who oversees the budget hearings. But the congratulatory handshakes will almost immediately be challenged by the harsh reality that Newark is facing a crisis unseen since the 1970s.</p>
        <p>Over the next few months, City Hall must find ways to fill a $180 million shortfall in the 2008 budget, a hole that equals about a quarter of the city's annual expenditures. ''I don't think people realize that we're about to enter a financial freefall,'' Mayor Cory A. Booker said. ''You can only squeeze so much blood from stone before you are forced to do some draconian things.''</p>
        <p>To prepare for the rough road ahead, officials have put together a three-year budget plan, something state officials say they have never seen before from a New Jersey municipality. Newark officials have been traveling the region with a presentation that lays out the problem to corporate executives and economists in the hope of enlisting help -- pro bono, of course.</p>
        <p>In an effort to ease the shock to residents, the mayor will also begin holding a kaffeeklatsch in various homes to explain the city's predicament. The city has also put the budget -- all 400 pages -- on the Internet.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Booker said he hoped to wring out tens of millions in savings by leaving vacancies unfilled and increasing government efficiency, he also said that painful tactics like layoffs and library closings were not out of the question. ''I think it's important to be upfront with people about the severe state of peril we're in,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The seeds of this looming crisis were planted in 2002, when the administration of Sharpe James and the Council decided to use a $400 million settlement from the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey to plug shortfalls in the city's operating budget. Only $120 million remains -- Mr. Booker is using $115 million to close the 2007 gap -- and when that runs out in three years, the city could find itself with a $240 million problem. (Bridging that chasm through taxation alone, officials warn, would require doubling the city's property tax rate.)</p>
        <p>Fiscal watchdogs have long warned the city that it was ignoring reality by treating the Port Authority money like limitless manna. ''They've become highly dependent on revenue from a source that is going to evaporate,'' said Edith Behr, an analyst at Moody's Investor Service, which downgraded Newark's bond rating in 2005 after the city failed to pass a budget that year and could not send out tax bills. Like nearly every municipality in New Jersey, Newark is suffering the effects of a decade-long pension holiday, sanctioned by the state, that allowed the city to sharply reduce its contributions to a fund for public workers. Next year Newark will have to spend an additional $30 million on pension and other employee benefits and $40 million in back pay and salary increases for firefighters and police officers as a result of contracts negotiated in recent months.</p>
        <p>Mr. Booker blames the James administration for much of the city's financial hardship. He said that the administration failed to set aside money for outstanding tax appeals and litigation. He also criticized Mr. James for giving superior officers in the Police Department a 4 percent pay raise, making it all but certain that other police and fire unions, whose contracts expired two years ago, would expect the same. He said the city also failed to stow away money for retroactive pay increases that resulted from those contracts.</p>
        <p>''We inherited a city whose finances should have been declared a national disaster area,'' Mr. Booker said.</p>
        <p>Richard Monteilh, the previous business administrator, rejected suggestions that the city's finances were mismanaged and said he presented the current administration a plan he insisted would have helped them avoid the current crisis. ''You have to shrink the municipal payroll and grow the revenue base,'' he said, adding, ''The skyline should be full of cranes right now.''</p>
        <p>Bo Kemp, the current business administrator, said that economic development can take years to bear fruit -- so in the meantime, he plans to start trimming fat at the edges. He estimated that the city could save as much as $100 million by improving the way it collects hotel and parking taxes, streamlining the city's purchasing system and tweaking the bureaucracy. ''It's yeoman's work, but I think we can do it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But that does not leave many options for bridging the remaining $80 million gap, at least not politically palatable ones. City Hall can raise taxes, eliminate jobs or hope the state hands over more cash, a situation that seems unlikely given the state's own ailing finances.</p>
        <p>If history is any guide, Mr. Kemp might be forced to take a path similar to the one traveled by Thomas A. Banker, the budget director and assistant business administrator in the 1970s. The budget shortfall became so severe that Wall Street locked the city out of the bond market, and the municipal work force shrank to 4,000 from 7,000, mostly through a decade of attrition.</p>
        <p>In the depth of the crisis in 1978, Newark police officers protested layoffs by standing at the city's main entry points and handing drivers fliers that said, ''Welcome to Fear City.''</p>
        <p>Three decades later, Mr. Banker, now a consultant and professor of public affairs at Columbia University, chuckled as he recalled how angry officers used his picture for target practice. ''I was the most hated person in the city,'' he said in an interview. ''I wish Bo or Cory the best of luck, because there are no popular choices.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
