<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When It Counts, Augusta Grinds Down a Laboring Els</title>
    <meta content="06masters" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/sports/golf/06masters.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838383"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Augusta National Golf Club</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Mickelson, Phil</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Stadler, Craig</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rose, Justin</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06EEDC173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="456" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When It Counts, Augusta Grinds Down a Laboring Els</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">When It Counts, Augusta Grinds Down Laboring Els</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hack, Damon</byline>
      <dateline>AUGUSTA, Ga., April 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ernie Els has spent his career being told that he has a game built for the Masters. He has come so close to winning that he could nearly feel a green jacket on his shoulders.</p>
        <p>But after an opening-round six-over-par 78 at Augusta National Golf Club on Thursday, which put him nine shots out of the lead, Els may be spending another year waiting for the next Masters to begin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After an opening-round six-over-par 78 at Augusta on Thursday, which put him nine shots out of the lead, Ernie Els may be spending another year waiting for the next Masters to begin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ernie Els has spent his career being told that he has a game built for the Masters. He has come so close to winning that he could nearly feel a green jacket on his shoulders.</p>
        <p>But after an opening-round six-over-par 78 at Augusta National Golf Club on Thursday, which put him nine shots out of the lead, Els may be spending another year waiting for the next Masters to begin.</p>
        <p>''I have to try and get something going and hopefully by Sunday get back to level par,'' he said. ''If I can do that, it will be a hell of a thing to do, but it is back to the drawing board, basically.''</p>
        <p>Els said he arrived at the tournament with confidence. Last month, he spent three days playing and practicing at Augusta National, but the course wore him down when it counted. He started his day with a double bogey and added a bogey at the second hole. The round deteriorated from there.</p>
        <p>''If you mis-hit a shot, you really paid the penalty,'' he said. ''The fairways were firm, even the rough was pretty firm. Everything was firm out there.''</p>
        <p>Three years ago, he watched Phil Mickelson pull on a green jacket after defeating Els by one stroke.</p>
        <p>After Thursday's first round, Els was tied for 72nd and miles from a green jacket.</p>
        <p>It was a disappointment that he did not want to measure.</p>
        <p>''You can figure that one out, can't you?'' he said.</p>
        <p>NO-NAME NO MORE -- Two weeks after finishing second to Tiger Woods at the CA Championship, Brett Wetterich is becoming a familiar name on leader boards. He finished the first round tied for the lead with Justin Rose after shooting a three-under-par 69.</p>
        <p>''This is the biggest tournament in my mind that I want to win,'' said Wetterich, who is playing in his first Masters. ''To be able to go out and start off with a good, solid round, it means a lot to me.''</p>
        <p>Wetterich played in the final round with Woods at the CA Championship and shot 71 to Woods's 73. Last year, he won the Byron Nelson Championship for his lone PGA Tour victory.</p>
        <p>BRIEF DETOUR FOR QUIGLEY -- One day after Brett Quigley's wife, Amy, gave birth to a daughter, he shot a four-over-par 76.</p>
        <p>Quigley left Augusta National in the middle of his practice round Tuesday and flew home to Jupiter, Fla., where he was able to witness the birth at 2:55 a.m. Wednesday morning.</p>
        <p>He flew back to Augusta in time for his 2:03 p.m. tee time Thursday.</p>
        <p>''I didn't sleep at all, but I had good adrenaline going,'' he said. ''I feel fine.''</p>
        <p>The baby's name? Lillian Augusta Quigley.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
