<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Quinn Urges More Money For Libraries In Budget</title>
    <meta content="06council" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/nyregion/06council.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838342"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bloomberg, Michael R (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Quinn, Christine C (Council Speaker)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rivera, Ray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Quinn, Christine C</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E1DD173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="727" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Quinn Urges More Money For Libraries In Budget</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Quinn Urges More Money for Libraries in Budget</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAY RIVERA; David M. Herszenhorn contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rivera, Ray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Council Speaker Christine C Quinn proposes adding $61 million to Mayor Michael R Bloomberg's $57.1 billion preliminary budget for New York City next year (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Council Speaker Christine C. Quinn called yesterday for increased library hours and money for new education initiatives and health clinics for underserved areas. Those changes are included in a proposal that would add $61 million to Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg's $57.1 billion preliminary budget for next year.</p>
        <p>Ms. Quinn urged the changes in a 45-minute speech in a packed room at Chatham Square Library in Chinatown, where she continued to position herself as an ally of the middle class as she prepares for a widely anticipated but as yet unannounced run for mayor in 2009.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Council Speaker Christine C. Quinn called yesterday for increased library hours and money for new education initiatives and health clinics for underserved areas. Those changes are included in a proposal that would add $61 million to Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg’s $57.1 billion preliminary budget for next year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Council Speaker Christine C. Quinn called yesterday for increased library hours and money for new education initiatives and health clinics for underserved areas. Those changes are included in a proposal that would add $61 million to Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg's $57.1 billion preliminary budget for next year.</p>
        <p>Ms. Quinn urged the changes in a 45-minute speech in a packed room at Chatham Square Library in Chinatown, where she continued to position herself as an ally of the middle class as she prepares for a widely anticipated but as yet unannounced run for mayor in 2009.</p>
        <p>Her budget proposal fleshed out many of the initiatives she outlined in her State of the City speech in February. Among them is a $300 tax credit for renters for families of four making less than $75,000 and individuals making less than $43,000. The program is expected to benefit about 1.1 million New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>Another initiative would lift the income cap for people qualifying for first-time home buyer's assistance, to $92,170 a year from about $56,720 for a family of four. She also proposed injecting $50 million over two years to help people buy and rehabilitate the decaying stock of homes being auctioned off by the federal Department of Housing and Urban Development.</p>
        <p>The financing would be dependent on the buyer agreeing to keep the housing available to low- and middle-income buyers.</p>
        <p>Her plan would also expand prekindergarten slots by 2,100 full-time seats, and create 96 slots to hire specialists to help parents wade through the complicated choices as their children move from prekindergarten to kindergarten, elementary to middle school and middle school to high school.</p>
        <p>The Council's budget response is aimed at influencing the mayor to incorporate its suggestions in his executive budget, which he is required to produce by early May. The Council and the mayor then negotiate a final budget to be adopted in June for the fiscal year that begins July 1.</p>
        <p>Ms. Quinn highlighted the Council's proposal to have all public libraries return to being open at least six days a week, a service that was lost in cuts after 9/11. To do that, the Council would inject $42.7 million into the budget over three years.</p>
        <p>The plan also calls for 10 new health care clinics in communities with the most severe health care shortages, at a cost of $10 million over the next five years and $17 million in capital expenses over four years.</p>
        <p>Among the few signs of discord between the mayor's budget plan and the Council's was a call by the Council to redirect $12 million it says is allocated to the Department of Education's Panel for Education Policy.</p>
        <p>The 13-member, unpaid advisory body was created by Mr. Bloomberg in his first administration to replace the Board of Education. Critics say it has become a powerless entity completely controlled by the mayor, who once fired two members who disagreed with him on a policy matter.</p>
        <p>''It's not quite the educational powerhouse we thought it would be when it was first created,'' Ms. Quinn said. ''We'd like to redirect that money to the classroom.''</p>
        <p>It was a rare jab at the mayor by the speaker, who has worked largely in concert with Mr. Bloomberg as she considers her own future as a mayoral contender.</p>
        <p>The mayor's aides said yesterday that no such money was earmarked for the panel, which receives only about $7,200 total in annual stipends plus miscellaneous expenses.</p>
        <p>As for the rest of the Council's budget proposal, Mr. Bloomberg said he would have to evaluate it but was glad to see that it included some money-saving ideas.</p>
        <p>To finance the budget plan, the Council included $243 million in agency cuts and savings and estimated tax revenues that would exceed the mayor's projections by $619 million based on a strong real estate market that continues to defy national trends.</p>
        <p>Dick Dadey, executive director of Citizens Union, which promotes transparency in government, said the budget proposal given by Ms. Quinn showed fiscal restraint and appeared to be largely in line with the mayor's own budget priorities.</p>
        <p>''What is remarkable is not just the substance but the way in which the response is being presented,'' Mr. Dadey said. ''It's collaborative and tries to avoid conflict with the mayor, which is a break from past responses to the budget.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
