<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Upgrade For Ye Olde History Park</title>
    <meta content="06will" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/arts/06will.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838265"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="EXHIBITION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia/Williamsburg</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Colonial Williamsburg</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E7DF173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1773" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Upgrade For Ye Olde History Park</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Upgrade for Ye Olde History Park</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD ROTHSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rothstein, Edward</byline>
      <dateline>WILLIAMSBURG, Va.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Patrick Henry was sitting just to my left in the Virginia House of Burgesses as the debate raged about the events that had been following the Boston Tea Party. Mr. Henry was a brilliant hothead, of course, though not yet moved to pose his famous nonnegotiable alternatives, demanding liberty or death. But when Governor Dunmore of the Virginia colony strode into the room, even Mr. Henry rose, out of respect to the authority of the king, as did we all, even those of us carrying digital cameras, umbrellas and souvenir bags.</p>
        <p>Then the governor announced to these local legislators, landed gentry every one, that he was dissolving the House of Burgesses because of their rebellious deliberations. Discussion about the imminent political crises of 1774 were adjourned to the tables of the Raleigh Tavern.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The historical village is a strange combination of education and entertainment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Patrick Henry was sitting just to my left in the Virginia House of Burgesses as the debate raged about the events that had been following the Boston Tea Party. Mr. Henry was a brilliant hothead, of course, though not yet moved to pose his famous nonnegotiable alternatives, demanding liberty or death. But when Governor Dunmore of the Virginia colony strode into the room, even Mr. Henry rose, out of respect to the authority of the king, as did we all, even those of us carrying digital cameras, umbrellas and souvenir bags.</p>
        <p>Then the governor announced to these local legislators, landed gentry every one, that he was dissolving the House of Burgesses because of their rebellious deliberations. Discussion about the imminent political crises of 1774 were adjourned to the tables of the Raleigh Tavern.</p>
        <p>We hangers-on would have been happy enough to join in or just listen. But further debate was not to be heard until later, leaving time to check in with the saddlemaker, with whom I discussed battles in the not-yet-fought Revolutionary War. Then it was off to a small room of another 18th-century building, where I overheard three slaves debating alternatives after reading a declaration from Dunmore promising them freedom if they escaped and joined him in defense of the crown.</p>
        <p>Being a colonial tourist is a bit disorienting, particularly on days like the recent ones I spent, in rain and off-season, with scarcely another person in modern dress to be seen. Instead there were ruffles and bonnets and velvet cloaks, the coal fires of the blacksmith, and much to-do among the gentry about gunpowder and taxes.</p>
        <p>Colonial Williamsburg, where all this took place (about 150 miles south of Washington), is variously called a historical village or a living museum. But that means much more now than it once did. Aside from dramatizing historical controversies, the town is also caught up in living ones: debates about who writes history and how it is told, about what historical realism is and how it should be portrayed, even about what aspects of our past are to be celebrated in this strange combination of education and entertainment.</p>
        <p>Everything here, for example, is from late-18th-century Virginia, with crucial exceptions including: no slavery apart from the dramatizations (although until just a few decades ago here forms of discrimination and segregation were still commonplace), flush toilets and freshly painted buildings as carefully tended as suburban developments, which in some ways Colonial Williamsburg resembles.</p>
        <p>One doesn't really step into the past here, or in any of the other historical villages developed after Colonial Williamsburg's pioneering success. Despite the obsession with authenticity -- historical techniques and period tools reign, the blue-gray glaze on the bricks is reproduced using local clay and hardwood fires, 88 Colonial buildings have been restored and more than 400 created based on research by architects and archaeologists -- nothing seems quite real. Reproductions and renovations and innovations intermingle, creating an image of the past so carefully constructed that it is a re-creation in all senses of the word.</p>
        <p>But what an astonishing enterprise it is, and what a difficult task Colonial Williamsburg now faces. It was always meant to be an inspiration. In the early 20th century the Rev. William Archer Rutherfoord Goodwin, rector of the local parish, imagined creating ''a living shrine that will present a picture, right before our eyes, of the shining days'' when the town was ''a crucible of freedom.'' He won the support of John D. Rockefeller Jr., who later said the historical village ''teaches of the patriotism, high purpose and unselfish devotion of our forefathers to the common good.'' At its opening in 1934 President Franklin D. Roosevelt visited and pronounced its central Duke of Gloucester Street ''the most historic avenue in all America.'' Since then almost every president has toured the premises; President Ronald Reagan even held an economic summit of industrialized nations here in 1983.</p>
        <p>But that symbolic weight may now be a burden. This living museum's very point -- a celebration of the origins of the United States -- is often greeted with skepticism. In their preoccupation with this country's past flaws and failures, organizers of the nearby Jamestown's 400th-anniversary events in May have shunned the term celebration in favor of commemoration.</p>
        <p>Even if it were flush with cultural confidence, though, can a 301-acre historical village now hope to compete with more extravagant theme parks? Attendance at Colonial Williamsburg has been increasing in recent years, according to a spokesman -- there were 745,000 paid visitors in 2006 -- but the peak was in 1985 with 1.1 million.</p>
        <p>The Colonial Williamsburg Foundation, which runs the village under the direction of its chairman and president, Colin G. Campbell, recently announced plans to sell a 400-acre plantation called Carter's Grove, on the banks of the James River, partly because of declining attendance and shifting priorities.</p>
        <p>Yet with the cushion of a $774 million endowment and continued fund-raising the foundation has added more extensive dramatizations for its costumed interpreters, increased its children's activities, renovated its conference center, is introducing audio tours for teenagers and has just opened a new Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Folk Art Museum, which has 5,000 objects. Plans call for continued growth of traditional museum space but -- significantly -- not for the high-tech annexes that other historical sites are establishing to lure audiences, which would undercut the institution's claims to colonial realism.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile Colonial Williamsburg has been changing its symbolic character. Instead of offering itself as a model colonial town, it presents itself as a town whose colonial past provides an opportunity to explore the United States' defining dramas. As Richard Handler and Eric Gable point out in their 1997 book, ''The New History in an Old Museum: Creating the Past at Colonial Williamsburg,'' the perspective changed under the influence of social and political historians in the 1970s. For the most part (and to the disappointment of those authors), this has meant not radical self-skepticism, but the establishment of a broader perspective, understanding, for example, as the institution's literature has said, ''how patriots and loyalists reached their different points of view.''</p>
        <p>It has also meant incorporating something previously ignored. As its Web site puts it: ''During the 18th century, half of Williamsburg's population was black. The lives of the enslaved and free people in this Virginia capital are presented in re-enactments and programs by Colonial Williamsburg's Department of African American Interpretation and Presentations, founded in 1988.'' Black craftsmen and guides are now familiar figures, as are interpreters playing the roles of slaves.</p>
        <p>''That the future may learn from the past'' was the motto Rockefeller chose for Colonial Williamsburg. But as even the institution's history and coffee-table book, ''Colonial Williamsburg'' by Philip Kopper, suggests, the area's own past may also hold some lessons. Before Colonial Williamsburg there were living museums in Europe, but the closest thing in the United States was Henry Ford's Greenfield Village in Dearborn, Mich., which had opened a few years earlier, in 1928. A patched-together reflection of Ford's vision of America's past, it included everything from the childhood home of Robert Frost to the one-room schoolhouse Ford attended.</p>
        <p>Williamsburg was something else. It really was Virginia's capital, a Southern counterpart to Boston, a political incubator for ideas about governance and liberty, where one of the colonies' first newspapers, The Virginia Gazette, was published. But after the capital moved to Richmond in 1780 under Gov. Thomas Jefferson, Williamsburg descended into sleepy irrelevance until Rockefeller secretly began to buy up houses in the late 1920s, under Goodwin's guidance.</p>
        <p>He eventually poured $68 million into the project, hiring architects and researchers and almost single-handedly creating an American culture of historical restoration (and perhaps, along with it, an association between America's 20th-century gentry and its Virginian predecessors). Life tenancies and relocations were offered to the 20th-century inhabitants of Williamsburg; now residences of employees and artisans mix with staged historical displays.</p>
        <p>The enterprise has always had its critics. One 1920s resident, Maj. S. D. Freeman, challenged his fellow citizens to imagine their future: ''Will you not be in the position of a butterfly pinned in a glass cabinet, or like a mummy unearthed in the tomb of Tutankhamen?'' In 1938 Frank Lloyd Wright described the project as an example of America's ''mawkish sentimentality for a past that wasn't any good.'' In their book Mr. Handler and Mr. Gable call it a ''Republican Disneyland,'' accusing it of hiding American history's darker aspects. And Ada Louise Huxtable, a former architecture critic for The New York Times, attacked the groomed artifice of its picturesque past in her book ''The Unreal America.''</p>
        <p>It is impossible to stroll the village without feeling that sense of artifice, beginning with an introductory film shown in the cavernous Visitor Center. A 1957 historical mini-epic, ''Williamsburg: The Story of a Patriot,'' invokes the sentiments of its cold war era, being ''dedicated to the principles of liberty wherever and whenever they may be threatened.'' Shot on site, the film can veer toward camp, with its images of smiling plantation slaves and story of a landowner won over by Patrick Henry's revolutionary convictions.</p>
        <p>The film is dated in manner and vision, but for all its flaws, it still has an effect: It dramatically captures many of the colonial era's issues, provides a sense of the period and reasons to pay attention to it, and provokes curiosity. Ultimately, its sentiments seem far less dated than they do at first.</p>
        <p>That same shift takes place while experiencing Colonial Williamsburg itself. The place is artificial and always was. But the debates I witnessed that rainy day among gentry legislators and anxious slaves provided glimpses of the significance and character of colonial-era Williamsburg; the repeated exposure to crafts seriously executed gave some sense of the devotion and labor that characterized colonial culture; and the hints of pain and shadow were enough to suggest the complications of the past, without eclipsing reasons to celebrate it.</p>
        <p>It is not the injustices that make Williamsburg unusual, but the steps taken there to seek more just forms of governance. The place's artifice eventually casts its spell, even while acknowledging that artifice is indeed at work. Perhaps that makes Colonial Williamsburg more postmodern than colonial.</p>
        <p>Fifes, Drums, Debate</p>
        <p>Colonial Williamsburg is about 150 miles south of Washington, midway between Richmond and Norfolk off Interstate 64 at Exit 238. It is open year round; hours through June 17 are 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. A one-day pass is $36; $18 for ages 6 to 17. Passes are available for periods from two days up to a year, and discount passes are available for guests in Colonial Williamsburg hotels. Information: (757) 229-1000, www.history.org.</p>
        <p>EXHIBITION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
