<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LIVING HERE | Houses in River Towns; Going With the Flow</title>
    <meta content="06live" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838355"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hudson River</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hudson (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Parker, Colleen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyttle, Bethany</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Havens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Living Here</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Upstate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E4DC173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="902" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LIVING HERE | Houses in River Towns; Going With the Flow</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">As told to Bethany Lyttle</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyttle, Bethany</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Colleen Parker comments on her second home near Hudson River in Hudson, NY; photos and brief descriptions of similar properties for sale around country (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHO -- Colleen Parker, 39, an information technology recruiter, shown with her husband, Alon Friedman, 40, a doctoral student and instructor  WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  WHERE -- Hudson, N.Y.</p>
        <p>We started looking for a place to escape in 2005. We wanted more space, but we weren't necessarily looking for a country setting. We live in the West Village in Manhattan and really enjoy stepping out of our door there and into the life of the neighborhood. We wanted a slower, smaller version of that somewhere else. We love the way, in Hudson, we can walk out for the newspaper and go to a cool coffee shop or a great restaurant. When we go to a bar, the bartender remembers what we drink. People on the street say hello. There's definitely a small-town feeling here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHO -- Colleen Parker, 39, an information technology recruiter, shown with her husband, Alon Friedman, 40, a doctoral student and instructor  WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  WHERE -- Hudson, N.Y.</p>
        <p>We started looking for a place to escape in 2005. We wanted more space, but we weren't necessarily looking for a country setting. We live in the West Village in Manhattan and really enjoy stepping out of our door there and into the life of the neighborhood. We wanted a slower, smaller version of that somewhere else. We love the way, in Hudson, we can walk out for the newspaper and go to a cool coffee shop or a great restaurant. When we go to a bar, the bartender remembers what we drink. People on the street say hello. There's definitely a small-town feeling here.</p>
        <p>We'd never been to Hudson before, but when we saw it, we were immediately taken by its architecture. During the 1800s, the town was a center for whaling, and everywhere there are row houses and Victorian houses, most beautifully preserved and all within walking distance of the Hudson River. Walking around, it's easy to imagine the town in its prime. It's definitely a shipping town.</p>
        <p>The houses in Hudson are built in rows up a hill away from the river. So you can stand on Warren Street, which is the main street of shops, galleries, and restaurants, and see the river at the end of the street.</p>
        <p>Our house is a plain-Jane Victorian that I've been remodeling one room at a time. Even though it's in town, not directly on the river, the light is amazing. I still remember the first time I saw one of those skies like the ones depicted in Frederic Church paintings. The colors are unreal.</p>
        <p>As told to Bethany Lyttle</p>
        <p>Information on properties was supplied by the listing companies.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Deep River, Conn.  WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $499,900</p>
        <p>This house, near the Connecticut River, was built in 2001. The property is just over three acres and is close to the Lyons Conservation Preserve. The house is 2,932 square feet and has granite countertops and stainless-steel appliances in the kitchen, a large dining room, two and a half bathrooms, a library and a great room with a vaulted ceiling. Deep River is about 40 miles northeast of New Haven and a two-hour drive from New York City. Broker: Maureen Wiltsie O'Grady, Rachel Thomas Associates, (860) 767-8635; www.rachelthomasrealty.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Aurora, Ind.  WHAT -- 6-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $475,900</p>
        <p>This fully restored Victorian house was built in 1850 and is on 1.5 acres. Aurora is on the Ohio River about 35 miles west of Cincinnati; three riverboat casinos are nearby. The house, which could be used as a bed and breakfast, is 4,877 square feet and has original details, including fireplaces and high ceilings. There are five bathrooms. Broker: Kathy Patterson, Premier Properties Real Estate, (513) 535-2877; www.kathyp.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Hannibal, Mo.  WHAT -- 3-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $164,500</p>
        <p>Hannibal was the hometown of Mark Twain and today is the site of the Mark Twain Boyhood Home and Museum. The town is on the Mississippi River. This two-story brick house, which is on 1.5 acres, was built in 1906 and has been partially renovated. Plumbing, electricity, heating and air-conditioning systems have been updated. Renovated bedrooms have solid cherry hardwood floors and quarter-sawn white oak doors. There are two and a half bathrooms. Agent: Jill Best, Prestige Realty, (573) 221-8171; www.prestigerealty.net.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Catskill, N.Y.  WHAT -- Subdivided house  HOW MUCH -- $255,000</p>
        <p>This 1,400-square-foot house is on the main street in the village of Catskill, which is on the Hudson River. Built in 1840, the house has hardwood floors, original moldings and a bathroom with original black and white tile and a claw-foot tub. Currently, the first floor is used as office space, and there are two one-bedroom, one-bathroom apartments, one on the second floor and one in the basement. There is a small barn, which can be used as a garage or a studio. Agent: Claudia Zucker, Living Structures, (888) 851-1552; www.livingstructures.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Florence, Ore.  WHAT -- 2-bedroom house with guesthouse  HOW MUCH -- $439,000</p>
        <p>This restored two-story house was built in 1906 and is known as the David House. It is in the historic area of Old Town Florence about one block from the Siuslaw River. It has original details, including fir floors, a claw-foot bathtub and high ceilings. There are one and a half bathrooms. The guesthouse has one bedroom; there is also a three-car garage. Florence is on Oregon's central coast about 60 miles from Eugene. Brokers: Patrick and Pamela Emmingham, Prudential Pacific Properties, (541) 999-0810; www.getrealrealestate.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Scottsville, Va.  WHAT -- 2-bedroom house with guesthouse  HOW MUCH -- $385,000</p>
        <p>This property is on 3.85 acres on the James and Hardware Rivers. The house, which was built in 1914, is 1,426 square feet and has wood floors, original cabinets and French doors that lead to the back yard. There are two bathrooms. The guesthouse or caretaker's cottage has one bedroom and one bathroom. Scottsville was a major river port during the mid-1800s, and its historic district is listed on the National Register of Historic Places. Agent: Peter Lee, Roy Wheeler Realty Co., (434) 951-5142; www.roywheeler.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
