<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a Handel Romp, Whimsy Collides With Tragedy</title>
    <meta content="06flav" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/arts/music/06flav.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838279"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York City Opera</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Rader-Shieber, Chas</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E3DF173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="453" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a Handel Romp, Whimsy Collides With Tragedy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In a Handel Romp, Whimsy Collides With Tragedy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE MIDGETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Midgette, Anne</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The shiny pinks and greens of Chas Rader-Shieber's production of Handel's ''Flavio'' are a nice complement to a score that presents arias nestled side by side, bright and sweet and varied as the offerings in a box of candy, linked by premises as ordered and flimsy as cardboard dividers. This ''Flavio,'' which returned to City Opera on Wednesday night, is a confection: much of a good thing, not all of it sophisticated or uniformly pleasing, but leaving a reasonably pleasant aftertaste.</p>
        <p>Not that ''Flavio,'' one of the early operas in Handel's London canon, is all sweetness and light. Its plot leads farce into the realm of the tragic: a silly argument escalates into a murder. This moment sends the whole evening around a bend; there is no way to return to the lighthearted slapstick of the past, even though all of the couples -- including Emilia, the daughter of the murdered man, and her lover, Guido, the murderer -- are reunited at the end, with bright-pink wedding cake.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chas Rader-Shieber’s production is a confection: much of a good thing, not all of it sophisticated or uniformly pleasing, but leaving a reasonably pleasant aftertaste.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The shiny pinks and greens of Chas Rader-Shieber's production of Handel's ''Flavio'' are a nice complement to a score that presents arias nestled side by side, bright and sweet and varied as the offerings in a box of candy, linked by premises as ordered and flimsy as cardboard dividers. This ''Flavio,'' which returned to City Opera on Wednesday night, is a confection: much of a good thing, not all of it sophisticated or uniformly pleasing, but leaving a reasonably pleasant aftertaste.</p>
        <p>Not that ''Flavio,'' one of the early operas in Handel's London canon, is all sweetness and light. Its plot leads farce into the realm of the tragic: a silly argument escalates into a murder. This moment sends the whole evening around a bend; there is no way to return to the lighthearted slapstick of the past, even though all of the couples -- including Emilia, the daughter of the murdered man, and her lover, Guido, the murderer -- are reunited at the end, with bright-pink wedding cake.</p>
        <p>A main interest of the evening lay in three company debuts, starting with the conductor William Lacey, who led a strong, lithe reading and was one of two harpsichordists in the elaborate continuo. The orchestra, as a whole, sounded firm, but the singers, as a whole, seemed oddly challenged with regard to intonation, from the opening duet -- as Vitige (Katherine Rohrer) takes his leave of his lover, Teodata (Kathryn Allyn) -- to the final one between Emilia (Marguerite Krull) and Guido (Gerald Thompson). This uncertainty threatened to spoil some generally good performances. Ms. Rohrer, another debutante, has a nice, clear, high mezzo (a strong contrast to Ms. Allyn's nearly contralto darkness) but often missed the center of her tones.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson, a countertenor, arrived with considerable acclaim for a double-barreled New York debut. (Later this month he will step into two performances of ''Giulio Cesare'' at the Metropolitan Opera.) The role of Guido offered a chance to hear plenty of him, almost more than the limits of his own endurance. An eager puppy-dog of a singer with a pleasing round tone, he lost focus and volume more than once in the vehement wildness of rapid arias.</p>
        <p>His tone may be more innately appealing than David Walker's, but Mr. Walker made a fine effect reprising the title role of the foppish, foolish king: both funny and flashy, with some impressive singing. Ms. Krull had some lovely moments as the bereaved Emilia, though she, too, fell victim to moments of approximate pitch. Matthew Chellis and Jan Opalach were both reasonably solid as the feuding fathers.</p>
        <p>Flavio continues for six more performances, through April 21, at New York City Opera, State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
