<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>True Story of a Fake Story About Hughes (Really)</title>
    <meta content="06hoax" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/movies/06hoax.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838272"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, A O</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hallstrom, Lasse</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gere, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Molina, Alfred</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tucci, Stanley</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Hoax, the (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Plagiarism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plagiarism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Hallstrom, Lasse</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Hoax, The (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E5DF173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1083" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>True Story of a Fake Story About Hughes (Really)</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">True Story of a Fake Story About Hughes (Really)</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By A.O. SCOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scott, A O</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>A O Scott reviews film The Hoax, directed by Lasse Hallstrom; Richard Gere, Alfred Molina and Stanley Tucci star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The literary and journalistic frauds of the present era -- the fudgings, thefts and fabulations of James Frey, Jayson Blair, Stephen Glass, Kaavya Viswanathan and their sorry ilk -- are small potatoes compared to the work of Clifford Irving. Mr. Blair led readers of The New York Times to believe he'd been to Texas; Mr. Frey convinced Oprah Winfrey and many others that he'd been to jail. But Mr. Irving, back in the early 1970s, conned a major publishing house and a popular magazine into buying a much bigger and more brazen lie.</p>
        <p>He told them that Howard Hughes -- the words ''reclusive billionaire'' were not actually part of the man's name, though they often seemed to be -- had appointed Mr. Irving to be his official biographer. Claiming to be in regular contact with his subject, and forging handwritten letters to back up his claim, Mr. Irving pocketed a large advance (some of it meant for Hughes) and produced a manuscript apparently spun out of a mix of careful research, inspired guesswork and pure invention.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The literary and journalistic frauds of the present era are small potatoes compared to the work of Clifford Irving, the subject of “The Hoax.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The literary and journalistic frauds of the present era -- the fudgings, thefts and fabulations of James Frey, Jayson Blair, Stephen Glass, Kaavya Viswanathan and their sorry ilk -- are small potatoes compared to the work of Clifford Irving. Mr. Blair led readers of The New York Times to believe he'd been to Texas; Mr. Frey convinced Oprah Winfrey and many others that he'd been to jail. But Mr. Irving, back in the early 1970s, conned a major publishing house and a popular magazine into buying a much bigger and more brazen lie.</p>
        <p>He told them that Howard Hughes -- the words ''reclusive billionaire'' were not actually part of the man's name, though they often seemed to be -- had appointed Mr. Irving to be his official biographer. Claiming to be in regular contact with his subject, and forging handwritten letters to back up his claim, Mr. Irving pocketed a large advance (some of it meant for Hughes) and produced a manuscript apparently spun out of a mix of careful research, inspired guesswork and pure invention.</p>
        <p>All these years later, even as Hughes's mystique has faded somewhat -- nowadays his name is likely to conjure the incongruous image of Leonardo DiCaprio cavorting with Cate Blanchett in ''The Aviator'' -- the audacity of Mr. Irving's stunt still has the power to astonish. How could he have expected to get away with counterfeiting the life of a living person, especially somebody widely thought to be paranoid, ruthless and more powerful than the government? Lasse Hallstrom's briskly entertaining new film, ''The Hoax,'' proposes a few intriguing hypotheses.</p>
        <p>The most obvious answer is that the scam was born out of desperation. Mr. Irving, impersonated with hungry, nervous intelligence by a roughed-up, curly-haired Richard Gere, starts out as an ambitious writer who has just seen his big break evaporate. The novel that was going to make his reputation has been summarily killed by the publisher, and to compound the insult Irving has already spent the notional advance on a new Mercedes and a scuba-diving vacation. He has also sworn off philandering, promising to devote himself to his wife, Edith, an artist played by Marcia Gay Harden, sporting a bizarre blond hairdo and an even stranger accent. (Julie Delpy plays the extramarital temptation Irving can't quite shake.)</p>
        <p>The Hughes project is an outrageous bluff that is also, in an odd way, Irving's last shot at going straight. You get the sense that he believes not only that it will succeed, but also that the success will be legitimate, making him the esteemed writer and devoted husband part of him longs to be.</p>
        <p>His sidekick in the enterprise is a nervous, nebbishy researcher named Dick Suskind (Alfred Molina), who is, at first glance, everything Irving is not. Uxorious, clumsy and a terrible liar, he is both Irving's reality check and his enabler: If someone as scrupulous and kind as Dick is in on the plot, then it can't be entirely wrong, can it? And the brilliance of Mr. Gere's performance -- one of his best since middle age liberated his wily charm from his leading-man looks -- is that he makes you believe in Irving without believing a word out of his mouth.</p>
        <p>Early on, his editor (Hope Davis) passes along a comment dismissing his novel as second-rate Philip Roth, and the dropping of that name, along with Norman Mailer's later, points toward the literary company Irving aspires to join. He is a brash, macho hustler whose seriousness of purpose is indistinguishable from his chutzpah. Watching him improvise excuses and balderdash for skeptical publishing executives is like watching a poker player shoving all his chips into the middle of the table over and over again. We can see his cards of course, and it's hard not to root for him to walk away from the table with all the money.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hallstrom, now that he has moved on from the somber duties of spinning middlebrow best sellers into high-toned Oscar bait (''The Shipping News,'' ''The Cider House Rules''), has proven himself to be a nimble filmmaker with a light and subtle touch. His underrated ''Casanova,'' starring Heath Ledger, managed to be both farcical and subtle, and ''The Hoax,'' with an excellent script by William Wheeler, achieves a similar complexity of tone. It is for the most part a jumpy, suspenseful caper, full of narrow escapes, improbable reversals and complicated intrigue. But it has a sinister, shadowy undertow, an intimation of dread that lingers after Irving's game is up.</p>
        <p>Some of the shadow is cast by Hughes himself, who appears in old tape recordings and film clips and also in Irving's creepy impersonations. As he sinks deeper into the autobiography, Irving conducts mock interviews with his subject, for which he puts on a thin mustache and a Texan drawl. At moments he seems to cross the line that separates deception from self-delusion. It's not quite that Irving believes Hughes is cooperating; rather, he thinks he understands Hughes so well that the latter's silence is a form of tacit approval.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gere's Clifford Irving, a charlatan and a fool, is also an innocent, blundering into something far bigger and darker than his talent or imagination can contain. Like ''Zodiac,'' another true story set in roughly the same period, ''The Hoax'' gestures beyond the particulars of its case toward a pervasive social unease, a sense of ambient danger and disorder that has no clear source or antidote.</p>
        <p>The specter of Watergate hovers over Mr. Hallstrom's picture, which hints at a sticky web of malfeasance and manipulation connecting Hughes with Richard M. Nixon. Irving, for all his big, bragging ambition, turns out to be small fry after all, a petty con man who stumbles into a much bigger game, one where liars are rarely caught, and the really consequential frauds are never fully exposed.</p>
        <p>''The Hoax'' is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has profanity and some nudity.</p>
        <p>The Hoax  Opens today nationwide.</p>
        <p>Directed by Lasse Hallstrom; written by William Wheeler, based on the book by Clifford Irving; director of photography, Oliver Stapleton; edited by Andrew Mondshein; music by Carter Burwell; production designer, Mark Ricker; produced by Mark Gordon, Leslie Holleran, Joshua D. Maurer, Betsy Beers and Bob Yari; released by Miramax Films. Running time: 115 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Richard Gere (Clifford Irving), Alfred Molina (Dick Suskind), Marcia Gay Harden (Edith Irving), Hope Davis (Andrea Tate), Julie Delpy (Nina Van Pallandt), Eli Wallach (Noah Dietrich) and Stanley Tucci (Shelton Fisher).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
