<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Hustle, Boston College Earns Trip to Title Game</title>
    <meta content="06hockey" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/sports/hockey/06hockey.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838409"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Michigan State University</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E3DB173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="599" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Hustle, Boston College Earns Trip to Title Game</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With Hustle, Boston College Earns Trip to Title Game</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAT BORZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Borzi, Pat</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS, April 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The puck, cleared the length of the ice by Boston College's Brian Boyle, caromed off the back boards and came to rest to the right of the empty North Dakota net. The Fighting Sioux, already on a power play, had pulled their goalie for a six-on-four advantage to try and tie this Frozen Four semifinal. Certainly, one of them would reach the puck first.</p>
        <p>Instead, the Eagles' senior forward Joe Rooney outraced North Dakota defenseman Brian Lee to score a shorthanded goal with 50 seconds to play. Each team added a goal in the final 16.4 seconds Thursday, but Rooney's hustle proved decisive as the Eagles won a wild one, 6-4, at the Scottrade Center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Michigan State became the first Central Collegiate Hockey Association team to reach the Frozen Four since 2003, and the first in the championship game since Michigan won in 1998.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The puck, cleared the length of the ice by Boston College's Brian Boyle, caromed off the back boards and came to rest to the right of the empty North Dakota net. The Fighting Sioux, already on a power play, had pulled their goalie for a six-on-four advantage to try and tie this Frozen Four semifinal. Certainly, one of them would reach the puck first.</p>
        <p>Instead, the Eagles' senior forward Joe Rooney outraced North Dakota defenseman Brian Lee to score a shorthanded goal with 50 seconds to play. Each team added a goal in the final 16.4 seconds Thursday, but Rooney's hustle proved decisive as the Eagles won a wild one, 6-4, at the Scottrade Center.</p>
        <p>''I never saw Joe skate so fast,'' Boyle said.</p>
        <p>Boston College (29-11-1) will play Michigan State (25-13-3), a 4-2 winner against Maine in an earlier semifinal, for the N.C.A.A. men's hockey title on Saturday night.</p>
        <p>Rooney was surprised he reached the puck first. ''I got to their blue line, and I figured I'd have a couple of guys on me,'' he said. ''I took a look around and didn't see many guys on me, so I knew I had some time.''</p>
        <p>The late flurry finished off a six-goal burst in the final seven minutes. The game was tied, 2-2, when Ben Smith put the Eagles ahead, finishing a three-on-two with a wrist shot off North Dakota goalie Philippe Lamoureux's glove. But with 4 minutes 38 seconds left and the Eagles on a power play, North Dakota's T. J. Oshie stole a pass from Benn Ferriero behind the Eagles' net and backhanded it top-shelf.</p>
        <p>Thirty-two seconds later, Nathan Gerbe restored the lead with Boston College's third power-play goal of the game.</p>
        <p>Though Rooney's goal was a stunner, North Dakota (24-14-5) kept working the power play, and Chris Porter, the team's captain, redirected a shot by Oshie with 16.4 seconds to play. Gerbe scored into an empty net for Boston College's final goal.</p>
        <p>Michigan State eagerly awaited its semifinal against Maine (23-15-2) for almost two weeks. Last year, the Black Bears knocked the Spartans out of the N.C.A.A. tournament in a regional final, jumping to a three-goal lead before holding on to win by one.</p>
        <p>Thursday's game started out like a repeat performance, with Maine's Keith Johnson scoring 23 seconds into the game, and Josh Soares adding another after 3:24. ''Two weeks of preparation out the window,'' Michigan State Coach Rick Comley said.</p>
        <p>When the Spartans' standout goalie, Jeff Lerg, turned to see Soares's shot go in, he extended his arms and looked up in a gesture of disgust. ''For a second, I thought back to last year and said, How do we stop them?'' Lerg said. ''I just kind of shrugged it off. I knew I had to shut the door or we'd be in trouble.''</p>
        <p>Lerg, an acrobatic 5-foot-6 sophomore, did just that, finishing with 29 saves. As Maine goalie Ben Bishop said, ''He did not give us another chance the rest of the game.''</p>
        <p>Chris Mueller, a junior center, had a goal and an assist for the Spartans. Mueller's goal, 7:25 into the first period, helped Michigan State regroup. Mueller batted a rebound of his own shot out of the air past the 6-foot-7 Bishop.</p>
        <p>In the third period, Mueller contributed to another odd goal, flipping a puck toward the net that Jim McKenzie tapped in.</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>Maine Coach Tim Whitehead's mother-in-law, Debra Smith, was killed in an auto accident Thursday morning near Springfield, Ohio, while en route to the game, a university official said. She was 57.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
