<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Their Best, Knicks Weren't Good Enough</title>
    <meta content="06knicks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/sports/basketball/06knicks.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838345"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Thomas, Isiah</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Robinson, Nate</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Marbury, Stephon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E0DD173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="882" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Their Best, Knicks Weren't Good Enough</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At Their Best, Knicks Weren’t Good Enough</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beck, Howard</byline>
      <dateline>GREENBURGH, N.Y., April 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Throughout the Knicks' early trials and their many, many stumbles, Isiah Thomas maintained an air of patience and calm. There was, he reasoned, another game, another week, another month to make things right.</p>
        <p>The Knicks' 43rd loss might have finally shredded that mental security blanket. They are two and a half games out of a playoff spot with eight games left. Their injured starters are not coming back to save them. The season is nearly lost.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At their best this season, the Knicks were merely a .500 team. The late-season injuries, and the resulting swoon, highlight their failure to capitalize when the roster was whole.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Throughout the Knicks' early trials and their many, many stumbles, Isiah Thomas maintained an air of patience and calm. There was, he reasoned, another game, another week, another month to make things right.</p>
        <p>The Knicks' 43rd loss might have finally shredded that mental security blanket. They are two and a half games out of a playoff spot with eight games left. Their injured starters are not coming back to save them. The season is nearly lost.</p>
        <p>''I went home last night and I had a long drive,'' Thomas, the Knicks' coach, said Thursday, reflecting on Wednesday's 92-90 loss to Philadelphia. ''I didn't sleep much.''</p>
        <p>Instead, he reviewed game film until about 4:30 a.m. It was at that point, Thomas said, that he found some comfort, concluding: ''These guys have given everything they got. Now, they may not be doing everything right, but effort, energy-wise, they're giving it.''</p>
        <p>The mistakes seem more forgivable now because the Knicks (31-43) are relying heavily on two rookies (Renaldo Balkman and Mardy Collins), two second-year players (Channing Frye and Nate Robinson), a banged-up star guard (Stephon Marbury) and a newly anointed franchise center (Eddy Curry) who has played 2,569 minutes -- 400 more than his previous career high.</p>
        <p>These are not the same Knicks who went 19-16 from Dec. 18 to March 3 and inspired visions of a playoff run. They are not even the same Knicks who momentarily occupied eighth place in the Eastern Conference a month ago.</p>
        <p>In his weaker moments, Thomas admits to pining for Jamal Crawford's clutch shooting, Quentin Richardson's know-how and David Lee's hustle. The Knicks are 6-12 since Lee injured his right leg, 5-11 since Crawford was lost to an ankle injury and 3-9 since Richardson's back flared up.</p>
        <p>Thomas, fantasizing about a rotation that still included them, said, ''We'd have 102 every night, and a lot of these games wouldn't have been close.''</p>
        <p>Crawford guessed that the Knicks would have 36 to 37 victories by now -- enough to place them seventh in the conference. The final weeks will be filled with such what-ifs and might-have-beens.</p>
        <p>Yet the angst of April may have less to do with the injuries of March than with the pratfalls of January and February. The lineup was rarely whole this season. But when it was, the Knicks often squandered opportunities -- losing games they should have won, stumbling in the final minutes of close games and generally following every victory with a loss.</p>
        <p>At their best this season, the Knicks were merely a .500 team, going 13-13 in January and February. The late-season injuries, and the resulting swoon, highlight their failure to capitalize when the roster was whole.</p>
        <p>''You just want to get every win possible, because you never know,'' the veteran forward Malik Rose said. ''We had chances this season that we didn't take full advantage of. Some of them were heartbreakers that we tried our hardest and just got beat. There were others we just let slip away, and we're really paying the price for it now.''</p>
        <p>A number of missed opportunities come to mind. In mid-January, the Knicks lost consecutive games in the final seconds -- to Washington (on a dunk by Caron Butler with 2.2 seconds left) and to the Nets (on a put-back by Clifford Robinson with 2.8 seconds left). On Feb. 10, they lost to Utah when Derek Fisher made a layup with 3.6 seconds left in overtime. On March 6, they lost by a point to Seattle when Marbury missed a free throw with 0.9 seconds left. Last weekend, the Knicks fell to Dallas when Marbury missed a shot at the buzzer, and to the Hornets in overtime.</p>
        <p>Rose pointed to a loss to Atlanta in the Knicks' second game, and a blowout loss to the Warriors on Feb. 14, when, as he said, ''We kind of packed it in the night before the All-Star break.''</p>
        <p>''There were probably 10 other games that we can say we had, that we let get away,'' Rose said. ''And maybe those games would have been a cushion for us trying to get to our goal.''</p>
        <p>Then there are the games the Knicks -- presuming they were worthy of making the playoffs -- should have won. They have gone 16-26 against teams under .500 and 3-10 against the weak Atlantic Division. In the past month, the Knicks lost home games to Seattle (30-45), New Orleans (35-40), Portland (30-44), Orlando (34-41) and Philadelphia (30-44).</p>
        <p>A more seasoned team might have grasped the importance of those games. The Knicks -- who still commit too many turnovers and miss too many free throws -- might have learned their lesson too late. They failed to win when they had their best players on the court and now have no room for error while their youngest players try to save the season.</p>
        <p>''You never appreciate the sunshine until you're in a rainstorm,'' Rose said. ''Those young guys, they're seeing what it is we were talking about.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>Although he suited up for Wednesday's game, David Lee is not ready to play a significant role, Coach Isiah Thomas said. Lee was placed on the active roster at the last minute, after Kelvin Cato went home sick. Thomas said that he would have used Lee only in an emergency. Lee avoided reporters Thursday.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
