<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rangers Head to Playoffs on Wave of Inspiration</title>
    <meta content="06rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/sports/hockey/06rangers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070410T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838411"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Montreal Canadiens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Montreal Canadiens</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Lundqvist, Henrik</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E3DB173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="905" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rangers Head to Playoffs on Wave of Inspiration</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rangers Head to Playoffs on Wave of Inspiration</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinser, Lynn</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The stage had been set for the Rangers so fittingly last night: the chance to clinch a playoff berth at Madison Square Garden, to culminate a grueling climb into contention after a struggle-filled season. They had an adoring crowd, an inspiring challenge by a police officer paralyzed in the line of duty and an opportunity to write their own story.</p>
        <p>That the Rangers rose to the occasion as resoundingly as they did in a 3-1 victory against Montreal said a lot about the team they have become: a far grittier one than started the season believing a repeat of last year's playoff appearance would come fairly easy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The victory capped a determined late-season run by the Rangers and turned a once-moribund season into a berth in the playoffs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The stage had been set for the Rangers so fittingly last night: the chance to clinch a playoff berth at Madison Square Garden, to culminate a grueling climb into contention after a struggle-filled season. They had an adoring crowd, an inspiring challenge by a police officer paralyzed in the line of duty and an opportunity to write their own story.</p>
        <p>That the Rangers rose to the occasion as resoundingly as they did in a 3-1 victory against Montreal said a lot about the team they have become: a far grittier one than started the season believing a repeat of last year's playoff appearance would come fairly easy.</p>
        <p>''If you look at it, we had a tough time the first 40-50 games,'' forward Jaromir Jagr said. ''Not many people believed we could do it after the All-Star break. It was tough. We had to win a lot of games to make it. Once you make it, you never know what's going to happen.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers not only clinched a playoff berth, they gave themselves an opportunity to finish as high as sixth place, which they currently occupy, a point ahead of Tampa Bay. They lifted their record to 42-29-10 and their 93 points and victory total mean they can finish no lower than seventh. The Rangers finish the regular season tomorrow night at Pittsburgh. If they finish sixth, their first-round opponent would probably be Atlanta. Seventh brings them a rematch of last year's first-round loss to the Devils.</p>
        <p>But for a night, the Rangers could enjoy getting there. It came in an emotional final regular-season home game. The Garden crowd was already fired up when Steven McDonald took the ice in his wheelchair and uniform to present the Extra Effort award named after him and given annually. McDonald announced forward Jed Ortmeyer as the winner, then described a night in a hospital room 20 years ago when several Rangers came to visit him after he had been shot. ''They left me with a challenge: live,'' he said to a hushed crowd. ''Tonight, I'm leaving them with a challenge: win.''</p>
        <p>The ensuing roar took on a new feeling.</p>
        <p>''I don't know if any human being on this planet could have inspired us any more than Steven McDonald,'' Rangers Coach Tom Renney said.</p>
        <p>The Rangers took control with a goal from forward Petr Prucha less than three minutes in. Jagr tacked on a goal midway through the second period and defenseman Marek Malik scored the unlikeliest goal -- only his second of the season -- when Sean Avery kicked him the puck and he blasted in a slap shot with 1 minute 34 seconds left in the second.</p>
        <p>From there, the Rangers clamped down, giving up only a 5-on-3 power-play goal with 4:43 left to defenseman Sheldon Souray, before beginning their celebration.</p>
        <p>Montreal (42-33-6) is also fighting for its playoff fate, holding eighth place with one game remaining, at Toronto tomorrow.</p>
        <p>''We didn't have the urgency in our game early as well as the desperation we have been playing with the last few weeks,'' Souray said.</p>
        <p>Perhaps, though, Montreal merely ran into a team that has been living in urgency and desperation for the past month. The Rangers were in 11th place in the Eastern Conference in early March when they rallied against St. Louis at home to start a 12-2-2 stretch that has carried them to sixth place.</p>
        <p>They have gotten stellar play from goalie Henrik Lundqvist and a renewed commitment to team defense.</p>
        <p>''That's the reason we are in the playoffs,'' center Blair Betts said. ''We have been great defensively. We have been putting less pressure on our goaltender and he has been coming up big when we need him.''</p>
        <p>Betts and Lundqvist combined for the biggest defensive play in this game, with 4:14 left in the second and the Rangers holding a 2-0 lead. Lundqvist stopped one shot, but the Montreal captain Saku Koivu had another shot with Lundqvist still down. Betts' stick was broken -- a penalty that would be called -- but he still thrust it at Koivu's stick, getting enough of the shot to send the puck trickling wide. The Rangers killed the power play and Malik's goal sealed the victory.</p>
        <p>It is that kind of play that gives the Rangers confidence that they are heading into this year's playoffs stronger this year. Last year, they lost the last five games of the season and lost the division on the last day to the Devils, who swept them in the first round.</p>
        <p>''What we've got going for us is some momentum,'' Renney said. ''We've got enough reference points of what good hockey looks like that we didn't have a year ago. I think we're a little more intelligent. We were committed last year, but I think this year we understand what commitment is going to involve.''</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>Jed Ortmeyer was named the Steven McDonald Extra Effort Award winner before the game, an award voted on by Rangers fans. Ortmeyer was found to have a pulmonary embolism in August and missed the first 40 games. He became a huge contributor.  The Rangers announced that a limited number of individual playoff tickets will go on sale Tuesday at noon via Ticketmaster, at newyorkrangers.com and Ticketmaster charge-by-phone at (212) 307-7171. A person may buy no more than four tickets, in any combination, for the six potential home games during the first two rounds.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 10, 2007, Tuesday  A sports article in some copies on Friday about the Rangers' 3-1 victory against the Montreal Canadiens referred imprecisely to the Rangers' point total and advantage over Tampa Bay in the N.H.L.'s Eastern Conference standings. The Rangers had 94 points, not 93, after that game and were ahead of Tampa Bay by 2 points, not 1. (The Rangers subsequently finished the regular season with 94 points, 1 point ahead of Tampa Bay.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 10, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A sports article in some copies on Friday about the Rangers' 3-1 victory against the Montreal Canadiens referred imprecisely to the Rangers' point total and advantage over Tampa Bay in the N.H.L.'s Eastern Conference standings. The Rangers had 94 points, not 93, after that game and were ahead of Tampa Bay by 2 points, not 1. (The Rangers subsequently finished the regular season with 94 points, 1 point ahead of Tampa Bay.)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
