<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>None Hurt, and Another Tale Added, in Collapse at Storied Village Bar</title>
    <meta content="06wall" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/nyregion/06wall.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070411T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838367"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chumley's (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Trymaine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Greenwich Village (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E1DC173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="634" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>None Hurt, and Another Tale Added, in Collapse at Storied Village Bar</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">None Hurt, and Another Tale Added, in Collapse at Storied Village Bar</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRYMAINE LEE; Steven McElroy and Colin Moynihan contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Trymaine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Part of wall collapses at Chumley's, popular Greenwich Village restaurant and onetime speakeasy; building will be closed indefinitely; three adjoining buildings are evacuated; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Part of a wall collapsed yesterday in a popular Greenwich Village restaurant and onetime speakeasy where literary giants like John Steinbeck and F. Scott Fitzgerald once gathered.</p>
        <p>Officials in the Fire and Buildings Departments said workers were repairing a wall at the restaurant, Chumley's, when an attached chimney collapsed about 1 p.m. No one was injured.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Part of a wall collapsed yesterday in a popular Greenwich Village restaurant and onetime speakeasy where literary giants like John Steinbeck and F. Scott Fitzgerald once gathered.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Part of a wall collapsed yesterday in a popular Greenwich Village restaurant and onetime speakeasy where literary giants like John Steinbeck and F. Scott Fitzgerald once gathered.</p>
        <p>Officials in the Fire and Buildings Departments said workers were repairing a wall at the restaurant, Chumley's, when an attached chimney collapsed about 1 p.m. No one was injured.</p>
        <p>Fire officials said the building, at 86 Bedford Street, would be closed indefinitely, until the wall was stabilized.</p>
        <p>The collapse forced the evacuation of three adjoining buildings. Residents of 10 apartments in them were affected, the Red Cross said.</p>
        <p>Chumley's and the other affected buildings -- at 82 Bedford Street and 56 and 58 Barrow Street -- form a horseshoe with a common courtyard.</p>
        <p>Not long after the collapse, neighbors gathered outside the bar and talked about the good times they had had there. Some spoke of an old dog that used to lie on the barroom floor, indifferent to the patrons laughing loudly or tossing back mugs of beer.</p>
        <p>Snowflakes fell upon the old speakeasy as firefighters stood staring into its now dusty guts.</p>
        <p>''That wall is in trouble,'' said Chief Jay Jonas of the Fire Department. ''It's unstable.'' He then smiled a bit, reminiscing on Chumley's fabled past.</p>
        <p>Leleand Chumley opened his speakeasy in 1922, replete with secret passageways and back-alley entrances. To this day, the bar has no sign.</p>
        <p>Like any decent speakeasy, Chumley's used its sneaky escape routes in case the police made one of their regular visits to enforce Prohibition.</p>
        <p>One of those escape routes, a fake bookcase in the front of the bar that opens out onto an alley, is still functional, although these days, the only people sneaking in and out are the waiters and waitresses who use it as a quick route between the front of the bar and the kitchen in the back.</p>
        <p>But Chumley's has legend and myth and a history as its fingerprint. Luminaries like E. E. Cummings and Willa Cather spent time on stools at Chumley's, as did Allen Ginsberg and Norman Mailer and other writers -- their marks remembered in the dust jackets from hundreds of their books that still line the walls.</p>
        <p>And there's also the occasional literary or drinking tours that visits the bar to soak up both literary history and suds.</p>
        <p>Large photos of some of Chumley's favorite patrons, including Ring Lardner and Eugene O'Neill, grace its walls like grainy ghosts from a bygone era. But yesterday, Chumley's looked more like a rebel in the winter of its life, an aging, hunched old man, than the spirited character it has been known as.</p>
        <p>Several tourists, shifting their gaze from pocket maps to the scene on the other side of the yellow tape and back to the maps, asked for directions to Chumley's.</p>
        <p>One visitor who needed no map was Tom Copeland, a photographer from Greensboro, N. C., who was on vacation with his family. He stood opposite Chumley's, his wife, Llewellyn, and his twins, Callie and Graham, 8, a few feet behind him.</p>
        <p>''I've been telling my wife and kids about this place,'' he said. ''The beer is great, and that old dog on the ground just lying there.''</p>
        <p>He reached into his pocket, still smiling, still disappointed, pulling out a piece of paper torn from a notepad. ''This,'' he said, ''was our itinerary:''</p>
        <p>9 a.m.: movies.</p>
        <p>10 a.m.: Macy's and Rockefeller Center</p>
        <p>12 noon: Central Park.</p>
        <p>5 p.m.: Chumley's</p>
        <p>Don Silva, an actor who lives nearby, described a series of occurrences over the last few months involving construction. He said that last May, nine people were evacuated after workers removing part of a fireplace at 82 Bedford Street caused structural damage, and seven or eight people left after a similar incident not long afterward.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 11, 2007, Wednesday  An article on Friday about the partial collapse of a wall at Chumley's, a popular Greenwich Village bar and restaurant, misspelled the given name of the original owner. He was Leland Chumley, not Leleand, and was known as Lee.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 11, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article on Friday about the partial collapse of a wall at Chumley's, a popular Greenwich Village bar and restaurant, misspelled the given name of the original owner. He was Leland Chumley, not Leleand, and was known as Lee.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
