<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Islanders Win and Keep Postseason Hopes Alive</title>
    <meta content="06islanders" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/sports/hockey/06islanders.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838410"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Toronto Maple Leafs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Islanders</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Blake, Jason</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E3DB173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="613" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Islanders Win and Keep Postseason Hopes Alive</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Islanders Win and Keep Postseason Hopes Alive</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONDALE, N.Y., April 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As distasteful as it seemed to be to their fans, the Islanders needed help from the Rangers on Thursday to even keep thinking about the playoffs. But the Islanders also needed to win, and that would turn out to be the hard part.</p>
        <p>Only 94 seconds after the Toronto Maple Leafs scored a tying goal that seemed to suck the air out of Nassau Coliseum, Jason Blake scored his 40th goal early in the third period, and the Islanders rolled to a 5-2 victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Islanders remained eligible to make the playoffs because they won their second consecutive game and the Rangers defeated Montreal, 3-1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As distasteful as it seemed to be to their fans, the Islanders needed help from the Rangers on Thursday to even keep thinking about the playoffs. But the Islanders also needed to win, and that would turn out to be the hard part.</p>
        <p>Only 94 seconds after the Toronto Maple Leafs scored a tying goal that seemed to suck the air out of Nassau Coliseum, Jason Blake scored his 40th goal early in the third period, and the Islanders rolled to a 5-2 victory.</p>
        <p>''If we don't take care of business, nothing else matters,'' Islanders Coach Ted Nolan said.</p>
        <p>The Islanders (38-30-12), who play Saturday at Philadelphia and end their regular season Sunday at Continental Arena against the Devils, remained eligible to make the playoffs because they won their second consecutive game and the Rangers defeated Montreal, 3-1.</p>
        <p>The Islanders cannot afford to lose either of their remaining games. But their chances of gaining the final playoff spot in the Eastern Conference are not so far-fetched. If they win both games, and Montreal (42-33-6) loses to Toronto on Saturday, the Islanders will make the playoffs.</p>
        <p>''We're alive for another day, and that's good stuff,'' said Islanders center Mike Sillinger, who scored a critical power-play goal and centered a line that shut down the Toronto line centered by Mats Sundin.</p>
        <p>Blake scored the Islanders' biggest goal of the season at 3 minutes 46 seconds of the third period by chasing down a loose puck, looping nearly to the blue line, then firing a wrist shot through a group of players and past Toronto goaltender Andrew Raycroft.</p>
        <p>Eight minutes later, Arron Asham scored his 11th goal on a slap shot that sped over Raycroft's left shoulder, and Miroslav Satan swept in an empty-net goal with 1:55 left to polish off the Maple Leafs (39-31-11), who are 1 point behind eighth-place Montreal.</p>
        <p>Wade Dubielewicz, who spent most of this season in the minor leagues, stopped 28 of 30 shots in his third consecutive start in goal in place of Rick DiPietro, who is out indefinitely with a concussion.</p>
        <p>Dubielewicz chastised himself for defenseman Carlo Colaiacovo's goal that tied the score at 2-2 at 2:12 of the third period. The shot was deflected by Islanders defenseman Chris Campoli, but Dubielewicz said he should have stopped it.</p>
        <p>''But we took a step in the right direction and played a little better,'' Dubielewicz said.</p>
        <p>The Islanders took a 1-0 lead at 16:57 of the first period on Ryan Smyth's 36th goal. It was Smyth's fourth goal in 16 games since he was acquired Feb. 27 from Edmonton.</p>
        <p>Toronto's John Pohl wiped out the lead with a second-period goal.</p>
        <p>With about a minute and a half left in the second, Maple Leafs defenseman Hal Gill tripped Blake behind the goal line, and the crowd cheered the Islanders' first power play. A minute into the power play, with the fans losing patience, Islanders defenseman Tom Poti slid a long pass from the point to Trent Hunter at the goal line. Hunter fed Sillinger, crossing the slot diagonally, and he gave the Islanders a 2-1 lead with his 26th goal.</p>
        <p>''I've got to give our team credit,'' Sillinger said. ''The last couple of games, we've buckled down.''</p>
        <p>Colaiacovo matched Sillinger's goal less than three minutes later. But Sillinger's line, which included Smyth on the left wing and Hunter on the right wing, continued hounding Sundin's line, and Blake started the Islanders' scoring surge.</p>
        <p>And the Rangers won, which was a good thing on Long Island.</p>
        <p>''The Rangers did a great job tonight -- played a great game,'' Nolan said, smiling. ''Now, I hope Toronto plays a great game against Montreal.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
