<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>American Express Gets Specific And Asks, 'Are You a Cardmember?'</title>
    <meta content="06adco" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/business/media/06adco.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838328"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit and Money Cards</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Express Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ogilvy &amp; Mather</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Credit and Money Cards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit and Money Cards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">American Express Company</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Ogilvy &amp; Mather</org>
        <org class="online_producer">WPP Group Plc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE6DD173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="985" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>American Express Gets Specific And Asks, 'Are You a Cardmember?'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">American Express Gets Specific and Asks, ‘Are You a Cardmember?’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STUART ELLIOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American Express Co changes its theme dropping 'My life. My card' slogan for 'Are you a cardmember?'; new inquisitive theme will be centerpiece of multimedia campaign with budget estimated at $400 million to $500 million; creator is longtime American Express agency Ogilvy &amp; Mather; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AMERICAN EXPRESS has decided there is no more life left in ''My life. My card.''</p>
        <p>The theme, appearing in ads for American Express charge cards since November 2004, is being supplanted, beginning Monday, with a campaign that replaces a general, image-oriented approach with a specific, product-focused tack.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>American Express is supplanting its “My life” theme with a specific, product-focused tack embodied by a rhetorical question.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AMERICAN EXPRESS has decided there is no more life left in ''My life. My card.''</p>
        <p>The theme, appearing in ads for American Express charge cards since November 2004, is being supplanted, beginning Monday, with a campaign that replaces a general, image-oriented approach with a specific, product-focused tack.</p>
        <p>The change is embodied by a rhetorical question, ''Are you a cardmember?'' -- Amex-speak for ''cardholder'' -- which is answered with demonstrations of what American Express believes are the benefits of its charge cards.</p>
        <p>It is unusual for American Express to switch campaign themes so quickly. For instance, according to a chronology provided by the company, ''Do you know me?'' ran from 1974 to 1987; ''Membership has its privileges'' appeared from 1987 to 1996, with a brief interruption; and ''Do more'' ran from 1996 to 2004.</p>
        <p>The new inquisitive theme will be the centerpiece of a multimedia campaign with a budget estimated at $400 million to $500 million. The creator is the longtime American Express agency, Ogilvy &amp; Mather Worldwide in New York, part of the WPP Group.</p>
        <p>The strategy is to convince consumers that there are meaningful advantages to carrying the green, gold, platinum and other colorful charge cards -- even if it means paying fees not assessed for the rival credit cards like Capital One, Discover, MasterCard and Visa.</p>
        <p>The new campaign offers ''more of a call to action,'' said John Hayes, chief marketing officer at the American Express Company in New York.</p>
        <p>For example, the first television commercial shows the snowboarder Shaun White going online again and again to book flights at the last minute, using the points he has accrued with his American Express card.</p>
        <p>The reason for his frenetic travel is a skein of snowstorms that he follows from Utah to Canada to Japan to Norway. ''Pay with points on any airline,'' the spot declares. ''Just click and fly.''</p>
        <p>Mr. White will also be featured on the American Express Web site (americanexpress.com). ''I need to be able to travel where I want, when I want,'' he will proclaim there.</p>
        <p>The specificity is in sharp contrast to the ethereal tenor of the ''My life'' campaign. Those ads featured celebrities like Robert De Niro, Ellen DeGeneres, the director M. Night Shyamalan and the surfer Laird Hamilton discussing their philosophies of living; Ms. DeGeneres also performed humorous skits with animals.</p>
        <p>The ''My life'' campaign ''really wasn't working,'' said Robert K. Passikoff, president at Brand Keys, a research company in New York that studies brand and customer loyalty.</p>
        <p>In 1997, the American Express brand was first in the category of charge and credit cards in the Brand Keys customer loyalty index, Mr. Passikoff said, but fell in the 2007 survey to fifth, trailing (in order) Discover, Capital One, Visa and MasterCard.</p>
        <p>American Express ''still has brand resonance,'' Mr. Passikoff said, ''but it has not been engaging consumer loyalty.''</p>
        <p>''Entertainment is not the same as engagement,'' he added. ''People looked at the Ellen DeGeneres commercials and said, 'This is the funniest thing, so clever.' And then they pulled out their Visa card.''</p>
        <p>Needless to say, executives at American Express take issue with that analysis. They provided data showing that the number of consumer cards in force last year, both in the United States and worldwide, increased from 2005, as did spending.</p>
        <p>''We do believe this brand is defined by the people who use and carry the card,'' said Diego Scotti, global head of marketing at American Express, and the ''My life'' campaign ''worked well in getting people to say, 'I want to be part of this group,' '' referring to the celebrities.</p>
        <p>''Now, we want to go into more depth about what you get out of membership,'' Mr. Scotti said. ''What has changed is the stories they tell will be connected to product, in an authentic way.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hayes said that the ''My life'' campaign ''has done a great job redefining the notion of membership'' as well as reminding consumers that ''American Express is a company, not just about transactions, but about relationships.''</p>
        <p>''We want now to include more and more prospects,'' Mr. Hayes said, referring to potential cardholders, ''and take 'My life. My card' to a broader audience.''</p>
        <p>That makes sense because credit card issuers, particularly MasterCard and Visa, are stepping up offers of rewards and perquisites. For example, a campaign for the Visa Signature credit card, aimed at upper-income consumers, promises it ''takes you places regular rewards cards can't, like a finish-line suite at Churchill Downs.''</p>
        <p>The arms race over rewards is intensifying because ''high spenders are very profitable'' for issuers of credit and charge cards, said Scott Henry, engagement manager at Fischer Jordan in New York, a consulting company.</p>
        <p>''We're seeing rewards programs as the primary differentiator between issuers,'' Mr. Henry said, which means that if ''Visa is chasing after the more premium market, they have to add more perks like American Express has'' -- or vice versa.</p>
        <p>For some time, the marketing battle was centered on what Mr. Henry called ''the earn rates and burn rates,'' that is, how easy (or hard) it is to earn rewards and how easy (or hard) it is to redeem them.</p>
        <p>More recently, ''experiential rewards are definitely something that are differentiating the rewards programs,'' he added, referring to less-tangible perks like being taken backstage at a concert to meet the band or being assured of great seats for a hit Broadway show.</p>
        <p>The last time American Express replaced an ad theme so quickly was 15 years ago, in a change omitted from the chronology provided by the company.</p>
        <p>In November 1991, American Express replaced Ogilvy with a New York agency known as Chiat/Day/Mojo and dropped ''Membership has its privileges'' in favor of a theme that sounded as if James Bond had written it: ''The card. The American Express card.''</p>
        <p>Eleven months later, Chiat/Day/Mojo was dismissed, the account was returned to Ogilvy and ''Membership has its privileges'' resumed its run.</p>
        <p>ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
