<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Full Career Of Cases, A Reputation For Diligence</title>
    <meta content="06agent" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/nyregion/06agent.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838379"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AN AGENT FALLS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bank Robberies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Readington (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nairobi (Kenya)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Amherst (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pnc Bank</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United States Foreign Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cruz, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berrios, Wilfredo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herrera-Genao, Francisco J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slepian, Barnett A (1947-98)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kopp, James C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fahim, Kareem</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Richard G</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Kenya/Nairobi</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E0DC173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="675" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Full Career Of Cases, A Reputation For Diligence</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Full Career of Cases, a Reputation for Diligence</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD G. JONES and KAREEM FAHIM; Nate Schweber contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fahim, Kareem; Jones, Richard G</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Barry Lee Bush, FBI agent accidentally shot to death while pursuing three bank robbery suspects in rural New Jersey, was with bureau for almost 20 years and is recalled by colleagues as dedicated agent known for his attention to detail; investigated 1998 bombing of US Embassy in Nairobi, Kenya, and played important role in solving murder of upstate New York obstetrician who was shot and killed by opponent of abortion (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his F.B.I. career of almost 20 years, Agent Barry Lee Bush led an evidence-collection team that investigated the 1998 bombing of the United States Embassy in Nairobi, Kenya.</p>
        <p>He also played an important role in solving the murder of an upstate New York obstetrician who was shot and killed by an opponent of abortion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Colleagues of Agent Barry Lee Bush, 52, recalled him as a dedicated agent known for his attention to detail.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his F.B.I. career of almost 20 years, Agent Barry Lee Bush led an evidence-collection team that investigated the 1998 bombing of the United States Embassy in Nairobi, Kenya.</p>
        <p>He also played an important role in solving the murder of an upstate New York obstetrician who was shot and killed by an opponent of abortion.</p>
        <p>Agent Bush, 52, was killed yesterday, apparently when a fellow agent's weapon accidentally discharged during a confrontation with gunmen outside a bank in central New Jersey, authorities said. Hours later, his colleagues recalled him as a dedicated agent known for his attention to detail.</p>
        <p>In 1998, Agent Bush helped solve the killing of Dr. Barnett A. Slepian, the Buffalo-area obstetrician who was killed by a sniper opposed to abortion.</p>
        <p>Agent Bush, while searching the home of the prime suspect in the case, James C. Kopp, found a notebook on a closet shelf. In it was the name Barnett and a telephone number for the doctor's office in Amherst, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Larry Wack, who worked on the Kopp case with Agent Bush, described the discovery of the notebook as a significant break in the case.</p>
        <p>''Oh boy, he played a very significant role in the investigation,'' said Mr. Wack, who is now retired. ''I'm in shock. The only thing I can tell you right now is he was a stand-up guy and a hell of an investigator. Incredibly dedicated.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wack noted that Agent Bush was just five years away from reaching the F.B.I.'s mandatory retirement age of 57. ''He was almost up,'' Mr. Wack said.</p>
        <p>Agent Bush joined the Federal Bureau of Investigation in 1987, working in its office in Kansas City, Mo. He transferred to Newark in 1991. A resident of Easton, Pa., Mr. Bush is survived by his wife, a son and a daughter.</p>
        <p>More than a dozen friends and neighbors gathered last night at the Bushes' two-story home in Easton, where nearly a dozen police cars with lights blazing were parked out front. Several neighbors wept openly as they walked away.</p>
        <p>Ron Skrzyniarz, 52, who lived two doors from the Bush family, recalled that Agent Bush spent summer afternoons digging in his garden and summer evenings strolling through the neighborhood with his wife.</p>
        <p>He was known to play host to boisterous barbecues when his spacious yard would fill up with children.</p>
        <p>Though he never talked about his job, Mr. Skrzyniarz said, ''everyone on the block knew he worked for the F.B.I.''</p>
        <p>Interviews with colleagues, court documents and newspaper accounts show that Agent Bush was present at some of the bureau's most prominent cases, and ones that hardly drew notice.</p>
        <p>In March 2001, Agent Bush, then a 13-year veteran of the bureau and the leader of an evidence collection team based in Newark, testified in Federal District Court in Manhattan about his techniques in searching a crime scene.</p>
        <p>Answering questions from the prosecutor, Patrick J. Fitzgerald, he described his work inspecting the area around the embassy in Nairobi, Kenya, where 213 people were killed on Aug. 7, 1998, and at least one other building.</p>
        <p>He arrived six days after the bombing, and he and Sammy Wakesa, an inspector with the Kenyan National Police, worked through a two-story building, he told the prosecutor. Agent Bush, along with a colleague, prepared a sketch of a building in Nairobi.</p>
        <p>''On any crime scene sketch, I generally designate a separate letter for each room that is involved in the search, and that way we are able to track what evidence comes from each room,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Less than a year later, Agent Bush was doing a more everyday brand of law enforcement, tracking down bank robbers. In 2002, his name and contact information appeared next to the number for the police in local New Jersey newspapers about small-time bank robberies.</p>
        <p>When he was killed yesterday, Agent Bush and his colleagues were part of a joint investigation in which they worked with the New Jersey State Police and the Middlesex County prosecutor's office.</p>
        <p>AN AGENT FALLS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
