<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Parent of Airbus Appoints a Board Member to Be Its German Co-Chairman</title>
    <meta content="06eads" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/business/worldbusiness/06eads.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838330"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Aeronautic Defense and Space Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Airbus Industrie</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grube, Rudiger</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bischoff, Manfred</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clark, Nicola</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">European Aeronautic Defense and Space</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bischoff, Manfred</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5DD173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="445" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Parent of Airbus Appoints a Board Member to Be Its German Co-Chairman</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Parent of Airbus Appoints a Board Member to Be Its German Co-Chairman</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICOLA CLARK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clark, Nicola</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, April 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>European Aeronautic Defense and Space Co names new German co-chairman Rudiger Grube, tapping longtime aerospace engineer who also played central role in conceiving group's delicate management structure; Grube succeeds Manfred Bischoff; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The European Aeronautic Defense and Space Company named a new German co-chairman Thursday, tapping a longtime aerospace engineer who also played a central role in conceiving the group's delicate management structure.</p>
        <p>The new executive, Rüdiger Grube, 55, had been widely expected to succeed Manfred Bischoff, who resigned Wednesday after being named chairman of DaimlerChrysler, one of EADS's core industrial shareholders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rudiger Grube, respected for his diplomatic skills and expertise in aerospace engineering, has been selected to help lead EADS.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The European Aeronautic Defense and Space Company named a new German co-chairman Thursday, tapping a longtime aerospace engineer who also played a central role in conceiving the group's delicate management structure.</p>
        <p>The new executive, Rüdiger Grube, 55, had been widely expected to succeed Manfred Bischoff, who resigned Wednesday after being named chairman of DaimlerChrysler, one of EADS's core industrial shareholders.</p>
        <p>Though he has been a member of the EADS board since 2004, Mr. Grube has kept a low public profile throughout a turbulent three years of boardroom power struggles and management fumbles that culminated in a major industrial crisis at Airbus, the group's largest division.</p>
        <p>Current and former colleagues described Mr. Grube as a detail-oriented manager and a skilled communicator, respected as much for his years of aerospace experience as for his reputation for diplomacy.</p>
        <p>''He is very open-minded, but also pragmatic,'' said Jürgen Thomas, a former Airbus head of engineering. Mr. Thomas said that Mr. Grube's personable style and sense of humor would serve him well as EADS steers Airbus through a painful revamping that is expected to result in the loss of 10,000 jobs across Europe over the next four years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Grube has been a trusted lieutenant of Mr. Bischoff since the early 1990s, when both men worked at Daimler-Benz Aerospace, the German company that in 2000 was merged with Aérospatiale Matra of France and Construcciones Aeronáuticas of Spain to form EADS. He was heavily involved in the months of painstaking negotiations that resulted in a controversial dual management structure -- with two chairmen and two chief executives -- aimed at balancing French and German interests.</p>
        <p>Industry analysts have long argued in favor of streamlining EADS's management. Top executives, including the current co-chief executives, Louis Gallois and Thomas O. Enders, also have expressed frustration with the constraints the structure imposes on their authority.</p>
        <p>Most recently, Mr. Grube has been in charge of corporate strategy at DaimlerChrysler and leads the group's operations in China. According to recent media reports, he is leading a team of executives meeting with prospective bidders for Chrysler, the struggling American automaker acquired by Daimler-Benz in 1998.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for DaimlerChrysler declined to comment on Mr. Grube's role in the Chrysler talks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Grube's first challenge over the next two weeks will be to resolve a dispute over a forthcoming capital increase, pitting the group's industrial shareholders against the French government, which owns an indirect 15 percent stake in EADS.</p>
        <p>The French government is thought to prefer to raise the cash through a share sale, while both DaimlerChrysler and Lagardère are arguing in favor of a bond that would be convertible into EADS shares after about five years.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
