<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wind and Fast Greens Get the Better of the Best</title>
    <meta content="06golf" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/sports/golf/06golf.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838413"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Palmer, Arnold</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rose, Justin</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E3DB173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="837" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wind and Fast Greens Get the Better of the Best</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Wind and Fast Greens Get the Better of the Best</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hack, Damon</byline>
      <dateline>AUGUSTA, Ga., April 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a postcard-pretty morning at an old converted nursery, a retired professional golfer walked to the first tee at Augusta National Golf Club and announced that it was a beautiful day. Arnold Palmer reared back, smacked a drive on the screws, and faded into the background of the Masters, leaving 96 players to give their own assessment of a tournament that teases and tempts them so.</p>
        <p>''Hard as I've ever played it,'' said Chris DiMarco, playing in his seventh Masters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Augusta National battered almost everyone and nearly toppled defending Masters champion Phil Mickelson on the first day of play.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a postcard-pretty morning at an old converted nursery, a retired professional golfer walked to the first tee at Augusta National Golf Club and announced that it was a beautiful day. Arnold Palmer reared back, smacked a drive on the screws, and faded into the background of the Masters, leaving 96 players to give their own assessment of a tournament that teases and tempts them so.</p>
        <p>''Hard as I've ever played it,'' said Chris DiMarco, playing in his seventh Masters.</p>
        <p>''It's a bitter golf course,'' said Troy Matteson, playing in his first.</p>
        <p>At the end of an unforgiving first round Thursday that made the best players in the world wobble, Brett Wetterich and Justin Rose each finished at three-under-par 69 to share a one-shot lead over David Toms and David Howell.</p>
        <p>Rich Beem was among five golfers two shots back. Davis Love III headlined a group of five players who trailed by three shots. And Tiger Woods, after making bogey on each of his last two holes, trailed by four shots after a round of one-over-par 73.</p>
        <p>With swirling winds and speedy greens, Augusta National battered almost everyone and nearly toppled Phil Mickelson. He opened with a bogey on his way to a front-nine 40, and shot a 76 to stand seven strokes off the lead in his pursuit to join Jack Nicklaus, Nick Faldo and Woods as back-to-back Masters champions.</p>
        <p>Ernie Els, who wants a Masters title more than any other, shot a 78. Paul Casey of England, a Ryder Cup standout, shot a 79.</p>
        <p>After being slowed by rainy conditions in recent years, Augusta National played hard and fast for a change, with greens that turned potential birdies into bogeys. Balls bounded over mounds, sped over humps, and generally dashed in any direction they pleased. Only two players -- Beem and Howell -- posted eagles on the day.</p>
        <p>''The greens have been firm before, but not like this,'' said Nick O'Hern, who shot a 76. ''A few of the holes, I could not read the greens.''</p>
        <p>Woods, chasing his third consecutive victory at a major, pieced together steady play with a few wild tee shots.</p>
        <p>As his round neared dusk, he missed the fairway on Nos. 17 and 18 to the right, leading to back-to-back bogeys and a frown.</p>
        <p>If it was not the pollen getting him down -- Woods rubbed his nose constantly during the round -- it was his finicky driver. ''I've got to go figure a few things out,'' he said. ''I threw away a good round of golf.''</p>
        <p>Woods, who has never broken 70 in the first round of the Masters, made par on his first six holes before adding a bogey on the seventh. He jumped on the leader board with birdies on the par-5 13th and 15th holes, only to hit drives into pine needles on the final two.</p>
        <p>He found only 7 of Augusta National's 14 fairways, which are among the widest in major championship golf.</p>
        <p>''I just wasn't driving it well,'' he said. ''I wasn't sweeping it very good.''</p>
        <p>Despite his disappointment, Woods's score was topped by only 14 players. The only player immune to the tough conditions was the 77-year-old Palmer, who greeted the day wearing a light-blue sweater, dark trousers, and wielding a golf bag filled with clubs.</p>
        <p>After declining a ceremonial role in recent years, Palmer accepted Augusta National's invitation to become the tournament's honorary starter, who is responsible for hitting a tee shot on the first hole and kindly stepping aside.</p>
        <p>In front of thousands who wrapped themselves around the tee, Palmer stepped up to his ball with a driver and briefly considered making his own rules.</p>
        <p>Why not sneak in a quick 18 holes?</p>
        <p>''Maybe I'll just keep going,'' he said as he waggled his driver.</p>
        <p>He hit a soft draw that traveled more than 200 yards before it settled into the left rough. The crowd erupted in applause, Palmer gave way, and the other golfers held on tight.</p>
        <p>Matteson, a Masters rookie, chunked his approach shot on No. 9 so badly that his ball traveled only halfway to the green. The crowd surrounding the hole let out a gasp. It was one of many on the day.</p>
        <p>''You do this on this golf course,'' said Matteson, who shot a 79. ''It's pretty painful. I hit a lot of bad golf shots. It's going to make for a tough week.''</p>
        <p>Rose was the only golfer who did not make a bogey Thursday. Three years ago, he led the Masters through two rounds before a third-round 81 dropped him from the leader board. He said he had trouble sitting on the lead because he could not find ways to occupy his time before the round.</p>
        <p>On Friday, Rose is scheduled to tee off at 2:14 p.m.</p>
        <p>''I'll probably watch a little bit of 'Little Britain' DVDs, Ali G DVDs, just stuff to occupy your mind, really,'' he said. ''You have to forget about it, reset the dial, and treat tomorrow as a clean slate.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
