<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inside Art</title>
    <meta content="06voge" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/arts/design/06voge.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838254"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Inside Art"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Inside Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Warhol, Andy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E0D8163FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="976" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inside Art</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Fasten Seat Belts for Warhol at Auction</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Carol Vogel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fasten Seat Belts For Warhol at Auction</p>
        <p>Now that Sotheby's has announced plans to auction paintings by Rothko and Bacon in May with estimates that exceed the records for these artists, its archrival, Christie's, says it has a rare Warhol that it also expects to topple the previous record.</p>
        <p>The painting, ''Green Car Crash (Green Burning Car I),'' is part of Warhol's ''Death and Disaster'' series. (In addition to car crashes, he produced Pop images of Jacqueline Kennedy in mourning, as well as electric chairs, riots, suicide and of course bold portraits of Marilyn Monroe made just after her death.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Christie’s expects Andy Warhol’s 1963 painting “Green Car Crash (Green Burning Car I),” based on photos of fatal accidents, to set a record for Warhol at auction.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fasten Seat Belts For Warhol at Auction</p>
        <p>Now that Sotheby's has announced plans to auction paintings by Rothko and Bacon in May with estimates that exceed the records for these artists, its archrival, Christie's, says it has a rare Warhol that it also expects to topple the previous record.</p>
        <p>The painting, ''Green Car Crash (Green Burning Car I),'' is part of Warhol's ''Death and Disaster'' series. (In addition to car crashes, he produced Pop images of Jacqueline Kennedy in mourning, as well as electric chairs, riots, suicide and of course bold portraits of Marilyn Monroe made just after her death.)</p>
        <p>''This painting is in a league of its own,'' said Brett Gorvy, one of the heads of postwar and contemporary art for Christie's worldwide. For ''Death and Disaster'' Warhol drew on six photographs, each documenting a different horrific fatal accident. One of those images was taken from a photo in a 1963 issue of Newsweek that showed a man whose car had crashed, impaling his body on a pole. Warhol used it for five paintings, one of them ''Green Car Crash.'' The other four paintings of the same image evoke black-and-white newsprint. ''Green Car Crash'' is the only one in color. ''Only a handful of the major 'Death and Disaster' paintings are still in private hands,'' Mr. Gorvy said.</p>
        <p>The seller is a European collector, described by Christie's only as ''very private,'' who has owned the painting for more than 30 years. ''In 1964 it was exhibited at the Sonnabend Gallery in Paris, which was Warhol's first major exhibition in Europe,'' Mr. Gorvy said. ''It showed the flip side of what was considered Pop, the underbelly of American life.''</p>
        <p>Christie's estimates the painting will bring $25 million to $35 million, exceeding the record for Warhol set at Christie's in November, when a 1972 portrait of Mao was bought by Joseph Lau, a Hong Kong collector, for $17.3 million.</p>
        <p>Asked why the estimate is so high, Mr. Gorvy said, ''There are so few 'Car Crashes' in private hands, and so many serious collectors are looking for one.'' He added that the owner had received many private offers that exceeded Christie's estimate but decided to see what the painting would bring at auction.</p>
        <p>Portraits of Colonial Jews</p>
        <p>Two years ago Alice L. Walton, the Wal-Mart heiress who is founding the Crystal Bridges Museum of American Art in Bentonville, Ark., bought six Colonial portraits, attributed to Gerardus Duyckinck, from the American Jewish Historical Society in Manhattan. Before Ms. Walton bought them privately, they were to be sold at Sotheby's.</p>
        <p>A generous lender to institutions around the world, Ms. Walton offered the Jewish Museum in Manhattan the opportunity to show them. Because the museum's space is tight and its exhibition schedule is full, the portraits are going on view in its permanent exhibition galleries two at a time beginning tomorrow.</p>
        <p>''They are an extremely important group of pictures not just for the American Jewish community, but for everyone,'' said Robert G. Workman, executive director of Crystal Bridges.</p>
        <p>Dating from the 1720s to 1735 the portraits span three generations of the Levy-Franks family, beginning with the German-born patriarch Moses Raphael Levy, a prominent Jewish merchant in New York; his wife, Grace Mears Levy; their daughter Abigaill Franks; her husband, Jacob Franks; and five of the Frankses' children.</p>
        <p>''They are the quintessential illustration of the Jewish experience,'' said Susan L. Braunstein, chairwoman of curatorial affairs at the Jewish Museum. ''The Jewish community was tiny in the 1730s, and this is a great story of a family living in New York around the time of the Revolutionary War.''</p>
        <p>There are eight portraits in the entire series, two from the 1720s that belong to the Museum of the City of New York and the six that Crystal Bridges owns, which were produced a decade later.</p>
        <p>The first two paintings to be shown are ''Portrait of Richa Franks'' and ''Portrait of Franks Children With Lamb'' (1735). They will be on view through Dec. 31. The second pair will be on view from January through September 2008, and the third from October 2008 through June 2009.</p>
        <p>Galleries Galore</p>
        <p>In today's frothy market for contemporary art, dealers in their galleries feel the way most city dwellers do in their apartments: cramped. Increasingly, dealers are realizing that one gallery and in some cases even two are no longer enough.</p>
        <p>In Chelsea, Barbara Gladstone has acquired a second space, at 530 West 21st Street. ''We moved here 10 years ago,'' Ms. Gladstone said, referring to her original gallery at 515 West 24th Street. ''Now I find we need more space for large installations.'' The second location building, a former recording studio, does not suit an art gallery, so she plans to tear it down. The new space probably won't be ready until January, she said.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile Paula Cooper is opening a third space at 465 West 23rd Street in Chelsea. (Her other two are at 521 and 534 West 21st Street.) Named Paula Cooper at 465, it is to open on Tuesday with an exhibition of recent work by the Conceptual artist Sherrie Levine. ''Galleries are working with more artists, and they like the option of working in different spaces,'' Steve Henry, director of Paula Cooper, said. ''This is a modest space, but it will give us the flexibility to do more focused, intimate shows.''</p>
        <p>In May, Per Skarstedt is opening a large gallery at 20 East 79th Street, the former home of the Salander O'Reilly Gallery. But he will not abandon his original space around the corner, at 1018 Madison Avenue. So he has formed a venture called 1018 Art with the Chelsea dealers Lawrence Luhring and Roland Augustine. The dealers have been informally organizing exhibitions together since 2000. Now they will present shows by artists who work with all of them.</p>
        <p>Inside Art</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
