<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To Mark a Cab Centennial, These Designers Look Ahead</title>
    <meta content="06cabs" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/nyregion/06cabs.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838340"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxicabs and Taxicab Drivers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Models and Replicas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York International Auto Show</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxicabs and Taxicab Drivers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxicabs and Taxicab Drivers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Art Center College of Design</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2DD173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="843" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To Mark a Cab Centennial, These Designers Look Ahead</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">To Mark a Cab Centennial, These Designers Look Ahead</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barron, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York International Auto Show includes eight full-size prototypes of taxicabs of the future as well as handful of smaller-scale models; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rocco Filippone trained his knowing eyes on his son's college project and said he would give it a B.</p>
        <p>As it happened, that was the same grade that the son's instructors at a California design college gave it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An exhibit at the New York International Auto Show celebrates the 100th anniversary of the modern-day taxi by presenting forward-looking concepts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rocco Filippone trained his knowing eyes on his son's college project and said he would give it a B.</p>
        <p>As it happened, that was the same grade that the son's instructors at a California design college gave it.</p>
        <p>The assignment was to design a new New York City taxi to be displayed at Taxi 07, an exhibit celebrating the 100th anniversary of the modern-day taxi.</p>
        <p>The nonprofit Design Trust for Public Space, wanted to prove that there is a bright future for the yellow cab. It arranged to display eight full-size prototypes and a handful of smaller-scale models at the New York International Auto Show, which opens today at the Jacob K. Javits Convention Center.</p>
        <p>As assignments go, this one was tough, said Chris Monier, who with Ben Merkel wrote ''The American Taxi: A Century of Service'' (Iconografix, 2006).</p>
        <p>''The hard part is to get the creative side along with the practical side,'' Mr. Monier said yesterday at a preview of the designers' work. He said the Checker cab -- to many New Yorkers still the quintessential taxi -- was the perfect balance between one and the other.</p>
        <p>But the last Checker cab rolled off the assembly line in 1982, and the Taxi 07 exhibit was supposed to be forward-looking.</p>
        <p>So Rides car magazine submitted a Ford Crown Victoria, a model in many of today's taxi fleets. But they raised the body 42 inches and positioned it on 30-inch wheels. The magazine calls the model the skyscraper cab on their Web site, www.rides-mag.com.</p>
        <p>Among the other entrants were minivan taxis with extra-wide signs and lights on the doors ''so you can see what you're going to step in,'' explained Tim Kennedy, the director of industrial design for Smart Design, one of the firms that worked on adapting a Kia Rondo sport utility vehicle for use as a taxi.</p>
        <p>And then there was the model designed by Mr. Filippone's son, Giuseppe, 25.</p>
        <p>He attends the Art Center College of Design in Pasadena, Calif., which trains would-be automotive designers. But his long-nosed taxi is not the work of some West Coast expert who figured that he could show New Yorkers a thing or two about what a taxi should be.</p>
        <p>That is because the younger Mr. Filippone grew up in Bensonhurst, Brooklyn, and his father was a cabdriver. So he sought pointers from his father. As Rocco Filippone explained it yesterday, ''He called me from the school and said, 'Dad, can you give me any ideas?' ''</p>
        <p>His advice was to create a cab for drivers who hustle the way he did. ''New York taxi drivers, they've got to rush to make the money,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He told his son that it would be a good idea to build a taxi that could handle a wheelchair. Too many drivers pass up passengers in wheelchairs because they do not believe they can afford the time it takes to help the passenger into the cab and then fold up the wheelchair and stow it in the trunk.</p>
        <p>Giuseppe Filippone interrupted with a question about the taxi he had designed: ''How do you compare it to an Alfa Romeo?''</p>
        <p>Rocco Filippone's eyes lit up. ''Ah, an Alfa Romeo,'' he said. ''Leave the Alfa Romeo to the streets of Milan. This is New York.''</p>
        <p>So this is no sports car.</p>
        <p>''The main premise behind it is to act like a logotype on wheels,'' the student designer said. ''I wanted it to have the power the Macintosh has to communicate Apple. I wanted this to communicate the relationship between driver and passenger as a symbol of the relationship between the immigrants and the natives that happens every day and makes us so cherished as a city.''</p>
        <p>Stewart Reed, the chairman of the transportation design department at the Art Center College, said he had instructed the students to design a cab that would be at home not just in New York but also in Las Vegas or Los Angeles. But the younger Mr. Filippone opted for his hometown's cab colors -- yellow and black. He also put his father's old medallion number, 6E33, on the door.</p>
        <p>That was not enough to earn him an A-plus from his father, who faulted his son's design for putting the advertisement on the front of the cab, on the hood.</p>
        <p>''If he put the advertisement on the top or on the side panel, I'd give it an A,'' Rocco said.</p>
        <p>A few steps away was a model that did get an A, from the College for Creative Studies in Detroit.</p>
        <p>Alter R. Buffenn said that he and another student, Chris Hardy, the designers of the A model, set out to solve communication problems between driver and passenger.</p>
        <p>He said they did that by eliminating the need for driver and passenger to talk to each other. Their taxi has a computer screen in the passenger compartment.</p>
        <p>The passenger types in the destination. A screen in the driver's compartment relays the information to the driver.</p>
        <p>No, he said, the partition separating the two compartments is not bullet-proof.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
