<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Police Academy to Move From Gramercy Park to a Corner of Queens</title>
    <meta content="06police" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/nyregion/06police.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838343"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Police Academy (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cardwell, Diane</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Police Academy</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E1DD173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="778" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Police Academy to Move From Gramercy Park to a Corner of Queens</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Police Academy to Move From Longtime Home in Gramercy Park to Queens</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANE CARDWELL; Colin Moynihan contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cardwell, Diane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City's Police Academy will move from current building on East 20th Street, which academy outgrew long ago, to 30-acre high-tech campus in College Point, Queens, at site of city's largest auto pound; department's current main firing range, at Rodman's Neck in Bronx, will be closed as part of move to Queens; new campus has not yet been designed, but city is setting aside $1 billion for it in capital budget; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The long-beleaguered Police Academy building, which has funneled generations of gray-shirted recruits onto the streets of Gramercy Park, will be replaced by a 30-acre, high-tech campus in Queens, Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The campus, which is to rise in College Point, at the site of the city's largest auto pound, will allow the Police Department to consolidate its far-flung training grounds -- now up to 25 miles apart -- at one collegiate-style location, officials said. Plans include 250 wireless classrooms, a 100,000 square-foot ''tactical village'' with a subway car and mock street scenes, and housing for visiting law enforcement agencies willing to pay for training there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The long-beleaguered Police Academy will move to a 30-acre, high-tech campus in Queens.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The long-beleaguered Police Academy building, which has funneled generations of gray-shirted recruits onto the streets of Gramercy Park, will be replaced by a 30-acre, high-tech campus in Queens, Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The campus, which is to rise in College Point, at the site of the city's largest auto pound, will allow the Police Department to consolidate its far-flung training grounds -- now up to 25 miles apart -- at one collegiate-style location, officials said. Plans include 250 wireless classrooms, a 100,000 square-foot ''tactical village'' with a subway car and mock street scenes, and housing for visiting law enforcement agencies willing to pay for training there.</p>
        <p>''The reality is that our current academy doesn't allow for the extensive scenario-based and computer-based simulations that are so important in today's world,'' Mr. Bloomberg said in making the announcement at the tow pound. ''A campus at this location, however, would be very conducive to modern-day training practices.''</p>
        <p>The Police Department has clamored for decades for a new academy, saying it had outgrown its tattered building on East 20th Street, between Second and Third Avenues.</p>
        <p>Opened in 1964 for a smaller force whose recruits were all men, the building can no longer accommodate its classes of more than 1,000. Training is broken into at least two shifts, the locker room is crudely divided for the sexes, the electrical wiring is questionable and the garage and hallways double as storage space.</p>
        <p>''We've expanded both the size of the force and its mission to include new counterterrorism and intelligence programs, expanded community outreach and greater focus on quality of life,'' Police Commissioner Raymond W. Kelly said at the news conference. ''All these activities create new demands on the Police Academy that this facility will meet.''</p>
        <p>Plans for the campus, yet to be designed, include an elaborate firing range, a 12-acre field for emergency-vehicle exercises and a 450,000 square-foot physical training area that could accommodate an entire class for graduations and lectures, Mr. Kelly said.</p>
        <p>The department's current main firing range, at Rodman's Neck, in the Bronx, will be closed as part of the move to Queens.</p>
        <p>Mayoral officials said that they could not be sure precisely how much it would cost to build the campus, which is to occupy a lot roughly bounded by College Point Boulevard, 28th Avenue, 31st Avenue and Ulmer Street, but they are setting aside $1 billion in the capital budget.</p>
        <p>The project must first be approved through the city's land use review process, so officials said they did not expect to begin construction until fall 2009. In the meantime, Mr. Bloomberg said, they will look for another place to put the cars that currently come to the pound.</p>
        <p>The administration considered seven other locations, including the abandoned Flushing Airport, the Seaview Hospital and Farm Colony in Staten Island and Floyd Bennett Field in Brooklyn, where the Police Department conducts emergency-vehicle training.</p>
        <p>Officials ultimately chose College Point because of its size, its proximity to public transportation and its likelihood of fitting into the surrounding community, in a largely industrial area north of Shea Stadium, and of being built.</p>
        <p>But that will mean that a world near Gramercy Park, where officials plan to sell the Police Academy building once the new campus is up and running, will be coming to an end. ''It will affect our neighborhood,'' said Bob Martin, 43, who was standing behind a cash register at his pizza and pasta restaurant, Andiamo, on 20th Street and Second Avenue, as cadets streamed in for lunch at 1 p.m.</p>
        <p>''All the businesses in this neighborhood are built on these guys.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Martin added that the cadets also help keep the neighborhood safe. ''When you see a lot of uniformed guys, if you're a thief or a robber, will you come around? Not unless you're an idiot.''</p>
        <p>Ingrid Abel, 22, a resident of Stuyvesant Town who attends St. John's University in Queens, echoed that thought. ''It would be a problem if they moved away,'' she said. ''It's good for the safety of the neighborhood.''</p>
        <p>For Wilfredo Vega, Jr., 45, who owns Junior's Police Equipment on East 21st Street, where generations of cadets have bought uniforms and other supplies, the move may just be another twist in an already long road. The shop, formerly called Frielich Police Equipment, moved to the block in 1964, when the current academy opened, he said. There had been a Frielich shop on Broome Street, near the old Academy on Market and Centre Streets.</p>
        <p>''We sell police equipment,'' he said. ''We're probably going to pack up and follow those guys. It's impossible for us to survive without the Academy presence.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
