<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Before Masters, Mickelson Misread Putts</title>
    <meta content="06anderson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/sports/golf/06anderson.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838412"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Mickelson, Phil</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Anderson, Dave</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E3DB173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="863" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Before Masters, Mickelson Misread Putts</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Before Masters, Mickelson Misread Putts</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>AUGUSTA, Ga.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Phil Mickelson thought he was ready to slip his arms into another Masters green jacket. On his arrival at Augusta National, he talked about how he would use two drivers again, as he had in winning here last year for the second time in three years. One of his drivers even had the latest titanium technology: a fashionably new square head.</p>
        <p>''It goes 20 yards longer than my regular driver, so when I need distance, I use the square one,'' Mickelson said. ''When I try to hit little low shots or work it around the trees, I'll use the regular-shaped driver.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Phil Mickelson, who was four-over-par in the first round on Thursday, did not play in a PGA Tour event last week, as he prefers to do the week before a major tournament.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Phil Mickelson thought he was ready to slip his arms into another Masters green jacket. On his arrival at Augusta National, he talked about how he would use two drivers again, as he had in winning here last year for the second time in three years. One of his drivers even had the latest titanium technology: a fashionably new square head.</p>
        <p>''It goes 20 yards longer than my regular driver, so when I need distance, I use the square one,'' Mickelson said. ''When I try to hit little low shots or work it around the trees, I'll use the regular-shaped driver.''</p>
        <p>As the host of the Masters champions dinner in the clubhouse Tuesday evening, Mickelson also had the menu ready: barbecued ribs, beef brisket, fried chicken, smoked sausage and vanilla ice cream.</p>
        <p>But Mickelson, the best left-handed golfer in history, acknowledged a nagging problem: He did not play in a PGA Tour event last week, as he prefers to do the week before a major tournament.</p>
        <p>At the BellSouth Classic outside Atlanta a year ago, Mickelson won by 13 strokes, then maintained his momentum among Augusta National's azaleas and pines, shooting a seven-under-par 281 to win by two strokes.</p>
        <p>''So I am a little bit nervous about not having played in a competition and having not been in contention in a little while,'' Mickelson said. ''That's probably my biggest concern. But on the other hand, I have had a chance to get some good work done.''</p>
        <p>Mickelson needed some good work. After having missed the cut at the FBR Open in Phoenix, he won the AT&amp;T National Pro-Am at Pebble Beach with a 20-under-par total and finished second at the Nissan Open near Los Angeles. In two recent Florida events, he finished far down, tied for 36th at the Arnold Palmer Invitational at Bay Hill and tied for 23rd at the CA Championship at Doral.</p>
        <p>''But I'm starting to feel pretty confident with how my game is improving,'' he said Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Mickelson never mentioned the possibility of putting problems. If anything, he minimized it.</p>
        <p>''I would say that the statistics of 5-footers made at Augusta National are the same as 3-footers on the PGA Tour,'' he said Tuesday. ''The greens are so perfect that you should be able to make a number of short putts.''</p>
        <p>But in opening this Masters yesterday with a four-over 76, putting was his problem on the hard, fast greens as he plodded along in a black cap, black shirt, black slacks and black shoes. After a bogey at No. 1 and a birdie at No. 3, he missed par putts in the 3-foot range at the two short holes on the front nine, Nos. 4 and 6. With a double-bogey 6 at No. 5 and another bogey at No. 7, he was a shocking five over par.</p>
        <p>On his way to the tee at No. 8, he got a hug from his wife, Amy, what he later described as a ''little morale boost to keep me fighting.''</p>
        <p>He responded with a birdie at the uphill 570-yard No. 8. On the back nine, he bogeyed No. 12, the scenic and windy par-3 beyond Rae's Creek, to go to five over par again. He then went to six over with a bogey at No. 14, before birdies at Nos. 15 and 16. His 76 equaled his highest score in 54 previous Masters rounds, in the first round in 1997, when he missed the 36-hole cut.</p>
        <p>''I didn't drive it as well as I wanted to, but I got it done in the end,'' he said yesterday outside the scorer's shed, with no mention of the gusty northwest wind that raised scores higher than usual. ''I'm more worried about the short putts I missed.''</p>
        <p>Instead of relaxing in the champions' locker room or going to the practice range to work with his two drivers, Mickelson hurried to the nearby practice green, where his swing coach, Rick Smith, waited. Oddly, Mickelson's short-game guru, Dave Pelz, who usually supervises his putting stroke at majors, was not around.</p>
        <p>Mickelson's caddie, Bones Mackay, tossed three golf balls on the green, about 6 feet from the cup, then stood aside. Mickelson chatted with Smith, then hunched into his putting stance and, one by one, putted the three balls. Sometimes downhill with a right-to-left break, sometimes uphill with a left-to-right break.</p>
        <p>In watching seven of those three-ball series of putts, Mickelson, with Smith crouched behind the line of the putt, missed the first putt in six before finally making the first putt in the seventh series -- hardly what's expected of one of the world's best putters. He made the second putt five times, the third putt five times.</p>
        <p>In today's second round, Mickelson won't have the luxury to take a second or third putt.</p>
        <p>''If I can go out there and shoot 68, I'll be right back in there,'' he had said outside the scorer's shed.</p>
        <p>But if Mickelson is to shoot 68, no matter how close his two drivers get him to the green, he has to make more of those short putts that he missed yesterday. Maybe he should use two putters.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
