<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Donovan Remains at Florida, But His Stars Enter the Draft</title>
    <meta content="06coaches" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/sports/ncaabasketball/06coaches.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838373"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Florida</org>
        <org class="online_producer">West Virginia University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Donovan, Billy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Huggins, Bob</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE1DC173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="688" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Donovan Remains at Florida, But His Stars Enter the Draft</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Donovan Remains at Florida, but His Stars Enter the Draft</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETE THAMEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Thamel, Pete</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Another dizzying day in college basketball's coaching carousel found the most sought-after coach staying at Florida, one of the most controversial moving to West Virginia and two of the nation's best players in limbo.</p>
        <p>Billy Donovan announced yesterday that he would remain as Florida's coach, leaving his primary suitor, Kentucky, still searching.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After two championships, the Florida coach is staying put. But the controversial Bob Huggins will leave Kansas State for West Virginia after one season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Another dizzying day in college basketball's coaching carousel found the most sought-after coach staying at Florida, one of the most controversial moving to West Virginia and two of the nation's best players in limbo.</p>
        <p>Billy Donovan announced yesterday that he would remain as Florida's coach, leaving his primary suitor, Kentucky, still searching.</p>
        <p>Donovan will be without his stellar junior class, however. Joakim Noah, Al Horford, Corey Brewer and Taurean Green, the heart of Florida's back-to-back N.C.A.A. title runs, declared for the N.B.A. draft yesterday.</p>
        <p>That news was not as surprising as Bob Huggins's decision to leave Kansas State to take over at West Virginia, his alma mater. The departure of Huggins also leaves two top players at a university in Manhattan, Kan., that they would not have considered if not for Huggins.</p>
        <p>Bill Walker, a 6-foot-10 freshman forward, played only six games for the Wildcats because of a knee injury and will probably play for them next season. He is ineligible for the draft since he has not been out of high school for at least a year. Michael Beasley, a 6-9 forward considered the nation's top prospect, signed a letter of intent with Kansas State early this year. But if he seeks to be let out of his commitment, as many believe he will, Kansas State Athletic Director Tim Weiser reiterated yesterday that it is university policy to not allow any athletes to do so.</p>
        <p>The busy afternoon in college basketball began with Donovan's decision to stay put. Donovan spoke with Kentucky's athletic director, Mitch Barnhart, before announcing his intention to remain in Gainesville. Throughout Florida's run to the national title this spring, Donovan was vague when responding to questions about the possibility that he would leave for Kentucky. But less than a week after Florida became the first team to win back-to-back N.C.A.A. basketball titles since Duke in 1992, Donovan made his intentions clear.</p>
        <p>''I'm happy here at Florida,'' he said. ''I love the University of Florida.''</p>
        <p>Donovan, who earned about $1.7 million last season, is due for a considerable raise. The amount will most likely not be determined for about two weeks, when the university's athletic finance committee meets. It would not be surprising if his annual salary exceeds $3 million.</p>
        <p>As for Huggins, his move to West Virginia creates some chaotic possibilities. First, his style of play is the opposite of John Beilein's, whom he replaced and who left the Mountaineers for Michigan. Beilein's team played a 1-3-1 zone defense and his offense was predicated on shooting and precision. Beilein's players rarely lift weights, their style of play more finesse than physical.</p>
        <p>The players Beilein recruited to West Virginia will now play for a coach whose teams are known for their suffocating man-to-man defense and bullying style.</p>
        <p>But what may be even more interesting is what happens to Walker and to Beasley, who chose to play for Huggins on a team with little recent success.</p>
        <p>''Where's the loyalty?'' said Sonny Vaccaro, who has served as an adviser to Walker. ''Here's a case where a young person was again put in jeopardy for the benefit of others who should have known better. The adults have the freedom to break every heart in the world. The young kids don't have the freedom to do anything. This is wrong.''</p>
        <p>Beasley, meanwhile, was playing with USA Basketball in Memphis and could not be reached for comment.</p>
        <p>The leading candidates for the Kansas State job will probably be Nevada Coach Mark Fox, who served six years there as an assistant, and Wichita State Coach Mark Turgeon.</p>
        <p>Huggins's decision ends a one-year stint at Kansas State that revived a stagnant program. Huggins went 23-12 and brought the Wildcats to the cusp of the N.C.A.A. tournament.</p>
        <p>After being forced out of his job at Cincinnati because the university president was unhappy with the image projected by Huggins and the team, Huggins sat out a season before taking the job at Kansas State.</p>
        <p>''Bob Huggins did a terrific job during his short tenure to put Kansas State back on the basketball map and we appreciate his efforts,'' Weiser said.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
