<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gillispie Leaves Texas A&amp;M for Kentucky</title>
    <meta content="07cnd-kentucky" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838425"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Tubby, Amaker, Tommy, Beilein, John, Huggins, Bob, Donovan, Billy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E1DF143FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="585" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gillispie Leaves Texas A&amp;M for Kentucky</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAY GLIER and THAYER EVANS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kentucky's basketball coaching vacancy, which hovered over the recent N.C.A.A. tournament and spurred countless rumors about which prominent coach would land in Lexington, was settled today with Billy Gillispie leaving Texas A&amp;M to take over the Wildcats.</p>
        <p>Gillispie, who had swiftly taken Texas A&amp;M's basketball program from obscurity to Big 12 Conference power, was introduced as Kentucky's new coach today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Kentucky's basketball coaching vacancy, which hovered over the recent N.C.A.A. tournament and spurred countless rumors about which prominent coach would land in Lexington, was settled today with Billy Gillispie leaving Texas A&amp;M to take over the Wildcats.</p>
        <p>Gillispie, who had swiftly taken Texas A&amp;M's basketball program from obscurity to Big 12 Conference power, was introduced as Kentucky's new coach today.</p>
        <p>"It's a great honor for me to be here standing at the place where they basically invented basketball," Gillispie said Friday at a school pep rally, according to the Associated Press.</p>
        <p>Kentucky has more victories than any other Division I program, and the coaching job is considered one of the most prestigious in college basketball. It is also perhaps the most demanding.</p>
        <p>Tubby Smith left Kentucky for Minnesota last month after leading the Wildcats to the N.C.A.A. tournament for 10 consecutive seasons, which was not enough success to satisfy the fans. The Wildcats won a national title in Smith's first year (1998), but have not been back to the Final Four since.</p>
        <p>Gillispie, 47, agreed to a new multiyear contract with Texas A&amp;M on March 30 and praised the university's commitment to build a top-shelf program. The Aggies were 27-7 last season, the most wins in team history, and were 13-3 in the Big 12, their highest finish ever in the conference.</p>
        <p>They advanced to the Round of 16 in the N.C.A.A. tournament for the first time in 27 years, defeating Penn and Louisville in the first two rounds -- at Rupp Arena in Lexington, Ky.</p>
        <p>Texas A&amp;M's athletic director, Bill Byrne, was not immediately available for comment, but a team spokesman said Byrne would issue a statement on Gillispie's departure later today.</p>
        <p>Gillispie was in Dallas on Thursday night and was set to fly with the senior guard Acie Law IV to Saturday's Wooden Award ceremony in Los Angeles when Kentucky was granted permission to talk with him, said the team spokesman, Colin Killian. He said Gillispie had not met with Texas A&amp;M players because many had already left for Easter weekend with no classes being held at the university Friday.</p>
        <p>"It all happened really, really quickly," Killian said.</p>
        <p>The fate of the five players who signed binding national letters of intent last year to attend Texas A&amp;M has not been determined, Killian said. The recruiting class, which is not ranked among the nation's top 25 best by Internet recruiting services, features DeAndre Jordan of Houston, a 7-footer, who is rated as the nation's second-best center.</p>
        <p>"We'll have some administrators that will be contacting those players," Killian said. "My guess is we wouldn't release anybody that quickly for sure."</p>
        <p>Only four days after the national championship game, there have been several significant coaching changes.</p>
        <p>After Smith's move to Minnesota, Michigan fired Tommy Amaker and lured John Beilein from West Virginia. Beilein was making approximately $720,000 and became a million-dollar-a-year coach when he agreed to coach the Wolverines.</p>
        <p>Bob Huggins, a West Virginia graduate, then left Kansas State -- after just one season -- to take over the Mountaineers program.</p>
        <p>Arkansas' coaching opening was filled for a day by Dana Altman, who left Creighton to replace the fired Stan Heath. Altman, however, changed his mind and went back to Creighton.</p>
        <p>Florida's Billy Donovan was considered the first choice for Kentucky, but on Thursday he agreed to a sweeter deal with the Gators. A day later, Gillispie, an avid horse racing fan, had made his move to the heart of horse racing country.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
