<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Teenager's Quiet Trek Toward Revenge</title>
    <meta content="06dara" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/movies/06dara.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838271"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dargis, Manohla</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haroun, Mahamat-Saleh</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">sarkai, Ali Bacha</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Daratt (Dry Season (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Daratt (Dry Season) (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E5DF173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="689" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Teenager's Quiet Trek Toward Revenge</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Teenager’s Quiet Trek Toward Revenge</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MANOHLA DARGIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dargis, Manohla</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Manohla Dargis reviews film Daratt (Dry Season), written and directed by Mahamat-Saleh Haroun; Ali Bacha Barkai stars; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Truth arrives as grudgingly as reconciliation in the Chadian film ''Daratt'' (''Dry Season''). Gently and quietly told, steeped in the kind of resigned sorrow that can come after years of hurt and disappointment, it is an unassumingly political work that unfolds with the simplicity of a parable and the gravity of a Bible story. In 2006, in the uneasy wake of the country's decades-long civil war, a fatherless boy sets out to murder a childless man.</p>
        <p>The boy is Atim (Ali Bacha Barkai), or, as he explains in the intermittent French-language voice-over, ''the orphan.'' His story opens with a blind old man, Atim's grandfather, calling out in Arabic for the 16-year-old, his voice echoing through dusty village streets. Barefoot, panting, Atim rushes home, where together he and the grandfather hear radio news of a general amnesty for war criminals, an announcement that sets off angry cries and machine-gun fire through the village. Atim voices outrage, but the old man presents a more concrete response in the form of a gun. ''My son was brave as a lion,'' the grandfather says. But the lion is long dead, and now it's left to the cub to exact revenge.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gently and quietly told, “Daratt” (“Dry Season”) is an unassumingly political work that unfolds with the simplicity of a parable and the gravity of a Bible story.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Truth arrives as grudgingly as reconciliation in the Chadian film ''Daratt'' (''Dry Season''). Gently and quietly told, steeped in the kind of resigned sorrow that can come after years of hurt and disappointment, it is an unassumingly political work that unfolds with the simplicity of a parable and the gravity of a Bible story. In 2006, in the uneasy wake of the country's decades-long civil war, a fatherless boy sets out to murder a childless man.</p>
        <p>The boy is Atim (Ali Bacha Barkai), or, as he explains in the intermittent French-language voice-over, ''the orphan.'' His story opens with a blind old man, Atim's grandfather, calling out in Arabic for the 16-year-old, his voice echoing through dusty village streets. Barefoot, panting, Atim rushes home, where together he and the grandfather hear radio news of a general amnesty for war criminals, an announcement that sets off angry cries and machine-gun fire through the village. Atim voices outrage, but the old man presents a more concrete response in the form of a gun. ''My son was brave as a lion,'' the grandfather says. But the lion is long dead, and now it's left to the cub to exact revenge.</p>
        <p>Revenge is generally wretched business, but in ''Daratt,'' written and directed by Mahamat-Saleh Haroun, it is mainly bedeviling, surprising. Enjoined to undertake what his grandfather calls his ''mission,'' Atim travels to the capital, Ndjamena, where he dashes through traffic, now in sneakers instead of bare feet. He meets a convivial rogue, Moussa (Djibril Ibrahim), who steals and sells fluorescent lights and cautiously makes his way to his target, a baker named Nassara (Youssouf Djaoro). A fierce-looking man somewhere in late middle age, Nassara lives with his pregnant, much younger wife, Aicha (Aziza Hisseine). He works hard, freely hands out his pale baguettes to beggars and worships with the frequency of the devout. He's an exemplary citizen, but there is blood on his hands, not just flour.</p>
        <p>Mr. Haroun, whose earlier films include ''Bye Bye Africa'' and ''Abouna,'' tells this story of a would-be boy-killer and his prey with restraint, a touch of humor and an elegant eye. Although the setup borders on the contrived -- sure enough, Atim is soon working for Nassara -- the result is anything but. The characters speak in the unrushed cadences of real life or not at all, with some interludes unwinding without a single word. Shortly before Atim goes to work for Nassara, the two wordlessly circle each other like dogs, like boxers squaring off in the ring. Nassara, who uses an electronic larynx to speak, asks Atim what he wants. ''Not charity,'' the scowling boy responds, touchingly unaware that benevolence is precisely what he needs most.</p>
        <p>Despite the film's subject, Mr. Haroun's storytelling shows little urgency, which might be cultural or symptomatic of war-weariness. The unhurried pace distracts as well as charms, and the same holds true of some of the more obvious rhetorical strategies, like the repeated images of Atim and Nassara sweating side by side while cutting dough and feeding the oven. Even so, the film has the feel of a gift. Particularly noteworthy are Mr. Haroun's eloquent silences, visual and aural. Among the more indelible moments is an early scene that finds Atim rushing into his village's center after news of the amnesty breaks and the guns start firing. There in the heart of this modest little place where, one imagines, blood once dampened the dust, Atim stands silent surrounded by dozens of hurriedly abandoned shoes. He picks up one shoe and then another, as if searching for answers.</p>
        <p>Daratt (Dry Season)  Opens today in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>Written (in French and Chadian Arabic, with English subtitles) and directed by Mahamat-Saleh Haroun; director of photography, Abraham Haile Biru; edited by Marie-Hélène Dozo; music by Wasis Diop; produced by Abderrahmane Sissako; released by ArtMattan Productions. At the BAM Rose Cinemas, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene. Running time: 95 minutes. This film is not rated.</p>
        <p>WITH: Ali Bacha Barkai (Atim), Youssouf Djaoro (Nassara), Aziza Hisseine (Aicha), Djibril Ibrahim (Moussa), Fatimé Hadje (Auntie Moussa) and Khayar Oumar Defallah (Grandfather).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
