<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shedding Light on America's Dark Recesses</title>
    <meta content="06simo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/arts/design/06simo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838262"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Simon, Taryn</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EED6163FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="693" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shedding Light on America's Dark Recesses</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Shedding Light on America’s Dark Recesses</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRIDGET L. GOODBODY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodbody, Bridget L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There's something quintessentially American about the way Taryn Simon's photography exhibition ''An American Index of the Hidden and Unfamiliar'' examines the culture's irreconcilable differences. Ms. Simon couches the show in the intellectual, power-to-the-people oratory of leftist politics. Yet she clearly delights in exposing, in a quasi-tabloid fashion, America's underbelly.</p>
        <p>Ms. Simon comes naturally to documenting places average citizens can't access. For the State Department her father photographed Soviet cities during the cold war, restricted sites in Southeast Asia during the war in Vietnam and out-of-the way locations in Afghanistan, Israel and Iran in the 1970s.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Taryn Simon is at her artistic best when she exposes America’s underbelly in her photography exhibit at the Whitney Museum.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There's something quintessentially American about the way Taryn Simon's photography exhibition ''An American Index of the Hidden and Unfamiliar'' examines the culture's irreconcilable differences. Ms. Simon couches the show in the intellectual, power-to-the-people oratory of leftist politics. Yet she clearly delights in exposing, in a quasi-tabloid fashion, America's underbelly.</p>
        <p>Ms. Simon comes naturally to documenting places average citizens can't access. For the State Department her father photographed Soviet cities during the cold war, restricted sites in Southeast Asia during the war in Vietnam and out-of-the way locations in Afghanistan, Israel and Iran in the 1970s.</p>
        <p>Though she has also worked in war-torn areas (the Gaza Strip, Lebanon and Syria), Ms. Simon is best known for ''The Innocents,'' a series of portraits of men and women who were wrongly convicted of crimes but later, in some cases after decades in prison, were cleared by DNA test results.</p>
        <p>Ms. Simon can work as long as a year to gain permission to photograph high-security zones like the government-regulated quarantine sites, nuclear waste storage facilities, prison death rows and C.I.A. offices on view in the show. There are also pictures with lighter themes, taken at sites with presumably fewer restrictions: the sandpit where the Grucci family tests fireworks, ski slopes being dynamited for avalanche control and the second Death Star, from ''Return of the Jedi,'' at George Lucas's Skywalker Ranch.</p>
        <p>What's amazing is how many closed doors open for Ms. Simon. Interestingly, Disney did refuse her request, saying it wanted to protect the fantasies of theme park visitors. (A copy of its reply is in the catalog.)</p>
        <p>Aware that realistic images can mislead, Ms. Simon goes to great lengths to explain the content of her photographs with label texts. She writes them herself in an objective journalistic tone, wanting the viewer to share her understanding of the images.</p>
        <p>At times her texts can obfuscate, rather than reveal. The label with her photograph of Thomas Downing's 1960s post-painterly abstractions in the halls of the C.I.A.'s former headquarters is one example. It reads like an excerpt from a conspiracy theory document as it alludes to the agency's earlier use of Abstract Expressionist art to promote its cold-war agenda.</p>
        <p>Ms. Simon is at her artistic best when her delight in the strangeness of American culture shines. She turns America's melting pot into a global compost heap in her image of the contraband room at Kennedy Airport: a cornucopia of once fresh, now rotting organic materials -- African cane rats, Bangladeshi cucurbit plants, a South American pig's head -- confiscated from the many different people who arrive daily.</p>
        <p>She caught Kenny, a genetically modified white tiger born mentally retarded, in a pose that makes him look stuffed. Her picture of the flat, white interior of a jury simulation room, where lawyers stage mock trials, recalls Thomas Demand's photographs of the airport security zones he created from cardboard.</p>
        <p>Other images suggest how complicated it can be when a member of one culture tries not to judge the traditions of another. ''Hymenoplasty,'' the label says, portrays an anonymous Palestinian woman, who has traveled to Atlanta, in a plastic surgeon's gynecological chair, moments before she is to have her hymen reconstructed. When she writes that the woman is undergoing the surgery ''to adhere to cultural and familial expectations regarding her virginity and marriage,'' you perceive that despite Ms. Simon's bland language, she is outraged by the woman's circumstances.</p>
        <p>Yet Ms. Simon can suggest hope in her images too. Her portrait of Don James, an Oregon cancer patient and advocate for the state's law permitting physician-assisted suicide, captures him as he has filled his prescription for a lethal dose of pentobarbital. (He died shortly afterward, before using it.)</p>
        <p>Ms. Simon illuminated Mr. James, in a wheelchair and looking tired, with an eerie light from above, suggesting that the right to choose one's time of death is sanctified. America may not be as free as Ms. Simon would like, but she marvels at its bravery.</p>
        <p>Taryn Simon's ''American Index of the Hidden and Unfamiliar'' continues through June at the Whitney Museum of American Art, 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street; (212) 570-3676.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
