<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Piers of California: At Sea Without a Sail</title>
    <meta content="06piers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/travel/escapes/06piers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838269"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recreation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Piers</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shukman, Henry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E6DF173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1630" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Piers of California: At Sea Without a Sail</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Piers of California: At Sea Without a Sail</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY SHUKMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shukman, Henry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on recreational piers of Southern California, most of which started as wharves where steamers could tie up or as amusement piers photos; map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A PIER is a folly, a highway to nowhere. Whether lined with fishermen or filled with the cries and clattering of a roller coaster, whether thick with the aromas of hot dogs and fries or freshly gutted fish, they are there for nothing but the pleasure of humanity.</p>
        <p>They didn't all begin that way. Piers are not quays or wharves, but many originally were. Most piers in Southern California started life as wharves where steamers could tie up, before the coastal shipping lines were superseded by railroads and highways.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Places where Southern Californians can escape the Hollywood hustle and freeway bustle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A PIER is a folly, a highway to nowhere. Whether lined with fishermen or filled with the cries and clattering of a roller coaster, whether thick with the aromas of hot dogs and fries or freshly gutted fish, they are there for nothing but the pleasure of humanity.</p>
        <p>They didn't all begin that way. Piers are not quays or wharves, but many originally were. Most piers in Southern California started life as wharves where steamers could tie up, before the coastal shipping lines were superseded by railroads and highways.</p>
        <p>Gold in the 1850s, black gold from the 1890s, the silver screen since the 1910s -- there has always been a glistening dream to lure people to California, but perhaps none so powerful as the promise of a long pleasure shore, where work is play and enterprise a spiritual adventure.</p>
        <p>The great amusement piers, including Santa Monica, Ocean Park, Venice, Long Beach -- came along in the early 20th century, and some no longer exist. But whether they began life for industry or amusement, just about all Southern California's piers sooner or later turned into pleasure decks, the special home of that most leisurely of pursuits, fishing. The recently restored and reopened Malibu Pier, once the dilapidated bohemian landmark of perhaps the first committed surfing scene in the mainland United States, was originally built in 1905 as a freight point for Malibu tiles and other goods from the Rancho Topanga Malibu Sequit, a 13,000-acre holding that dated from the days of Spanish control. Today, the pier is the refuge of fishermen.</p>
        <p>The history of the piers is tied not only to shipping but also to the arrival of the Big Red Car. Newport, Balboa, Huntington and several other piers were erected to coincide with the coming of Henry Huntington's trolley line from Los Angeles. Some, like Huntington Pier itself, seem to represent a triumph of human will over nature. The area of Huntington Beach around Huntington Pier, a fairly bleak spot between swampland filled with rocking oil derricks and the ocean, can look a little forbidding on a gray winter day. Yet even on a day like that there's a scene there -- kites, surfers, 22 volleyball courts lining the pier, families, the rules of the pier up on a board, a lifeguard enforcing one of them on his megaphone (''No Rollerblading on the pier'') -- the whole human panoply is here.</p>
        <p>ON the day I visited Newport Pier just after Christmas such a fierce wind was blowing that the tide raced under the pier like a fast river. Strollers became staggerers, shielding their eyes from scouring sand. Trash cans gave up their lids to the wind. The whole pier trembled like the sound box of a viola, and mist seethed from the piled up white breakers.</p>
        <p>On a day like this, what is a pier for? For getting out to sea in a blazing bright storm without ever leaving land. For looking back at the hills and town as you never could from shore. And for feeling O.K. about doing nothing in particular.</p>
        <p>''Mostly, out on the pier you understand that you're not really on the way to somewhere else. You're already there,'' is how Jean Femling put it in ''Great Piers of California.''</p>
        <p>At the lifeguard tower at the foot of Newport Pier, hunky guys with weather-beaten faces and temple-hugging shades surveyed the strand. One of them filled me in on the history.</p>
        <p>Newport Pier may well be the oldest on the coast, originally built in 1888 as McFadden's Wharf. Ships could easily navigate there, thanks to an undersea canyon that keeps the seas calm. Mr. Huntington brought his trolley line down to Newport Beach in 1905, opening up the area.</p>
        <p>Most piers along this coast have undergone structural changes caused by weather, economics, even politics, and Newport is no exception. In a giant September 1939 storm, 30-foot waves destroyed the last 400 feet; the pier reopened the next year with a huge fish-fry at which three tons of fish were said to have been eaten. The seas here are certainly rich. Even today, in the lee of the white clapboard restaurant at the end of the pier, closed for the gale, a handful of fishermen tweaked and plied their lines. I spoke with a young man in shades, and it turned out that his mum was from Banbury, England, 20 miles from where I grew up. That's what piers are for, too: idle chat with strangers, where an ad hoc bond forms under the semblance of being at sea.</p>
        <p>Children seem to understand the point of a pier intuitively. They can't help but charge around on it, slaloming toward the end, running desperately to pace themselves against passing waves. But a pier is the natural home of courting couples, too, who cavort as the wind whips their hair and coats about, of elderly couples who try to stroll sedately, of families who are out for multigenerational bracing breaths of air and of gulls, which in a wind like this day's, must enjoy the feeling of flying at great speed while hovering motionless above the rails.</p>
        <p>The gale blew itself out in the night. Around 7 the next morning, when the shadows were long and the early surfers were out on the glassy, post-storm water, the Newport dory men were coming in. It was quite a sight. The old salts revved their boats and aimed straight at the beach. The surfers paddled desperately to get out of the way. Then the boats rammed straight up the sand. Meanwhile, as a small crowd gathered at the dory men's encampment of old huts, one fellow was busy cutting and selling fish rolled in brown paper. The seaside is one of the last places where you regularly see the loss of life associated with food.</p>
        <p>According to Ms. Femling, Santa Monica Pier has quite a history. First there was the Shoo-Fly Landing, then in the 1890's the mile-long Long Wharf was built; in 1909 the city fishing pier went up. The adjacent Looff Pier dates to 1916, with its roller coaster and carousel and La Monica Ballroom (1924), which could hold about 10,000 people.</p>
        <p>On New Year's Day, Santa Monica Pier was a zoo. Parking alone took 20 minutes. Under all the crowded humanity, it was a wonder the pier didn't give a groan and settle into the waves. The light was perfect, though -- rich and creamy -- so the whole scene seemed gilded. Waves thundered in the background, people chattered, laughed, yelled. The roller coaster rumbled and clattered. A man with a machine filled the air with large bubbles that drifted over Arlington West, the field of white crosses set up every Sunday on the beach by the pier to remind us that America is at war.</p>
        <p>THE reason I was there on New Year's Day in a fragile morning-after state was not to ride the yellow roller coaster but to get into Santa Monica Pier Seafood (258 Santa Monica Pier, 310-394-9683), an unprepossessing place with plastic tables, metal chairs and a long counter where vats of self-service ketchup and mayo wait with congealed spouts. An extractor fan ground away in the background. But behind the counter on a grill, halves of giant lobster were deliciously flaming.</p>
        <p>And this place happens to serve one of the most restorative dishes on earth. The spicy Korean seafood soup -- scallion, squid, mussel, crab, hunks of halibut with fins spiking off them, clams, Asian turnip, little green chilies, tomatoes -- is a kind of Pacific Rim bouillabaisse ($21.75), and a faultless restorer after a big night. With every mouthful my gratitude to Calisto Vasquez, its modest maker, swelled, while outside the human throng enjoyed the carnival rides, the sea air, the sunshine.</p>
        <p>There's no better way to arrive on San Clemente Pier than to climb onto a stool at the bar of the Fisherman's Restaurant (611 Avenida Victoria, 949-498-6390) for a half-dozen oysters ($8.95). It's hard to beat the European method -- a squeeze of lemon, a grind of pepper -- but the horseradish is ferocious there, and a dab on each was bracing and seemed to match the exuberance of the crowd of boisterous customers and crash of the wild white rollers outside. The wind was back, and it was the kind of wind that makes just being out in it a sporting activity deserving of a nourishing reward. If you need a greater reward, try the White Horses (610 Avenida Victoria; 949-429-1800), a new restaurant opposite the pier, for dishes like garlic shrimp with grilled romaine hearts (about $35 to $50 a person).</p>
        <p>Allegedly used as a drop-off during Prohibition, the San Clemente Pier was in effect a gift to the town from Ole Hanson, its developer. Twenty-five men and many mule teams built the pier in 1928. It received a lot of damage in 1939 and 1983 but is thriving now, with a popular bait-and-tackle stall near the end, as well as Schleppy's espresso bar, graced by a pelican weathervane.</p>
        <p>Part of the charm of these piers comes from the way they thread through the affluence of California with an ordinary workadayness: fishermen pulling up their lines and crab baskets, the Amtrak Pacific Surfliner croaking and clanking by in San Clemente and the rough wooden boards through which you can see the green water stirring in some places. A pod of dolphins might cruise by, a few sea lions might bark hoarsely from the pilings, and a pelican might patrol the long swells. For a moment -- far from the suburbia, the freeways, Hollywood and Los Angeles -- it might all be a scene from Steinbeck's ''Cannery Row.'' In the mellow air under the creamy sky out over the water, all California seems to be a place of innocence.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
