<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reyes Starts to Bring His Power Up to Speed</title>
    <meta content="06mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/sports/baseball/06mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838416"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Reyes, Jose</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DB173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="928" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reyes Starts to Bring His Power Up to Speed</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mets’ Reyes Is Adding Thunder to His Lightning</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shpigel, Ben</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, April 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By 8 a.m. six mornings a week during the off-season, José Reyes was already sprinting in the outfield of a small stadium near his home in the Dominican Republic. ''I want to be faster,'' Reyes said.</p>
        <p>At 10 p.m. most evenings, Reyes retreated to his workout room for a few hours. ''I wanted to get stronger,'' Reyes said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is becoming increasingly apparent that José Reyes is evolving into the rare leadoff hitter who can claim both power and speed as elements of his game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By 8 a.m. six mornings a week during the off-season, José Reyes was already sprinting in the outfield of a small stadium near his home in the Dominican Republic. ''I want to be faster,'' Reyes said.</p>
        <p>At 10 p.m. most evenings, Reyes retreated to his workout room for a few hours. ''I wanted to get stronger,'' Reyes said.</p>
        <p>There is no telling if Reyes can get any faster; he has already been timed in under three seconds while running from first base to second. But Reyes reported to spring training with five pounds of added muscle and, a season removed from hitting a career-high 19 home runs, it is becoming increasingly apparent that he is evolving into the rare leadoff hitter who can claim both power and speed as elements of his game.</p>
        <p>It may not be this season, and it may not be next season, but the Mets believe that the 23-year-old Reyes could eventually gain entrance into the 30-homer, 30-steal club. If it happens, he would join an exclusive group of leadoff hitters. Of the 48 30-30 seasons in baseball history, according to the Elias Sports Bureau, only 6 have been by a player who spent the majority of the season batting leadoff: Alfonso Soriano (2002, 2003, 2006), Bobby Bonds (1973, 1975) and Tommy Harper (1970).</p>
        <p>''No doubt in my mind,'' said Rickey Henderson, the Mets' special instructor who is considered the greatest leadoff hitter of all time. ''But if he's trying to hit 30, he'll never do it. He needs to get better in a few other areas, and then, if he does those well, the home runs may come. And even if they don't, he'll still be a pretty darn good player.''</p>
        <p>The Mets have projected Reyes to do about what he did last season, when he hit .300, and led the league in triples (17) and stolen bases (64). He also played such solid defense that a Gold Glove award seems inevitable. Only two players -- Honus Wagner in 1908 and Willie McGee in 1985 -- preceded Reyes in hitting .300 with at least 15 triples, 10 home runs, 20 doubles and 50 steals. For the Mets, Reyes's home runs are a bonus because they were never expected; he hit only 13 home runs through 343 minor league games.</p>
        <p>''I was trying to be a better hitter, not hit for power,'' Reyes said.</p>
        <p>But at nearly the same pace as Reyes has improved his plate discipline and started taking walks, his 6-foot-1 frame has continued filling out to 199 pounds. The combination has helped him develop the power seen Wednesday night, when he hit his first homer of the season in the Mets' 10-0 victory in St. Louis. He led the Mets with five spring home runs and was the team's only player to hit three in one game last season, Aug. 15 in Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>Henderson hit 20 or more home runs four times in his career. The first time was in 1985 with the Yankees, but that did not happen until his sixth full season in the major leagues. That season, Henderson batted .314, picked up 99 walks and scored 146 runs. He said those statistics are the ones Reyes should aspire to, rather than the number of home runs he can hit.</p>
        <p>''Think about it, pitchers would love him to hit home runs because they wouldn't have to worry about him on the bases anymore,'' said Henderson, whose season high in home runs was 28. ''José is feared on the bases like I was feared on the bases. But he's not feared at the plate yet. When he gets to that point, he'll put the fear of God into everyone.''</p>
        <p>Even if his power develops soon, his overall game should benefit. Pitchers concerned about putting him on base may leave a pitch or two over the plate. If they worry about him hitting a home run, pitching around him could backfire. With him on base, a pitcher may throw more fastballs to those hitting behind Reyes to improve the catcher's odds of throwing him out.</p>
        <p>Tom Glavine said he could think of only three players aside from Reyes -- Henderson, Soriano and Rafael Furcal -- who wreak as much havoc at the plate as they do on the basepaths.</p>
        <p>''In the long run, you worry about his speed more because once you hit a home run, the damage is done, it's over with,'' Glavine said. ''But if a guy like José gets on first, you start thinking about the stolen base. It lingers and increases the likelihood that you're going to pay more attention to him and less attention to the batter.''</p>
        <p>When told of Glavine's remarks, Reyes nodded and smiled. He knows that, more than anything, he is counted on to ignite the offense. When opposing coaches invoke Reyes's name during pregame strategy meetings, they focus on his speed. When Reyes reaches first base, some players have told him, it's like hitting a triple. ''I steal second, and then I steal third,'' Reyes said. ''That's why I'm going to take more walks this year. I think I'm going to be even better.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>With the Braves completing their three-game sweep of Philadelphia on Thursday, their home opener Friday night against the Mets, the team that dethroned them, may seem like an early season showdown for divisional supremacy. The Mets will start Oliver Pérez against the left-hander Mark Redman. Tom Glavine will face John Smoltz on Saturday, and Orlando Hernández is scheduled to pitch against Kyle Davies in Sunday's finale.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
