<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Material Muse for Some Strange Bedfellows</title>
    <meta content="06bran" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/arts/design/06bran.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838261"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Whitney Museum of American Art</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00EED6163FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="774" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Material Muse for Some Strange Bedfellows</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Material Muse for Some Strange Bedfellows</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARTHA SCHWENDENER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schwendener, Martha</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the 1950s art and poetry were the hottest couple in downtown Manhattan. Painters referenced poetry. Poets wrote art criticism. John Ashbery claimed to approach words ''abstractly, as an artist uses paint.'' In the 1960s, however, poetry's influence faded and advertising became art's favored muse.</p>
        <p>Now, in a small, tight show at the Whitney Museum of American Art at Altria, organized by the branch's manager, Howie Chen, and titled ''Where Were We,'' Matthew Brannon brings these subjects -- art, poetry and advertising -- back together, after a fashion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Matthew Brannon uses art, poetry and advertising to comment on mainstream consumer culture in a small, tight show at the Whitney Museum of American Art at Altria.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the 1950s art and poetry were the hottest couple in downtown Manhattan. Painters referenced poetry. Poets wrote art criticism. John Ashbery claimed to approach words ''abstractly, as an artist uses paint.'' In the 1960s, however, poetry's influence faded and advertising became art's favored muse.</p>
        <p>Now, in a small, tight show at the Whitney Museum of American Art at Altria, organized by the branch's manager, Howie Chen, and titled ''Where Were We,'' Matthew Brannon brings these subjects -- art, poetry and advertising -- back together, after a fashion.</p>
        <p>Art in this context is no longer the big, gestural, heroic painting it was in the 1950s, but neatly composed poster-size prints. Mr. Brannon's silkscreen, lithograph and letterpress images borrow from traditional art sources like Japanese ukiyo-e prints, but more significantly from mid-20th-century advertising layouts, corporate reports and the textile designs of the Swedish artist Astrid Sampe and the Finnish company Marimekko.</p>
        <p>Poetry is reconceived as a cross between pop-music lyrics and advertising slogans. And advertising? The public relations arm of the American Dream, with its winning blend of snappy text and eye-catching image, is presented here as a roiling stew of poisoned psychology where nothing is possible. (Mr. Brannon titled an earlier series of posters ''A Pessimistic Production.'')</p>
        <p>''Pigs, Like Us'' features silhouette images of office supplies (paper clips, pencils, Post-its) and an iPod -- emblems of the white-collar worker -- rendered in crisp, atomic-era advertising colors: red, black and sky blue. There is also an expressionist touch in the form of a ring of coffee from a mug. Below these pictogramlike images is text, standard for Mr. Brannon in its emphasis on paranoia, careerism, consumption and excess. It reads, ''They had to pump her stomach/amazing what they found/among the arugula, watercress, bluefin tuna, age-dried steak/there it is/your heart/and look /a bunch of razor blades/little light bulbs/cocaine/little travel bottles/anti-depressants/your old untouched job application.''</p>
        <p>''Say It Again'' shows a 1950s-style backyard grill rendered in atomic blue and an existential rumination: ''When you read this I will be dead/Well if not really dead -- then one day/and you too -- one day/will be dead/but even then/one could say/that you had read this/but that's not what matters now.''</p>
        <p>Artistic concerns collapse into noir halfway through ''Adult Education,'' a poster populated with black silhouettes of pigeons. ''It's abstract,'' Mr. Brannon starts, ''it's totally abstract/I copied it/I stole it from you/I ripped the page right out of the book/word for word/you weren't doing much with it anyway/uh/when we pull off we make a right/then it's about five miles before we turn left onto the dirt road/you should see it on the right/the place where the bodies were found.''</p>
        <p>In his writing, Mr. Brannon has carved out a niche between classic Conceptualism, with its cerebral, perceptual musings, and the fragmented borrowing of Language poetry (and perhaps even the crime fiction of Jim Thompson). Mr. Brannon also owes plenty to Mike Kelley, Richard Prince and Barbara Kruger, artists who have mined the depths of mainstream consumer culture and employed text in their works.</p>
        <p>But where irony has been a mainstay for Mr. Prince and Mr. Kelley, with the artist standing apart from mass culture and commenting on it like a disinterested viewer, everyone is implicated in Mr. Brannon's work -- even the contemporary artist who wants, as much as any American, an iPod, organic produce and someone perfect to love him.</p>
        <p>Two posters without text particularly recall Ms. Sampe's textile designs and include items from a sushi dinner, depicted as colorful geometric motifs and laid out against pink and light-blue grounds. In the upper corner of one poster is an abstracted but identifiable image of an American Express card, a reminder that tasteful objects and our desire for them is tied to the world of commerce and advertising.</p>
        <p>In this context, referencing mid-20th-century visual culture -- and especially design, with its populist, utopian view toward outfitting the world with attractive, modern accessories -- seems particularly appropriate. Mr. Brannon generally avoids specific historical markers, mixing contemporary images with styles from the past, but he throws up a tiny flare in one work: a letterpress print with an abstract motif -- a large, unbounded square filled with smaller black and yellow squares -- that simply reads, ''JFK International Airport.'' The work serves as a terse nod to an age when everything seemed possible, even flying to the moon.</p>
        <p>We've been there and done that, of course. Yet, Mr. Brannon reminds us, even that didn't sate our desires, cure our phobias or make us happy.</p>
        <p>''Matthew Brannon: Where Were We'' continues through Aug. 31 at the Whitney Museum of American Art at Altria, 120 Park Avenue, at 42nd Street, (917) 663-2453.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
