<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giuliani Reaffirms That He Would Not Seek Abortion Changes</title>
    <meta content="06giuliani" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/us/politics/06giuliani.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838349"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HEADING TOWARD 2008"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Santora, Marc</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Giuliani, Rudolph W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E5DC173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giuliani Reaffirms That He Would Not Seek Abortion Changes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Giuliani Reaffirms That He Would Not Seek Abortion Changes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARC SANTORA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Santora, Marc</byline>
      <dateline>CHARLESTON, S.C., April 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rudolph W Giuliani, campaigning in South Carolina, firmly states as president he would not seek to make abortion illegal; says he believes abortion is wrong, but that it is woman's right; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rudolph W. Giuliani, campaigning in South Carolina, firmly stated that as president he would not seek to make abortion illegal.</p>
        <p>Aware of the damage his position might do to him among some conservative voters, Mr. Giuliani said that if someone was inclined to vote against him solely because of his stance on abortion, then so be it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“I think abortion is wrong,” Rudolph W. Giuliani said. “But ultimately, I think it is a woman’s right, a woman’s choice.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rudolph W. Giuliani, campaigning in South Carolina, firmly stated that as president he would not seek to make abortion illegal.</p>
        <p>Aware of the damage his position might do to him among some conservative voters, Mr. Giuliani said that if someone was inclined to vote against him solely because of his stance on abortion, then so be it.</p>
        <p>''I think abortion is wrong,'' he said. ''But ultimately, I think it is a woman's right, a woman's choice. And government should not interfere with it by imposing criminal penalties on people.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani, a Roman Catholic who once considered joining the priesthood, has wrestled with the abortion question for years, often expressing his personal opposition. But he has also long supported keeping abortion legal.</p>
        <p>From the moment he entered the presidential race, he has faced questions about whether his stance might hurt him with voters. When he campaigned in South Carolina two months ago, he said that, as president, he would appoint ''strict constructionist'' justices to the Supreme Court. Many saw that as a coded endorsement of the position of abortion rights opponents who want candidates to pledge to appoint justices who would overturn Roe v. Wade, the 1973 court ruling declaring a constitutional right to abortion.</p>
        <p>At an earlier appearance Thursday in the state capital, Columbia, Mr. Giuliani said that was not the case.</p>
        <p>''The present state of the law on these issues is not something that I would seek to change,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Later, in Charleston, when asked if he worried that this stance might hurt his chances in the South Carolina primary next year, he offered no apologies.</p>
        <p>''What I would say to people who disagree with me,'' he said, ''is, How much is the disagreement, and then, what are the other important issues to you?''</p>
        <p>His comments came on the last day of a four-state campaign swing that began Monday night in New Hampshire. In his speeches, he has focused little on social issues, talking instead about fighting terrorism, cutting taxes and promoting energy independence.</p>
        <p>The questions about abortion came after he again stated his support for public financing of abortion in an interview with CNN in Florida on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, in response to reporters' questions, Mr. Giuliani expanded on why he supported public financing.</p>
        <p>''The best way to handle funding is to follow the law,'' he said. ''Federal funds are used only in very limited cases for abortion, and it is left for a state-by-state decision. I have expressed previously that I am very comfortable with that.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani's position puts him at odds with the other leading Republican presidential candidates, Mitt Romney and Senator John McCain of Arizona.</p>
        <p>Mr. Romney, the former governor of Massachusetts who won office with significant Democratic support, has in the past supported abortion rights. Now, he promises voters that as president he would seek to overturn the Roe decision.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain has taken a similar public position.</p>
        <p>But as Mr. Giuliani begins to introduce himself to voters, he made it clear on Thursday that he was prepared to live with the consequences of his position on abortion.</p>
        <p>On another issue important to conservative voters, gun control, Mr. Giuliani said he believed that the Constitution clearly supported a right to bear arms and that any regulation should be done state by state.</p>
        <p>Abortion opponents and religious groups, including the Southern Baptist Convention, have already voiced their unease with Mr. Giuliani's stance on abortion, even earlier this year when he spoke of strict constructionism and it seemed to some that he might be moving closer to their view. But on Thursday, Mr. Giuliani left little room for a change in his position.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, it will be voters like John and Chris Schuler of Summerville, S.C., who decide if Mr. Giuliani's stance on abortion will keep them from voting for him.</p>
        <p>Both Republicans, the Schulers said they did not yet know whom they would support. They stood on the sidewalk outside Magnolia's restaurant in downtown Charleston, hoping to see the man they mainly knew from television after Sept. 11.</p>
        <p>''We are pro-life, and that is a big issue with us,'' Mrs. Schuler said. But she said she was not sure the abortion issue alone would make her vote one way or another. On social issues, she said, Mr. Romney probably held views closer to her own.</p>
        <p>''But with Mitt Romney, there is the whole Mormon issue,'' she said, referring to Mr. Romney's religion. ''They have different family values than Christians and Catholics.''</p>
        <p>HEADING TOWARD 2008</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
