<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Again, Kerkorian Makes a Move for Chrysler</title>
    <meta content="06auto" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/business/06auto.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838368"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tracinda Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Automobile Workers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerkorian, Kirk</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">York, Jerome B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zetsche, Dieter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Iacocca, Lee A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maynard, Micheline</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Chrysler Group</org>
        <org class="online_producer">DaimlerChrysler AG</org>
        <org class="online_producer">United Automobile Workers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Renault SA</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Nissan Motor Co</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Morgan, J P, Chase &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Daimler-Benz AG</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Blackstone Group</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Magna International Incorporated</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Kerkorian, Kirk</person>
        <person class="online_producer">York, Jerome B</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Zetsche, Dieter</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Ghosn, Carlos</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Iacocca, Lee A</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E1DC173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1414" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Again, Kerkorian Makes a Move for Chrysler</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Again, Kerkorian Makes a Move for Chrysler</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHELINE MAYNARD; Nick Bunkley contributed reporting from New York, and Ian Austen from Ottawa.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Maynard, Micheline; York, Jerome B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kirk Kerkorian's investment arm Tracinda Corp makes $4.5 billion cash offer for struggling Chrysler Group that hinges on winning exclusive right to negotiate with DaimlerChrysler and deal with United Automobile Workers union that could mean worker concessions; bid is made public in letters from Jerome B York, Kerkorian's longtime financial adviser and former Chrysler chief financial officer; letters were sent to DaimlerChrysler's chief executive Dieter Zetsche and to company's supervisory board; bid has support of Chrysler's former chief Lee A Iacocca, who joined Kerkorian in his 1995 takeover attempt; Tracinda deal would also depend on reaching new labor agreement with United Auto Workers, which opens national contract talks with Detroit companies in summer; would also hinge on whether Tracinda and DaimlerChrysler can agree to share Chrysler's $18 billion employee health care liability, seen as sticking point in any deal DaimlerChrysler might reach; graph; chart; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kirk Kerkorian is back. After making billions on brazen investments in Hollywood, Las Vegas and Detroit, he is now pursuing Chrysler once more, a dozen years after his last attempt.</p>
        <p>His investment arm, the Tracinda Corporation, made a $4.5 billion cash offer yesterday for the struggling Chrysler Group that hinges on winning the exclusive right to negotiate with DaimlerChrysler and a deal with the United Automobile Workers union that could mean worker concessions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After failing in one takeover in the 1990s, the billionaire has returned with a $4.5 billion bid for the automaker.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Kirk Kerkorian is back. After making billions on brazen investments in Hollywood, Las Vegas and Detroit, he is now pursuing Chrysler once more, a dozen years after his last attempt.</p>
        <p>His investment arm, the Tracinda Corporation, made a $4.5 billion cash offer yesterday for the struggling Chrysler Group that hinges on winning the exclusive right to negotiate with DaimlerChrysler and a deal with the United Automobile Workers union that could mean worker concessions.</p>
        <p>The bid -- showing that Mr. Kerkorian cannot break his Chrysler habit -- was made public in letters from Jerome B. York, Mr. Kerkorian's longtime financial adviser and a former Chrysler chief financial officer. The letters were sent to DaimlerChrysler's chief executive, Dieter Zetsche, and to the company's supervisory board.</p>
        <p>''Tracinda believes by taking a long-term approach to solving Chrysler's problems, it can become a robust and lasting stand-alone entity,'' the company said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerkorian's bid for Chrysler comes less than a year after he bought 10 percent of General Motors, had Mr. York put on the G.M. board and then tried to broker an alliance between the automaker and Renault of France and Nissan of Japan, both run by Carlos Ghosn.</p>
        <p>Now, both Chrysler and the union must decide how to respond to the unexpected offer from Mr. Kerkorian, who turns 90 on June 6.</p>
        <p>The group of bidders seemed to have been winnowed down to two investment firms and a Canadian auto parts company. Mr. Kerkorian tried to align with the initial group, his lawyer, Terry Christensen, said yesterday. When JPMorgan, which is handling the bidding process, did not send the packet of information provided to the others, Mr. Christensen said, Mr. Kerkorian directed him to make the offer and handle the details later.</p>
        <p>The bid has the support of Lee A. Iacocca, Chrysler's former chief who joined Mr. Kerkorian in his 1995 takeover attempt.</p>
        <p>''I talked to Lee, and he said, 'Terry, this is great,' '' Mr. Christensen said. He said he did not know whether Mr. Iacocca would want to serve on the Chrysler board should Mr. Kerkorian finally buy the company, or whether Mr. York would serve as its chairman or chief executive.</p>
        <p>It is the second time in a dozen years that Mr. Kerkorian has tried to buy Chrysler, whose stock he first bought in 1990 when the company was battered by another industry downturn. That investment ultimately grew to 100 million shares, and he reaped billions of dollars in profit when Daimler-Benz bought Chrysler in 1998.</p>
        <p>Tracinda, which does not hold any DaimlerChrysler shares, joined Cerberus Capital, the Blackstone Group and Magna International of Canada in making initial proposals to buy Chrysler, which Mr. Zetsche said Wednesday had officially been put up for sale. Magna's bid is thought to be in the range of the Tracinda offer, about $4.6 billion. The other bids are said to be as high as $13 billion.</p>
        <p>Tracinda's goal is to restore an American automotive icon and run it with a long-term view, the company said in the letters to Mr. Zetsche and DaimlerChrysler.</p>
        <p>Tracinda would put up $100 million for the exclusive right to perform due diligence on Chrysler, with $25 million going to DaimlerChrysler if the deal does not go through.</p>
        <p>Tracinda would give stock in the company to Chrysler employees, something they had received after a federal rescue plan in 1979 that helped the company avoid bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>That could take the form of an employee stock ownership plan, although Tracinda does not need an ESOP to arrange financing for the deal, Mr. Christensen said.</p>
        <p>A Tracinda deal would also depend on reaching a new labor agreement with the U.A.W., which opens national contract talks with Detroit companies this summer.</p>
        <p>It would also hinge on whether Tracinda and DaimlerChrysler could agree to share Chrysler's $18 billion employee health care liability, seen as a sticking point in any deal DaimlerChrysler might reach.</p>
        <p>Mr. Christensen said Chrysler workers would need to make sacrifices in wages and benefits, something he said that they would face in any case given the poor financial conditions at the Detroit auto companies.</p>
        <p>''Obviously they will be asked to give concessions, but they should not have to do that for nothing,'' Mr. Christensen said.</p>
        <p>The offer was the first to become public in the seven weeks since DaimlerChrysler said it was keeping its options open for Chrysler, which lost $1.5 billion last year and has required two overhauls since the 1998 merger that created a global automotive giant.</p>
        <p>''It's a pretty bold move,'' said Stefano Aversa, co-president of AlixPartners, a restructuring firm in Southfield, Mich.</p>
        <p>''You certainly can't say they lack a sense of theater,'' Mr. Aversa said.</p>
        <p>It gives ammunition to DaimlerChrysler stockholders who have called for the automaker to dump Chrysler and regroup as a luxury carmaker, focusing on Mercedes-Benz.</p>
        <p>Indeed, investors greeted the bid with enthusiasm. DaimlerChrysler shares rose $4.24, to $84.80, an all-time high when adjusted for splits and dividends.</p>
        <p>Yet the conditions put pressure on Mr. Zetsche and union leaders to give an indication of whether they would prefer to deal with Mr. Kerkorian or continue the bidding process with those already in the fray.</p>
        <p>Mr. Christensen said Mr. Kerkorian was interested in receiving a response as quickly as possible, and planned to conclude his due diligence within 60 days.</p>
        <p>But analysts, industry executives and bankers involved in the negotiations all said Mr. Zetsche would do best to bide his time.</p>
        <p>''We are in contact with various interested parties,'' a DaimlerChrysler spokesman, Han Tjan, said yesterday. ''Mr. Zetsche is very pleased with the process and all options are still open.''</p>
        <p>The first inkling of a Chrysler sale came last October, when Bodo Uebber, the chief financial officer at DaimlerChrysler, said the company was exploring its options. Chrysler officials quickly denied that meant Chrysler was for sale.</p>
        <p>But the automaker reported losses of $1.5 billion in 2006, when its sales and market share dropped in the United States after gains in 2005. Chrysler dealers were saddled with big supplies of sport utility vehicles and pickups, which make up nearly 75 percent of the company's lineup, despite the rise in gasoline prices.</p>
        <p>In February, Chrysler announced a revamping plan, its second in the last six years, that calls for it to eliminate 13,000 jobs and to close all or part of four plants through 2008. It will shut its assembly plant in Newark, Del.</p>
        <p>The U.A.W. did not comment on the Tracinda bid, but its president, Ron Gettelfinger, previously said that he preferred to see the company remain part of Chrysler rather than be sold to an investor. Mr. Gettelfinger sits on the DaimlerChrysler supervisory board, which will ultimately decide Chrysler's fate.</p>
        <p>The president of the Canadian Auto Workers, Basil Hargrove, criticized the bid and said he would work with other company unions to oppose it.</p>
        <p>Animosity toward Mr. Kerkorian at DaimlerChrysler may run deeper than just the unions, however.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerkorian had a number of battles with Chrysler management in the 1990s, and in 2005, he lost a federal lawsuit in which he charged that he had been deceived by DaimlerChrysler management. Mr. Kerkorian contended that management won his support for the $36 billion deal in 1998 by portraying it as a ''merger of equals'' when, in fact, it was a takeover of Chrysler by Daimler-Benz.</p>
        <p>That history may explain why DaimlerChrysler delayed providing him with the deal book.</p>
        <p>''Just a few years ago, he was suing DaimlerChrysler. I'm sure Germany said, 'We're not sending Kirk Kerkorian a book,' '' said one investment adviser involved in the bidding, who spoke on condition of anonymity.</p>
        <p>Said Mr. Christensen, ''It was always an interesting relationship.''</p>
        <p>But he said there was no animosity on Mr. Kerkorian's part toward Mr. Zetsche, whom, he said, Mr. Kerkorian does not even know.</p>
        <p>Mr. York was named to the G.M. board in February 2006 and left the board last October after G.M. rejected the idea of the alliance. Mr. Kerkorian, who was G.M.'s biggest shareholder, sold his stock soon after that and made a tiny return.</p>
        <p>The latest chapter in Mr. Kerkorian's chase of a Detroit auto company is bound to be the talk of two continents this weekend.</p>
        <p>''Everything's in play right now,'' said David Cole, chairman of the Center for Automotive Research in Ann Arbor, Mich. ''These guys are smart financial people, but you can't disregard the role that egos play in this.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
