<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>This Deal Is Encouraging And Absurd</title>
    <meta content="06norris" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/business/media/06norris.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838369"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HIGH &amp; LOW FINANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tribune Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zell, Samuel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Floyd Norris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Tribune Company</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Zell, Samuel</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E1DC173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="812" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>This Deal Is Encouraging And Absurd</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">This Deal Is Encouraging and Absurd</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Floyd Norris column on real estate tycoon Samuel Zell's acquisition of Tribune Co; says deal is tale of two markets: one has unbridled optimism and believes that risk is thing of past, while other has experienced severe losses and can think of no reason those losses will not become worse; says first market is leveraged loan market, which is growing rapidly and is willing to take risks that would have been deemed foolhardy few years ago; holds second market is one for newspaper stocks; says over last three years, average such stock has lost more than third of its value, while overall American stock market has gained 25 percent; notes owners are depressed and fearful, and so are employees; says combination has produced one of most absurd deal ever; holds deal is absurd because those who will lend money to company are taking on equity risks if things go wrong, but will not get equity benefits if they go right (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THIS is a tale of two markets. One has unbridled optimism and believes that risk is a thing of the past. The other has experienced severe losses and can think of no reason those losses will not become worse.</p>
        <p>Put those markets together, throw in some generous tax breaks, and you have Sam Zell taking over the Tribune Company for almost nothing, with shareholders happy to get out at a price that is well below the company's average share price over the last decade.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lenders and workers are taking the risks in the Tribune Company deal, but most of the benefits will go to Sam Zell.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THIS is a tale of two markets. One has unbridled optimism and believes that risk is a thing of the past. The other has experienced severe losses and can think of no reason those losses will not become worse.</p>
        <p>Put those markets together, throw in some generous tax breaks, and you have Sam Zell taking over the Tribune Company for almost nothing, with shareholders happy to get out at a price that is well below the company's average share price over the last decade.</p>
        <p>The first market is the leveraged loan market, which is growing rapidly and is willing to take risks that would have been deemed foolhardy a few years ago.</p>
        <p>The rates on loans rated in the nether regions of junk are higher than the rates on high-quality loans, but not by much. The bond rating agencies moan that such rates in no way cover the risk of default, but in recent years there have been few defaults. Almost any corporate loan can be financed these days.</p>
        <p>The second market is the one for newspaper stocks. Over the last three years, the average such stock has lost more than a third of its value, while the overall American stock market has gained 25 percent. Owners are depressed and fearful, and so are employees.</p>
        <p>The combination has produced one of the most absurd deals ever, albeit one that seems likely to be completed if no higher bid emerges and the loan market does not suddenly grow conservative.</p>
        <p>The deal is absurd not because Mr. Zell is likely to lose his money. He may, but the potential rewards more than offset the risk. It is absurd because those who will lend the money to the company are taking on equity risks if things go wrong, but will not get equity benefits if they go right.</p>
        <p>The employees could prosper -- eventually -- from the employee stock ownership plan, or ESOP, that will own the company until Mr. Zell exercises his right to buy 40 percent of it. But it will be a decade before employees will be allowed to cash in even a part of their ESOP shares.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, the company will be cutting the cash it sets aside for their retirement. If the company falters, the workers could find that they have no jobs, and a lot of company stock that has little value. Most of Mr. Zell's investment will be classified as a loan to the company, giving him a chance of recovering money even if the stock becomes worthless.</p>
        <p>The workers will also be working for a company saddled with $13 billion of debt. Will there be more and more rounds of staff reductions? No one is saying.</p>
        <p>To make this deal work, Tribune is relying on a combination of tax benefits that assure the company will not pay a dime of income tax for years to come. Its annual profits, if there are any, will be attributed to the ESOP -- and the ESOP is exempt from paying taxes on them.</p>
        <p>''Taxpayers are silent partners in this deal,'' said Robert Willens, a tax analyst with Lehman Brothers. ''But we don't get any of the upside.''</p>
        <p>To those of us who care deeply about the future of newspapers, this deal is encouraging. At long last, someone without an existing tie to the industry has stepped up to say he sees value in it. No such person turned up when Knight Ridder was auctioned.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zell's record as an investor is not flawless, but it is very good. He has just cashed in on commercial real estate at a time when prices are high, and is buying something that Wall Street hates. He appears to be in it for the money, not for the psychic value of owning a paper that makes him a big man in town.</p>
        <p>It would be more encouraging if someone had stepped up without relying so much on tax breaks that will increase the government's budget deficit without bringing much net benefit to the employees, since the elimination of company contributions to existing 401(k) plans will offset the benefits of the ESOP.</p>
        <p>Those tax breaks have been around for decades, and were used by Tribune nearly two decades ago when it set up an earlier ESOP and froze benefits in its traditional defined-benefit pension plan.</p>
        <p>They are largely the legacy of Senator Russell Long, a Louisiana Democrat who led the Senate Finance Committee and was passionate about encouraging employee ownership.</p>
        <p>Senator Long once remarked that the attitude of those who came before his committee could be summarized as: ''Don't tax you. Don't tax me. Tax that fellow behind the tree.''</p>
        <p>These days, that attitude seems almost quaint, since it assumes someone should pay taxes. Tribune will no longer do so. But at least one smart investor is betting that newspapers have a future.</p>
        <p>HIGH &amp; LOW FINANCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
