<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fort Worth, With a Cowboy Past, Has an Artistic Present</title>
    <meta content="06american" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/travel/escapes/06american.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838291"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AMERICAN JOURNEYS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Fort Worth (Tex)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Texas</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woodward, Richard B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas/Fort Worth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Fort Worth (Tex)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E1DF173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1655" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fort Worth, With a Cowboy Past, Has an Artistic Present</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Fort Worth, With a Cowboy Past, Has an Artistic Present</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD B. WOODWARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Woodward, Richard B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on visit to Fort Worth, Tex, concentrating on its museums and art galleries; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SEEING Fort Worth and skipping Dallas is sort of like visiting Buda but not Pest. The two cities are so codependent by now, intertwined by their joint airport and a network of interstates, that outsiders can be forgiven for lumping them together.</p>
        <p>That would be a mistake. Each locale still jealously guards its own identity. Citizens from one place tend to slight the other. Dallas has the razzle-dazzle and loves to flaunt its wealth, while Fort Worth clings to its origins as a cow town and has a sleepier pace.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even with tony museums that provide a rare chance to study masterworks, it still feels like Texas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SEEING Fort Worth and skipping Dallas is sort of like visiting Buda but not Pest. The two cities are so codependent by now, intertwined by their joint airport and a network of interstates, that outsiders can be forgiven for lumping them together.</p>
        <p>That would be a mistake. Each locale still jealously guards its own identity. Citizens from one place tend to slight the other. Dallas has the razzle-dazzle and loves to flaunt its wealth, while Fort Worth clings to its origins as a cow town and has a sleepier pace.</p>
        <p>Both cities have outstanding art museums, but Fort Worth's are on a uniformly intimate scale that provides a rare opportunity to study closely, and for prolonged lengths of time, any number of individual masterworks from every period of history and part of the globe. On weekdays, the crowds can be so sparse that it feels as if these little palaces have been cordoned off just for you.</p>
        <p>Three distinct areas of Fort Worth cater to tourists -- the Cultural District, where the city discreetly husbands many of its finest art treasures; Sundance Square downtown, where the one museum has an appropriately western focus; and the former Stockyards, whose stores and restaurants invite a post-gallery break. For art, the essential stop is the Cultural District, but you'll want to sample all three, especially if your interest extends to architecture.</p>
        <p>Fort Worth is a city dominated by a few families, none mightier than the billionaire Bass clan, famous for giving generously to George W. Bush's campaigns and for revitalizing the north end of Fort Worth. The two square blocks they bought in 1978 -- and renamed Sundance Square -- have expanded to more than 35 square blocks dominated by a pair of brutalist skyscrapers designed by Paul Rudolph in the '70s and now holding the headquarters of the Bass businesses.</p>
        <p>Local attitudes about the Basses' creation of Sundance Square vary from gratitude (the downtown was sorely blighted in the '70s, and the Bass family could easily have adopted other causes) to sotto voce resentment -- the nickname for their private security force, which patrols the area on foot and bicycles, is the ''Bass-tapo.''</p>
        <p>David Schwarz, the Bass family's favorite architect, has contributed buildings in the Texas Deco style (blending Art Deco with state symbols like the star), including Bass Performance Hall, the city's major site for opera, symphony, and touring Broadway shows. It's also the site where every four years finalists in the vaunted international piano competition, begun by and named after a local hero, Van Cliburn, fight it out. The buildings in this part of town that most warrant inspection, though, are the Sinclair Building, an authentic Art Deco landmark from 1930, and the pink-granite Beaux Arts-style Tarrant County Courthouse, erected in 1895 and lovingly restored in 1983.</p>
        <p>At the newly reopened Sid Richardson Museum in the square, 38 oil paintings by Frederic Remington, Charles Russell and other Western artists show only a tiny sample of the romantic taste of Sid Richardson, a millionaire oilman and Bass relative, who collected work on Indian and cowboy themes.</p>
        <p>Better works by both artists can be seen in abundance at the Amon Carter Museum, which should be your first stop in the Cultural District, about five miles west of Sundance. Carter, who made his fortune in newspapers and radio, was one of Richardson's best friends and a Fort Worth booster who hated Dallas so much he reportedly carried his lunch whenever he had to visit so he wouldn't have to spend money there. His bequest financed what is now one of the leading collections of American art in the country, especially strong in Western paintings, 19th century photographs, and Remington sculptures.</p>
        <p>The museum's original 1961 building by Philip Johnson was expanded in the late '90s into a visitor-friendly place -- during my visit a volunteer demonstrated old camera equipment and encouraged visitors to handle it -- which the curators balance with scholarly shows. Their latest, on the painter William Ranney, popular before the Civil War for his scenes of frontier life, runs through May 13. In keeping with much of the art inside, a warning at the museum entrance reminds visitors that carrying firearms inside is illegal -- another sign that you're in Texas.</p>
        <p>Too many museums in a row can be deadly, even when they're as excellent and relatively small as those in the Cultural District. My wife and I broke up the tour by visiting the nearby Fort Worth Botanic Garden. Our timing was perfect: hundreds of cedar waxwings on their way north decided to rest in the gardens' blossoming trees.</p>
        <p>Refreshed, we were primed for the Kimbell Art Museum and the Modern Art Museum of Fort Worth.</p>
        <p>The Kimbell provides an unrivaled museum experience combining first-rate architecture and first-rate art. From the street, the 1972 building designed by Louis I. Kahn, offers a plain travertine exterior that will not prepare you for the soaring harmonies inside. To step into the lobby is to enter a Romanesque church of a museum. Long slits and diffusing louvers in the barrel-vaulted ceiling allow the light to both cut spaces dramatically and softly spill over them.</p>
        <p>The collections, from all periods and places, are noteworthy for both aesthetic quality and historical depth. An 11th-century Cambodian statue of Siva is less a representative object than a stunningly beautiful one. European paintings -- with masterpieces by Bellini, Mantegna, Caravaggio, Velázquez, de la Tour, Goya, Cézanne -- are mostly presented without glass.</p>
        <p>The guards don't hover at the Kimbell. The airy installations and low-key exhibitions, like the show on Japanese ukiyo-e painting and calligraphy that runs through April 29, encourage serious, face-to-face communion with great art. We were tempted to stay at the Kimbell for dinner in its restaurant, but opted instead for drinks in the garden.</p>
        <p>The Modern Art Museum next door has been another isle of tranquillity since it opened a new building in 2002. The architect, Tadao Ando, oriented the building around a shallow pool so that several of the wings extend outward and seem to float on the water.</p>
        <p>The galleries are arrayed with a select group of postwar and contemporary works -- usual suspects like Jackson Pollock and Dan Flavin, as well as rarities in American museums, like the German Minimalist sculptor Ulrich Rückriem.</p>
        <p>Whether in the sunlit bays beside the water, where you may find a lead floor piece by Carl Andre, or in a cul-de-sac where a wooden ladderlike sculpture by Martin Puryear reaches between floors, the building is still very much the star.</p>
        <p>If the art in Fort Worth is top-notch, the eating was not, at least on this trip. Steak houses predominate: we had a terrific lunch but a disappointing and overpriced dinner at one of them, the Mercury Chop House. Our most enjoyable outing for a meal was breakfast at the Paris Coffee Shop, a Fort Worth institution since the Depression era. Who could resist a place that offers green tea as well as cheese grits and has ads on the menu for everything from music lessons to bail bondsmen?</p>
        <p>Choices for nighttime activities are also limited in Fort Worth. The live theaters (the experimental Hip Pocket and the black Jubilee) were not performing when I was there last month. But this being Texas, I felt obliged to go in search of country music. So while my wife stayed in our hotel to watch a Dixie Chicks documentary on pay-per-view, I drove out to mix with the Chicks' antagonists at Billy Bob's Texas, touted as the world's largest honky-tonk.</p>
        <p>In the Stockyards District since 1981, Billy Bob's, housed in a former cattle barn, should be visited at least once,and perhaps only once. Walk around and select your entertainment option: play pool or the 25-cent slot machines, watch live bull riding in a ring or sports on TV, eat barbecue or popcorn, shop for cowboy hats, try your luck at outmoded carnival games, drink at any of 32 bars, or dance and listen to acts on the two musical stages. Capacity is more than 6,000.</p>
        <p>Randy Travis was the main draw on my night, and the crowd was impressively huge and responsive. My few hours at Billy Bob's didn't measure up to my afternoon at Kahn's Kimbell or Mr. Ando's Modern Art Museum. Then again, I had to admit as I merged with the herd, sipping bourbon and envying the gliding two-steppers on the dance floor, it felt like a much more authentic and less imported aesthetic experience -- much more like Texas.</p>
        <p>IF YOU GO</p>
        <p>Billy Bob's, Museums and Architecture</p>
        <p>BECAUSE Fort Worth is not compact, a car is essential if you aren't going to crash your budget on very expensive cabs. Rentals are available at the Dallas/Fort Worth International Airport.</p>
        <p>Most visitors stay in Sundance Square, where hotels are plentiful. The Renaissance Worthington (200 Main Street; 817-870-1000) is vast enough, with 474 guestrooms and 30 suites, to offer a variety of prices, starting at $209 for a double on weekends. The Ashton (610 Main Street; 817-332-0100) is a boutique hotel, with 39 rooms starting at $280 a night.</p>
        <p>The Sid Richardson Museum, at 309 Main Street (817-332-6554) is open daily, and admission is free.</p>
        <p>Art museums in the Cultural District include the Amon Carter Museum (3501 Camp Bowie Boulevard; 817-738-1933; admission free); the Kimbell Art Museum (3333 Camp Bowie Boulevard; 817-332-8451; admission free); and the Modern Art Museum of Fort Worth (3200 Darnell Street; 817-738-9215; $8). All are closed Mondays.</p>
        <p>At the Paris Coffee Shop (704 West Magnolia Avenue; 817-335-2041), most items cost less than $5. The long lines for tables in the morning move quickly -- the place seats more than 100 -- or you can sit at the counter.</p>
        <p>At Billy Bob's Texas (2520 Rodeo Plaza; 817-624-7117), a general admission charge, which varies according to the performer, allows a customer to stand and listen to the musicians. Seating, food, drinks and some activities are extra.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN JOURNEYS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
