<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Arenas Out for Season, Playoffs Lose Some Flair</title>
    <meta content="06arenas" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/sports/basketball/06arenas.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838418"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Washington Wizards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Washington Wizards</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Arenas, Gilbert</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wallace, Gerald</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Grunfeld, Ernie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E2DB173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="568" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Arenas Out for Season, Playoffs Lose Some Flair</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With Arenas Out for Season, Playoffs Lose Some Flair</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gilbert Arenas limped off the court Wednesday night, his quiet concern in ominous contrast to his usual flamboyance. Yesterday, the Washington Wizards' title hopes flickered all but out when they learned that Arenas, their leading scorer, would be lost for the rest of the season. His injury also means the N.B.A. will be without the player who would have been its most colorful character in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>Arenas collided with Charlotte's Gerald Wallace, and a magnetic resonance imaging exam showed that Arenas tore a lateral meniscus in his left knee. He will be sidelined two to three months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Gilbert Arenas limped off the floor Wednesday night, the Wizards lost their leading scorer for the season and the N.B.A. lost one of its most colorful personalities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gilbert Arenas limped off the court Wednesday night, his quiet concern in ominous contrast to his usual flamboyance. Yesterday, the Washington Wizards' title hopes flickered all but out when they learned that Arenas, their leading scorer, would be lost for the rest of the season. His injury also means the N.B.A. will be without the player who would have been its most colorful character in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>Arenas collided with Charlotte's Gerald Wallace, and a magnetic resonance imaging exam showed that Arenas tore a lateral meniscus in his left knee. He will be sidelined two to three months.</p>
        <p>''His numbers have been M.V.P. caliber, he's had a great year and you feel for him because he's so competitive and loves to play so much,'' the Wizards' president, Ernie Grunfeld, said yesterday in a telephone interview. ''That competitive nature ensures that he'll do what it takes rehab-wise to get back on the court. This is one of those other things that he'll use to motivate himself.''</p>
        <p>Arenas is a dynamic force who has called himself Agent Zero and shouted out ''Hibachi!'' whenever he hit buzzer-beating shots. He is the player who wagered with fans, made games personal against the opposing coaches who cut him last summer from Team U.S.A. and threw his jersey into the stands after games with unrestrained zeal. Now, he has been muted far earlier than anyone expected.</p>
        <p>Arenas wrote on his Web blog after the surgery that there was ''no point in being sad. I can't do nothing about it.''</p>
        <p>He said that when he informed his teammates of the seriousness of his injury ''actually they thought I was playing when I said that I was done because I joke so much. But I think they'll do fine. They're a strong-minded team.''</p>
        <p>The Wizards, in sixth place in the Eastern Conference, have lost 7 of their last 10 games, including back-to-back games against lowly Charlotte.</p>
        <p>Arenas's injury proved to be a culmination of the team's problems that had been mounting since the All-Star Game break. Last Sunday in a game against Milwaukee, Caron Butler, the Wizards' other All-Star, fractured his right hand. The Wizards believe he will be lost for six to eight weeks.</p>
        <p>Antawn Jamison sprained his knee at the end of January, missing 12 games. Andray Blatche sprained his knee two weeks ago. He has missed six games and will likely miss five more.</p>
        <p>Arenas has averaged 28.5 points a game (fourth best in the league), won four games with buzzer-beating shots and was the Eastern Conference player of the month in December.</p>
        <p>''</p>
        <p>The Wizards play host to the Cavaliers tonight, the team that knocked them out of the playoffs in the first round last season after a memorable battle between Arenas and Cleveland's LeBron James. What will not be a part of this year's playoff memories is Arenas's certain quirkiness.</p>
        <p>HEAT 94, CAVALIERS 90 -- Antoine Walker and Shaquille O'Neal scored 20 points apiece and Miami clinched a spot in the Eastern Conference playoffs by beating host Cleveland.</p>
        <p>The first-place Heat moved one and a half games ahead of Washington in the Southeast Division. Walker made six 3-pointers and Alonzo Mourning had a big block in the final minute of overtime. LeBron James scored 35 points, with 9 rebounds and 5 assists, for the Cavaliers, who fell from second place to fifth in the Eastern Conference. (AP)</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
