<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Urgency In Debating Health Care</title>
    <meta content="06schism" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/business/06schism.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838370"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kaiser Family Foundation</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hewitt Associates</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Better Health Care Together (Orgn)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Costco Wholesale Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kelly Services Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pitney Bowes Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Electric Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Business Machines Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sinegal, James D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Camden, Carl T</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Critelli, Michael J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Galvin, Robert S (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Macdonald, J Randall</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freudenheim, Milt</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E1DC173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1558" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Urgency In Debating Health Care</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New Urgency in Debating Health Care</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MILT FREUDENHEIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freudenheim, Milt</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Top executives of large companies are starting to speak up about fixing health care in light of ballooning medical costs; few advocate wholesale shift to government-directed medicine, but most are seeking broad changes in employer-subsidized health system, which they regard as unsustainable in its current form; business executives are motivated by health insurance premiums that are rising much faster than inflation, adding to their costs at time when many are facing more intense competition from abroad, where companies rely on government-supported health care systems largely financed by taxes; 2006 study by Kaiser Family Foundation and Hewitt Associates found that premiums in US rose about 87 percent since 2000; unlikely coalition of businesses and labor unions called Better Health Care Together recently called for new American health care system by 2012; health care debate is heating up as candidates polish their positions for next year's presidential primaries, and as Democrats in Congress assert their newfound power; Costco chief executive James D Sinegal, Kelly Services president Carl T Camden, Pitney Bowes chairman Michael J Critelli, GE policy director Dr Robert S Galvin and IBM senior vice president J Randall MacDonald comment; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Since Hillary Rodham Clinton's effort to overhaul the nation's medical system was rejected in 1994, most big employers have stayed out of the debate on health care reform.</p>
        <p>But with their medical costs ballooning, top executives of large companies are starting to speak up again -- and many are calling for a national approach to fixing health care. Few advocate a wholesale shift to government-directed medicine, but most are seeking broad changes in the employer-subsidized health system, which they regard as unsustainable in its current form.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many executives of large companies are starting to call for a national approach to fixing health care, warning that an employer-subsidized health system is unsustainable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Since Hillary Rodham Clinton's effort to overhaul the nation's medical system was rejected in 1994, most big employers have stayed out of the debate on health care reform.</p>
        <p>But with their medical costs ballooning, top executives of large companies are starting to speak up again -- and many are calling for a national approach to fixing health care. Few advocate a wholesale shift to government-directed medicine, but most are seeking broad changes in the employer-subsidized health system, which they regard as unsustainable in its current form.</p>
        <p>Business executives are motivated in large part by health insurance premiums that are rising much faster than inflation, adding to their costs at a time when many are facing more intense competition from abroad, where companies rely on government-supported health care systems largely financed by taxes. A 2006 study  by the Kaiser Family Foundation and Hewitt Associates found that premiums in the United States had risen about 87 percent since 2000.</p>
        <p>''Five years from now this problem will have to be cured, or the competitiveness of the United States will be dramatically affected,'' said J. Randall MacDonald, senior vice president for human resources at I.B.M.</p>
        <p>But companies are by no means speaking with one voice. Everybody's problem -- the growing cost of health coverage -- can be felt differently depending on the size of a company and whether it has promised health benefits to retirees.</p>
        <p>Older companies, for example, are more likely to welcome government help on coverage for workers who leave before they are eligible for Medicare and may find they cannot afford insurance. But Silicon Valley technology companies that do not have or need retiree coverage are wary of new taxpayer-financed subsidies.</p>
        <p>The health care debate is heating up as candidates polish their positions for next year's presidential primaries, and as Democrats in Congress assert their newfound power.</p>
        <p>In general, employers ''are more interested in reform today than at any time since the Clinton effort'' in the early 1990s, said Robert S. Galvin, global health care and policy director at General Electric, which provides health benefits for 460,000 employees and dependents and 240,000 retirees and dependents.</p>
        <p>The surge of interest, Mr. Galvin said, ''is driven by compounding health cost increases at three times the general inflation rate, plus the entrance of Wal-Mart and other retailers'' that are beginning to feel the pain of out-of-control increases in costs.</p>
        <p>Wal-Mart Stores introduced lower-cost coverage for its huge work force last year, after state officials and editorial writers criticized the numbers of Wal-Mart employees on state Medicaid rolls.</p>
        <p>Many retailers, with large staffs of low-paid, temporary and part-time workers, would welcome a larger government role.</p>
        <p>''The way it's going, there will be 75 million uninsured in another 10 years,'' said James D. Sinegal, chief executive of Costco Wholesale, which subsidizes health care for 81,000 of its 100,000 workers in the United States. ''The federal government has to lend some assistance.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sinegal said he had agreed to support an unlikely coalition of businesses and labor unions that recently called for ''achieving a new American health care system by 2012.'' The group, the Better Health Care Together campaign, includes Wal-Mart, AT&amp;T, Intel and Kelly Services, the temporary-staffing company, as well as the Service Employees International Union and the Communications Workers of America.</p>
        <p>''The system is going to break,'' warned Carl T. Camden, president and chief executive of Kelly Services. ''You can only put so many uninsured people through the emergency rooms before employers stop offering coverage.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, a bill proposed by Senator Ron Wyden, Democrat of Oregon, would scale back the role of employers while requiring individuals and companies to share in the costs. President Bush's proposal would treat high-cost health care plans paid by employers as wages subject to income tax, and would also offer a new tax deduction to people who buy insurance on their own.</p>
        <p>Economists say that employers would raise wages if they did not have to pay for employee health care. The Treasury would stand to gain $140 billion a year in personal income taxes if the benefits were treated as wages, said Len Burman, director of the nonpartisan Tax Policy Center in Washington. There would be about $70 billion more in additional payroll taxes due on those wages, he said.</p>
        <p>But taxes would have to go up to keep the health care system functioning.</p>
        <p>Leslie Dach, executive vice president for corporate affairs and government relations at Wal-Mart, said that the company's ''message to elected officials is: 'The time to act is now.' '' Mr. Dach, a public relations specialist based in Washington and a frequent adviser to Democratic presidential candidates, joined Wal-Mart last year.</p>
        <p>While employers generally agree that steps must be taken to control health care costs, they are divided over whether or not the solutions should come from the government.</p>
        <p>''That is the elephant in the room,'' said Mr. Galvin of General Electric.</p>
        <p>Craig R. Barrett, the chairman of Intel, another participant in the Better Health Care Together campaign, is skeptical about a new government role. He said the private sector could do the best job at improving efficiency in the system.</p>
        <p>Corporate purchasers could use their buying power, he said, to insist on technological aids like electronic prescriptions, remote monitoring of patients with chronic illnesses and electronic health records for Americans.</p>
        <p>Companies like General Motors argue that government agencies, which spend about half of the $2 trillion in annual health spending, should join with employers in pushing for changes to lower costs.</p>
        <p>''Working with the government as a fellow purchaser can accomplish a great deal to help improve our health care system,'' said Bruce E. Bradley, director of health care strategy and public policy at G.M., which provides health care for 1.1 million people, including more than 500,000 retirees and their spouses.</p>
        <p>Michael J. Critelli, chairman of Pitney Bowes, the business services company, says he backs changes that emphasize preventive medicine. ''Any health plan, whether employer, government or private insurance needs to invest its most significant dollars in incentives for people to take good care of themselves,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He added: ''The spiraling cost of health care is a result of an explosive growth in chronic diseases like diabetes, cardiovascular conditions and asthma. The health care debate needs to be focused on the core issue: making Americans healthier.''</p>
        <p>By providing clinics, exercise and other wellness programs as well as low-cost or free drugs for certain types of patients, he said, annual cost increases for Pitney Bowes employees have fallen into the low single digits over the last 15 years. That is well below the double-digit percentage increases that many companies have experienced.</p>
        <p>Neither G.M. nor Wal-Mart favors a government-based central payer system. But older companies and their unions are very interested in Congressional measures that would allow early retirees under age 65 to qualify for Medicare or to buy into the Medicare program, with help from their former employers, said Alan Reuther, legislative director of the United Automobile Workers.</p>
        <p>General Motors has far different concerns, of course, than Wal-Mart, a retailer that covers more than one million employees and dependents in the United States but does not provide a retiree health benefit.</p>
        <p>Another set of issues divides large companies from small businesses, which employ 50 percent of working Americans. Their owners worry that in some states they may be forced to spend for coverage of young workers with little interest in health coverage.</p>
        <p>''The premium keeps going up and, even worse, the insurance companies keep decreasing the benefits,'' said Steve Caughran, who owns three small companies in Fresno, Calif. One, a Quiznos fast-food restaurant, has 14 uninsured high school and college students who work part time.</p>
        <p>Requiring employers to cover workers who lack health insurance will hardly correct the forces pushing up costs, like expensive new drugs, insurance fraud and inefficient state programs, Mr. Caughran argues.</p>
        <p>Mr. Camden of Kelly Services notes that the majority of the 45 million Americans who do not have health insurance have jobs. He argues that many of these workers are essential to keeping the United States economy competitive.</p>
        <p>''In the next decade or two, manufacturing is going to steadily decline,'' he said. ''Employment will come from the entrepreneurial, scientific parts of the economy,'' including many who work as independent contractors and temporary employees.</p>
        <p>Part of the solution should be to ''separate health care from employer sponsorship,'' Mr. Camden said. ''The employer-provided health care system is just dead, although some people haven't recognized it as dead yet.''</p>
        <p>Similarly, Andrew L. Stern, president of the Service Employees International Union, criticizes the current employer-sponsored system as ''a relic of the industrial economy.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Camden listed possible remedies as an ''employment-based'' withholding tax, matched by employers as in Social Security, with Medicare and Medicaid expanded to cover the unemployed.</p>
        <p>But most big companies are not ready to give up on their health care obligations. ''Regardless of who takes the lead, we collectively as a national society have to consolidate around three or four different ideas,'' Mr. MacDonald of I.B.M. said.</p>
        <p>He called for a national debate on such topics as maintaining existing employer-subsidized health care, with ''some level of umbrella coverage over that, some level of a single payer system.''</p>
        <p>''A lot of positioning is going on now,'' he said. ''The reality is that changes are inevitable, I think sooner rather than later.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
