<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Vote for Bonds</title>
    <meta content="06play.email.lede" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838423"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E1DF143FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="404" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Vote for Bonds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROB MACKEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The waters behind Pac-Bell Park in San Francisco have been relatively calm this month. Yes, Barry Bonds is off to his usual slow start; with only one home run as of Thursday, he still needs 21 more to surpass Hank Aaron's career record. But if the Bay has been placid, the usual undercurrents that surround Bonds have been stirring up the ingredients for the perfect baseball storm: pressure, spotlight, history in the making, and the game's most controversial, temperamental player.</p>
        <p>What good can come of this? Well, a lot, says Michael Lewis, the author of the best-selling "Moneyball''and "The Blind Side,'' who also wrote a compelling profile of Bill Parcells for the November issue of Play last year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The waters behind Pac-Bell Park in San Francisco have been relatively calm this month. Yes, Barry Bonds is off to his usual slow start; with only one home run as of Thursday, he still needs 21 more to surpass Hank Aaron's career record. But if the Bay has been placid, the usual undercurrents that surround Bonds have been stirring up the ingredients for the perfect baseball storm: pressure, spotlight, history in the making, and the game's most controversial, temperamental player.</p>
        <p>What good can come of this? Well, a lot, says Michael Lewis, the author of the best-selling "Moneyball''and "The Blind Side,'' who also wrote a compelling profile of Bill Parcells for the November issue of Play last year.</p>
        <p>Lewis is a Bay area resident who has closely observed Bonds during the slugger's years with the Giants. We caught up with him this week as he took a break from writing to tend to his two daughters and five-month-old son.</p>
        <p>In Lewis's view, Bonds's clouded pursuit of a hallowed baseball record provides instructive contrast to the usual day-glo wrapping that accompanies such milestones. "This is a useful reminder that baseball, our national past-time, has a darker side, and we have to acknowledge it and deal with it. It will give us a fuller picture. We have to realize that not all of the game's great accomplishments will come with the feel-good fireworks that accompanied Cal Ripken's breaking the consecutive-game record.''</p>
        <p>Once we come to grips with the totality, Lewis says, we can decide how we want to view Bonds's place in the record books. "If you prefer black and white,'' he says, "you can either discount his accomplishment altogether as a drug-tainted record by a miserable human being, or celebrate him as perhaps the greatest hitter of all-time. If you prefer gray, you can mix all these perspectives and give him a more nuanced place in history. Either way, you'll have a clearer understanding of what's happenign in front of you.''</p>
        <p>And where does Lewis stand, black, white or gray? "I wouldn't say I like him, but I admire him,'' Lewis says. "For his ability to achieve through everything surrounding him, and for his singular skill, hitting a baseball, a fine art that maybe no one has ever been better at. The heat of current events is singing him now; history will be kinder.</p>
        <p>Hall of Fame? "You bet,'' Lewis says. "Absolutely.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
