<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Traditional Hawaiian Sounds, Seasoned With Pop Ideas</title>
    <meta content="06hapa" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/arts/music/06hapa.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838280"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Hawaii</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Hawaii</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Hawaii</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Hapa</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E3DF173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="526" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Traditional Hawaiian Sounds, Seasoned With Pop Ideas</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Traditional Hawaiian Sounds, Seasoned With Pop Ideas</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATE CHINEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Feeling homesick yet?'' the Polynesian chanter Charles Ka'upu puckishly asked on Wednesday night at Merkin Concert Hall. He was addressing those in the audience with ties to the Hawaiian Islands: a majority, judging by the response he received.</p>
        <p>Hapa, the most successful Hawaiian-music group in recent history, is, at its core, an acoustic duo consisting of the guitarist-singers Barry Flanagan and Nathan Aweau. Wednesday's concert also included, in addition to Mr. Ka'upu, two hula dancers, Malia Petersen and Naomi Pi'iliani Klein. The group draws from a wellspring of Polynesian traditions, but with a sure-footed pop sensibility. Mr. Ka'upu's query, for example, came after ''Anjuli,'' a crystalline instrumental piece that Mr. Flanagan said he had written in the style of the guitarist Earl Klugh. Later in the show there were less successful appropriations of Bob Marley and U2.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The group performed signature instrumentals, chants and standards sung in the traditional Hawaiian falsetto style to a captive audience on Wednesday at Merkin Concert Hall.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Feeling homesick yet?'' the Polynesian chanter Charles Ka'upu puckishly asked on Wednesday night at Merkin Concert Hall. He was addressing those in the audience with ties to the Hawaiian Islands: a majority, judging by the response he received.</p>
        <p>Hapa, the most successful Hawaiian-music group in recent history, is, at its core, an acoustic duo consisting of the guitarist-singers Barry Flanagan and Nathan Aweau. Wednesday's concert also included, in addition to Mr. Ka'upu, two hula dancers, Malia Petersen and Naomi Pi'iliani Klein. The group draws from a wellspring of Polynesian traditions, but with a sure-footed pop sensibility. Mr. Ka'upu's query, for example, came after ''Anjuli,'' a crystalline instrumental piece that Mr. Flanagan said he had written in the style of the guitarist Earl Klugh. Later in the show there were less successful appropriations of Bob Marley and U2.</p>
        <p>Yet the allusions made a kind of sense. The melding of influences is central to Hapa, a word that means half in the Hawaiian language, but has come to connote mixed ethnicity. Mr. Flanagan was an island-dwelling transplant from New Jersey when he officially teamed up with a native Hawaiian vocalist, Keli'i Kaneali'i, to form the original group, which had an international hit with its self-titled debut album, released in 1993. It still turns up on island charts; it's the top-selling recording by any group in Hawaiian-music history.</p>
        <p>Four years ago Mr. Aweau took over the chair vacated by Mr. Kaneali'i, who had retired from music, and the sound of the group shifted perceptibly. Mr. Aweau, who spent 15 years as the musical director for Don Ho, brought a more pronounced virtuosity to Hapa. He has prodigious skill as an electric bassist -- during an unaccompanied tear through ''Greensleeves'' he strongly evoked Stanley Clarke -- and his 12-string rhythm-guitar playing showed an advanced understanding of harmony and orchestration.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Aweau's most valuable gift to the group is his singing, in the traditional Hawaiian falsetto style. One highlight of the concert was his lyrical solo performance of a Hawaiian standard, ''Akaka Falls''; another was his rendition of ''Lei Manoa,'' a love song by Mr. Flanagan. In both instances Mr. Aweau sang gorgeously, with a weightless vibrato and a light emphasis on the break, or ha'i, between vocal ranges.</p>
        <p>One more tradition associated with Hapa is the ki ho'alu instrumental style, more commonly known as slack-key guitar. Early in the concert Mr. Flanagan played a signature instrumental, ''Olinda Road,'' that neatly justified his stature as an innovator in the field. Throughout the evening he indulged in intricate fingerpicking and tricky harmonics; he often flexed the special graphite neck of his instrument to warp a pitch, with deftness and flair.</p>
        <p>As on Hapa's most recent album, ''Maui'' (Finn), Mr. Ka'upu delivered several powerful chants. He also kept up a congenial and sometimes giddy commentary that gave the concert a casual air. When he invited members of the audience onstage to dance a hula to Edith Kanaka'ole's ''Ka Uluwehi O Ke Kai,'' more than 30 people responded. They all appeared to know the movements, and the words.</p>
        <p>Hapa performs tonight in Somerville, Mass., and tomorrow night in Boulder, Colo.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
