<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>3 Are Charged With Aiding London Transit Attack</title>
    <meta content="06terror" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/world/europe/06terror.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838320"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perlez, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shakil, Mohammed</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saleem, Sadeer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ullah, Shipon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">London (England)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E7DD173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="607" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>3 Are Charged With Aiding London Transit Attack</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">3 Are Charged With Aiding London Transit Attack</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perlez, Jane</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, April 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>British authorities charge three Muslim men with conspiring to help with reconnaissance and planning for London transit attack by four suicide bombers that killed 52 people in July 2005; bombers, and three just arrested, are all British and of South Asian descent; three charged are Mohammed Shakil, Sadeer Saleem and Waheed Ali, formerly kjnown as Shipon Ullah; all three live in district of Leeds where three of four bombers lived; Shakil and Ullah were arrested two weeks ago while trying to board plane for Pakistan; security specialists consider three as helpers, not masterminds (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The British authorities charged three Muslim men on Thursday with conspiring to help with reconnaissance and planning for the London transit attack that killed 52 people in July 2005.</p>
        <p>The charges were the first brought in the attack, Britain's deadliest in peacetime, which was carried out by four British suicide bombers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The chief of counterterrorism at Scotland Yard said that the police now had a better picture of the preparations for the suicide mission.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The British authorities charged three Muslim men on Thursday with conspiring to help with reconnaissance and planning for the London transit attack that killed 52 people in July 2005.</p>
        <p>The charges were the first brought in the attack, Britain's deadliest in peacetime, which was carried out by four British suicide bombers.</p>
        <p>Announcing the charges against the three men, also British and of South Asian descent, Peter Clarke, the chief of counterterrorism at Scotland Yard, made clear that the police now had a better picture of the preparations for the suicide mission.</p>
        <p>''Over 21 months, the relentless search for every tiny detail gave us a wealth of information about the background to the attacks,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But there was still a lot to learn, he said, including crucial facts about who encouraged the bombers, who backed them and who helped them.</p>
        <p>''I firmly believe that there are other people who have knowledge of what lay behind the attacks in July 2005 -- knowledge they have not shared with us,'' he said Thursday at a news conference. ''In fact, I don't only believe it, I know it for a fact.''</p>
        <p>He pleaded for residents of the West Yorkshire area, where the three are from, to share information and ignore those who would try to use intimidation to silence them.</p>
        <p>The three charged are Mohammed Shakil, 30; Sadeer Saleem, 26; and Waheed Ali, 23, formerly known as Shipon Ullah. All three are from the working-class area of Beeston, a district of Leeds in northern England. Three of the four suicide bombers lived nearby in Beeston, frequenting the same Islamic bookshop as the men who were charged. Mr. Shakil, a taxi driver, lived in a town house in a more prosperous section of Beeston.</p>
        <p>He and Mr. Ullah were arrested at Manchester airport two weeks ago as they were about to board a plane for Pakistan. Security experts have said there was debate about whether to arrest the men, with some British officials wanting more time to follow the three to gather information about the extent of the plot.</p>
        <p>''When two of the men who have been charged today tried to leave the country on March 22, our judgment was that the time was right to arrest them,'' Mr. Clarke said. Mr. Saleem was arrested at his home.</p>
        <p>The director of the counterterrorism division of the crown prosecution service, Susan Hemming, said that from Nov. 1, 2004, to June 29, 2005, the three men conspired with the four suicide bombers to ''cause by an explosive substance explosions'' in the London transit system and tourist attractions she did not identify. She said the men had helped with reconnaissance and planning.</p>
        <p>The British authorities want to learn how the four suicide bombers were recruited, security specialists say, and the men charged could provide such facts. But it appeared clear, they said, that even if guilty, the men were at the periphery of the operation, helpers, not masterminds.</p>
        <p>The police will want to determine if the men traveled to Pakistan, and if so, where they went, said Sajjan M. Gohel, executive director of Asia Pacific Foundation in London.</p>
        <p>The continuing trial of six men charged with organizing a terrorist plot in London two weeks after the transit attack has provided some insight into the four suicide bombers.</p>
        <p>One of the defendants, Muktar Said Ibrahim, accused of being the ringleader of a failed plot on July 21, testified that he was in Pakistan at the same time as Mohammad Siddique Khan and Shehzad Tanweer, two of the suicide bombers and that the July 7 attacks inspired him to do a ''fake'' copycat mission.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
