<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Aspiring Buyer Of Starrett City Is Back Onstage</title>
    <meta content="06starrett" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/nyregion/06starrett.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838403"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Starrett City Housing Development (Brooklyn)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Beyer Blinder Belle</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Housing and Urban Development Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bistricer, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Butts, Calvin O III (Rev)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernard, A R Sr (Rev)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schumer, Charles E (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spitzer, Eliot (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Towns, Edolphus (Rep)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bagli, Charles V</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Brooklyn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E4DB173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1568" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Aspiring Buyer Of Starrett City Is Back Onstage</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Aspiring Buyer of Starrett City Is Back Onstage</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES V. BAGLI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bagli, Charles V</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Bistricer and his investment group, Clipper Equity, enlist support of Rev Calvin O Butts III, who leads Abyssinian Baptist Church in Harlem, and Rev A R Bernard, founder of Christian Cultural Center in Brooklyn, in new bid to acquire Starrett City housing complex in Brooklyn; also hires prominent lobbyists in New York and Washington and well-regarded architectural firm Beyer Blinder Belle to redesign complex; Bistricer's offer of $1.3 billion for complex has received cool reception from Gov Eliot Spitzer, Sen Charles E Schumer and Rep Edolphus Towns, and officials at federal Department of Housing and Urban Development have not wavered in pledge to preserve complex as housing for people with low or moderate incomes; Bistricer insists that complex will remain affordable, but critics fear rents will have to rise or services will have to be cut to justify heady sales price; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>David Bistricer, whose initial attempt to buy the Starrett City housing complex in Brooklyn was rejected a month ago by federal regulators, is back.</p>
        <p>He has a new plan, a well-regarded architect, powerful lobbyists and something he was missing in his first go-round: potential backing from two politically influential black ministers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The potential buyer, David Bistricer, is back with a new plan, powerful lobbyists and potential backing from two politically influential black ministers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>David Bistricer, whose initial attempt to buy the Starrett City housing complex in Brooklyn was rejected a month ago by federal regulators, is back.</p>
        <p>He has a new plan, a well-regarded architect, powerful lobbyists and something he was missing in his first go-round: potential backing from two politically influential black ministers.</p>
        <p>The ministers, the Rev. Calvin O. Butts III, who leads the storied Abyssinian Baptist Church in Harlem, and the Rev. A. R. Bernard, founder of a large evangelical congregation across the street from Starrett City, have not worked out a formal partnership with Mr. Bistricer.</p>
        <p>But they accompanied him to Washington for a March 23 meeting with the federal housing secretary, Alphonso R. Jackson, effectively blessing the project with a degree of credibility it did not have before.</p>
        <p>''He seems sincere in wanting to work with us and in making sure that the tenants in Starrett City remain in affordable housing,'' Mr. Butts said. ''I think what we bring to this is credibility, to the extent that we have been really aggressive in maintaining affordable housing.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bistricer's unusual alliance with the two ministers, who were introduced to him by a lobbyist on his payroll, exemplifies the kind of choreographed maneuvering that goes into billion-dollar real estate projects in New York.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, Mr. Bistricer has hired the lobbyists Suri Kasirer -- who has connections to Gov. Eliot Spitzer -- in New York and Brad Card -- the brother of President Bush's former chief of staff -- in Washington. And he retained the well-regarded architectural firm Beyer Blinder Belle to redesign the 140-acre complex, the largest federally subsidized housing project in the country.</p>
        <p>''Real estate transactions in New York are played out on a very public stage,'' said Jerilyn Perine, a former city housing commissioner. ''To do them successfully, most developers look to forge relationships with political, civic or advocacy groups. When that doesn't happen, you end up running the risk of dying by a thousand cuts.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bistricer's latest plan to buy Starrett City for $1.3 billion has already received a chilly reception from Governor Spitzer, who spoke out in support of the tenants early on. In a letter last night to the Bistricer group, Mr. Spitzer's housing commissioner, Deborah Van Amerongen, said the plan ''failed to adequately ensure that Starrett City would be preserved as viable affordable housing in the future, and would be unworkable under existing statutory law.''</p>
        <p>Federal housing officials, whose approval is required, are still reviewing the matter, although a spokesman said the agency had not waivered in its pledge to preserve the complex as housing for people with low or moderate incomes.</p>
        <p>Senator Charles E. Schumer also sent Mr. Bistricer a letter this week saying he had ''serious concerns'' that the proposal ''shifts a significant burden to the federal government, while not doing enough to protect the middle-class character of the development.''</p>
        <p>Representative Edolphus Towns of Brooklyn, who met recently with members of the Bistricer group, said, ''I'm not on board, at this point.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bistricer and his investment group, Clipper Equity, are undeterred.</p>
        <p>''Clipper is in this to stay,'' said Lisa Linden, a spokeswoman for the group. ''Our proposal is a work in progress. The centerpiece is affordability. We are confident that we can and will maintain affordability for current and future tenants, which Senator Schumer seeks, tenants require, and we support.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bistricer, who is from Borough Park, was a relatively unknown figure when he won the bidding on Feb. 8 for Starrett City, a complex of 5,881 apartments in 46 buildings on Jamaica Bay. He was unprepared for the avalanche of criticism, which started even before his bidding success. In the minds of housing advocates, some politicians and many New Yorkers, the sales of Stuyvesant Town and Starrett City highlighted the dwindling supply of affordable housing for poor and middle-class New Yorkers in a city where the price of an ''average'' apartment has soared to $1.2 million.</p>
        <p>Critics feared that the new owner of Starrett City would have to raise rents to justify the heady sale price, or cut services at the racially mixed complex, which has its own security force, shopping center, schools, power plant, churches and synagogue.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bistricer, who insisted that the complex would remain affordable, was still hiring his team when Senator Schumer, Governor Spitzer, Attorney General Andrew M. Cuomo, Councilman Charles Barron and others lined up against the deal.</p>
        <p>''I think he was shocked by the initial response,'' Sheena Wright, president of the Abyssinian Church's development corporation, said of Mr. Bistricer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bistricer brought in Ms. Linden and John L. Kelly, a partner at Nixon Peabody and a well-known lawyer in the housing field, in addition to Ms. Kasirer, one of the most prolific lobbyists and political fund-raisers in New York. She is married to Bruce J. Teitelbaum, a former member of the Giuliani administration, who is a lawyer for the Starrett City project, along with Leonard Grunstein.</p>
        <p>Later, he hired Mr. Card, whose brother is Andrew H. Card Jr., President Bush's first White House chief of staff, to lobby the Department of Housing and Urban Development and Secretary Jackson.</p>
        <p>On Feb. 9, one of Ms. Kasirer's partners, Patrick Jenkins, called Mr. Bernard's office to talk about the pending deal. Mr. Jenkins, who had served as deputy campaign manager for Mr. Spitzer, was well acquainted with the minister, because the 28,000-member Christian Cultural Center is a requisite stop for any politician on the campaign trail.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bernard had built his church on land he bought from the owners of Starrett City, a group led by Disque Deane. Roughly 2,100 of the 14,000 residents of the complex attend services at the Cultural Center, although Mr. Bernard has not been active in the life of Starrett City.</p>
        <p>Seemingly without any allies, Mr. Bistricer received a public lashing -- unfairly, he insisted -- from both Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg and Mr. Cuomo over his role as landlord of other properties. On March 2, Secretary Jackson rejected Mr. Bistricer's application to buy Starrett City. The same day, Mr. Schumer, tenants, the community advocacy group Acorn and others celebrated the decision at the Christian Cultural Center.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bistricer did not give up. His lobbyists and lawyers continued working on a plan that they said would protect the existing tenants at Starrett City, and on creating a politically potent alliance. Mr. Jenkins, the lobbyist, called Ms. Wright at the Abyssinian Development Corporation to talk about a partnerhship that could help them both. Abyssinian could become involved in an unusually large project in Brooklyn and Mr. Bistricer would get the assistance of a powerful black minister who knew Secretary Jackson.</p>
        <p>Mr. Butts, a fraternity brother of Mr. Jackson's, said he knew the deal had been stopped but thought there was ''probably another opportunity to follow through.'' He talked with Mr. Bistricer and determined that his past record was no better or worse than those of other landlords.</p>
        <p>''Starrett City is a sizable deal,'' Mr. Butts said. ''My first concern is with the tenants, affordability and creating an even better quality of life. I've never been out after the money, but if there's money to be made, I want to be fairly represented in that, too.''</p>
        <p>As for Mr. Schumer's criticism, Mr. Butts said: ''We continue to work with Bistricer to make his purchase come into line with whatSchumer wants. Bistricer seems like he wants to do it the right way. If we can do this successfully, we will have the wherewithal to show others how to do it.''</p>
        <p>Around March 13, Mr. Bernard called Mr. Jenkins -- he said he had waited a month to do his own ''investigation'' of Mr. Bistricter's plan -- to set up the first in a series of meetings with the Bistricer group. Aside from being an influential figure in the community surrounding Starrett City, Mr. Bernard controlled a 4.5-acre parcel at Flatlands and Pennsylvania Avenues where he wanted to build housing and retail space.</p>
        <p>It is also where Mr. Bistricer's architects planned to build a ''gateway'' for the complex, as part of a proposal to build new stores and new housing, which would have to be approved by city officials. They discussed how they might work together.</p>
        <p>Both ministers joined Mr. Bistricer last month when he laid out his tentative plans for Secretary Jackson. ''I guess it was kind of an endorsement,'' Mr. Butts conceded, although both ministers emphasized that there was still no formal arrangement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bernard insisted that he was still seeking answers from the Bistricer group concerning its development plan and wanted promises that no residents would be displaced. They are convinced that the ownership of the complex will change, whether Mr. Bistricer is accepted or not.</p>
        <p>''I have not reached a conclusion, but I am impressed that it is doable,'' Mr. Bernard said. ''This change is inevitable. Either we'll be involved with it to help shape it and lead it, or it will lead us.''</p>
        <p>Government officials acknowledge that the possible involvement of the ministers has given them pause. But they are not convinced that Mr. Bistricer can fashion a viable plan while paying what Senator Schumer said was $1.4 billion when all the fees were included.</p>
        <p>''I will do anything I can to keep it middle class,'' Mr. Schumer said of Starrett City. ''But I'm not going to fight for more subsidies so the seller can make a bigger profit.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
