<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Passion for Golf Bound Three Who Died in Plane Crash</title>
    <meta content="06plane" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/nyregion/06plane.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838402"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Maryland</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">mahopac golf club</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Doppke, Gregory D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lomas, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Young, Andrew (Airplane Accident Victim)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Massaro, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fernandez, Manny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Maryland</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E4DB173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Passion for Golf Bound Three Who Died in Plane Crash</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Passion for Golf Bound Three Who Died in Plane Crash</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MANNY FERNANDEZ; Nate Schweber and Stacey Stowe contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fernandez, Manny</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gregory D Doppke, Richard Lomas and Andrew Young, three men who died in crash of small plane on Maryland's Eastern Shore, were golf buddies at Mahopac Golf Club in Mahopac, NY, and were on their way to North Carolina to play several rounds of golf; Joe Massaro, other member of foursome, had to visit his daughter in Reno and was unable to join friends in flight from Westchester County; severe thunderstorm was reported at time of crash, but it remains unclear if weather played role in crash; Young photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was a 10-year-old tradition among golfing buddies: Every spring, Joe Massaro and three of his close friends would fly to North Carolina for some good times and -- weather and skills permitting -- some good golf.</p>
        <p>This year, Mr. Massaro, 60, was supposed to be on the plane with his friends, but a trip to Reno to visit his daughter prevented the four men from flying out of Westchester County together. So on Wednesday, Mr. Massaro arrived at the Moore County Airport in Southern Pines, N.C., and waited for the small plane carrying the three others to land at 11:17 a.m.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A golfing buddy recalls the men who died in Wednesday's crash of a small plane that took off from Westchester County Airport and crashed in Maryland.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was a 10-year-old tradition among golfing buddies: Every spring, Joe Massaro and three of his close friends would fly to North Carolina for some good times and -- weather and skills permitting -- some good golf.</p>
        <p>This year, Mr. Massaro, 60, was supposed to be on the plane with his friends, but a trip to Reno to visit his daughter prevented the four men from flying out of Westchester County together. So on Wednesday, Mr. Massaro arrived at the Moore County Airport in Southern Pines, N.C., and waited for the small plane carrying the three others to land at 11:17 a.m.</p>
        <p>On board were Gregory D. Doppke, co-owner of an air-conditioning and heating business in Hawthorne, N.Y.; Mr. Doppke's business partner, Richard Lomas; and Andrew Young, who ran a restaurant consulting firm in Manhattan. The four friends had become inseparable golfing buddies at the Mahopac Golf Club in Mahopac, N.Y.</p>
        <p>But 11:17 a.m. came and went. ''I just kept waiting for that plane to come in,'' Mr. Massaro said.</p>
        <p>It never did: the twin-engine Piper PA-30 built in 1967 crashed in a field on Maryland's Eastern Shore Wednesday morning. All three men on board were killed.</p>
        <p>They had taken off in Mr. Doppke's airplane from Westchester County Airport, in White Plains, Wednesday morning. In southern Maryland, air traffic controllers at Patuxent River Naval Air Station lost radio communication with the aircraft, according to a spokesman for the Federal Aviation Administration's eastern region. The plane went off their radar screens at 9:37 a.m., said the spokesman, Jim Peters. There was no indication from the pilot that there was anything wrong before the plane lost communication with air traffic controllers, Mr. Peters said.</p>
        <p>At the time of the crash, a severe thunderstorm had hit the area, the Maryland State Police said. It remained unclear if the weather played a role in the crash, according to the F.A.A. The exact cause is under investigation by the National Transportation Safety Board.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, friends and relatives described Mr. Doppke, who they believed was at the controls on Wednesday, as an avid and careful pilot, flying his wife and daughter on trips to the Bahamas and Martha's Vineyard. Mr. Massaro had flown numerous times over the years with Mr. Doppke. ''He kept up on everything,'' Mr. Massaro said yesterday. ''His plane was in the shop more than it was in the air.''</p>
        <p>Word of the deaths of Mr. Doppke, Mr. Lomas and Mr. Young shocked the Mahopac club, where Mr. Young was the president, as well as relatives and friends of the three men, who came from different backgrounds and cities but were bound by a love of golf.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, at Mr. Doppke's house in Greenwich, Conn., his daughter, Kelly Doppke, 33, clutched a bottle of her father's after-shave. ''I can't put this down, because every time I smell it, I picture him,'' she said. ''I can't believe he's gone.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Doppke, 62, was known as the mayor of the breakfast club, a group of pilots who met at the Westchester airport on the weekends and flew to other airports for their morning meal, family members said. He bought his first plane when his daughter was 9 years old, Ms. Doppke said, and he spent so much time flying and talking about it that she referred to the plane as if it were a sibling, calling it ''Sissy.''</p>
        <p>His daughter and his wife, Mary, said Mr. Doppke had navigated airplanes through rough weather before, and had successfully made at least two emergency crash landings. ''I keep telling myself he was doing what he loved, and headed somewhere to do what he loved,'' Ms. Doppke said.</p>
        <p>At the Mahopac golf course, which Mr. Young helped to redesign recently, Howard Kelly, the club manager, pulled down a photo book from a bookshelf outside his office and turned to a snapshot of the four men in two golf carts. They were creatures of habit. Mr. Young and Mr. Massaro usually squared off against Mr. Doppke and Mr. Lomas. Before they played, they would eat breakfast together in the clubhouse, always sitting at the same table, Mr. Kelly said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Massaro, who lives in Juno Beach, Fla., and Mahopac, met Mr. Young when they both joined the club around the same time, about 15 years ago. He then introduced Mr. Young to Mr. Doppke and Mr. Lomas, with whom he had worked at their business, ABM Air Conditioning and Heating.</p>
        <p>Family members of Mr. Lomas, who lived in Stamford, Conn., could not be reached for comment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Young, 51, who lived in Mahopac, founded an international consulting firm, Andrew Young &amp; Company, working with hotels, restaurants, theme parks and museums to develop and hone their dining and hospitality services. At Ma Maison, a former restaurant in Los Angeles that was popular with Hollywood celebrities in the 1970s and 80s, Mr. Young worked in the kitchen with Wolfgang Puck, according to a biography on his firm's Web site. In Manhattan, he managed Café des Artistes and at one time owned what he called a maverick Mexican restaurant, El Teddy's.</p>
        <p>Nick Valenti, a New York restaurateur and chief executive officer of Patina Restaurant Group, remembers working with Mr. Young to develop the restaurants around the ice-skating rink at Rockefeller Center in the early 1980s. After a long day, he said, Mr. Young liked to relax by taking a few laps around the rink. ''We will miss him.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
