<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Listings: April 6-April 12</title>
    <meta content="06listcov" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070426T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838250"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E1D8163FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="15731" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Listings: April 6-April 12</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. ? denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'THE ACCOMPLICES' In previews; opens on Monday. The New Group presents a play by Bernard Weinraub, a former reporter for The New York Times. Based on historical events, it is about an activist who seeks American help during World War II to rescue European Jews from the Nazis (2:00). Acorn Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'ACCOMPLICE: NEW YORK'  Opens tomorrow. An interactive theater piece takes audiences around the city helping a criminal outsmart the feds (3:00). Site is secret. You receive a call one day before the performance with information on location; (212) 209-3370.</p>
        <p>'ALL THE WRONG REASONS: A TRUE STORY OF NEO-NAZIS, DRUG SMUGGLING AND UNDYING LOVE' In previews; opens on April 15. John Fugelsang is the son of an ex-nun and a former Franciscan brother. He tells his story in this solo show. New York Theater Workshop, 79 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 460-5475.</p>
        <p>'BLACKBIRD' In previews; opens on Tuesday. Jeff Daniels stars in the American premiere of this provocative play about a man coming to terms with a troubling relationship from his past. Joe Mantello directs (1:30). Manhattan Theater Club at City Center Stage I, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212.</p>
        <p>'DEUCE' Previews start on Wednesday. Opens on May 6. Grand dames Angela Lansbury and Marian Seldes play retired tennis players in this new Terrence McNally comedy. Michael Blakemore directs. Music Box Theater, 239 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'FROST/NIXON' In previews; opens on April 22. Frank Langella plays Richard M. Nixon in this acclaimed London transfer about the famous post-Watergate interview. With Michael Sheen. (1:40). Jacobs Theater, 242 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'INHERIT THE WIND' In previews; opens on Thursday. This revival of the classic courtroom drama based on the famous ''monkey trial'' stars a lineup of heavy-hitters: Brian Dennehy, Christopher Plummer, Denis O'Hare and Byron Jennings (2:00). Lyceum Theater, 149 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'LEGALLY BLONDE' In previews; opens on April 29. Laura Bell Bundy plays the smiling, ditsy sorority girl who takes Harvard Law by storm in this musical adaptation. Jerry Mitchell directs (2:20). Palace Theater, 1564 Broadway, at 47th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'LOVEMUSIK' Previews start on Thursday. Opens on May 3. Tony-winners Michael Cerveris and Donna Murphy star in a prestige musical about the relationship between Kurt Weill and Lotte Lenya (with songs by Weill). Harold Prince directs (2:30). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'A MOON FOR THE MISBEGOTTEN' In previews; opens on Monday. Kevin Spacey and Eve Best star in the London transfer of this Eugene O'Neill classic. Howard Davies directs (3:00). Brooks Atkinson Theater, 256 West 47th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'TRANSFIGURES' Previews start today. Opens on April 16. Created from sources including the writings of Joan of Arc, scientific journals and Post-it notes from the desks of corporate secretaries, this new show examines the Jerusalem Syndrome (1:30). Julia Miles Theater, 424 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'A CHORUS LINE' If you want to know why this show was such a big deal when it opened 31 years ago, you need only experience the thrilling first five minutes of this revival. Otherwise, this archivally exact production, directed by Bob Avian, feels like a vintage car that has been taken out of the garage, polished up and sent on the road once again (2:00). Schoenfeld Theater, 236 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE COAST OF UTOPIA' Lincoln Center Theater's brave, gorgeous, sprawling and ultimately exhilarating production of Tom Stoppard's trilogy about intellectuals errant in 19th-century Russia. A testament to the seductive powers of narrative theater, directed with hot and cool canniness by Jack O'Brien and featuring a starry cast (Brian F. O'Byrne, Jennifer Ehle, Martha Plimpton, Josh Hamilton and Ethan Hawke, among others) in a tasty assortment of roles. Vivian Beaumont Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'COMPANY' Fire, beckoning and dangerous, flickers beneath the frost of John Doyle's elegant, unexpectedly stirring revival of Stephen Sondheim and George Furth's era-defining musical from 1970, starring a compellingly understated Raúl Esparza. Like Mr. Doyle's ''Sweeney Todd,'' this production finds new clarity of feeling in Sondheim by melding the roles of performers and musicians (2:20). Barrymore Theater, 243 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CURTAINS' This musical comedy about a musical-comedy murder -- featuring songs by John Kander and Fred Ebb and a book by Rupert Holmes -- lies on the stage like a promisingly gaudy string of firecrackers, waiting in vain for a match. The good news is that David Hyde Pierce, playing a diffident Boston detective, steps into full-fledged Broadway stardom. Scott Ellis directs a talent-packed cast that includes Debra Monk and Karen Ziemba. (2:45). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE'  (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920s stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, it has theatergoers responding as if they were withering houseplants finally being watered after long neglect. (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'GREY GARDENS' Christine Ebersole is absolutely glorious as the middle-aged, time-warped debutante called Little Edie Beale in this uneven musical adaptation of the notorious 1975 documentary of the same title. She and the wonderful Mary Louise Wilson (as her bedridden mother), in the performances of their careers, make ''Grey Gardens'' an experience no passionate theatergoer should miss (2:40). Walter Kerr Theater, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HOWARD KATZ' The subject of Patrick Marber's comedy of unhappiness about a rabid talent agent, starring a baleful Alfred Molina and directed by Doug Hughes, is nothing more nor less than your standard-issue midlife crisis. This familiar topic gets the better of all the talented people here trying to make it seem fresh (1:30). Laura Pels Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'JOURNEY'S END' A splendid revival of R. C. Sherriff's 1928 drama of life in the trenches during World War I. Acutely staged (by David Grindley) and acted by a fine ensemble led by Hugh Dancy and Boyd Gaines, this production offers an exemplary presentation of that theatrical rarity, an uncompromising, clear-eyed play about war and the experience of day-to-day combat. An essential ticket (2:40). Belasco Theater, 111 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MARY POPPINS' This handsome, homily-packed, mechanically ingenious and rather tedious musical, adapted from the P. L. Travers stories and the 1964 film, is ultimately less concerned with inexplicable magic than with practical psychology. Ashley Brown, who sings prettily as the family-mending nanny, looks like Joan Crawford trying to be nice and sounds like Dr. Phil. Directed by Richard Eyre and Matthew Bourne (2:30). New Amsterdam Theater, 214 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LES MISÉRABLES' This premature revival, a slightly scaled-down version of the well-groomed behemoth that closed only three years ago, appears to be functioning in a state of mild sedation. Appealingly sung and freshly orchestrated, this fast-moving adaptation of Victor Hugo's novel isn't sloppy or blurry. But its pulse rate stays well below normal (2:55). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'PRELUDE TO A KISS' Craig Lucas's broken-hearted romantic comedy from 1990 receives a first-rate remounting, courtesy of the Roundabout Theater Company. Alan Tudyk and Annie Parisse play a young couple whose marriage founders shortly after the bride receives a kiss from an elderly stranger (John Mahoney). The kiss awakens all three to an unsettling awareness of love's frailty and, paradoxically, of its durability too (2:00). American Airlines Theater, 227 West 42nd Street, (212) 719-1300. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' Duncan Sheik and Steven Sater's bold adaptation of the Frank Wedekind play is the freshest and most exciting new musical Broadway has seen in some time. Set in 19th-century Germany but with a ravishing rock score, it exposes the splintered emotional lives of adolescents just discovering the joys and sorrows of sex. Performed with brio by a great cast, with supple direction by Michael Mayer and inventive choreography by Bill T. Jones (2:00). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'TALK RADIO' The most lacerating portrait of a human meltdown this side of a Francis Bacon painting. Playing an abrasive radio talk show host with a God complex, the astounding Liev Schreiber seems to fill the air as inescapably as weather in Robert Falls's gut-grabbing revival of Eric Bogosian's 1987 play (1:40). Longacre Theater, 220 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN'  This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a superdeluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE YEAR OF MAGICAL THINKING' Joan Didion's arresting but ultimately frustrating adaptation of her best-selling memoir about being blindsided by grief, starring Vanessa Redgrave. The tension between style and emotional content that made the book such a stunner does not translate to the stage. The substance here is in the silences, when the focus shifts from words to Ms. Redgrave's wry, wounded face (1:40). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'BE' A high-energy, low-content Israeli show that blends music, dance and sex appeal in the latest attempt to tap into the ''Stomp'' market (1:30). Union Square Theater, 100 East 17th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'BILL W. AND DR. BOB' This insightful new play about the founders of Alcoholics Anonymous subtly makes the claim that the recovery movement was born as a series of accidents. Patrick Husted is excellent as Bob Smith, Bill Wilson's partner in combating addictions (2:15). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Ginia Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'DEFENDER OF THE FAITH' This grim tale by Stuart Carolan of low-level I.R.A. agitators trying to identify the informer in their midst features some visceral performances and a set by Charles Corcoran that makes excellent use of the Irish Rep's small stage. If only the cause itself didn't feel so small in these days of global terrorism (1:30). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>* 'DYING CITY' Christopher Shinn's crafty and unsettling play about grief and violence, set in the shadow of the Iraq war. Directed by James Macdonald and fiercely acted by Pablo Schreiber and Rebecca Brooksher, this quiet, transfixing production turns passive aggression into a theatrical dynamic (1:30). Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-7600. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'ESSENTIAL SELF-DEFENSE' Adam Rapp's new play is a quirky love story about a wholesome but anxious girl (the charming Heather Goldenhersh) and an automaton with a beating heart and a big vocabulary (Paul Sparks, impressively affectless). Dark, zany, entirely mannered and mostly empty (2:15). Peter Jay Sharp Theater, Playwrights Horizons, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE FANTASTICKS' A revival -- well, more like a resuscitation -- of the Little Musical That Wouldn't Die. This sweet-as-ever production of Tom Jones and Harvey Schmidt's commedia-dell'arte-style confection is most notable for Mr. Jones's touching performance (under the pseudonym Thomas Bruce) as the Old Actor, a role he created when the show opened in 1960. Mr. Jones also directs (2:05). Snapple Theater Center, 210 West 50th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'FUGUE' ''Mary Smith'' is found wandering the streets of Chicago, suffering from amnesia. A young psychiatrist, who has his own demons, is consulted, and the process of treatment and Mary's memories in flashback are the action of ''Fugue,'' Lee Thuna's unrewarding play, directed by the Tony-winning actress Judith Ivey (2:15). Cherry Lane Theater, 38 Commerce Street, between Barrow and Bedford Streets, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Honor Moore)</p>
        <p>'GUTENBERG! THE MUSICAL' A very funny if not terribly original satire of musical theater features what must be the worst backers' audition of all time (2:05). Actors' Playhouse, 100 Seventh Avenue South, at Fourth Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 239-6200. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>* 'IN THE HEIGHTS' Lin-Manuel Miranda's joyous songs paint a vibrant portrait of daily life in Washington Heights in this flawed but enjoyable show. Essentially a valentine to the barrio -- conflict of a violent or desperate kind is banished from the picture -- the musical contains a host of funny performances and brings the zesty sound of Latin pop to the stage. (2:10). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'JACK GOES BOATING' Bob Glaudini's gentle comedy about pothead losers in love is a reminder of how engrossing uneventful lives can be in the hands of the right actors. Peter DuBois directs the easygoing ensemble, brilliantly led by Philip Seymour Hoffman (2:00). Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'A JEW GROWS IN BROOKLYN' You don't have to be Jewish or Brooklynish to empathize with Jake Ehrenreich, but in terms of fully appreciating his essentially one-man show, it probably helps. Especially the Catskills jokes (2:05). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 560-8912. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>* 'KING HEDLEY II' The Signature Theater Company concludes its season dedicated to August Wilson with a gritty, strongly cast revival of this play set in a violence-ravaged Pittsburgh in the 1980s. Russell Hornsby gives a galvanizing performance in the title role, as a man struggling to live down the errors of his past and plant the seeds for a promising new life (2:45). Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 244-7529. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'LA MAGNANI' Theresa Gambacorta reincarnates the Italian film star in this one-woman show, which reveals her to be more irritating than interesting -- loud and self-absorbed. Ms. Gambacorta does, however, get some pathos out of her relationship to her son, who had polio (1:10). Arclight Theater, 152 West 71st Street, (212) 279-4200. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'MY MOTHER'S ITALIAN, MY FATHER'S JEWISH AND I'M IN THERAPY'  Steve Solomon does skillful impersonations in his one-man show, but some of his jokes are as old as the hills (1:30). Little Shubert Theater, 422 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'MY TRIP TO AL-QAEDA' Lawrence Wright, author of a deeply researched book about the rise of Islamic terrorism, conducts a theatrical seminar about the events leading to the horror of 9/11. He combines a linear narrative of the development of Al Qaeda with reminiscences about the experience of writing the book. Absorbing, and chilling too (1:30). Culture Project, 55 Mercer Street, at Broome Street, SoHo, (212) 352-3101. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'NO CHILD'  Teachers will love Nilaja Sun's one-woman show about the challenges of teaching drama at Malcolm X High School (1:10). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, at Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'OUR LEADING LADY' Kate Mulgrew stars as Laura Keene, who was starring in ''Our American Cousin'' the night Lincoln was shot, in Charles Busch's uneven new comedy. An occasionally lively but mostly lumpen tribute to the glamour and grit of the theatrical life of a past era (2:00). Manhattan Theater Club at City Center Stage II, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'PROMETHEUS BOUND' With a splendid performance by David Oyelowo, this is a smart revival of Aeschylus' 2,500-year-old play, rich in poetic imagery. It still has things to say about the abuse of power by an autocratic ruler who vindictively runs roughshod over anyone who disagrees with him (1:20). Classic Stage Company, 136 East 13th Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101. (Wilborn Hampton)</p>
        <p>'ROOM SERVICE' The Peccadillo Theater Company puts a charge into this comedy from the 1930s, thanks to a brisk pace by the director, Dan Wackerman, and a dozen dandy performances. David Edwards is the would-be producer whose bills threaten to swamp his efforts to put a show on Broadway, and Fred Berman is particularly fine as his director (2:00). SoHo Playhouse, 15 Vandam Street, South Village, (212) 691-1555. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'SOME MEN' Terrence McNally's hit-and-miss comedy about gay life is a parade of cleanly drawn types, zippy one-liners and sentimental set pieces, woven into a pageant of the ages à la ''Cavalcade,'' Noel Coward's generations-spanning tribute to the British stiff upper lip. Trip Cullman directs the agile, appealing cast (2:00). Second Stage, 307 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 246-4422. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SPALDING GRAY: STORIES LEFT TO TELL' A disarming collage of selections from the monologues and journals of Mr. Gray, the ultimate stand-up solipsist, who died in 2004. Directed by Lucy Sexton, and read by five performers, none of whom resemble Mr. Gray, with an affection that shrewdly stops short of hero worship (1:30). Minetta Lane Theater, 18 Minetta Lane, Greenwich Village, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TALL GRASS' Brian Harris's three short plays, black farces all, are not nearly as slight as any sound-bite synopsis would have them seem. Here Mr. Harris, a former stock analyst, explores the alliances formed between love and brutality in scenarios in which the tension builds to culminating shock (1:30). The Beckett Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'TEA AND SYMPATHY' The specter of the Ted Haggard scandal hangs over the Keen Company's revival of Robert Anderson's 1953 play about life in a psychologically stifling boys' boarding school. Girded by Jonathan Silverstein's skillful, understated direction, the play attains an unexpected timeliness as it evolves into a story about the dangers of sexual repression (2:00). Clurman Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>* 'WAKE UP MR. SLEEPY! YOUR UNCONSCIOUS MIND IS DEAD!' Richard Foreman's latest film-theater hybrid is a memorial service, of sorts, for the intuitive self, killed by a surface-worshiping world. It is also a dazzling exercise in reality shifting that is as invigorating as it is mournful (1:05). Ontological Theater at St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'T J AND DAVE' The comics T. J. Jagodowski and Dave Pasquesi miraculously improvise a one-hour play at every performance. This is an impressive feat of mental athletics, but the results are also observant, complex and frequently enormously funny (1:00). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden Theater, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' Singing CliffsNotes for Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' Often more entertaining than the real thing (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS'  The biomusical that walks like a man (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT'  A singing scrapbook for Monty Python fans (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' ''A Chorus Line'' with pimples (1:45). Circle in the Square, 254 West 50th Street, Manhattan, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Spectacles</p>
        <p>'RINGLING BROTHERS AND BARNUM &amp; BAILEY CIRCUS' An eye- and earful (2:10). Madison Square Garden, (212) 307-7171. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'BLINDNESS' Joe Tantalo's adaptation of José Saramago's best-selling novel, about an unnamed city struck with an inexplicable epidemic of ''white blindness,'' is set in a cell-like space surrounded by white scrim. This setting and the mostly strong acting drive home the fearful basic circumstances. Unfortunately, the script also streamlines Mr. Saramago's reflective story to the point of draining it of moral complexity (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200; closes on Sunday. (Jonathan Kalb)</p>
        <p>'THE CAVE DWELLERS' This revival of William Saroyan's 1957 play about a group of misfits inhabiting an abandoned theater examines the virtue of charity and the nobility of failure but feels as stifling and constricted as the building in which the outcasts find themselves. A production that asks us to revere the theater without inviting reverence itself (1:30). Pearl Theater, 80 St. Marks Place, East Village, (212) 598-9802; closes on Sunday. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'CHICKEN' Michael Batistick's new play about cockfighting and emasculation could benefit from subtler metaphors but manages to touch us gently even as it deploys a heavy hammer. E J Carroll, Michael Imperioli and his ''Sopranos'' cast mate Sharon Angela give fine performances as struggling urban nobodies (1:45). Studio Dante, 257 West 29th Street, Chelsea, (212) 868-4444; closes tomorrow. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'DID YOU USED TO BE R. D. LAING?' This sweet, nostalgic solo show explores the life and work of the controversial Scottish psychiatrist -- an international celebrity and countercultural guru in the 1960s -- from the perspective of a genial admirer. It's well acted and empathetic but a bit too pleasantly tranquil to bring such a prickly and passionately disputed figure into full focus (1:30). The American Theater of Actors, 314 West 54th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444; closes tomorrow. (Kalb)</p>
        <p>'THE EXILES'  Theodora Skipitares's rendering, with life-size puppets, music and video, of the story of Orestes, adapted from Euripides but inspired by Sartre. A short and rather slight play that continues the mining of the Trojan War for contemporary equivalents by the conceiver and director of last season's Trilogy (1:00). La MaMa Annex, 74A East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 475-7710; closes on Sunday. (Moore)</p>
        <p>'MEN OF STEEL' This darkly comic twist on superheroes is a loony, guilty pleasure (2:00). Center Stage, 48 West 21st Street, Chelsea, (212) 352-3101; closes on Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'WIDOWERS' HOUSES' An adaptation of George Bernard Shaw's play, updated to 1990s Harlem, tests the limits of credibility (1:40). Kirk Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200; closes on Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>'AFTER THE WEDDING' (R, 119 minutes, in Danish) A modern creation with a classic theme involving haves and have-nots, bloodlines and family ties. The canned realism of the Danish director Susanne Bier is strictly Dogme-lite, but the spiky, screen-filling performances of her two male leads, Mads Mikkelsen and Rolf Lassgard, are really something to see. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'AIR GUITAR NATION' (R, 82 minutes) Alexandra Lipsitz's breezy competition documentary follows pantomiming would-be rockers as they compete for the right to represent their country in a global championship based in Oulou, Finland. The movement, such as it is, aims to unite a war-torn planet in musical fantasy and to rawwwwwwk!  -- but not necessarily in that order. Stylistically, it's nothing special, but the film's droll humor and wild performances are hard to resist. (Matt Zoller Seitz)</p>
        <p>'AMERICAN CANNIBAL' (No rating, 91 minutes) Illustrating the premise that if you lie down with dogs you wake up with fleas, the documentary about a failed reality television series is absorbing in the same sick way as the lowest examples of the genre it examines. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'BEHIND THE MASK: THE RISE OF LESLIE VERNON' (R, 92 minutes) Scott Glosserman's mockumentary about a celebrity-seeking serial killer is sustained by rapier-sharp observations and a firmer grasp of tone than that in many more generously financed projects. The movie subtly prods at the sick dance between the news media and über-criminals without belaboring its point or lowering its tone. If Christopher Guest ever turned his attention to psycho killers instead of dog breeders, this is exactly the sort of movie he would make. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'Blades of Glory' (PG-13, 93 minutes) In this fast, light, frequently funny comedy about a male figure-skating team, Will Ferrell and Jon Heder stake an early claim to being the comedy couple of the year. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'BOY CULTURE' (No rating, 88 minutes) Q. Allan Brocka's absorbing drama follows an emotionally repressed gay hustler (Derek Magyar) as he rebels against the obsessions of his culture -- grooming, cruising, working out -- and a powerful attraction to his roommate. Only when he takes on a reclusive and much older client is he forced to pay attention to a story other than his own. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'CHILDREN OF MEN' (R, 100 minutes) The end is nigh in this superbly directed political thriller directed by Alfonso Cuarón about a nervously plausible future. Based on the P. D. James book, the film stars an excellent Clive Owen and features equally sterling support from the actors Michael Caine, Danny Huston and Chiwetel Ejiofor, among others. , as well as the great cinematographer Emmanuel Lubezki. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'COLOR ME KUBRICK' (No rating, 90 minutes) If it doesn't add up to more than a fitfully amusing collection of comic sketches, the fictional portrait of Alan Conway, a real-life British con man who hustled his way across England by impersonating the reclusive filmmaker Stanley Kubrick, is a platform for John Malkovich to burst into lurid purple flame. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'DEAD SILENCE' (R, 90 minutes) In this new film from the makers of the ''Saw'' series, a young man (Ryan Kwanten) whose wife was murdered by a demonic ventriloquist's dummy returns to his hometown to unravel the roots of a century-old curse. The film's playfully self-aware touches (like a grand old theater named the Guignol) distract from its leaden pacing, three too many final twists and various behavioral idiocies. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>'FIRST SNOW' (R, 101 minutes) Guy Pearce, in his ''Memento'' mode, is a fast-talking salesman in this moody little thriller, which asks metaphysical questions about fate, death and fortunetelling. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE HAWK IS DYING' (No rating, 106 minutes) In this painfully earnest backwoods tale from the director Julian Goldberger, Paul Giamatti plays George Gattling, a dispirited auto upholsterer with a passion for falconry. Set in Central Florida and based on the book by Harry Crews, ''The Hawk Is Dying'' is a dreary study of male angst groaning beneath the weight of its own symbolism. Not since Ken Loach's ''Kes'' has a bird of prey carried so much dramatic responsibility. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'THE HILLS HAVE EYES 2' (R, 89 minutes) Wes Craven's 1977 film, ''The Hills Have Eyes,'' in which suburbanites battled mutant cannibals, was a pulpy parable of the thin line separating civilization from savagery. Last year's remake was basically the same movie with glossier production values and a less satirical, more bludgeoning approach to violence. This follow-up, in which National Guard trainees are trapped on a former atomic test site and are stalked by flesh-eating freaks headquartered in a warrenlike mountain hideout, is essentially a catalog of transgressive images, lighted and edited like a heavy-metal video. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>'I THINK I LOVE MY WIFE' (R, 94 minutes) An unusually smart and brisk comedy of marital frustration and sexual temptation, based on Eric Rohmer's ''Chloe in the Afternoon,'' with Chris Rock (who directed and is co-author of the script) as a Manhattan investment banker distracted by the charms of a bombshell played by the wonderful Kerry Washington. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'KILLER OF SHEEP' (No rating, 83 minutes) Largely hidden from view for three decades, Charles Burnett's lyrical film about a working-class family living in a broken-down home in a bombed-out stretch of Los Angeles is an American masterpiece, independent to the bone. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE LAST MIMZY' (PG, 94 minutes) This overstuffed yet warmhearted sci-fi drama follows a pair of wide-eyed siblings as they solve the riddle of a box from the future. Despite leaden direction (by the New Line Cinema honcho Robert Shaye) and a story crammed with pseudoscientific flotsam -- including palm reading, levitation and telepathy -- this wholesome entertainment doesn't talk down. Nevertheless, a film gazing this far into the future shouldn't be quite so unwilling to look beyond the frame. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'THE LOOKOUT' (R, 99 minutes) This directorial debut by the veteran screenwriter Scott Frank (''Out of Sight'') is a variation of an old, old story, about a nobody (a brain-damaged janitor played by Joseph Gordon-Levitt) who falls in with crooks who make him feel like somebody. Although the movie's no masterpiece -- the final stretch feels forced and unconvincing -- there's a lot to like here. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>* 'OFFSIDE' (PG, 93 minutes, in Persian) The Iranian director Jafar Panahi follows a group of young woman into a Tehran soccer stadium, where they have come to see their nation's team compete for a spot in the World Cup. Instead they are arrested -- women are forbidden to attend sporting events in Iran -- and their predicament yields comedy as well as a trenchant critique of gender politics in the Islamic Republic. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE PAGE TURNER' (No rating, 85 minutes, in French) A pretty young thing slithers into the bosom of a bourgeois family like an asp in this shivery little thriller from the French filmmaker Denis Dercourt. Not Chabrol, but not bad, either. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'PRIDE' (PG, 104 minutes) The Zimbabwean-born filmmaker Sunu Gonera's directorial debut, ''Pride,'' about a swim coach (Terrence Howard, star of ''Hustle &amp; Flow'') leading an urban recreational center's swim team to a championship, about 1971, is a silk ascot wrapped around an ear of corn. But when sinewy young idealists glide through water to the tune of ''I'll Take You There,'' the heart still swells. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>'REIGN OVER ME' (R, 124 minutes) Mike Binder's comic drama of post-9/11 grief is wildly uneven -- by turns insightful and grindingly mawkish. Don Cheadle and Adam Sandler are two college buddies who reunite, somewhat improbably, some years after the attacks that robbed one of them of his family. The actors rise above the material, particularly in the longer, looser scenes that allow their contrasting temperaments -- Mr. Cheadle's tense understatement and Mr. Sandler's shaggy emoting -- to find a workable syncopation. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'SACCO AND VANZETTI' (No rating, 81 minutes) This feature filmmaking debut by Peter Miller, a PBS veteran, hews to standard television documentary format: archival photographs and talking heads. But the movie's meat-and-potatoes style seems less a failure of imagination than a means of putting in the foreground its subject matter: the still-controversial tale of Nicola Sacco and Bartolomeo Vanzetti, Italian immigrants and outspoken anarchists charged with the 1920 robbery of a Massachusetts shoe factory and the murder of two of its employees. A good film on a great subject. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>'SHOOTER' (R, 126 minutes) Muscles bulge and heads explode in this thoroughly reprehensible, satisfyingly violent entertainment about men and guns and things that go boom. Antoine Fuqua directs, and Mark Wahlberg entertains, with and without his shirt. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'U-CARMEN' (No rating, 120 minutes, in Xhosa) Winner of the top award at the 2005 Berlin Film Festival, ''U-Carmen'' pushes against every expectation you would normally bring to a movie version of Bizet's opera. It relocates the tale's doomed romantic triangle to Khayelitsha, an industrial community near Cape Town, South Africa; sets the action in and around a cigarette factory; and translates its libretto into Xhosa, a regional language distinguished by its abundance of pops and clicks. For the most part, the film's action is intentionally plain, always acknowledging its physical environment, which can be frustrating when the melodies soar. But the music still pierces, the blood still flows, and the overall conception is so original that even when the movie falters in the moment, it dazzles in the memory. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>'BERLIN ALEXANDERPLATZ' (Tuesday through April 15) Rainer Werner Fassbinder made this 13-part adaptation of the grueling social realist novel by Alfred Doblin for West German television in 1980, but because the film was shot on 16 millimeter, it has been in fragile condition and out of sight for many years. But now the Fassbinder Foundation, with the support of the Museum of Modern Art, has completed a restoration, transferring the original 16-millimeter negative to 35 millimeter. Gunter Lamprecht stars as the downtrodden hero, a Weimer everyman struggling to keep his stomach full and his dignity intact. Parts 1 through 3 will be shown on Tuesday; 4 through 7 on Wednesday; 8 through 11 on Thursday; and 12, 13 and the epilogue on April 13. (The film will also be repeated in two parts on April 14 and 15.) This screening is part of a three-week series of Fassbinder films from MoMA's collection, which this week will include ''Despair'' (tonight), ''The Merchant of Four Seasons'' (tomorrow), ''Jail Bait'' (tomorrow) and ''Whity'' (Sunday). On Monday, Juliane Lorenz, Fassbinder's longtime editor, will introduce two documentaries, ''Fassbinder's Berlin Alexanderplatz: Notes on the Restoration'' and ''A Mega Movie and Its Story.'' Mr. Lamprecht and one of his co-stars, Barbara Sukowa, are expected to attend. Museum of Modern Art Roy and Niuta Titus Theaters, (212) 708-9400, moma.org; $10. (Dave Kehr)</p>
        <p>FARES TO REMEMBER: TAXI '07 (Today through Sunday) The IFC Center celebrates the 100th anniversary of the taxi in New York City with a month of cab-centric movies. This Friday and Sunday at noon, Harold Lloyd stars in the silent comedy ''Speedy,'' in which one of his duties as a New York cabbie is getting Babe Ruth to the stadium on time. At midnight on Friday and Saturday, Robert De Niro plays a less accommodating chauffeur in Martin Scorsese's dark, expressionist ''Taxi Driver'' (1976). IFC Center, 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 924-7771, ifccenter.com; $10.75. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>THE REAL EDIE SEDGWICK (Tomorrow and Sunday) The Museum of the Moving Image concludes a survey of the film work of this Warhol superstar, society figure and all-around study in self-destructiveness with several rarely shown Warhol films, including ''Kitchen,'' ''Restaurant,'' ''Afternoon'' (made from outtakes from ''Chelsea Girls''), ''Beauty #2'' and ''Horse,'' all from 1965. There's also a pair of non-Warhol efforts: ''Poem Posters,'' a 1967 documentary by Charles Henri Ford in which Sedgwick appears among the downtown celebrities at an art opening, and the 1972 ''Ciao, Manhattan,'' a semi-autobiographical feature completed just weeks before Sedgwick's death. Museum of the Moving Image, 35th Avenue, at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718) 784-0077, movingimage.us; $10. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>CHRISTINA AGUILERA, PUSSYCAT DOLLS, DANITY KANE (Tomorrow) Frau Farbissina of the ''Austin Powers'' movies said it best: ''Send in the Fembots!'' Ms. Aguilera may have the most virtuosic voice of her generation of bubble-gum pop stars, but as she showed with her endless melismatic protraction of James Brown's ''It's a Man's Man's Man's World'' at the Grammys in February, she can sometimes seem like a singing robot gone berserk. Her tour includes a hit burlesque girl group (the Pussycat Dolls) and an imitation hit burlesque girl group (Danity Kane). At 7:30 p.m., Nassau Coliseum, 1255 Hempstead Turnpike, Uniondale, N.Y., (516) 794-9300, nassaucoliseum.com; $55 to $95. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>* LILY ALLEN, THE BIRD AND THE BEE (Wednesday) A 21-year-old British singer with deceptively sweet, ska-infused electro-pop songs, Ms. Allen is at her best when snarkily putting down disagreeable suitors. ''Smile,'' a No. 1 hit in England, is pure schadenfreude, and ''Knock 'Em Out'' a catalog of snappy answers to bad pickup lines: ''I've got herpes. No, I've got syphilis.'' The Bird and the Bee, a well-dressed duo from Los Angeles, toys with two fashionable ideas: retro French pop glittering with electronics, and ''Sex and the City''-style sexual conundrums. This show inaugurates the newly renamed Fillmore New York at Irving Plaza. At 8:40 p.m., 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, irvingplaza.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* ALLMAN BROTHERS (Tonight through Sunday) The best spring ritual on the Upper West Side is the arrival of this archetypal Southern rock band for its annual series of concerts at the Beacon Theater, ending this weekend. At 8, 2124 Broadway, at 74th Street, (212) 307-7171, beacontheatrenyc.com; $54.99 to $94.99. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BLUE CHEER, AN ALBATROSS (Tomorrow) On a few gloriously untidy albums in the late 1960s and early '70s, Blue Cheer followed the blunter edges of Jimi Hendrix's sound into a bludgeoning kind of primordial heavy metal, and played it with an un-self-conscious glee that made the band sound like cave men discovering fire. An Albatross, from Wilkes-Barre, Pa., shrieks its way through dizzying but lighthearted prog-hardcore songs that borrow something from Captain Beefheart. At 8 p.m., Rebel, 251 West 30th Street, Manhattan, (212) 695-2747, rebelnyc.com; $12 in advance, $15 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BARBARA CARROLL (Sunday and Monday) Elegant, witty and touching, this classically trained jazz pianist and singer, now 82, is in her prime: the female counterpart of Bobby Short. Sunday at 2 p.m., Monday at 8 p.m., Oak Room at the Algonquin Hotel, 59 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212) 419-9331, algonquinhotel.com; $58 on Sunday, with brunch at noon; $40 on Monday, with a $20 minimum. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>CÉU (Monday and Tuesday) With an easy, dragging beat, bossa nova becomes something like light dub in the lithe and playful songs of Céu, a young woman from São Paulo who is rising fast in the Brazilian circuit. Monday at 9:30 p.m., Tuesday at 7:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $15. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* COLD WAR KIDS, TOKYO POLICE CLUB (Tonight, tomorrow and Monday nights) The craggy guitars and piano, elliptical songwriting and verge-of-a-breakdown vocals of Cold War Kids, from Long Beach, Calif., may be par for the indie-rock course. But if the band's three sold-out shows this week at the Bowery Ballroom are any indication, it is still basking in the microfame bestowed over the last year by zealous bloggers. Tonight and tomorrow night, Cold War Kids play with Tokyo Police Club, a Canadian group that spikes Strokes-like songs with noisy petulance. At 9, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com. Tokyo Police Club also plays Monday at 10 p.m. at the Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700, mercuryloungenyc.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JOÃO DONATO (Tonight) Mr. Donato is one of the great bossa nova composers of the late-'50s generation, and probably the one most influenced by American jazz; his performances these days are nostalgic and sometimes anarchically funny. At 7 and 9:30, Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $30. (Ben Ratliff)</p>
        <p>* IGGY AND THE STOOGES (Monday) Suffice it to say that ''The Weirdness'' (Virgin), the first Stooges album in 34 years, is not likely to become a classic. But as with every one of Iggy Pop's many mediocre solo albums over the years, any excuse to keep him on the road is worthwhile. Even nearing 60, he remains an inspirationally feral performer, and on past tours the reunited Stooges have ably summoned some of the raw, menacing groove that made them one of the primary godfathers of punk rock. With Sistas in the Pit. At 7 p.m., United Palace Theater, 4140 Broadway, at 175th Street, Washington Heights, (212) 307-7171, bowerypresents.com; $39.50 to $59.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JUNIOR BOYS (Wednesday) When dance music goes sad: squiggly, awkward beats and droopy keyboards surround the forlorn vocals of this Canadian electronic group, who sing about missed birthdays and phones that don't ring. With San Serac and TigerCity. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>KAISER CHIEFS, WALKMEN (Thursday) Gracefully but not always excitingly, the Kaiser Chiefs, from Leeds, England, mingle the spunky minimalism of XTC-vintage post-punk with the ballad-friendly melodicism of '90s Britpop. The Walkmen, from New York, play exquisitely articulated songs of exhaustion and disaffection, with Hamilton Leithauser's weary whine surrounded by an echoey wash of guitar and keyboards. With the Annuals. At 7:30 p.m., Roseland Ballroom, 239 West 52nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, roselandballroom.com; $31 in advance, $35 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>KIKI AND HERB (Sunday) A few years ago this brilliantly perverse cabaret duo played their farewell show at Carnegie Hall. Then came a run on Broadway. And some late-night gigs at Joe's Pub. And the inimitable Christmas show. (Highlight: a medley of ''Smells Like Teen Spirit'' and ''Frosty the Snowman.'') Kiki and Herb can't stay away from the stage, and New York is the better for it. At 11:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* KLAXONS (Tuesday) This British trio's eerie rave-punk is punctuated by the peal of air-raid sirens and paranoid, shouted lyrics that allude to William S. Burroughs and Thomas Pynchon. How the band manages to cram in such fear and loathing and still make exhilarating, danceable grooves is what makes it fascinating. With Bonde do Role, a Brazilian baile-funk group that makes silly but contagiously high-energy electronic pastiches. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>SONDRE LERCHE (Tomorrow) A 24-year-old Norwegian with a kind tenor and a light touch, Mr. Lerche plays elegant, melodically rich but sometimes overly coy folk-pop. With Willy Mason and Thomas Dybdahl. At 6:30 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; $25. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LOSER'S LOUNGE TRIBUTE TO HALL AND OATES (Thursday) As Nick Lowe said, you've got to be cruel to be kind. Joe McGinty's enduring Loser's Lounge series, now 14 years old, both honors and skewers pop greats with cleverly over-the-top performances, and turns its attention here to Hall and Oates, whose mega-selling soul-pop ranged from the sublime (''She's Gone'') to the farcical (''Portable Radio''). At 9:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $25. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LOW; LONEY, DEAR (Tonight) With exquisite care, Low, from Duluth, Minn., featuring the husband-and-wife team of Alan Sparhawk on guitar and Mimi Parker on vocals, and Matt Livingston on bass, creates hushed, stark songs on a vast sonic scale. Loney, Dear, led by the Swedish songwriter Emil Svanangen, plays placid folk-pop decorated with endearing, '60s-style harmonies. At 6:30 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PARTS AND LABOR (Tonight) This squally Brooklyn three-piece ably pulls off the tricky task of being both anarchic and anthemic. With Big Bear, Gowns and Alex Delivery. At 8:30, Luna Lounge, 361 Metropolitan Avenue, at Havemeyer Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, lunalounge.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PEEPING TOM (Monday) The latest project of Mike Patton, the naughty boy of heavy metal turned naughty boy of the avant-garde. The gimmick here is creepy lounge and trip-hop, with various collaborators in on the joke. For this show the guests are Dan the Automator, Miho Hatori of Cibo Matto and the rapper Pigeon John. At 9 p.m., Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, irvingplaza.com; $25. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PRETTY RICKY (Tomorrow) This R&amp;B boy band from Miami has hit the top of the charts with amorous crooning -- and some rapping -- that drops flirtatious pretense in pursuit of the girl and cuts right to the chase: ''Can I put a little peer pressure on ya?'' At 7 p.m., Roseland Ballroom, 239 West 52nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, roselandballroom.com; $29.50 in advance, $35 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>RASPUTINA (Tonight) Rasputina is a charmingly improbable project: part Marie Antoinette, part metal. Three women who are cellists in corsets (as well as a drummer) sing about Transylvanian concubines as their music seesaws between elaborate chamber-music counterpoint and grunting hard-rock chords, complete with distortion. With the Bowmans. At 9, Gramercy Theater, 127 East 23rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171; $20.50. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>DIANA ROSS (Tonight) In her guest performance on ''American Idol'' last month, Ms. Ross showed that at 63 she remains every bit the ''dreamgirl'': breezing her way through the Spiral Starecase song ''More Today Than Yesterday,'' she was smooth, cocky and in love with her own voice -- a true superstar. At 8, the Theater at Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741, thegarden.com; $59.50 to $149.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MARTIN SEXTON (Tonight) This singer and songwriter can groan like an alternative rocker, slide like a soul man or leap up to a pearly falsetto. Singing about restlessness and love while he picks syncopations on his guitar, Mr. Sexton can turn an ordinary song into a jazzy showcase, and a good one into a transmission from the heart. With Jonah Smith. At 9, Nokia Theater, 1515 Broadway, at 44th Street, (212) 307-7171, nokiatheatrenyc.com; $30. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>STONE SOUR, SHADOWS FALL, LACUNA COIL (Tonight) Stone Sour, featuring Corey Taylor of the horror-metal crew Slipknot, leads a strong bill of angry guitars and punishing drums. Slipknot is indiscriminate in its misanthropy, but in the poppier Stone Sour, Mr. Taylor chooses his targets more carefully, including some not-so-veiled political ones: ''We're more in danger than before you took power.'' At 7:20, Roseland Ballroom, 239 West 52nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800 roselandballroom.com; $34. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* KOKO TAYLOR (Tonight) For five decades Ms. Taylor, 71, has sung brawny, carnal blues like ''Wang Dang Doodle'' with a strength and swagger rivaling that of any man. After a health crisis a few years ago, she has returned with a new album, ''Old School'' (Alligator), in which she shows that her ego remains as strong as her voice: ''You don't want to tangle with me,'' she sings. At 8, B. B. King Blues Club &amp; Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $35. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>TEDDYBEARS (Monday) This Swedish band has one of the year's bigger head-scratchers with ''Punkrocker,'' a paranoid jaunt with new-wave synthesizers and a deadpan vocal by Iggy Pop that is being used in a Cadillac ad -- makes perfect sense, right? With Foreign Islands. At 7 p.m., Gramercy Theater, 127 East 23rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171; $14.50 in advance, $16 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>WORLD/INFERNO FRIENDSHIP SOCIETY (Tomorrow) The World/Inferno Friendship Society's ''red-eyed soul'' is a raucous mix of ska, punk and horn-driven retro R&amp;B. With Paint It Black, the Vicious and Measure SA. At 7 p.m., Europa, 98 Meserole Avenue, at Manhattan Avenue, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 383-5723, europaclub.com; $13. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>* JOHN ABERCROMBIE QUARTET (Wednesday and Thursday) The guitarist John Abercrombie has a new album, ''The Third Quartet'' (ECM), that captures the thoughtful chemistry of this group with the violinist Mark Feldman, the bassist Marc Johnson and the drummer Joey Baron. (Through April 14.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>* ALL THAT JAZZ: NOW THAT'S HIP (Tuesday) This annual concert, sponsored by the HIP Health Plan of New York, invariably spotlights the trumpeter Wynton Marsalis with his working band. This edition, ''New Orleans Rising,'' also benefits from the inclusion of the pianist-singer Dr. John, with his rollicking swamp-funk band the Lower 911. At 8 p.m., Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 721-6500, jalc.org; $32.50 to $87.50. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CARL ALLEN AND NEW SPIRIT (Tonight and tomorrow night) The drummer Carl Allen leads a gospel-steeped bop unit with Vincent Herring on alto saxophone and Aaron Goldberg on piano. At 8, 10 and midnight, Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212) 255-3626, sweetrhythmny.com; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVE ALLEN (Monday) Mr. Allen is a guitarist with a coolly modernistic sensibility, as he demonstrated on his last album, ''Untold Stories'' (Fresh Sound New Talent). Two musicians from the album, the tenor saxophonist Seamus Blake and the drummer Mark Ferber, join him here. At 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SAM BARDFELD'S STUFF SMITH PROJECT (Thursday) Sam Bardfeld, a violinist with a wide-ranging résumé, pays tribute to a swing-era hero of his instrument with help from the pianist Anthony Coleman, the bassist Sean Conly and the guitarist and vocalist Doug Wamble. At 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PETER BRÖTZMANN, MARINO PLIAKAS AND MICHAEL WERTMUELLER (Wednesday) Few modern saxophonists can sound as powerfully abrasive as Mr. Brötzmann, whose most recent album, ''Full Blast'' (Jazzwerkstatt), is a collaboration with Mr. Pliakas, a guitarist and bassist, and Mr. Wertmueller, a drummer. At 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* RAVI COLTRANE QUARTET / DAVID SÁNCHEZ QUARTET (Tuesday through Thursday) Ravi Coltrane and David Sánchez are two of the more assertively creative tenor saxophonists to emerge within the jazz mainstream in the last dozen or so years, and each has a knack for organizing rhythmically sophisticated working bands. (Through April 15.) At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $30 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* DAVE DOUGLAS AND KEYSTONE (Thursday) On his recent album ''Keystone'' (Greenleaf), the trumpeter Dave Douglas imagines a vividly contemporary soundtrack to the silent films of Roscoe (Fatty) Arbuckle. The music sounds best in performance, thanks to a smartly thrashing electro-acoustic band with Marcus Strickland on tenor saxophone, Adam Benjamin on Fender Rhodes piano, Brad Jones on bass, DJ Olive on turntables and Gene Lake on drums. (Through April 15.) At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>FOR THOSE WE LOVE (Thursday) This glittery but heartfelt benefit concert -- with the jazz-pop ensemble New York Voices, the jazz-cabaret singers Jane Monheit and Louise Rogers, and the Latin-jazz saxophonist and clarinetist Paquito D'Rivera -- supports the New York chapter of the Alzheimer's Association. At 7:30 p.m., Kaye Playhouse at Hunter College, East 68th Street between Park and Lexington Avenues, (212) 772-4448, alznyc.org; $50 to $250. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SONNY FORTUNE TRIO (Tomorrow) Since the 1960s, countless saxophonists have adopted the methodology of John Coltrane, but few have captured his restless spirit. Mr. Fortune, the saxophonist of choice for the late Coltrane drummer Elvin Jones, is chief among them; he performs with the bassist David Williams and the drummer Neal Smith. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Sista's Place, 456 Nostrand Avenue, at Jefferson Avenue, Brooklyn, (718) 398-1766, sistasplace.org; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILL FRISELL TRIO (Tuesday through Thursday) On his last two trio releases, both partly recorded at the Village Vanguard, the guitarist Bill Frisell conjures a compelling hallucination of the American popular songbook. His partners are the bassist Tony Scherr and the drummer Kenny Wollesen, a widely traveled rhythm team. (Through April 15.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ROBERT GLASPER TRIO (Tonight) A percussive and tuneful pianist, Robert Glasper mines a jazz tradition informed by gospel and many strains of R&amp;B. His trio, with Vicente Archer on bass and Damion Reid on drums, just released a strong second album, ''In My Element'' (Blue Note). At 11:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, 425 Lafayette Street, East Village, (212) 967-7555 , joespub.com; cover, $15, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* JIM HALL AND RON CARTER (Tonight through Sunday) Summoning the effervescent spirit of ''Alone Together,'' an album issued 35 years ago, the guitarist Jim Hall and the bassist Ron Carter engage in discursive and articulate duets. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $35 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* ICP ORCHESTRA (Tonight) The acronym stands for Instant Composers Pool, which conveys both the immediacy and the structural integrity of this 10-piece ensemble's creations. The group, now celebrating its 40th anniversary, also has the finest improvisers in Amsterdam. At 8 and 9:30 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE LEHMAN QUARTET (Tomorrow) The saxophonist Steve Lehman pursues an abstract lyricism informed by myriad traditions. His quintet includes sharp and sympathetic peers: the trumpeter Jonathan Finlayson, the bassist Drew Gress and the drummer Tyshawn Sorey. At midnight, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $10, $5 for students, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVID LIEBMAN GROUP (Tonight and tomorrow night) An incantatory saxophonist working in the post-Coltrane idiom, David Liebman plays here with his longstanding quartet, with Vic Juris on guitar, Tony Marino on bass and Marko Marcinko on drums. At 10, 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PAT MARTINO (Tonight through Sunday) A powerfully proficient guitarist, Mr. Martino favors a brand of post-bop that has more than a little in common with the blistering fusion of his youth. At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., with a midnight set tonight and tomorrow, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $35, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MODERN ROMANCE: IGOR BUTMAN AND IGOR RAYKHELSON (Tomorrow) Mr. Butman is a saxophonist and one of Russia's top jazz musicians, and Mr. Raykhelson is a pianist and composer equally drawn to jazz and classical music. Performing here with musicians including the violinist Elena Revich and the cellist Boris Andrianov, they advance a crossover ideal. At 7:30 p.m., Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $40 and $35. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>AMANDA MONACO 4 / NICOLAS MASSON QUARTET (Wednesday) Amanda Monaco is a guitarist whose recent album, ''Intention'' (Innova), showcases her playfully restive compositions for a quartet with Jason Gillenwater on tenor saxophone, Sean Conly on bass and Jeff Davis on drums. In a later set, the saxophonist Nicolas Masson leads his own quartet, with the trumpeter Russ Johnson, the bassist Eivind Opsvik and the drummer Gerald Cleaver. At 8 and 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* THELONIOUS MONK 90TH BIRTHDAY CELEBRATION (Thursday) A premature celebration, perhaps -- Thelonious Monk was born in October -- but a thoughtfully programmed one, involving a pianist deeply familiar with Monkish expression (Kenny Barron) and a repertory band led by one of Monk's former drummers (Ben Riley's Monk Legacy Septet). As a bonus, the actor Rome Neal will revisit his role in ''Monk'' (the one-man play, not the television show). At 8 p.m., TriBeCa Performing Arts Center, Borough of Manhattan Community College, 199 Chambers Street, (212) 220-1460, tribecapac.org; $30, $27.50 for students. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>WOLFGANG MUTHSPIEL AND BRIAN BLADE (Tomorrow and Sunday) Mr. Muthspiel is an Austrian guitarist, and Mr. Blade is a drummer from Louisiana. They have an engrossing and remarkably full-sounding new duo album, ''Friendly Travelers'' (Material), that features crystalline playing and a liquid sort of rapport. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MILES OKAZAKI (Thursday) Mr. Okazaki is a confident guitarist and composer whose recent album, ''Mirror,'' involves a pair of powerful alto saxophonists: David Binney and Miguel Zenón, who join him here. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ONE FOR ALL (Tonight and tomorrow night) The driving hard bop of Art Blakey's Jazz Messengers lends a mission and a method for this band, which consists of the saxophonist Eric Alexander, the trumpeter Jim Rotondi, the trombonist Steve Davis, the pianist David Hazeltine, the bassist Nat Reeves and the drummer Joe Farnsworth. At 8, 10 and 11:30, Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662, smokejazz.com; cover, $30. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MISHA PIATIGORSKY (Wednesday) On his new album, ''Uncommon Circumstance'' (Mishamusic), the pianist Misha Piatigorsky plays original music informed both by classical and groove-based music, with impressive but sometimes airless results. He has an excellent rhythm section, though, in the bassist Hans Glawischnig and the drummer Ari Hoenig, who appear here. At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JENNY SCHEINMAN (Tuesday) Ms. Scheinman is that rare jazz violinist who embraces her instrument's folksier side without making concessions to genre. She performs here with two frequent foils, the guitarist Adam Levy and the clarinetist Doug Weiselman. At 7 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SING INTO SPRING FESTIVAL (Tonight through Thursday) Singers reign at Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola through mid-April, appearing with first-rate backing bands. The estimable Claudia Acuña performs this weekend, while a promising newcomer, Sachal Vasandani, appears on Tuesday. Wednesday's shows feature Jamie Davis; on Thursday, the legendary Jimmy Scott begins a four-night run. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m. with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LOREN STILLMAN QUARTET (Wednesday) Loren Stillman, an alto saxophonist with an inquisitive relationship to jazz conventions, leads a quartet with the guitarist Nate Radley, the bassist Matt Pavolka and the drummer Ted Poor. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Tea Lounge, 837 Union Street, between Sixth and Seventh Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 789-2762, tealoungeny.com; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STRYKER/SLAGLE BAND (Tonight through Sunday) The guitarist Dave Stryker and the saxophonist Steve Slagle have worked together in hard-driving settings since as far back as the mid-1980s; their rhythm section here consists of the eminently capable Jay Anderson and Billy Hart, on bass and drums. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow, Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25, $20 on Sunday. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* RANDY WESTON (Wednesday) Mr. Weston's pianism can recall Duke Ellington and Thelonious Monk, but as a composer he has long reached beyond the specific parameters of jazz. He performs under the auspices of the Central Brooklyn Jazz Festival with his dynamic African Rhythms Trio. At 7 p.m., Brooklyn Historical Society, 128 Pierrepont Street, at Clinton Street, Brooklyn, (718) 222-4111 Ext. 250, brooklynhistory.org; $45, $30 for members, reservations required. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera  'DIE ÄGYPTISCHE HELENA' (Tomorrow) With its convoluted libretto by Hugo von Hofmannsthal and unevenly inspired score by Richard Strauss, this wry contemporary take on the Helen of Troy myth, has remained a rarity since its 1928 premiere. But the Metropolitan Opera's fancifully surreal new production by David Fielding, mounted for the soprano Deborah Voigt, makes a compelling case for this intriguing work, thanks to Mr. Voigt's vocally lustrous and affecting portrayal of the title role as well as the vibrant and insightful conducting of Fabio Luisi. The brilliant coloratura Diana Damrau is wonderful as the sorceress Aithra. The German tenor Torsten Kerl sings Menelas. This is the final performance of the season. At 8:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $42 to $220. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'ANDREA CHÉNIER' (Tomorrow and Wednesday) Ben Heppner, arguably the leading Wagnerian tenor of our day, continues his bold explorations of far-flung repertory with the title role of Giordano's swashbuckling verismo opera, in the Met's revival of Nicolas Joël's 1996 production. Mr. Heppner may lack the vocal colorings and idiomatic expressivity of the heroic Italian tenors who excelled in this touchstone role, a poet with libertarian fervor during the French Revolution. But in his honest and compelling portrayal he sings with burnished sound, vigor and lyrical sensitivity. The rich-voiced soprano Violeta Urmana as Maddalena and the powerful baritone Mark Delavan as Gérard are very strong. Marco Armiliato conducts. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m. and Wednesday at 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $220 to $320 tomorrow, $15 to $175 for Wednesday. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'LA DONNA DEL LAGO' (Tomorrow) Rossini's sleek, simple and lovely take on Sir Walter Scott is ending its run at the New York City Opera. Elena, the Donna in question, is sung by Alexandrina Pendatchanska. The two high-flying tenor parts are taken by Barry Banks as Uberto and Andrew Drost as Rodrigo. At 8 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nycopera.com; $25 to $130. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>'CURLEW RIVER' (Thursday) Britten called his one-act opera ''Curlew River'' a church parable. Inspired by a Japanese Noh play, the work takes the form of a sacred ritual, with a procession of monks enacting a mystery play about a madwoman who crosses a river with a ferryman in search of her abducted son. The Japan Society offers a staging of this haunting and seldom-seen work, a co-production with the L'Opéra Rouen/Haute-Normandie directed by Yoshi Oida, starring the tenor Michael Bennett as the madwoman, with musical direction by David Stern. At 7:30 p.m., 333 East 47th Street, Manhattan, (212) 715-1258, japansociety.org; $52; $45 for members. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'GIULIO CESARE' (Tonight and Tuesday) The Metropolitan Opera joins a big week for Handel opera with the first ''Giulio Cesare'' of the season. David Daniels and Ruth Ann Swenson are in principal roles, and Harry Bicket conducts. At 7:30, Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $110 to $320 tickets remaining tonight, $15 to $175 for Tuesday. (Holland)</p>
        <p>'MADAMA BUTTERFLY' (Tomorrow) New principals take over the City Opera's current run of Puccini's inspired tearjerker. Shu-Ying Li is Cio-Cio-San and Christopher Jackson is Pinkerton. Atsushi Yamada is the new conductor. At 1:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nycopera.com; $25 to $125. (Holland)</p>
        <p>'LA TRAVIATA' (Wednesday) The stylishly realistic production of Verdi's ''Traviata'' created by the soprano Renata Scotto for the New York City Opera returns to the repertory. Making her company debut as Violetta is the French soprano Anne-Sophie Duprels, who has won high praise for her portrayal of the role in London and other cities. The tenor Bruce Sledge sings Alfredo. George Manahan conducts. At 7:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nycopera.com; $25 to $125. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'TURANDOT' (Monday) For spectacle and big music, the Franco Zeffirelli production at the Met of Puccini's final opera is hard to beat. For compelling leads, you might have to look elsewhere: Andrea Gruber sounded wobbly and thin on the first night of this revival, and Richard Margison effort-full, though he marshaled his forces for ''Nessun dorma.'' Only Hei-Kyung Hong's Liu, with her reliably floating pianos, was really worth the price of admission. But spectacle and size are evidently enough to keep tickets selling briskly for this one. Marco Armiliato conducts. At 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000 metopera.org; sold out. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>'DIE ZAUBERFLÖTE' (Monday and Wednesday) William Kentridge, the South African art-world star, is an animator, a draughtsman and a man of the theater. After a range of smaller-scale works -- the puppet operas ''Zeno at 4 a.m.'' and ''Il Ritorno di Ulisse in Patria'' were both seen at Lincoln Center in recent years -- he took on Mozart's final opera for the Théâtre Royal de la Monnaie in Belgium in 2005. Set in a Victorian age of exploration, with antic animations, the resulting production (conducted by an assistant of René Jacobs, who led the original) comes to Brooklyn for four performances through next weekend. At 7:30 p.m., Brooklyn Academy of Music, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, (718) 636-4100, bam.org; $30 to $110. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>'ABSOLUTE ARABIAN NIGHTS' (Tomorrow) Conceived by Kristjan Jarvi, the adventurous young conductor who founded the hip Absolute Ensemble, and the Swiss-born composer Daniel Schnyder, ''Absolute Arabian Nights'' is, the presenters state, a classical, jazz and ethnic music fusion of the sights and spirit of the Middle East. This ensemble's guests for this timely program include Marcel Khalife on oud and vocals, Bachar Khalife on hand percussion and Bassam Saba on nay. At 8 p.m., Town Hall, 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 840-2824, the-townhall-nyc.org; $37.50 and $40. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* BARGEMUSIC (Tonight, tomorrow, Sunday and Thursday) This floating concert hall, moored at the foot of the Brooklyn Bridge, is making the most of its intimate atmosphere by having the musicologist Maya Pritsker on hand tonight and tomorrow to discuss the music on the programs. Tonight, the pianist Daniel Vaiman plays sonatas by Rachmaninoff, Scriabin and Prokofiev. Tomorrow, the violinist Michael Vaiman and the pianist Dina Yoffe play sonatas by Mozart, Shostakovich and Schumann. On Sunday, the New York Chamber Soloists perform Bach's ''Musical Offering'' as well as Mozart's Adagio and Rondo in C minor (K. 617) and the premiere of Gerald Fried's ''Chess Game,'' a work inspired by ''Alice in Wonderland.'' On Thursday, the pianist and composer Dick Hyman leads an ensemble that also includes clarinet and strings in works by Gershwin and Rodgers and Hammerstein, as well as his own ''Baby Boom'' and Sextet. Mozart's exquisite Clarinet Quintet and a Leclair sonata fill out the program. Tonight, tomorrow and Thursday at 8 p.m., Sunday at 4 p.m., Fulton Ferry Landing next to the Brooklyn Bridge, Brooklyn, (718) 624-2083, bargemusic.org. $35 tonight and tomorrow; $40 on Sunday; $45 on Thursday. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>THOMAS BUCKNER (Thursday) The baritone Thomas Buckner, here presented by the World Music Institute as part of the Interpretations series (which he curates), has long been a champion of avant-garde music. He will perform new works for voice and various instruments, including William Duckworth's ''Their Song'' for baritone and piano. Petr Kotik conducts the New York premiere of Christian Wolff's ''37 Haiku'' for baritone, oboe, horn, viola and cello, and the world premiere of ''A People's History'' by R. Chris Dahlgren for baritone, flute, clarinet, percussion, piano, celeste, violin and cello. At 8 p.m., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212) 501-3330, kaufman-center.org; $10; $7 for students. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>SARAH CHANG (Tuesday) Sarah Chang, a former prodigy who has matured into a gifted artist, and Ashley Wass, a pianist, play Beethoven's ''Kreutzer'' Sonata and Prokofiev's Violin Sonata No. 2. Sandwiched between these two extroverted works is the New York premiere of Richard Danielpour's introverted ''River of Light,'' written in memory of Isaac Stern. At 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $25 to 79. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>COLLEGIUM VOCALE GENT (Sunday) Whatever your religious persuasions, for a music lover there is no better way to spend Easter Sunday than listening to the Collegium Vocale Gent under Philippe Herreweghe perform Bach's ''St. John Passion.'' The ensembles (both chorus and orchestra) are first-rate, the music breathtaking, the soloists (including Camilla Tilling and Christoph Prégardien as the Evangelist) reliable: superlatives fail us. Just go. At 3 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $60. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>CUTTING EDGE ENSEMBLE (Monday) The conductor and composer Victoria Bond is the host of a series of concerts that bring together music and other art forms -- in this case, weaving and digital art. Pamela Topham's ''Water Music,'' a tapestry inspired by the East Hampton landscape, will be paired with Libby Larsen's ''Slow Structures,'' a composition inspired by water as it freezes. Judith Shatin's ''Penelope's Song,'' for cello and electronics, uses the sounds of a weaver's loom. And Kenji Bunch's ''Crawl Space,'' ''Sarabande'' and ''The 3 G's'' will be accompanied by video of digital painting and animation. At 8 p.m., the Thalia at Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, symphonyspace.org; $15; $10 for students. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>EITHER/OR FESTIVAL (Tonight and tomorrow night) Concerts presented by Either/Or offer new works for solo instruments and unconventional chamber ensembles. A mini-festival offers solo and chamber works for piano, guitar, violin, cello and percussion. The lineup tonight features music by Michael Gordon, Richard Carrick, Xenakis and premieres by Nick Didkovsky, Andrew Byrne and Mauricio Rodriguez. Tomorrow's concert features a premiere by Mr. Carrick and pieces by Helmut Lachenmann, Keeril Makan and Massimo Lauricella. At 8, Tenri Cultural Institute, 43A West 13th Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 645- 2800, eitherormusic.org; $15, $10 for students, $25 for both concerts. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>RICHARD GOODE (Thursday) This pianist's work has been consistently thoughtful and enlightening. He addresses himself here to Bach's Partita No. 5, Mozart's Rondo in A (K. 511), Brahms's Fantasies (Op. 116) and Debussy's Preludes, Book II. At 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $28 to $90. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* JERUSALEM STRING QUARTET (Thursday) This young ensemble played a memorable concert at the 92nd Street Y last season in which it framed a Brahms Piano Quintet with American and Israeli works. The group's program at Zankel Hall looks more cautious -- the repertory is Beethoven's Quartet in F (Op. 18, No. 1), Janacek's gritty ''Kreutzer Sonata'' Quartet, and Tchaikovsky's Quartet No. 1 -- but presumably these musicians play this works with the same electricity that enlivened their performance last year. At 7:30 p.m., Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $30 to $42. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>WOLFGANG HOLZMAIR AND HERMINE HASELBÖCK (Monday) Hot on the heels of their exploration of the songs of Hugo Wolf, Mr. Holzmair, a baritone, and Ms. Haselböck, a mezzo-soprano (both excellent Austrian singers), turn their attention to the songs of Franz Schreker, a major opera composer of the early 20th century whose music was branded ''degenerate'' by the Nazis. The event is offered in tandem with the American premiere of Schreker's 1910 opera, ''Der Ferne Klang,'' in a concert performance by the American Symphony Orchestra and Leon Botstein. At 8 p.m., Austrian Cultural Forum, 11 East 52nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 319-5300; acfny.com; free, but reservations are required. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>MIKLOS PERENYI AND ANDRAS SCHIFF (Wednesday and Thursday) Two distinguished Hungarians, the cellist Mr. Perenyi and his friend the pianist Mr. Schiff, take on Beethoven's cello and piano repertory with back-to-back concerts at the 92nd Street Y. At 8 p.m., 1395 Lexington Avenue, (212) 415-5500, 92y.org; $45. (Holland)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK FESTIVAL OF SONG (Wednesday and Thursday) Latin song has become a great passion among the many wide-ranging passions of Steven Blier, the polymathic co-founder, co-director, accompanist and speaker of the New York Festival of Song. ''Amores Nuevos'' is a new program of music by Alberto Hemsi, Maria Grever, Gisela Hernández and many other composers one will probably be glad to have heard of at evening's end. Michelle Areyzaga, Jeffrey Picon and Ricardo Herrera are the soloists. At 8 p.m., Weill Recital Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $48. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC (Wednesday and Thursday) This week's focus is on Shostakovich's first violin concerto, introduced by Peter Schickele at an ''Inside the Music'' event on Wednesday, performed by Lisa Batiashvili with the conductor Sakari Oramo on that night and Thursday. For Mr. Oramo, however, another highlight is his compatriot Sibelius's Sixth Symphony: the rising star, who successfully succeeded Simon Rattle in Birmingham, is recording a complete Sibelius cycle. Wednesday at 6:45 p.m., Thursday at 7:30 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nyphil.org; $24 to $60 for Wednesday, $28 to $94 for Thursday. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>* POMERIUM (Tomorrow) Alexander Blachly leads his superb choir in a program of Renaissance Passion and Resurrection motets for Easter. Among the composers represented in this broadly international program are Dufay, Gesualdo, Monteverdi, Senfl, Lassus and Byrd. At 1 and 3 p.m., the Cloisters, Fort Tryon Park, Washington Heights, (212) 650-2290, metmuseum.org; $35. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>ILYA YAKUSHEV (Tomorrow) Ilya Yakushev, the winner of the 2005 World Piano Competition in Cincinnati, is a graduate of Mannes College of Music and currently studies with Vladimir Feltsman. Mr. Yakushev, a 25-year-old native of St. Petersburg, Russia, has been executive director of the International Keyboard Institute and Festival at Mannes since 2002. In his Alice Tully recital debut, he will play Haydn's Sonata in D (Hob. XVI:37), Prokofiev's Sonata No. 7 (''War Sonata 2/Stalingrad'') and Mussorgsky's ''Pictures at an Exhibition.'' At 8 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $20. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>* AILEY II (Wednesday and Thursday) Alvin Ailey created a second, or junior, company in 1974, almost casually, as a way of working on new choreography. Ailey II is now a world-class troupe, filled with dancers who not only are good but also perform with a youthful hunger for their art, along with a reverence for dance that is a part of the mission of the company director, Sylvia Waters, whom Ailey himself chose to direct that first group. Now Ailey II is coming home, performing in the black-box theater that is part of the Ailey headquarters -- newer, grander and more gleaming than Ailey ever envisioned. The repertory will include new dances by Abdel Salaam, Darrell Grand Moultrie and Jessica Lang, along with Ailey's ''Streams'' and a chunk of Ailey highlights. (Through April 22.) At 8 p.m., Ailey Citigroup Theater, 405 West 55th Street, Chelsea, (212) 868-4444, alvinailey.org; $40; $10 student rush tickets available. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>* 'THE ART OF FALLING' (Thursday) This free performance-installation, choreographed by Catherine Hourihan with video by Pam Kray, juxtaposes live dancers' bodies with projected images of New York City and its architecture to suggest the inherent fragility of solid, everyday life in the 21st century. (Through April 20.) The installation alone will be visible April 13 to 20. At 7:30 p.m., Lower Manhattan Cultural Council Swing Space, 15 Nassau Street, between Cedar and Pine Streets, Lower Manhattan, (877) 919-8326, chourihan.com (Dunning)</p>
        <p>JONAH BOKAER AND LIUBO BORRISOV (Monday through Thursday) If you find yourself in Chelsea this month, hop into Dance Theater Workshop to see if there's ''A Cure for Surveillance.'' This public media piece, by Jonah Bokaer and Liubo Borrisov, marks the workshop's new Gallery Installation Fellowship. (Through April 28.) During theater hours; Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077, dtw.org; free. (Claudia La Rocco)</p>
        <p>JOHN BUTLER: AN AMERICAN MASTER (Tuesday through Thursday) John Butler's dances have been performed by companies from Australia to Canada. Next week, several of the late choreographer's works will get a new look by some artists closer to home, including Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater, the Richmond Ballet and Desmond Richardson. (Through April 14.) Tuesday and Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., Friday at 7 p.m., Saturday at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 2 and 7:30 p.m. Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800; $42. (La Rocco)</p>
        <p>DANCE AT DNA (Tonight, tomorrow and Thursday) Ellis Wood and her all-female modern-dance company perform Ms. Wood's new ''Flat Affect,'' a piece about women's irrational fears. Tonight and tomorrow at 8 p.m. Tami Stronach Dance follows on Thursday, through April 15, in Ms. Stronach's ''Pinchas the Fisher-People and the Great Flood.'' This retelling of the ancient myth, set to klezmer music, is from the perspective of mermaids. Thursday at 8 p.m., Dance New Amsterdam, 280 Broadway, at Chambers Street, TriBeCa, (212) 279-4200, dnadance.org; $17. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'DANCE CONVERSATIONS AT THE FLEA' (Tuesday) This free series of performing and discussion continues with work by Sasha Welsh, Roxanne Steinberg, Jackie Moynahan and HoffTanzt/Daniela Hoff, all chosen by Yasuko Yokoshi. At 7 p.m., Flea Theater, 41 White Street, Lower Manhattan, (212) 645-6462, theflea.org. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'DANCING WITH BISHOP' (Tonight through Sunday) This piece by Saskia Hegt combines poetry and letters written by Elizabeth Bishop with movement and music. Tonight and tomorrow at 10 p.m., Sunday at 5:30 p.m., La MaMa E.T.C., 74A East Fourth Street, East Village (212) 475-7710, lamama.org; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'GREEN SPACE BLOOMS: DANCE IN QUEENS' (Tonight through Sunday) This program features a performance each night by Valerie Green and her Dance Entropy, with the guest companies and musicians Stankovic Ballet Company and Andreas Altmann (tonight), Duncan Dance Collective and Sami Abu Shumays (tomorrow) and Alan Good Dance and Graciela Carriqui (Sunday). (Through April 15.) At 8 p.m. Green Space Studio, 37-24 24th Street, between 37th and 38th Avenues, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 956-3037, Greenspacestudio.com; $20; $15 for students, dancers and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>PHILIPPA KAYE COMPANY AND AIR BAND (Tonight) In Ms. Kaye's ''Ritual for a Non-Repeating Universe,'' computers track dancers' moves and translate them into digital animation, to music performed live by AirBand. At 8, Location One, 26 Greene Street, Manhattan, (212) 334-3347, location1.org; $20. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* AMANDA LOULAKI AND SHORT MEAN LADY (Thursday through Sunday) In ''Delirium, or That Taste in My Mouth,'' the Crete-born choreographer Amanda Loulaki and her collaborators explore the choices people make in their bodies, before the mind can fully weigh in -- and given the bodies in question, these should be some captivating decisions indeed. At 8:30 p.m., Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194; $15. (La Rocco)</p>
        <p>MOVEMENT RESEARCH AT THE JUDSON CHURCH (Monday) Carrie Ahern, Jeffrey Peterson and Sasha Welsh investigate works in progress in the latest installment of this terrific series. Doors open at 7:45, and seating is limited. At 8 p.m., 55 Washington Square South, Greenwich Village, (212) 598-0551, movementresearch.org; free. (La Rocco)</p>
        <p>ODYSSEY DANCE THEATER OF UTAH (Tonight through Sunday) In its New York debut, the company will perform two programs of jazz-ballet dances, created by its director, Derryl Yeager, and Mia Michaels, Eddie Ocampo, Dee Caspary, Liz Imperio and Mandy Moore. Tonight and tomorrow at 8 p.m., tomorrow at 3 p.m., Sunday at 2 p.m., Ailey Citigroup Theater, 405 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444; $20; $10 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>PALISSIMO (Thursday) Injuries to two cast members forced the postponement of ''Le Petit Mort/Now It's Time to Say Goodbye'' by Pavel Zustiak. Mr. Zustiak's company is back in business now, with a new work that ponders death and confrontations with mortality. (Through April 15.) At 8 p.m., Performance Space 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101, ps122.org; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>BETH SOLL &amp; COMPANY (Tomorrow and Sunday) This modern-dance company will perform ''Black Flower'' and ''Rustling Solo,'' choreographed by Ms. Soll, a longtime and major presence in the Boston dance scene. At 8:30 p.m., Merce Cunningham Studio, 55 Bethune Street, at Washington Street, West Village, (212) 927-0476; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'GLOBAL FEMINISMS,' through July 1. Too much of the work in this sprawling, international assembly of recent pieces by nearly 90 women from nearly 50 countries is body-oriented and doesn't venture far beyond the essentialism of Judy Chicago's indomitable 1975-79 installation opus, ''The Dinner Party,'' whose enshrinement in the new Elizabeth A. Sackler Center for Feminist Art this exhibition celebrates. Thoroughly dominated by photography and video, with a documentary slant to many of its better moments, the show is more about information, politics and the struggle for equality than it is about art in any very concentrated or satisfying sense. That doesn't keep parts of it from being energetic and illuminating, especially as a record of the way that feminism has gripped and jump-started the imaginations of women around the world. 200 Eastern Parkway, Brooklyn, (718) 638-5000, brooklynmuseum.org. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'KINDRED SPIRITS: ASHER B. DURAND AND THE AMERICAN LANDSCAPE,' through July 29. This show of about 60 works by one of the greats of 19th-century American landscape painting has as its centerpiece ''Kindred Spirits'' (1849), a tribute to the landscapist Thomas Cole and his friend the poet-journalist William Cullen Bryant. A founder of the Hudson River School but one of its less dramatic painters, Durand (1796-1886) favored the realistic approach to landscape advocated by the English critic John Ruskin, rather than the metaphorical view held by Cole and other Hudson River artists that its representation ought to express God's sublimity. Obeying Ruskin's call for truth to nature, Durand explored forest interiors with close attention to the ways of trees, foliage, rocks and ground cover in smaller works, while his larger and more elaborate exhibition pictures, influenced by European masters, are Arcadian visions suffused with light, color and atmospheric perspective. If the show reveals some of Durand's weaknesses -- repetitive themes and borrowings from other artists -- it also reveals his strong sense of artistic mission and his potent role in shaping the aesthetic of 19th-century America. (See above.) (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>FRICK COLLECTION: 'GEORGE STUBBS (1724-1806): A CELEBRATION,' through May 27. One of the finest horse painters ever, Stubbs knew his subjects from head to hoof and skin to bones. He painted other mammals too: dogs, lions, tigers, oxen, monkeys and humans. This intimate show of 17 Stubbs paintings from English collections reveals his admirable range, although the people he portrayed in two large, late canvases have the stiffness of figures on a candy box. His horses are his true monuments. 1 East 70th Street, Manhattan, (212) 288-0700, frick.org. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'FAMILY PICTURES,' through April 16. This show sounds ripe with possibilities. The results, however, are more mixed. The exhibition is drawn from the museum's collection, which explains some of its exclusions and limitations. Many artists you associate with contemporary photography and the family are not in attendance: Richard Bellingham, Tina Barney, Malerie Marder. There is also a sense of false advertising in the exhibition's title. The museum's news release extends the exhibition's exploration into ''representation of families and children in contemporary art and video.'' Images of children, you quickly realize, can operate as a completely different genre. Rineke Dijkstra's ''Beach Portraits'' of adolescents awkwardly posing against stark seascape horizons are isolated (and isolating) images of children on the threshold of adulthood. You don't think about family when gazing at these photographs. Sally Mann is perhaps the best-known contemporary photographer of children, specifically her own. Ms. Mann, represented here by black-and-white photographs from the late 1980s and early 1990s of her ethereally gorgeous children, has been accused of everything from neglect to child abuse. The questions raised by her dual role as artist and mother, simultaneous protector and potential exploiter of the family, remain vitally interesting. 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3500, guggenheim.org. (Martha Schwendener)</p>
        <p>* METROPOLITAN MUSEUM OF ART: 'VENICE AND THE ISLAMIC WORLD, 828-1797,' through July 8. At its peak in the Renaissance, Venice, the Most Serene, was a giant, clamorous Costco-on-the-Rialto. All the necessities, and most of the luxuries, of life flowed into and through it, with many items arriving from Islamic Africa and the Near East. With classic Met largesse, this exhibition suggests the spectacle of two different cultures meeting in one fantastic city, in which commerce and love of beauty, those great levelers, unite them in a fruitful bond. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>* THE MET: 'INCISIVE IMAGES: IVORY AND BOXWOOD CARVINGS,' through Nov. 25. This extraordinary show, drawn almost entirely from the Met's vaults, presents an array of nearly 100 carved figures, crucifixes, reliefs, containers, hand-held weapons and the occasional piece of furniture. It is an engrossing hive of religious fervor, Classical erudition (and occasional naughtiness), style shifts and multicultural cross-currents. And among the many feats of drop-dead artistic skill are several of traffic-stopping caliber. Don't miss it. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (See above.) (Smith)</p>
        <p>MORGAN LIBRARY &amp; MUSEUM: 'APOCALYPSE THEN: MEDIEVAL ILLUMINATIONS FROM THE MORGAN,' through June 17. Even in the contemporary art world the symbolism of the Book of Revelation, with its demons and lakes of fire, has a subversive appeal. This new exhibition at the Morgan Library celebrates a facsimile of ''Las Huelgas Apocalypse'' (1220), the largest surviving Spanish illuminated commentary on the Apocalypse. The show, which includes 50 leaves from the original text, unbound and installed around the gallery's perimeter, offers a walking tour of the medieval imagination. 225 Madison Avenue, at 36th Street, (212) 685-0008, morganlibrary.org. (Andrea K. Scott)</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'COMIC ABSTRACTION: IMAGE-BREAKING, IMAGE-MAKING,' through June 11. This unimaginative and uniformed treatment of a big idea -- the healthy and essential contamination of Modernist abstraction by popular culture -- should be seen if only because it is such a dispiriting symptom of the Modern's paralysis where contemporary art is concerned. Although it promises work that addresses ''perplexing questions,'' nearly everything here is perfectly pleasant and innocuous. The exceptions are provided by Gary Simmons, Ellen Gallagher and Sue Williams. (212) 708-9400, moma.org. (212) 708-9400, moma.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* MOMA: JEFF WALL, through May 14. This majestic show makes a great case for Mr. Wall as the most complete, if traditional, of the untraditional artists who emerged from the turmoil of Conceptual Art. His often immense color transparencies mounted on light boxes are enthralling vehicles, intent on giving pleasure while making a point or two about society, art, history, visual perception, the human animal or all of the above. An imposing blend of painting, street photography and movies, they blur reality and artifice, narrative and form, detail and the big statement. You can't stop looking at them. (See above.) (Smith)</p>
        <p>* NEUE GALERIE: 'VAN GOGH AND EXPRESSIONISM,' through July 2. The Neue has, as usual, gathered a stellar roundup of Expressionist art. In one of the show's most exciting rooms, a third-floor gallery devoted mostly to self-portraits, two extraordinary van Goghs hang at opposite ends: ''Self-Portrait With Straw Hat'' (1887-88), from the Metropolitan Museum's collection, filled with energetic, radiating brushstrokes, and the National Gallery's vibrant self-portrait of the artist holding a palette and brushes, painted about a year later. The most compelling pairing in this room, though, is van Gogh's ''Bedroom'' from 1889, the second of three versions he painted of his room in Arles, with Egon Schiele's obvious homage, ''The Artist's Bedroom in Neulengbach,'' painted in 1911, in a darker palette and with a perspective tipped precariously toward the viewer. 1048 Fifth Avenue, at 86th Street, (212) 628-6200, neuegalerie.org. (Schwendener)</p>
        <p>WADSWORTH ATHENEUM MUSEUM OF ART: 'FAITH AND FORTUNE: FIVE CENTURIES OF EUROPEAN MASTERWORKS,' through Dec. 9. One of the most appealing things about this gathering of some 400 treasures is the mix, with knockout paintings keeping company with small sculptures, elaborate table furnishings, decorative platters, Meissen knockoffs of Chinese pottery, a porcelain birdcage and vases and such. Strolling through the galleries, you'll find treasures like ''Saint Francis of Assisi in Ecstasy'' (about 1594-95), said to be the first authentic Caravaggio in an American museum; Fra Angelico's poignant, poetic fragment ''Head of an Angel'' (about 1455-50); and Francisco de Zurbarán's fearsome portrayal of a dead martyr, ''Saint Serapion'' (1628). But the pièce de résistance is an entire gallery made into an art and curio cabinet, with a planned clutter of brilliant objects that play to a viewer's inner acquisitor: exotic shells mounted in gold; an extraordinary Baroque ivory carving (presumed to be before 1650) of Adam and Eve; an automatic tabletop clock (about 1619) with a standing lion that could roll its eyes, open its jaws and stick out its tongue when the hours struck. Dazzlement prevails. 600 Main Street, Hartford, (860) 278-2670, wadsworthatheneum.org (Glueck)</p>
        <p>WHITNEY MUSEUM OF AMERICAN ART: 'GORDON MATTA-CLARK RETROSPECTIVE,' through June 3. I have no doubt that Matta-Clark is now being turned into a hot commodity, but at least at the Whitney you can see what he aspired to be. He came up with various wonderfully harebrained ideas. Literally, in one case: after letting his hair grow for a year, he cut it off as a kind of performance and phrenological gag. The preserved hair, dutifully tagged piece by piece, opens the show like a holy relic. He also sautéed a Polaroid of a Christmas tree in grease. The copy he sent to Robert Smithson, golden brown on the outside, is here too, and none too appetizing, I might add. At the center of the exhibition is ''Splitting.'' To a plain single-family suburban frame house in Englewood, N.J., he made a cut straight down the middle, bisecting the building, then severing the four corners of the roof. The retrospective consists of films, drawings, photographs and some of the architectural pieces he cut out of buildings. The drawings are casual and not too interesting, but the luxurious black-and-white photographs from Paris speak more to Matta-Clark's formal elegance. The big message was: Life as art, and art as life, a philosophy dependent on our being properly attuned and keen to the moment. (212) 570-3676, whitney.org. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* WHITNEY MUSEUM OF AMERICAN ART: 'LORNA SIMPSON,' through May 6. This tight, refined and impassioned survey covers more than 20 years of Lorna Simpson's career, from her photo-and-text meditations on race and sexism in the 1980s, to her more recent short films, which unite American history and personal history in forceful and lyrical ways. It would be easy to put some of this work on a shelf as ''identity art,'' but with an African-American woman holding one of the highest offices in the United States government, an African-American man running for president, and the nation embroiled in what some people view as an ethnic war, this art is entirely of the moment. (See above.) (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>JEAN SHIN: KEY PROMISES The idea is obvious, if you're as keen as this artist on recycling everyday objects: an installation using the word commands of countless computer keyboards to orchestrate a flow of suggested actions, desires and emotional states across four walls of a small gallery. From esc and shift to return and home. Art lite, perhaps, but expertly done. Frederieke Taylor Gallery, 535 West 22nd Street, (646) 230-0992, frederieketaylorgallery.com, through tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Other</p>
        <p>'GIFTS OF THE FOREST: NATIVE TRADITIONS IN WOOD AND BARK' Drawn from the collections of the Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center in Connecticut, this show celebrates the trees of the rich forests that once covered the Northeast, yielding essential materials to the Pequot and other Eastern Woodland cultures. The objects run from ancient woodworking tools to contemporary objects that carry on tribal traditions, like the simple and beautiful wooden flute made in 1999 by Hawk Henires (Nipmuc) and adorned with an elegantly carved bird motif. Many things here were made in the 19th and 20th centuries: handsome woven baskets, carved bowls and spoons, decorated cradle boards for carrying babies, birch bark canoe models, an elegant birch-bark hamper whose sides bear a stylized tree motif. UBS Art Gallery, 1285 Avenue of the Americas, between 51st and 52nd Streets, (212) 713-2885, through April 27. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* 'EARLY CHINESE BUDDHIST SCULPTURE,' Asia Week is over, but its essence lingers on in this exhibition of beautiful carved stone figures of Buddhas and bodhisattvas dating from the Northern Wei to Tang periods in China. This is the type of work that elicited rapturous responses when shown in London and Washington a few seasons back. Throckmorton Fine Art, 145 East 57th Street, third floor, (212) 223-1059, through April 14. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* MORGAN LIBRARY &amp; MUSEUM: 'PRIVATE TREASURES: FOUR CENTURIES OF EUROPEAN MASTER DRAWINGS,' through Sunday. This show is drawn entirely from an anonymous private collection. Despite the veil of secrecy, a couple of things are obvious: the collector had significant capital for investing in old masters and either an exceptional eye or a good adviser (or both). The strongest concentration is in Italian drawings. The earliest works come from a period when drawing wasn't an autonomous practice but was used as a form of exercise, to apply one's craft, to experiment and to make preliminary sketches for larger works. The best example -- and the most historically significant work here -- is a black chalk drawing, ''The Dead Christ'' (1529-35), by Agnolo Bronzino. With more than 90 drawings in the show, being a diligent observer quickly becomes exhausting. In which case, put down the guide, find a few drawings you like, and enjoy them while you can. After all, you don't know where they came from, where they're going, or when you'll see them again. (See above.) (Schwendener)</p>
        <p>* JOHANNES VANDERBEEK The debut solo show of this artist at is a poetic, storybook tableau with a full-scale sculpture of a medieval knight reclining on his tomb and a walled-up archway set in the gallery wall. Both are made of papier-mâché made from old copies of Time and National Geographic. The beautiful little tree that stands between them is also of paper and paste. And check out the time-and-space-warped sleepers in the back room. Zach Feuer Gallery, 530 West 24th Street, Chelsea, (212) 989-7700; closes tomorrow. (Cotter)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. ? denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'THE ACCOMPLICES' In previews; opens on Monday. The New Group presents a play by Bernard Weinraub, a former reporter for The New York Times. Based on historical events, it is about an activist who seeks American help during World War II to rescue European Jews from the Nazis (2:00). Acorn Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'ACCOMPLICE: NEW YORK'  Opens tomorrow. An interactive theater piece takes audiences around the city helping a criminal outsmart the feds (3:00). Site is secret. You receive a call one day before the performance with information on location; (212) 209-3370.</p>
        <p>'ALL THE WRONG REASONS: A TRUE STORY OF NEO-NAZIS, DRUG SMUGGLING AND UNDYING LOVE' In previews; opens on April 15. John Fugelsang is the son of an ex-nun and a former Franciscan brother. He tells his story in this solo show. New York Theater Workshop, 79 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 460-5475.</p>
        <p>'BLACKBIRD' In previews; opens on Tuesday. Jeff Daniels stars in the American premiere of this provocative play about a man coming to terms with a troubling relationship from his past. Joe Mantello directs (1:30). Manhattan Theater Club at City Center Stage I, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212.</p>
        <p>'DEUCE' Previews start on Wednesday. Opens on May 6. Grand dames Angela Lansbury and Marian Seldes play retired tennis players in this new Terrence McNally comedy. Michael Blakemore directs. Music Box Theater, 239 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'FROST/NIXON' In previews; opens on April 22. Frank Langella plays Richard M. Nixon in this acclaimed London transfer about the famous post-Watergate interview. With Michael Sheen. (1:40). Jacobs Theater, 242 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'INHERIT THE WIND' In previews; opens on Thursday. This revival of the classic courtroom drama based on the famous ''monkey trial'' stars a lineup of heavy-hitters: Brian Dennehy, Christopher Plummer, Denis O'Hare and Byron Jennings (2:00). Lyceum Theater, 149 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'LEGALLY BLONDE' In previews; opens on April 29. Laura Bell Bundy plays the smiling, ditsy sorority girl who takes Harvard Law by storm in this musical adaptation. Jerry Mitchell directs (2:20). Palace Theater, 1564 Broadway, at 47th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'LOVEMUSIK' Previews start on Thursday. Opens on May 3. Tony-winners Michael Cerveris and Donna Murphy star in a prestige musical about the relationship between Kurt Weill and Lotte Lenya (with songs by Weill). Harold Prince directs (2:30). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'A MOON FOR THE MISBEGOTTEN' In previews; opens on Monday. Kevin Spacey and Eve Best star in the London transfer of this Eugene O'Neill classic. Howard Davies directs (3:00). Brooks Atkinson Theater, 256 West 47th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'TRANSFIGURES' Previews start today. Opens on April 16. Created from sources including the writings of Joan of Arc, scientific journals and Post-it notes from the desks of corporate secretaries, this new show examines the Jerusalem Syndrome (1:30). Julia Miles Theater, 424 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'A CHORUS LINE' If you want to know why this show was such a big deal when it opened 31 years ago, you need only experience the thrilling first five minutes of this revival. Otherwise, this archivally exact production, directed by Bob Avian, feels like a vintage car that has been taken out of the garage, polished up and sent on the road once again (2:00). Schoenfeld Theater, 236 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE COAST OF UTOPIA' Lincoln Center Theater's brave, gorgeous, sprawling and ultimately exhilarating production of Tom Stoppard's trilogy about intellectuals errant in 19th-century Russia. A testament to the seductive powers of narrative theater, directed with hot and cool canniness by Jack O'Brien and featuring a starry cast (Brian F. O'Byrne, Jennifer Ehle, Martha Plimpton, Josh Hamilton and Ethan Hawke, among others) in a tasty assortment of roles. Vivian Beaumont Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'COMPANY' Fire, beckoning and dangerous, flickers beneath the frost of John Doyle's elegant, unexpectedly stirring revival of Stephen Sondheim and George Furth's era-defining musical from 1970, starring a compellingly understated Raúl Esparza. Like Mr. Doyle's ''Sweeney Todd,'' this production finds new clarity of feeling in Sondheim by melding the roles of performers and musicians (2:20). Barrymore Theater, 243 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CURTAINS' This musical comedy about a musical-comedy murder -- featuring songs by John Kander and Fred Ebb and a book by Rupert Holmes -- lies on the stage like a promisingly gaudy string of firecrackers, waiting in vain for a match. The good news is that David Hyde Pierce, playing a diffident Boston detective, steps into full-fledged Broadway stardom. Scott Ellis directs a talent-packed cast that includes Debra Monk and Karen Ziemba. (2:45). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE'  (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920s stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, it has theatergoers responding as if they were withering houseplants finally being watered after long neglect. (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'GREY GARDENS' Christine Ebersole is absolutely glorious as the middle-aged, time-warped debutante called Little Edie Beale in this uneven musical adaptation of the notorious 1975 documentary of the same title. She and the wonderful Mary Louise Wilson (as her bedridden mother), in the performances of their careers, make ''Grey Gardens'' an experience no passionate theatergoer should miss (2:40). Walter Kerr Theater, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HOWARD KATZ' The subject of Patrick Marber's comedy of unhappiness about a rabid talent agent, starring a baleful Alfred Molina and directed by Doug Hughes, is nothing more nor less than your standard-issue midlife crisis. This familiar topic gets the better of all the talented people here trying to make it seem fresh (1:30). Laura Pels Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'JOURNEY'S END' A splendid revival of R. C. Sherriff's 1928 drama of life in the trenches during World War I. Acutely staged (by David Grindley) and acted by a fine ensemble led by Hugh Dancy and Boyd Gaines, this production offers an exemplary presentation of that theatrical rarity, an uncompromising, clear-eyed play about war and the experience of day-to-day combat. An essential ticket (2:40). Belasco Theater, 111 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MARY POPPINS' This handsome, homily-packed, mechanically ingenious and rather tedious musical, adapted from the P. L. Travers stories and the 1964 film, is ultimately less concerned with inexplicable magic than with practical psychology. Ashley Brown, who sings prettily as the family-mending nanny, looks like Joan Crawford trying to be nice and sounds like Dr. Phil. Directed by Richard Eyre and Matthew Bourne (2:30). New Amsterdam Theater, 214 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LES MISÉRABLES' This premature revival, a slightly scaled-down version of the well-groomed behemoth that closed only three years ago, appears to be functioning in a state of mild sedation. Appealingly sung and freshly orchestrated, this fast-moving adaptation of Victor Hugo's novel isn't sloppy or blurry. But its pulse rate stays well below normal (2:55). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'PRELUDE TO A KISS' Craig Lucas's broken-hearted romantic comedy from 1990 receives a first-rate remounting, courtesy of the Roundabout Theater Company. Alan Tudyk and Annie Parisse play a young couple whose marriage founders shortly after the bride receives a kiss from an elderly stranger (John Mahoney). The kiss awakens all three to an unsettling awareness of love's frailty and, paradoxically, of its durability too (2:00). American Airlines Theater, 227 West 42nd Street, (212) 719-1300. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' Duncan Sheik and Steven Sater's bold adaptation of the Frank Wedekind play is the freshest and most exciting new musical Broadway has seen in some time. Set in 19th-century Germany but with a ravishing rock score, it exposes the splintered emotional lives of adolescents just discovering the joys and sorrows of sex. Performed with brio by a great cast, with supple direction by Michael Mayer and inventive choreography by Bill T. Jones (2:00). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'TALK RADIO' The most lacerating portrait of a human meltdown this side of a Francis Bacon painting. Playing an abrasive radio talk show host with a God complex, the astounding Liev Schreiber seems to fill the air as inescapably as weather in Robert Falls's gut-grabbing revival of Eric Bogosian's 1987 play (1:40). Longacre Theater, 220 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN'  This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a superdeluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE YEAR OF MAGICAL THINKING' Joan Didion's arresting but ultimately frustrating adaptation of her best-selling memoir about being blindsided by grief, starring Vanessa Redgrave. The tension between style and emotional content that made the book such a stunner does not translate to the stage. The substance here is in the silences, when the focus shifts from words to Ms. Redgrave's wry, wounded face (1:40). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'BE' A high-energy, low-content Israeli show that blends music, dance and sex appeal in the latest attempt to tap into the ''Stomp'' market (1:30). Union Square Theater, 100 East 17th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'BILL W. AND DR. BOB' This insightful new play about the founders of Alcoholics Anonymous subtly makes the claim that the recovery movement was born as a series of accidents. Patrick Husted is excellent as Bob Smith, Bill Wilson's partner in combating addictions (2:15). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Ginia Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'DEFENDER OF THE FAITH' This grim tale by Stuart Carolan of low-level I.R.A. agitators trying to identify the informer in their midst features some visceral performances and a set by Charles Corcoran that makes excellent use of the Irish Rep's small stage. If only the cause itself didn't feel so small in these days of global terrorism (1:30). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>* 'DYING CITY' Christopher Shinn's crafty and unsettling play about grief and violence, set in the shadow of the Iraq war. Directed by James Macdonald and fiercely acted by Pablo Schreiber and Rebecca Brooksher, this quiet, transfixing production turns passive aggression into a theatrical dynamic (1:30). Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-7600. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'ESSENTIAL SELF-DEFENSE' Adam Rapp's new play is a quirky love story about a wholesome but anxious girl (the charming Heather Goldenhersh) and an automaton with a beating heart and a big vocabulary (Paul Sparks, impressively affectless). Dark, zany, entirely mannered and mostly empty (2:15). Peter Jay Sharp Theater, Playwrights Horizons, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE FANTASTICKS' A revival -- well, more like a resuscitation -- of the Little Musical That Wouldn't Die. This sweet-as-ever production of Tom Jones and Harvey Schmidt's commedia-dell'arte-style confection is most notable for Mr. Jones's touching performance (under the pseudonym Thomas Bruce) as the Old Actor, a role he created when the show opened in 1960. Mr. Jones also directs (2:05). Snapple Theater Center, 210 West 50th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'FUGUE' ''Mary Smith'' is found wandering the streets of Chicago, suffering from amnesia. A young psychiatrist, who has his own demons, is consulted, and the process of treatment and Mary's memories in flashback are the action of ''Fugue,'' Lee Thuna's unrewarding play, directed by the Tony-winning actress Judith Ivey (2:15). Cherry Lane Theater, 38 Commerce Street, between Barrow and Bedford Streets, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Honor Moore)</p>
        <p>'GUTENBERG! THE MUSICAL' A very funny if not terribly original satire of musical theater features what must be the worst backers' audition of all time (2:05). Actors' Playhouse, 100 Seventh Avenue South, at Fourth Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 239-6200. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>* 'IN THE HEIGHTS' Lin-Manuel Miranda's joyous songs paint a vibrant portrait of daily life in Washington Heights in this flawed but enjoyable show. Essentially a valentine to the barrio -- conflict of a violent or desperate kind is banished from the picture -- the musical contains a host of funny performances and brings the zesty sound of Latin pop to the stage. (2:10). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'JACK GOES BOATING' Bob Glaudini's gentle comedy about pothead losers in love is a reminder of how engrossing uneventful lives can be in the hands of the right actors. Peter DuBois directs the easygoing ensemble, brilliantly led by Philip Seymour Hoffman (2:00). Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'A JEW GROWS IN BROOKLYN' You don't have to be Jewish or Brooklynish to empathize with Jake Ehrenreich, but in terms of fully appreciating his essentially one-man show, it probably helps. Especially the Catskills jokes (2:05). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 560-8912. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>* 'KING HEDLEY II' The Signature Theater Company concludes its season dedicated to August Wilson with a gritty, strongly cast revival of this play set in a violence-ravaged Pittsburgh in the 1980s. Russell Hornsby gives a galvanizing performance in the title role, as a man struggling to live down the errors of his past and plant the seeds for a promising new life (2:45). Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 244-7529. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'LA MAGNANI' Theresa Gambacorta reincarnates the Italian film star in this one-woman show, which reveals her to be more irritating than interesting -- loud and self-absorbed. Ms. Gambacorta does, however, get some pathos out of her relationship to her son, who had polio (1:10). Arclight Theater, 152 West 71st Street, (212) 279-4200. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'MY MOTHER'S ITALIAN, MY FATHER'S JEWISH AND I'M IN THERAPY'  Steve Solomon does skillful impersonations in his one-man show, but some of his jokes are as old as the hills (1:30). Little Shubert Theater, 422 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'MY TRIP TO AL-QAEDA' Lawrence Wright, author of a deeply researched book about the rise of Islamic terrorism, conducts a theatrical seminar about the events leading to the horror of 9/11. He combines a linear narrative of the development of Al Qaeda with reminiscences about the experience of writing the book. Absorbing, and chilling too (1:30). Culture Project, 55 Mercer Street, at Broome Street, SoHo, (212) 352-3101. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'NO CHILD'  Teachers will love Nilaja Sun's one-woman show about the challenges of teaching drama at Malcolm X High School (1:10). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, at Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'OUR LEADING LADY' Kate Mulgrew stars as Laura Keene, who was starring in ''Our American Cousin'' the night Lincoln was shot, in Charles Busch's uneven new comedy. An occasionally lively but mostly lumpen tribute to the glamour and grit of the theatrical life of a past era (2:00). Manhattan Theater Club at City Center Stage II, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'PROMETHEUS BOUND' With a splendid performance by David Oyelowo, this is a smart revival of Aeschylus' 2,500-year-old play, rich in poetic imagery. It still has things to say about the abuse of power by an autocratic ruler who vindictively runs roughshod over anyone who disagrees with him (1:20). Classic Stage Company, 136 East 13th Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101. (Wilborn Hampton)</p>
        <p>'ROOM SERVICE' The Peccadillo Theater Company puts a charge into this comedy from the 1930s, thanks to a brisk pace by the director, Dan Wackerman, and a dozen dandy performances. David Edwards is the would-be producer whose bills threaten to swamp his efforts to put a show on Broadway, and Fred Berman is particularly fine as his director (2:00). SoHo Playhouse, 15 Vandam Street, South Village, (212) 691-1555. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'SOME MEN' Terrence McNally's hit-and-miss comedy about gay life is a parade of cleanly drawn types, zippy one-liners and sentimental set pieces, woven into a pageant of the ages à la ''Cavalcade,'' Noel Coward's generations-spanning tribute to the British stiff upper lip. Trip Cullman directs the agile, appealing cast (2:00). Second Stage, 307 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 246-4422. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SPALDING GRAY: STORIES LEFT TO TELL' A disarming collage of selections from the monologues and journals of Mr. Gray, the ultimate stand-up solipsist, who died in 2004. Directed by Lucy Sexton, and read by five performers, none of whom resemble Mr. Gray, with an affection that shrewdly stops short of hero worship (1:30). Minetta Lane Theater, 18 Minetta Lane, Greenwich Village, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TALL GRASS' Brian Harris's three short plays, black farces all, are not nearly as slight as any sound-bite synopsis would have them seem. Here Mr. Harris, a former stock analyst, explores the alliances formed between love and brutality in scenarios in which the tension builds to culminating shock (1:30). The Beckett Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'TEA AND SYMPATHY' The specter of the Ted Haggard scandal hangs over the Keen Company's revival of Robert Anderson's 1953 play about life in a psychologically stifling boys' boarding school. Girded by Jonathan Silverstein's skillful, understated direction, the play attains an unexpected timeliness as it evolves into a story about the dangers of sexual repression (2:00). Clurman Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>* 'WAKE UP MR. SLEEPY! YOUR UNCONSCIOUS MIND IS DEAD!' Richard Foreman's latest film-theater hybrid is a memorial service, of sorts, for the intuitive self, killed by a surface-worshiping world. It is also a dazzling exercise in reality shifting that is as invigorating as it is mournful (1:05). Ontological Theater at St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'T J AND DAVE' The comics T. J. Jagodowski and Dave Pasquesi miraculously improvise a one-hour play at every performance. This is an impressive feat of mental athletics, but the results are also observant, complex and frequently enormously funny (1:00). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden Theater, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' Singing CliffsNotes for Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' Often more entertaining than the real thing (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS'  The biomusical that walks like a man (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT'  A singing scrapbook for Monty Python fans (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' ''A Chorus Line'' with pimples (1:45). Circle in the Square, 254 West 50th Street, Manhattan, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Spectacles</p>
        <p>'RINGLING BROTHERS AND BARNUM &amp; BAILEY CIRCUS' An eye- and earful (2:10). Madison Square Garden, (212) 307-7171. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'BLINDNESS' Joe Tantalo's adaptation of José Saramago's best-selling novel, about an unnamed city struck with an inexplicable epidemic of ''white blindness,'' is set in a cell-like space surrounded by white scrim. This setting and the mostly strong acting drive home the fearful basic circumstances. Unfortunately, the script also streamlines Mr. Saramago's reflective story to the point of draining it of moral complexity (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200; closes on Sunday. (Jonathan Kalb)</p>
        <p>'THE CAVE DWELLERS' This revival of William Saroyan's 1957 play about a group of misfits inhabiting an abandoned theater examines the virtue of charity and the nobility of failure but feels as stifling and constricted as the building in which the outcasts find themselves. A production that asks us to revere the theater without inviting reverence itself (1:30). Pearl Theater, 80 St. Marks Place, East Village, (212) 598-9802; closes on Sunday. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'CHICKEN' Michael Batistick's new play about cockfighting and emasculation could benefit from subtler metaphors but manages to touch us gently even as it deploys a heavy hammer. E J Carroll, Michael Imperioli and his ''Sopranos'' cast mate Sharon Angela give fine performances as struggling urban nobodies (1:45). Studio Dante, 257 West 29th Street, Chelsea, (212) 868-4444; closes tomorrow. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'DID YOU USED TO BE R. D. LAING?' This sweet, nostalgic solo show explores the life and work of the controversial Scottish psychiatrist -- an international celebrity and countercultural guru in the 1960s -- from the perspective of a genial admirer. It's well acted and empathetic but a bit too pleasantly tranquil to bring such a prickly and passionately disputed figure into full focus (1:30). The American Theater of Actors, 314 West 54th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444; closes tomorrow. (Kalb)</p>
        <p>'THE EXILES'  Theodora Skipitares's rendering, with life-size puppets, music and video, of the story of Orestes, adapted from Euripides but inspired by Sartre. A short and rather slight play that continues the mining of the Trojan War for contemporary equivalents by the conceiver and director of last season's Trilogy (1:00). La MaMa Annex, 74A East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 475-7710; closes on Sunday. (Moore)</p>
        <p>'MEN OF STEEL' This darkly comic twist on superheroes is a loony, guilty pleasure (2:00). Center Stage, 48 West 21st Street, Chelsea, (212) 352-3101; closes on Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'WIDOWERS' HOUSES' An adaptation of George Bernard Shaw's play, updated to 1990s Harlem, tests the limits of credibility (1:40). Kirk Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200; closes on Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>'AFTER THE WEDDING' (R, 119 minutes, in Danish) A modern creation with a classic theme involving haves and have-nots, bloodlines and family ties. The canned realism of the Danish director Susanne Bier is strictly Dogme-lite, but the spiky, screen-filling performances of her two male leads, Mads Mikkelsen and Rolf Lassgard, are really something to see. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'AIR GUITAR NATION' (R, 82 minutes) Alexandra Lipsitz's breezy competition documentary follows pantomiming would-be rockers as they compete for the right to represent their country in a global championship based in Oulou, Finland. The movement, such as it is, aims to unite a war-torn planet in musical fantasy and to rawwwwwwk!  -- but not necessarily in that order. Stylistically, it's nothing special, but the film's droll humor and wild performances are hard to resist. (Matt Zoller Seitz)</p>
        <p>'AMERICAN CANNIBAL' (No rating, 91 minutes) Illustrating the premise that if you lie down with dogs you wake up with fleas, the documentary about a failed reality television series is absorbing in the same sick way as the lowest examples of the genre it examines. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'BEHIND THE MASK: THE RISE OF LESLIE VERNON' (R, 92 minutes) Scott Glosserman's mockumentary about a celebrity-seeking serial killer is sustained by rapier-sharp observations and a firmer grasp of tone than that in many more generously financed projects. The movie subtly prods at the sick dance between the news media and über-criminals without belaboring its point or lowering its tone. If Christopher Guest ever turned his attention to psycho killers instead of dog breeders, this is exactly the sort of movie he would make. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'Blades of Glory' (PG-13, 93 minutes) In this fast, light, frequently funny comedy about a male figure-skating team, Will Ferrell and Jon Heder stake an early claim to being the comedy couple of the year. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'BOY CULTURE' (No rating, 88 minutes) Q. Allan Brocka's absorbing drama follows an emotionally repressed gay hustler (Derek Magyar) as he rebels against the obsessions of his culture -- grooming, cruising, working out -- and a powerful attraction to his roommate. Only when he takes on a reclusive and much older client is he forced to pay attention to a story other than his own. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'CHILDREN OF MEN' (R, 100 minutes) The end is nigh in this superbly directed political thriller directed by Alfonso Cuarón about a nervously plausible future. Based on the P. D. James book, the film stars an excellent Clive Owen and features equally sterling support from the actors Michael Caine, Danny Huston and Chiwetel Ejiofor, among others. , as well as the great cinematographer Emmanuel Lubezki. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'COLOR ME KUBRICK' (No rating, 90 minutes) If it doesn't add up to more than a fitfully amusing collection of comic sketches, the fictional portrait of Alan Conway, a real-life British con man who hustled his way across England by impersonating the reclusive filmmaker Stanley Kubrick, is a platform for John Malkovich to burst into lurid purple flame. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'DEAD SILENCE' (R, 90 minutes) In this new film from the makers of the ''Saw'' series, a young man (Ryan Kwanten) whose wife was murdered by a demonic ventriloquist's dummy returns to his hometown to unravel the roots of a century-old curse. The film's playfully self-aware touches (like a grand old theater named the Guignol) distract from its leaden pacing, three too many final twists and various behavioral idiocies. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>'FIRST SNOW' (R, 101 minutes) Guy Pearce, in his ''Memento'' mode, is a fast-talking salesman in this moody little thriller, which asks metaphysical questions about fate, death and fortunetelling. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE HAWK IS DYING' (No rating, 106 minutes) In this painfully earnest backwoods tale from the director Julian Goldberger, Paul Giamatti plays George Gattling, a dispirited auto upholsterer with a passion for falconry. Set in Central Florida and based on the book by Harry Crews, ''The Hawk Is Dying'' is a dreary study of male angst groaning beneath the weight of its own symbolism. Not since Ken Loach's ''Kes'' has a bird of prey carried so much dramatic responsibility. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'THE HILLS HAVE EYES 2' (R, 89 minutes) Wes Craven's 1977 film, ''The Hills Have Eyes,'' in which suburbanites battled mutant cannibals, was a pulpy parable of the thin line separating civilization from savagery. Last year's remake was basically the same movie with glossier production values and a less satirical, more bludgeoning approach to violence. This follow-up, in which National Guard trainees are trapped on a former atomic test site and are stalked by flesh-eating freaks headquartered in a warrenlike mountain hideout, is essentially a catalog of transgressive images, lighted and edited like a heavy-metal video. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>'I THINK I LOVE MY WIFE' (R, 94 minutes) An unusually smart and brisk comedy of marital frustration and sexual temptation, based on Eric Rohmer's ''Chloe in the Afternoon,'' with Chris Rock (who directed and is co-author of the script) as a Manhattan investment banker distracted by the charms of a bombshell played by the wonderful Kerry Washington. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'KILLER OF SHEEP' (No rating, 83 minutes) Largely hidden from view for three decades, Charles Burnett's lyrical film about a working-class family living in a broken-down home in a bombed-out stretch of Los Angeles is an American masterpiece, independent to the bone. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE LAST MIMZY' (PG, 94 minutes) This overstuffed yet warmhearted sci-fi drama follows a pair of wide-eyed siblings as they solve the riddle of a box from the future. Despite leaden direction (by the New Line Cinema honcho Robert Shaye) and a story crammed with pseudoscientific flotsam -- including palm reading, levitation and telepathy -- this wholesome entertainment doesn't talk down. Nevertheless, a film gazing this far into the future shouldn't be quite so unwilling to look beyond the frame. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'THE LOOKOUT' (R, 99 minutes) This directorial debut by the veteran screenwriter Scott Frank (''Out of Sight'') is a variation of an old, old story, about a nobody (a brain-damaged janitor played by Joseph Gordon-Levitt) who falls in with crooks who make him feel like somebody. Although the movie's no masterpiece -- the final stretch feels forced and unconvincing -- there's a lot to like here. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>* 'OFFSIDE' (PG, 93 minutes, in Persian) The Iranian director Jafar Panahi follows a group of young woman into a Tehran soccer stadium, where they have come to see their nation's team compete for a spot in the World Cup. Instead they are arrested -- women are forbidden to attend sporting events in Iran -- and their predicament yields comedy as well as a trenchant critique of gender politics in the Islamic Republic. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE PAGE TURNER' (No rating, 85 minutes, in French) A pretty young thing slithers into the bosom of a bourgeois family like an asp in this shivery little thriller from the French filmmaker Denis Dercourt. Not Chabrol, but not bad, either. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'PRIDE' (PG, 104 minutes) The Zimbabwean-born filmmaker Sunu Gonera's directorial debut, ''Pride,'' about a swim coach (Terrence Howard, star of ''Hustle &amp; Flow'') leading an urban recreational center's swim team to a championship, about 1971, is a silk ascot wrapped around an ear of corn. But when sinewy young idealists glide through water to the tune of ''I'll Take You There,'' the heart still swells. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>'REIGN OVER ME' (R, 124 minutes) Mike Binder's comic drama of post-9/11 grief is wildly uneven -- by turns insightful and grindingly mawkish. Don Cheadle and Adam Sandler are two college buddies who reunite, somewhat improbably, some years after the attacks that robbed one of them of his family. The actors rise above the material, particularly in the longer, looser scenes that allow their contrasting temperaments -- Mr. Cheadle's tense understatement and Mr. Sandler's shaggy emoting -- to find a workable syncopation. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'SACCO AND VANZETTI' (No rating, 81 minutes) This feature filmmaking debut by Peter Miller, a PBS veteran, hews to standard television documentary format: archival photographs and talking heads. But the movie's meat-and-potatoes style seems less a failure of imagination than a means of putting in the foreground its subject matter: the still-controversial tale of Nicola Sacco and Bartolomeo Vanzetti, Italian immigrants and outspoken anarchists charged with the 1920 robbery of a Massachusetts shoe factory and the murder of two of its employees. A good film on a great subject. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>'SHOOTER' (R, 126 minutes) Muscles bulge and heads explode in this thoroughly reprehensible, satisfyingly violent entertainment about men and guns and things that go boom. Antoine Fuqua directs, and Mark Wahlberg entertains, with and without his shirt. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'U-CARMEN' (No rating, 120 minutes, in Xhosa) Winner of the top award at the 2005 Berlin Film Festival, ''U-Carmen'' pushes against every expectation you would normally bring to a movie version of Bizet's opera. It relocates the tale's doomed romantic triangle to Khayelitsha, an industrial community near Cape Town, South Africa; sets the action in and around a cigarette factory; and translates its libretto into Xhosa, a regional language distinguished by its abundance of pops and clicks. For the most part, the film's action is intentionally plain, always acknowledging its physical environment, which can be frustrating when the melodies soar. But the music still pierces, the blood still flows, and the overall conception is so original that even when the movie falters in the moment, it dazzles in the memory. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>'BERLIN ALEXANDERPLATZ' (Tuesday through April 15) Rainer Werner Fassbinder made this 13-part adaptation of the grueling social realist novel by Alfred Doblin for West German television in 1980, but because the film was shot on 16 millimeter, it has been in fragile condition and out of sight for many years. But now the Fassbinder Foundation, with the support of the Museum of Modern Art, has completed a restoration, transferring the original 16-millimeter negative to 35 millimeter. Gunter Lamprecht stars as the downtrodden hero, a Weimer everyman struggling to keep his stomach full and his dignity intact. Parts 1 through 3 will be shown on Tuesday; 4 through 7 on Wednesday; 8 through 11 on Thursday; and 12, 13 and the epilogue on April 13. (The film will also be repeated in two parts on April 14 and 15.) This screening is part of a three-week series of Fassbinder films from MoMA's collection, which this week will include ''Despair'' (tonight), ''The Merchant of Four Seasons'' (tomorrow), ''Jail Bait'' (tomorrow) and ''Whity'' (Sunday). On Monday, Juliane Lorenz, Fassbinder's longtime editor, will introduce two documentaries, ''Fassbinder's Berlin Alexanderplatz: Notes on the Restoration'' and ''A Mega Movie and Its Story.'' Mr. Lamprecht and one of his co-stars, Barbara Sukowa, are expected to attend. Museum of Modern Art Roy and Niuta Titus Theaters, (212) 708-9400, moma.org; $10. (Dave Kehr)</p>
        <p>FARES TO REMEMBER: TAXI '07 (Today through Sunday) The IFC Center celebrates the 100th anniversary of the taxi in New York City with a month of cab-centric movies. This Friday and Sunday at noon, Harold Lloyd stars in the silent comedy ''Speedy,'' in which one of his duties as a New York cabbie is getting Babe Ruth to the stadium on time. At midnight on Friday and Saturday, Robert De Niro plays a less accommodating chauffeur in Martin Scorsese's dark, expressionist ''Taxi Driver'' (1976). IFC Center, 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 924-7771, ifccenter.com; $10.75. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>THE REAL EDIE SEDGWICK (Tomorrow and Sunday) The Museum of the Moving Image concludes a survey of the film work of this Warhol superstar, society figure and all-around study in self-destructiveness with several rarely shown Warhol films, including ''Kitchen,'' ''Restaurant,'' ''Afternoon'' (made from outtakes from ''Chelsea Girls''), ''Beauty #2'' and ''Horse,'' all from 1965. There's also a pair of non-Warhol efforts: ''Poem Posters,'' a 1967 documentary by Charles Henri Ford in which Sedgwick appears among the downtown celebrities at an art opening, and the 1972 ''Ciao, Manhattan,'' a semi-autobiographical feature completed just weeks before Sedgwick's death. Museum of the Moving Image, 35th Avenue, at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718) 784-0077, movingimage.us; $10. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>CHRISTINA AGUILERA, PUSSYCAT DOLLS, DANITY KANE (Tomorrow) Frau Farbissina of the ''Austin Powers'' movies said it best: ''Send in the Fembots!'' Ms. Aguilera may have the most virtuosic voice of her generation of bubble-gum pop stars, but as she showed with her endless melismatic protraction of James Brown's ''It's a Man's Man's Man's World'' at the Grammys in February, she can sometimes seem like a singing robot gone berserk. Her tour includes a hit burlesque girl group (the Pussycat Dolls) and an imitation hit burlesque girl group (Danity Kane). At 7:30 p.m., Nassau Coliseum, 1255 Hempstead Turnpike, Uniondale, N.Y., (516) 794-9300, nassaucoliseum.com; $55 to $95. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>* LILY ALLEN, THE BIRD AND THE BEE (Wednesday) A 21-year-old British singer with deceptively sweet, ska-infused electro-pop songs, Ms. Allen is at her best when snarkily putting down disagreeable suitors. ''Smile,'' a No. 1 hit in England, is pure schadenfreude, and ''Knock 'Em Out'' a catalog of snappy answers to bad pickup lines: ''I've got herpes. No, I've got syphilis.'' The Bird and the Bee, a well-dressed duo from Los Angeles, toys with two fashionable ideas: retro French pop glittering with electronics, and ''Sex and the City''-style sexual conundrums. This show inaugurates the newly renamed Fillmore New York at Irving Plaza. At 8:40 p.m., 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, irvingplaza.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* ALLMAN BROTHERS (Tonight through Sunday) The best spring ritual on the Upper West Side is the arrival of this archetypal Southern rock band for its annual series of concerts at the Beacon Theater, ending this weekend. At 8, 2124 Broadway, at 74th Street, (212) 307-7171, beacontheatrenyc.com; $54.99 to $94.99. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BLUE CHEER, AN ALBATROSS (Tomorrow) On a few gloriously untidy albums in the late 1960s and early '70s, Blue Cheer followed the blunter edges of Jimi Hendrix's sound into a bludgeoning kind of primordial heavy metal, and played it with an un-self-conscious glee that made the band sound like cave men discovering fire. An Albatross, from Wilkes-Barre, Pa., shrieks its way through dizzying but lighthearted prog-hardcore songs that borrow something from Captain Beefheart. At 8 p.m., Rebel, 251 West 30th Street, Manhattan, (212) 695-2747, rebelnyc.com; $12 in advance, $15 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BARBARA CARROLL (Sunday and Monday) Elegant, witty and touching, this classically trained jazz pianist and singer, now 82, is in her prime: the female counterpart of Bobby Short. Sunday at 2 p.m., Monday at 8 p.m., Oak Room at the Algonquin Hotel, 59 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212) 419-9331, algonquinhotel.com; $58 on Sunday, with brunch at noon; $40 on Monday, with a $20 minimum. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>CÉU (Monday and Tuesday) With an easy, dragging beat, bossa nova becomes something like light dub in the lithe and playful songs of Céu, a young woman from São Paulo who is rising fast in the Brazilian circuit. Monday at 9:30 p.m., Tuesday at 7:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $15. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* COLD WAR KIDS, TOKYO POLICE CLUB (Tonight, tomorrow and Monday nights) The craggy guitars and piano, elliptical songwriting and verge-of-a-breakdown vocals of Cold War Kids, from Long Beach, Calif., may be par for the indie-rock course. But if the band's three sold-out shows this week at the Bowery Ballroom are any indication, it is still basking in the microfame bestowed over the last year by zealous bloggers. Tonight and tomorrow night, Cold War Kids play with Tokyo Police Club, a Canadian group that spikes Strokes-like songs with noisy petulance. At 9, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com. Tokyo Police Club also plays Monday at 10 p.m. at the Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700, mercuryloungenyc.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JOÃO DONATO (Tonight) Mr. Donato is one of the great bossa nova composers of the late-'50s generation, and probably the one most influenced by American jazz; his performances these days are nostalgic and sometimes anarchically funny. At 7 and 9:30, Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $30. (Ben Ratliff)</p>
        <p>* IGGY AND THE STOOGES (Monday) Suffice it to say that ''The Weirdness'' (Virgin), the first Stooges album in 34 years, is not likely to become a classic. But as with every one of Iggy Pop's many mediocre solo albums over the years, any excuse to keep him on the road is worthwhile. Even nearing 60, he remains an inspirationally feral performer, and on past tours the reunited Stooges have ably summoned some of the raw, menacing groove that made them one of the primary godfathers of punk rock. With Sistas in the Pit. At 7 p.m., United Palace Theater, 4140 Broadway, at 175th Street, Washington Heights, (212) 307-7171, bowerypresents.com; $39.50 to $59.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JUNIOR BOYS (Wednesday) When dance music goes sad: squiggly, awkward beats and droopy keyboards surround the forlorn vocals of this Canadian electronic group, who sing about missed birthdays and phones that don't ring. With San Serac and TigerCity. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>KAISER CHIEFS, WALKMEN (Thursday) Gracefully but not always excitingly, the Kaiser Chiefs, from Leeds, England, mingle the spunky minimalism of XTC-vintage post-punk with the ballad-friendly melodicism of '90s Britpop. The Walkmen, from New York, play exquisitely articulated songs of exhaustion and disaffection, with Hamilton Leithauser's weary whine surrounded by an echoey wash of guitar and keyboards. With the Annuals. At 7:30 p.m., Roseland Ballroom, 239 West 52nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, roselandballroom.com; $31 in advance, $35 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>KIKI AND HERB (Sunday) A few years ago this brilliantly perverse cabaret duo played their farewell show at Carnegie Hall. Then came a run on Broadway. And some late-night gigs at Joe's Pub. And the inimitable Christmas show. (Highlight: a medley of ''Smells Like Teen Spirit'' and ''Frosty the Snowman.'') Kiki and Herb can't stay away from the stage, and New York is the better for it. At 11:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* KLAXONS (Tuesday) This British trio's eerie rave-punk is punctuated by the peal of air-raid sirens and paranoid, shouted lyrics that allude to William S. Burroughs and Thomas Pynchon. How the band manages to cram in such fear and loathing and still make exhilarating, danceable grooves is what makes it fascinating. With Bonde do Role, a Brazilian baile-funk group that makes silly but contagiously high-energy electronic pastiches. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>SONDRE LERCHE (Tomorrow) A 24-year-old Norwegian with a kind tenor and a light touch, Mr. Lerche plays elegant, melodically rich but sometimes overly coy folk-pop. With Willy Mason and Thomas Dybdahl. At 6:30 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; $25. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LOSER'S LOUNGE TRIBUTE TO HALL AND OATES (Thursday) As Nick Lowe said, you've got to be cruel to be kind. Joe McGinty's enduring Loser's Lounge series, now 14 years old, both honors and skewers pop greats with cleverly over-the-top performances, and turns its attention here to Hall and Oates, whose mega-selling soul-pop ranged from the sublime (''She's Gone'') to the farcical (''Portable Radio''). At 9:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $25. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LOW; LONEY, DEAR (Tonight) With exquisite care, Low, from Duluth, Minn., featuring the husband-and-wife team of Alan Sparhawk on guitar and Mimi Parker on vocals, and Matt Livingston on bass, creates hushed, stark songs on a vast sonic scale. Loney, Dear, led by the Swedish songwriter Emil Svanangen, plays placid folk-pop decorated with endearing, '60s-style harmonies. At 6:30 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PARTS AND LABOR (Tonight) This squally Brooklyn three-piece ably pulls off the tricky task of being both anarchic and anthemic. With Big Bear, Gowns and Alex Delivery. At 8:30, Luna Lounge, 361 Metropolitan Avenue, at Havemeyer Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, lunalounge.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PEEPING TOM (Monday) The latest project of Mike Patton, the naughty boy of heavy metal turned naughty boy of the avant-garde. The gimmick here is creepy lounge and trip-hop, with various collaborators in on the joke. For this show the guests are Dan the Automator, Miho Hatori of Cibo Matto and the rapper Pigeon John. At 9 p.m., Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, irvingplaza.com; $25. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PRETTY RICKY (Tomorrow) This R&amp;B boy band from Miami has hit the top of the charts with amorous crooning -- and some rapping -- that drops flirtatious pretense in pursuit of the girl and cuts right to the chase: ''Can I put a little peer pressure on ya?'' At 7 p.m., Roseland Ballroom, 239 West 52nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, roselandballroom.com; $29.50 in advance, $35 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>RASPUTINA (Tonight) Rasputina is a charmingly improbable project: part Marie Antoinette, part metal. Three women who are cellists in corsets (as well as a drummer) sing about Transylvanian concubines as their music seesaws between elaborate chamber-music counterpoint and grunting hard-rock chords, complete with distortion. With the Bowmans. At 9, Gramercy Theater, 127 East 23rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171; $20.50. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>DIANA ROSS (Tonight) In her guest performance on ''American Idol'' last month, Ms. Ross showed that at 63 she remains every bit the ''dreamgirl'': breezing her way through the Spiral Starecase song ''More Today Than Yesterday,'' she was smooth, cocky and in love with her own voice -- a true superstar. At 8, the Theater at Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741, thegarden.com; $59.50 to $149.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MARTIN SEXTON (Tonight) This singer and songwriter can groan like an alternative rocker, slide like a soul man or leap up to a pearly falsetto. Singing about restlessness and love while he picks syncopations on his guitar, Mr. Sexton can turn an ordinary song into a jazzy showcase, and a good one into a transmission from the heart. With Jonah Smith. At 9, Nokia Theater, 1515 Broadway, at 44th Street, (212) 307-7171, nokiatheatrenyc.com; $30. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>STONE SOUR, SHADOWS FALL, LACUNA COIL (Tonight) Stone Sour, featuring Corey Taylor of the horror-metal crew Slipknot, leads a strong bill of angry guitars and punishing drums. Slipknot is indiscriminate in its misanthropy, but in the poppier Stone Sour, Mr. Taylor chooses his targets more carefully, including some not-so-veiled political ones: ''We're more in danger than before you took power.'' At 7:20, Roseland Ballroom, 239 West 52nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800 roselandballroom.com; $34. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* KOKO TAYLOR (Tonight) For five decades Ms. Taylor, 71, has sung brawny, carnal blues like ''Wang Dang Doodle'' with a strength and swagger rivaling that of any man. After a health crisis a few years ago, she has returned with a new album, ''Old School'' (Alligator), in which she shows that her ego remains as strong as her voice: ''You don't want to tangle with me,'' she sings. At 8, B. B. King Blues Club &amp; Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $35. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>TEDDYBEARS (Monday) This Swedish band has one of the year's bigger head-scratchers with ''Punkrocker,'' a paranoid jaunt with new-wave synthesizers and a deadpan vocal by Iggy Pop that is being used in a Cadillac ad -- makes perfect sense, right? With Foreign Islands. At 7 p.m., Gramercy Theater, 127 East 23rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171; $14.50 in advance, $16 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>WORLD/INFERNO FRIENDSHIP SOCIETY (Tomorrow) The World/Inferno Friendship Society's ''red-eyed soul'' is a raucous mix of ska, punk and horn-driven retro R&amp;B. With Paint It Black, the Vicious and Measure SA. At 7 p.m., Europa, 98 Meserole Avenue, at Manhattan Avenue, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 383-5723, europaclub.com; $13. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>* JOHN ABERCROMBIE QUARTET (Wednesday and Thursday) The guitarist John Abercrombie has a new album, ''The Third Quartet'' (ECM), that captures the thoughtful chemistry of this group with the violinist Mark Feldman, the bassist Marc Johnson and the drummer Joey Baron. (Through April 14.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>* ALL THAT JAZZ: NOW THAT'S HIP (Tuesday) This annual concert, sponsored by the HIP Health Plan of New York, invariably spotlights the trumpeter Wynton Marsalis with his working band. This edition, ''New Orleans Rising,'' also benefits from the inclusion of the pianist-singer Dr. John, with his rollicking swamp-funk band the Lower 911. At 8 p.m., Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 721-6500, jalc.org; $32.50 to $87.50. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CARL ALLEN AND NEW SPIRIT (Tonight and tomorrow night) The drummer Carl Allen leads a gospel-steeped bop unit with Vincent Herring on alto saxophone and Aaron Goldberg on piano. At 8, 10 and midnight, Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212) 255-3626, sweetrhythmny.com; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVE ALLEN (Monday) Mr. Allen is a guitarist with a coolly modernistic sensibility, as he demonstrated on his last album, ''Untold Stories'' (Fresh Sound New Talent). Two musicians from the album, the tenor saxophonist Seamus Blake and the drummer Mark Ferber, join him here. At 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SAM BARDFELD'S STUFF SMITH PROJECT (Thursday) Sam Bardfeld, a violinist with a wide-ranging résumé, pays tribute to a swing-era hero of his instrument with help from the pianist Anthony Coleman, the bassist Sean Conly and the guitarist and vocalist Doug Wamble. At 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PETER BRÖTZMANN, MARINO PLIAKAS AND MICHAEL WERTMUELLER (Wednesday) Few modern saxophonists can sound as powerfully abrasive as Mr. Brötzmann, whose most recent album, ''Full Blast'' (Jazzwerkstatt), is a collaboration with Mr. Pliakas, a guitarist and bassist, and Mr. Wertmueller, a drummer. At 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* RAVI COLTRANE QUARTET / DAVID SÁNCHEZ QUARTET (Tuesday through Thursday) Ravi Coltrane and David Sánchez are two of the more assertively creative tenor saxophonists to emerge within the jazz mainstream in the last dozen or so years, and each has a knack for organizing rhythmically sophisticated working bands. (Through April 15.) At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $30 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* DAVE DOUGLAS AND KEYSTONE (Thursday) On his recent album ''Keystone'' (Greenleaf), the trumpeter Dave Douglas imagines a vividly contemporary soundtrack to the silent films of Roscoe (Fatty) Arbuckle. The music sounds best in performance, thanks to a smartly thrashing electro-acoustic band with Marcus Strickland on tenor saxophone, Adam Benjamin on Fender Rhodes piano, Brad Jones on bass, DJ Olive on turntables and Gene Lake on drums. (Through April 15.) At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>FOR THOSE WE LOVE (Thursday) This glittery but heartfelt benefit concert -- with the jazz-pop ensemble New York Voices, the jazz-cabaret singers Jane Monheit and Louise Rogers, and the Latin-jazz saxophonist and clarinetist Paquito D'Rivera -- supports the New York chapter of the Alzheimer's Association. At 7:30 p.m., Kaye Playhouse at Hunter College, East 68th Street between Park and Lexington Avenues, (212) 772-4448, alznyc.org; $50 to $250. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SONNY FORTUNE TRIO (Tomorrow) Since the 1960s, countless saxophonists have adopted the methodology of John Coltrane, but few have captured his restless spirit. Mr. Fortune, the saxophonist of choice for the late Coltrane drummer Elvin Jones, is chief among them; he performs with the bassist David Williams and the drummer Neal Smith. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Sista's Place, 456 Nostrand Avenue, at Jefferson Avenue, Brooklyn, (718) 398-1766, sistasplace.org; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILL FRISELL TRIO (Tuesday through Thursday) On his last two trio releases, both partly recorded at the Village Vanguard, the guitarist Bill Frisell conjures a compelling hallucination of the American popular songbook. His partners are the bassist Tony Scherr and the drummer Kenny Wollesen, a widely traveled rhythm team. (Through April 15.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ROBERT GLASPER TRIO (Tonight) A percussive and tuneful pianist, Robert Glasper mines a jazz tradition informed by gospel and many strains of R&amp;B. His trio, with Vicente Archer on bass and Damion Reid on drums, just released a strong second album, ''In My Element'' (Blue Note). At 11:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, 425 Lafayette Street, East Village, (212) 967-7555 , joespub.com; cover, $15, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* JIM HALL AND RON CARTER (Tonight through Sunday) Summoning the effervescent spirit of ''Alone Together,'' an album issued 35 years ago, the guitarist Jim Hall and the bassist Ron Carter engage in discursive and articulate duets. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $35 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* ICP ORCHESTRA (Tonight) The acronym stands for Instant Composers Pool, which conveys both the immediacy and the structural integrity of this 10-piece ensemble's creations. The group, now celebrating its 40th anniversary, also has the finest improvisers in Amsterdam. At 8 and 9:30 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE LEHMAN QUARTET (Tomorrow) The saxophonist Steve Lehman pursues an abstract lyricism informed by myriad traditions. His quintet includes sharp and sympathetic peers: the trumpeter Jonathan Finlayson, the bassist Drew Gress and the drummer Tyshawn Sorey. At midnight, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $10, $5 for students, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVID LIEBMAN GROUP (Tonight and tomorrow night) An incantatory saxophonist working in the post-Coltrane idiom, David Liebman plays here with his longstanding quartet, with Vic Juris on guitar, Tony Marino on bass and Marko Marcinko on drums. At 10, 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PAT MARTINO (Tonight through Sunday) A powerfully proficient guitarist, Mr. Martino favors a brand of post-bop that has more than a little in common with the blistering fusion of his youth. At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., with a midnight set tonight and tomorrow, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $35, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MODERN ROMANCE: IGOR BUTMAN AND IGOR RAYKHELSON (Tomorrow) Mr. Butman is a saxophonist and one of Russia's top jazz musicians, and Mr. Raykhelson is a pianist and composer equally drawn to jazz and classical music. Performing here with musicians including the violinist Elena Revich and the cellist Boris Andrianov, they advance a crossover ideal. At 7:30 p.m., Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $40 and $35. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>AMANDA MONACO 4 / NICOLAS MASSON QUARTET (Wednesday) Amanda Monaco is a guitarist whose recent album, ''Intention'' (Innova), showcases her playfully restive compositions for a quartet with Jason Gillenwater on tenor saxophone, Sean Conly on bass and Jeff Davis on drums. In a later set, the saxophonist Nicolas Masson leads his own quartet, with the trumpeter Russ Johnson, the bassist Eivind Opsvik and the drummer Gerald Cleaver. At 8 and 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* THELONIOUS MONK 90TH BIRTHDAY CELEBRATION (Thursday) A premature celebration, perhaps -- Thelonious Monk was born in October -- but a thoughtfully programmed one, involving a pianist deeply familiar with Monkish expression (Kenny Barron) and a repertory band led by one of Monk's former drummers (Ben Riley's Monk Legacy Septet). As a bonus, the actor Rome Neal will revisit his role in ''Monk'' (the one-man play, not the television show). At 8 p.m., TriBeCa Performing Arts Center, Borough of Manhattan Community College, 199 Chambers Street, (212) 220-1460, tribecapac.org; $30, $27.50 for students. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>WOLFGANG MUTHSPIEL AND BRIAN BLADE (Tomorrow and Sunday) Mr. Muthspiel is an Austrian guitarist, and Mr. Blade is a drummer from Louisiana. They have an engrossing and remarkably full-sounding new duo album, ''Friendly Travelers'' (Material), that features crystalline playing and a liquid sort of rapport. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MILES OKAZAKI (Thursday) Mr. Okazaki is a confident guitarist and composer whose recent album, ''Mirror,'' involves a pair of powerful alto saxophonists: David Binney and Miguel Zenón, who join him here. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ONE FOR ALL (Tonight and tomorrow night) The driving hard bop of Art Blakey's Jazz Messengers lends a mission and a method for this band, which consists of the saxophonist Eric Alexander, the trumpeter Jim Rotondi, the trombonist Steve Davis, the pianist David Hazeltine, the bassist Nat Reeves and the drummer Joe Farnsworth. At 8, 10 and 11:30, Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662, smokejazz.com; cover, $30. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MISHA PIATIGORSKY (Wednesday) On his new album, ''Uncommon Circumstance'' (Mishamusic), the pianist Misha Piatigorsky plays original music informed both by classical and groove-based music, with impressive but sometimes airless results. He has an excellent rhythm section, though, in the bassist Hans Glawischnig and the drummer Ari Hoenig, who appear here. At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JENNY SCHEINMAN (Tuesday) Ms. Scheinman is that rare jazz violinist who embraces her instrument's folksier side without making concessions to genre. She performs here with two frequent foils, the guitarist Adam Levy and the clarinetist Doug Weiselman. At 7 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SING INTO SPRING FESTIVAL (Tonight through Thursday) Singers reign at Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola through mid-April, appearing with first-rate backing bands. The estimable Claudia Acuña performs this weekend, while a promising newcomer, Sachal Vasandani, appears on Tuesday. Wednesday's shows feature Jamie Davis; on Thursday, the legendary Jimmy Scott begins a four-night run. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m. with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LOREN STILLMAN QUARTET (Wednesday) Loren Stillman, an alto saxophonist with an inquisitive relationship to jazz conventions, leads a quartet with the guitarist Nate Radley, the bassist Matt Pavolka and the drummer Ted Poor. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Tea Lounge, 837 Union Street, between Sixth and Seventh Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 789-2762, tealoungeny.com; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STRYKER/SLAGLE BAND (Tonight through Sunday) The guitarist Dave Stryker and the saxophonist Steve Slagle have worked together in hard-driving settings since as far back as the mid-1980s; their rhythm section here consists of the eminently capable Jay Anderson and Billy Hart, on bass and drums. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow, Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25, $20 on Sunday. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* RANDY WESTON (Wednesday) Mr. Weston's pianism can recall Duke Ellington and Thelonious Monk, but as a composer he has long reached beyond the specific parameters of jazz. He performs under the auspices of the Central Brooklyn Jazz Festival with his dynamic African Rhythms Trio. At 7 p.m., Brooklyn Historical Society, 128 Pierrepont Street, at Clinton Street, Brooklyn, (718) 222-4111 Ext. 250, brooklynhistory.org; $45, $30 for members, reservations required. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera  'DIE ÄGYPTISCHE HELENA' (Tomorrow) With its convoluted libretto by Hugo von Hofmannsthal and unevenly inspired score by Richard Strauss, this wry contemporary take on the Helen of Troy myth, has remained a rarity since its 1928 premiere. But the Metropolitan Opera's fancifully surreal new production by David Fielding, mounted for the soprano Deborah Voigt, makes a compelling case for this intriguing work, thanks to Mr. Voigt's vocally lustrous and affecting portrayal of the title role as well as the vibrant and insightful conducting of Fabio Luisi. The brilliant coloratura Diana Damrau is wonderful as the sorceress Aithra. The German tenor Torsten Kerl sings Menelas. This is the final performance of the season. At 8:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $42 to $220. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'ANDREA CHÉNIER' (Tomorrow and Wednesday) Ben Heppner, arguably the leading Wagnerian tenor of our day, continues his bold explorations of far-flung repertory with the title role of Giordano's swashbuckling verismo opera, in the Met's revival of Nicolas Joël's 1996 production. Mr. Heppner may lack the vocal colorings and idiomatic expressivity of the heroic Italian tenors who excelled in this touchstone role, a poet with libertarian fervor during the French Revolution. But in his honest and compelling portrayal he sings with burnished sound, vigor and lyrical sensitivity. The rich-voiced soprano Violeta Urmana as Maddalena and the powerful baritone Mark Delavan as Gérard are very strong. Marco Armiliato conducts. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m. and Wednesday at 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $220 to $320 tomorrow, $15 to $175 for Wednesday. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'LA DONNA DEL LAGO' (Tomorrow) Rossini's sleek, simple and lovely take on Sir Walter Scott is ending its run at the New York City Opera. Elena, the Donna in question, is sung by Alexandrina Pendatchanska. The two high-flying tenor parts are taken by Barry Banks as Uberto and Andrew Drost as Rodrigo. At 8 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nycopera.com; $25 to $130. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>'CURLEW RIVER' (Thursday) Britten called his one-act opera ''Curlew River'' a church parable. Inspired by a Japanese Noh play, the work takes the form of a sacred ritual, with a procession of monks enacting a mystery play about a madwoman who crosses a river with a ferryman in search of her abducted son. The Japan Society offers a staging of this haunting and seldom-seen work, a co-production with the L'Opéra Rouen/Haute-Normandie directed by Yoshi Oida, starring the tenor Michael Bennett as the madwoman, with musical direction by David Stern. At 7:30 p.m., 333 East 47th Street, Manhattan, (212) 715-1258, japansociety.org; $52; $45 for members. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'GIULIO CESARE' (Tonight and Tuesday) The Metropolitan Opera joins a big week for Handel opera with the first ''Giulio Cesare'' of the season. David Daniels and Ruth Ann Swenson are in principal roles, and Harry Bicket conducts. At 7:30, Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $110 to $320 tickets remaining tonight, $15 to $175 for Tuesday. (Holland)</p>
        <p>'MADAMA BUTTERFLY' (Tomorrow) New principals take over the City Opera's current run of Puccini's inspired tearjerker. Shu-Ying Li is Cio-Cio-San and Christopher Jackson is Pinkerton. Atsushi Yamada is the new conductor. At 1:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nycopera.com; $25 to $125. (Holland)</p>
        <p>'LA TRAVIATA' (Wednesday) The stylishly realistic production of Verdi's ''Traviata'' created by the soprano Renata Scotto for the New York City Opera returns to the repertory. Making her company debut as Violetta is the French soprano Anne-Sophie Duprels, who has won high praise for her portrayal of the role in London and other cities. The tenor Bruce Sledge sings Alfredo. George Manahan conducts. At 7:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nycopera.com; $25 to $125. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'TURANDOT' (Monday) For spectacle and big music, the Franco Zeffirelli production at the Met of Puccini's final opera is hard to beat. For compelling leads, you might have to look elsewhere: Andrea Gruber sounded wobbly and thin on the first night of this revival, and Richard Margison effort-full, though he marshaled his forces for ''Nessun dorma.'' Only Hei-Kyung Hong's Liu, with her reliably floating pianos, was really worth the price of admission. But spectacle and size are evidently enough to keep tickets selling briskly for this one. Marco Armiliato conducts. At 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000 metopera.org; sold out. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>'DIE ZAUBERFLÖTE' (Monday and Wednesday) William Kentridge, the South African art-world star, is an animator, a draughtsman and a man of the theater. After a range of smaller-scale works -- the puppet operas ''Zeno at 4 a.m.'' and ''Il Ritorno di Ulisse in Patria'' were both seen at Lincoln Center in recent years -- he took on Mozart's final opera for the Théâtre Royal de la Monnaie in Belgium in 2005. Set in a Victorian age of exploration, with antic animations, the resulting production (conducted by an assistant of René Jacobs, who led the original) comes to Brooklyn for four performances through next weekend. At 7:30 p.m., Brooklyn Academy of Music, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, (718) 636-4100, bam.org; $30 to $110. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>'ABSOLUTE ARABIAN NIGHTS' (Tomorrow) Conceived by Kristjan Jarvi, the adventurous young conductor who founded the hip Absolute Ensemble, and the Swiss-born composer Daniel Schnyder, ''Absolute Arabian Nights'' is, the presenters state, a classical, jazz and ethnic music fusion of the sights and spirit of the Middle East. This ensemble's guests for this timely program include Marcel Khalife on oud and vocals, Bachar Khalife on hand percussion and Bassam Saba on nay. At 8 p.m., Town Hall, 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 840-2824, the-townhall-nyc.org; $37.50 and $40. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* BARGEMUSIC (Tonight, tomorrow, Sunday and Thursday) This floating concert hall, moored at the foot of the Brooklyn Bridge, is making the most of its intimate atmosphere by having the musicologist Maya Pritsker on hand tonight and tomorrow to discuss the music on the programs. Tonight, the pianist Daniel Vaiman plays sonatas by Rachmaninoff, Scriabin and Prokofiev. Tomorrow, the violinist Michael Vaiman and the pianist Dina Yoffe play sonatas by Mozart, Shostakovich and Schumann. On Sunday, the New York Chamber Soloists perform Bach's ''Musical Offering'' as well as Mozart's Adagio and Rondo in C minor (K. 617) and the premiere of Gerald Fried's ''Chess Game,'' a work inspired by ''Alice in Wonderland.'' On Thursday, the pianist and composer Dick Hyman leads an ensemble that also includes clarinet and strings in works by Gershwin and Rodgers and Hammerstein, as well as his own ''Baby Boom'' and Sextet. Mozart's exquisite Clarinet Quintet and a Leclair sonata fill out the program. Tonight, tomorrow and Thursday at 8 p.m., Sunday at 4 p.m., Fulton Ferry Landing next to the Brooklyn Bridge, Brooklyn, (718) 624-2083, bargemusic.org. $35 tonight and tomorrow; $40 on Sunday; $45 on Thursday. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>THOMAS BUCKNER (Thursday) The baritone Thomas Buckner, here presented by the World Music Institute as part of the Interpretations series (which he curates), has long been a champion of avant-garde music. He will perform new works for voice and various instruments, including William Duckworth's ''Their Song'' for baritone and piano. Petr Kotik conducts the New York premiere of Christian Wolff's ''37 Haiku'' for baritone, oboe, horn, viola and cello, and the world premiere of ''A People's History'' by R. Chris Dahlgren for baritone, flute, clarinet, percussion, piano, celeste, violin and cello. At 8 p.m., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212) 501-3330, kaufman-center.org; $10; $7 for students. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>SARAH CHANG (Tuesday) Sarah Chang, a former prodigy who has matured into a gifted artist, and Ashley Wass, a pianist, play Beethoven's ''Kreutzer'' Sonata and Prokofiev's Violin Sonata No. 2. Sandwiched between these two extroverted works is the New York premiere of Richard Danielpour's introverted ''River of Light,'' written in memory of Isaac Stern. At 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $25 to 79. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>COLLEGIUM VOCALE GENT (Sunday) Whatever your religious persuasions, for a music lover there is no better way to spend Easter Sunday than listening to the Collegium Vocale Gent under Philippe Herreweghe perform Bach's ''St. John Passion.'' The ensembles (both chorus and orchestra) are first-rate, the music breathtaking, the soloists (including Camilla Tilling and Christoph Prégardien as the Evangelist) reliable: superlatives fail us. Just go. At 3 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $60. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>CUTTING EDGE ENSEMBLE (Monday) The conductor and composer Victoria Bond is the host of a series of concerts that bring together music and other art forms -- in this case, weaving and digital art. Pamela Topham's ''Water Music,'' a tapestry inspired by the East Hampton landscape, will be paired with Libby Larsen's ''Slow Structures,'' a composition inspired by water as it freezes. Judith Shatin's ''Penelope's Song,'' for cello and electronics, uses the sounds of a weaver's loom. And Kenji Bunch's ''Crawl Space,'' ''Sarabande'' and ''The 3 G's'' will be accompanied by video of digital painting and animation. At 8 p.m., the Thalia at Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, symphonyspace.org; $15; $10 for students. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>EITHER/OR FESTIVAL (Tonight and tomorrow night) Concerts presented by Either/Or offer new works for solo instruments and unconventional chamber ensembles. A mini-festival offers solo and chamber works for piano, guitar, violin, cello and percussion. The lineup tonight features music by Michael Gordon, Richard Carrick, Xenakis and premieres by Nick Didkovsky, Andrew Byrne and Mauricio Rodriguez. Tomorrow's concert features a premiere by Mr. Carrick and pieces by Helmut Lachenmann, Keeril Makan and Massimo Lauricella. At 8, Tenri Cultural Institute, 43A West 13th Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 645- 2800, eitherormusic.org; $15, $10 for students, $25 for both concerts. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>RICHARD GOODE (Thursday) This pianist's work has been consistently thoughtful and enlightening. He addresses himself here to Bach's Partita No. 5, Mozart's Rondo in A (K. 511), Brahms's Fantasies (Op. 116) and Debussy's Preludes, Book II. At 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $28 to $90. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* JERUSALEM STRING QUARTET (Thursday) This young ensemble played a memorable concert at the 92nd Street Y last season in which it framed a Brahms Piano Quintet with American and Israeli works. The group's program at Zankel Hall looks more cautious -- the repertory is Beethoven's Quartet in F (Op. 18, No. 1), Janacek's gritty ''Kreutzer Sonata'' Quartet, and Tchaikovsky's Quartet No. 1 -- but presumably these musicians play this works with the same electricity that enlivened their performance last year. At 7:30 p.m., Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $30 to $42. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>WOLFGANG HOLZMAIR AND HERMINE HASELBÖCK (Monday) Hot on the heels of their exploration of the songs of Hugo Wolf, Mr. Holzmair, a baritone, and Ms. Haselböck, a mezzo-soprano (both excellent Austrian singers), turn their attention to the songs of Franz Schreker, a major opera composer of the early 20th century whose music was branded ''degenerate'' by the Nazis. The event is offered in tandem with the American premiere of Schreker's 1910 opera, ''Der Ferne Klang,'' in a concert performance by the American Symphony Orchestra and Leon Botstein. At 8 p.m., Austrian Cultural Forum, 11 East 52nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 319-5300; acfny.com; free, but reservations are required. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>MIKLOS PERENYI AND ANDRAS SCHIFF (Wednesday and Thursday) Two distinguished Hungarians, the cellist Mr. Perenyi and his friend the pianist Mr. Schiff, take on Beethoven's cello and piano repertory with back-to-back concerts at the 92nd Street Y. At 8 p.m., 1395 Lexington Avenue, (212) 415-5500, 92y.org; $45. (Holland)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK FESTIVAL OF SONG (Wednesday and Thursday) Latin song has become a great passion among the many wide-ranging passions of Steven Blier, the polymathic co-founder, co-director, accompanist and speaker of the New York Festival of Song. ''Amores Nuevos'' is a new program of music by Alberto Hemsi, Maria Grever, Gisela Hernández and many other composers one will probably be glad to have heard of at evening's end. Michelle Areyzaga, Jeffrey Picon and Ricardo Herrera are the soloists. At 8 p.m., Weill Recital Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $48. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC (Wednesday and Thursday) This week's focus is on Shostakovich's first violin concerto, introduced by Peter Schickele at an ''Inside the Music'' event on Wednesday, performed by Lisa Batiashvili with the conductor Sakari Oramo on that night and Thursday. For Mr. Oramo, however, another highlight is his compatriot Sibelius's Sixth Symphony: the rising star, who successfully succeeded Simon Rattle in Birmingham, is recording a complete Sibelius cycle. Wednesday at 6:45 p.m., Thursday at 7:30 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nyphil.org; $24 to $60 for Wednesday, $28 to $94 for Thursday. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>* POMERIUM (Tomorrow) Alexander Blachly leads his superb choir in a program of Renaissance Passion and Resurrection motets for Easter. Among the composers represented in this broadly international program are Dufay, Gesualdo, Monteverdi, Senfl, Lassus and Byrd. At 1 and 3 p.m., the Cloisters, Fort Tryon Park, Washington Heights, (212) 650-2290, metmuseum.org; $35. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>ILYA YAKUSHEV (Tomorrow) Ilya Yakushev, the winner of the 2005 World Piano Competition in Cincinnati, is a graduate of Mannes College of Music and currently studies with Vladimir Feltsman. Mr. Yakushev, a 25-year-old native of St. Petersburg, Russia, has been executive director of the International Keyboard Institute and Festival at Mannes since 2002. In his Alice Tully recital debut, he will play Haydn's Sonata in D (Hob. XVI:37), Prokofiev's Sonata No. 7 (''War Sonata 2/Stalingrad'') and Mussorgsky's ''Pictures at an Exhibition.'' At 8 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $20. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>* AILEY II (Wednesday and Thursday) Alvin Ailey created a second, or junior, company in 1974, almost casually, as a way of working on new choreography. Ailey II is now a world-class troupe, filled with dancers who not only are good but also perform with a youthful hunger for their art, along with a reverence for dance that is a part of the mission of the company director, Sylvia Waters, whom Ailey himself chose to direct that first group. Now Ailey II is coming home, performing in the black-box theater that is part of the Ailey headquarters -- newer, grander and more gleaming than Ailey ever envisioned. The repertory will include new dances by Abdel Salaam, Darrell Grand Moultrie and Jessica Lang, along with Ailey's ''Streams'' and a chunk of Ailey highlights. (Through April 22.) At 8 p.m., Ailey Citigroup Theater, 405 West 55th Street, Chelsea, (212) 868-4444, alvinailey.org; $40; $10 student rush tickets available. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>* 'THE ART OF FALLING' (Thursday) This free performance-installation, choreographed by Catherine Hourihan with video by Pam Kray, juxtaposes live dancers' bodies with projected images of New York City and its architecture to suggest the inherent fragility of solid, everyday life in the 21st century. (Through April 20.) The installation alone will be visible April 13 to 20. At 7:30 p.m., Lower Manhattan Cultural Council Swing Space, 15 Nassau Street, between Cedar and Pine Streets, Lower Manhattan, (877) 919-8326, chourihan.com (Dunning)</p>
        <p>JONAH BOKAER AND LIUBO BORRISOV (Monday through Thursday) If you find yourself in Chelsea this month, hop into Dance Theater Workshop to see if there's ''A Cure for Surveillance.'' This public media piece, by Jonah Bokaer and Liubo Borrisov, marks the workshop's new Gallery Installation Fellowship. (Through April 28.) During theater hours; Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077, dtw.org; free. (Claudia La Rocco)</p>
        <p>JOHN BUTLER: AN AMERICAN MASTER (Tuesday through Thursday) John Butler's dances have been performed by companies from Australia to Canada. Next week, several of the late choreographer's works will get a new look by some artists closer to home, including Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater, the Richmond Ballet and Desmond Richardson. (Through April 14.) Tuesday and Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., Friday at 7 p.m., Saturday at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 2 and 7:30 p.m. Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800; $42. (La Rocco)</p>
        <p>DANCE AT DNA (Tonight, tomorrow and Thursday) Ellis Wood and her all-female modern-dance company perform Ms. Wood's new ''Flat Affect,'' a piece about women's irrational fears. Tonight and tomorrow at 8 p.m. Tami Stronach Dance follows on Thursday, through April 15, in Ms. Stronach's ''Pinchas the Fisher-People and the Great Flood.'' This retelling of the ancient myth, set to klezmer music, is from the perspective of mermaids. Thursday at 8 p.m., Dance New Amsterdam, 280 Broadway, at Chambers Street, TriBeCa, (212) 279-4200, dnadance.org; $17. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'DANCE CONVERSATIONS AT THE FLEA' (Tuesday) This free series of performing and discussion continues with work by Sasha Welsh, Roxanne Steinberg, Jackie Moynahan and HoffTanzt/Daniela Hoff, all chosen by Yasuko Yokoshi. At 7 p.m., Flea Theater, 41 White Street, Lower Manhattan, (212) 645-6462, theflea.org. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'DANCING WITH BISHOP' (Tonight through Sunday) This piece by Saskia Hegt combines poetry and letters written by Elizabeth Bishop with movement and music. Tonight and tomorrow at 10 p.m., Sunday at 5:30 p.m., La MaMa E.T.C., 74A East Fourth Street, East Village (212) 475-7710, lamama.org; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'GREEN SPACE BLOOMS: DANCE IN QUEENS' (Tonight through Sunday) This program features a performance each night by Valerie Green and her Dance Entropy, with the guest companies and musicians Stankovic Ballet Company and Andreas Altmann (tonight), Duncan Dance Collective and Sami Abu Shumays (tomorrow) and Alan Good Dance and Graciela Carriqui (Sunday). (Through April 15.) At 8 p.m. Green Space Studio, 37-24 24th Street, between 37th and 38th Avenues, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 956-3037, Greenspacestudio.com; $20; $15 for students, dancers and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>PHILIPPA KAYE COMPANY AND AIR BAND (Tonight) In Ms. Kaye's ''Ritual for a Non-Repeating Universe,'' computers track dancers' moves and translate them into digital animation, to music performed live by AirBand. At 8, Location One, 26 Greene Street, Manhattan, (212) 334-3347, location1.org; $20. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* AMANDA LOULAKI AND SHORT MEAN LADY (Thursday through Sunday) In ''Delirium, or That Taste in My Mouth,'' the Crete-born choreographer Amanda Loulaki and her collaborators explore the choices people make in their bodies, before the mind can fully weigh in -- and given the bodies in question, these should be some captivating decisions indeed. At 8:30 p.m., Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194; $15. (La Rocco)</p>
        <p>MOVEMENT RESEARCH AT THE JUDSON CHURCH (Monday) Carrie Ahern, Jeffrey Peterson and Sasha Welsh investigate works in progress in the latest installment of this terrific series. Doors open at 7:45, and seating is limited. At 8 p.m., 55 Washington Square South, Greenwich Village, (212) 598-0551, movementresearch.org; free. (La Rocco)</p>
        <p>ODYSSEY DANCE THEATER OF UTAH (Tonight through Sunday) In its New York debut, the company will perform two programs of jazz-ballet dances, created by its director, Derryl Yeager, and Mia Michaels, Eddie Ocampo, Dee Caspary, Liz Imperio and Mandy Moore. Tonight and tomorrow at 8 p.m., tomorrow at 3 p.m., Sunday at 2 p.m., Ailey Citigroup Theater, 405 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444; $20; $10 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>PALISSIMO (Thursday) Injuries to two cast members forced the postponement of ''Le Petit Mort/Now It's Time to Say Goodbye'' by Pavel Zustiak. Mr. Zustiak's company is back in business now, with a new work that ponders death and confrontations with mortality. (Through April 15.) At 8 p.m., Performance Space 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101, ps122.org; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>BETH SOLL &amp; COMPANY (Tomorrow and Sunday) This modern-dance company will perform ''Black Flower'' and ''Rustling Solo,'' choreographed by Ms. Soll, a longtime and major presence in the Boston dance scene. At 8:30 p.m., Merce Cunningham Studio, 55 Bethune Street, at Washington Street, West Village, (212) 927-0476; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'GLOBAL FEMINISMS,' through July 1. Too much of the work in this sprawling, international assembly of recent pieces by nearly 90 women from nearly 50 countries is body-oriented and doesn't venture far beyond the essentialism of Judy Chicago's indomitable 1975-79 installation opus, ''The Dinner Party,'' whose enshrinement in the new Elizabeth A. Sackler Center for Feminist Art this exhibition celebrates. Thoroughly dominated by photography and video, with a documentary slant to many of its better moments, the show is more about information, politics and the struggle for equality than it is about art in any very concentrated or satisfying sense. That doesn't keep parts of it from being energetic and illuminating, especially as a record of the way that feminism has gripped and jump-started the imaginations of women around the world. 200 Eastern Parkway, Brooklyn, (718) 638-5000, brooklynmuseum.org. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'KINDRED SPIRITS: ASHER B. DURAND AND THE AMERICAN LANDSCAPE,' through July 29. This show of about 60 works by one of the greats of 19th-century American landscape painting has as its centerpiece ''Kindred Spirits'' (1849), a tribute to the landscapist Thomas Cole and his friend the poet-journalist William Cullen Bryant. A founder of the Hudson River School but one of its less dramatic painters, Durand (1796-1886) favored the realistic approach to landscape advocated by the English critic John Ruskin, rather than the metaphorical view held by Cole and other Hudson River artists that its representation ought to express God's sublimity. Obeying Ruskin's call for truth to nature, Durand explored forest interiors with close attention to the ways of trees, foliage, rocks and ground cover in smaller works, while his larger and more elaborate exhibition pictures, influenced by European masters, are Arcadian visions suffused with light, color and atmospheric perspective. If the show reveals some of Durand's weaknesses -- repetitive themes and borrowings from other artists -- it also reveals his strong sense of artistic mission and his potent role in shaping the aesthetic of 19th-century America. (See above.) (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>FRICK COLLECTION: 'GEORGE STUBBS (1724-1806): A CELEBRATION,' through May 27. One of the finest horse painters ever, Stubbs knew his subjects from head to hoof and skin to bones. He painted other mammals too: dogs, lions, tigers, oxen, monkeys and humans. This intimate show of 17 Stubbs paintings from English collections reveals his admirable range, although the people he portrayed in two large, late canvases have the stiffness of figures on a candy box. His horses are his true monuments. 1 East 70th Street, Manhattan, (212) 288-0700, frick.org. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'FAMILY PICTURES,' through April 16. This show sounds ripe with possibilities. The results, however, are more mixed. The exhibition is drawn from the museum's collection, which explains some of its exclusions and limitations. Many artists you associate with contemporary photography and the family are not in attendance: Richard Bellingham, Tina Barney, Malerie Marder. There is also a sense of false advertising in the exhibition's title. The museum's news release extends the exhibition's exploration into ''representation of families and children in contemporary art and video.'' Images of children, you quickly realize, can operate as a completely different genre. Rineke Dijkstra's ''Beach Portraits'' of adolescents awkwardly posing against stark seascape horizons are isolated (and isolating) images of children on the threshold of adulthood. You don't think about family when gazing at these photographs. Sally Mann is perhaps the best-known contemporary photographer of children, specifically her own. Ms. Mann, represented here by black-and-white photographs from the late 1980s and early 1990s of her ethereally gorgeous children, has been accused of everything from neglect to child abuse. The questions raised by her dual role as artist and mother, simultaneous protector and potential exploiter of the family, remain vitally interesting. 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3500, guggenheim.org. (Martha Schwendener)</p>
        <p>* METROPOLITAN MUSEUM OF ART: 'VENICE AND THE ISLAMIC WORLD, 828-1797,' through July 8. At its peak in the Renaissance, Venice, the Most Serene, was a giant, clamorous Costco-on-the-Rialto. All the necessities, and most of the luxuries, of life flowed into and through it, with many items arriving from Islamic Africa and the Near East. With classic Met largesse, this exhibition suggests the spectacle of two different cultures meeting in one fantastic city, in which commerce and love of beauty, those great levelers, unite them in a fruitful bond. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>* THE MET: 'INCISIVE IMAGES: IVORY AND BOXWOOD CARVINGS,' through Nov. 25. This extraordinary show, drawn almost entirely from the Met's vaults, presents an array of nearly 100 carved figures, crucifixes, reliefs, containers, hand-held weapons and the occasional piece of furniture. It is an engrossing hive of religious fervor, Classical erudition (and occasional naughtiness), style shifts and multicultural cross-currents. And among the many feats of drop-dead artistic skill are several of traffic-stopping caliber. Don't miss it. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (See above.) (Smith)</p>
        <p>MORGAN LIBRARY &amp; MUSEUM: 'APOCALYPSE THEN: MEDIEVAL ILLUMINATIONS FROM THE MORGAN,' through June 17. Even in the contemporary art world the symbolism of the Book of Revelation, with its demons and lakes of fire, has a subversive appeal. This new exhibition at the Morgan Library celebrates a facsimile of ''Las Huelgas Apocalypse'' (1220), the largest surviving Spanish illuminated commentary on the Apocalypse. The show, which includes 50 leaves from the original text, unbound and installed around the gallery's perimeter, offers a walking tour of the medieval imagination. 225 Madison Avenue, at 36th Street, (212) 685-0008, morganlibrary.org. (Andrea K. Scott)</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'COMIC ABSTRACTION: IMAGE-BREAKING, IMAGE-MAKING,' through June 11. This unimaginative and uniformed treatment of a big idea -- the healthy and essential contamination of Modernist abstraction by popular culture -- should be seen if only because it is such a dispiriting symptom of the Modern's paralysis where contemporary art is concerned. Although it promises work that addresses ''perplexing questions,'' nearly everything here is perfectly pleasant and innocuous. The exceptions are provided by Gary Simmons, Ellen Gallagher and Sue Williams. (212) 708-9400, moma.org. (212) 708-9400, moma.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* MOMA: JEFF WALL, through May 14. This majestic show makes a great case for Mr. Wall as the most complete, if traditional, of the untraditional artists who emerged from the turmoil of Conceptual Art. His often immense color transparencies mounted on light boxes are enthralling vehicles, intent on giving pleasure while making a point or two about society, art, history, visual perception, the human animal or all of the above. An imposing blend of painting, street photography and movies, they blur reality and artifice, narrative and form, detail and the big statement. You can't stop looking at them. (See above.) (Smith)</p>
        <p>* NEUE GALERIE: 'VAN GOGH AND EXPRESSIONISM,' through July 2. The Neue has, as usual, gathered a stellar roundup of Expressionist art. In one of the show's most exciting rooms, a third-floor gallery devoted mostly to self-portraits, two extraordinary van Goghs hang at opposite ends: ''Self-Portrait With Straw Hat'' (1887-88), from the Metropolitan Museum's collection, filled with energetic, radiating brushstrokes, and the National Gallery's vibrant self-portrait of the artist holding a palette and brushes, painted about a year later. The most compelling pairing in this room, though, is van Gogh's ''Bedroom'' from 1889, the second of three versions he painted of his room in Arles, with Egon Schiele's obvious homage, ''The Artist's Bedroom in Neulengbach,'' painted in 1911, in a darker palette and with a perspective tipped precariously toward the viewer. 1048 Fifth Avenue, at 86th Street, (212) 628-6200, neuegalerie.org. (Schwendener)</p>
        <p>WADSWORTH ATHENEUM MUSEUM OF ART: 'FAITH AND FORTUNE: FIVE CENTURIES OF EUROPEAN MASTERWORKS,' through Dec. 9. One of the most appealing things about this gathering of some 400 treasures is the mix, with knockout paintings keeping company with small sculptures, elaborate table furnishings, decorative platters, Meissen knockoffs of Chinese pottery, a porcelain birdcage and vases and such. Strolling through the galleries, you'll find treasures like ''Saint Francis of Assisi in Ecstasy'' (about 1594-95), said to be the first authentic Caravaggio in an American museum; Fra Angelico's poignant, poetic fragment ''Head of an Angel'' (about 1455-50); and Francisco de Zurbarán's fearsome portrayal of a dead martyr, ''Saint Serapion'' (1628). But the pièce de résistance is an entire gallery made into an art and curio cabinet, with a planned clutter of brilliant objects that play to a viewer's inner acquisitor: exotic shells mounted in gold; an extraordinary Baroque ivory carving (presumed to be before 1650) of Adam and Eve; an automatic tabletop clock (about 1619) with a standing lion that could roll its eyes, open its jaws and stick out its tongue when the hours struck. Dazzlement prevails. 600 Main Street, Hartford, (860) 278-2670, wadsworthatheneum.org (Glueck)</p>
        <p>WHITNEY MUSEUM OF AMERICAN ART: 'GORDON MATTA-CLARK RETROSPECTIVE,' through June 3. I have no doubt that Matta-Clark is now being turned into a hot commodity, but at least at the Whitney you can see what he aspired to be. He came up with various wonderfully harebrained ideas. Literally, in one case: after letting his hair grow for a year, he cut it off as a kind of performance and phrenological gag. The preserved hair, dutifully tagged piece by piece, opens the show like a holy relic. He also sautéed a Polaroid of a Christmas tree in grease. The copy he sent to Robert Smithson, golden brown on the outside, is here too, and none too appetizing, I might add. At the center of the exhibition is ''Splitting.'' To a plain single-family suburban frame house in Englewood, N.J., he made a cut straight down the middle, bisecting the building, then severing the four corners of the roof. The retrospective consists of films, drawings, photographs and some of the architectural pieces he cut out of buildings. The drawings are casual and not too interesting, but the luxurious black-and-white photographs from Paris speak more to Matta-Clark's formal elegance. The big message was: Life as art, and art as life, a philosophy dependent on our being properly attuned and keen to the moment. (212) 570-3676, whitney.org. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* WHITNEY MUSEUM OF AMERICAN ART: 'LORNA SIMPSON,' through May 6. This tight, refined and impassioned survey covers more than 20 years of Lorna Simpson's career, from her photo-and-text meditations on race and sexism in the 1980s, to her more recent short films, which unite American history and personal history in forceful and lyrical ways. It would be easy to put some of this work on a shelf as ''identity art,'' but with an African-American woman holding one of the highest offices in the United States government, an African-American man running for president, and the nation embroiled in what some people view as an ethnic war, this art is entirely of the moment. (See above.) (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>JEAN SHIN: KEY PROMISES The idea is obvious, if you're as keen as this artist on recycling everyday objects: an installation using the word commands of countless computer keyboards to orchestrate a flow of suggested actions, desires and emotional states across four walls of a small gallery. From esc and shift to return and home. Art lite, perhaps, but expertly done. Frederieke Taylor Gallery, 535 West 22nd Street, (646) 230-0992, frederieketaylorgallery.com, through tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Other</p>
        <p>'GIFTS OF THE FOREST: NATIVE TRADITIONS IN WOOD AND BARK' Drawn from the collections of the Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center in Connecticut, this show celebrates the trees of the rich forests that once covered the Northeast, yielding essential materials to the Pequot and other Eastern Woodland cultures. The objects run from ancient woodworking tools to contemporary objects that carry on tribal traditions, like the simple and beautiful wooden flute made in 1999 by Hawk Henires (Nipmuc) and adorned with an elegantly carved bird motif. Many things here were made in the 19th and 20th centuries: handsome woven baskets, carved bowls and spoons, decorated cradle boards for carrying babies, birch bark canoe models, an elegant birch-bark hamper whose sides bear a stylized tree motif. UBS Art Gallery, 1285 Avenue of the Americas, between 51st and 52nd Streets, (212) 713-2885, through April 27. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* 'EARLY CHINESE BUDDHIST SCULPTURE,' Asia Week is over, but its essence lingers on in this exhibition of beautiful carved stone figures of Buddhas and bodhisattvas dating from the Northern Wei to Tang periods in China. This is the type of work that elicited rapturous responses when shown in London and Washington a few seasons back. Throckmorton Fine Art, 145 East 57th Street, third floor, (212) 223-1059, through April 14. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* MORGAN LIBRARY &amp; MUSEUM: 'PRIVATE TREASURES: FOUR CENTURIES OF EUROPEAN MASTER DRAWINGS,' through Sunday. This show is drawn entirely from an anonymous private collection. Despite the veil of secrecy, a couple of things are obvious: the collector had significant capital for investing in old masters and either an exceptional eye or a good adviser (or both). The strongest concentration is in Italian drawings. The earliest works come from a period when drawing wasn't an autonomous practice but was used as a form of exercise, to apply one's craft, to experiment and to make preliminary sketches for larger works. The best example -- and the most historically significant work here -- is a black chalk drawing, ''The Dead Christ'' (1529-35), by Agnolo Bronzino. With more than 90 drawings in the show, being a diligent observer quickly becomes exhausting. In which case, put down the guide, find a few drawings you like, and enjoy them while you can. After all, you don't know where they came from, where they're going, or when you'll see them again. (See above.) (Schwendener)</p>
        <p>* JOHANNES VANDERBEEK The debut solo show of this artist at is a poetic, storybook tableau with a full-scale sculpture of a medieval knight reclining on his tomb and a walled-up archway set in the gallery wall. Both are made of papier-mâché made from old copies of Time and National Geographic. The beautiful little tree that stands between them is also of paper and paste. And check out the time-and-space-warped sleepers in the back room. Zach Feuer Gallery, 530 West 24th Street, Chelsea, (212) 989-7700; closes tomorrow. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 26, 2007, Thursday  A dance entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on April 6, about performances and discussions at the Flea Theater in Lower Manhattan, misidentified the curator who chose the works performed. She was Nina Winthrop -- not Yasuko Yokoshi, who had been scheduled to be the moderator, but who was repalced by Ms Winthrop.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 26, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>A dance entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on April 6, about performances and discussions at the Flea Theater in Lower Manhattan, misidentified the curator who chose the works performed. She was Nina Winthrop -- not Yasuko Yokoshi, who had been scheduled to be the moderator, but who was repalced by Ms Winthrop.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
