<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Three-Way Connection Of Minds And Bodies</title>
    <meta content="06jasp" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/arts/dance/06jasp.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838288"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Dance Theater Workshop</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Jasperse, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DF173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="536" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Three-Way Connection Of Minds And Bodies</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Three-Way Connection of Minds and Bodies</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAUDIA LA ROCCO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If ever there were a show to quash the ridiculous notion that art and entertainment are necessarily separate realms, it's ''Becky, Jodi and John,'' choreographed by John Jasperse in collaboration with the other two performers.</p>
        <p>The hourlong dance, which opened Wednesday night at Dance Theater Workshop, is teeming with laugh-out-loud gags, theatrical surprises and passages of pure, sensuous beauty. Yet you feel, after one viewing, that you are barely scratching the surface of this complex work, with its layered reflections on aging, on impermanence and on the individual performer, who is both transformed and revealed by the paradoxical vulnerability and power of live theater. But like most intelligent art ''Becky, Jodi and John'' energizes, rather than enervates, and you want to keep digging till you unearth these layers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The hourlong dance at Dance Theater Workshop is teeming with laugh-out-loud gags, theatrical surprises and passages of pure, sensuous beauty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If ever there were a show to quash the ridiculous notion that art and entertainment are necessarily separate realms, it's ''Becky, Jodi and John,'' choreographed by John Jasperse in collaboration with the other two performers.</p>
        <p>The hourlong dance, which opened Wednesday night at Dance Theater Workshop, is teeming with laugh-out-loud gags, theatrical surprises and passages of pure, sensuous beauty. Yet you feel, after one viewing, that you are barely scratching the surface of this complex work, with its layered reflections on aging, on impermanence and on the individual performer, who is both transformed and revealed by the paradoxical vulnerability and power of live theater. But like most intelligent art ''Becky, Jodi and John'' energizes, rather than enervates, and you want to keep digging till you unearth these layers.</p>
        <p>More than that, at a time when so much art delights in insider gamesmanship, one of the most delightful things about this work is its openness. The audience is brought into a set of particular relationships -- longstanding ones between these dancers -- at a particular moment in New York dance, which are then connected to a larger world of ideas and feelings about life and art. What a gift.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jasperse, at the top of his (very good) game here, is further elevated by Becky Hilton and Jodi Melnick. A fourth dancer, Chrysa Parkinson, appears as an endearing talking head on a television screen. Snippets of her one-sided conversation offer a glimpse into the artists' creative lives and their enduring friendships. Nothing can match Ms. Parkinson's magical physical presence, but her verbal contribution is pretty great, not to mention a key cameo by her toy elephant.</p>
        <p>Highly personal elements like that rub up against Mr. Jasperse's articulate, formal choreography, informing and blurring its cool clarity. Early on, Ms. Hilton, donning glasses, reads an e-mail message sent by Ms. Melnick near the start of their collaborative process. It contains a lengthy catalog of her physical injuries and limitations, a list of don'ts that seems to dwarf her dos. But then Ms. Melnick begins to dance, and the possibilities opened up by a rotated hip or crooked arm make a mockery of this list, even though someday the ailments will win out.</p>
        <p>The knowledge of that someday and the delight that it is not yet here for these dancers hover like ghosts over ''Becky, Jodi and John,'' whose dancers are all 43 years old. Their bodies are still able to do what is asked, and their performing brains are seasoned and sophisticated enough to ask the right questions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jasperse's feel for the architecture of bodies in space is unerring, whether in quiet solos or deft, fluid partnering. His sensitivity is matched by Hahn Rowe's live, delicate score, which includes everything from a psaltery to a laptop, and the lighting design by Joe Levasseur and Mr. Jasperse. And who came up with the grand idea of affixing a smoke machine to Mr. Jasperse's body? This is art by and for adults: deeply silly and moving and smart.</p>
        <p>''Becky, Jodi and John'' runs through tomorrow at 7:30 p.m., with an extra 10 p.m. show tonight at Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea; (212) 924-0077, dtw.org.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
