<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Creatures More Slothful Than You and Me</title>
    <meta content="06wind" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/arts/television/06wind.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838270"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Public Broadcasting Service</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Grahame, Kenneth</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E6DF173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="567" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Creatures More Slothful Than You and Me</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Creatures More Slothful Than You and Me</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINIA BELLAFANTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bellafante, Ginia</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By the time ''The Wind in the Willows'' was published in 1908, its author, Kenneth Grahame, had committed himself to a life of consummate lollygagging, a vocation for which he presumably had affectionate disdain. The book came about as a series of stories he had written for his son; in them the slothfully well-to-do take a fair amount of ribbing. Though Grahame, who had written for much of his life, left his banking career in 1907, he lived 25 more years without producing another book.</p>
        <p>The latest adaptation of Grahame's children's classic comes on Sunday night from ''Masterpiece Theater,'' and while the production is ultimately too jaunty to be considered 100 percent safe for someone over 10, it makes a sufficiently heavy investment in the particularities of Grahame's class consciousness. It dispenses with animation, using live actors, none to better advantage than the British comic Matt Lucas. Mr. Lucas plays Mr. Toad, a scalawag son of great fortune who displays none of the humility and restraint of his other animal friends in Grahame's Edwardian river kingdom.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>PBS’s adaptation of Kenneth Grahame’s children’s classic places at the center his apparent belief that wealthy people were lazy buffoons, endlessly amusing in their indulgences and best kept around.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By the time ''The Wind in the Willows'' was published in 1908, its author, Kenneth Grahame, had committed himself to a life of consummate lollygagging, a vocation for which he presumably had affectionate disdain. The book came about as a series of stories he had written for his son; in them the slothfully well-to-do take a fair amount of ribbing. Though Grahame, who had written for much of his life, left his banking career in 1907, he lived 25 more years without producing another book.</p>
        <p>The latest adaptation of Grahame's children's classic comes on Sunday night from ''Masterpiece Theater,'' and while the production is ultimately too jaunty to be considered 100 percent safe for someone over 10, it makes a sufficiently heavy investment in the particularities of Grahame's class consciousness. It dispenses with animation, using live actors, none to better advantage than the British comic Matt Lucas. Mr. Lucas plays Mr. Toad, a scalawag son of great fortune who displays none of the humility and restraint of his other animal friends in Grahame's Edwardian river kingdom.</p>
        <p>''The Wind in the Willows'' is hardly bitter satire. In 1981 a children's author, Jan Needle, turned it into a socialist parable, creating a story using Grahame's characters and putting Toad's mansion in the hands of lower-class weasels. ''Masterpiece Theater'' does no such thing. It places at the center Grahame's apparent belief that wealthy people were lazy buffoons, endlessly amusing in their indulgences and best kept around.</p>
        <p>Everything revolves around Toad here -- figuratively and, because he is so round, literally. In ordinary life Mr. Lucas's frame does not suggest that he is a salad-and-pea-shoots kind of guy, and here he has fun with an exaggerated corpulence that seems to leave him channeling W. C. Fields.</p>
        <p>Toad is a gadget freak, addicted to boats and motorcars, which he doesn't handle particularly well; this fixation supplies the vague plot. His friends are always trying to reel him in, and we are meant to think of him as lovably silly, even though he is horrified by his encounters with washerwomen and all those belonging to the less than plummy ranks. ''What fun is life,'' he asks his friends, ''without a little showing off?''</p>
        <p>Was Grahame disgusted by ostentation or enthralled by it? This PBS production, made in conjunction with the BBC and the Canadian Broadcasting Corporation, leaves you hungering in the end for a film of his life. Grahame's father was an alcoholic, his mother a victim of scarlet fever. He was denied the Oxford education he wanted by his elderly guardians.</p>
        <p>As an adult he went unwillingly toward banking. He had an unfulfilling marriage and a son who committed suicide, all of this further suggesting that the great children's book writers who have lived happy, well-adjusted lives could probably fit comfortably on a unicycle. Take it away, ''Masterpiece Theater.''</p>
        <p>Masterpiece Theater  The Wind in the Willows</p>
        <p>Sunday night on most PBS stations (check local listings).</p>
        <p>Written by Lee Hall; adapted from the book by Kenneth Grahame; directed by Rachel Talalay; Justin Thomson-Glover, Patrick Irwin and Rebecca Eaton, executive producers; Gub Neal, producer. A Box TV production for the BBC, produced in association with the Canadian Broadcasting Corporation; WGBH, Boston; and NBDTV.</p>
        <p>WITH: Matt Lucas (Mr. Toad), Bob Hoskins (Badger), Mark Gattis (Ratty), Lee Ingleby (Mole), Anna Maxwell Martin (Jailer's daughter) and Imelda Staunton (Barge Lady).</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
