<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>First Trip to Augusta Elicits a (Quiet) Cheer</title>
    <meta content="06vecsey" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/sports/golf/06vecsey.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070410T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838363"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Vecsey, George</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Singh, Vijay</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mickelson, Phil</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Palmer, Arnold</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E2DC173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1036" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>First Trip to Augusta Elicits a (Quiet) Cheer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">First Trip to Augusta Elicits a (Quiet) Cheer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
      <dateline>AUGUSTA, Ga.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If there is one landmark American sports event about which I know next to nothing, it is the Masters. There's always other stuff going on in early April and I cannot say I've ever watched more than five straight minutes of the Masters on television.</p>
        <p>So when a friend of mine, Abe Schear, invited me to the Masters yesterday, I decided it was time to find out what the fuss is all about.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Having been to Augusta once now, I made up my mind to pay more attention to the dogwoods and the azaleas and, yes, the golfers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If there is one landmark American sports event about which I know next to nothing, it is the Masters. There's always other stuff going on in early April and I cannot say I've ever watched more than five straight minutes of the Masters on television.</p>
        <p>So when a friend of mine, Abe Schear, invited me to the Masters yesterday, I decided it was time to find out what the fuss is all about.</p>
        <p>Abe is a real-estate lawyer in Atlanta who, every few months, issues a newsletter called AGG Baseball Digest -- a series of interviews with people who love their baseball (Jimmy Carter and Ernie Harwell, just to drop two names). I would quickly discover my friend is equally passionate about golf.</p>
        <p>He drove straight east on Interstate 20 into the rising sun, took his favorite back route to the edge of the course, parked his car for $20 in somebody's yard and told me to check my laptop, camera and cellphone in the trunk.</p>
        <p>Unlike other sports events, the Masters does not permit any electronic devices on the premises, which would spare us from the ubiquitous self-important fan at baseball and football games who chatters to his friends all through the event. But there were free phones -- free phones -- in discreet little clusters far from the course. I was already impressed.</p>
        <p>Once we were inside, I noticed that there were no advertisements, no logos, no corporate presence whatsoever. The predominant color is a somber green, setting a tone for the event. They also hand out free start lists with a diagram of the course on the back. I decided to be a good guest and leave issues like the lack of female membership for some other day.</p>
        <p>We stopped for the $1 coffee and, for me, the $1 biscuit and sausage -- subsidized, I am sure, by the gigantic television contract. A middle-aged woman asked if she could cut into the line to buy a banana for her mother (price 75 cents), and Abe asked her how long her mother had been coming to the Masters and the woman said over 50 years.</p>
        <p>Everywhere we looked, we saw middle-aged people escorting their aging parents to this event that clearly means a great deal to all of them. Everybody was polite. Young men in Ohio State or Florida gear, who might have been a trifle boisterous at the Final Four in Atlanta last weekend, were on their best behavior.</p>
        <p>It was now time for golf. We headed toward the course, through solid pathways and elegant stone embankments and exquisite plantings of azaleas and dogwood in bloom. Everything had a feeling of permanence to it, even though this extremely private club is used for only four days of the Masters competition every year. The television camera towers at every hole are a dignified green, built solidly into the ground, with no thicket of cables splayed all over the grounds, as there is on the perimeter of other major events.</p>
        <p>We walked the course, with Abe pointing out the historic moments that have taken place here and there. On the 17th hole he recalled how a jovial Arnold Palmer, playing one of his final rounds here a few years ago, paused before hitting the ball to wink at a pretty young woman standing a few feet away.</p>
        <p>We joined the patrons near the first tee. I am careful to say ''patrons'' because I have heard how the distinguished commentator Jack Whitaker was banned from the CBS broadcast by Cliff Roberts, the grim mandarin of the Masters, for the crime of referring to the ''mob'' one day. The Masters does not consider them to be ''fans'' or ''spectators,'' either. So ''patrons'' it is.</p>
        <p>Dressed in black, the left-handed Phil Mickelson hit the ball to a corner of the green and gave a disgusted wave of his hand. We watched him trudge off in pursuit, but everybody applauded just the same. From a distance we watched him reach the errant ball, make five or six sweeping motions with his left hand to approximate the magic he would have to perform, and then he missed his first putt, anyway.</p>
        <p>We continued our walk, with Abe pointing out a very serious-looking female marshal in yellow helmet (to protect the workers from flying golf balls) who had once chastised him for changing footwear too close to the course. With a quick glare, marshals have been known to freeze patrons from running -- ''like Lot's wife,'' Abe said.</p>
        <p>We reached the famous 13th hole, where, a monument on a water fountain informed us, Palmer hit an eagle to secure the 1958 Masters, his first victory here, with an 18-foot putt. The 13th hole is the third part of the so-called Amen Corner, a Bermuda Triangle of holes named by the Sports Illustrated golf writer, Herbert Warren Wind, also in 1958.</p>
        <p>I've done a little research on this -- for my sake; I assume golf fans all know this stuff by now -- and discovered that Wind, a jazz authority, got this title from a recording, ''Shouting at Amen Corner,'' by a Chicago-based musician, Milton Mezzrow. That made me giggle a bit because Mezzrow was quite the hipster, and yet his composition has given a gospel-sounding name to a sacred corner of America's golfing shrine.</p>
        <p>As a rare observer of golf, I am always impressed by just how good these athletes are -- and that they do not kill the spectators craning their necks to watch a ball whiz pass them. But even the great ones have a bad moment. Bernhard Langer of Germany, the champion in 1985 and 1993, chose to use a putter to get from the smooth collar around the green toward the pin, but his first attempt sputtered short of the green. The patrons groaned and decided he got an A for choice but a D for execution.</p>
        <p>My friend and I watched Tiger Woods and Vijay Singh laboring one fairway away. We decided it was time to drive back into the sun, now far in the west. Having been to Augusta once now, I made up my mind to pay more attention to the dogwoods and the azaleas and, yes, the golfers.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 10, 2007, Tuesday  A picture caption with a Sports of The Times column on Friday, about experiencing the Masters in person for the first time, referred incorrectly to the body of water near the 16th green at Augusta National. It is a pond -- not Rae's Creek, which runs at the back of the 11th green and in front of the 12th green, and which has a tributary at the 13th tee.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 10, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A picture caption with a Sports of The Times column on Friday, about experiencing the Masters in person for the first time, referred incorrectly to the body of water near the 16th green at Augusta National. It is a pond -- not Rae's Creek, which runs at the back of the 11th green and in front of the 12th green, and which has a tributary at the 13th tee.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
