<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AHEAD | Cycling Races; Why Bicyclists Head to Georgia</title>
    <meta content="06ahead" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070413T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838290"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tour De Georgia (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collier, Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Biking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E1DF173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="832" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AHEAD | Cycling Races; Why Bicyclists Head to Georgia</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER P. COLLIER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Collier, Christopher</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Tour de Georgia bicycle race; other bicycle races scheduled around country listed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE'S a rhythm to watching, eating and pedaling your way through the 667-mile Tour de Georgia, a roving, carnivalesque professional road cycling race (held this year April 16 to 22) that brings about 500,000 visitors to some of Georgia's highest mountains and most colorful hamlets. About 120 are competitors in the race. For most of the rest, the tour is part sports spectacle, part Appalachian sightseeing trip and part movable party.</p>
        <p>Over seven days, the tour moves through a landscape of sandstone ridgelines; gushing, rhododendron-lined creeks; blooming dogwoods; and green mountain vistas. Quirky distractions are inextricably linked to stops along the way: Peachtree City, where cars are banned and residents tool around on 85 miles of golf-cart trails; Dalton, home to more than 100 carpet outlet stores; Rock City, where visitors roam through a network of mountaintop caves adorned with glow-in-the-dark gnomes; Stone Mountain, where a laser light show illuminates the faces of Confederate leaders carved into a massive hunk of granite.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE'S a rhythm to watching, eating and pedaling your way through the 667-mile Tour de Georgia, a roving, carnivalesque professional road cycling race (held this year April 16 to 22) that brings about 500,000 visitors to some of Georgia's highest mountains and most colorful hamlets. About 120 are competitors in the race. For most of the rest, the tour is part sports spectacle, part Appalachian sightseeing trip and part movable party.</p>
        <p>Over seven days, the tour moves through a landscape of sandstone ridgelines; gushing, rhododendron-lined creeks; blooming dogwoods; and green mountain vistas. Quirky distractions are inextricably linked to stops along the way: Peachtree City, where cars are banned and residents tool around on 85 miles of golf-cart trails; Dalton, home to more than 100 carpet outlet stores; Rock City, where visitors roam through a network of mountaintop caves adorned with glow-in-the-dark gnomes; Stone Mountain, where a laser light show illuminates the faces of Confederate leaders carved into a massive hunk of granite.</p>
        <p>Traversing the steep climbs are some of the best cyclists in the world. Levi Leipheimer, Tyler Hamilton and George Hincapie are all expected this year. Lance Armstrong and Floyd Landis are former winners.</p>
        <p>Each day, as the start and finish lines move forward through the course, not only the racers, but also their entourages, the race officials and the fans are on the move. Tour buses emblazoned with corporate logos, sedans crowned with a half-dozen bikes each, trucks loaded with spare bike parts and thousands of carloads of spectators move up mountainous roads and through blink-and-you'll-miss-it towns.</p>
        <p>Now five years old, the Tour de Georgia is an infant in the world of professional bicycle racing; the Tour de France is more than 100 years old. But on this side of the Atlantic, where opportunities to watch overland bike races are increasing, it is already an old-timer.</p>
        <p>The Tour of California, which runs close to the Pacific Coast in February, is just two years old; the Tour of Missouri and a race from Montreal to Boston are new this year. Tours coming this spring and early summer are in Virginia, New Mexico, Nevada and Utah.</p>
        <p>In world competition, the Tour de Georgia is well placed to serve as a benchmark, said Jim Birrell, the race designer and director. It comes at midseason -- after the spring classics in Europe and before the Giro d'Italia and the Tour de France -- when riders should be at or near their best. And although sections like Brasstown Bald and Burkhalter Gap may sound tame compared with climbs through the Alps and the Pyrenees, riders can attest that the north Georgia mountains are daunting.</p>
        <p>Watching the tour isn't just about seeing the next Lance Armstrong without taking a money-sapping trip to Europe. Many fans travel with their bikes and, after racers pass, sample sections of the course themselves. Or they move ahead, parking cars remotely and cycling halfway up a mountain to find good spots to watch. They also go to festivals like the Taste of Thomaston, listen to bands and join scheduled amateur rides with names like Biking for Beans and Circle the Bald.</p>
        <p>The competitors start with a flat sprint to Macon from Peachtree City, 30 miles south of Atlanta. Then comes a 135-mile southeasterly push ending with the infamous Clocktower Climb: two-tenths of a mile with a pitch of 10 percent to 12 percent. Later, there's a day of climbing up long, narrow Lookout Mountain three times -- with a total elevation gain of 7,000 feet. (''There are no breaks,'' R.J. Wamsley, a recreational road cyclist who lives in the town of Lookout Mountain, said of the Burkhalter Gap ascent. ''It's one of the toughest climbs around.'')</p>
        <p>The most daunting leg of the tour runs to the top of 4,793-foot Brasstown Bald, the highest point in Georgia. As racers slow to about 18 miles an hour near the summit, cheering fans crowd the edge of the steep, winding forest road, some in costume (Elvis, the devil, Vikings and the pope are common). Finally, after a day of circling Stone Mountain, the largest exposed granite dome in North America, the competitors ride through Atlanta, where Champagne corks pop at the finish line.</p>
        <p>The course is reminiscent of some in Europe. But, as race organizers readily admit, the vibe is distinctly American. ''During the Tour de France, spectators drink fine wine from nearby vineyards and eat brie cheese,'' Mr. Birrell said. ''At the Tour de Georgia, expect beer and boiled peanuts.''</p>
        <p>DETAILS</p>
        <p>GEORGIA</p>
        <p>What: Tour de Georgia, beginning in Peachtree City; www.tourdegeorgia.com.</p>
        <p>When: April 16 to 22.</p>
        <p>VIRGINIA</p>
        <p>What: Tour of Virginia, western Virginia; www.tourofvirginia.com.</p>
        <p>When: April 24 to 29.</p>
        <p>NEW MEXICO</p>
        <p>What: Tour of the Gila, beginning in Silver City; www.tourofthegila.com.</p>
        <p>When: May 2 to 6.</p>
        <p>NEVADA</p>
        <p>What: Tour de Nez, Reno and Lake Tahoe; www.tourdenez.com.</p>
        <p>When: June 13 to 16.</p>
        <p>UTAH</p>
        <p>What: Tour of Utah, www.tourofutah.com.</p>
        <p>When: July 1 to 7.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 13, 2007, Friday  The Ahead column last Friday about the Tour de Georgia bicycle race misstated the status of cars in Peachtree City, a community on the bike race route. The city, a planned community where many residents drive golf carts on 85 miles of multiuse paths, also allows cars; they are not banned.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 13, 2007, Friday</p>
        <p>The Ahead column last Friday about the Tour de Georgia bicycle race misstated the status of cars in Peachtree City, a community on the bike race route. The city, a planned community where many residents drive golf carts on 85 miles of multiuse paths, also allows cars; they are not banned.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
