<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Freed Britons Are Back Home but Face Questions About Their Capture and Behavior</title>
    <meta content="06britain" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/06/world/europe/06britain.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838317"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyall, Sarah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iran</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E7DD173FF935A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="880" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Freed Britons Are Back Home but Face Questions About Their Capture and Behavior</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Freed Britons Are Back Home but Face Questions About Their Capture and Behavior</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH LYALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyall, Sarah</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, April 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>British marines and sailors held captive in Iran for nearly two weeks arrive back home; their carefully choreographed homecoming described; Britain's relief is tarnished by questions about how they behaved during their detention and why they had been captured in first place; 15 captives were repeatedly displayed on Iranian state television, sometimes looking relaxed and smiling; in several cases they confessed to and apologized for having trespassed on Iranian territorial waters; Prime Min Tony Blair, abandoning diplomatic language he used during crisis, becomes tough, almost antagonistic, as he speaks of possible links between Iran and terrorism in Iraq; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 15 British marines and sailors held captive in Iran for nearly two weeks arrived back home on Thursday. But Britain's relief at their safe return was tarnished by questions about how they behaved during their detention and why they had been captured in the first place.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Prime Minister Tony Blair abandoned the careful, diplomatic language he had used during the crisis. The captives safely en route to Britain, his tone on Thursday became tough, almost antagonistic, as he spoke of possible links between Iran and terrorism in Iraq.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Britain’s relief at the sailors’ and marines’ safe return was tarnished by questions about how they behaved during their detention.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The 15 British marines and sailors held captive in Iran for nearly two weeks arrived back home on Thursday. But Britain's relief at their safe return was tarnished by questions about how they behaved during their detention and why they had been captured in the first place.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Prime Minister Tony Blair abandoned the careful, diplomatic language he had used during the crisis. The captives safely en route to Britain, his tone on Thursday became tough, almost antagonistic, as he spoke of possible links between Iran and terrorism in Iraq.</p>
        <p>The homecoming was carefully choreographed.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, before their release, the seven marines and eight sailors were shown on television wearing outfits issued by the Iranians -- ill-fitting business suits for the men, and a head-scarf-and-trouser ensemble for the lone woman, Leading Seaman Faye Turney. But upon arrival at Heathrow airport, they were dressed in military uniforms the British had provided.</p>
        <p>Boarding two helicopters, they left for their base in Devon, where they are to be debriefed and to undergo medical and psychological checkups, said Air Chief Marshal Sir Jock Stirrup, the chief of the defense staff.</p>
        <p>Seized March 23 while conducting a routine operation in the disputed Shatt al-Arab waterway, just north of the Persian Gulf, the captives were repeatedly displayed on Iranian state television, sometimes looking relaxed and smiling. In several cases, they confessed to and apologized for having trespassed on Iranian territorial waters.</p>
        <p>The images were jarring, verging on the bizarre. At one point they lined up for handshakes and chats with President Mahmoud Ahmadinejad. The latest videotape showed the detainees sipping cups of tea, accepting goody bags of gifts and answering questions from Iranian journalists about things like whether Iran reminded them of Wales. Several appeared to go out of their way to thank the Iranians for releasing them.</p>
        <p>''The treatment has been great,'' Seaman Turney said. ''Thank you for letting us go. We apologize for our actions.''</p>
        <p>Defense Secretary Des Browne told the BBC that the captives ''acted with immense courage and dignity during the time that they have been detained and indeed presented before the media of the world.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, when Mr. Blair discussed relations with Iran, his tone was grim. Referring to the announcement that four British soldiers were killed on Thursday near Basra, Iraq, when a roadside bomb struck their armored personnel carrier, Mr. Blair pointedly said he was not holding Iran responsible. But he repeated charges that Iran had been linked to terrorism inside Iraq.</p>
        <p>''It is far too early to say the particular terrorist act that killed our forces was an act committed by terrorists who were backed by any elements of the Iranian regime, so I make no allegation,'' Mr. Blair told reporters outside 10 Downing Street. ''But the general picture, as I said before, is that there are elements, at least, of the Iranian regime that are backing, financing, arming, supporting terrorism in Iraq.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair reiterated the government's assertion that Britain had traded nothing for the detainees' freedom. Throughout what became a diplomatic stalemate, Britain insisted that the sailors and marines were in Iraqi waters on United Nations-mandated business. Iran contended that they had trespassed Iranian waterways and demanded that Britain apologize and never do it again -- an apology Britain does not appear to have made, at least publicly.</p>
        <p>The focus is now on the detainees. How, analysts are asking, did they come to be so vulnerable in a waterway they knew was disputed, at a time when the Iranians had been particularly jumpy? And were they coerced into confessing or did they speak voluntarily?</p>
        <p>On BBC radio, Mike Dewar, a retired army colonel who is a security expert, said the sailors and marines had not had proper protection.</p>
        <p>Christopher Dandeker, a professor of military sociology in the department of war studies at King's College London, said he would reserve judgment on the captives' behavior in Iran. ''I know many military people are concerned about the overly loquacious and positive statements made by the service personnel,'' he said via e-mail. ''But as yet we don't know what kinds of coercion were present before the 'hostages' made their TV statements.''</p>
        <p>Several members of the military said in interviews on Thursday that the captured Britons probably had not received a great deal of training in how to behave if captured.</p>
        <p>''I'd be surprised if they'd had a lot of in-depth training,'' said an officer in the army, who insisted on anonymity because he had not cleared the interview with his commanding officer. Before he served in Iraq, the officer said in a telephone interview, ''we had about half an hour briefing by some bored guy with slides, and he certainly wasn't envisaging the type of situation that they got into.''</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the Ministry of Defense said that the military offered ''basic captive training'' but would not elaborate.</p>
        <p>In The Daily Mail, the columnist Steven Glover compared the captives with those from other conflicts. ''I do not blame the hostages for their apparent willingness to confess and apologize,'' he wrote. ''But we had better be honest with ourselves. In no previous era -- not during World War II or Korea or Suez or the Falklands -- would British servicemen have behaved in such a manner.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
