<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unheralded American Pushes Elite In London</title>
    <meta content="23marathon" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/sports/othersports/23marathon.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070426T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842401"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MARATHON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Running</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E0DA173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="527" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unheralded American Pushes Elite In London</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Kenyan Wins London Marathon</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JESSICA STONE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stone, Jessica</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, April 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With less than five miles to go in the London Marathon on Sunday, the lead pack in the men's field comprised many of the world's best runners, including the defending champion, the world-record holder and the reigning New York City Marathon champion. But they were all a step or more behind Ryan Hall, an American making his marathon debut.</p>
        <p>Hall showed that he was capable of staying with the event's elite competitors, leading for almost 22 miles. Down the stretch, though, he drifted to seventh, yielding to a more predictable winner, Martin Lel of Kenya, who was runner-up to Felix Limo in a sprint finish last year. This time, Lel, who won in 2005, could not be caught, finishing in 2 hours 7 minutes 41 seconds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ryan Hall, an American upstart making his marathon debut, held his own but yielded down the stretech to a more predictable winner, Martin Lel of Kenya.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With less than five miles to go in the London Marathon on Sunday, the lead pack in the men's field comprised many of the world's best runners, including the defending champion, the world-record holder and the reigning New York City Marathon champion. But they were all a step or more behind Ryan Hall, an American making his marathon debut.</p>
        <p>Hall showed that he was capable of staying with the event's elite competitors, leading for almost 22 miles. Down the stretch, though, he drifted to seventh, yielding to a more predictable winner, Martin Lel of Kenya, who was runner-up to Felix Limo in a sprint finish last year. This time, Lel, who won in 2005, could not be caught, finishing in 2 hours 7 minutes 41 seconds.</p>
        <p>Another first-time marathoner, Abderrahim Goumri of Morocco, was three seconds behind Lel. Limo, a Kenyan, was three seconds behind Goumri in third.</p>
        <p>In the women's race, Zhou Chunxiu became the first Chinese runner to win in London, finishing in 2:20:38, comfortably ahead of Gete Wami of Ethiopia (2:21:45) and Constantina Tomescu-Dita of Romania (2:23:55).</p>
        <p>More than 36,000 runners took part in Sunday's race, and they had to endure temperatures well above 70 degrees.</p>
        <p>The men's race, on a fast course, had one of the strongest marathon fields ever. The runners included Paul Tergat of Kenya, the world-record holder in 2:04:55; Stefano Baldini of Italy, the reigning Olympic champion; Jaouad Gharib of Morocco, the two-time world champion; Marilson Gomes dos Santos of Brazil, the 2006 New York City Marathon winner; Khalid Khannouchi of the United States, the former world-record holder; and Haile Gebrselassie of Ethiopia, regarded as perhaps the greatest distance runner ever.</p>
        <p>Baldini, Khannouchi and Gebrselassie had dropped out by Mile 20, giving confidence to Hall, 24, a former cross-country and track standout at Stanford.</p>
        <p>Hall trains in Mammoth Lakes, Calif., with Deena Kastor, who set the women's American record here last year, and Meb Keflezighi, the Olympic silver medalist in Athens, who dropped out Sunday at Mile 10 with a blister.</p>
        <p>Hall hovered with the leaders until falling off the pace with a mile and a half to go. His time, 2:08:24, was an American record for a debut marathon. Alberto Salazar (1980, in New York) and Alan Culpepper (2002, in Chicago) had shared the record: 2:09:41. Hall's time was also the fifth fastest for an American. The better times were all run by Khannouchi.</p>
        <p>''I felt really comfortable,'' said Hall, whose breakthrough performance came in January in a half-marathon in Houston, where he ran 59:43, shattering the American record by 72 seconds. ''I just wanted to make it as far as I could with those guys.''</p>
        <p>For most of the race, it seemed as if ''those guys'' would cross the finish together. Even after Lel made his late move, Goumri and Limo were on his heels as he sprinted past the Houses of Parliament, looking over his shoulder to make sure he was home free.</p>
        <p>''I didn't know I was going to win because the race was very tactical,'' Lel said. ''I had to run with them all the way, and the finish was very quick.''</p>
        <p>MARATHON</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 26, 2007, Thursday  Because of an editing error, a sports article on Monday about the London Marathon referred incorrectly to the performance of Ryan Hall, an American making his marathon debut. He led the race near Mile 22; he was not the leader for almost 22 miles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 26, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, a sports article on Monday about the London Marathon referred incorrectly to the performance of Ryan Hall, an American making his marathon debut. He led the race near Mile 22; he was not the leader for almost 22 miles.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
