<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Smile, Say 'I Do,' and Punk the Wedding Party</title>
    <meta content="23stan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/arts/television/23stan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070430T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842361"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Broadcasting Co</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Kutcher, Ashton</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E6DA173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="926" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Smile, Say 'I Do,' and Punk the Wedding Party</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Smile, Say ‘I Do,’ and Punk the Wedding Party</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALESSANDRA STANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stanley, Alessandra</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rebecca Mead's ''Perfect Day: The Selling of the American Wedding'' is about to appear in bookstores, and it's about time. It is remarkable, even suspicious, that there have not been more investigations into the wedding industry in the vein of Jessica Mitford's 1963 expose of the burial business, ''The American Way of Death.''</p>
        <p>Last year American couples spent an average of about $27,000 to exchange vows, according to an online market research service (theweddingreport.com), and that figure does not include the honeymoon, engagement ring or bridal consultant. A wedding, unlike a funeral, is not necessarily a once-in-a-lifetime event. There is also a burgeoning market for second and third weddings, which includes Bride Again, a magazine aimed at ''encore brides,'' who seek an off-white look for their return trip to the altar: a triumph of taupe over experience.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>One crashed wedding can be entertaining, but a steady stream could wear thin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rebecca Mead's ''Perfect Day: The Selling of the American Wedding'' is about to appear in bookstores, and it's about time. It is remarkable, even suspicious, that there have not been more investigations into the wedding industry in the vein of Jessica Mitford's 1963 expose of the burial business, ''The American Way of Death.''</p>
        <p>Last year American couples spent an average of about $27,000 to exchange vows, according to an online market research service (theweddingreport.com), and that figure does not include the honeymoon, engagement ring or bridal consultant. A wedding, unlike a funeral, is not necessarily a once-in-a-lifetime event. There is also a burgeoning market for second and third weddings, which includes Bride Again, a magazine aimed at ''encore brides,'' who seek an off-white look for their return trip to the altar: a triumph of taupe over experience.</p>
        <p>And that makes the state of the marriage industry all the more worrisome. The fuss, folly and high cost of weddings in the United States suggests a civilization out of whack, if not in decline. Sadly weddings increasingly seem mass produced and impersonal, despite or because of all the customized frills and bridezilla flourishes: metallic wedding cakes, bungee-jumping groomsmen and Disney princess brides. (The Disney Company has teamed up with bridal designer Kirstie Kelly to produce wedding gowns inspired by favorite Disney princesses; Cruella De Vil mother-of-the-bride outfits cannot be far behind.) Events planners, bridal consultants and the vast armies of wedding-centric television shows, magazines and Web sites have served to streamline tastes, good and bad.</p>
        <p>For many guests a wedding is less a joy than an ordeal, something to get through, like PBS pledge drives or Lyme disease. That's why there is something poignant about ''The Real Wedding Crashers,'' a reality show that begins tonight on NBC: Some couples are so desperate to make their ceremony memorable and distinctive that they deliberately sabotage it.</p>
        <p>Borrowing the concept from the 2005 hit movie that starred Owen Wilson and Vince Vaughn, ''The Real Wedding Crashers'' sends a team of five actors to perform hidden camera pranks on families and friends as they prepare for the big day. The brides and grooms are in on the joke, which waters down the shock value. In the premiere the pranks include letting the best man think he has ruined the bride's dress and staging a mock arrest of the groom and his friends for smoking an illegal Cuban cigar the night before the wedding. The minister -- one of the actors -- receives a call on his cellphone in the middle of the service. ''It's in the medicine cabinet,'' he hisses into the phone as the guests stare, slack-jawed. ''Top shelf.''</p>
        <p>NBC has become part of the marriage industrial complex. Couples compete to win an all-extravagances-paid wedding on the regular ''Today'' show feature ''Today Throws a Wedding.'' This new series is also a marketing tool, one that takes the process a little further, but not too far. ''The Real Wedding Crashers'' is not seeking to provide social satire, nor is it very mean-spirited. Ashton Kutcher, a creator of the practical joke show ''Punk'd'' on MTV, is an executive producer, and the tone is careful and carefully all-in-good-fun: the actors actually wink at the camera in the middle of a fake crisis.</p>
        <p>The appeal of hidden camera shows is not really the mark's reaction; most people are surprisingly silent and passive when faced with the weird and the unexpected. It's the relief and laughter that explode when the joke is revealed and the masks are pulled off. Here, when an announcer says, ''This wedding has been crashed,'' guests, relatives, bridesmaids laugh, exclaim and gush with the kind of giddiness and good feeling that weddings are expected to evoke, and too often do not.</p>
        <p>Weddings are supposed to release emotions but too often leave guests cold and a bit bored. ''The Real Wedding Crashers'' claims to provide something ''a couple will never forget and their guests will remember forever.'' There are other motives besides excitement. Couples also receive a free honeymoon and a nationally televised wedding video.</p>
        <p>It's still not entirely clear why Derek and Jonnie, the likeable and laid-back couple in the premiere episode, agreed to allow a reality show to infiltrate and undermine their ceremony, though that they both come from Las Vegas, the land of Elvis-impersonating ministers, may explain a lot.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless they and their friends and relatives are too nice and too humble to make the wedding crashers really fun for viewers.</p>
        <p>The pranks would be more amusing if pulled on a more pompous and pretentious wedding party. But people who want to be on ''The Real Wedding Crashers'' are a self-selecting subset, and that is reflected in the advertisers. Priscilla of Boston is not a sponsor; Planet Hollywood Resort and Casino is.</p>
        <p>A little of this kind of excitement goes a long way. One crashed wedding can be entertaining, but a steady stream could wear thin. ''Punk'd,'' as did ''Candid Camera'' before it, constantly changes locations and social groups, bringing a broad variety of marks to the same basic prank. Weddings tend to all look alike, no matter how personalized the party favors. Too many crashed weddings can become a crashing bore.</p>
        <p>The Real Wedding Crashers</p>
        <p>NBC, tonight at 10, Eastern and Pacific times; 9, Central time.</p>
        <p>Ashton Kutcher, Jason Goldberg, Karey Burke, Rich Meehan, Jon Kroll and Jim Rosenthal, executive producers. A production of Katalyst Films &amp; Television and New Line Television.</p>
        <p>WITH: Steve Byrne, Ben Gleib, Catherine Reitman, Gareth Reynolds and Desi Lydic.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 30, 2007, Monday  Because of an editing error, a television review last Monday about ''The Real Wedding Crashers,'' on NBC, omitted the first word of the title of a forthcoming book on weddings by Rebecca Mead. The title is ''One Perfect Day: The Selling of the American Wedding.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 30, 2007, Monday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, a television review last Monday about ''The Real Wedding Crashers,'' on NBC, omitted the first word of the title of a forthcoming book on weddings by Rebecca Mead. The title is ''One Perfect Day: The Selling of the American Wedding.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
