<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Payroll Is Down But Tension Is Rising</title>
    <meta content="23roberts" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842467"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Selena Roberts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E0D8173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="847" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Payroll Is Down But Tension Is Rising</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Daisuke Matsuzaka was all theirs. Red Sox devotees entered Fenway Park last night with martial arts headbands and Dice-K T-shirts and red K's on poster board as if to advertise they had something the Yankees did not: a secret weapon, a mystical man and the catch of the off-season.</p>
        <p>His debut against the Yankees wasn't fable material. ''Part of it is facing that lineup,'' Red Sox Manager Terry Francona said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Daisuke Matsuzaka was all theirs. Red Sox devotees entered Fenway Park last night with martial arts headbands and Dice-K T-shirts and red K's on poster board as if to advertise they had something the Yankees did not: a secret weapon, a mystical man and the catch of the off-season.</p>
        <p>His debut against the Yankees wasn't fable material. ''Part of it is facing that lineup,'' Red Sox Manager Terry Francona said.</p>
        <p>Matsuzaka gave up six runs over seven innings in a 7-6 Red Sox victory, but he did satiate the Boston cravings for captivation with seven strikeouts. Throughout a mild evening, Dice-K was alternately mesmerizing and mediocre, with one loopy, indescribable pitch followed by a flat fastball. The latter hardly seemed to matter to a crowd that seemed content with a double allowed to Doug Mientkiewicz as long as Matsuzaka didn't flinch at Alex Rodriguez.</p>
        <p>He tested A-Rod's nerve on a pitch high and tight, hitting Rodriguez in the first inning and then coming back to strike him out twice. The Fenway fans cheered Dice-K's wow factor and hardly noticed his wobbles.</p>
        <p>All they knew was that the most intriguing pitcher in baseball, a Japanese folk hero with a cagey smile, eight bedeviling pitches and comic timing in his motion -- he waits a beat and then delivers a screwball zinger -- had not been swiped by the sharks in pinstripes.</p>
        <p>The Red Sox had not lost the love of their lives to The Boss. They landed Dice-K fair and square. The Yankees made a conservative bid of about $33 million for the right to negotiate with Matsuzaka while Boston dug deep into its lobster pots to fork over $51 million.</p>
        <p>The final price tag on Dice-K of $103 million didn't guarantee anything. But the prospect of wizardry is for the Red Sox to fantasize about. Not the Yankees.</p>
        <p>Coveting is an unnatural emotion for the Yankee faithful. But given the Yankees' history of getting what they want when they want it, it would stand to reason if, in a wistful moment, a fan with a Bronx accent asked, ''Why couldn't Dice-K be ours?''</p>
        <p>The Yankees have scaled down their Neiman Marcus tastes to Macy's. The old strategy of impulse shopping, of superstar talent stashes, wasn't working anymore. The pale man who positioned himself under the green accountant's visor was Brian Cashman.</p>
        <p>But how much tolerance is there for a Yankee franchise in a philosophical transition? This isn't about public pressure, but tension inside the club.</p>
        <p>How is Joe Torre holding up? You can see fissures.</p>
        <p>Torre has been understandably celebrated as a manager with the soothing voice akin to ocean waves, capable of calming even the most neurotic superstars.</p>
        <p>But the smaller his cache of go-to talents -- where are those second-tier stars to stand in for the injured marquee players? -- the more his game-day managing is open for inspection. On Friday night, he looked oddly desperate to grab a game in April when he broke his vow to save Mariano Rivera for ninth-inning work by inserting him in the eighth against Boston.</p>
        <p>Rivera melted down and the game slipped away. Last night, Torre let Andy Pettitte pitch in relief -- the second time he has put his starter at risk this season. The bullpen isn't trustworthy, but Torre, in misusing Rivera, in making Pettitte vulnerable, is clutching at sentimental choices, proving he has yet to accept the new math of the Yankees.</p>
        <p>Rivera is averse to Thriftville, also. He felt betrayed when he was not offered a contract extension in the off-season as per policy in the era of Cashman autonomy. Certainly, Rivera hasn't lost it -- his reservoir of greatness is deeper than two blown saves -- but it is not so far-fetched to wonder if his confidence would be more resilient if he had the security of a new deal.</p>
        <p>A contract is a contract to Cashman. This includes the one with an escape hatch belonging to Rodriguez. The Yankees declined trade offers for A-Rod in the winter, but they could lose him for nothing if Rodriguez decides to opt out of his deal and exit. Imagine if his ridiculous tear picks up again. Imagine the price escalation.</p>
        <p>Controlling his destiny has liberated Rodriguez. It's almost as if his pace has been part of an in-your-face final lap around New York. Could he end up with the Red Sox after all? In the past, the Red Sox routinely watched players they had made offers to go to the Yankees for one reason or another. Johnny Damon was one of them. In his case, the Yankees offered a more lucrative deal than Boston.</p>
        <p>''I'm in a much better place,'' Damon said.</p>
        <p>The Yankee world is a different place from when Damon arrived. Now there is more bean-counting, less disposable income. The Red Sox are reflecting the old Yankee way.</p>
        <p>They looked at Dice-K last night, with flashbulbs popping from his first strike, and didn't regret the extravagance. He could have been yours, Yankees. Can you tolerate the change in philosophical direction? Can you be patient with the transition?</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: selenasports@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: selenasports@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
