<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mozart, Sunny to Savage, Played by a Youthful Ensemble</title>
    <meta content="23verb" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/arts/music/23verb.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070426T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842382"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Carnegie Hall</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Vengerov, Maxim</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E3DA173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="400" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mozart, Sunny to Savage, Played by a Youthful Ensemble</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mozart, Sunny to Savage, Played by a Youthful Ensemble</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIVIEN SCHWEITZER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schweitzer, Vivien</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A number of fine training orchestras, including the East-West Divan Orchestra, the New World Symphony, the Oberlin Conservatory Orchestra and iPalpiti, have recently played at Carnegie Hall. On Thursday night it was the turn of the UBS Verbier Festival Chamber Orchestra, an offshoot of the UBS Verbier Festival Orchestra, whose members are aged 17 to 29. The violinist Maxim Vengerov performed as soloist and conducted works by Shostakovich and Mozart.</p>
        <p>Training orchestras often play with outstanding technique and musicianship, and (no doubt because they haven't played the standard repertory innumerable times) a joy and passion sometimes missing from concerts by established orchestras. The youthful ensembles also frequently have more time to rehearse than most professional orchestras, which is certainly necessary to play Mozart well.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Verbier played Mozart very well, with stately tempos and a warmly romantic sound.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A number of fine training orchestras, including the East-West Divan Orchestra, the New World Symphony, the Oberlin Conservatory Orchestra and iPalpiti, have recently played at Carnegie Hall. On Thursday night it was the turn of the UBS Verbier Festival Chamber Orchestra, an offshoot of the UBS Verbier Festival Orchestra, whose members are aged 17 to 29. The violinist Maxim Vengerov performed as soloist and conducted works by Shostakovich and Mozart.</p>
        <p>Training orchestras often play with outstanding technique and musicianship, and (no doubt because they haven't played the standard repertory innumerable times) a joy and passion sometimes missing from concerts by established orchestras. The youthful ensembles also frequently have more time to rehearse than most professional orchestras, which is certainly necessary to play Mozart well.</p>
        <p>And the Verbier played Mozart (which it has recently recorded for EMI) very well indeed, with stately tempos and a warmly romantic sound, a world apart from the fleet, crisp approach now often heard. The program opened with a lilting, graceful performance of his youthful Violin Concerto No. 2 in D (K. 211), with Mr. Vengerov as soloist and conductor. He spun out long, singing phrases and conducted with his bow when not playing.</p>
        <p>Then like a mood swing, the Verbier plunged from the sunny high of the lighthearted Mozart to the paranoid despair of Shostakovich's Chamber Symphony (Op. 110a), Rudolf Barshai's transcription of Shostakovich's String Quartet No. 8. It was an ideally savage performance, bristling with seething tension.</p>
        <p>After intermission Mr. Vengerov announced from the stage that as he had recently injured his right arm, it was ''a little tough'' for him to play. So the violinist Mayumi Seiler was the fine substitute in Mozart's Sinfonia Concertante in E flat, which features solo violin and viola in a dialogue like that of a couple who speak in unison and finish each other's sentences. The excellent violist was Lawrence Power, who played with a lovely tone.</p>
        <p>The ensemble concluded the program with a sweet-toned rendition of Mozart's Symphony No. 29 in A (which replaced the originally scheduled Violin Concerto No. 4). When conducting Mr. Vengerov sometimes flailed like a drowning man, but his gestures were clear, and the musicians responded magnetically to him.</p>
        <p>The Verbier's performance was yet another reminder that perhaps the grim prophecies rattled off with tiresome regularity about the future of classical music will likely remain fictional rather than factual.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 26, 2007, Thursday  A music review on Monday about the UBS Verbier Festival Chamber Orchestra, at Carnegie Hall, misstated the name of another training orchestra that recently played there. It is the West-Eastern Divan Orchestra, not the East-West Divan Orchestra.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 26, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>A music review on Monday about the UBS Verbier Festival Chamber Orchestra, at Carnegie Hall, misstated the name of another training orchestra that recently played there. It is the West-Eastern Divan Orchestra, not the East-West Divan Orchestra.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
