<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After 44 Years, Pitcher Gains A Partner in the Record Book</title>
    <meta content="23pitcher" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842462"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E1D8173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="398" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After 44 Years, Pitcher Gains A Partner in the Record Book</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, April 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Paul Foytack was watching the N.B.A. playoffs Sunday night, but he switched to the Yankees-Red Sox game during a commercial. He saw Manny Ramírez hit a home run before shifting back to the basketball game. That is how Foytack missed history. History that he was a part of.</p>
        <p>By the time Foytack went back to watching baseball, Chase Wright of the Yankees had allowed three more home runs to become only the second pitcher to surrender four consecutive homers. The first was Foytack.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Paul Foytack was watching the N.B.A. playoffs Sunday night, but he switched to the Yankees-Red Sox game during a commercial. He saw Manny Ramírez hit a home run before shifting back to the basketball game. That is how Foytack missed history. History that he was a part of.</p>
        <p>By the time Foytack went back to watching baseball, Chase Wright of the Yankees had allowed three more home runs to become only the second pitcher to surrender four consecutive homers. The first was Foytack.</p>
        <p>''I saw the left fielder hit one, but then I went back to the basketball,'' Foytack said in a telephone interview from his home in Spring Hill, Tenn. ''I missed the last three. How about that?''</p>
        <p>When Foytack was with the Los Angeles Angels in 1963, he volunteered to pitch in relief two days after a seven-inning start because of a doubleheader. Foytack was summoned July 31 against the Cleveland Indians, and he allowed homers to Woodie Held; pitcher Pedro Ramos; Tito Francona, whose son Terry now manages the Red Sox; and Larry Brown. Those four Indians combined for a mere 35 homers that season.</p>
        <p>''I never thought that much about it,'' Foytack said. ''After I was told that it was a record, I said, 'Well, I finally got in the record book.' ''</p>
        <p>While Foytack, now 76, said he was never bothered by giving up four homers in a row, he expressed concern for Wright. Foytack, who was nicked in the second-to-last year of his career, said he planned to write a letter to Wright and mail it Monday.</p>
        <p>''I kind of feel bad for the kid because he's young,'' Foytack said. ''I'm going to tell him that these things happen and that he shouldn't let it get to him.''</p>
        <p>After Foytack was offered a Yankees e-mail address to get his message to Wright quicker, he said, ''I don't even know how to turn on the computer.''</p>
        <p>Foytack, 76, was 86-87 with a 4.14 earned run average in 11 years with the Detroit Tigers and the Angels. In addition to the four-homer game, Foytack also gave up Roger Maris's first homer of 1961. That was the year Maris hit 61, which was the record until 1998.</p>
        <p>''I told Roger he should have sent me $400 a month after that,'' Foytack said. ''If it wasn't for me, he wouldn't have hit 61.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
