<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>South Africa vs. Itself, in Race to Get Ready for World Cup</title>
    <meta content="23worldcup" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/world/africa/23worldcup.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842396"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="JOHANNESBURG JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">World Cup (Soccer)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Cup (Soccer)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">South Africa</location>
        <org class="online_producer">FIFA</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DA173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1072" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>South Africa vs. Itself, in Race to Get Ready for World Cup</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">South Africa vs. Itself, in Race to Get Ready for World Cup</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHARON LAFRANIERE</byline>
      <dateline>JOHANNESBURG, April 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The World Cup of soccer is still three years away. But in South Africa, the site of the 2010 games, it already feels disturbingly close at hand.</p>
        <p>A giant race is on to renovate airports, build a high-speed rail link from Johannesburg's airport to the suburbs and erect or renovate stadiums here and in eight other cities. Thousands of new police officers must be hired and trained; hundreds of buses purchased; an untold number of bed-and-breakfast inns rated and registered. It is at once nerve-racking and exhilarating, South Africa's own slow-motion, nail-biting contest with itself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For South Africa, hosting the World Cup of soccer in 2010 is a chance to erase a whole host of stereotypes about Africa and its people.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The World Cup of soccer is still three years away. But in South Africa, the site of the 2010 games, it already feels disturbingly close at hand.</p>
        <p>A giant race is on to renovate airports, build a high-speed rail link from Johannesburg's airport to the suburbs and erect or renovate stadiums here and in eight other cities. Thousands of new police officers must be hired and trained; hundreds of buses purchased; an untold number of bed-and-breakfast inns rated and registered. It is at once nerve-racking and exhilarating, South Africa's own slow-motion, nail-biting contest with itself.</p>
        <p>''It is a wonderful opportunity, and I am sure South Africa will come out of it well,'' Paul Browning, a transportation consultant, said in a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>''We also have the opportunity to fall flat on our face,'' he quickly added.</p>
        <p>As the first Africans to stage one of the world's most popular sporting events, people here are exquisitely aware of their chance not merely to burnish their image as the continent's leader, but also to erase a whole host of stereotypes about Africa and its people.</p>
        <p>They insist that they will be ready -- and in general, officials with the Fédération Internationale de Football Association, or FIFA, say they are pleased with the state of preparations.</p>
        <p>By at least some measures, however, South Africa is cutting it perilously close. In early January, Joseph S. Blatter, FIFA's president, complained that the margin allotted for delays in stadium construction had been eaten up even before building began.</p>
        <p>Work has now started on all five new stadiums, after a series of legal challenges and budget problems. Renovations of five existing stadiums are either under way or imminent. Still, South Africa's organizers say that the timetable is so tight that even a three-week rain delay could wreak havoc.</p>
        <p>Building a modern transportation system almost from scratch in three years may be even more difficult, analysts say. Then there are the dauntingly high crime rates and the fact that no one is sure how many beds actually exist at the bed and breakfast inns on which many fans must rely.</p>
        <p>Like first-time Broadway producers, South Africa's organizers veer between euphoria and quiet terror. ''I don't think I will sleep well for the next two-and-a-half to three years, until the last stadium is finished,'' Danny Jordaan, the chief executive officer of the South African organizing committee, said in an interview.</p>
        <p>FIFA departed from its norms -- and perhaps took a gamble -- when it awarded the 2010 World Cup to South Africa in 2004. Not since Chile was the host of the games in 1962 has soccer's governing body chosen a nation as underdeveloped as this one, according to Econometrix, an economic analysis firm here.</p>
        <p>And never before has South Africa undertaken such a huge event. The 350,000 anticipated visitors may be one-tenth the number that descended on Germany for the 2006 games. But they are 10 times the crowd that showed up for the 1995 Rugby World Cup, the 2002 World Summit on Development or the 2003 Cricket World Cup held in South Africa.</p>
        <p>Rumors have flown that FIFA was reserving nations like Australia or Brazil as backups should preparations here falter. FIFA executives vehemently deny that. Plan A, B and C ''is called South Africa,'' Mr. Blatter said in January.</p>
        <p>Beyond sheer determination, South Africans also have some formidable assets. Their government is adept at planning and economically flush enough to muster more than $2 billion for stadiums, infrastructure, the police and other needs. The corporate world has pledged $3.5 billion in sponsorships -- more than any previous World Cup, Mr. Jordaan said.</p>
        <p>Nor are South Africans exactly pikers at entertaining guests. Nearly a quarter million foreigners flew to South Africa last December alone, a 13 percent increase over December 2005 and a sign of the nation's rise as a global tourism destination.</p>
        <p>Although cricket and rugby are more popular than soccer here, many South Africans see the World Cup as a font of national pride and, perhaps, national profit. Surveys show three-fourths of medium to large businesses expect to gain financially from the games. Bed and breakfast inns are springing up like acacia trees.</p>
        <p>Even ordinary citizens are caught up in the spell: Early this month, organizers warned families living near the Soweto stadium not to buy washing machines in hopes of earning money by laundering players' jerseys, because each player will arrive with at least 30 clean ones.</p>
        <p>''The World Cup is empowering our country, our people,'' said Jofta Rishoto, 41, as he watched a soccer match broadcast recently at a Soweto bar. ''You are going to see miracles.''</p>
        <p>Still, a commuter system suitable for visitors simply doesn't exist. Most South Africans travel on battered minibuses that belch smoke, stop at random intersections, follow near-indecipherable schedules and flout traffic laws with élan. Nor are the trains, typically rundown and poorly policed, an option.</p>
        <p>The government is promising a major overhaul that will include 600 new luxury or semiluxury intercity buses, 10,000 new minibuses and 60 new trains. But Mr. Browning, the transportation specialist, said officials needed to move beyond paper. ''We have got wonderful plans. The question is, can we put them into action?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>To transport spectators between cities, organizers are counting heavily on the nation's three low-cost airlines, although some analysts say the airlines would need to acquire many more planes.</p>
        <p>Keeping the fans safe could be as tough as moving them about. South Africa suffers a daily average of 50 murders, 700 grievous assaults and 356 aggravated robberies. ''Who is going to be interested in spending a significant amount of money coming here on holiday to have a good time when you are concerned about the possibility of getting hurt?'' Eric M. Bost, the American ambassador here, said last November.</p>
        <p>The police force, continuing a seven-year steady buildup, is now hiring at least 11,000 new officers each year, officials said. But the commissioner, Jackie Selebi, is prone to fouls.</p>
        <p>Last month he proposed setting up dedicated red-light districts where prostitution and public drinking would be tolerated during the World Cup, as he said they were in Germany.</p>
        <p>To organizers, he missed a crucial point: Germany is not South Africa, with its raging AIDS epidemic.</p>
        <p>Mr. Browning says planners must bear in mind such distinctions. If they approach the games as cold-eyed realists, he said, getting ready ''will be difficult, but it will just be possible.''</p>
        <p>JOHANNESBURG JOURNAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
