<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Israel's Finance Minister Steps Down During Investigation</title>
    <meta content="23mideast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/world/middleeast/23mideast.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842421"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Embezzlement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embezzlement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Israel</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE4D9173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="856" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Israel's Finance Minister Steps Down During Investigation</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Israel’s Finance Minister Steps Down During Investigation</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ISABEL KERSHNER</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, April 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Israel's finance minister, Abraham Hirchson, said Sunday that he was leaving office for three months pending the outcome of a police investigation against him. The investigation involves suspicions that he embezzled funds before he joined the government, an Israeli police spokesman said.</p>
        <p>Ehud Olmert, Israel's prime minister, announced that he would temporarily take over the finance portfolio for Mr. Hirchson, who is a close political ally.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The inquiry involves suspicions that Israel’s finance minister embezzled funds before he joined the government, the police said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Israel's finance minister, Abraham Hirchson, said Sunday that he was leaving office for three months pending the outcome of a police investigation against him. The investigation involves suspicions that he embezzled funds before he joined the government, an Israeli police spokesman said.</p>
        <p>Ehud Olmert, Israel's prime minister, announced that he would temporarily take over the finance portfolio for Mr. Hirchson, who is a close political ally.</p>
        <p>Also on Sunday, Azmi Bishara, an Israeli Arab lawmaker and leader of the Arab nationalist party Balad, resigned from Parliament in a letter sent via the Israeli Embassy in Cairo. His resignation came one day before a court-imposed silence on the details of a police investigation against him was due to expire.</p>
        <p>Mr. Olmert's government has been dogged by investigations and scandals over the past year, contributing to a dive in approval ratings that are now in the single digits. Mr. Olmert himself is facing numerous investigations, including one involving his role in the sale of the government's controlling share in a bank when he was finance minister. Mr. Olmert's former justice minister, Haim Ramon, was found guilty in January of indecent behavior for kissing a soldier against her will.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hirchson has been under investigation since the end of January and is suspected of embezzling from a nonprofit group associated with the National Workers' Labor Federation in 2003, the police spokesman, Micky Rosenfeld, said. Mr. Hirchson had served as chairman of the labor federation and its health fund.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hirchson denies any wrongdoing, his lawyer, Yaakov Weinrot, told Army Radio on Sunday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hirchson issued a statement on Sunday afternoon saying that his ''public responsibility'' and his ''conscience'' were the deciding factors in his decision to suspend himself, ''as well as the recognition that my family members are the ones being harmed.''</p>
        <p>The resignation of Mr. Bishara, the Israeli Arab lawmaker, followed a period of feverish speculation in Israel about his whereabouts and intentions. Mr. Bishara, whose party has three seats in the 120-seat Parliament, has been abroad under mysterious circumstances since early April. Until last week, a court order prevented publication of the fact that he was under investigation.</p>
        <p>While not revealing anything about the investigation, Mr. Bishara told Al Jazeera Arabic television on April 15 that he had been questioned by the police twice before leaving the country. Mr. Bishara, whose aides have said he is a victim of a political witch hunt, told the Arabic news media that his options were to become ''a martyr, a prisoner or an exile.''</p>
        <p>He is being investigated by the International Crimes Unit of the police, which deals with serious crimes committed either at home or abroad, the police spokesman said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bishara has been interrogated by the police in the past, after visiting Syria, a country that does not have normal diplomatic relations with Israel. Israeli critics consider his political positions a threat to the future character of the country; Mr. Bishara rejects Israel's definition of itself as a Jewish state and has called for it to become a ''state of all its citizens.'' That idea has gained popularity in recent years among the Arab minority, which makes up almost 20 percent of Israel's population, and among Israel's Arab political and intellectual leadership.</p>
        <p>Shortly after Israel's war against Hezbollah in Lebanon last summer, Mr. Bishara and two other Balad members of Parliament traveled to Syria and Lebanon to express their solidarity with the other side. Mr. Bishara had openly opposed Israel's decision to go to war. According to Syrian news reports at the time, he warned Damascus of what he said were Israeli plans to attack Syria in order to restore Israel's deterrent capability.</p>
        <p>The Israeli daily newspaper Maariv reported in September that Mr. Bishara had ''violated a relatively new law forbidding travel to an enemy country without the approval of the minister of the interior.'' The paper said that the attorney general was considering opening a criminal investigation.</p>
        <p>An official in Jerusalem familiar with the allegations against Mr. Bishara suggested that the investigation that had apparently prompted his resignation was not connected with the trip to Syria and Lebanon.</p>
        <p>Although the court-ordered silence about the investigation of Mr. Bishara was due to expire on Monday, the court on Sunday extended the order until Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Separately, Israeli troops killed two militants in the West Bank city of Nablus during an operation to arrest them early Sunday morning, Israeli security officials said. The security officials said the two had died in an exchange of fire, and that one, Amin Lubadeh, was a leading bomb maker associated with a militia affiliated with Fatah.</p>
        <p>Palestinian medical officials also confirmed the death of a Palestinian youth, Karim Zahran, 16, who was shot by Israeli troops on Sunday in a village northeast of Ramallah. According to an Israeli Army spokesman, soldiers had been confronted by dozens of Palestinians, ''some of whom were holding firebombs and knives.''</p>
        <p>Up to nine Palestinians died in an upsurge of Israeli-Palestinian violence over the weekend. A Hamas spokesman in Gaza, Fawzi Barhoum, urged the Palestinian factions to unite and use ''all means to retaliate'' against Israel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
