<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Quiet Weekend at Virginia Tech, Reminders of a Tragedy and Hope for the Future</title>
    <meta content="23vatech" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/us/23vatech.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842438"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cho Seung-Hui</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EED9173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1083" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Quiet Weekend at Virginia Tech, Reminders of a Tragedy and Hope for the Future</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Virginia Tech Struggles to Recover From Shootings</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN URBINA and MANNY FERNANDEZ; Reporting was contributed by Sarah Abruzzese and Christine Hauser in Blacksburg; Suevon Lee in Centreville, Va.; and Alicia C. Shepard in Washington, Va.</byline>
      <dateline>BLACKSBURG, Va., April 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A girl in an orange and maroon bikini basked in the sun less than 20 feet from the Virginia Tech dorm in which one of the worst massacres in American history had begun.</p>
        <p>A group of international students gathered for dinner downtown here to escape a campus emptied as many of their American classmates went home to try to heal with the aid of family.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Virginia Tech was quiet, sunny, sad and playful over the weekend, as the campus tried to move forward.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A girl in an orange and maroon bikini basked in the sun less than 20 feet from the Virginia Tech dorm in which one of the worst massacres in American history had begun.</p>
        <p>A group of international students gathered for dinner downtown here to escape a campus emptied as many of their American classmates went home to try to heal with the aid of family.</p>
        <p>A mother slathered suntan lotion on her toddler as they watched a college baseball game only blocks from where students crowded around a coffin and struggled to find the right way to talk about a dead friend.</p>
        <p>''She was a great person,'' a young man named Chris said of Austin Michelle Cloyd, a freshman killed during French class in last Monday's massacre. ''She is a great person,'' he said, restating his thought.</p>
        <p>The Virginia Tech campus was quiet, sunny, sad and playful this weekend. On parts of campus, a hush fell as most administrators, professors and journalists left, leaving behind an awkward mix of painful reminders and signs of the struggle to return to normal.</p>
        <p>Norris Hall, where 30 of the 32 killings occurred, has become a somber spectacle. A line of motorcycles and cars moved slowly on Sunday around the Drill Field, in front of the hall where memorials of flowers, candles and signs were erected.</p>
        <p>The chief of the campus police, Wendell Flinchum, posed for photographs with well-wishers not far from a woman wearing a placard that said, ''Jesus Loves You.''</p>
        <p>Alumni clad in orange and maroon, the university's colors, huddled under a white tent for a picnic on Saturday, while the campus bookstore struggled to handle the surge in demand for Virginia Tech gear.</p>
        <p>Plywood had been erected to seal off the area of the dorm where Mr. Cho claimed his first victim.</p>
        <p>And pastors strained in their Sunday sermons to make sense of the senseless. ''There is good, and there is hope because we all know that God's love prevails,'' the Rev. Susan Verbrugge told the several hundred parishioners who gathered for services at the Blacksburg Presbyterian Church.</p>
        <p>Ms. Verbrugge recounted breaking through the previous week's numbness as she stopped on a morning walk and found herself yelling at the mountains and at God. Though her shouts were initially met with silence, she said, she soon was reassured by the simplest of things, the chirping of birds.</p>
        <p>''God was doing something about the world,'' she said. ''Starting with my own heart, I could see good.''</p>
        <p>In Centreville, Va., where the gunman Seung-Hui Cho was reared, the Korean community grappled with feelings of shame and grief.</p>
        <p>''Part of it is that we are feeling shame because he is Korean,'' said Myung Sub Chung, pastor of the Young Saeng Korean Presbyterian Church about a mile and a half from the house of Mr. Cho's family. ''Mainly, we are angry because he is the gunman.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Chung counseled his parishioners to spend more time with their children and not to overlook the spiritual part of life. He added that the tragedy had struck close to home for him because his son graduated from high school in the same class as Mr. Cho, and his daughter was a close friend of one of his victims.</p>
        <p>Classes resume here on Monday, and while professors try to find a sensitive way to shift the discussion back toward course work, investigators continue trying to solve the mystery of Mr. Cho's motive.</p>
        <p>Much of the investigators' attention is focused on the computer and cellphone of the woman thought to have been the first of Mr. Cho's victims. Police officials are hoping to see if he might have known the woman, Emily Jane Hilscher.</p>
        <p>Investigators are also trying to obtain records related to e-mail and eBay accounts that Mr. Cho might have used to buy magazine clips for one of his guns, evidence that could help them fill in the extent of his premeditation.</p>
        <p>Memorial services were held in Blacksburg and across the country this weekend for at least 11 victims, with more scheduled for this week.</p>
        <p>In Washington, Va., on Saturday, a flock of white doves was released in memory of Ms. Hilscher, an 18-year-old freshman from Woodville, Va.</p>
        <p>''She'd rather wear jeans than a dress, drive a truck than a sports car, clean a stall than her room and visit the stables than the mall,'' said Ms. Hilscher's sister, Erica, 21.</p>
        <p>On campus, the weekend was especially difficult for the Virginia Tech's 2,100 international students, many of whom were stranded far from their families as other students returned home. Many of the international students also spoke of exhaustion after having suddenly become spokespeople for their communities and news providers to their countries.</p>
        <p>At times, their burden was unbearable.</p>
        <p>One Korean student, a freshman, locked himself away in his dorm room for much of the week and through the weekend to avoid reporters and other students, a university official said.</p>
        <p>An engineering student, Rhondy Rahardja, 23, from Jakarta, Indonesia, fought back tears as he told of the guilt he felt having told people back home in the chaotic first hours after the shootings that all the university's Indonesian students had survived, when in fact one -- Partahi Mamora Lumbantoruan, a 34-year-old graduate student -- had died.</p>
        <p>''That's why I haven't really slept much,'' Mr. Rahardja said. ''We've been working hard to process his belongings, so we went to his apartment packing his stuff and then go through the process of expediting the body to Indonesia.''</p>
        <p>Healing has been hastened in part by a spike in school spirit.</p>
        <p>At the Campus Emporium on North Main Street here, workers struggled to handle the backlog of 400 orders for Virginia Tech coffee mugs, footballs, teddy bears, clothing and other gear. On campus, the University Bookstore sold a season's supply of VT lapel pins in two days last week.</p>
        <p>The chants, banners and slogans typically associated with Virginia Tech sports have gained a more emotional currency. At a convocation the day after the shootings, the rousing student chants filled Cassell Coliseum. The nickname for the university's athletic teams, Hokies, has become a kind of shorthand for a unity that many students said they felt. ''After what happened, we chanted, and at that moment, I really felt like I'm a Hokie,'' said Ingrid Ngai, 19, a native of Hong Kong.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
