<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Gordon Moves Up, New Car Loses Ground</title>
    <meta content="23nascar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/sports/othersports/23nascar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842408"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn of Stock Car Auto Racing</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Phoenix International</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Gordon, Jeff</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E7D9173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1050" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Gordon Moves Up, New Car Loses Ground</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">As Gordon Moves Up, New Car Loses Ground</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIV BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Viv</byline>
      <dateline>AVONDALE, Ariz., April 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With four championships in a career that few can rival, Jeff Gordon had long ago established his place among the best drivers to ever compete in Nascar. Week by week and year by year, Gordon has only history left to chase as he secures his standing among the series' greats.</p>
        <p>On Saturday night, he finally caught one of the greatest of all.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With four championships in a career that few can rival, Jeff Gordon as only history left to chase as he secures his standing among the series’ greats.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With four championships in a career that few can rival, Jeff Gordon had long ago established his place among the best drivers to ever compete in Nascar. Week by week and year by year, Gordon has only history left to chase as he secures his standing among the series' greats.</p>
        <p>On Saturday night, he finally caught one of the greatest of all.</p>
        <p>Gordon's victory in the Subway Fresh Fit 500 Nextel Cup race at Phoenix International Speedway was the 76th of his career, tying him with Dale Earnhardt for sixth on the career list. Gordon's achievement, which came after a spirited battle with Tony Stewart, overshadowed a race that raised more concerns about the controversial Nascar-designed Car of Tomorrow. At least for a moment, it did not matter what Gordon was driving as he celebrated by honoring Earnhardt and waving a No. 3 flag -- representing the car number Earnhardt immortalized in winning six of his seven Cup championships -- while he took a victory lap around a track where he had never won.</p>
        <p>It was a fitting tribute to Earnhardt, the driver who pushed Gordon harder than any other in a rivalry that helped to increase the sport's national profile in the 1990s, when Gordon won three of his titles and Earnhardt won four.</p>
        <p>''I will say that Senior and I, we did have a rivalry on the racetrack,'' Gordon said, referring to Earnhardt. ''We loved to beat one another. We battled hard on the track, and he certainly didn't mind shoving me around.''</p>
        <p>Nascar has not found a rivalry to match that since Earnhardt died in a crash on the final lap of the 2001 Daytona 500. Although some Dale Earnhardt Jr. fans still consider Gordon the archenemy, the two drivers have never established that same enmity on the racetrack and are friendly off it.</p>
        <p>When Gordon won Saturday night, Dale Earnhardt Jr. was among the first to congratulate him.</p>
        <p>''He told me, 'That was a class act,' what we did,'' said Gordon, who remains the series points leader as he establishes himself among the early favorites for the title. Earnhardt Jr. had known of the planned tribute, having given approval when the idea first came up in the Gordon camp. The Gordon team had carried that Earnhardt flag from track to track since last season -- Gordon had gone 25 races between victories before he finally got to wave it.</p>
        <p>Although Gordon started on the pole and led early in the race, the third event for the new Car of Tomorrow racecar had created little drama for most of the race. Only four drivers had led for a significant stretch, and green-flag passes for the lead had happened only twice in the first 286 laps of the event.</p>
        <p>With Gordon in second place and Stewart's No. 20 Chevy dominating after leading 132 laps in the second half, it appeared that Gordon would have to hold onto that flag for another week. But he got the break of the race when he came down pit road just before a yellow flag came out for a crash. Gordon was able to pit his racecar and return to the track before falling a lap behind the leaders. And when those leaders, including Stewart, went into the pits during the caution period, Gordon cycled out to the front of the pack.</p>
        <p>It was not over yet. Stewart surged ahead with 14 laps to go, but Gordon went low to retake the lead with 13 laps remaining before cruising to a victory.</p>
        <p>The Hendrick Motorsports race team has dominated Car of Tomorrow events, winning all three, including Kyle Busch's victory at Bristol Motor Speedway on March 25 and Jimmie Johnson's a week later at Martinsville. Johnson was fourth and Busch seventh at Phoenix.</p>
        <p>Not even Gordon, who has come in first, second and third in the three Car of Tomorrow races, could bring himself to praise the car after winning with it. ''It was better than I thought it was going to be; it really was,'' Gordon said.</p>
        <p>''I'm not saying I'm sold on it yet. I think there's still a little bit more to do. I think we can make this car better.''</p>
        <p>That was perhaps the kindest comment to come out of the garage after the race. Denny Hamlin, whose No. 11 Chevy finished third and led 70 laps, was highly critical. He lost his lead when he was penalized for speeding on pit road and was sent back to 31st.</p>
        <p>He spent the rest of the race trying to get back to the front because of the difficulty in passing in the boxier car.</p>
        <p>''To be as nice as I can, it's frustrating,'' Hamlin said. ''People will say, 'But you went from the back to the front.' But yeah, it took us 300 laps to do it when it shouldn't have. Our car was just that much better than everyone else's. It shouldn't have took that long.</p>
        <p>''I don't know how we're going to run these cars on bigger tracks without changes.''</p>
        <p>Phoenix International Speedway is a one-mile oval in contrast to the half-mile ovals at Bristol and Martinsville, the sites of the first two Car of Tomorrow races.</p>
        <p>Nascar walked away officially thrilled with the results. Ramsey Poston, the managing director of corporate communications, pointed out that the top 10 drivers included Jeff Green in the No. 66 Chevrolet in sixth place, Bobby Labonte in the No. 43 Dodge in eighth and Johnny Sauter in the No. 70 Chevrolet in ninth.</p>
        <p>''When was the last time those three guys were in the top 10?'' Poston asked, an indication that the Car of Tomorrow allowed midsize and smaller teams to compete with the top programs.</p>
        <p>But Green and Sauter, teammates at Haas CNC Racing, get their equipment from Hendrick Motorsports.</p>
        <p>''If that was the point of it, to make it more competitive for everyone, mission failed, in my opinion,'' said Hamlin, Stewart's teammate at Joe Gibbs Racing. ''You're going to have some that run faster than others, and more than likely, it's going to be the big teams.''</p>
        <p>And that may be Nascar's biggest concern coming out of Phoenix. The way it is going right now, the competition at the front of the pack is as lopsided as ever.</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
