<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Specter Says Gonzales Presence Is 'Harmful' for Justice Dept.</title>
    <meta content="23gonzales" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842419"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E4D9173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="374" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Specter Says Gonzales Presence Is 'Harmful' for Justice Dept.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANA JEAN SCHEMO</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator Arlen Specter of Pennsylvania, the ranking Republican on the Senate Judiciary Committee, said Sunday that Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales's failure to step down was ''no doubt, bad for the Justice Department.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Specter's comments, made on the television program ''Fox News Sunday,'' reflected a growing lack of support for Mr. Gonzales among key Republicans on Capitol Hill as he faces accusations that the dismissals of eight United States attorneys were politically motivated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senator Arlen Specter of Pennsylvania, the ranking Republican on the Senate Judiciary Committee, said Sunday that Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales's failure to step down was ''no doubt, bad for the Justice Department.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Specter's comments, made on the television program ''Fox News Sunday,'' reflected a growing lack of support for Mr. Gonzales among key Republicans on Capitol Hill as he faces accusations that the dismissals of eight United States attorneys were politically motivated.</p>
        <p>Only one Republican senator, Tom Coburn of Oklahoma, has called outright for Mr. Gonzales to resign, though others made their anger at him clear in a blistering hearing over the dismissals on Thursday. In his testimony, Mr. Gonzales cited a faulty memory at least 50 times in responding to questions about the dismissals.</p>
        <p>After the hearing, aides to Mr. Gonzales reportedly called the absence of a demand for his resignation from Mr. Specter a ''positive barometer.'' But Mr. Specter said Sunday that they were misreading him.</p>
        <p>''I don't think they should be celebrating that, because the attorney general's testimony was very, very damaging to his own credibility,'' he said. ''Charges are being made that the Department of Justice was the political arm of the White House.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Specter said that it was up to President Bush to demand a resignation, but that Mr. Gonzales's presence ''is bad for the Department of Justice.''</p>
        <p>''It is harmful,'' he said. ''There has been a very substantial decrease in morale. There's no doubt about that.''</p>
        <p>On the same program, Senator Charles E. Schumer of New York, a Democratic member of the Judiciary Committee who has called for Mr. Gonzales to step down, denied reports that he would block confirmation of a successor as a means of pressing advisers to the president, including Karl Rove and Harriet E. Miers, the former White House counsel, to testify about the dismissals.</p>
        <p>''I would not want to hold up the next attorney general nomination because we need to administer justice,'' Mr. Schumer said. ''But at the same time, I think there's an imperative for the White House to help us interview people like Rove and Miers, because recent testimony, including Gonzales's, more and more indicates that they may be at the nexus of this.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
