<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Have Lenders Lost Students' Trust?</title>
    <meta content="l23loans" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842415"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Virginia</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United States Student Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milonopoulos, Niko</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hubbard, Yvonne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ochroch, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pae, Jennifer S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5D9173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="456" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Have Lenders Lost Students' Trust?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Four letters comment on student loans (April 13 and 15 articles); Niko Milonopoulos says lending companies should not be allowed to offer incentives to universities to receive preferred lender status; Yvonne Hubbard says neither University of Virginia, where she is director of student financial services, nor any of its employees benefits financially from its preferred lending program; David Ochroch says government should not be directly invovled in lending to students; Jennifer S Pae (United States Student Association) says Higher Education Act must be reauthorized to insure that lenders and financial aid institutions can no longer take advantage of students</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Lenders Sought Edge Against U.S. in Student Loans'' (front page, April 15):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Lenders Sought Edge Against U.S. in Student Loans'' (front page, April 15):</p>
        <p>Like many students facing steep tuition costs, I took a student loan from the private lender Sallie Mae. Imagine how deeply betrayed and disheartened I was to discover that students like me were being taken advantage of not only by private lenders, but also by universities.</p>
        <p>As a sophomore at Stanford University who depends on low-interest student loans to attend college, I am appalled that companies are offering incentives to universities to receive ''preferred lender'' status.</p>
        <p>As the government fails to provide adequate financing for federal and state student loans, many students are forced to turn to private lenders. And by engaging in unethical practices, universities are placing an additional hurdle in the way of middle- and low-income students trying to receive a top education.</p>
        <p>Niko Milonopoulos  Stanford, Calif., April 17, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''Lenders Sought Edge Against U.S. in Student Loans'' (front page, April 15) did not mention key facts about the University of Virginia and its student loan program.</p>
        <p>When we moved to the ''preferred lending'' model, it was only after a request for proposals to the lending community and an open and rigorous review. We awarded a contract because we believe it offers the greatest number of benefits to our students.</p>
        <p>Neither the university nor any university employee benefits financially. At the University of Virginia, we put students and their parents first.</p>
        <p>Yvonne Hubbard  Director of Student Financial Services, University of Virginia  Charlottesville, Va., April 16, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Lending to students is not inherently a government activity; nor is mortgage lending. The government can establish loan guarantees and financing in the public interest without becoming directly involved in such transactions.</p>
        <p>Government incursions into private-sector activities should be resisted.</p>
        <p>David Ochroch  Arlington, Va., April 15, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer worked as senior director of technology procurement at Sallie Mae, 1991 to 2000.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''College Administrator's Dual Roles Are a Focus of Student Loan Inquiry'' (news article, April 13):</p>
        <p>The student loan scandal makes a mockery of college students and families struggling to pay for higher education.</p>
        <p>Lenders and financial aid institutions are taking advantage of millions of students who can no longer depend on federal grant aid.</p>
        <p>To restore students' faith in higher education, the Higher Education Act must be reauthorized. This law, the single most comprehensive piece of higher-education legislation, can protect millions of students against gluttonous lenders and their lackeys.</p>
        <p>Government oversight can also ensure that every eager, qualified student has access to higher education regardless of economic status.</p>
        <p>Jennifer S. Pae  President  United States Student Association  Washington, April 13, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
