<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Die and Four Are Hurt in Weekend Crashes</title>
    <meta content="23dwi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/nyregion/23dwi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842399"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drunken and Reckless Driving</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (NYC)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Bronx (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E0DA173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="466" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Die and Four Are Hurt in Weekend Crashes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Two Die and Four Are Hurt in Weekend Crashes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WILSON; Tanzina Vega contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilson, Michael</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Queens woman returning home with her family after a day at Coney Island was killed early yesterday when a man drove through a red light and struck a livery van the family was riding in, the police said.</p>
        <p>The man, Qadir T. Ahmad, 19, of Lake Grove in Suffolk County, was arrested at the scene and charged with driving while intoxicated and vehicular manslaughter, the police said. Neither he nor his two passengers, men ages 19 and 20, were injured.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A man was arrested at the scene of one of the crashes and charged with driving while intoxicated and vehicular manslaughter, the police said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Queens woman returning home with her family after a day at Coney Island was killed early yesterday when a man drove through a red light and struck a livery van the family was riding in, the police said.</p>
        <p>The man, Qadir T. Ahmad, 19, of Lake Grove in Suffolk County, was arrested at the scene and charged with driving while intoxicated and vehicular manslaughter, the police said. Neither he nor his two passengers, men ages 19 and 20, were injured.</p>
        <p>The victim, Paula Serrano, 28, was holding her 20-day-old son, Arturo, in her lap when Mr. Ahmad's Toyota Camry struck the van, according to the police and members of her family. The baby and Mrs. Serrano's nephew, Rodrigo, 10 months old, and her sister, Maria, were being treated at Elmhurst Hospital Center yesterday, although the family did not know the extent of their injuries, said her brother, Eloy Coatl.</p>
        <p>According to the family, there were seven adults in the van, including Mrs. Serrano's husband, Saturnino Serrano; Maria and her husband; Mr. Coatl and his girlfriend; and the livery driver. Besides the two babies, there was a third child in the van, Mrs. Serrano's 6-year-old daughter, Ana, who suffered minor injuries.</p>
        <p>The accident occurred shortly before 2 a.m. at 65th Place and Queens Boulevard, as the van approached the family's home. Mr. Coatl said he saw the Camry coming, but there was no time to react. ''That car was speeding very fast,'' he said. ''We all screamed.'' Mrs. Serrano and the two babies were thrown from the vehicle, he said.</p>
        <p>The accident was one of three over the weekend in which a woman was badly hurt or killed and someone was charged with driving while intoxicated. In Far Rockaway, a woman who was stepping out of her parked car on Saturday afternoon was struck by a car on Beach Channel Drive, the police said.</p>
        <p>The driver, Kirk Blake, of West Hempstead, was charged with driving while intoxicated, and the woman remained in critical condition at Peninsula Hospital Center, the police said yesterday.</p>
        <p>In the Bronx, Glenn Salera, 29, was arrested after he ran from the scene of an accident on the Cross Bronx Expressway on Friday, where his car had rear-ended a tractor-trailer, the police said; his passenger, Carmen Irizarry, was killed.</p>
        <p>Well-wishers streamed into the Serrano family's apartment in Woodside yesterday, many of them too overcome with emotion to speak to reporters. A family friend, Oliverta Manzana, said of Mrs. Serrano: ''She's a good person. Always happy. We have no words.''</p>
        <p>The family hopes to raise money to bury Mrs. Serrano in her native Mexico, Mr. Coatl said.</p>
        <p>''She always took care of us,'' he said. ''She would cook for us, even though she had her two children.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
