<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>3 Puccinis, Separate, But Equal In Grandeur</title>
    <meta content="23trit" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/arts/music/23trit.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842370"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Metropolitan Opera</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Puccini, Giacomo</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Levine, James</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Guleghina, Maria</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Licitra, Salvatore</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Burchinal, Frederick</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Frittoli, Barbara</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Blythe, Stephanie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE5DA173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1094" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>3 Puccinis, Separate, But Equal In Grandeur</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">3 Puccinis, Separate, but Equal in Grandeur</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's official. The Metropolitan Opera's new production of ''Il Trittico,'' Puccini's triptych of one-act operas, is the most elaborate show in the company's current repertory. Measured by the number of stage wagons required to transport the sets, ''Trittico,'' staged by Jack O'Brien in his Met debut, has broken the house record long held by Zeffirelli's extravagant ''Turandot.''</p>
        <p>One reason for the cumulative size of the sets (designed by Douglas W. Schmidt) is that ''Trittico,'' which opened on Friday night, is really three productions in one. These one-act operas have nothing in common. Some commentators try to make the case that each offers a different take on death.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Metropolitan Opera’s new production of Puccini’s triptych of one-act operas is the most elaborate show in the company’s current repertory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's official. The Metropolitan Opera's new production of ''Il Trittico,'' Puccini's triptych of one-act operas, is the most elaborate show in the company's current repertory. Measured by the number of stage wagons required to transport the sets, ''Trittico,'' staged by Jack O'Brien in his Met debut, has broken the house record long held by Zeffirelli's extravagant ''Turandot.''</p>
        <p>One reason for the cumulative size of the sets (designed by Douglas W. Schmidt) is that ''Trittico,'' which opened on Friday night, is really three productions in one. These one-act operas have nothing in common. Some commentators try to make the case that each offers a different take on death.</p>
        <p>''Il Tabarro'' portrays death as the brutal justice exacted by a wronged husband upon his wife's lover. ''Suor Angelica'' presents suicide as a longed-for step taken by a young nun who desperately yearns to be with her dead child. In the irreverent ''Gianni Schicchi'' death is a pesky impediment to the avaricious relatives of a wealthy Florentine who has willed his entire estate to a monastery. But how many operas do not present some take or other on death?</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Brien found his justification for the scenic grandeur in the text and music of each work. He wanted to realize Puccini's vision in ''real and natural'' settings, as he has explained in recent interviews. His sympathetic partner in this approach was James Levine, who conducted elegant, animated and beautifully detailed accounts of each work. The Met can certainly stake a claim to ''Il Trittico,'' having presented the premiere in 1918. (The Met's previous production was last seen complete in 1989.)</p>
        <p>''Il Tabarro'' (''The Cloak''), here set in 1927, tells of Michele, a middle-aged barge owner, and his young wife, Giorgetta. The grim and bulky barge is docked one evening on a channel off the Seine in Paris. Across the channel is a row of gritty factories.</p>
        <p>A tall crane hovers near the stern of the barge, where grimy, strong-shouldered stevedores unload cargo. A huge steel pedestrian bridge dominates the stage. Yet the action is placed forward, and the characters are never dwarfed.</p>
        <p>In a poignant stroke as the opera begins Mr. O'Brien conveys the tragedy that has befallen this couple. The bedraggled Giorgetta, the soprano Maria Guleghina, while going through the laundry, finds a little cap belonging to her infant son, dead for just a year. The grief-stricken Giorgetta, feeling alienated from her husband, has found comfort in the arms of a young stevedore, Luigi, here the tenor Salvatore Licitra.</p>
        <p>The opening orchestral music -- solemn, weighty, with harmonies as murky as the tar-pool surface of the glistening channel -- quickly suggests where this tragedy is heading: The still-smitten Michele will discover the truth and strangle Luigi.</p>
        <p>The baritone Frederick Burchinal, taking the place of Juan Pons, who was ill, was a sturdy-voiced and pitiable Michele. Ms. Guleghina brought earthy colorings and dramatic intensity to Giorgetta. Looking aptly rugged and impulsive as Luigi, Mr. Licitra sang with husky power and ardent delivery, if not much subtlety. The formidable mezzo-soprano Stephanie Blythe almost stole the show as Frugola, a stevedore's wife who rummages through rags and has an endless store of trinkets and tales.</p>
        <p>Some opera experts disparage ''Suor Angelica'' as maudlin and pseudomystical. Ignore them. The work, especially as presented in this beautifully sensitive staging, set in Tuscany in 1938, is a 60-minute masterpiece. Sister Angelica, born to aristocracy, has lived as a nun since giving birth to a boy out of wedlock seven years earlier. As Angelica, the affecting Italian soprano Barbara Frittoli sang with impassioned lyricism while conveying this vulnerable young woman's pervasive sadness.</p>
        <p>The set depicts the interior courtyard of a convent: imagine the Cloisters moved from Fort Tryon Park to the stage of the Met. Ms. Blythe portrayed the Princess, Angelica's stern aunt. Angelica's parents, who died long ago, entrusted their children to the Princess.</p>
        <p>What came through in Ms. Blythe's riveting performance was that this matronly woman believes that she has utterly failed in this obligation to her dead sister. Driven by guilt, she forces herself to be reproachful to Angelica, whom she has not visited in seven years.</p>
        <p>She comes seeking Angelica's signature on a document regarding her inheritance. Angelica craves news of her son. Coldly, the Princess explains that the boy took ill and died two years ago. Ms. Frittoli's singing of the aria ''Senza mamma,'' when the anguished Angelica thinks of the child who has died without ever knowing his mother's embrace, was so emotional and honest that the audience refrained from breaking the mood with applause.</p>
        <p>The opera ends with a tough-to-stage miracle. Angelica, an expert herbalist, takes a fatal potion but then, in panic, fearing that she has committed a mortal sin, begs the Virgin Mother for forgiveness. Here a beam of sunlight engulfs her as a statue of the Virgin and Child on the church wall glows. A little boy dressed in a cream-colored Sunday suit appears at the church steps to invite Angelica to the hereafter. Hokey? Not the way Mr. Levine drew shimmering delicacies from the orchestra as the offstage chorus sang Puccini's wistfully angelic harmonies.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Brien playfully zaps ''Gianni Schicchi'' from 1299 to 1959. Buoso Donati, the owner of a palazzo in Florence and numerous country properties, is on his deathbed, surrounded by greedy relatives in mock prayer. When they discover that he has left everything to a bunch of monks, young Rinuccio (the appealing tenor Massimo Giordano), urges them to turn to the town's shrewdest citizen, Gianni Schicchi, who comes up with a scheme. The penniless Rinuccio has an ulterior motive: He wants to marry Schicchi's daughter Lauretta (Olga Mykytenko, a bright, lyric soprano, in her Met debut).</p>
        <p>The robust and stylish Italian baritone Alessandro Corbelli, made an endearing and unflappable Schicchi. Ms. Blythe, as the scheming Zita, was an indomitable force onstage. She is the surprise star of the Met's grandly old-fashioned yet smart and effective ''Trittico.''</p>
        <p>Il Trittico</p>
        <p>Three one-act operas by Giacomo Puccini; libretti by Giuseppe Adami (''Il Tabarro'') and Giovacchino Forzano (''Suor Angelica,'' ''Gianni Schicchi''); conductor, James Levine; production by Jack O'Brien; sets by Douglas W. Schmidt; costumes by Jess Goldstein; lighting by Jules Fisher and Peggy Eisenhauer. At the Metropolitan Opera through May 12.</p>
        <p>IL TABARRO  WITH: Maria Guleghina (Giorgetta), Salatore Licitra (Luigi) and Frederick Burchinal (Michele).</p>
        <p>SUOR ANGELICA  WITH: Barbara Frittoli (Sister Angelica), Heidi Grant Murphy (Sister Genovieffa) and Stephanie Blythe (La Principessa).</p>
        <p>GIANNI SCHICCHI  WITH: Alessandro Corbelli (Gianni Schicchi), Olga Mykytenko (Lauretta) and Massimo Giordano (Rinuccio).</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
