<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jefferson Continues To Give Nets a Lift</title>
    <meta content="23nets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/sports/basketball/23nets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842447"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Toronto Raptors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Toronto Raptors</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Jefferson, Richard</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E5D8173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="784" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jefferson Continues To Give Nets a Lift</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Jefferson Continues to Give Nets a Lift</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON and MICHAEL S. SCHMIDT; John Eligon contributed reporting from Toronto, and Michael S. Schmidt from East Rutherford, N.J.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eligon, John; Schmidt, Michael S</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO, April 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Not long ago, when Richard Jefferson returned after missing 21 games because of an injured right ankle, he cautioned that he would not magically take the Nets to new heights.</p>
        <p>Twenty-two games later, the Nets' body of work with Jefferson in the lineup paints a telling picture of how much they value their third star.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Nets’ body of work with Richard Jefferson in the lineup paints a telling picture of how much they value their third star.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Not long ago, when Richard Jefferson returned after missing 21 games because of an injured right ankle, he cautioned that he would not magically take the Nets to new heights.</p>
        <p>Twenty-two games later, the Nets' body of work with Jefferson in the lineup paints a telling picture of how much they value their third star.</p>
        <p>Since March 12, when Jefferson scored 18 points against the Memphis Grizzlies in his third game back, the Nets have gone 14-6. The most important victory during that stretch came Saturday, when Jefferson led the sixth-seeded Nets with 28 points in their 96-91 victory against the third-seeded Toronto Raptors in Game 1 of their Eastern Conference first-round playoff series.</p>
        <p>''R. J.'s confidence has soared,'' Vince Carter said after the game. ''He is playing phenomenal basketball. I think that our team as a whole trusts each other and we are just playing off of each other. It is just great. I think our spacing is better, just the whole machine is well oiled, so to speak.''</p>
        <p>Game 2 of the best-of-seven series is here Tuesday night. The Nets returned home Saturday and practiced Sunday in East Rutherford, N.J. They will practice there again Monday before returning to Toronto.</p>
        <p>Jefferson proved to be a vital safety net in Game 1. Carter struggled, making only 5 of 19 shots and finishing with 16 points. Jefferson shot an efficient 11 of 21. He put pressure on the Raptors by continually looking to drive the lane and getting out for fast breaks. He scored nearly half of the Nets' 20 fast-break points.</p>
        <p>''Every time I have a good game, everyone wants to know how good I feel,'' Jefferson said Sunday. ''It comes in flows. You are not as consistent because you have not been playing consistently. When you have only been playing for a month and a half, you are not as consistent as you would like, and that is something I am working at.''</p>
        <p>Jefferson said he would not be fully recovered from the arthroscopic surgery on his ankle until he had a chance to rest in the off-season. But after being frustrated by career-low averages early in the season, he has been salvaging his season in recent weeks. Including Game 1, Jefferson has averaged 18.5 points and shot 44.8 percent in the Nets' past 20 games.</p>
        <p>''Now that Richard is getting better physically, it really helps us because it opens the court,'' Rod Thorn, the Nets' president, said. ''We're a better team.''</p>
        <p>SOME ADVICE FOR BOSH -- As N.B.A. players, Vince Carter, the Raptors' former franchise player, and Chris Bosh, the heir apparent to Carter in Toronto, have crossed paths several times. And Carter has offered Bosh advice on to how to survive as the marquee player in Toronto.</p>
        <p>''He said it's tough,'' Bosh said, recalling a conversation with Carter. ''Not only in this city, but anywhere, because when things are not going as good as they're supposed to, you're going to have to do something. You're going to have to rally up the guys and put them on your back.''</p>
        <p>The most difficult part of being a franchise player, Bosh said, has been developing his skills and leading on the fly. Bosh, in his first playoffs, is playing in only his fourth N.B.A. season. He is not a vocal person by nature.</p>
        <p>''It's been really hard,'' he said. ''I enjoy it. That's a great challenge. I love challenges. I don't think it'll ever get old.''</p>
        <p>After his first postseason game, Bosh is already realizing that he has to adjust his game. He said he was surprised by how much more physical the game was around the basket.</p>
        <p>A versatile frontcourt player, Bosh is also learning how to channel his excitement. He picked up two quick fouls in the first quarter of Game 1 and was limited to less than 10 minutes in the first half.</p>
        <p>''I feel like I can guard anybody; I feel like I can score anytime or get somebody an open shot,'' Bosh said. ''That's the next level of basketball, where you have to do it. I feel that something has to happen every time I touch the ball.''</p>
        <p>Has Carter shared anything about dealing with the Toronto fans, who boo him at every opportunity because they feel he gave up on them?</p>
        <p>''Nah, we don't mention the fans too much,'' Bosh said, laughing.</p>
        <p>NACHBAR HAS SORE NECK -- Forward Bostjan Nachbar, who had 16 points on Saturday, said he continued to be bothered by a sore neck. He said he expected to play Tuesday.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
