<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Views Clash Among Neighbors As Builders Destroy Old for New</title>
    <meta content="23massapequa" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/nyregion/23massapequa.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842439"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEED9173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1554" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Views Clash Among Neighbors As Builders Destroy Old for New</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Views Clash Among Neighbors as Builders Destroy Old for New</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL VITELLO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vitello, Paul</byline>
      <dateline>MASSAPEQUA, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the chain saw man working from above and the wood chipper man working from below, removing one of the last trees on the newly cleared lot at Bay Drive and Nassau Street here took all of an hour the other day. The 75-year-old, 100-foot cedar came down in 6-foot chunks that made a slight tremor underfoot when they hit the ground.</p>
        <p>''There used to be a charming little house here on a heavily wooded lot, with pepperidge and cedar and some beech trees,'' said Kevin Kobs, a longtime resident of the neighborhood who stopped to watch the last stages of the clearing and grading of a lot bought by a home builder last year. ''They tore down the house, ripped out the trees, and now they're going to put up one of these, these ''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For most of the last decade, older suburban neighborhoods have undergone a building boom that has divided communities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the chain saw man working from above and the wood chipper man working from below, removing one of the last trees on the newly cleared lot at Bay Drive and Nassau Street here took all of an hour the other day. The 75-year-old, 100-foot cedar came down in 6-foot chunks that made a slight tremor underfoot when they hit the ground.</p>
        <p>''There used to be a charming little house here on a heavily wooded lot, with pepperidge and cedar and some beech trees,'' said Kevin Kobs, a longtime resident of the neighborhood who stopped to watch the last stages of the clearing and grading of a lot bought by a home builder last year. ''They tore down the house, ripped out the trees, and now they're going to put up one of these, these ''</p>
        <p>He grasped for the word, then pointed down the street at the plywood frame of a vast, rectangular house with big picture windows under construction. ''These monstrosities,'' Mr. Kobs said as sawdust fell on him like a light spring snow.</p>
        <p>Although there are signs that things may be starting to change, for most of the last decade older suburban neighborhoods like Mr. Kobs's, an enclave called Harbour Green built on the South Shore of Long Island in the 1930s, have undergone a building boom that has divided communities.</p>
        <p>On one side are longtime residents who value amenities like old trees, old homes, wide lawns and the intangible qualities referred to as scale and neighborhood character; on the other side are relative newcomers who might share those values in principle but who prefer to tear down the old houses and replace them with ones sometimes twice as big.</p>
        <p>The National Trust for Historic Preservation, a nonprofit group based in Washington, produced a survey last year indicating fierce conflicts about teardowns, as they are called by opponents -- or new construction on existing lots, as home builders call the phenomenon -- from Montclair, N.J., Delray Beach, Fla., and the Hamptons of Long Island to Atlanta, Austin, Tex., and suburban communities outside Chicago, Washington, Baltimore, Denver, Houston, San Francisco, Los Angeles, Cincinnati and Boston.</p>
        <p>''It's a huge phenomenon, and a very large concern of ours,'' Richard Moe, president of the organization, said in an interview. ''In the last several decades, the average size of the American home has doubled. When you inject these super-sized mansions into communities built according to an older standard, it can create enormous damage to the character of a place.''</p>
        <p>But there are signs of an emerging shift in this culture war of architectural taste.</p>
        <p>Partly as a result of the slowdown in home buying in some areas of the country, and partly because of a long-term effort by preservationists to enlist the help of local governments, a small but growing number of municipalities have imposed building moratoriums in the last two years.</p>
        <p>In 2005, the town council in Chevy Chase, Md., passed a six-month building moratorium while it reviewed and tightened its zoning laws in response to a protest against the construction of McMansions; the following year the Maryland Legislature adopted a bill, which was signed into law, granting broader powers to local governments to limit how high, how wide and how big in relation to surrounding homes, new houses could be.</p>
        <p>Similar moratoriums and zoning restrictions were adopted last year in municipalities large and small -- including Austin, Tex., Atlanta, Salt Lake City, Ocean City, N.J., Larchmont and Brighton, N.Y., and the Chicago suburbs of Evanston, Oak Park, and Naperville.</p>
        <p>''To us, we see it as a conflict between two groups that are basically well-intentioned,'' said Stephen Melman, director of research and economic forecasting for the National Association of Home Builders, a Washington-based industry lobby. ''You start with a desirable neighborhood, usually in a close-in suburb where the homes are older, and because it is such a nice place to live, it attracts your more selective clientele, who are looking for a higher-quality home.''</p>
        <p>The home builders association estimates there were 330,000 home demolitions in the country last year, although that includes every category, from teardowns of the Harbour Green kind to those made necessary by damage and disrepair.</p>
        <p>Mr. Melman said the total was about 20 percent lower last year than in 2005, the peak year of the boom in new housing. Still, he said it was impossible to know whether that was because of building moratoriums or the general decline in new housing construction.</p>
        <p>By Long Island standards, the old houses in Mr. Kobs's neighborhood, like the one just demolished along with the cedar tree, are very old. Pre-Levittown old.</p>
        <p>The original 400 houses in this canal-fingered waterfront area were built from 1931 to 1940, and were among the first of their kind for middle-class homebuyers.</p>
        <p>With their screened-in porches, fireplaces and steeply pitched gable roofs, Harbour Green homes were featured in magazines like ''Life'' and ''Better Homes and Gardens'' as encouraging examples of how far $4,500 could take the average person toward realizing the American Dream, a term that was then newly minted. By now, many of the original houses have been added to and renovated, but most retain the ivy-covered and tree-shaded look of the cottages they were designed to be.</p>
        <p>It was about five years ago when the first of about two dozen homes here were torn down, neighbors say. In most cases, builders bought single-story houses with about 2,400 square feet of space for $600,000 to $800,000. They tore them down and built larger homes with two stories and 4,000 to 6,000 square feet of space that sold for more than $1 million.</p>
        <p>Besides their size, a feature that stirred almost equal chagrin among neighbors was their height: to give the houses full-size basements on land so close to the water, builders heaped soil on the lots to raise the height of the foundation. That practice made the two-story houses seem to tower over the others, some neighbors said.</p>
        <p>Dan Ryan, manager of a Prudential Douglas Elliman real estate agency in Massapequa, which has been a partner in some of the new building, said it was a matter of giving customers what they wanted.</p>
        <p>''Buyers today want extra master bedrooms,'' Mr. Ryan said. ''They want dens. They want two-car garages. They want saunas. Is it the builder's fault that he builds them bigger because someone wants to buy it that way?''</p>
        <p>Beginning several years ago, Mr. Kobs, a business manager for an investment banking firm, and a nucleus of several activists including Robert Salamack, a Wall Street trader, and Mark Snider, who owns a local advertising company, convened a series of meetings among Harbour Green residents to discuss the changes in their neighborhood. They arranged meetings with Mr. Ryan, the real estate broker.</p>
        <p>They called on their town councilman and on Jack Libert, a Long Island real estate lawyer who is also commissioner of planning and development in the Town of Oyster Bay, where Harbour Green is situated.</p>
        <p>By their account, the talks were sporadic and inconclusive until early this year, when Mr. Ryan and Mr. Libert indicated some willingness to consider their concerns. In the meantime, two things happened that may have favored the group. The real estate market slowed enough that in Harbour Green, no fewer than four new homes built by developers -- all larger than the cottages they replaced -- have gone unsold for six months to a year.</p>
        <p>The other factor came from the community of Oyster Bay, a hamlet on the North Shore. Last year, activists there won the support of town officials in efforts to stopthe demolition of late 19th-century and early 20th-century homes. A yearlong moratorium, which ended in January, was put in effect while the town reconsidered the rules of new construction.</p>
        <p>''We recognize that this is a problem in Harbour Green,'' Mr. Libert said. ''These squarish boxes seem to be overbuilt in relation to their neighbors.''</p>
        <p>Mary Korber, who lives in one of the larger new houses in Harbour Green, answered her door the other day with a phone at her ear. A furniture store had failed to deliver one piece of new den furniture. Her house, on a raised foundation, has two stories, five bedrooms and a total 6,200 feet of space on a lot that once held a modest three-bedroom ranch.</p>
        <p>''I have mixed feelings,'' Ms. Korber said, a hand resting on the head of one of her four children, Collin, 5. ''We moved here because we loved the charm of the neighborhood. I know people think our house is too big, but we thought it fit in. On the other hand, the land here is very expensive, and people who come here are not first-time homebuyers. They want a little more room. They have a lot of stuff.''</p>
        <p>Her phone rang a lot: The furniture store calling back. A brother who lives in a house nearby. A friend down the street.</p>
        <p>''But I have to tell you, that house where they were taking down that tree the other day,'' she said. As it turned out, she had driven by at the same time that Mr. Kobs was watching the removal of the cedar tree at Bay Drive and Nassau Street.</p>
        <p>''That was one of my favorite houses,'' she said. ''It was horrible when they knocked that down.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
