<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Whistles Are Stopping The Bulls and the Heat</title>
    <meta content="23bulls" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/sports/basketball/23bulls.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842423"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Chicago Bulls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Miami Heat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Chicago Bulls</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Miami Heat</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hinrich, Kirk</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E1D9173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="815" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Whistles Are Stopping The Bulls and the Heat</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bulls Rely on Youth and Effort in Victory</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <dateline>DEERFIELD, Ill., April 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Kirk Hinrich's mouthguard sailed into the stands, the moment seemed to capture the flights and frustrations of both the Bulls and the Heat in their first playoff game Saturday.</p>
        <p>Hinrich, Chicago's fourth-year point guard, uncharacteristically flung the piece of plastic as he walked off the court, angry over his fourth personal foul, which came one minute into the third quarter and put him on the bench.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lacking big-name stars and oversized personalities, the Chicago Bulls relied on a gutsy group effort for a 96-91 victory over the Miami Heat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As Kirk Hinrich's mouthguard sailed into the stands, the moment seemed to capture the flights and frustrations of both the Bulls and the Heat in their first playoff game Saturday.</p>
        <p>Hinrich, Chicago's fourth-year point guard, uncharacteristically flung the piece of plastic as he walked off the court, angry over his fourth personal foul, which came one minute into the third quarter and put him on the bench.</p>
        <p>That was where Hinrich was parked for all but 19 minutes of the game.</p>
        <p>His absence underlined the way the young Bulls, lacking big-name stars and oversized personalities, relied on a gutsy group effort for a 96-91 victory in the Eastern Conference first-round best-of-seven series. Chicago's response to losing its floor leader was one that Miami -- without its two superstars, Shaquille O'Neal and Dwyane Wade, who were also in foul trouble -- could not replicate.</p>
        <p>O'Neal complained to reporters after the game, saying the Bulls players were flopping and that officials -- specifically Eddie F. Rush -- took him out of his game. Hinrich let his mouthpiece be just that.</p>
        <p>He was clearly reluctant to talk Sunday, remaining at the far end of the gym shooting with a Bulls assistant coach after a short practice while the news media waited.</p>
        <p>''You got to face the music, man,'' Bulls Coach Scott Skiles yelled teasingly across the gym to Hinrich. ''They aren't going anywhere.''</p>
        <p>Five minutes later, Hinrich shuffled over to discuss his dismal performance -- 2 points on 1-for-7 shooting, 4 turnovers and 5 fouls.</p>
        <p>''I was about as frustrated as I've ever been playing basketball,'' Hinrich said Sunday, saying he was jarred out of his normally aggressive game by quick whistles.</p>
        <p>''It makes it tougher; it's always in the back of your mind you can't foul. It takes a little bit of your edge away.''</p>
        <p>As upset as he was at himself, he said, ''It would have been worse if we lost.''</p>
        <p>From his vantage point on the bench, Hinrich could see how a personable rookie from Switzerland, Thabo Sefolosha, took his place. Despite his inexperience, Sefolosha unabashedly bothered Wade with his seven-foot wingspan and quick instincts.</p>
        <p>Hinrich saw how the third-year forward Luol Deng had a breakout game, scoring a playoff career-high 33 points against a team that he usually struggled against. He saw Ben Gordon take over the backcourt and finish with 11 assists and 24 points.</p>
        <p>''It's encouraging,'' Hinrich said. ''It epitomizes we're a team. All year we had guys step up and we had a good effort.''</p>
        <p>But as point guard, Hinrich is the Bulls' unofficial leader. His playmaking is the reason he was chosen for the United States national team last summer. But even after that, he is reluctant to be a vocal leader.</p>
        <p>The Bulls need Hinrich's consistency on the court, not on the bench.</p>
        <p>''You can't make somebody be a leader,'' Skiles said. ''People have it or they don't. If Kirk is thinking too much about those kinds of things, he normally doesn't play well. He has to go out there and be relaxed and play without thinking, do what the defense gives him.''</p>
        <p>Skiles, a former teammate of O'Neal's in Orlando, is used to O'Neal's complaints about refereeing but also knows that O'Neal will adjust.</p>
        <p>''No matter how long the series lasts, we're not going to get Shaq and Wade in foul trouble in the same game again,'' Skiles said. ''It just doesn't happen as much.''</p>
        <p>For one half, O'Neal had his way against the Heat, powering inside and finishing with his patented jump hooks.</p>
        <p>Then came the whistles. O'Neal fouled out with 3 minutes 19 seconds remaining, having scored only 2 of his 19 points in the second half. His fifth and final fouls were made on blocking calls.</p>
        <p>He said that the Bulls were trying to just ''act a lot'' and that the referees fell for it.</p>
        <p>''I'm used to just outplaying somebody and just playing hard,'' O'Neal said, ''but I guess that's what you got to do to stop Shaq.''</p>
        <p>Skiles said he instructed his team not to practice flopping. ''We do like to step in and take charges, and we took seven of them,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Bulls' Ben Wallace, who has had three consecutive seasons of playoff experience against O'Neal, took the high road.</p>
        <p>''Everybody's got their own opinion,'' Wallace said, sounding his familiar refrain. ''It is what it is.''</p>
        <p>And what it is now, Hinrich and the Heat hope, will not be the same Tuesday, in Game 2.</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>Shaquille O'Neal appeared to have his heels inside the lower half-circle for his fifth and sixth fouls Saturday. The line is the difference between a blocking foul (inside the circle) and a charge call. Scott Skiles said he did not think there should be a half-circle. ''I'm not fond of it,'' he said. ''I'm of the belief there's way too many lines on the floor.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
