<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Francona Uses His Power of Suggestion to the Benefit of the Red Sox</title>
    <meta content="23ortiz" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/sports/baseball/23ortiz.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070425T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842461"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ortiz, David</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E1D8173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="722" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Francona Uses His Power of Suggestion to the Benefit of the Red Sox</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Francona Uses His Power of Suggestion to the Benefit of the Red Sox</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, April 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From his position inside the first-base dugout at always cozy and often crazy Fenway Park, Red Sox Manager Terry Francona has watched hundreds of pitchers search for outs. Francona knows how uncomfortable it can feel in a park where the 37-foot-high fence in left field feels as if it is barely behind shortstop.</p>
        <p>So, when Francona was quizzed about Chase Wright, the Yankees rookie who made his second career start in this caldron Sunday night, he said that he hoped the atmosphere would cause Wright to struggle with his pitches.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees have the highest payroll in the major leagues, but they have been unable to disguise the pitching problems that injuries have helped create.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From his position inside the first-base dugout at always cozy and often crazy Fenway Park, Red Sox Manager Terry Francona has watched hundreds of pitchers search for outs. Francona knows how uncomfortable it can feel in a park where the 37-foot-high fence in left field feels as if it is barely behind shortstop.</p>
        <p>So, when Francona was quizzed about Chase Wright, the Yankees rookie who made his second career start in this caldron Sunday night, he said that he hoped the atmosphere would cause Wright to struggle with his pitches.</p>
        <p>But, a few seconds later, Francona retreated.</p>
        <p>''Just because he's a young kid doesn't mean we're going to knock him around,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Or maybe it did. The Red Sox knocked Wright around with an epic display in the third inning, when they hit four consecutive home runs during a 7-6 victory. Manny Ramírez, J. D. Drew, Mike Lowell and Jason Varitek all homered off Wright, only the second time in major league history a team hit four consecutive home runs off the same pitcher.</p>
        <p>''It certainly brought some life back into the ballpark in a hurry,'' Francona said.</p>
        <p>Francona actually had a memorable day as a prophet of sorts, since he also predicted that Ramírez, who had only one homer in the first 16 games, was due to punish the baseball. Francona said Ramírez was close to producing in a major way, which is what happened a few hours later.</p>
        <p>When Wright threw Ramírez an 89-mile-an-hour fastball, Ramírez drilled it to center field, then flipped his bat aside and watched it soar. The other homers came in a blur. Drew hit one beyond the Red Sox' bullpen in right center. Lowell lined one into the Green Monster seats, and Varitek sent one there, too. It took only 10 pitches for Boston to destroy Wright after he got the first two outs.</p>
        <p>''I was feeling better as the number mounted,'' Francona said.</p>
        <p>David Ortiz, who flied out to left before the onslaught, said before he took his first swing in spring training that the Red Sox had better starting pitchers than the Yankees. Ortiz was polite and pointed as he sat by his locker in Fort Myers, Fla., appraising the pitchers and giving Boston the edge.</p>
        <p>That was two months ago. That was before Mike Mussina, Chien-Ming Wang and Carl Pavano went on the disabled list. That was before the Yankees needed to use a neophyte like Wright, who had never pitched above Class AA Trenton before last week, to try to prevent a three-game sweep. The 24-year-old Wright lasted three innings and gave up four runs.</p>
        <p>So what does Ortiz, who has feasted on the Yankees in recent years, think about a rotation that he already considered fragile?</p>
        <p>''I'm sure right now they're trying to get their pitching staff together,'' Ortiz said before the game. ''It's hard to go through a situation like that. We went through it last year. But I'm pretty sure they're going to get better when they get their guys back.''</p>
        <p>Ortiz was being diplomatic about what the Yankees face as they wait until Wang returns Tuesday, until Mussina returns next week and until Pavano stops being the $40 million pitcher who does not pitch.</p>
        <p>When Reggie Jackson, the Yankees' adviser, was asked earlier this month if the Yankees would be successful this season, he said, ''It depends on the pitching.''</p>
        <p>That was a Hall of Fame hitter's answer. That is the same answer Manager Joe Torre gives day after day, year after year. No matter how many homers Alex Rodriguez hits, the Yankees are vulnerable when their pitchers cannot stop anyone.</p>
        <p>Although Ortiz did not homer Sunday, it is rare when the Yankees have throttled him. Since Ortiz joined the Red Sox, he is batting .314 with 21 homers and 64 runs batted in across 74 games against the Yankees. Some scouts have said the Yankees let Ortiz get too comfortable. In 278 at-bats, Ortiz has not been hit by a pitch once.</p>
        <p>The other Red Sox looked awfully comfortable in the third, when they did to Wright what they would struggle to do consistently against a batting practice pitcher. Francona wondered if his hitters would be able to knock a kid around at a frenzied Fenway, which is exactly what they did.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 25, 2007, Wednesday  A sports article in some copies on Monday about Manager Terry Francona's power of suggestion in helping the Red Sox batters succeed in Sunday night's game against the Yankees, referred imprecisely to a home run hit by Mike Lowell in the third-inning. The ball left Fenway Park; it did not land in the Green Monster seats.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 25, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A sports article in some copies on Monday about Manager Terry Francona's power of suggestion in helping the Red Sox batters succeed in Sunday night's game against the Yankees, referred imprecisely to a home run hit by Mike Lowell in the third-inning. The ball left Fenway Park; it did not land in the Green Monster seats.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
