<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Praying for 'Troubled Soul' And Mourning for Victims</title>
    <meta content="23church" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/us/23church.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842437"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Korean-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cho Seung-Hui</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00EED9173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="634" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Praying for 'Troubled Soul' And Mourning for Victims</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Praying for a ‘Troubled Soul’ and Mourning for Victims</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUEVON LEE</byline>
      <dateline>CENTREVILLE, Va., April 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Addressing the congregation of Young Saeng Korean Presbyterian Church here on Sunday, the Rev. Myung Sub Chung spoke of a loving family but a profoundly troubled soul.</p>
        <p>''In the end, he couldn't be happy,'' Mr. Chung, the lead minister, told the roughly 200 congregation members, referring to 23-year-old Seung-Hui Cho, who took the lives of 32 people and then his own on the campus of Virginia Tech in Blacksburg, Va., last Monday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Korean-Americans gathered at churches near the campus of Virginia Tech, they embraced a time for reflection and spiritual solace.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Addressing the congregation of Young Saeng Korean Presbyterian Church here on Sunday, the Rev. Myung Sub Chung spoke of a loving family but a profoundly troubled soul.</p>
        <p>''In the end, he couldn't be happy,'' Mr. Chung, the lead minister, told the roughly 200 congregation members, referring to 23-year-old Seung-Hui Cho, who took the lives of 32 people and then his own on the campus of Virginia Tech in Blacksburg, Va., last Monday.</p>
        <p>As Korean-Americans gathered here and at churches throughout the area on Sunday, they embraced a time for reflection and spiritual solace, trying like others to come to terms with the rampage. Weighing heavily on Mr. Chung, and on many in his congregation, was their common heritage with Mr. Cho..''He's Korean, so that means he's our family,'' Mr. Chung said after services, as he sat in the church's reception hall, where bowls of steaming noodles were passed around to people seated around long tables.</p>
        <p>He spoke about his shock at first seeing the image of the gunman on television.</p>
        <p>''I never imagined that type of face,'' he said. ''That face looked like my son's.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Chung's church is a mile and a half from the Cho family home, but neither the minister nor members of his congregation could recall whether the family had ever worshipped at Young Saeng Korean Presbyterian.</p>
        <p>During the services, Mr. Chung read aloud a letter sent to him by a family that lives in the same neighborhood as the Chos. In the letter, the family wrote, ''Jesus loves you deeply and grieves with you.''</p>
        <p>For many Korean-Americans, church is more than just a place of worship; it is the center of the community. And it was at churches where they came together in the past week for candlelight vigils in tribute to those who were killed, and where they began working, in some cases with Korean advocacy groups, to raise money for the families of the shooting victims.</p>
        <p>At services on Sunday at the Korean Central Presbyterian Church in Vienna, Va., the largest Korean congregation in Northern Virginia, congregation members fastened to their lapels interlocking ribbons of orange and maroon -- Virginia Tech school colors -- to recall the lost lives.</p>
        <p>Some wiped away tears during a slide show featuring photos of the victims and images of the mourning that took place on the Virginia Tech campus.</p>
        <p>''I think there has been a special connection because the shooter was Korean,'' said Jeannie Hwang Ng, 42, as she stood outside with other members. ''Our hearts really go out to the family.''</p>
        <p>The Rev. Hank Hahm, delivering a sermon to a Korean-American congregation at the Christ Central Presbyterian Church, said that everyone, including himself, feels angry and isolated at times.</p>
        <p>''I look at him and I look at his rantings and ravings, and he was disturbed,'' Mr. Hahm said, ''but he wasn't that different from me.''</p>
        <p>Won Sang Lee, before delivering a sermon at another service at the same church, to a congregation of mostly Korean-born immigrants, said in an interview that he would urge members to become more involved in each other's lives.</p>
        <p>''With our family members, make sure mentally and spiritually they are all right and to pay attention to our neighbors more closely, and see how we can help,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Jenny Chung, the wife of the Rev. Chung of Young Saeng Korean Presbyterian Church, said the Korean community felt an enormous sense of loss after the shootings, not only because many in the congregation have children who attend Virginia Tech, but because of what she views as potential tensions between Koreans and the neighborhoods they inhabit.</p>
        <p>Although Fairfax County remains home to more than 32,000 Koreans, whose numbers continue to rapidly increase, Ms. Chung said, ''We've still got a reputation as the minority in this area.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
