<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cold Shoulder, Perhaps Deserved, Hurts Baseball</title>
    <meta content="23rhoden" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/sports/baseball/23rhoden.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842448"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/William C Rhoden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Major League Baseball</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bonds, Barry</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Aaron, Hank</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Selig, Bud</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E5D8173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="853" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cold Shoulder, Perhaps Deserved, Hurts Baseball</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cold Shoulder Toward Bonds, Perhaps Deserved, Hurts Baseball</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rhoden, William C</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a month, maybe two, Barry Bonds is likely to break the most prestigious record in team sports. He will pass Hank Aaron to become the career home run leader and set a mark that may not be surpassed until late in his own lifetime. Bonds hit his 739th career home run Saturday in San Francisco and No. 740 yesterday.</p>
        <p>For those who thought that this broken-down veteran with a bad knee and a bad reality TV show was finished, Bonds is on fire.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Baseball’s greatest problem is its hypocrisy  its failure to face up to its complicity in creating a rampant drug culture and its attempt to sweep that era under the rug.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a month, maybe two, Barry Bonds is likely to break the most prestigious record in team sports. He will pass Hank Aaron to become the career home run leader and set a mark that may not be surpassed until late in his own lifetime. Bonds hit his 739th career home run Saturday in San Francisco and No. 740 yesterday.</p>
        <p>For those who thought that this broken-down veteran with a bad knee and a bad reality TV show was finished, Bonds is on fire.</p>
        <p>An accomplishment that seemed like a universe away is close enough to touch: Bonds needs 16 homers to pass Aaron.</p>
        <p>He will be baseball's king.</p>
        <p>Its emperor. Its czar.</p>
        <p>For Commissioner Bud Selig, Bonds is Major League Baseball's nightmare. With its head in the ground, baseball, with Selig in the lead, is treating Bonds like the bad dream come to life.</p>
        <p>While the San Francisco Giants are beginning to plan for the inevitable celebration, Major League Baseball, which should be taking the lead, is sitting back, wavering.</p>
        <p>''The Giants have begun to put together ideas for honoring Barry and paying tribute, and we look forward to hearing Major League Baseball's plans down the line,'' Larry Baer, the Giants' chief operating officer, said yesterday.</p>
        <p>''It's still early. He still needs 16 home runs, but we are beginning to put together ideas to celebrate the accomplishment.''</p>
        <p>What will baseball do? Specifically, how will Selig, and the current home run king, Aaron, deal with Bonds's imminent ascendancy to baseball's mountain top? Their respective responses will go a long way in setting the tone of the national discourse over Bonds as he approaches Aaron's mark.</p>
        <p>Will Aaron and Selig congratulate Bonds? Acknowledge a herculean feat few thought would be accomplished in their lifetimes?</p>
        <p>Or will Selig and Aaron, two old and dear friends, walk away?</p>
        <p>Sounds as if they plan to ignore him.</p>
        <p>Aaron has said he has no plans to attend an event commemorating Bonds's milestone. Selig has repeatedly--and cryptically -- said that baseball would provide an ''appropriate tribute,'' but he has not articulated what that means. He has not decided whether he will be present when Bonds reaches home run No. 755 and is one homer from the record.</p>
        <p>Earlier this month, Aaron told the Atlanta Journal Constitution columnist Terrence Moore, that he would be nowhere to be found.</p>
        <p>''I'd probably fly to West Palm Beach to play golf,'' Aaron said. ''Again, it has nothing to do with anybody, other than I had enough of it. I don't want to be around that sort of thing anymore. I just want to be at peace with myself. I don't want to answer questions.''</p>
        <p>Baseball has a tremendous problem, and in many ways, Selig and Aaron are making the problems worse, making the cloud over baseball thicker.</p>
        <p>Baseball's greatest problem is its hypocrisy -- its failure to face up to its complicity in creating a rampant drug culture and its attempt now to sweep that era under the rug.</p>
        <p>Baseball is larger than any given scandal, any one player or any one scoundrel. Baseball is larger than Aaron or Bonds or Selig. Aaron, despite his distaste for the news media, and for Bonds's demeanor, can set a tone of reconciliation.</p>
        <p>Precisely because he is so revered, Aaron must be on hand to congratulate Bonds.</p>
        <p>The overriding imperative must be getting the game back on track. Baseball caused its drug problems, is dealing with this issue and has moved on.</p>
        <p>I understand why Selig and Aaron want no part of Bonds: He can be difficult to deal with and he is universally suspected of consciously using performance-enhancing drugs, even though he has never been reported to have tested positive.</p>
        <p>Beyond that, Aaron is still wounded from the experience of catching and passing Babe Ruth. He received death threats and hate mail. On top of that, the commissioner at the time, Bowie Kuhn, was not present in 1974 when Aaron broke Ruth's career home run record.</p>
        <p>Now, 33 years later, Aaron has the opportunity to give Bonds the cold shoulder. As much as Bonds may deserve to be ignored, this is a time of reconciliation and moving forward. If anyone understands that, it's Aaron.</p>
        <p>I doubt that Aaron will change his mind. He has will of steel. He told Moore: ''It's going to be a no-win situation for me anyway. If I go, people are going to say, 'Well, he went because of this.' If I don't go, they'll say whatever. I'll just let them make their own mind up.''</p>
        <p>If baseball ever hopes to get out from under the so-called steroid era that it was slow in dealing with and move on, Aaron and the commissioner can set the tone. Attend the ceremony for Bonds, acknowledge the achievement.</p>
        <p>Barry Bonds is on a tear at age 42, and barring injury, he will soon be Major League Baseball's new home run king. Between then and now, Selig and Aaron will hopefully change each other's minds and attend the celebration whenever it comes and embrace the history.</p>
        <p>In the best interest of baseball.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: wcr@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: wcr@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
