<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>VOTING SETS UP LEFT-RIGHT DUEL TO LEAD FRANCE</title>
    <meta content="23france" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/world/europe/23france.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842433"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">France</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Sarkozy, Nicolas</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Royal, Segolene</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EED9173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1705" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>VOTING SETS UP LEFT-RIGHT DUEL TO LEAD FRANCE</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Voting Sets Up Left-Right Duel to Lead France</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELAINE SCIOLINO; Ariane Bernard contributed reporting from Normandy, Maia de la Baume from Paris and James Kanter from Argenteuil.</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, April 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nicolas Sarkozy, the conservative, and Ségolène Royal, the Socialist, won the first round of the presidential election on Sunday, setting up a classic left-right contest next month between two candidates with competing visions of how to govern France.</p>
        <p>Whoever is elected will also usher in a new generation of leadership: For the first time, France will have an elected president who did not come of age during World War II.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The presidential election is now a classic battle between two candidates with competing visions for France.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nicolas Sarkozy, the conservative, and Ségolène Royal, the Socialist, won the first round of the presidential election on Sunday, setting up a classic left-right contest next month between two candidates with competing visions of how to govern France.</p>
        <p>Whoever is elected will also usher in a new generation of leadership: For the first time, France will have an elected president who did not come of age during World War II.</p>
        <p>With more than 99 percent of the vote counted, Mr. Sarkozy was leading with about 30.7 percent of the vote, and Ms. Royal had about 25.2 percent. François Bayrou, the centrist who vowed to plot a new, conciliatory way of governing, came in a distant third with about 18.4 percent.</p>
        <p>A field of nine other candidates, including the far-right Jean-Marie Le Pen, who came in second in the first round in 2002, captured the remaining vote.</p>
        <p>The balloting on Sunday was marked by high anxiety, sunny weather and an exceptionally high turnout.</p>
        <p>More than 84 percent of France's 44.5 million registered voters cast ballots, about 13 percentage points higher than five years ago. The lines were so long at some polling stations that they had to stay open beyond their scheduled closing time of 8 p.m.</p>
        <p>The enormousness of the turnout was reflected in another statistic: By 5 p.m., 74 percent of France's registered voters had cast their ballots -- higher than the total percentage participation in the first round of the 2002 contest.</p>
        <p>The election finds the country in a gloomy mood. There is little confidence that the next president will succeed in reversing the economic decline of the country, whose gross domestic product per person in the past quarter-century has fallen to seventeenth place in the world, from seventh place.</p>
        <p>The country suffers from the fastest-growing public debt in Europe, high unemployment, entrenched protectionism, a bloated public sector and concerns about both immigration and the failure to integrate ethnic Arab and African populations.</p>
        <p>Minutes after the first results were announced, Mr. Sarkozy was at a rented hall in Paris, congratulating French voters for their wisdom for choosing him -- and Ms. Royal.</p>
        <p>Voters ''clearly marked their wish to go to the end of the debate between two ideas of the nation, two projects for society, two value systems, two concepts of politics,'' Mr. Sarkozy said.</p>
        <p>More than an hour later, Ms. Royal appeared before a rally in the Poitou-Charentes region, where she is regional president, promising to change France, but softly.</p>
        <p>Many French people, she said, ''do not want a France ruled by the law of the strongest or the most brutal, sewn-up by financial interests, where all powers are concentrated in the same few hands.'' She added, ''I am a free woman, as you are a free people.''</p>
        <p>Public opinion polls have predicted that Mr. Sarkozy, 52, head of the governing Union for a Popular Movement party and the former interior minister, could easily defeat Ms. Royal, 53, in the second round.</p>
        <p>An IPSOS poll conducted Sunday night after the voting ended indicated that Mr. Sarkozy would probably prevail with 54 percent of the vote against 46 percent for Ms. Royal.</p>
        <p>The shock and shame of a second-place showing by Mr. Le Pen in 2002 seems to have resonated among voters in Sunday's contest. In that election, Mr. Le Pen charged ahead of Lionel Jospin, the Socialist candidate and sitting prime minister, assuring the incumbent president, Jacques Chirac, of an overwhelming victory in the second round. Mr. Le Pen benefited at the time from an apathetic electorate, worries over an alarming rise in crime and a large field of candidates, some of whom drained support from Mr. Jospin.</p>
        <p>This time, many voters said they were deeply aware that their vote in the first round counted and broke with the long-held tradition of ''voting with their hearts,'' and then ''voting with their heads'' in the final round.</p>
        <p>That tendency gave the top two candidates about 56 percent of the vote. In 2002, by contrast, the vote was so splintered that the top two candidates got less than 37 percent of the vote.</p>
        <p>Mr. Le Pen won only about 10.5 percent of the vote this time, compared with 16.7 percent in 2002.</p>
        <p>''Listen, I must have made an error of judgment,'' a shaken Mr. Le Pen told about 300 supporters. He said he thought the French people were very unhappy, but instead, he said, ''The French are very happy. And the proof is that they have just re-elected -- my goodness, with a very comfortable lead and even a little more -- the parties that have been in power and who are responsible for the situation in France.''</p>
        <p>Since, as expected, no candidate won more than 50 percent of the vote, the election will be decided in a second round on May 6.</p>
        <p>The contest this time was marked by eleventh-hour suspense, fueled by the confusion, disillusionment and indecision of much of the electorate. Also, an aggressive voter registration campaign, particularly among the young and in ethnic African and Arab neighborhoods, added more than a million new voters to the rolls.</p>
        <p>The election now is transformed into a classic battle between representatives of the two big parties, one on the left and the other on the right. But whoever emerges as the winner will be the first president of France born after World War II and will be expected to make changes -- however undefined at the moment -- after 12 years of the stagnant presidency of Jacques Chirac.</p>
        <p>Certainly how Mr. Bayrou's supporters vote in the second round will be a factor. According to the CSA polling analyst Mathieu Doiret, Mr. Bayrou's voters lean slightly to the right of center.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Sarkozy, and Ms. Royal, who is seeking to become France's first woman president, have promised to break with the past and usher in a new era of leadership in France.</p>
        <p>But the election this time hinged as much around the personalities of the candidates as the issues. Throughout the campaign, Mr. Sarkozy and Ms. Royal have been deeply divisive candidates, pushing Mr. Bayrou into the spotlight as a champion of a new third way.</p>
        <p>Both have choleric characters and have portrayed themselves as victims. ''I am covered in scars,'' Mr. Sarkozy said just last week, while Ms. Royal repeatedly has charged that she is being treated unfairly because she is a woman.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sarkozy is a pragmatist who took a tough law-and-order approach as interior minister. He believes that France will progress only if its people work harder and has promised to lower personal and corporate taxes, eliminate obstacles to job creation but at the same time protect French corporations from foreign competition.</p>
        <p>Ms. Royal is a natural nurturer who pushes the ideal of ''participatory democracy,'' reduction of the powers of the presidency and the maintaining of France's generous social welfare system and strong state involvement in the economy.</p>
        <p>Throughout the country, even in deprived suburbs where unrest broke out in 2005, voters who chose Mr. Sarkozy said they did so out of a conviction that he was best qualified to revitalize the French economy, and because of his strong stand on law and order.</p>
        <p>In Argenteuil, the Paris suburb where Mr. Sarkozy in 2005 described young delinquents as ''scum,'' Jocelyne Chauvin, a 53-year-old post office administrator, said that security concerns had driven her to vote for Mr. Sarkozy.</p>
        <p>''We need to tighten things up,'' said Ms. Chauvin, adding that putting young people to work should be the highest priority for the next president.</p>
        <p>A rightward shift byMr. Sarkozy in recent months, including his adoption of some of the same right-wing language of Mr. Le Pen, resonated among many Le Pen voters.</p>
        <p>''When I see France invaded by immigrants from everywhere, and we practically did nothing about it and it continues -- that's why I've always voted Le Pen even though I didn't share his most extreme opinions,'' said Daniel Baboz, a 75-year-old retired bailiff who voted in an upscale neighborhood of Paris.</p>
        <p>''This time I voted for Sarko because recently he started speaking like Le Pen,'' he added, using a popular nickname for Mr. Sarkozy.</p>
        <p>Other voters, however, said they could not bring themselves to vote for Mr. Sarkozy because of his authoritarian approach.</p>
        <p>''I voted for Bayrou, but it was not a vote of trust,'' said Sophie Szerbojm, a 36-year-old dentist, after she voted in Paris. ''I vacillated until last night.'' The decisive factor for her, she added, was a trip to Israel where she heard a speech of Hitler at the Yad Vashem Holocaust memorial museum.</p>
        <p>''I was shocked to find troubling parallels, because Hitler's speech -- had been so seductive in 1933 and, bizarrely, it made me think of Sarkozy,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Many of the voters who chose Ms. Royal said they did it without enthusiasm. ''She's not on the left enough, she has to learn to speak better and fix the problems of the suburbs,'' said Sylvain Lesobre, a 33-year-old railway worker from the Paris suburb of Nanterre. But, he added, ''I always vote Socialist, and I don't like any of the others.''</p>
        <p>Nathalie Fergani, a 43-year-old technician from the town of Lanquetot in Normandy, said she made up her mind in the voting booth. ''In the end, I voted Ségolène to counter Sarkozy,'' she said. ''I hesitated, I stood there with both names in my hands for at least three minutes. But then I told myself, Ségolène. Bayrou, he'll get a lot of votes, but not enough to counter Sarkozy.''</p>
        <p>Some voters took the opposite tack, throwing their support to Mr. Bayrou in the belief he would be better positioned than Ms. Royal to beat Mr. Sarkozy in the second round.</p>
        <p>''It has to be anybody but Sarkozy, and Bayrou has the most chance of beating Sarkozy,'' said Jean-Claude Lombardo, a 54-year-old ophthalmologist in Paris.</p>
        <p>Still others chose one of several fringe candidates, arguing that politicians cannot be trusted. ''They're all liars,'' said Patrick Lefevre, a 47-year-old carpenter from a Paris suburb who voted for Arlette Laguiller, a Trotskyite. ''Once they're in place, they just want to stay there, where it's warm.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
