<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>State's Back At the Table In Planning Downtown</title>
    <meta content="23zero" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/arts/23zero.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842367"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEWS ANALYSIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom Tower (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom Tower (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Lower Manhattan Development Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">World Trade Center Memorial Foundation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Battery Park City Authority</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Lower Manhattan Cultural Council</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Port Authority of New York and New Jersey</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Spitzer, Eliot L</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Emil, David</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Schick, Avi</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E5DA173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1507" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>State's Back At the Table In Planning Downtown</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">State’s Back at the Table in Planning Downtown</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN POGREBIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pogrebin, Robin</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer's appointment last week of two top officials to a development corporation that had been considered all but dead appears to set the stage for yet another power struggle at ground zero.</p>
        <p>In a way it also seems to be a rebuke for the city's recent solo announcement that the Joyce Theater would be the sole occupant of a performing arts center planned for the former World Trade Center site. Many of those involved in planning Lower Manhattan now wonder whether the center, to be designed by Frank Gehry, will become the focus of a long tug of war.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer’s appointment of two top officials to a development corporation that had been considered all but dead appears to set the stage for another power struggle at ground zero.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer's appointment last week of two top officials to a development corporation that had been considered all but dead appears to set the stage for yet another power struggle at ground zero.</p>
        <p>In a way it also seems to be a rebuke for the city's recent solo announcement that the Joyce Theater would be the sole occupant of a performing arts center planned for the former World Trade Center site. Many of those involved in planning Lower Manhattan now wonder whether the center, to be designed by Frank Gehry, will become the focus of a long tug of war.</p>
        <p>The revival of the Lower Manhattan Development Corporation is perhaps the clearest sign that the Spitzer administration is determined to take back the reins, or at least strengthen its grip, on the center. Having chosen a master plan and a memorial design and allocated federal money for cultural programs, the development corporation said last summer that its work was done. The agency had already been defanged by George E. Pataki, then the governor; he had bowed to criticism from relatives of 9/11 victims and eliminated the Drawing Center and an International Freedom Center from the site. Yet last Monday Governor Spitzer announced that he had appointed Avi Schick as chairman of the development corporation and David Emil as president. Mr. Schick is also president of the Empire State Development Corporation, the state's economic development agency, and served as a deputy attorney general under Governor Spitzer, who was then attorney general. Mr. Emil owned Windows on the World, the restaurant at the top of the World Trade Center, and is a former president of the Battery Park City Authority.</p>
        <p>The same day, at a City Council committee hearing on the performing arts center, Mr. Schick made clear that the development corporation was coming back strong. ''L.M.D.C. will be the vehicle through which Governor Spitzer expresses his vision and articulates his voice in Lower Manhattan,'' he said. ''With new leadership and new direction, a reinvigorated L.M.D.C. will help revitalize an area that is important not only to New Yorkers but to all Americans.''</p>
        <p>For City Council members Mr. Schick's message was unambiguous. ''The state made it clear they are not delegating this issue to the city,'' said Councilman Alan J. Gerson, chairman of the council's Committee on Lower Manhattan Redevelopment, which held the hearing.</p>
        <p>Over the past year most of the development corporation's responsibilities have been assumed by other players. The World Trade Center Memorial Foundation had taken over planning for the memorial and a memorial museum. The city picked up the cultural component, seeking a new home for the Drawing Center and deciding that it would be too costly -- an estimated $700 million -- for the performing arts center to house both the Joyce and the Signature Theater.</p>
        <p>The city announced last month that the center would be occupied solely by the Joyce, which presents dance, and that the Signature, an Off Broadway theater, would seek to relocate to nearby Fiterman Hall, part of the City University of New York. ''The Pataki administration didn't stand up to the role at all,'' said Tom Healy, president of the Lower Manhattan Cultural Council. ''He abdicated it, and the city stepped in.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Schick's testimony makes clear that the state is back in the picture when it comes to the performing arts center. In view of costs and the overall state of construction at ground zero, Mr. Schick told the panel, the situation ''mandates that we return to the drawing board.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schick said that planners needed to identify sources of funds and determine a governance structure for the performing arts center. Any budget must also acknowledge that construction of the center cannot begin until 2011 because of a temporary PATH train exit at the site, he told the committee.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Schick also emphasized that the Spitzer administration was committed to ''the establishment of vibrant cultural institutions in Lower Manhattan,'' and that it would work with the city to make the performing arts center a reality.</p>
        <p>''Done right, a performing arts center will be a beautiful and meaningful addition to the cultural fabric of this city, a welcome and necessary addition to the life of Lower Manhattan and a potent salve that will erase the scars left by Sept. 11,'' he said.</p>
        <p>When Governor Spitzer took office in January, some critics of the master plan for ground zero hoped that he would seize the opportunity to cancel construction of the 1,776-foot Freedom Tower. He had previously referred to it as an unattractive ''white elephant'' and expressed doubts that it would draw enough tenants.</p>
        <p>But Governor Spitzer announced in February that while it was not the tower he would have wanted, he would support its continued construction.</p>
        <p>The performing arts center, on the other hand, is one of the few remaining projects at the site that is still in the planning stages, which affords the governor an opportunity to exert his influence.</p>
        <p>Officials at the affected arts organizations say they hope the expanded cast of characters will not mean more delays. ''They're the new players,'' said Linda Shelton, executive director of the Joyce Theater. ''I hope they follow the direction that the city is going in.''</p>
        <p>Yet even some cultural advocates are urging public officials to question whether a performing arts center makes economic sense at ground zero. ''I'm not a believer that, given its current scale and cost, it's a wise investment that we can afford,'' Mr. Healy said. ''There is no cachet to being there if the building can't be built, or if the building is built and no one can afford to run it.''</p>
        <p>Still unclear is who will be responsible for raising money for the institution. The city has estimated its cost -- together with that of creating three theaters for the Signature at Fiterman Hall -- at $350 million.</p>
        <p>Through the development corporation the state has committed $55 million to the performing arts component at ground zero, but only for organizations that are specifically on the site. As a result the city said it expected to make its contributions to the Signature project through the city's capital budget.</p>
        <p>The memorial foundation's mandate originally included raising money for an arts center, but that was abandoned in favor of concentrating on the memorial. The foundation's $350 million goal is now in sight; Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg said Tuesday that more than $165 million had been raised over the last six months, bringing the total so far to more than $300 million. Whether the foundation is willing to take up the performing arts center next remains an open question.</p>
        <p>In an interview Mr. Schick said the state had no interest in overpowering the city on ground zero, nor in refighting old battles. ''It's not that the city's role will be diminished, but that we will be an active partner working alongside them,'' he said. ''We're here. We have a presence. For projects like these, we're going to be part of the conversation.''</p>
        <p>''We're not going to revisit things that, for better or worse, have been decided,'' he added. ''On the other hand there is a lot that still has to be knit together if we are going to deliver the revitalized Lower Manhattan we have promised.''</p>
        <p>There were practical reasons for delaying the demise of the development corporation. Congressional legislation established it as a conduit for federal grants for ground zero from the Department of Housing and Urban Development. But the corporation was also a big symbol of state involvement.</p>
        <p>With Mayor Bloomberg now serving as chairman of the World Trade Center Memorial Foundation, some of those involved say, Governor Spitzer saw the Lower Manhattan Development Corporation as a possible counterweight. While it was created as a city-state agency, it is a subsidiary of the Empire State Development Corporation and has always been dominated by the state. The Lower Manhattan corporation also includes the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, which tips the balance toward the governor.</p>
        <p>What is more, Governor Spitzer, having just taken office, can play a role at ground zero until January 2011 -- or until 2015 if he wins a second term. Mayor Bloomberg must step down at the end of 2009. ''We will have a new mayor,'' said Madelyn Wils, a longtime director of the Lower Manhattan Development Corporation. ''It's an opportunity for the governor to make his mark. He'll be the only one around.''</p>
        <p>Some officials involved in rebuilding in Lower Manhattan, insisting on anonymity, say that Daniel L. Doctoroff, the city's deputy mayor for economic development and rebuilding, is distressed by the reinsertion of another strong player in the planning. But in a telephone interview Mr. Doctoroff said he welcomed Mr. Emil and Mr. Schick at the table. ''What I'd be more concerned about is if the state were not playing an active role,'' he said. ''We have to work together.''</p>
        <p>''However the state wants to manage its involvement in Lower Manhattan is perfectly fine with us,'' he added.</p>
        <p>NEWS ANALYSIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
