<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chaos in Somalia as Fighting Intensifies and Death Toll Rises</title>
    <meta content="23somalia" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/world/africa/23somalia.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842395"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Somalia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Somalia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Somalia</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E1DA173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="738" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chaos in Somalia as Fighting Intensifies and Death Toll Rises</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Chaos in Somalia as Fighting Intensifies and Death Toll Rises</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFFREY GETTLEMAN; Mohammed Ibrahim and Yuusuf Maxamuud contributed reporting from Mogadishu, Somalia.</byline>
      <dateline>NAIROBI, Kenya, April 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Government forces and insurgents in Somalia blasted each other for a fifth straight day on Sunday, killing scores of civilians and plunging the country deeper into chaos.</p>
        <p>United Nations officials say Somalia, which has gone 16 years without a central government, is headed toward its worst crisis ever. More than 320,000 people have fled Mogadishu, the capital, since heavy fighting erupted in February. Many are now trapped in wet, squalid camps ringing the capital, with relief efforts severely hampered by the increasingly dangerous conditions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Government forces and insurgents blasted each other for a fifth straight day on Sunday, killing scores of civilians and plunging the country deeper into chaos.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Government forces and insurgents in Somalia blasted each other for a fifth straight day on Sunday, killing scores of civilians and plunging the country deeper into chaos.</p>
        <p>United Nations officials say Somalia, which has gone 16 years without a central government, is headed toward its worst crisis ever. More than 320,000 people have fled Mogadishu, the capital, since heavy fighting erupted in February. Many are now trapped in wet, squalid camps ringing the capital, with relief efforts severely hampered by the increasingly dangerous conditions.</p>
        <p>Fatality figures vary widely, but the most conservative estimates put the toll from the past month near 1,000, with 200 people killed in the past week.</p>
        <p>Most of the victims are civilians caught in a cross-fire of shelling between insurgents and government troops. Entire city blocks and countless homes have been leveled.</p>
        <p>The shelling in some of Mogadishu's neighborhoods was so intense on Sunday that many residents were unable to get to hospitals -- or cemeteries. Some people buried their relatives in makeshift graves, along streets under mounds of gravel.</p>
        <p>''They are pounding us,'' said Fadumo Ali Hussein, a mother of eight children.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hussein said her sister bled to death on Sunday after she was hit by a piece of shrapnel.</p>
        <p>''We couldn't get her to a doctor,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Diplomatically, things look grim, too. On Saturday, Eritrea, a neighbor widely suspected by Ethiopian intelligence agents of supporting Islamists in Somalia, pulled out of a regional organization that had been acting as a counterweight to rising tensions in the region.</p>
        <p>The organization, the Intergovernmental Authority on Development, which included Kenya, Uganda, Djibouti, Ethiopia, Sudan, Somalia and Eritrea, was trying to broker peace in Somalia and address the combustible rivalry between Eritrea and Ethiopia. The two countries recently fought a costly border war, and many diplomats fear that Somalia could turn into a proxy battle, with Ethiopia supporting Somalia's weak transitional government and Eritrea backing the insurgents.</p>
        <p>The Foreign Ministry of Eritrea issued a short statement saying that it had ''suspended membership'' in the regional organization because of ''a number of repeated and irresponsible resolutions.''</p>
        <p>The African Union has also tried to intervene in Somalia and earlier this year promised to quickly dispatch 8,000 peacekeepers. But so far, only about 1,500 Ugandan soldiers have arrived, and they are mostly hunkered down at the airport in Mogadishu.</p>
        <p>Secretary General Ban Ki-moon of the United Nations said in a report released Friday that more drastic steps might need to be taken, including forming a ''coalition of the willing'' to step into Somalia to restore order.</p>
        <p>But Somalia's government seems to be in no mood to stop the fighting. Ali Mohamed Gedi, the transitional prime minister, warned Mogadishu's residents, thought to number around two million before the recent clashes, to clear out of the city because there was no cease-fire in sight.</p>
        <p>''Until the terrorists are wiped out from Somalia, the fighting will go on,'' Mr. Gedi said in a radio interview broadcast this weekend. ''The battle is clearly between terrorists linked to Al Qaeda and the government supported by Ethiopian and A.U. troops.''</p>
        <p>Many residents in Mogadishu disagree. They describe the insurgency as multiheaded -- and growing. Several witnesses said the men attacking the government and Ethiopian soldiers were a loose band of Somali nationalists, businessmen who have been profiting for years from a lack of government, clans opposed to the clan of the transitional president and radical Islamists.</p>
        <p>In December, Ethiopian troops helped topple the Islamist forces that controlled much of Somalia. Somalia's transitional government then entered the capital for the first time. In some neighborhoods, transitional leaders were greeted with cheers.</p>
        <p>But recently, the transitional government seems to have lost support, even among its own members. Last week, Hussein Aideed, a deputy prime minister, left Somalia for Eritrea, where he joined an alliance of former Islamist leaders. Mr. Aideed, who is still technically a member of the transitional government, called the Ethiopian counterinsurgency strikes a ''genocide.''</p>
        <p>Ethiopian and Somali officials have denied killing civilians intentionally. But at this point, it is getting difficult to find many people in Mogadishu who believe them.</p>
        <p>''Both sides are creating mayhem because they don't know how to fight a war,'' said Hassan Omar Osman, who was an officer in the Somali national army, which no longer exists. ''The insurgents are bad. But the government is really disgraceful.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
