<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Rivals Prepare for a Long Summer</title>
    <meta content="23chass" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/sports/baseball/23chass.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842400"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Atlanta Braves</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Chass, Murray</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Glavine, Tom</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E0DA173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="897" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Rivals Prepare for a Long Summer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Two Rivals Prepare for a Long Summer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Mets erupted for five runs against John Smoltz in the sixth inning for a 6-3 lead yesterday, they put themselves in position to have a delightful afternoon at sunny Shea Stadium.</p>
        <p>Tom Glavine suddenly was only three innings away from career victory No. 294, and the Mets were on their way to their third victory in six games with Atlanta this season and a game-and-a-half lead over the Braves in the National League East.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Braves are trying to bounce back after having watched the Mets end their unparalleled string of 14 division championships.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Mets erupted for five runs against John Smoltz in the sixth inning for a 6-3 lead yesterday, they put themselves in position to have a delightful afternoon at sunny Shea Stadium.</p>
        <p>Tom Glavine suddenly was only three innings away from career victory No. 294, and the Mets were on their way to their third victory in six games with Atlanta this season and a game-and-a-half lead over the Braves in the National League East.</p>
        <p>And then the Mets pulled the plug on themselves, especially the bullpen in a year in which the relief pitchers have been terrific. The outcome, a 9-6 Atlanta victory, left the Braves wondering if Chipper Jones's pregame assessment did not give them enough credit.</p>
        <p>This is the year the Braves are trying to bounce back after having watched the Mets end their unparalleled string of 14 division championships.</p>
        <p>''They're a better team than they were at this time last year,'' said Glavine, who played on 11 of the Braves' title teams. ''They're playing with a little bit of an edge this year. They lost last year for the first time in a long time, and they want to get back to a position they're accustomed to being in and trying to get that swagger back.''</p>
        <p>Jones, the Braves' elder statesman among everyday players, acknowledged the Braves' desire that Glavine spoke of, but he wasn't sure they were ready to reassert themselves.</p>
        <p>Responding to my observation that the Braves and the Mets were staging an interesting two-team division race, he said: ''It's been an interesting two-team division race thus far in April. Put it that way. I don't see us as equals with the Mets. They're head and shoulders the team to beat in this division. We started the season playing well, but I'm not ready and willing to anoint us in their league yet.''</p>
        <p>Jones's comments should not be taken lightly, as if he is deliberately playing poor mouth to take attention off the Braves and enable them to sneak up on the Mets.</p>
        <p>Just about a year ago, he gave a state-of-the-Braves report at my request and said of the Mets: ''They have a very good ball club. They're not just built to win the East; they're built for the long haul. They have all the attributes of a championship team -- a great manager, a solid bullpen, good starting pitching, an everyday lineup that can throw up runs in a big way.''</p>
        <p>The Mets proved him right, even if they stumbled in the last game of the league championship series against the St. Louis Cardinals.</p>
        <p>When Jones was asked yesterday what he saw as the Braves' possible shortcomings, he said: ''We've got a lot of young guys, and young guys aren't as consistent. If we have a hiccup like we did last year in June when we went 6-20, it could hurt us. I'm going to wait until our young guys show consistency for 162 games.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''Are we capable of playing with the Mets at any point during the season? Yes, we're capable of playing with them. We're capable of beating them. But I don't know if we're capable of going through a 162-game schedule as consistently as they can. They've got a lot of good, a lot of consistent players, players who have learned how to win.''</p>
        <p>The Mets, on the other hand, are not taking the Braves lightly.</p>
        <p>''We figure they're going to be around all summer long,'' Glavine said. ''I think they're the solid team we all felt they were coming out of spring training.''</p>
        <p>The Braves' comeback yesterday did nothing to alter Glavine's view.</p>
        <p>Faced with a three-run deficit and two outs and the bases empty in the seventh, the Braves rallied with a pair of three-run homers in successive innings against a bullpen that had allowed one home run in 48 2/3 innings in the first three weeks of the season.</p>
        <p>At the time the Braves staged their first rally, the Mets' relief corps had a major league-best 1.29 earned run average.</p>
        <p>''As good as our bullpen has been and figures to be, when something like this happens, I don't know if what you feel is more shock or more disappointment,'' Glavine said. ''But this kind of stuff is going to happen. Even knowing that, you're still surprised when it happens because the guys have been so good.''</p>
        <p>The uncharacteristic bullpen failure cost Glavine a chance to move closer to 300 victories.</p>
        <p>''I guess it's easy to think, 'Gosh, it would have gotten me one win closer,' but it's a long year and along the way I'll probably win some games I shouldn't have won or the bullpen will bail me out,'' Glavine said. ''But from the standpoint of wanting to get it over for my sake and the sake of the rest of the team, there's a little bit of a sting to it but not a lot.''</p>
        <p>Scott Schoeneweis, who gave up Édgar Rentería's game-tying home run in the seventh, also felt the sting.</p>
        <p>''I'd be lying if I said it's not in the back of your mind,'' he said of Glavine and 300. ''He's such a great guy and a professional. You want to see him win every game he pitches. It's tough.''</p>
        <p>But then he added, ''If that never happened to him, he'd probably have 400 wins.''</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
