<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Finding Her Inspirations Long Ago and Far Away</title>
    <meta content="23lore" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/arts/music/23lore.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070509T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842363"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DA173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="478" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Finding Her Inspirations Long Ago and Far Away</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Finding Her Inspirations Long Ago and Far Away</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN RATLIFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ratliff, Ben</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Canadian singer-songwriter Loreena McKennitt respects old ways: old nomenclature, customs, languages, architecture, literature. She has written songs that adapt verse from, or climb inside the heads of, Homer, Dante, Shakespeare and Tennyson. In her love of craftsmanship she seems bigger-souled than your average pop star; her way of praising her band, onstage at Radio City Music Hall on Friday night, was to suggest that its abilities were much greater than needed to play her simple music.</p>
        <p>Someone who loves travel and research this much and really seems to feel the stirrings of ancient voices -- you might expect such a person to have a hang-up about authenticity. To a degree she does. Playing for a fascinatingly docile audience, Ms. McKennitt's band used a hurdy-gurdy, an oud, a bouzouki and tabla drums. She herself played the harp or the accordion when not sitting at the piano and channeling distant centuries in a cool, even mezzo-soprano.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ms. McKennitt’s game is conjuring pleasant pop from popular thoughts about ancient cultures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Canadian singer-songwriter Loreena McKennitt respects old ways: old nomenclature, customs, languages, architecture, literature. She has written songs that adapt verse from, or climb inside the heads of, Homer, Dante, Shakespeare and Tennyson. In her love of craftsmanship she seems bigger-souled than your average pop star; her way of praising her band, onstage at Radio City Music Hall on Friday night, was to suggest that its abilities were much greater than needed to play her simple music.</p>
        <p>Someone who loves travel and research this much and really seems to feel the stirrings of ancient voices -- you might expect such a person to have a hang-up about authenticity. To a degree she does. Playing for a fascinatingly docile audience, Ms. McKennitt's band used a hurdy-gurdy, an oud, a bouzouki and tabla drums. She herself played the harp or the accordion when not sitting at the piano and channeling distant centuries in a cool, even mezzo-soprano.</p>
        <p>In composing her albums, which she produces herself, Ms. McKennitt has made a point of following historical trails. She has explored much about the ancient Celtic diaspora, for example, and more recently about the Silk Road, which gave her ideas for her latest record, ''An Ancient Muse'' (Quinlan Road). Between numbers on Friday she had some stimulating things to say about the psychology of nomadic tribes and (pertaining to ''Caravanserai,'' a new song about Silk Road rest stops) the concept of home in a place where disparate cultures are thrown together.</p>
        <p>But within frames of Celtic or Middle Eastern-sounding melodies and modes, a lot of Ms. McKennitt's music remains steadfastly bland. Her game is conjuring pleasant pop from popular thoughts about ancient cultures. (A version of this concert, recorded in September at the Alhambra in Spain, is to be shown, naturally, on PBS.)</p>
        <p>You could easily complain that there's a gap between the specificity of her texts and the specificity of her music, except that you'd be complaining to yourself. A huge audience sits happily in that gap. Much of that audience has been with her since she had an international hit, ''The Mummer's Dance,'' 10 years ago; many others had been listening to her for the decade before that.</p>
        <p>Her current tour is her first trip -- or ''journey,'' as she breathily said -- through North America since 1998, and she played with a nine-piece group. Light funk rhythms girded most of the songs, and the violinist Hugh Marsh played many of the lead lines, making you think of both Celtic and Arabic music.</p>
        <p>Occasionally Mr. Marsh and the electric guitarist, Brian Hughes, played a competent breakaway solo, but they hardly mattered; the ironbound show seemed a pop-literary endeavor almost more than a musical one. The musical ramifications of all those centuries of culture were never developed much before Ms. McKennitt's voice, pushing us back into the heavy mist of the journey.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 9, 2007, Wednesday  A music review on April 23 of the singer-songwriter Loreena McKennitt, at Radio City Music Hall, misstated the timing of PBS's showing of a concert of hers recorded in Spain in September. It has in fact already been shown, in March.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 9, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A music review on April 23 of the singer-songwriter Loreena McKennitt, at Radio City Music Hall, misstated the timing of PBS's showing of a concert of hers recorded in Spain in September. It has in fact already been shown, in March.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
