<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Debates Losing A Bit of Luster In a Big Field</title>
    <meta content="23debates" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/us/politics/23debates.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070425T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842464"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/John Edwards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Edwards, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">McCain, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Obama, Barack</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Richardson, Bill</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Romney, Mitt</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E1D8173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1075" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Debates Losing A Bit of Luster In a Big Field</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Debates Losing a Bit of Luster in a Big Field</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The last time Jonathan Prince checked, there were nearly 40 requests for John Edwards, the Democratic presidential candidate for whom he works, to appear at a candidate debate or forum.</p>
        <p>They came from state Democratic parties and county Democratic committees. From newspapers and television stations. From unions, advocates for the homeless, church groups, black Democrats, Hispanic Democrats, Jewish Democrats and an association of big-city mayors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Aides to the major candidates have concluded that the large number of debates has become a hindrance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The last time Jonathan Prince checked, there were nearly 40 requests for John Edwards, the Democratic presidential candidate for whom he works, to appear at a candidate debate or forum.</p>
        <p>They came from state Democratic parties and county Democratic committees. From newspapers and television stations. From unions, advocates for the homeless, church groups, black Democrats, Hispanic Democrats, Jewish Democrats and an association of big-city mayors.</p>
        <p>''It's a mess,'' said an exasperated-sounding Mr. Prince, Mr. Edwards's deputy campaign manager. ''Debates are important, but in these big multicandidate races they end up not being an exchange of ideas, but just an exchange of sound bites. They have become a distraction.''</p>
        <p>A flood of invitations is besieging Republican and Democratic presidential candidates alike this year, thrusting them into a complicated political vortex as they struggle to balance their own needs with the demands of sensitive and powerful debate sponsors whom candidates are eager not to offend.</p>
        <p>The result has been public -- and not-so-public -- maneuvering by candidates from both parties as they try to limit the number of debates without making it look as if they might be trying to limit the number of debates. The sprint begins with a Democratic debate this Thursday in South Carolina and a Republican debate a week later in California.</p>
        <p>After a private dinner of Democratic campaign managers at a Washington steakhouse last month with Howard Dean, the Democratic National Committee chairman, the party agreed that starting in July it would limit debates to one a month through the end of the year. Mr. Dean, blocking for his candidates, will choose the sponsors.</p>
        <p>But the situation is more fluid among Republicans, where private negotiations among aides to the leading candidates in hopes of doing what the Democrats are trying to do have had no effect.</p>
        <p>''We're getting deluged,'' said Brian Jones, the communications director for Senator John McCain, Republican of Arizona. ''If you actually ended up saying yes to every debate, you'd have a debate a week until the Iowa caucuses.''</p>
        <p>''It's important to participate in the debates, but there becomes a point of diminishing returns and insanity: I mean, does it make sense for us to do the Huffington Post debate?'' Mr. Jones continued, referring to a well-known liberal blog. ''I think probably not. Arianna Huffington called me at home. I said no.'' Not everybody is applauding efforts to limit campaign debates. Some of the lesser-known candidates view them as a way to get attention in a campaign that often seems to be an Obama-Clinton-Giuliani-McCain blur.</p>
        <p>''The D.N.C. should stand firm and demand as many debates as possible,'' said Bill Richardson, the Democratic governor of New Mexico who is running for president. ''This is one way there is equity in this presidential process because there are several candidates with alarmingly more money and resources than everyone else.''</p>
        <p>''It's wrong,'' Mr. Richardson said. ''It's a way to shirk their responsibilities as full-fledged candidates.''</p>
        <p>Would-be sponsors of debates on specific issues like homelessness or the fight against poverty expressed some frustration that they had been shut out to date.</p>
        <p>''I can see it from both sides,'' said the Rev. David Beckmann, president of the Alliance to End Hunger, who tried to arrange a June candidate forum. ''It's difficult for the candidates. But on the other hand, we'd like to know from both Republicans and Democrats what they are going to do about poverty.''</p>
        <p>Some organizers say they are looking for ways to entice candidates. Advocates for the homeless are considering a vigil by homeless people outside the offices of the candidates to try to promote a debate on poverty as part of the 11th Annual Homelessness Marathon in San Francisco in January. The organizer of the effort, Jeremy Alderson, said he had asked all the campaigns to participate.</p>
        <p>''The Democrats didn't even mention homelessness in their 2004 platform,'' Mr. Alderson said. ''We know we've got to do something to attract their attention.''</p>
        <p>As much as debates may be viewed as integral to American democracy, aides to the major candidates have concluded that the sheer number of debate and forum demands combined with a sprawling field of candidates on both sides have made them more of a hindrance than a help, at least for now.</p>
        <p>They are, the argument goes, time-consuming and money-burning obligations in which a candidate will realistically get perhaps eight minutes to lay out his views. That is because of the many candidates that are guaranteed to be on stage, since the field on both sides includes candidates that most voters -- indeed, most political reporters -- have probably never heard of.</p>
        <p>In that kind of situation, the most likely way to stand out from the pack is to make a mistake.</p>
        <p>The cost of participating in a debate? Days spent on preparation and travel to the often smaller cities where the forums are held. These obligations can take candidates out of states like Iowa and New Hampshire, with their culture of relatively small candidate-to-voter encounters, which presumably can be more valuable for candidate and voters alike. And there is the actual cost of getting the candidate and the large staff contingent needed for a debate to the site, including policy experts and press aides whose job is to tell reporters how well the candidate did.</p>
        <p>''There is a lot to do this year,'' said David Plouffe, campaign manager for Senator Barack Obama, Democrat of Illinois. ''There are four early primary states, and there could be more. There is grass-roots work to do with voters. There are resources to raise. You have a Senate schedule for us in Washington.</p>
        <p>''Voters are going to have ample opportunity to see these candidates together,'' Mr. Plouffe continued.</p>
        <p>The Democrats' first-of-the-season debate, the one in South Carolina, is sponsored by the state Democratic Party -- ''and this one has commercial breaks,'' Mr. Plouffe said as he calculated the diminished minutes left for his candidate.</p>
        <p>From there, the candidates are to board charter and commercial planes to San Diego, site of a weekend-long forum sponsored by the California Democratic Party.</p>
        <p>The first Republican debate will be at the Ronald W. Reagan Presidential Library and Museum in Simi Valley, Calif. Republican candidates have said no to a debate proposed for April sponsored by the television station WMUR in New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>But, said Carl Forti, the political director for the campaign of Mitt Romney, the former Republican governor of Massachusetts, ''you're not going to say no to Mrs. Reagan.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 25, 2007, Wednesday  A front-page article on Monday about an increase in debate requests for presidential candidates referred incorrectly in some copies to the timing of a debate promoted by advocates for the homeless. The debate has been proposed for January 2008 during the 11th Annual Homelessness Marathon, a nationwide radio broadcast originating in San Francisco. The advocates did not propose it for this past February in Fresno, Calif., during the 10th marathon broadcast.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 25, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A front-page article on Monday about an increase in debate requests for presidential candidates referred incorrectly in some copies to the timing of a debate promoted by advocates for the homeless. The debate has been proposed for January 2008 during the 11th Annual Homelessness Marathon, a nationwide radio broadcast originating in San Francisco. The advocates did not propose it for this past February in Fresno, Calif., during the 10th marathon broadcast.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
