<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Greater (and the Lesser) Considered at the Ad Summit</title>
    <meta content="23adcol" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/business/media/23adcol.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842357"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">American Assn of Advertising Agencies</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E7DA173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="989" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Greater (and the Lesser) Considered at the Ad Summit</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Greater (and the Lesser) Considered at the Ad Summit</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STUART ELLIOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <dateline>NAPLES, Fla.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here is a look back at some of the highlights, lowlights and sidelights of the 2007 management conference of the American Association of Advertising Agencies, known as the Four A's, which was held here last Wednesday through Friday.</p>
        <p>GIMME A 'D'? -- Before his speech to the conference on Thursday, Howard Draft, chairman and chief executive at Draft FCB, part of the Interpublic Group of Companies, spoke with Andrew McMains, a reporter for the trade publication Adweek, about his agency's performance in the annual Agency Report Cards issue, which came out last week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The highlights, lowlights and sidelights of the 2007 management conference of the American Association of Advertising Agencies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here is a look back at some of the highlights, lowlights and sidelights of the 2007 management conference of the American Association of Advertising Agencies, known as the Four A's, which was held here last Wednesday through Friday.</p>
        <p>GIMME A 'D'? -- Before his speech to the conference on Thursday, Howard Draft, chairman and chief executive at Draft FCB, part of the Interpublic Group of Companies, spoke with Andrew McMains, a reporter for the trade publication Adweek, about his agency's performance in the annual Agency Report Cards issue, which came out last week.</p>
        <p>Needless to say, Mr. Draft was not thrilled that Draft FCB had received a grade of C minus over all and a grade of D for how the agency was managed in 2006.</p>
        <p>''The last time I got a D was in high school,'' Mr. Draft told Mr. McMains, ''and that was when I wasn't going to class.''</p>
        <p>THE GRIPES OF ROTH -- Each year, the Four A's tries to schedule a speaker who is the chairman or the chief executive, or both, of one of the giant holding companies that own many of its member agencies. This year, filling that slot was Michael I. Roth, chairman and chief at Interpublic.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roth described how he led insurance companies like the Mony Group before taking over the helm at Interpublic.</p>
        <p>''I was your typical client,'' Mr. Roth said, in that ''I guess you could say I was a pain.''</p>
        <p>Actually, Mr. Roth said, he is not new to advertising, having spent ''35 years in the industry'' -- only it was ''all crammed into two years.'' His rueful reference was to his work to solve the myriad financial and operational difficulties that have hampered Interpublic's performance.</p>
        <p>SAY WHAT? -- When advertising executives speak at conferences before their peers, jargon tends to creep into their remarks.</p>
        <p>For instance, Mr. Roth in his speech urged the audience to ''break down the silos'' that keep different disciplines within agencies from working together and that impede the development of ''holistic solutions'' to clients' problems.</p>
        <p>At another point, Mr. Roth suggested that ''interdependence'' was ''the way to deliver the holistic offering.''</p>
        <p>And in explaining why certain campaigns resonated with consumers in the last year, Susan Gianinno, chairwoman and chief executive at Publicis USA, part of the Publicis Worldwide division of the Publicis Groupe, praised them for ''linking and integrating experiences across interconnection points to deepen and broaden involvement.''</p>
        <p>SO LONG, FAREWELL -- The conference was likely to be the last one to be presided over by O. Burtch Drake, president and chief executive at the Four A's. Mr. Drake, 65, intends to retire at the end of the year, he said, after leading the association since January 1994. A committee has been named to oversee the search for a successor, working with a consultant, Gilbert &amp; Partners.</p>
        <p>''It's a good time for me to be moving on,'' Mr. Drake said. ''The hope is to have my replacement on board in early 2008.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Drake listed among his accomplishments leading the organization through two recessions, the dot-com bust and the ''ongoing predictions in the press that the advertising agency business is doomed.''</p>
        <p>Among the issues that face the industry, Mr. Drake cited ''attracting and retaining the right talent'' as paramount, particularly minority employees, because ''diversity in the ranks of ad agencies still has a very long way to go.''</p>
        <p>There was no formal send-off for Mr. Drake at the conference. Rather, he is to be ''roasted'' at the Friars Club in September, during Advertising Week in New York.</p>
        <p>''I did agree'' to it, Mr. Drake said, laughing. ''I don't know what I was thinking.''</p>
        <p>AT A CROSSROADS -- The choice of a successor to Mr. Drake is expected to help set a course for the Four A's for years to come as the organization seeks to remain relevant while sweeping changes remake the industry.</p>
        <p>Some executives involved in the search said they hoped to hire a chief executive with a background in the fastest-growing parts of the business, like digital advertising and new media. The executives spoke on the condition of anonymity because the search process is getting under way.</p>
        <p>The executives also said they would be pleased if the age of the next chief executive began with a ''3'' or ''4'' rather than a ''5'' or ''6.'' Their most ambitious goal of all: hiring the first woman, black or Hispanic to lead the Four A's.</p>
        <p>BRAND LAND -- Each year, sponsors help the Four A's defray the cost of the conference. They are usually media companies hoping to catch the attention of the senior agency managers who attend the event.</p>
        <p>At the first conference over which Mr. Drake presided, in 1994, sponsors included the Big Three broadcast television networks, he recalled. But now ABC, CBS and NBC are gone, replaced by ''MSN, Google, AOL and Yahoo, among others,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''In these days of clutter in advertising, there's a lot of clutter in our sponsors,'' Mr. Drake said, ''but we do appreciate their support.''</p>
        <p>Actually, as conference clutter goes, the 12 sponsors were not that many. By comparison, the conference last October of the organization that is the counterpart to the Four A's, the Association of National Advertisers, had 51 sponsors.</p>
        <p>Attendees at the Four A's conference could drink coffee and tea at the breakfasts from oversize china cups bearing the Yahoo logo. Google set up six PCs. And at one reception, AOL, part of Time Warner, gave away cigars made of tobacco or chocolate.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most visible sponsor was the Microsoft Digital Advertising Solutions division of Microsoft, which sells ads for units like MSN and the Xbox video game system.</p>
        <p>The division had an elaborate sand sculpture built on the beach at the opening reception Wednesday night, and bought ad space on the plastic key cards attendees used at the conference hotel.</p>
        <p>ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
