<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When David Faced a Wounded Goliath</title>
    <meta content="23fros" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/theater/reviews/23fros.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842362"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brantley, Ben</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morgan, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grandage, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sheen, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Langella, Frank</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Frost/Nixon (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Donmar Warehouse Theater</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Morgan, Peter</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Langella, Frank</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Sheen, Michael</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Nixon, Richard Milhous</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Grandage, Michael</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Nixon, Richard Milhous</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kunken, Stephen</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Frost, David</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Frost/Nixon (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE6DA173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1271" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When David Faced a Wounded Goliath</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">When David Faced a Wounded Goliath</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN BRANTLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brantley, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Brantley reviews Peter Morgan play Frost/Nixon, directed by Michael Grandage; Michael Sheen and Frank Langella star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Television mows down a titan in ''Frost/Nixon,'' the briskly entertaining new play by Peter Morgan about the 1977 face-off between its title characters, the British talk show host (as in David) and the former American president (as in Richard M.). But let it be proclaimed, with drums and fanfare, that theater decisively trumps television in the production that opened last night at the Bernard B. Jacobs Theater.</p>
        <p>Most of the credit for this victory belongs to a truly titanic performance from the man playing the famously sweaty victim of a cool medium. That's Frank Langella, whose portrayal of Nixon is one of those made-for-the-stage studies in controlled excess in which larger-than-life seems truer-to-life than merely life-size ever could.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This briskly entertaining new play by Peter Morgan has been staged with the momentum of a ticking-bomb thriller and the zing of a boulevard comedy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Television mows down a titan in ''Frost/Nixon,'' the briskly entertaining new play by Peter Morgan about the 1977 face-off between its title characters, the British talk show host (as in David) and the former American president (as in Richard M.). But let it be proclaimed, with drums and fanfare, that theater decisively trumps television in the production that opened last night at the Bernard B. Jacobs Theater.</p>
        <p>Most of the credit for this victory belongs to a truly titanic performance from the man playing the famously sweaty victim of a cool medium. That's Frank Langella, whose portrayal of Nixon is one of those made-for-the-stage studies in controlled excess in which larger-than-life seems truer-to-life than merely life-size ever could.</p>
        <p>No screen, big or small, could accommodate such showy grandeur. And it's telling that when this production -- which recreates the story behind the widely watched television interviews between Nixon and Mr. Frost (the excellent Michael Sheen) -- projects Mr. Langella's image onto the bank of monitors at the back of the stage, his face registers as that of some grotesque mythic creature in uncomfortable captivity.</p>
        <p>This tension between camera and subject italicizes a central theme of ''Frost/Nixon,'' a British import staged, with the momentum of a ticking-bomb thriller and the zing of a boulevard comedy, by Michael Grandage, the artistic director of the Donmar Warehouse in London. Structured as a prize fight between two starkly ambitious men in professional crisis, ''Frost/Nixon'' makes it clear that the competitor who controls the camera reaps the spoils.</p>
        <p>It should be stated that Mr. Morgan, whose more sophisticated screenplay for the movie ''The Queen'' also dealt with the triumph of spin over substance, is guilty of spelling out his message too bluntly. ''The first and greatest sin of television is that it simplifies, diminishes,'' he has one of his characters say. The same accusation could be leveled against ''Frost/ Nixon.'' The play asks us to take on faith Frost's understanding of ''the power of the close-up,'' instead of giving us real evidence of his mastery of the medium. Much of what happens behind the scenes, as Frost's team prepares to take on the notoriously slippery Nixon, has an improbably naïve, college studentish air. (''Hey, guys, let's put on a show to humiliate Tricky Dick.'')</p>
        <p>And to enhance the play's nail-biting quotient, which hinges on whether Frost will induce Nixon to apologize for his role in Watergate, Mr. Morgan has blithely rejiggered and rearranged facts and chronology.</p>
        <p>(To appreciate how wide some of the discrepancies are, read ''The Conviction of Richard Nixon: The Untold Story of the Frost/Nixon Interviews'' the coming memoir by James Reston Jr. -- who appears as a character in this play, convincingly played by Stephen Kunken -- about his experience as one of Frost's advisers on the interviews.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Morgan, a specialist in fact-based fiction for screen and television (''The Queen,'' ''The Last King of Scotland'' and, for British television, ''The Deal''), has spoken of ''the difference between accuracy and truth'' in eliciting private drama from public records. But here he sometimes seems to be forsaking accuracy less in the pursuit of truth than of conventional entertainment value.</p>
        <p>This means that while Nixon scholars may gnash their teeth, average theatergoers are likely to have a good time. The structure of ''Frost/Nixon'' -- a time-skipping, globe-spanning montage of narrative scenes and expository asides, largely delivered by Mr. Kunken as Mr. Reston and Corey Johnson as Jack Brennan, Nixon's top aide de camp -- makes more for lively breadth than penetrating depth. (Christopher Oram's set and Neil Austin's terrific lighting help keep the play fast and fluid.)</p>
        <p>But it does allow two superb actors to explore the racing, anxious minds behind two much-photographed faces. Admittedly Mr. Sheen has the less rewarding job. One of the brightest actors of the London stage, who has presented his own searing take on the pathology of power in the title role of the Donmar's production of Camus's ''Caligula,'' Mr. Sheen is best known for his sly, multidimensional portraits of Prime Minister Tony Blair in ''The Queen'' and ''The Deal.''</p>
        <p>As written by Mr. Morgan, the character of David Frost offers fewer complexities to snack on. He is presented as a bit of a celebrity bimbo, a vain man who lives for the perfect table in the best restaurant amid A-list companions. What makes him worthy of concentrated attention here is the raw hunger of his ambition and the insecurity that feeds it.</p>
        <p>Though his surface remains relentlessly, well, superficial and upbeat, this character brims with the self-doubts and need for approval that keep him in motion. Look for the barely perceptible flinch, like that of someone pricked by a needle, that Mr. Sheen produces every time the term ''talk show host'' crops up.</p>
        <p>This is the mien of a man afraid of being pegged as a fraud and determined not to let that happen. This makes him the ideal listener in the show's high point, a late-night phone call Frost receives from a drunken Nixon, on the eve of the last of their series of interviews.</p>
        <p>The moment is one of the few in the play that is pure fabrication. Yet it rings ineffably true. It makes us feel, rather than only register intellectually, the extent to which these two mismatched men are emotional mirrors.</p>
        <p>Throughout the production Mr. Langella's Nixon has come across as a man of quick intellect, maudlin sentimentality, vulgar wit and studied social reflexes that have never acquired the semblance of natural grace. You are always aware of someone who struggles to conceal not only a defensive self-consciousness but also a cancerous anger and fear.</p>
        <p>That's what comes to the surface, like black bilious lava, in the phone-call scene. And it's one of those great moments, which only theater affords, when acting takes on the tidal force of an operatic aria.</p>
        <p>From the moment he steps onstage, with his hunched walk and lumbering step, Mr. Langella has avoided the obvious route of Rich Little-style impersonation of one of the most impersonated figures in history. What he delivers instead is an interpretation that, without imitation, still captures and exaggerates Nixon's essential public traits: the buttered-gravel voice, the scowling smile, the joviality that seemed to contain an implicit threat.</p>
        <p>The friend with whom I saw the play asked me afterward if I had noticed how much better Mr. Langella's Nixon impersonation became as the show progressed. Mr. Langella's performance had not changed, but by evening's end it had eclipsed the familiar photographic image of the real man. Like Helen Mirren's understated Elizabeth II in ''The Queen,'' this overstated Nixon seems destined forever to blend into and enrich the perceptions of its prototype for anyone who sees it.</p>
        <p>Frost/Nixon</p>
        <p>By Peter Morgan; directed by Michael Grandage; sets and costumes by Christopher Oram; lighting by Neil Austin; music and sound by Adam Cork; video design by Jon Driscoll; hair and wig design by Richard Mawbey; general manager, 101 Productions Ltd.; production stage manager, Rick Steiger; technical supervisors, Aurora Productions (United States) and Patrick Molony (Britain). The Donmar Warehouse production presented by Arielle Tepper Madover, Matthew Byam Shaw, Robert Fox, Act Productions, David Binder, Debra Black, Annette Niemtzow/Harlene Freezer and the Weinstein Company. At theBernard B. Jacobs Theater, 242 West 45th Street, Manhattan; (212) 239-6200. Through Aug. 18. Running time: 1 hour 40 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Frank Langella (Richard Nixon), Michael Sheen (David Frost), Remy Auberjonois (John Birt), Shira Gregory (Evonne Goolagong), Corey Johnson (Jack Brennan), Stephen Kunken (James Reston Jr.), Stephen Rowe (Swifty Lazar/Mike Wallace), Triney Sandoval (Manolo Sanchez), Armand Schultz (Bob Zelnick) and Sonya Walger (Caroline Cushing).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
