<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Philadelphia Journalism's New Order</title>
    <meta content="23inky" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/business/media/23inky.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070430T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842389"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Philadelphia (Pa)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Philadelphia Inquirer</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Tierney, Brian</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E2DA173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1919" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Philadelphia Journalism's New Order</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Philadelphia Journalism’s New Order</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Starting next week, The Philadelphia Inquirer will run a new column called PhillyInc., written by Inquirer reporters and editors, on the first page of its business section.</p>
        <p>What is unusual is that the column will be sponsored by a local advertiser, Citizens Bank. It will carry the bank's logo and be outlined in the bank's distinctive green ink. The bank will also run ads across the bottom of the page and in an upper corner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At The Philadelphia Inquirer, a joint venture with an advertiser that in other times might have raised questions is being rethought.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Starting next week, The Philadelphia Inquirer will run a new column called PhillyInc., written by Inquirer reporters and editors, on the first page of its business section.</p>
        <p>What is unusual is that the column will be sponsored by a local advertiser, Citizens Bank. It will carry the bank's logo and be outlined in the bank's distinctive green ink. The bank will also run ads across the bottom of the page and in an upper corner.</p>
        <p>Many newspapers are losing advertising revenue these days and have taken steps that they might not have taken when times were flush. But at The Inquirer, everything -- even a joint venture with an advertiser that in other times might have raised questions about editorial integrity -- is being rethought.</p>
        <p>The sponsored column is part of the new world here as Brian P. Tierney, a local advertising executive, settles in as the paper's hands-on publisher and promoter in chief for what has become a grand experiment in private local ownership of a major metropolitan daily.</p>
        <p>It is being closely watched in the newspaper industry -- still made up mostly of public companies -- where the Tribune Company, owner of The Los Angeles Times, Chicago Tribune and Newsday, is going private and others are considering such moves, to get away from the harsh, disapproving glare of Wall Street. And it is being watched by journalists to see whether a once-great newspaper with scaled-back ambitions can still fly.</p>
        <p>Since spearheading the purchase nine months ago, Mr. Tierney, a hard-charging entrepreneur, has avoided a strike while extracting concessions from the paper's unions and laying off 17 percent of newsroom employees. He has also poured millions of dollars into promotion and new equipment, reaching deals with advertisers and hiring columnists on contract -- which is cheaper than hiring regular staff members.</p>
        <p>And he has brought in a new editor, William K. Marimow, a former Inquirer reporter and two-time Pulitzer Prize winner, who has the widespread respect of the staff and lends journalistic credibility to Mr. Tierney's venture. ''Now,'' Mr. Tierney said, ''I'm more confident than I was nine months ago.''</p>
        <p>He said statistics supported his confidence: daily circulation has held up over the last six months, rising 0.6 percent to about 352,600, while circulation at most other papers is down. Ad revenue for the company has ''significantly improved'' from the period a year earlier. (Because the company is privately owned, the numbers are not available.) And page views on the Web site, www.philly.com, have climbed to 30 million a month from 20 million in July.</p>
        <p>Just as important, readers and even critics have been impressed by the newspaper.</p>
        <p>''Some days I'll look at The Inquirer and say, 'Wow!''' said Michael Days, the editor of The Inquirer's sister paper, The Daily News. ''You'd rarely see a columnist on the front or a sports story leading the paper, and now you do.''</p>
        <p>But these nine months have been trying. Many in the newsroom are still bitter about the concessions -- on pensions, sick pay and seniority -- and they are stretched thin. The staff, now 330, is half its size in the paper's heyday in the 1980s and '90s. The layoffs cost the paper many of its younger and minority journalists.</p>
        <p>Andrew Maykuth, a longtime foreign correspondent who has returned to the metropolitan desk, said: ''I'm not happy about losing my pension, and I hope if we keep the numbers up that Brian Tierney will consider chipping into my 401(k). Hiring Bill was a stroke of genius, but there is still a lot of grumbling, and you can see the stress levels because we're so short-staffed.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Marimow said that when he arrived in November from National Public Radio, morale at The Inquirer was ''F minus'' and that by the time of the layoffs in January, it had dropped to ''F minus minus.'' Amid that, he had to take time off early this year for prostate cancer surgery (he says now that his health is excellent).</p>
        <p>Mr. Marimow has set about reorganizing the newsroom, learning to do less with a lot less. While saying that The Inquirer is a work in progress, he saw ''signs of promise,'' first in his reshaping of the paper and second in interest expressed to him by former Inquirer editors and reporters in coming back. To make it easier to recruit talent, Mr. Tierney has pledged that there would be no more layoffs.</p>
        <p>''Unless a meteor hits this building, I can honestly say to folks that this is it,'' Mr. Tierney said in an interview in his tower office above the newsroom. ''I said to Bill, 'I won't come back in October and say the numbers are off,' and I shook his hand on that. There isn't another shoe to drop.''</p>
        <p>While Mr. Marimow and Mr. Tierney might seem worlds apart -- the ad man and the methodical, shoe-leather journalist -- they say they are working together as partners, with much e-mail back and forth during the day.</p>
        <p>This has included Mr. Marimow's blessing of the column sponsored by Citizens Bank, which rankles many in the newsroom because it looks as if the newspaper's editorial content has been co-opted.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Tierney said that the column was just the kind of high-visibility, creative ''brand-building'' opportunity that advertisers crave.</p>
        <p>Mr. Marimow said he had come to terms with it. ''Instinctively, as a reporter, I would have recoiled at the idea,'' he said in an interview in his office off the newsroom. But he also said that the editorial staff would have complete, independent control. And that some of the revenue from the bank's ads would go toward hiring an editor for the column. He said the new hire and more content were worth the tradeoff for what he said would be ''discreet'' labeling. Moreover, he said, if Citizens Bank was involved in anything untoward, the paper would aggressively report such news prominently.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tierney and Mr. Marimow said they see eye to eye on their mission: to make The Inquirer (including its Web site) the indispensable source of news for Philadelphia, its suburbs and South Jersey.</p>
        <p>While that might seem a logical step for a regional paper, The Inquirer is under pressure to live up to a distinguished past. In the 1970s and '80s, Gene Roberts, the executive editor, guided it to 17 Pulitzer Prizes in 18 years as the newspaper covered important national and international issues. Now, the first section of The Inquirer still carries articles on national and international subjects, but most of them are from other newspapers or wire services.</p>
        <p>It has also pulled back from the heavily local news coverage it once provided, down to the township level, as it tries to ''right-size'' its mission to the size of the staff. But Mr. Marimow sees no loss of aspiration. The Inquirer's reporting laid the groundwork for the recent federal indictment of a prominent state senator. The story of a local woman still struggling with the effects of a car accident from more than three decades ago dominated the front page on a recent Sunday and filled two inside pages. ''It was short at 120 inches,'' Mr. Marimow said.</p>
        <p>The new metropolitan editor, Vernon Loeb, a former Inquirer reporter who was until recently the California investigations editor at The Los Angeles Times, said he is trying to steer reporters to cover the region as a national or foreign correspondent might, with articles that appeal to readers across the area, not just to a narrow segment.</p>
        <p>''It's simpler here now,'' Mr. Loeb said. ''We have to do one thing well -- cover our region. But every assignment you make has a tradeoff. There are lots of things we are not covering, and that is a problem. Deciding that murder is a priority is pretty simple. But we're not covering mental health, or poverty or higher education -- some pretty basic things.''</p>
        <p>While the top editors say that they want more selective local coverage, staff members say this is easier said than done.</p>
        <p>''It's a juggling act,'' said Monica Yant Kinney, a columnist. ''We have huge swaths of land to cover and a very limited staff, and there is confusion on a daily basis over what people are supposed to be doing.''</p>
        <p>Henry Holcomb, a reporter who is also president of the Newspaper Guild's local unit, said he is now covering five beats. ''Yes, the anger is slightly less intense,'' Mr. Holcomb said. ''Bill is a good, stabilizing force. He's the gold standard on reporting. But the crisis is not over.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Maykuth, the former foreign correspondent, said there was still a disjunction between management's goals and the daily response. ''People are still trying to do the coverage we used to, and Marimow's standards are so high, the message is clear that you can't underreport a story,'' he said. ''They haven't come to terms with that; they want to be what we were and cover everything.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Maykuth, who is now covering the Philadelphia mayoral race, said he was beginning to prefer local coverage to globetrotting. He said his dispatches from Afghanistan were met with ''silence'' from readers, but when he wrote in January about swaying exit ramps at Lincoln Financial Field, where the Eagles play, he received ''a ton'' of e-mail messages and letters.</p>
        <p>What seems most encouraging to the newsroom is Mr. Marimow's practiced hand on the tiller. He recently heard that a reporter had arranged for local doctors, beauticians and others to give a woman a free makeover in exchange for a mention of their names in an article. It was the kind of editorial endorsement that money couldn't buy. And as soon as Mr. Marimow heard about the arrangement, he canceled the article.</p>
        <p>''It was a quid pro quo and it was conceived before I came or without consulting me,'' Mr. Marimow said. ''I said, 'Pay everyone who did these services, pay them 100 percent, and we do nothing in print.' ''</p>
        <p>A decision that put off people in the newsroom was the ending of a nationally prominent television column by Gail Shister, who had been writing it for 25 years. In the new spirit of thinking locally, she was assigned to write features instead. Ms. Shister said that at a time when Mr. Tierney is brands, canceling her column was ''throwing the baby out with the bath water.''</p>
        <p>''People are anxious because we know there are many more changes to come,'' she said. ''And we're feeling discombobulated because many of us are doing things we don't usually do.''</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Tierney seems to be learning the language of journalism, a switch from his days as a local ad man who regularly jousted with the paper and tried to kill articles that reflected badly on his clients.</p>
        <p>Now, each day, copies of the front pages of the nation's major dailies are tacked up on his wall so he can compare them. He has brought new columnists on board, including Mark Bowden, the author of ''Black Hawk Down'' and a former Inquirer reporter. Near the elevator to his suite of offices he has displayed a large photograph from The Inquirer of two Amish women after last year's shooting of 10 girls in a schoolhouse.</p>
        <p>''The photojournalist who took this slept in a car, walked across a field where she wasn't supposed to be and hid in a tree to get this shot,'' he said proudly. ''As long as I have folks who are that committed to what we're trying to do, we are going to be very, very successful.''</p>
        <p>MEDIA</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 30, 2007, Monday  An article in Business Day last Monday about changes at The Philadelphia Inquirer, using information supplied by the newspaper, misstated the source of a photograph of two Amish women taken after last year's shooting at a schoolhouse. The photograph, which hangs near the office of Brian P. Tierney, the publisher, was in The Daily News, not in The Inquirer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 30, 2007, Monday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day last Monday about changes at The Philadelphia Inquirer, using information supplied by the newspaper, misstated the source of a photograph of two Amish women taken after last year's shooting at a schoolhouse. The photograph, which hangs near the office of Brian P. Tierney, the publisher, was in The Daily News, not in The Inquirer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
