<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>American Snared in Kazakh Legal Dispute</title>
    <meta content="23kazakhstan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/world/asia/23kazakhstan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070430T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842457"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kazakhstan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Kazakhstan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Extortion and Blackmail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Extradition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Extradition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Extortion and Blackmail</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Kazakhstan</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E4D8173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1312" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>American Snared in Kazakh Legal Dispute</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">American Snared in Kazakh Legal Dispute</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ILAN GREENBERG</byline>
      <dateline>ALMATY, Kazakhstan, April 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mark Seidenfeld, a 39-year-old American, lived for years in this booming alpine city as a prominent telecommunications executive, one of thousands of foreign businessmen who shuttled around town in chauffeured sport-utility vehicles as they managed Kazakhstan's transition from Communism to one of the most sophisticated market economies in the former Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>But in November 2006, he returned to Almaty bruised and exhausted after a three-week journey from Siberia in a Russian prison train after a 10-month imprisonment there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Authorities in Kazakhstan have accused an American telecommunications executive of embezzling funds from his own Kazakh company, a charge he denies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mark Seidenfeld, a 39-year-old American, lived for years in this booming alpine city as a prominent telecommunications executive, one of thousands of foreign businessmen who shuttled around town in chauffeured sport-utility vehicles as they managed Kazakhstan's transition from Communism to one of the most sophisticated market economies in the former Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>But in November 2006, he returned to Almaty bruised and exhausted after a three-week journey from Siberia in a Russian prison train after a 10-month imprisonment there.</p>
        <p>Kazakhstan authorities had issued an arrest warrant for Mr. Seidenfeld after a Kazakh citizen accused him of siphoning $40,000 from his Almaty company, pocketing funds meant to buy a piece of machinery. After a series of postponements, preliminary hearings for Mr. Seidenfeld's criminal trial were delayed again last week for at least another month for translation of court documents.</p>
        <p>An assessment in February by the Almaty office of the accounting firm PricewaterhouseCoopers and provided to The New York Times found that the equipment that Mr. Seidenfeld is accused of falsely listing on company books was located in the company's offices.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seidenfeld, who speaks fluent Russian and has worked most of his career in the former Soviet Union, says his troubles began when, as chief executive, he insisted on an open auction to sell his company, a Kazakhstan subsidiary of Golden Telecom, a Moscow-based Internet and telecommunications company listed on NASDAQ. Competitive bids forced Golden Telecom's sole Kazakhstan investor to raise his initial offer for the company by $5 million.</p>
        <p>Nearly a dozen former employees at Golden Telecom involved with the sale say Mr. Seidenfeld's insistence on the auction made him a target for retribution. Though his accuser was a Kazakh citizen, he was also an employee of Golden Telecom, which was why Mr. Seidenfeld was extradited and imprisoned in Russia.</p>
        <p>Concerned that Mr. Seidenfeld's prosecution is politically motivated, several members of Congress, including Senator Harry Reid, the majority leader, have lobbied American and Kazakh officials on Mr. Seidenfeld's behalf.</p>
        <p>''I understand Mr. Seidenfeld's accuser is bragging he has this situation wired,'' said Representative Shelley Berkley, a Nevada Democrat, who has written to Kazakh authorities about Mr. Seidenfeld's case. ''I'm concerned that his accuser is very well connected, that he will use his contacts and his friendships to harm my constituent.'' She added that she believed the case was ''just extortion pure and simple.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Seidenfeld's prosecution echoes tactics used throughout the former Soviet Union to use the courts to deprive foreign investors of their assets.</p>
        <p>News of the case has only recently rippled through the sizable group of foreign businesspeople here, causing increasing concern at the noose that the local judicial system can swing above anyone who angers the wrong local party.</p>
        <p>''If a local partner can use his influence in this country to put a foreign businessman in prison for a civil case, it creates an almost intolerable atmosphere for foreigners to invest here,'' said an American businessman, who spoke on the condition of anonymity because he is currently involved in a large real estate project in Kazakhstan.</p>
        <p>Investments by American companies and individuals make up the largest national bloc of investments in Kazakhstan, according to the State Department.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seidenfeld has hired a local lawyer. Baker &amp; McKenzie, Golden Telecom's corporate counsel, declined Golden Telecom's request to represent Mr. Seidenfeld.</p>
        <p>''I think if the U.S. government is trying to have a special relationship with Kazakhstan I don't think it's a contradiction for the U.S. to say, 'Listen, we'll help you, thank you for your help with oil and Afghanistan, but in return we don't think it's ridiculous to say don't play games with our citizens,' '' Mr. Seidenfeld said in an interview from his prison cell in Almaty. ''If the Kazakhs got a message like that, I don't think my case would happen.''</p>
        <p>Many foreign businesspeople in Kazakhstan, a country generally perceived as the least repressive in the region, say Mr. Seidenfeld's case is part of chilling legal trend. They see it as meant to intimidate foreigners lured by Kazakhstan's booming economy and aggressive courtship of foreign investment, and say it is emblematic of Kazakhstan's rampant use of its judicial system to punish those who have failed to further the business interests of Kazakhs connected to the government.</p>
        <p>''Of course we have a judicial system that can be abused,'' said Oraz Jandosov, co-chairman of Ak Zhol, an opposition political party, and the former chief of the central bank. ''Our courts are not only corrupt but competence is an issue. Not only can Americans be squeezed but vice versa. It's the natural result of the country's current political system.''</p>
        <p>While Mr. Seidenfeld will be the first American businessman to go on trial in Kazakhstan, his incarceration coincides with two other widely criticized criminal trials in Central Asia, provoking an outcry from human rights advocates who say the cases illustrate just how deeply the region is calcifying into a uniform authoritarian rule.</p>
        <p>Uzbekistan's criminal court on April 19 began considering the case of Umida Niazova, a well known Uzbek journalist and translator, on charges of illegally crossing a national border, smuggling, and ''distributing material causing public disorder.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, there have been recent high-level visits from American officials and public announcements from various European Union officials that it is considering lifting limited sanctions imposed after a violent government crackdown on civilians, some of whom were armed, in the Uzbek city of Andijon in 2005.</p>
        <p>Since that crackdown, regional watchdogs say, Uzbekistan has used its judicial system to silence critics, imprisoning at least 15 other journalists and activists in the past two years.</p>
        <p>In the Xinjiang Uighur Autonomous Region of China, the son of a prominent human rights leader of the Uighur ethnic minority was sentenced last week on charges of ''instigating and engaging in secessionist activities.'' The verdict said that the man, Ablikim Kadeer, would be ''deprived of his political rights'' for three years because he wrote two newspaper articles and circulated a ''rumor'' that the Chinese authorities intended to confiscate businesses owned by his family.</p>
        <p>He is the son of Rebiya Kadeer, an outspoken critic of China's Uighur policies, who now lives in the United States.</p>
        <p>Central Asian governments keep a close eye on Chinese trials of politically active Uighurs because the political aspirations of ethnic Uighurs are widely perceived as a threat to the stability of governments across the region.</p>
        <p>Taken together, regional analysts say, the cases represent how Central Asian governments -- far from evolving into more transparent, business-friendly entities as many had hoped only a few years ago -- have used their courts to inoculate themselves from outside calls for reform and to outmaneuver foreign governments and businesses.</p>
        <p>''Despite all the Western donor money and American-financed projects aimed at reforming the judiciaries here, this is all part of a bigger Central Asian trend to make their judicial systems subordinate to their presidents,'' said Michael Hall, an analyst in Bishkek, Kyrgyzstan, with the International Crisis Group, which seeks to prevent violent conflict. ''The result is a significant retreat in America's ability to project its public and business interests in the region.</p>
        <p>''Plus, the U.S. has suffered a massive loss of credibility when it comes to talking about the rule of law and independent judiciaries in the wake of the abuses we've been hearing about in places like Guantánamo.''</p>
        <p>In addition, some critics say, the lure of Central Asia's huge oil and gas reserves has made the West reluctant to interfere in the region's internal politics.</p>
        <p>''What is not changing is the nature of these regimes,'' said Rachel Denber of Human Rights Watch, in New York. ''What is changing is the way the U.S. and the E.U. are placing value on energy, and what they perceive is the best conditions in the regions for creating the best deals on energy. They're not looking to rock the boat.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 30, 2007, Monday  An article last Monday about the prosecution of an American business executive in Kazakhstan on charges he stole $40,000 from his company omitted the company's name and misidentified its owners. The company is Arna Inc., and it is owned by GIMV, a Belgian investment company; the European Bank for Reconstruction and Development; and Murat Zhunussov, a Kazakh investor. Arna is not a Kazakhstan subsidiary of Golden Telecom, a Moscow-based Internet and telecommunications company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 30, 2007, Monday</p>
        <p>An article last Monday about the prosecution of an American business executive in Kazakhstan on charges he stole $40,000 from his company omitted the company's name and misidentified its owners. The company is Arna Inc., and it is owned by GIMV, a Belgian investment company; the European Bank for Reconstruction and Development; and Murat Zhunussov, a Kazakh investor. Arna is not a Kazakhstan subsidiary of Golden Telecom, a Moscow-based Internet and telecommunications company.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
