<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Working Together, the Devils Finish Taking Apart the Lightning</title>
    <meta content="23devils" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/sports/23devils.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842459"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Tampa Bay Lightning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Tampa Bay Lightning</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Brodeur, Martin</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E2D8173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="909" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Working Together, the Devils Finish Taking Apart the Lightning</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Devils Spread Load to Eliminate Lightning</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crouse, Karen</byline>
      <dateline>TAMPA, Fla., April 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On days like this, it is hard for Devils center Scott Gomez to picture himself gone. For seven years, the Devils have been the only team Gomez has known. He has been around long enough to have grown almost blasé about goaltender Martin Brodeur's brilliance and the team's closeness and the franchise's postseason success.</p>
        <p>At season's end, Gomez will be a free agent, eligible to follow the money trail to a huge pot of gold. But on Sunday, as the Devils celebrated clinching their Eastern Conference quarterfinal with a 3-2 victory in Game 6 against the Tampa Bay Lightning, Gomez sounded like someone who sensed that he was part of something special. ''Everyone gets along, everyone cares about each other,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Martin Brodeur stopped 32 shots and Brian Gionta scored two goals to lead the Atlantic Division champions to a victory over Tampa Bay.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On days like this, it is hard for Devils center Scott Gomez to picture himself gone. For seven years, the Devils have been the only team Gomez has known. He has been around long enough to have grown almost blasé about goaltender Martin Brodeur's brilliance and the team's closeness and the franchise's postseason success.</p>
        <p>At season's end, Gomez will be a free agent, eligible to follow the money trail to a huge pot of gold. But on Sunday, as the Devils celebrated clinching their Eastern Conference quarterfinal with a 3-2 victory in Game 6 against the Tampa Bay Lightning, Gomez sounded like someone who sensed that he was part of something special. ''Everyone gets along, everyone cares about each other,'' he said.</p>
        <p>From the most grizzled veteran to the greenest rookie, ''you're expected to contribute,'' Gomez said. ''It's always a team effort.''</p>
        <p>On Sunday at the St. Pete Times Forum, the Devils' top line of Gomez, Patrik Elias and Brian Gionta generated enough scoring chances to see the Devils through to the next round, where they will meet the Ottawa Senators. Gionta scored twice, Elias had three assists and Gomez contributed two assists.</p>
        <p>But if top-line contributions were all that was required for success, the Lightning would still be playing. Tampa Bay's top line accounted for 11 of its 14 goals in the series, including two by Brad Richards on Sunday. The difference was that the Devils received contributions from everybody.</p>
        <p>''I think there were a lot of people that did a lot of good things at the right time,'' said Lou Lamoriello, the Devils' general manager and interim coach.</p>
        <p>One of those people, naturally, was Brodeur. His excellence in the postseason is such a given that Devils fans must have been concerned when he allowed 12 goals in the first four games of the series.</p>
        <p>After shutting out the Lightning in Game 5 on Friday, Brodeur finished with 32 saves Sunday, one more than on Friday.</p>
        <p>He made 10 stops in the final 20 minutes, when the Lightning played like a desperate team.</p>
        <p>Brodeur's third-period flourish included a glove save of a slap shot by Ryan Craig, a stop of defenseman Filip Kuba on a backdoor play that the Lightning had used with great effectiveness the first three games, and three point-blank shots in the closing minutes, one by Richards and two by Martin St. Louis.</p>
        <p>''He was phenomenal the other night,'' Devils defenseman Richard Matvichuk said, referring to Brodeur's performance Friday, ''and I think he was even better today.''</p>
        <p>The same could be said of Matvichuk, for whom little was expected at the start of the series. He had back surgery in June and did not return until the Devils' final regular-season game. After not dressing in the first two games against the Lightning, Matvichuk was thrust into action in Game 3, when Colin White's balky back prevented him from playing.</p>
        <p>Matvichuk was paired with Paul Martin, who logged more than 30 minutes Sunday. Together, they did a laudable job of curtailing, if not containing, the Lightning's top goal scorer, Vincent Lecavalier, and his right-hand man, St. Louis.</p>
        <p>In the game's first minute, Matvichuk threw his body in front of a Lecavalier shot for the first of his six blocked shots. Lecavalier's frustration at being covered like clear wrap got the better of him in the final minute of the first period. He struck Matvichuk in the back with his stick a couple feet in front of Brodeur.</p>
        <p>Matvichuk was slow to get up and looked wobbly on his skates as he headed straight for the dressing room.</p>
        <p>''It was just a little jolt of pain,'' said Matvichuk, who returned to play 15 minutes over the next two periods.</p>
        <p>Lecavalier's cross-checking penalty looked even worse when, in the second minute of the second, his teammate Jason Ward received a hooking penalty.</p>
        <p>In their 3-2 loss here in Game 3, the Devils had squandered a two-man advantage. That was before their power-play unit, led by Gomez, started playing as if the ice beneath their skates were cracking.</p>
        <p>In the final seconds of Lecavalier's penalty, Gomez and Elias set up defenseman Brian Rafalski for his second goal of the series, extending the Devils' lead to 2-0.</p>
        <p>Less than four minutes later, Richards broke up Brodeur's bid for a league record-tying 23rd playoff shutout with a power-play goal, which ended the Lightning's 123-minute scoring drought.</p>
        <p>Thirty-nine seconds later, the public-address announcer was just getting around to saying, in his booming voice, ''Another power-play goal  '' and inducing delirious cheering from the crowd of 20,019 when Gionta scored his second goal on feeds from Elias and Gomez.</p>
        <p>The goal, coming so quickly after the Lightning's, gave the Devils a huge psychological lift. ''No question about it,'' Elias said.</p>
        <p>In the tense third period, the Devils could feel the momentum at their backs with every big save Brodeur made.</p>
        <p>Between Matvichuk's locker and Gionta's was a giant grease board with HUGE WIN scrawled in black letters. Gionta was answering questions about the game when the left side of the grease board detached from the nail holding it up.</p>
        <p>The board swung from the wall and toward Gionta's head. ''Watch it,'' Matvichuk said, raising his voice only slightly, and Gionta calmly stepped aside in time to avoid being struck.</p>
        <p>It was one final catastrophe coolly averted in a series in which the final momentum swing belonged to the Devils.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
