<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ON THE CAMPAIGN: The Birth of the 'Breck Girl' Story Line</title>
    <meta content="23web-nagourney" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="ContinuousNews" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842472"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edwards, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E0DA1F31F930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1106" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ON THE CAMPAIGN: The Birth of the 'Breck Girl' Story Line</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The tale of John Edwards' $400 haircuts may have ended or at least his campaign hopes it ended when Mr. Edwards told Iowans on Friday that he was embarrassed by the episode. It arguably began four years ago this weekend with a story in The New York Times about the White House's strategy for dealing with prospective Democratic challengers to President Bush.</p>
        <p>In the last paragraph of that story, which I wrote with a colleague, Richard W. Stevenson, an unnamed ''Bush associate'' was quoted as referring to Mr. Edwards as ''the Breck Girl of politics.'' Another Bush adviser, again unnamed, was quoted as saying of Senator John Kerry of Massachusetts, ''he looks French.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The tale of John Edwards' $400 haircuts may have ended or at least his campaign hopes it ended when Mr. Edwards told Iowans on Friday that he was embarrassed by the episode. It arguably began four years ago this weekend with a story in The New York Times about the White House's strategy for dealing with prospective Democratic challengers to President Bush.</p>
        <p>In the last paragraph of that story, which I wrote with a colleague, Richard W. Stevenson, an unnamed ''Bush associate'' was quoted as referring to Mr. Edwards as ''the Breck Girl of politics.'' Another Bush adviser, again unnamed, was quoted as saying of Senator John Kerry of Massachusetts, ''he looks French.''</p>
        <p>In both instances, we were attempting to flesh out for readers the White House's plans for discrediting prospective Democratic opponents. Both people quoted were at the senior levels of the Bush political operation. And in both cases as Mr. Kerry and Mr. Edwards could certainly attest by the end of 2004 election the Bush machine had followed through on the plan it laid out 18 months earlier to define the Democrats on Republican terms.</p>
        <p>Our story may have had the result of not only previewing what the Bush campaign intended to do, but, by introducing such memorably biting characterizations into the political dialogue, helping it.</p>
        <p>Was that a mistake on our part? Perhaps. Our goal is to give people as much information and insight as we can, in this case to help them understand what was happening in a campaign and to give them a heads-up about what to watch for. Political journalists make judgments all the time about what is and what is not newsworthy, but the bias is to err on the side of giving information to readers.</p>
        <p>That said, faced with the same situation again, I would press the Bush officials to be named in offering their characterizations; no justification for anonymity here. And based on my experience in trying to insist more often that sources speak on the record in this campaign season, I think I might have succeeded.</p>
        <p>Still, the Bush campaign was not alone in trying to push a story line in 2004 that characterized Mr. Edwards as a pretty boy and an empty suit. Jim Jordan, who was Mr. Kerry's campaign manager during that primary, frequently referred to Mr. Edwards as ''the cute Beatle.'' (No disrespect to Paul, of course). Mr. Edwards' campaign aides knew about the efforts: they tried to defuse the attack with humor by handing out ''commemorative bottles of Breck shampoo,'' at the campaign's formal kick-off in September 2003.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Edwards began his second bid for he White House, the Breck Girl story line was still out there. Its persistence reflected what Mr. Jordan and others asserted were reservations about Mr. Edwards among voters as well as vulnerabilities that his opponents have always tried to exploit.</p>
        <p>As anyone who has interviewed Mr. Edwards, or seen him this year talking with voters about, say, his health care plan, the lightweight label seems unfair, whatever you think of his politics. Voters routinely walk away from such events describing him as a substantial candidate immersed in serious issues.</p>
        <p>But last week, as the story of the haircuts reverberated across Iowa and New Hampshire, on to the Drudge Report and finally to both David Letterman and Jay Leno, it was a reminder that, fair or not, this remains a persistent vulnerability for Mr. Edwards. To the frustration of some of his own supporters, it is one that he and his campaign have at times played into through elementary mistakes that underlined the image he is trying to dispel.</p>
        <p>In one memorable moment, Mr. Edwards was captured on videotape waiting for an interview to begin; the tape shows him and his make-up artist fret with his hair for nearly two minutes.</p>
        <p>Rule No. 1 of politics in this era of YouTube: if you are sitting in front of a camera, assume it is rolling. This clip was posted on YouTube, to the tune of ''I Feel Pretty,'' last November. It had been viewed nearly 362,000 times as of Monday morning, and in another indication of why the haircut and attendant publicity was so unwelcome in the Edwards camp nearly 80,000 times over the six days since news of the haircut expenditure first started getting wide circulation, based on campaign expenditure reports filed with the Federal Election Commission.</p>
        <p>An episode like this would have been a problem in his last campaign, for the all the obvious reasons. It had particular resonance again this time because of the effort Mr. Edwards has made to position himself as a populist champion of the middle- and working classes at a time of growing economic disparity. His target audience is not the $400-haircut voter.</p>
        <p>As one of Mr. Edwards' advisers said over the weekend, his campaign organization failed the candidate here. Campaigns routinely scrutinize the list of their own expenditures to weed our precisely these kind of items before an opponent does it for them; in this case, the haircuts were supposed to have been paid for by Mr. Edwards personally (if he had paid out of his own pocket from the start, there would have been no requirement to disclose the cost) rather than having them paid for by the campaign (campaign expenditures are a matter of public record).</p>
        <p>But the reaction from voters suggest that it was not a matter of who paid for it; it was the simple fact of a $400 haircut. A reporter for the Quad City Times in eastern Iowa surveyed barbers for their reaction in a part of the state where haircuts go for $10 to $12 a pop. From the story: ''''If I charged $400 for a haircut, they'd come after me with white coats,'' said Leo Fier, who has been cutting hair for 49 years at his shop in DeWitt, Iowa.''</p>
        <p>Surely it was not a coincidence that one of Mr. Edwards' rivals, Senator Christopher Dodd of Connecticut, invited a photographer in on Friday to shoot him as he was getting a $12 haircut at Dude's Barber Shop in Manchester on Friday. That photo was featured on the front page of the Union Leader.</p>
        <p>Mr. Edwards' advisers argued over the weekend that the financial circumstances of his life he became wealthy as a trial lawyer should not detract from the sincerity of his message, or the depth of his concern about issues of poverty.</p>
        <p>Still, appearances matter in politics, and four years after the Breck Girl line first appeared in print, Mr. Edwards continues to have trouble leaving it behind.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
