<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METROPOLITAN DIARY</title>
    <meta content="23diary" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/nyregion/23diary.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842398"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Metropolitan Diary"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metropolitan Diary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Upper West Side (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E0DA173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="733" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METROPOLITAN DIARY</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Dear Diary</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>Walking past a bus stop in Lower Manhattan recently, I was stopped by a mature, well-dressed woman with a foreign accent, who asked me where she should stand and wait for the M6 bus.</p>
        <p>I told her she was in the right place: the bus stop.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A passer-by clarifies for a bus rider the meaning of a sign that says "No standing."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>Walking past a bus stop in Lower Manhattan recently, I was stopped by a mature, well-dressed woman with a foreign accent, who asked me where she should stand and wait for the M6 bus.</p>
        <p>I told her she was in the right place: the bus stop.</p>
        <p>''Yes, but the sign says, 'No standing,' '' she replied.</p>
        <p>I explained, we smiled at each other, and I went on my way.</p>
        <p>Doreen S. Howard</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>A woman pleading to the driver of the uptown M104 bus on Broadway:</p>
        <p>''Please, would you let me back on? I got off at Fairway by mistake. I meant to get off at Zabar's.''</p>
        <p>Diane Feldman</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>I arrived at the Park Circle entrance of Prospect Park at 5:05 p.m. and was pleased to note that the park drive had just opened. This meant that I could take the scenic and shorter route to Grand Army Plaza. I was no more than one-quarter of a mile into the park when traffic came to a halt even though the light was green.</p>
        <p>The reason, I saw, was that a huge flock of Canada geese was walking, or I should say, strolling, across the road. There were eight cars backed up, including a New York City patrol car, and no one honked a horn or got out to try and chase the majestic birds.</p>
        <p>Everyone sat quietly through three or four light changes, enjoying one of the delights of Mother Nature on a beautiful afternoon. Who says that New Yorkers are always in a hurry?</p>
        <p>Edgar Lichstein</p>
        <p>THE SALE OF MY PARENTS' APARTMENT</p>
        <p>I walk into my childhood lair for the last time.</p>
        <p>''You're never going to come back here again,'' the housekeeper says.</p>
        <p>She smiles crazily, like a fortune teller in a Russian novel.</p>
        <p>She is the only person in the world who has ever called me ''sir.''</p>
        <p>I open Mom's closet, its shelves empty, and wonder about the configuration.</p>
        <p>Why was hers in the hall outside the bedroom, where, as a child, I used to surprise her as she was dressing?</p>
        <p>Now that both my parents are dead, there's no one left to answer, no ultimate authority.</p>
        <p>I can almost hear the clink of Scotch glasses in the living room, where a solitary chest waits to be removed, can almost hear the arguments about the Kennedy/Nixon debate.</p>
        <p>There are certain nooks and crannies I don't pursue.</p>
        <p>I'd meant to use the bathroom one last time, but I was too empty to go.</p>
        <p>Francis Levy</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>While dropping off something for Uncle Randy on West 90th Street, we noticed this very Upper West Side notice posted on the door of the garbage chute room:</p>
        <p>''To Whom It May Concern:</p>
        <p>''It remains a mystery to the majority of us as to why you have not yet understood the simple concept that trash must be placed down the trash chute -- not just inside the door of the room the trash chute occupies.</p>
        <p>''Perhaps you have not previously resided in an apartment building. Perhaps you lack understanding of the nature of the semi-communal living situation involved therein.</p>
        <p>''Whatever the case, your fellow residents of the 21st floor are fed up with your continued inconsideration. We are not your mother, and therefore it is not our job to clean up after you.</p>
        <p>''Put your trash down the trash chute!</p>
        <p>''Sincerely, your neighbors on the 21st floor.''</p>
        <p>We moved across town many years ago, but we do miss these types of notes.</p>
        <p>Laura and George Tannenbaum</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>I was standing near one of the fountains at Lincoln Center waiting for a friend. A small, quite elderly couple stood next to me.</p>
        <p>A beautiful, striking young woman walked by, stopped and stood near us. Her appearance was electric. All heads turned in her direction.</p>
        <p>She was very tall, over six feet. Her long, long legs were sheathed in shiny black thigh-high boots, with four-inch heels. Her leather skirt was very mini, and her leather jacket was skin-tight.</p>
        <p>She wore several heavy silver chains and chandelier earrings. Her platinum hair was fluffed up, and out, adding to her height.</p>
        <p>The old man next to me leaned toward his sweet-faced, roly-poly wife, gave her a squeeze and said, ''Why don't you get an outfit like that?''</p>
        <p>''I have an outfit like that,'' she replied.</p>
        <p>Evelyn Malina</p>
        <p>Metropolitan Diary</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
