<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rancor Rises Over Santa Barbara Newspaper</title>
    <meta content="23barbara" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/business/media/23barbara.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842424"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Santa Barbara News-Press</org>
        <person class="online_producer">McCaw, Wendy P</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE1D9173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="702" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rancor Rises Over Santa Barbara Newspaper</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rancor Rises Over Santa Barbara Newspaper</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHARON WAXMAN</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, April 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An ugly conflict involving a wealthy local publisher turned even uglier Sunday as The Santa Barbara News-Press published a front-page article suggesting that the paper's former editor had kept child pornography on his work computer, a claim that the editor promptly denounced as ''malicious.''</p>
        <p>The publisher, Wendy P. McCaw, has a history of contentious relations with that editor, Jerry Roberts, who resigned his post last July over what he called her interference in news decisions. Several other editors and a columnist resigned at that time in protest, and many others have resigned or been fired over the last year because of ongoing disagreements with Ms. McCaw.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Santa Barbara News-Press published a story suggesting that the paper’s former editor had kept child pornography on his work computer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An ugly conflict involving a wealthy local publisher turned even uglier Sunday as The Santa Barbara News-Press published a front-page article suggesting that the paper's former editor had kept child pornography on his work computer, a claim that the editor promptly denounced as ''malicious.''</p>
        <p>The publisher, Wendy P. McCaw, has a history of contentious relations with that editor, Jerry Roberts, who resigned his post last July over what he called her interference in news decisions. Several other editors and a columnist resigned at that time in protest, and many others have resigned or been fired over the last year because of ongoing disagreements with Ms. McCaw.</p>
        <p>Current and past employees of the paper are at odds with Ms. McCaw over their vote to unionize last fall, which she has declined to recognize. Ms. McCaw has also stirred broader tension in the community with threats of legal action against local merchants who hung signs sympathetic to the union cause, and against a journalist who wrote an unfavorable article about her in The American Journalism Review.</p>
        <p>But the latest twist took the antagonisms even further. In the article on Sunday, which carried no byline, the newspaper wrote that Ampersand Publishing, the parent company of The News-Press, was seeking to retrieve from police the hard drive of the computer used by Mr. Roberts, ''which contains according to the police more than 15,000 images of child and adult pornography.''</p>
        <p>The article noted that the city opposed the newspaper's attempts to obtain the hard drive, and that the district attorney had declined to file charges after a police investigation. It added that Ampersand ''is conducting its own internal investigation to determine the source of the material.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Roberts held a news conference on Sunday to refute the suggestion that the illegal material was his. ''It is false, defamatory, malicious and was published in full knowledge that it was untrue,'' he said in an interview afterward. ''It was a cowardly attack, unsigned, and not preceded by any attempt to contact me for comment.''</p>
        <p>The article did note that Mr. Roberts, who is now the publisher of the student newspaper at the University of California, Santa Barbara, denied any involvement with the child pornography on his computer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roberts said he would demand a retraction of the article, and if that was not forthcoming, he would consider suing for defamation. Barry Cappello, the lawyer for The News-Press, did not return calls seeking comment.</p>
        <p>In a letter dated March 2, the district attorney's chief trial deputy, Eric A. Hanson, wrote that there was no basis for filing charges over the pornography, since the computer was used by several people at The News-Press. ''At the present time there is insufficient evidence to warrant bringing charges against any individual,'' the letter stated.</p>
        <p>And a former systems director for the newspaper, Raul Gil, gave a signed statement in January that the computer drive used by Mr. Roberts might have been used by former employees years ago. Mr. Gil has resigned from The News-Press over the matter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roberts said the computer had been bought in used condition, and was used by three other editors before his arrival at the paper.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roberts also took, and passed, a polygraph test saying he had nothing to do with the pornography on his computer. Last year, he received an ethics award from the Society of Professional Journalists for his decision to resign from The News-Press because of editorial pressures imposed by Ms. McCaw.</p>
        <p>The article did not note that Ms. McCaw and Mr. Roberts were in the throes of legal arbitration of claims each has filed against the other. Ms. McCaw has filed a claim of $25 million against Mr. Roberts for breach of contract; he has filed a counterclaim of $10 million for damages.</p>
        <p>In his statement at the news conference, Mr. Roberts said he believed the article was an attempt to undercut his credibility during arbitration over the competing legal claims.</p>
        <p>The New York Times Company sold The News-Press to Ms. McCaw, the ex-wife of the cellphone entrepreneur Craig McCaw, in 2000. The National Labor Relations Board said earlier this year it would prosecute The News-Press for unfairly firing eight reporters.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
