<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shaky Effort By Bullpen Lets Braves Off the Hook</title>
    <meta content="23mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/23/sports/baseball/23mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842466"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1D8173EF930A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="929" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shaky Effort By Bullpen Lets Braves Off the Hook</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Braves’ Bullpen Secures Victory Over Mets</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID PICKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Picker, David</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Mets' bullpen has been like a life preserver since last season. When the starters have taken on water, so to speak, the Mets have been able to hang on to games with their relievers, who have earned a reputation as one of the best corps in the major leagues.</p>
        <p>Through five innings yesterday at Shea Stadium, there was no reason to believe the Mets would need to rescue Tom Glavine, who was matching John Smoltz of the Atlanta Braves in what was shaping up as a pitchers' duel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The much-anticipated showdown between Tom Glavine and John Smoltz fizzled as neither pitcher lasted more than six innings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Mets' bullpen has been like a life preserver since last season. When the starters have taken on water, so to speak, the Mets have been able to hang on to games with their relievers, who have earned a reputation as one of the best corps in the major leagues.</p>
        <p>Through five innings yesterday at Shea Stadium, there was no reason to believe the Mets would need to rescue Tom Glavine, who was matching John Smoltz of the Atlanta Braves in what was shaping up as a pitchers' duel.</p>
        <p>But neither starter lasted past the sixth inning. Only this time, the Mets' relievers stumbled mightily, allowing the Braves to come from behind and win, 9-6.</p>
        <p>''They have been outstanding all year,'' Mets Manager Willie Randolph said of his bullpen, which entered the game having allowed only one home run this season and owning the best earned run average in the majors (1.31). ''But it's a matter of time every once in a while when you're going to have these types of things happen.''</p>
        <p>The Mets (11-6) have lost four of six games to the Braves (12-6) this season. The seesaw series began with the Mets owning a half-game lead in the National League East, but Atlanta won the first and third games and left Queens ahead by a half-game.</p>
        <p>When the Mets scored five runs off Smoltz in the sixth inning to seize a 6-3 advantage, the sun was shinning and the 55,671 fans were cheering. Glavine was replaced by a pinch-hitter in that inning, signaling the entrance of the bullpen, and it seemed as if nothing could go wrong.</p>
        <p>For the first two batters of the seventh inning, with the right-hander Ambiorix Burgos on the mound, things went as planned. Then Burgos allowed a two-out double to pinch-hitter Scott Thorman -- a hit that glanced off Shawn Green's glove in right field -- and Randolph turned to the left-hander Scott Schoeneweis to face the left-handed Kelly Johnson.</p>
        <p>Schoeneweis walked Johnson, putting runners on first and second and bringing up Édgar Rentería, who bats right-handed. Randolph could have replaced Schoeneweis with a right-hander -- a safer matchup, on paper, at least.</p>
        <p>Schoeneweis had not allowed an earned run in six and a third innings this season, but his second pitch to Rentería was a sinker, and it ended up over the center-field wall for a three-run homer, tying the score, 6-6.</p>
        <p>''It's impossible to go the whole season without something like that going on,'' said Schoeneweis, who allowed a double and an intentional walk before inducing an inning-ending flyout.</p>
        <p>The Mets could not go more than one inning before something like that went on again.</p>
        <p>Aaron Heilman entered the game at the start of the eighth inning. There were two outs and runners on first and second when Heilman faced Johnson, who had homered off Glavine on the game's first pitch.</p>
        <p>Heilman offered a fastball that Johnson devoured for a three-run homer, capping the scoring. None of the runs were earned since the inning began with Jeff Francoeur reaching first base on a fielding error by second baseman José Valentín. But it stung just the same.</p>
        <p>''We had the lead and unfortunately we gave it up,'' Heilman said. ''It's certainly a tough loss.''</p>
        <p>The Braves used four relievers, and none of them allowed a run.</p>
        <p>Glavine and Smoltz, who played together for 15 seasons in Atlanta and remain close friends, were facing each other for the third time since Glavine joined the Mets in 2003, and they looked sharp.</p>
        <p>The score after five innings was 1-1. The Mets' only run came through Green, who homered against Smoltz in the fifth inning.</p>
        <p>After allowing Johnson's first homer, Glavine settled down, retiring 17 of the next 20 batters. But he slipped in the sixth inning, allowing Francoeur's two-out two-run single that gave Atlanta a 3-1 lead.</p>
        <p>In the bottom of the inning, Smoltz began to unravel. With the bases loaded and one out, Valentín smacked a run-scoring single. With the Mets trailing by a run, Glavine was due up. Randolph replaced him with pinch-hitter Julio Franco, who flied out, but the next batter, José Reyes, belted a three-run triple into the right-field corner.</p>
        <p>''Smoltz is a great pitcher,'' Green said. ''To be able to get to him and get that lead, it's a game we need to win.''</p>
        <p>Suddenly Glavine was in line for the victory. He said it was unusual for a pitcher to be in line for the loss, be lifted for a pinch-hitter, then be in a position to win.</p>
        <p>Reyes scored on Paul Lo Duca's single, which ended Smoltz's afternoon and gave the Mets a 6-3 lead. Smoltz allowed six runs and nine hits in five and two-thirds innings.</p>
        <p>Glavine's pitching line was solid: three runs and seven hits over six innings, no walks and five strikeouts.</p>
        <p>''I was happy with it,'' Glavine said. ''I was comfortable out there today.''</p>
        <p>If only the bullpen could say the same.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>John Smoltz struck out Carlos Beltrán in the fifth inning for his 2,799th career strikeout, moving him past Cy Young and into 18th place on the career list.  Braves Manager Bobby Cox was ejected for arguing with the home-plate umpire, Paul Emmel, after Shawn Green walked to load the bases in the sixth inning.  A Mets fan pleaded not guilty yesterday to shining a high-powered flashlight at two Braves players during Friday's game. Frank Martinez was arraigned in Queens criminal court on charges of interfering with a professional sporting event and second-degree reckless endangerment.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
