<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cold Currency</title>
    <meta content="22lives.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="126" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/magazine/22lives.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841959"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Lives"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Singapore</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yew Leong Lee</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Singapore</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Yunnan Province/Kunming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Singapore</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Kunming (China)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CEED7113FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cold Currency</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cold Currency</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Yew Leong Lee</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yew Leong Lee</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article by Singaporean writer Yew Leong Lee on visit to China in which his relative wealth set him apart from people whose language and culture he shared, particularly a young man with whom he spent a night in bed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In 2005, I took a year off from my graduate studies in the States to teach art at a university in Kunming, in southwestern China. At 28, I looked as young -- and as Chinese -- as the students I was supposed to teach, and although I was raised in Singapore and lived in New York, I grew up in a family that spoke Mandarin and practiced Chinese customs. Any delusions I might have entertained about passing incognito, however, were quickly dispelled. Two weeks into my stay, I was negotiating the price on a camcorder battery when the shopkeeper cut me off with: ''Don't bargain. You're rich.'' My branded clothes and spiked hair gave me away as a first-worlder; my relative affluence was not something I could hide. On the other hand, I doubt he knew I was gay.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A visit to Shanghai leads to an encounter, which establishes a connection, which reveals a divide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In 2005, I took a year off from my graduate studies in the States to teach art at a university in Kunming, in southwestern China. At 28, I looked as young -- and as Chinese -- as the students I was supposed to teach, and although I was raised in Singapore and lived in New York, I grew up in a family that spoke Mandarin and practiced Chinese customs. Any delusions I might have entertained about passing incognito, however, were quickly dispelled. Two weeks into my stay, I was negotiating the price on a camcorder battery when the shopkeeper cut me off with: ''Don't bargain. You're rich.'' My branded clothes and spiked hair gave me away as a first-worlder; my relative affluence was not something I could hide. On the other hand, I doubt he knew I was gay.</p>
        <p>I had read that although homosexuality was decriminalized in China in 1997, a strong stigma still prevailed. Four out of five gay men end up marrying women, or so the unofficial statistic went. On my first free Friday night, I hopped into a cab with a few addresses from the Internet: places where gay men might convene. But every establishment I visited was closed, save for a seedy-looking sauna that I did not want to enter.</p>
        <p>About a month later, taking advantage of a weeklong national holiday, I flew to Shanghai to see my brother, who had a business there. During this visit, I met a young man in a mall. I was riding an escalator down; he was gazing at me from above. He wore a pink sweater, which complemented the rosiness in his cheeks. On each of these, a dimple now appeared. I turned around and rode the escalator back up.</p>
        <p>''You also know this place?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>''Sorry?''</p>
        <p>He seemed disappointed with my answer. Conversation faltered. After a while, I decided to try my luck. ''Would you like to come to my hotel for a drink?''</p>
        <p>Afterward, riding in the taxi with Yang, he explained: that particular floor in the mall was an unofficial ''rendezvous spot.''</p>
        <p>In my hotel room, Yang, who seemed tense until then, finally relaxed. It turned out that he was a migrant worker from Anhui, a province notorious for its poverty, waiting on tables 28 days a month for less money than it costs to see a Broadway show. I watched him undress from my bed, folding each piece of clothing into a square. ''I'm too skinny, you must think,'' he said. ''Hope you don't mind.''</p>
        <p>I was caught off guard. ''You know something?'' I finally recovered enough to say. ''You're cute when you smile.'' Yang blushed. ''Can you turn down the wind?'' he asked. He meant the air-conditioning. ''Sure,'' I said. But no matter what I did with the remote control, the air-conditioner did not respond. Apparently, Yang had never slept in an air-conditioned room before. Later that night, as we dozed off, our bodies intertwined to keep warm.</p>
        <p>When I woke up sometime in the early hours, we had disentangled. At first I did not even remember about Yang, but soon I made out a breathing sound over and above the noisy air-conditioning. In the darkness, his silhouette slowly formed before me. I looked at his face wonderingly. What was it like to be this boy?</p>
        <p>Then a thought crossed my mind. My brother had warned me against petty theft. ''The holiday week is the season for crime,'' he said. A lot of people come to town to get work; if they don't get it, they need money to go back home.</p>
        <p>Was my wallet where I had left it?</p>
        <p>Of course it was. Otherwise Yang wouldn't still be there. I put my arms around him. The air-conditioner blew with a vengeance. I clung to Yang even more, shivering, helpless to stop further thoughts as they came: if this stranger were to get up now and take everything -- my money, my cards, our warmth -- could I blame him? Should I feign sleep and let him?</p>
        <p>In the end, nothing that dramatic happened, but after our night together, everything became imbued with what I now see as a certain fatedness. We left that third-rate hotel in the morning. I took Yang to a breakfast place specializing in bean curd and dough sticks. I asked him what he wanted; then, while he found us a seat, I paid for his meal. After breakfast, because my brother would be arriving soon, I sent him on his way.</p>
        <p>It was here I made the mistake. I hailed a cab and handed Yang money to cover the ride. Because I had already opened the door, he had no choice but to get in. But because the offer was too direct, he would not take the cash from me.</p>
        <p>Even as I waved goodbye, I understood that as soon as I was out of sight, Yang would order the driver to stop the car. He would get out and walk the rest of the way.</p>
        <p>Lives Yew Leong Lee is a Singaporean writer and video artist whose work has been shown in China, Singapore, Germany, France and the United States.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Yew Leong Lee is a Singaporean writer and video artist whose work has been shown in China, Singapore, Germany, France and the United States.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
