<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Do No Harm</title>
    <meta content="Chen.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Health; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/books/review/Chen.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841910"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Gawande, Atul</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Better: A Surgeon's Notes on Performance (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE7D7123FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="807" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Do No Harm</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Do No Harm</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAULINE W. CHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chen, Pauline W (Dr)</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BETTER</p>
        <p>A Surgeon's Notes on Performance.</p>
        <p>By Atul Gawande.</p>
        <p>273 pp. Metropolitan Books/</p>
        <p>Henry Holt &amp; Company. $24.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Why the best doctors are so good, and how the rest can learn to improve.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BETTER</p>
        <p>A Surgeon's Notes on Performance.</p>
        <p>By Atul Gawande.</p>
        <p>273 pp. Metropolitan Books/</p>
        <p>Henry Holt &amp; Company. $24.</p>
        <p>Ask people who have spent any time there and they will tell you this: The hospital can be a dangerous place. Families in waiting rooms will fill you in on the long list of delayed procedures. Patients will reel off complications suffered because of medical care. Doctors will warn of drug-resistant infections contracted only on the wards. And nurses, especially the seasoned ones, will urge you to do everything in your power not to land in the hospital in July, when the newest crop of interns are let loose on medical centers everywhere.</p>
        <p>It's a wonder anyone ever gets better.</p>
        <p>But patients do. In droves. They do so well that epidemiologists these days can flaunt some near miraculous statistics: over the last 50 years, the cancer survival rate has climbed to 70 percent, the risk of death from strokes has fallen more than 80 percent, and mortality from heart disease has dropped by almost two-thirds.</p>
        <p>So how do doctors, in this imperfect, occasionally messy and ultimately all-too-human endeavor called medical care, manage to do better?</p>
        <p>Atul Gawande asks this question in ''Better.'' As with his first book, ''Complications,'' Gawande provides a cleareyed view of the medical profession that both resonates and gives pause. Once again, he spares no one, himself included. Gawande, a surgeon, manages to capture medicine in all of its complex and chaotic glory, and to put it, still squirming with life, down on the page. While fans of his work may be disappointed to find they've already read half of the chapters in The New Yorker (where Gawande is a staff writer) or elsewhere, Gawande's meditation on performance is not only an absorbing collection of essays on how some doctors manage to do better but also an exhilarating call for the rest of us to do the same.</p>
        <p>Gawande divides the essays into three sections -- ''Diligence,'' ''Doing Right'' and ''Ingenuity'' -- based on the essential components ''for success in medicine or in any endeavor that involves risk and responsibility.'' Each essay focuses on a problem -- the importance of hand-washing, health care delivery in India, the role of physicians in executions -- that Gawande uses to anchor wide-ranging reflections. Weaving clinical narratives and anecdotes from disciplines as diverse as history, economics and baseball, Gawande shows us that hand-washing turns out to be a profoundly complex and intractable quandary, that the moral obligations of physicians to death-row patients are not as clear as life and death, and that providing care to the poorest in the world takes a degree of ingenuity that should be categorized not simply as ''better'' but as downright heroic.</p>
        <p>But heroism -- and there's plenty of it in this book -- also makes Gawande's categories seem sometimes insufficient. In the section ''Diligence,'' for instance, Gawande writes about the advances in military medicine responsible for decreased mortality rates from battle wounds. Diligence -- ''the necessity of giving sufficient attention to detail to avoid error and prevail against obstacles'' -- is no doubt a requisite. But implementing such medical advances on the front lines also requires a few heroes, health care professionals willing not only to give up comfortable situations back home but to risk their lives.</p>
        <p>Gawande has the ability to deconstruct and explain the most difficult issues while preserving, even celebrating, their complexity. He applies a sly sense of humor to even the most unsettling topics. And his voice is so direct that at times it borders on painful (at least from the perspective of a fellow doctor). For example, after detailing the numerous, unsuccessful attempts to get doctors to wash their hands regularly, Gawande describes one of his own patients, a 62-year-old who developed an overwhelming infection from hospital-acquired, antibiotic-resistant bacteria. Gawande writes: ''Until that moment ... it had not occurred to me that I might have given him that infection. But the truth is I may have. One of us certainly did.''</p>
        <p>Toward the end of the book, Gawande compares his ''orderly life'' with the lives of those he has written about. For all the awesome tools at the disposal of doctors today, he writes, ''it can be hard not to feel that one is just a white-coated cog in a machine -- an extraordinarily successful machine, but a machine nonetheless. ... So not surprisingly, in this work one begins to wonder: how do I really matter?'' Gawande goes on to offer five suggestions. But by the time I got to these, I had already caught myself being a little more persistent, weighing consequences more purposefully and pushing my middle-aged mind to wrap itself around old problems in new ways. I even found myself reaching for hand-washing alcohol gel more often.</p>
        <p>With this book, Gawande inspires all of us, doctor or not, to be better.</p>
        <p>Pauline W. Chen is the author of ''Final Exam: A Surgeon's Reflections on Mortality.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Pauline W. Chen is the author of ''Final Exam: A Surgeon's Reflections on Mortality.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
