<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Varmints!</title>
    <meta content="22wwln--safire.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/magazine/22wwlnsafire.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070506T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841968"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 04-22-07: ON LANGUAGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safire, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/On Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Romney, Mitt</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Boyd, William</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wayne, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7D6113FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="972" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Varmints!</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Varmints!</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Safire</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Safire, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Safire column on word 'varmint'; solicits suggestions on how to refer to someone who is half-Native American and half-Anglo, since 'half-breed' is now widely regarded as offensive (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''I'm not a big-game hunter,'' said Mitt Romney, campaigning in Indianapolis. ''I've made that very clear. I've always been a rodent and rabbit hunter. Small varmints, if you will.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>How to win the West.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''I'm not a big-game hunter,'' said Mitt Romney, campaigning in Indianapolis. ''I've made that very clear. I've always been a rodent and rabbit hunter. Small varmints, if you will.''</p>
        <p>There's a gem of dialect out of the Wild West. In hundreds of cowboy movies, the man in the white hat -- from William Boyd to John Wayne -- scowls at the rustlers and the gunfighters and excoriates them with varmint, the meanest, dirtiest, most lowdown word permitted by the prim self-censorship office then run by Will Hays.</p>
        <p>And there was that scene in ''Duel in the Sun,'' a 1946 David Selznick epic widely known as ''Lust in the Dust,'' which was directed by King Vidor and was at the time the most expensive movie ever made. Lewt, the ne'er-do-well son played by Gregory Peck, leers at Pearl Chavez, the beautiful half-Indian, half-Anglo who is trying to be virtuous, and says, ''I'll try to get you one of them newfangled bathing suits'' -- to which Pearl, played by Jennifer Jones, furious at his sexist, lascivious put-down, hisses the most severe derogation then permissible: ''You -- you varmint!''</p>
        <p>The word had appeared in P. T. Barnum's 1854 autobiography as an imprecation -- ''ye young varmint!'' -- as well as in a 1907 A. Conan Doyle story as an adjective: ''thin, ascetic, varminty'' and as the title of a 1910 Western novel by Owen Johnson. It is a dialect form of vermin, rooted in the Latin for ''worm,'' and encompasses animals of cunning (foxes, raccoons, snakes) as well as animals -- innocent though they may be -- that cause revulsion or anger in humans, like moles, gophers, mice, rats and skunks.</p>
        <p>The word's usage is bipartisan: in 2004, President Bush told Outdoor Life magazine that one of the guns he kept in his collection was a gift from ''Bob Bullock, my old buddy'' on his deathbed, a .243-caliber ''varmint rifle.'' Last month, a Times headline over an article about a health inspector's campaign to rid a fast-food chain's infestation by unwelcome nocturnal visitors was '' 'The Rats Will Not Win,' Chief Varmint Hunter Vows.''</p>
        <p>The political reason for the word's careful selection by Mitt Romney is plain: Most people who recoil from shooting Bambi are not so troubled by aiming a rifle at a weasel. (I recall a crisis at the Nixon White House when the gardener who put down rat poison was accused of endangering a beloved Rose Garden squirrel. Ron Ziegler, the press secretary, made certain that the poison was rat-specific and laid down that day's main talking point: ''We're against the rats, but we're for the squirrels.'')</p>
        <p>The cultural reason for the selection of varmint is that it is not a word commonly associated with Massachusetts, where he was governor; on the contrary, it reeks of Western lore filtered through a cowhand haze, and if the purpose of its selection was to help diffuse criticism of his change of mind about gun control, at least the usage makes him tall in the straddle.</p>
        <p>In fairness, I should note that Romney recently impressed the inside-the-Beltway set with his delivery of a joke at the Gridiron Club dinner in Washington. Despite the quaint admonition that ''reporters are never present'' at the bipartisan ribbing, The Chicago Tribune covered it, so I can pass it on. To reassure the 95 percent of Americans who are not Mormons that members of that church are not squares, prudes or stiffs, Romney told of an outing with Senators Harry Reid and Orrin Hatch, fellow Mormons, ''at which we really 'let 'er rip.' '' But we'll never read about it in the papers or see pictures on the screen about their secret escapade because, as Romney confided, ''What happens in Disneyland stays in Disneyland.''</p>
        <p>Heavy Breeding</p>
        <p>I had a problem in doing some research on the Web about the item above. The character of Pearl Chavez in ''Duel in the Sun'' was described in contemporary reviews as a half-breed, and in recent references as half-Native American, half-Anglo.</p>
        <p>Back when Niven Busch's novel was filmed, to label someone a half-breed was not regarded widely as an unprintable slur (which, to non-whites, it was). But the new five-word alternative, half-Native etc., is too long and the placement of the hyphen is awkward -- what's a half-Native American? -- and although most readers think of Indians as ''red'' Indians, as in ''cowboys and Indians,'' another choice, Indian-American, now suggests someone with one parent from India. Native American-white is a possibility, but many aboriginal Americans prefer to be called American Indians, and many white, black or brown Americans born in this country consider themselves to be native Americans, not to be confused with naturalized Americans.</p>
        <p>In light of the firestorm that followed Don Imus's racist-sexist double slur, writers are on guard not to give offense. My choice was to identify the character played by Ms. Jones (whose passionate portrayal received an Oscar nomination) as half-Indian, half-Anglo. That's just not satisfying. A current locution, applied to and by Tiger Woods and Barack Obama, is of mixed heritage, which sounds overly formal or not specific enough, but that may be because it is relatively new.</p>
        <p>Mixed is also part of a euphemism chosen by pet lovers (the most avid of whom call themselves ''companion animal'' lovers) to substitute for the word mongrel; that word, from the Old English gemang, ''mixed,'' has a bad connotation, perhaps influenced by its growling gr. Dog breeders have taken up mixed breed (not to mention designer breed) as a euphemism just as the human population in general has put down half-breed as a dysphemism.</p>
        <p>Today's most acceptable all-around term is person of color, which may lead to the return someday of colored without any racist resonance. I will entertain an e-mail discussion of this from the wide spectrum of the Mavenhood, but no snarling, ye young varmints.</p>
        <p>THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 04-22-07: ON LANGUAGE</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 6, 2007, Sunday  The On Language column on April 22, about ''varmint,'' misstated the magazine in which President Bush used the word in 2004. It was Field &amp; Stream, not Outdoor Life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 6, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>The On Language column on April 22, about ''varmint,'' misstated the magazine in which President Bush used the word in 2004. It was Field &amp; Stream, not Outdoor Life.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
