<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Danube (Both Sides) on Hudson</title>
    <meta content="22weekend" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/travel/22weekend.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841945"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEEKEND IN NEW YORK | ROMANIAN AND BULGARIAN CULTURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Romanian-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bulgarian-Americans</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kugel, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE1DA113FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1030" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Danube (Both Sides) on Hudson</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Danube (Both Sides) on Hudson</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH KUGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kugel, Seth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Seth Kugel Weekend in New York column on Romanian and Bulgarian neighborhoods, restaurants and festivals; list; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ROMANIA and Bulgaria joined the European Union in January, so in the long run, there may be less economic incentive for their residents to emigrate to New York. Luckily for lovers of mititei and shopska salad, plenty of them are already here.</p>
        <p>About 22,000 Romanian and 4,000 Bulgarian immigrants live in New York, according to the Department of City Planning. And for those who want to know what the European Union gained without traveling to Europe, the next month is a great time to come to New York: with festivals and concerts, it's a virtual Danube-visits-the-Hudson.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Luckily for lovers of mititei and shopska salad, there are plenty of ways to get a fix in the city this month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ROMANIA and Bulgaria joined the European Union in January, so in the long run, there may be less economic incentive for their residents to emigrate to New York. Luckily for lovers of mititei and shopska salad, plenty of them are already here.</p>
        <p>About 22,000 Romanian and 4,000 Bulgarian immigrants live in New York, according to the Department of City Planning. And for those who want to know what the European Union gained without traveling to Europe, the next month is a great time to come to New York: with festivals and concerts, it's a virtual Danube-visits-the-Hudson.</p>
        <p>First, food. The Bulgarians may claim to have invented yogurt, but unless you count the Dannon and Yoplait shelves at the supermarket, there are more places in New York to eat Romanian. They're concentrated in Sunnyside, Queens, a short subway ride from Grand Central or Times Square on the No. 7 line. Peter Meehan, a Times restaurant critic, recommends Acasa, where he liked the caviar spread and a dessert translated as ''Fried Cheese Donuts with sweet vanilla creamy sauce.'' He also sampled the seltzer-in-your-wine tradition that some Romanians love and others consider a national embarrassment.</p>
        <p>At other spots, like Casa Romana and Harmony 2, you can try the mititei, often translated as Romanian sausage but closer to a grilled mini-meatloaf made with ground pork, ground beef and spices. Served with standard-issue mustard, it can seem a bit of a plain Jane, but smile and tell the Romanians you love it. There's also stuffed cabbage with polenta, and genuinely lovable dips and pastes made from eggplant and beans.</p>
        <p>Be prepared for the décor, which can topple hopelessly over the kitsch cliff. Among the topplers: Casa Romana, with its disco ball, fake plants and textured ceiling that looks like an upside-down lemon-meringue pie. On weekend nights, there is live entertainment. Gigi Marga, the octogenarian singer and former Romanian celebrity, often takes the stage, causing double-takes among those who used to love her when she (and they) lived back home.</p>
        <p>Harmony 2 is more refined: white tablecloths and attentive service buffer the chandeliers and the banquet-hall feel. The skylights make it especially nice for lunch, as does its proximity to Nita European Bakery. This bakery is no pain au chocolat and cannoli spot, though. There is amandina, a chocolate cake with almond flavoring, and savarina, a cake soaked in rum syrup. A sweet bread known as cozonac comes in flavors like chocolate and Turkish delight.</p>
        <p>You can skip the trip to Queens if you come the weekend of May 5: that's the eighth annual Romanian Day Festival, on a half-mile stretch of Water Street downtown. You'll find all the food there, along with regional costumes of Moldavia (not to be confused with the neighboring country of Moldova), Transylvania (the region, not the vampire lair) and others. If you happen to be stuck in Bucharest and can't make it to New York for the festival, you can catch it live on Romanian television.</p>
        <p>But enough of Romania. There are two legit Bulgarian spots in town, including the Bulgarian Bar, a k a the Bulgarian Disco, a k a Mehanata, a k a ''that crazy Bulgarian place at Canal and Broadway.'' It reopened last year in a hipper spot, on the Lower East Side, but some Bulgarians say they remember when a performer at its old, weird Canal and Broadway spot in Chinatown once made the papers back home for having ''debuted on Broadway.'' There are two floors: an upstairs bar and restaurant, with a stress on the bar (you have to ask for the food menu), and a downstairs disco where the Slavic beat goes on.</p>
        <p>But if you just want to eat, you're better off at Bulgara, an island of charm in industrial Long Island City. The shopska salad, with its creamy Bulgarian feta topping a mix of cucumbers and tomatoes, is on almost every table (and the feta-and-cottage-cheese-stuffed fried peppers should be). Main courses come off the grill; the drink of choice is rakia, a Bulgarian brandy.</p>
        <p>Bulgarian music sometimes gets going at 9 or 10 p.m., and though the trend toward pop-folk may not be sophisticated (note the scanty outfits and only slightly less scanty singing talent) but people get up and dance, in couples or in a long line with the singer in front. If you do well at Greek or Jewish weddings, with a few rakias you should be able to fake the Bulgarian steps, too.</p>
        <p>The Bulgarian Film Festival wraps up next Friday at the Scandinavian House (sorry, no Swedish subtitles), and next Sunday there is the Bulgarian Virtuosi Chamber Orchestra concert in Weill Hall at Carnegie Hall. The Bulgarian Concert Evenings in New York series offers concerts free to the public (on weekdays); the next one is ''Schubertiada'' on May 9 at the Bulgarian Consulate. And at Weill Hall, ''Musical Treasures from Bulgaria'' can be heard on May 22.</p>
        <p>Starting May 1, you can also study Bulgaria through non-Bulgarian eyes at the Jadite Gallery, whose assistant director is Bulgarian. Eleanor Gilpatrick, an American painter, will be taking over the three-room space, and the largest room will be devoted to her landscapes of Bulgaria, where she traveled last year, so you don't have to.</p>
        <p>PASS THE MITETEI AND SHOPSKA</p>
        <p>ROMANIAN</p>
        <p>Acasa, 48-06 Skillman Avenue, Sunnyside, Queens; (718) 651-1364; www.acasany.com.</p>
        <p>Casa Romana, 39-20 Queens Boulevard, Sunnyside, Queens; (718) 784-4768; www.casaromanarestaurant.com.</p>
        <p>Harmony 2, 47-57 41st Street, Sunnyside, Queens; (718) 784-4651.</p>
        <p>Nita's European Bakery, 40-10 Greenpoint Avenue, Sunnyside, Queens; (718) 784-4047.</p>
        <p>Romanian Day Festival, Sunday, May 5, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; on Water Street between Fulton and Broad Streets, Lower Manhattan.</p>
        <p>BULGARIAN</p>
        <p>Mehanata Bulgarian Bar, 113 Ludlow Street, Lower East Side; (212) 625-0981; www.mehanata.com.</p>
        <p>Bulgara, 37-10 11th Street, Long Island City, Queens; (718) 392-5373; www.bulgara-ny.com.</p>
        <p>Bulgarian Concert Evenings in New York, at the Bulgarian Consulate, 121 East 62nd Street. Information: www.bceny.blog-city.com; reservations: (212) 726-0428.</p>
        <p>Bulgarian Film Festival, at Scandinavian House, 58 Park Avenue; (914) 433-2938; www.ny-bgfilmfest.com. Final films are April 27.</p>
        <p>Weill Hall at Carnegie Hall, 57th Street and Seventh Avenue; www.carnegiehall.com. April 29: Bulgarian Virtuosi Chamber Orchestra, 2 p.m. May 22: ''Musical Treasures From Bulgaria,'' 8 p.m.</p>
        <p>WEEKEND IN NEW YORK | ROMANIAN AND BULGARIAN CULTURE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
