<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Model Child</title>
    <meta content="Wagner.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/books/review/Wagner.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841931"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Shapiro, Dani</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Black &amp; White (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E4D7123FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1263" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Model Child</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Model Child</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERICA WAGNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wagner, Erica</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Black &amp; White</p>
        <p>By Dani Shapiro.</p>
        <p>256 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $24.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dani Shapiro’s protagonist was her photographer/mother’s favorite subject.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Black &amp; White</p>
        <p>By Dani Shapiro.</p>
        <p>256 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $24.</p>
        <p>To whom does a novel belong? There it is -- an object of a certain size, shape and weight, its title, its author's name on the cover. So there can be, you would think, little doubt. ''Black &amp; White,'' this one says, ''a novel by Dani Shapiro.'' So this novel belongs to, is made by, Dani Shapiro. So far, so good. But when I read Shapiro's book, she is not with me. I have only her words, black marks on white pages, though in this novel her title should be taken to refer, of course, to the photographic images that have made its protagonist a celebrity, albeit an unwilling one. But art exists just as much in the mind of the reader (or beholder) as it does in the mind of its creator, if not more so. I once heard Margaret Atwood respond to an intricate question of interpretation with regard to the sexual politics of ''The Handmaid's Tale'' with three simple words, dryly delivered: ''You tell me.'' Some might call that evasive; I'd say it's right on the money.</p>
        <p>Shapiro's novel hinges on this question of interpretation: the interpretation of art and, in this context, the interpretation of a life. As the novel opens, Clara Brodeur returns to Manhattan to face her dying mother, Ruth Dunne, whom she has not seen in 14 years. Clara dropped out of high school, fled New York at 18 and finally made herself a home all the way up in Maine, on Mount Desert Island; it seems to Clara that if she goes this far, finally, she will have escaped her past. Mount Desert is her husband's idea, and to Clara it offers a dream of freedom: ''He had said the magic word. Island. A place disconnected from the mainland. A place floating on its own, separate, apart.'' And so her city-girl self vanishes, or apparently so, swallowed into a life as the wife of a jewelry maker who makes a good living in the summer months, and as the mother of Samantha, their 9-year-old daughter, who is ignorant of her mother's past.</p>
        <p>Clara had fled, all those years ago, because her mother's fame as a photographer arose out of the images she took of her daughter, images Clara has needed to leave behind so that ''Clara Dunne no longer exists, at least not as a living, breathing person. Clara Dunne is only a flat black-and-white series of images, frozen in time: a toddler, a little nymph, a prepubescent creature, a teenager -- hanging on the walls of museums and galleries, sold at auction to the highest bidder.'' (The images described in the novel resemble, to some degree, the work of the photographer Sally Mann.) Now, Clara's older sister, Robin, has called Clara back to New York because their mother has cancer. You could say, at this point, that the novel's central proposition is trite: how will Clara face the demons of her past?</p>
        <p>Yet all universal dilemmas -- and this is certainly one -- could be dismissed as trite. The truth is they face us all, and it is the novelist's job to breathe life into them one way or another, and this is something Shapiro does very well indeed. The strength of this novel is its particularity, its specificity, whether Shapiro is raking over the changes wrought by the years to the Upper West Side or describing Clara's sense of dislocation as she attempts to blend in with the other moms on the Maine island: ''Good sharing, honey! they'd call encouragingly from the sidelines. Nice work!''</p>
        <p>This clarity is peculiarly, disturbingly on show in the scenes of flashbacks that describe the making of what would come to be called ''The Clara Series,'' the photographs that catapult their maker -- and their subject -- into the weird upper stratosphere of New York art world fame. They begin almost by accident; the first in the series, ''Clara With the Lizard,'' is taken when Clara is 3; prints now sell for nearly a quarter of a million dollars. Shapiro layers the perceptions of Clara as a toddler with a plastic lizard in her mouth (''She puts the lizard in her mouth and tries to ignore the taste. It isn't so bad, really. Kind of like the soft fat-free yogurt her dad let her try one day when he was pushing her in her stroller down Broadway.'' ) with the knowing perceptions of the adult Clara: ''Her mouth around the lizard, her eyes huge and glistening, her leg raised on the edge of the tub, her private parts, as Ruth liked to call them, splayed open.'' She layers a child's desire to please alongside Ruth's ambition, her willingness to wake her little girl in the dead of night and make her stand naked in a fountain. Ruth Dunne does not emerge from all this with much parental credit, as you may already imagine. Clara flees because she feels violated, because she feels her childhood has been stolen, that her desired closeness with her mother has come at too high a price. The reader doesn't blame her.</p>
        <p>And so it is surprising that this novel's denouement is more gentle than one would have -- until quite close to its end -- imagined. I found myself wondering, if I were Clara, if I could be reconciled to this mother, if I could ever fall under the sway of downtown gallery owners, however noble their intentions. And this is where the question of ownership comes in. We never see, of course, Ruth Dunne's photographs of Clara; we can only ever see them through Clara's eyes, whether those eyes are those of a small child or those of a grown woman -- the eyes of the novelist. We can know, because we are told, that they are sensational, that newspaper reporters try to ambush Clara at her fancy East Side private school on her second day of fourth grade, that her classmates know about the ''bad words and stuff'' that protesters daub on her mother's images. We are told, too, that Clara's two week absence from Mount Desert causes her own daughter to stop eating, to pull away from her mother, to distrust her; for Clara, up until this point, has never mentioned her own mother's existence, never mind her fame.</p>
        <p>The reader must conjure Ruth Dunne's photographs as she must the lives in this novel; and, though it seems strange to say it, the weakness of the novel's ending demonstrates its strength. For when a writer has the skill to make those black scratches on white paper somehow live and breathe, it is the reader who feels she comes to own those characters, not the writer. As I turned the last pages of this book I found myself saying, out loud, Really? I had the strange feeling I somehow knew them better than their own creator did, that I would have chosen differently, that this resolution was nothing more than an illusion.</p>
        <p>And perhaps it is. Good novels go on beyond their final pages. They leave their authors and enter the minds of readers, who will ask questions, make demands and sometimes find themselves dissatisfied, just as they do with the flesh and blood creatures who inhabit the world outside the pages of a book. I'm glad it seemed to work for Clara, in the end. But I'm also glad that I'm not so sure that was the end. It's no bad thing to close a book and still be left wondering what happens next.</p>
        <p>Erica Wagner is the literary editor of The Times of London. Her new book is ''Seizure,'' a novel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Erica Wagner is the literary editor of The Times of London. Her new book is ''Seizure,'' a novel.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
