<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>They're Here. They're Funny. Get Used to It.</title>
    <meta content="22itzk" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/arts/television/22itzk.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841983"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Logo (Cable Channel)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Itzkoff, Dave</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Big Gay Sketch Show, The (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DE1E3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1342" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>They're Here. They're Funny. Get Used to It.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">They’re Here. They’re Funny. Get Used to It.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ITZKOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Itzkoff, Dave</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on new TV show The Big Gay Sketch Show, comedy series about to debut on Logo, the gay- and lesbian-themed cable channel; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS many times as ''The Honeymooners'' has been parodied, it's never been done quite like this. While Alice Kramden tends to her kitchen, her housekeeping duties are interrupted by the entrance of her bus-driving spouse -- not a big lummox named Ralph, but her ''secret homosexual lifetime commitment partner companion,'' a woman named Rhonda. And when Alice pesters Rhonda for ''a new black-and-white TV set with rabbit ears,'' Rhonda delivers: She gives her wife an African-American transvestite wearing a white satin gown and, yes, rabbit ears.</p>
        <p>This is what classic television looks like through the pink prism of ''The Big Gay Sketch Show,'' a comedy series making its debut Tuesday on Logo, MTV Networks' gay- and lesbian-themed cable channel. Yes, as the title indicates, it is a traditional half-hour showcase of skits featuring original characters and sendups of popular culture. And by the way, it's the first show of its kind to put its gay identity front and center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A gay-friendly cable channel veers from its “earnest, respectful path” to make room for comedy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS many times as ''The Honeymooners'' has been parodied, it's never been done quite like this. While Alice Kramden tends to her kitchen, her housekeeping duties are interrupted by the entrance of her bus-driving spouse -- not a big lummox named Ralph, but her ''secret homosexual lifetime commitment partner companion,'' a woman named Rhonda. And when Alice pesters Rhonda for ''a new black-and-white TV set with rabbit ears,'' Rhonda delivers: She gives her wife an African-American transvestite wearing a white satin gown and, yes, rabbit ears.</p>
        <p>This is what classic television looks like through the pink prism of ''The Big Gay Sketch Show,'' a comedy series making its debut Tuesday on Logo, MTV Networks' gay- and lesbian-themed cable channel. Yes, as the title indicates, it is a traditional half-hour showcase of skits featuring original characters and sendups of popular culture. And by the way, it's the first show of its kind to put its gay identity front and center.</p>
        <p>It is also a series that did not seem to fit into Logo's lineup, at least initially. When the network was started in 2005, its programming favored dramas, independent films and reality shows that offered inclusive, rather than potentially polarizing, depictions of gay people.</p>
        <p>''We sort of, by design, went down a very earnest, respectful path, because I really wanted to put out a diverse, grounded representation of gay people,'' said Brian Graden, the president of Logo and an MTV executive who has helped develop subversive comedy series like ''South Park'' and ''Wonder Showzen.'' ''There's been enough cartoonish gay characters over the years.''</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Graden said he had hoped that the channel would eventually be able to accommodate a more ironic voice, and he extended an invitation to Rosie O'Donnell to develop such a show for him.</p>
        <p>In a concise, all-caps e-mail message, Ms. O'Donnell, who is an executive producer of the show, was clear about her ambitions in taking on the project: ''To make a funny sketch show for Logo,'' she wrote. ''They need original programming.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Graden added that he wanted a series that would augment the small supply of gay-positive messages television comedy has offered -- in sitcoms like ''Will &amp; Grace'' and in the public coming-out experiences of personalities like Ms. O'Donnell and Ellen DeGeneres -- while using satire to push past negative stereotypes.</p>
        <p>''What I love is that it lets you repossess the platform,'' Mr. Graden explained. ''You say: 'Guess what? We know our culture better than anyone. We're going to be the joke-tellers this time.' ''</p>
        <p>Early last year Ms. O'Donnell and the producers of the show began recruiting writers and a director and auditioning performers. In March they staged two live test shows: one for close friends and industry colleagues (and Liza Minnelli) and one for an audience that included Mr. Graden, who promptly ordered six episodes.</p>
        <p>Staff members like Amanda Bearse, the show's director, say the series is an opportunity to continue doing the work they have always done, but now in the company of their gay and lesbian peers. A former star of the Fox sitcom ''Married  With Children,'' Ms. Bearse came out publicly at the height of that show's popularity and has since enjoyed a second career directing series like ''Reba'' and ''Mad TV.''</p>
        <p>''Some people know me as a lesbian, some people don't know that aspect of my life,'' Ms. Bearse said. ''This is just one more job. In a sense it's that generic. But for me, I chose it for its pointed quality.''</p>
        <p>For others the show offered the freedom to create material they had been unable to produce on previous series. Scott King, the head writer and one of the executive producers, previously held those same positions at ''Mad TV'' but left in 2005 after falling out with a show runner who, Mr. King said, accused him of having a gay agenda.</p>
        <p>''My gay agenda is basically to make out with Lenny Kravitz while wearing expensive shoes,'' Mr. King said. ''Absolutely nothing to do with my comedy.'' (Through a publicist at Fox, the producers of ''Mad TV'' declined to comment for this article.)</p>
        <p>The advantage that ''The Big Gay Sketch Show'' offered, Mr. King said, was the opportunity not only to write the sketches he wanted to write, but also to use a vocabulary that viewers would immediately understand.</p>
        <p>He pointed to a skit about a suburban family whose backyard is invaded by a bear -- that is, a burly man in a leather cap and overalls. ''On a regular show,'' Mr. King said, ''you'd have to go through this explanation: 'You see, there are these big gay men that are hairy, and that we refer to as bears.' In the explanation, you wind up becoming offensive in a way you didn't mean to be.''</p>
        <p>The skits on ''The Big Gay Sketch Show'' aren't solely grounded in gay culture; some are simply born from personalities the performers find funny. One cast member, Kate McKinnon, portrays everyone from Heidi Klum to Rachael Ray to an original character named Fitzwilliam, a nasty little British boy who yearns to be a nasty little British girl. ''I just wanted to do a cantankerous little child who you have to love anyway, 'cause he's British,'' said Ms. McKinnon, a recent Columbia graduate who was discovered at an open casting call.</p>
        <p>Not every member of the eight-member cast is gay, but that doesn't mean they're not in on the joke. Nicol Paone, a comedian who performed with the Los Angeles troupe the Groundlings, said she was thrilled to find herself impersonating Elaine Stritch in the first episode of the show, in a skit that finds that brassy actress and gay favorite employed as a greeter for Wal-Mart. ''That's important to me,'' Ms. Paone said, ''to play people that I admire and respond to.''</p>
        <p>The track record for socially conscious television comedy is not a promising one. The producers of ''The Big Gay Sketch Show'' are all too aware of the lessons of ''Chappelle's Show,'' whose host, Dave Chappelle, walked off the series, arguing that viewers were laughing at the racial caricatures in the skits and not their underlying messages, and ''In Living Color,'' which began with promise but rapidly ran out of creative energy.</p>
        <p>''I feel like we're in an enviable and an unenviable position of being the first ones that are doing this, and there's so much material to choose from,'' Mr. King said. ''If we're on the air for 8 or 9 or 10 years, and we start to say, 'How do we do this and not repeat ourselves?' -- I'm sure it will happen at some point, God willing.''</p>
        <p>They may not even reach Season 2 if viewers are turned off by the show's bold title. But several of the performers said they were proud of it. ''If we're not going to embrace what we are, then why bother even doing it?'' asked Michael Serrato, a cast member who was also recruited from the Groundlings. ''But I love it. When people ask me what I've been working on and I say, 'The Big Gay Sketch Show,' they're automatically intrigued. It's not like saying, 'From the writers of ''Friends.'' ' ''</p>
        <p>Logo, which reaches just 26 million homes nationwide and appeals to advertisers by connecting them to a gay demographic, does not necessarily need a crossover audience for the show to be a success. ''It's just not our aim, but what a great incidental effect,'' Mr. Graden said. Yet without really trying, the show may still end up reaching viewers outside its intended audience. When Ms. Paone, who plays Alice Kramden in the ''Honeymooners'' parody, surprised her father, a lifelong Jackie Gleason fan, by bringing him to a taping of the skit, she got a surprise in return.</p>
        <p>''I may have made an Italian man from New Jersey cry a little,'' she said. ''Now, interestingly enough, he can't stop talking about the show. There are 20 Italian men in Newark, probably half of them named Joey, waiting for 'The Big Gay Sketch Show.' ''</p>
        <p>TELEVISION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
