<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Archie Bunker's Feisty Feminist Flip Side</title>
    <meta content="22deca" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/arts/television/22deca.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070506T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841982"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DVD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Video)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Decaro, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arthur, Bea</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Maude (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">CBS Corp</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Arthur, Bea</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE0DE1E3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="811" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Archie Bunker's Feisty Feminist Flip Side</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Archie Bunker’s Feisty Feminist Flip Side</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK DeCARO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Decaro, Frank</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on 1970s TV show Maude, whose first season has been released on DVD; strength of Maude's character as played by Bea Arthur, show's origins and examples of controversial themes explored on show discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FEMINISM first reared its lacquered head on a hit sitcom in 1966.</p>
        <p>Marlo Thomas, playing ''That Girl'' Ann Marie, proved that an aspiring New York actress with a flip hairdo could live alone and conquer showbiz -- or at least persuade Ethel Merman to come over and cook dinner for her once.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 1970s show starring Bea Arthur that dealt with topics like racism, infidelity and most notoriously, abortion, shows how smart television could be.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FEMINISM first reared its lacquered head on a hit sitcom in 1966.</p>
        <p>Marlo Thomas, playing ''That Girl'' Ann Marie, proved that an aspiring New York actress with a flip hairdo could live alone and conquer showbiz -- or at least persuade Ethel Merman to come over and cook dinner for her once.</p>
        <p>Four years later Mary Tyler Moore's budding newswoman, Mary Richards, was showing once a week that a spunky singleton with an M on her wall could make it after all surrounded by warm friends in frigid Minneapolis on ''The Mary Tyler Moore Show.''</p>
        <p>They were both independent women, but they weren't ''liberated.''</p>
        <p>And then there was ''Maude,'' in 1972, and no one, except perhaps the series's creator, the TV pioneer Norman Lear, had ever spent his Tuesday nights with a woman like her. Based in part on Mr. Lear's flamboyantly opinionated wife, Frances, Maude Findlay was an eardrum-shattering, upper-middle-class liberal from Tuckahoe, N.Y., who popped tranquilizers, drank martinis and changed husbands as often as she changed her signature maxi-vests.</p>
        <p>With her voluptuous adult daughter, Carol, a divorcée played by Adrienne Barbeau, and her precocious grandson sharing her comfortable suburban home, Maude didn't turn the world on with her smile, as Mary Richards did, but instead with one fatal look could wither her Republican neighbor, Arthur (Conrad Bain). Maude's oft-repeated deep-voiced warning to her beleaguered fourth husband (Bill Macy), ''God'll get you for that, Walter,'' was deadly compared with Ann Marie's exasperated cry to her milquetoast boyfriend, ''Oh, Donald.'' Maude was the kind of woman who would threaten to rip even her grandson's heart out if he disobeyed her.</p>
        <p>Running for six seasons -- and riotously funny for almost as long -- ''Maude'' unleashed on television the formidable Bea Arthur, a Broadway actress whose boozy Vera Charles in the musical ''Mame'' is the stuff of theater legend. Ms. Arthur appeared as Edith Bunker's left-wing cousin Maude on a 1971 episode of Mr. Lear's first hit, ''All in the Family,'' and made such an impression with audiences that, as the story goes, the CBS programming executive Fred Silverman suggested a spinoff as fast as the producers could get it on the air.</p>
        <p>''All in the Family'' had introduced to the domestic sitcom real-life topics, from social politics to bathroom use, and dealt with them in language franker than TV audiences had ever heard. ''Maude'' went even further in its weekly squabbles. The first season's 22 episodes, which Sony recently released as a three-DVD set (with no extras), dealt with topics like racism, infidelity, sexual equality, divorce, menstruation, malpractice and, most notoriously, abortion, when Maude found herself pregnant at 47.</p>
        <p>That two-part episode, titled ''Maude's Dilemma,'' came in the wake of the Roe v. Wade decision. It was sensitively written by Susan Harris, who went on to create ''The Golden Girls.'' The subject was as controversial then as it would probably be now, but it shows how smart ''Maude'' and television could be.</p>
        <p>Maude Findlay has often been called the anti-Archie Bunker, but she was a lot more like him than she would have ever wanted to believe. He was a blue-collar bigot as lovable as he was infuriating. She was an upscale bleeding-heart matron as misguided as she was well intentioned. In an early episode, for instance, Maude's attempts at what we now call political correctness backfire when she hires a housekeeper named Florida Evans (played by the wonderful Esther Rolle, who would get her own spinoff, ''Good Times,'' in 1974). Both Maude and Archie had their hearts in the right place no matter what was coming out of their mouths, which is why audiences loved them.</p>
        <p>While caught up in a suburban whirl of dinner parties and fund-raisers as the wife of a successful appliance dealer, Maude spends a lot of time navigating her way in a proto-feminist world, trying (often unsuccessfully) to shake off the gender stereotypes of earlier generations. She stands up to every man who challenges her -- even John Wayne, playing himself in a memorable third-season episode, ''Maude Meets the Duke'' -- but, like a faithful puppy, she always obediently responds to Walter's command ''Moooo-aude, sit,'' when she knows she has gotten out of hand.</p>
        <p>Rarely rebroadcast since it was initially on the air, ''Maude'' was last seen in 1999 in a brief run on TV Land. The groundbreaking character is much less widely known by younger audiences than Ms. Arthur's turn as Dorothy Zbornak on ''The Golden Girls,'' a gentler if no less important series repeated endlessly on cable. Everybody loves Dorothy. But Maude Findlay was Bea Arthur's career-defining role, and ''Maude'' is where she perfected the slow burn that even now no one does better. If a Zbornak zinger is lethal on Lifetime, a Maude Findlay put-down, even after 35 years, is a weapon of mass destruction just waiting to be detonated on DVD.</p>
        <p>FRANK DeCARO</p>
        <p>DVD</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 6, 2007, Sunday  An article on April 22 about a DVD of the first season of the television series ''Maude'' misstated the date a two-part episode about abortion was broadcast. It was a few months before the Supreme Court's decision in Roe v. Wade in January 1973, not after.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 6, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article on April 22 about a DVD of the first season of the television series ''Maude'' misstated the date a two-part episode about abortion was broadcast. It was a few months before the Supreme Court's decision in Roe v. Wade in January 1973, not after.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
