<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dublin</title>
    <meta content="22hours" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/travel/22hours.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070506T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841946"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="36 HOURS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Dublin (Ireland)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ireland</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Knight, Wendy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/36 Hours</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Ireland/Dublin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Dublin (Ireland)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E0DA113FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1571" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dublin</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">36 Hours in Dublin</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WENDY KNIGHT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Knight, Wendy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wendy Knight travel article on 36-hour visit to Dublin, Ireland; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A pint of beer in Dublin will run you 4 to 5 euros, but the famed Irish wit is free. With an economic boom fueled by banks, high-tech companies and tourism, this compact Gaelic city is no longer the land of ramshackle pubs and baked-potato pushcarts. Stylish restaurants, designer hotels and pricey shopping malls abound. But Dublin's wealth has also brought with it an influx of Poles and other Eastern European immigrants, who are helping to keep prices in check, while also giving this ancient city a cosmopolitan face-lift. So expect phone-card kiosks next to old butcher shops and Slavic accents alongside the charming Irish brogues.</p>
        <p>Friday</p>
        <p>3:30 p.m.  1) European Masters  One of Dublin's finest cultural landmarks, the National Gallery of Ireland, is also its most economical: admission is free. The National Gallery (Merrion Square West and Clare Street; 353-1-661-5133; www.nationalgallery.ie.) displays works by 17th- to 20th-century Irish artists including Jack Butler Yeats, brother of the poet William Butler Yeats, and an impressive selection of Italian works including Caravaggio's magnificent '' Taking of Christ,'' which he painted in 1602. Van Gogh's ''Rooftop in Paris'' is among the museum's recent acquisitions.</p>
        <p>7:30 p.m.  2) Friday Night Lights  Although the culinary scene in Dublin is becoming more varied, its traditional choice of two extremes -- standard pub grub and overpriced French cuisine-- can be tiring. Solas (31 Wexford Street, 353-1-478-0583, www.solasbars.com), which means light in Gaelic, is an enlightening alternative. An artsy and media clientele gather downstairs at the 22-foot-long stainless-steel bar with red-cushion stools. The new second-floor bar is filled with light from the adjoining roof terrace. This nonchalantly hip establishment boasts a 40-plus list of world beers (5.30 euros, or $7.20, at $1.36 to the euro) and a Mediterranean menu with an antipasto salad with Serrano ham and chorizo (9.50 euros), which will leave you wondering whether your flight detoured to Madrid or Rome.</p>
        <p>10 p.m.  3) Pints and Reels  Dublin has more than 1,000 pubs, many featuring live Irish music, though you won't find a posted schedule anywhere. Skip the trendy Temple Bar area and wander north of the River Liffey to Hughes Bar (19 Chancery Street, 353-1-872-6540), which is just behind the eerily quiet Courthouse area. Local musicians like Paul Doyle and a renowned Cape Breton fiddler, Jerry Holland, perform at the bar. The faded pumpkin-colored walls, the plastic plants and old men in cardigan sweaters let you know you've found the real deal. For more merriment, head to O'Donoghue's (15 Merrion Row, 353-1-660-7194) in the South Georgian area, where musicians congregate at the front of the bar, sipping pints of Guinness (4.50 euros) and playing their fiddles and tin whistles, just as the Dubliners, one of Ireland's best-known bands did in the 1970s.</p>
        <p>Saturday</p>
        <p>9:30 a.m.  4) Brew Tour  Although it might seem sacrilegious to step inside a brewery before noon, consider that Guinness was once prescribed to nursing mothers and patients for its ''cheer-producing effect.'' Besides, you will want to visit the Guinness Storehouse (St. James's Gate, Dublin 8, 353-1-408-4800; www.guinness-storehouse.com; admission is 14 euros) before the crowds grow thick around 11 a.m. The storehouse may scream tourist trap, but it's an engaging and sleek tour of how the dark stout has been made since 1759, beginning with water from the Wicklow Mountains that streams throughout the exhibit. The tour takes you through a labyrinth of catwalks, past an old roasting oven and up a circular staircase that wraps around a huge oak barrel. It ends at the seventh-floor Gravity Bar, where one free pint of Guinness is served per visitor. If you're still hungry after a Guinness, head to Bruxelle (7-8 Harry Street, Dublin 2; 353-1-677-5362), a barley-smelling pub with worn wood floors that serves a hearty Irish breakfast of fried eggs, sausage, bacon, beans, blood pudding and toast -- for just 6 euros.</p>
        <p>Noon  5) Literary Traditions  Dublin was the birthplace of erudite lions like James Joyce and Samuel Beckett, so immerse yourself in its literary traditions. The Old Library Building at Trinity College (College Green, Nassau Street, 353-1- 896-2308; www.tcd.ie, 8 euros) houses the Book of Kells, a masterpiece of ancient calligraphy and art by ninth-century Irish monks. Upstairs, the magnificent vaulted Long Room has 200,000 of the college's oldest books, stacked in neat floor-to-ceiling rows, including a rare first edition of Dante's ''Divine Comedy.'' Make sure to also visit the less-heralded Dublin Writers' Museum (18 Parnell Square, 353-1-872-2077; 7 euros admission), which has the original chair used by Handel for the first performance of ''The Messiah'' (in the Temple Bar in 1742) and a first edition of ''Dracula,'' written by the Dublin-born writer Bram Stoker.</p>
        <p>2:30 p.m.  6) Oral Traditions  A major renovation of the historic Abbey Theatre (26 Lower Abbey Street, 353-1-878-7222, www.abbeytheatre.ie), unveiled this spring, will thankfully replace the Sinatra-era décor and dingy burgundy carpeting with plush new seats and interiors by the French designer Jean Guy LeCat. Built in 1904 (and rebuilt in 1966 after a fire), the Abbey had been the cultural home to such playwrights as William Butler Yeats, while continuing to promote new Irish playwrights like Billy Roche. Coming shows include Arthur Miller's ''Crucible'' (May 26 through July 7). Even though ticket prices rarely exceed 30 euros, you can catch the Saturday 2:30 p.m. matinee for 15 euros.</p>
        <p>4:30 p.m.  7) Three Funky Markets  You'll see mimes, gents in three-piece flannel suits and stroller-pushing moms walking briskly past the windows of Brown Thomas (88-95 Grafton Street, 353-1-605-6666; www.brownthomas.com), one of Dublin's grand department stores. But for funky and affordable shopping, check out the Saturday markets in the Temple Bar neighborhood (www.templebar.ie). The Fashion and Design Market (Cow's Land) is where you'll find Irish designers like the jewelry maker Clare Grennan (www.claregrennan.com) showcasing their latest creations. The Book and Record Market (Temple Bar Square) sells used and limited-edition books, as well as vinyl records and CDs. And the Food Market (Meeting House Square) sells delectable raw milk Irish cheeses and organic produce directly from farmers.</p>
        <p>7 p.m.  8) Beer Break  In the land of Guinness, the 470-bottle wine cellar at the Ely Wine Bar (22 Ely Place, 353-1-676-8986; www.elywinebar.ie) is a refreshing change. The two-story bistro has more than 90 wines available by the glass (6 to 14 euros) and one of the hottest singles scenes in town. Draped in wrap dresses, cashmere sweaters and stone-washed jeans, Dublin's fresh-faced professionals pack the dining room, cellar bars and a romantic, street-level lounge with an onyx bar and a stone fireplace. A family farm in County Clare supplies the restaurant with organic meat for dishes like lamb burger on creamed potatoes (15.95 euros) and bangers and mash (15 euros).</p>
        <p>9 p.m.  9) Village People  Dublin's younger, cosmopolitan set heads to the Village Venue (26 Wexford Street, 353-1-475-8555; www.thevillagevenue.com). The 650-seat hall features top acts like Tony Bennett and Morrissey (tickets around 25 euros), and the two-level space with stone interiors turns into a popular lounge and nightclub in the late evening. Expect women in short skirts and lads in button-down shirts. Established D.J.'s like John and Aoife Dermody spin techno, rock and pop music at 10 p.m. in the downstairs bar, and the dance floor opens at 11 p.m. (cover charge 7 to 10 euros).</p>
        <p>Sunday</p>
        <p>11 a.m.  10) Secret Garden  Walk off last night at Iveagh Gardens (Clonmel Street; 353-1-475-7816), an 8.5-acre gem of a park hidden behind the National Concert Hall near St. Stephen's Square. With its beheaded and broken statues, unkempt landscaping and leaf-canopied corners, the rambling park feels like a former starlet past her prime, though she springs to life every April, when the bluebells are in full bloom.</p>
        <p>1 p.m.  11) Queen for a Day  Sample the city's sweet side at Queen of Tarts (4 Corkhill Dame Street, 353-1-670-7499), a darling confectionery in Dublin's quiet medieval area. The glass display cases overflow with nectar-oozing plum tarts, savory scones and warm chocolate ganache cake (1.25 to 4.75 euros). And after a weekend of pints, a spot of tea goes down nicely.</p>
        <p>THE BASICS</p>
        <p>Continental flies direct to Dublin from the New York City area, starting at about $650. Aer Lingus flies from New York to Dublin, with a short stopover in Shannon, starting at $358. If you're already in London, Ryanair operates as many as 30 daily flights to Dublin for about 25 euros round trip, or $34, at $1.36 to the euro, not including taxes and fees.</p>
        <p>From Dublin Airport, a taxi ride into the city costs 20 to 35 euros. Dublin Bus (353-1-873-4222; www.dublinbus.ie) offers 35-minute rides into town every 10 minutes for 6 euros. Traffic in Dublin is hellish, and cabs are expensive, so it's best to walk.</p>
        <p>With its hip clientele and sunken lounge area, Number 31 (31 Lesson Close, 353-1-676-5011; www.number31.ie) is a B&amp;B that feels more like a boutique hotel. Fresh from a major renovation, the Georgian town house and adjoining coach house has 21 rooms, 8 of them very large. Rooms start at 160 euros and include a full Irish breakfast.</p>
        <p>Harrington Hall (70 Harcourt Street, Dublin 2, 353-1-475-3497; www.harringtonhall.com) is a 28-room guesthouse in a refurbished Georgian town house near St. Stephen's Green. All rooms have high-speed Internet connections and trouser presses. Rates begin at 120 euros and include a full breakfast.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stylish restaurants, designer hotels and pricey shopping malls abound in the Irish capital. No, this compact Gaelic city is no longer the land of ramshackle pubs and baked-potato pushcarts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A pint of beer in Dublin will run you 4 to 5 euros, but the famed Irish wit is free. With an economic boom fueled by banks, high-tech companies and tourism, this compact Gaelic city is no longer the land of ramshackle pubs and baked-potato pushcarts. Stylish restaurants, designer hotels and pricey shopping malls abound. But Dublin's wealth has also brought with it an influx of Poles and other Eastern European immigrants, who are helping to keep prices in check, while also giving this ancient city a cosmopolitan face-lift. So expect phone-card kiosks next to old butcher shops and Slavic accents alongside the charming Irish brogues.</p>
        <p>Friday</p>
        <p>3:30 p.m.  1) European Masters  One of Dublin's finest cultural landmarks, the National Gallery of Ireland, is also its most economical: admission is free. The National Gallery (Merrion Square West and Clare Street; 353-1-661-5133; www.nationalgallery.ie.) displays works by 17th- to 20th-century Irish artists including Jack Butler Yeats, brother of the poet William Butler Yeats, and an impressive selection of Italian works including Caravaggio's magnificent '' Taking of Christ,'' which he painted in 1602. Van Gogh's ''Rooftop in Paris'' is among the museum's recent acquisitions.</p>
        <p>7:30 p.m.  2) Friday Night Lights  Although the culinary scene in Dublin is becoming more varied, its traditional choice of two extremes -- standard pub grub and overpriced French cuisine-- can be tiring. Solas (31 Wexford Street, 353-1-478-0583, www.solasbars.com), which means light in Gaelic, is an enlightening alternative. An artsy and media clientele gather downstairs at the 22-foot-long stainless-steel bar with red-cushion stools. The new second-floor bar is filled with light from the adjoining roof terrace. This nonchalantly hip establishment boasts a 40-plus list of world beers (5.30 euros, or $7.20, at $1.36 to the euro) and a Mediterranean menu with an antipasto salad with Serrano ham and chorizo (9.50 euros), which will leave you wondering whether your flight detoured to Madrid or Rome.</p>
        <p>10 p.m.  3) Pints and Reels  Dublin has more than 1,000 pubs, many featuring live Irish music, though you won't find a posted schedule anywhere. Skip the trendy Temple Bar area and wander north of the River Liffey to Hughes Bar (19 Chancery Street, 353-1-872-6540), which is just behind the eerily quiet Courthouse area. Local musicians like Paul Doyle and a renowned Cape Breton fiddler, Jerry Holland, perform at the bar. The faded pumpkin-colored walls, the plastic plants and old men in cardigan sweaters let you know you've found the real deal. For more merriment, head to O'Donoghue's (15 Merrion Row, 353-1-660-7194) in the South Georgian area, where musicians congregate at the front of the bar, sipping pints of Guinness (4.50 euros) and playing their fiddles and tin whistles, just as the Dubliners, one of Ireland's best-known bands did in the 1970s.</p>
        <p>Saturday</p>
        <p>9:30 a.m.  4) Brew Tour  Although it might seem sacrilegious to step inside a brewery before noon, consider that Guinness was once prescribed to nursing mothers and patients for its ''cheer-producing effect.'' Besides, you will want to visit the Guinness Storehouse (St. James's Gate, Dublin 8, 353-1-408-4800; www.guinness-storehouse.com; admission is 14 euros) before the crowds grow thick around 11 a.m. The storehouse may scream tourist trap, but it's an engaging and sleek tour of how the dark stout has been made since 1759, beginning with water from the Wicklow Mountains that streams throughout the exhibit. The tour takes you through a labyrinth of catwalks, past an old roasting oven and up a circular staircase that wraps around a huge oak barrel. It ends at the seventh-floor Gravity Bar, where one free pint of Guinness is served per visitor. If you're still hungry after a Guinness, head to Bruxelle (7-8 Harry Street, Dublin 2; 353-1-677-5362), a barley-smelling pub with worn wood floors that serves a hearty Irish breakfast of fried eggs, sausage, bacon, beans, blood pudding and toast -- for just 6 euros.</p>
        <p>Noon  5) Literary Traditions  Dublin was the birthplace of erudite lions like James Joyce and Samuel Beckett, so immerse yourself in its literary traditions. The Old Library Building at Trinity College (College Green, Nassau Street, 353-1- 896-2308; www.tcd.ie, 8 euros) houses the Book of Kells, a masterpiece of ancient calligraphy and art by ninth-century Irish monks. Upstairs, the magnificent vaulted Long Room has 200,000 of the college's oldest books, stacked in neat floor-to-ceiling rows, including a rare first edition of Dante's ''Divine Comedy.'' Make sure to also visit the less-heralded Dublin Writers' Museum (18 Parnell Square, 353-1-872-2077; 7 euros admission), which has the original chair used by Handel for the first performance of ''The Messiah'' (in the Temple Bar in 1742) and a first edition of ''Dracula,'' written by the Dublin-born writer Bram Stoker.</p>
        <p>2:30 p.m.  6) Oral Traditions  A major renovation of the historic Abbey Theatre (26 Lower Abbey Street, 353-1-878-7222, www.abbeytheatre.ie), unveiled this spring, will thankfully replace the Sinatra-era décor and dingy burgundy carpeting with plush new seats and interiors by the French designer Jean Guy LeCat. Built in 1904 (and rebuilt in 1966 after a fire), the Abbey had been the cultural home to such playwrights as William Butler Yeats, while continuing to promote new Irish playwrights like Billy Roche. Coming shows include Arthur Miller's ''Crucible'' (May 26 through July 7). Even though ticket prices rarely exceed 30 euros, you can catch the Saturday 2:30 p.m. matinee for 15 euros.</p>
        <p>4:30 p.m.  7) Three Funky Markets  You'll see mimes, gents in three-piece flannel suits and stroller-pushing moms walking briskly past the windows of Brown Thomas (88-95 Grafton Street, 353-1-605-6666; www.brownthomas.com), one of Dublin's grand department stores. But for funky and affordable shopping, check out the Saturday markets in the Temple Bar neighborhood (www.templebar.ie). The Fashion and Design Market (Cow's Land) is where you'll find Irish designers like the jewelry maker Clare Grennan (www.claregrennan.com) showcasing their latest creations. The Book and Record Market (Temple Bar Square) sells used and limited-edition books, as well as vinyl records and CDs. And the Food Market (Meeting House Square) sells delectable raw milk Irish cheeses and organic produce directly from farmers.</p>
        <p>7 p.m.  8) Beer Break  In the land of Guinness, the 470-bottle wine cellar at the Ely Wine Bar (22 Ely Place, 353-1-676-8986; www.elywinebar.ie) is a refreshing change. The two-story bistro has more than 90 wines available by the glass (6 to 14 euros) and one of the hottest singles scenes in town. Draped in wrap dresses, cashmere sweaters and stone-washed jeans, Dublin's fresh-faced professionals pack the dining room, cellar bars and a romantic, street-level lounge with an onyx bar and a stone fireplace. A family farm in County Clare supplies the restaurant with organic meat for dishes like lamb burger on creamed potatoes (15.95 euros) and bangers and mash (15 euros).</p>
        <p>9 p.m.  9) Village People  Dublin's younger, cosmopolitan set heads to the Village Venue (26 Wexford Street, 353-1-475-8555; www.thevillagevenue.com). The 650-seat hall features top acts like Tony Bennett and Morrissey (tickets around 25 euros), and the two-level space with stone interiors turns into a popular lounge and nightclub in the late evening. Expect women in short skirts and lads in button-down shirts. Established D.J.'s like John and Aoife Dermody spin techno, rock and pop music at 10 p.m. in the downstairs bar, and the dance floor opens at 11 p.m. (cover charge 7 to 10 euros).</p>
        <p>Sunday</p>
        <p>11 a.m.  10) Secret Garden  Walk off last night at Iveagh Gardens (Clonmel Street; 353-1-475-7816), an 8.5-acre gem of a park hidden behind the National Concert Hall near St. Stephen's Square. With its beheaded and broken statues, unkempt landscaping and leaf-canopied corners, the rambling park feels like a former starlet past her prime, though she springs to life every April, when the bluebells are in full bloom.</p>
        <p>1 p.m.  11) Queen for a Day  Sample the city's sweet side at Queen of Tarts (4 Corkhill Dame Street, 353-1-670-7499), a darling confectionery in Dublin's quiet medieval area. The glass display cases overflow with nectar-oozing plum tarts, savory scones and warm chocolate ganache cake (1.25 to 4.75 euros). And after a weekend of pints, a spot of tea goes down nicely.</p>
        <p>THE BASICS</p>
        <p>Continental flies direct to Dublin from the New York City area, starting at about $650. Aer Lingus flies from New York to Dublin, with a short stopover in Shannon, starting at $358. If you're already in London, Ryanair operates as many as 30 daily flights to Dublin for about 25 euros round trip, or $34, at $1.36 to the euro, not including taxes and fees.</p>
        <p>From Dublin Airport, a taxi ride into the city costs 20 to 35 euros. Dublin Bus (353-1-873-4222; www.dublinbus.ie) offers 35-minute rides into town every 10 minutes for 6 euros. Traffic in Dublin is hellish, and cabs are expensive, so it's best to walk.</p>
        <p>With its hip clientele and sunken lounge area, Number 31 (31 Lesson Close, 353-1-676-5011; www.number31.ie) is a B&amp;B that feels more like a boutique hotel. Fresh from a major renovation, the Georgian town house and adjoining coach house has 21 rooms, 8 of them very large. Rooms start at 160 euros and include a full Irish breakfast.</p>
        <p>Harrington Hall (70 Harcourt Street, Dublin 2, 353-1-475-3497; www.harringtonhall.com) is a 28-room guesthouse in a refurbished Georgian town house near St. Stephen's Green. All rooms have high-speed Internet connections and trouser presses. Rates begin at 120 euros and include a full breakfast.  36 HOURS</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 6, 2007, Sunday  The 36 Hours column on April 22, about Dublin, misstated the location of the Fashion and Design Market there. It is on Cow's Lane, not Cow's Land.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 6, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>The 36 Hours column on April 22, about Dublin, misstated the location of the Fashion and Design Market there. It is on Cow's Lane, not Cow's Land.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
