<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Eat; Paris Match</title>
    <meta content="22food.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="73" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841955"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Costume Institute (Metropolitan Museum)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metropolitan Museum of Art (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Poiret, Paul (1879-1944)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Browne, Alix</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EED7113FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1289" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Eat; Paris Match</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Aleksandra Crapanzano</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Exhibition of fashions created by Paul Poiret is set to open at Costume Institute at Metropolitan Museum of Art; his influence can be seen in fall collections of several designers; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When it comes to food, Paris has long been the capital of nostalgia -- a grand lover of itself and its storied culinary ways, but no lover of fads or progress for progress's sake. More than anything, the city has rewarded memory and its tastes: a delicious contract that there will always be a certain amount of butter, cream and wine and a right way of doing things.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When it comes to food, Paris has long been the capital of nostalgia -- a grand lover of itself and its storied culinary ways, but no lover of fads or progress for progress's sake. More than anything, the city has rewarded memory and its tastes: a delicious contract that there will always be a certain amount of butter, cream and wine and a right way of doing things.</p>
        <p>But no longer, perhaps. This is the quiet but unmistakable message of two new and quite different cookbooks by Parisians -- one by the veteran food writer Patricia Wells (who is the restaurant critic for The International Herald Tribune, which is owned by The New York Times), the other by the relative newcomer Clotilde Dusoulier. What the French are eating is gradually being transformed by immigration, the whirlwind speed of contemporary life and even -- sacré bleu! -- the population's growing awareness of nutritional realities.</p>
        <p>''Vegetable Harvest'' is Wells's 10th book. And though she has made her well-earned reputation as a celebrator and interpreter of the French classics -- a bard of the bistro -- this is her first book that openly champions the changes in the French culinary mind-set. From the photographs of produce to the listing of calories, fat, protein and carbohydrates with each recipe, ''Vegetable Harvest'' marks a healthful departure for Wells, who is better known for dishes like cheese-and-bacon potato cake and tartes Tatin containing half a pound of butter. While there are recipes for fish and meat, including a garlic-rich seven-hour leg of lamb so tender I ate mine with a spoon, the reason for buying this book -- and buy it you should -- is the vegetables. There are shaved salads, grated salads, julienned salads. Her daube is of eggplant, not beef. The beef in her braised beef with carrots is intriguingly superfluous. Her papillote is of mushrooms, not fish. Her stew is of curried chickpeas, lentils and swiss chard. (My only complaint with Wells is with her serving sizes. If you ate such minuscule portions, you, too, would proudly announce the calorie content of each dish. You, too, might enjoy a gratin of potatoes for only 153 calories, providing you shared the meager 1 1/4 pounds of Yukon Golds with five other people!)</p>
        <p>In previous books, Wells, 60, has looked to chefs and friends for inspiration -- most notably in her two collaborations with JoÃdegreesl Robuchon; in ''Vegetable Harvest'' she turns instead to her own garden in Provence and produces her most original cooking yet. Short on butter and cream, these recipes are accented with Espelette pepper, enriched with a drizzle of pistachio oil, spiced with cumin and enlivened with lemon fleur de sel. Julienned celeriac is topped with fresh crabmeat, a play of tangy and sweet. A tomato broth is pared down to essentials: tomatoes, chicken stock, salt, tarragon. A particularly earnest recipe for spinach calls for, well, spinach with nothing much else besides salt and a pinch of nutmeg. It is a reminder of how little embellishment a good vegetable needs -- if any at all.</p>
        <p>While Wells has a fervent love for her vegetable garden, Dusoulier has contagious enthusiasm for her local Montmartre markets. Reading ''Chocolate and Zucchini'' is like going on a slightly frenetic shopping spree -- in other words, irresistible. Dusoulier is the Parisian friend we all wish we had. Call her for a recipe, and she might tell you (as she does in her wonderful recipe for lamb and prune meatballs) to marinate the meat for 8 hours, 30 minutes or merely for 10 minutes, as your schedule permits. And while the meatballs were certainly best with eight hours of marinating time, they also satisfied at 10 minutes.</p>
        <p>A 27-year-old Parisian, Dusoulier is best known for her blog ChocolateandZucchini.com. Started in 2003 as an extension of the copious cooking notes she kept for herself, the blog now tallies more than 4.5 million hits a month. Dusoulier's voice is boisterous, spirited, delightful and entirely forgiving. Upon realizing, for example, that ''the galaxy of food knows no bounds,'' that you could travel the globe over and still find entire new worlds of flavor, she stops to add with a child's glee, ''Excuse me while I clap my hands in excitement.'' Or consider her zany claim that no food was harmed in the process of photographing it. What a relief! Yet for all her playfulness, she's serious about food. Her take on the classics is modern and original, full of unexpected scents and tastes. Her madeleines are studded with diced pear, Roquefort and walnuts. Her gougÃ  Aleksandra Crapanzano, a screenwriter, lives in Brooklyn.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Aleksandra Crapanzano, a screenwriter, lives in Brooklyn.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
