<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Good Provider Is One Who Leaves</title>
    <meta content="22Workers.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="50" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841961"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Philippines</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Philippines</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Deparle, Jason</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Philippines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Philippines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E7D6113FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="8159" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Good Provider Is One Who Leaves</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jason DeParle</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Deparle, Jason</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jason DeParle article on Overseas Filipino Workers (OFP's), how their families and country benefit from foreign earnings they they regularly send home and the enormous personal costs of extended family separations; notes that OFP's are only part of global migrant workforce that totals 200 million and transferred estimated $300 billion home in 2006 from host countries; says Philippines is unique among these countries in bureaucracy pledged to reduce risks their nationals face abroad and manage social costs at home; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On June 25, 1980 (a date he would remember), a good-natured Filipino pool-maintenance man gathered his wife and five children for an upsetting ride to the Manila airport. At 36, Emmet Comodas had lived a hard life without growing hardened, which was a mixed blessing given the indignities of his poverty. Orphaned at 8, raised on the Manila streets where he hawked cigarettes, he had hustled a job at a government sports complex and held it for nearly two decades. On the spectrum of Filipino poverty, that alone marked him as a man of modest fortune. But a monthly salary of $50 did not keep his family fed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On June 25, 1980 (a date he would remember), a good-natured Filipino pool-maintenance man gathered his wife and five children for an upsetting ride to the Manila airport. At 36, Emmet Comodas had lived a hard life without growing hardened, which was a mixed blessing given the indignities of his poverty. Orphaned at 8, raised on the Manila streets where he hawked cigarettes, he had hustled a job at a government sports complex and held it for nearly two decades. On the spectrum of Filipino poverty, that alone marked him as a man of modest fortune. But a monthly salary of $50 did not keep his family fed.</p>
        <p>Home was a one-room, scrap-wood shanty in a warren of alleys and stinking canals, hidden by the whitewashed walls of an Imelda Marcos beautification campaign. He had borrowed money at usurious rates to start a tiny store, which a thief had plundered. His greatest fears centered on his 11-year-old daughter, Rowena, who had a congenital heart defect that turned her lips blue and fingernails black and who needed care he could not afford. After years of worrying over her frail physique, Emmet dropped to his moldering floor and asked God for a decision: take her or let him have her.</p>
        <p>God answered in a mysterious way. Not long after, Emmet's boss offered him a pool-cleaning job in Saudi Arabia. Emmet would make 10 times as much as he made in Manila. He would also live 4,500 miles from his family in an Islamic autocracy where stories of abused laborers were rife. He accepted on the spot. His wife, Tita, was afraid of the slum where she soon would be raising children alone, and she knew that overseas workers often had affairs. She also knew their kids ate better because of the money the workers sent home. She spent her last few pesos for admission to an airport lounge where she could wave at the vanishing jet, then went home to cry and wait.</p>
        <p>Two years later, on Aug. 2, 1982 (another date he would remember), Emmet walked off the returning flight with chocolate for the kids, earrings for Tita and a bag of duty-free cigarettes, his loneliness abroad having made him a chain smoker. His 2-year-old son, Boyet, considered him a stranger and cried at his touch, though as Emmet later said, ''I was too happy to be sad.'' He gave himself a party, replaced the shanty's rotted walls and put on a new roof. Then after three months at home, he left for Saudi Arabia again. And again. And again and again: by the time Emmet ended the cycle and came home for good, he had been gone for nearly two decades. Boyet was grown.</p>
        <p>Deprived of their father while sustained by his wages, the Comodas children spent their early lives studying Emmet's example. Now they have copied it. All five of them, including Rowena, grew up to become overseas workers. Four are still working abroad. And the middle child, Rosalie -- a nurse in Abu Dhabi -- faces a parallel to her father's life that she finds all too exact. She has an 18-month-old back in the Philippines who views her as a stranger and resists her touch. What started as Emmet's act of desperation has become his children's way of life: leaving in order to live.</p>
        <p>About 200 million migrants from different countries are scattered across the globe, supporting a population back home that is as big if not bigger. Were these half-billion or so people to constitute a state -- migration nation -- it would rank as the world's third-largest. While some migrants go abroad with Ph.D.'s, most travel as Emmet did, with modest skills but fearsome motivation. The risks migrants face are widely known, including the risk of death, but the amounts they secure for their families have just recently come into view. Migrants worldwide sent home an estimated $300 billion last year -- nearly three times the world's foreign-aid budgets combined. These sums -- ''remittances'' -- bring Morocco more money than tourism does. They bring Sri Lanka more money than tea does.</p>
        <p>The numbers, which have doubled in the past five years, have riveted the attention of development experts who once paid them little mind. One study after another has examined how private money, in the form of remittances, might serve the public good. A growing number of economists see migrants, and the money they send home, as a part of the solution to global poverty.</p>
        <p>Yet competing with the literature of gain is a parallel literature of loss. About half the world's migrants are women, many of whom care for children abroad while leaving their own children home. ''Your loved ones across that ocean . . . ,'' Nadine Sarreal, a Filipina poet in Singapore, warns:</p>
        <p>Will sit at breakfast and try not to gaze</p>
        <p>Where you would sit at the table.</p>
        <p>Meals now divided by five</p>
        <p>Instead of six, don't feed an emptiness.</p>
        <p>Earlier waves of globalization, the movement of money and goods, were shaped by mediating institutions and protocols. The International Monetary Fund regulates finance. The World Trade Organization regularizes trade. The movement of people -- the most intimate form of globalization -- is the one with the fewest rules. There is no ''World Migration Organization'' to monitor the migrants' fate. A Kurd gaining asylum in Sweden can have his children taught school in their mother tongue, while a Filipino bringing a Bible into Riyadh risks being expelled.</p>
        <p>The growth in migration has roiled the West, but demographic logic suggests it will only continue. Aging industrial economies need workers. People in poor countries need jobs. Transportation and communication have made moving easier. And the potential economic gains are at record highs. A Central American laborer who moves to the United States can expect to multiply his earnings about six times after adjusting for the higher cost of living. That is a pay raise about twice as large as the one that propelled the last great wave of immigration a century ago.</p>
        <p>With about one Filipino worker in seven abroad at any given time, migration is to the Philippines what cars once were to Detroit: its civil religion. A million Overseas Filipino Workers -- O.F.W.'s -- left last year, enough to fill six 747s a day. Nearly half the country's 10-to-12-year-olds say they have thought about whether to go. Television novellas plumb the migrants' loneliness. Politicians court their votes. Real estate salesmen bury them in condominium brochures. Drive by the Central Bank during the holiday season, and you will find a high-rise graph of the year's remittances strung up in Christmas lights.</p>
        <p>Across the archipelago, stories of rags to riches compete with stories of rags to rags. New malls define the landscape; so do left-behind kids. Gain and loss are so thoroughly joined that the logo of the migrant welfare agency shows the sun doing battle with the rain. Local idiom stresses the uncertainty of the migrant's lot. An O.F.W. does not say he is off to make his fortune. He says, ''I am going to try my luck.''</p>
        <p>A kilometer of crimson stretched across the Manila airport, awaiting a planeload of returning workers and the president who would greet them. The V.I.P. lounge hummed with marketing schemes aimed at migrants and their families. Globe Telecom had got its name on the security guards' vests. A Microsoft rep had flown in from the States with a prototype of an Internet phone. An executive from Philam Insurance noted that overseas workers buy one of every five new policies. Sirens disrupted the finger food, and a motorcade delivered the diminutive head of state, President Gloria Macapagal-Arroyo, who once a year offers rice cakes and red carpet to those she calls ''modern heroes.''</p>
        <p>Bleary from the eight-hour flight, a few hundred workers from Abu Dhabi swapped puzzled looks for presidential handshakes on their way to baggage claim. Roderick de Guzman, a young car porter, took home the day's grand prize, a ''livelihood package'' that included a jeepney, life insurance, $1,000 and a karaoke machine. Too dazed to smile, he held an oversize sweepstakes check while the prize's sponsors and the president beamed at his side and a squad of news photographers fired away. When it comes to O.F.W.'s, politics and business speak with one voice. Message: We Care.</p>
        <p>On the way to the photo op, I squeezed into an elevator beside Arroyo. A president and daughter of a president, she is a seasoned pol who attended Georgetown University (Bill Clinton was a classmate) and has a Ph.D. in economics. I asked why she called migrant workers ''heroes'' and gathered from her impatient look that it was all she could do to keep from saying ''du-uh.''</p>
        <p>''They send home more than a billion dollars a month,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''O.F.W.'s get V.I.P. Treatment, Treats,'' reported the next day's Philippine Daily Inquirer, which runs nearly 600 O.F.W. articles a year. Half have the fevered tone of a gold-rush ad. Half sound like human rights complaints.</p>
        <p>''Deployment of O.F.W.'s Hits 1-M Mark.''</p>
        <p>''Remittances Seen to Set New Record.''</p>
        <p>''Happy Days Here Again for Real Estate Sector.''</p>
        <p>''5 Dead O.F.W.'s in Saudi.''</p>
        <p>''O.F.W. 18th Pinay Rape Victim in Kuwait.''</p>
        <p>''We Slept With Dog, Ate Leftovers for $200/month.''</p>
        <p>Nearly 10 percent of the country's 89 million people live abroad. About 3.6 million are O.F.W.'s -- contract workers. Another 3.2 million have migrated permanently, largely to the United States -- and 1.3 million more are thought to be overseas illegally. (American visas, which are probably the hardest to get, are also the most coveted, both for the prosperity they promise and because the Philippines, a former colony, retains an unrequited fascination with the U.S.) There are a million O.F.W.'s in Saudi Arabia alone, followed by Japan, Hong Kong, the United Arab Emirates and Taiwan. Yet with workers in at least 170 countries, the O.F.W.'s are literally everywhere, including the high seas. About a quarter of the world's seafarers come from the Philippines. The Greek word for maid is Filipineza. The ''modern heroes'' send home $15 billion a year, a seventh of the country's gross domestic product. Addressing a Manila audience, Rick Warren, the evangelist, called Filipino guest workers the Josephs of their day -- toiling in the homes of modern Pharaohs to liberate their people.</p>
        <p>For the sheer visuals of the O.F.W. boom, consider Pulong Anahao, a village two hours south of Manila that has been sending Filipinezas to Italy for 30 years. Cement block is the regional style, but these streets boast -- the only verb that will do -- faux Italianate villas. For the social complexity, turn on ''Dahil sa Iyong Paglisan'' (''Because You Left''), a Tagalog telenovela. Each show explores a familiar type. ''Dodgie,'' a driver in Dubai, is livid at his wife's profligacy. ''Dennis'' gets fleeced by crooked recruiters on his way to Singapore. ''Carlos,'' with a wife in Riyadh, is a hapless househusband; he cannot cook or wash, and his son is left out in the rain.</p>
        <p>Manila Hospital was aflutter one morning with the taping of the episode about ''Wally.'' A seafarer home from Greece, he demanded to know where his money had gone, only to discover that his pregnant wife had spent it on antiviral medication. His port-of-call promiscuity had given her H.I.V.</p>
        <p>''Qui-et!'' the director bellowed, with Wally about to learn of his own infection. It took the actor five takes to summon a sufficiently chilling mix of fear and remorse. A giggly nursing student, fresh from a cameo, paused to chat. She was getting a degree to -- what else? -- ''go abroad and try my luck.''</p>
        <p>While the Philippines has exported labor for at least 100 years, the modern system took shape three decades ago under Ferdinand Marcos. Clinging to power through martial law, he faced soaring unemployment, a Communist insurgency and growing urban unrest. Exporting idle Filipinos promised a safety valve and a source of foreign exchange. With a 1974 decree (''to facilitate and regulate the movement of workers in conformity with the national interest''), Marcos sent technocrats circling the globe in search of labor contracts. Annual deployments rose more than tenfold in a decade, to 360,000.</p>
        <p>The ''People Power'' revolution of 1986 replaced him with Corazon Aquino, who as the widow of his slain rival was a figure as un-Marcosian as they come. But the surge in labor migration continued. By the end of her six-year term, annual deployments had nearly doubled. There is no anti-migration camp in Filipino politics. The labor secretary, Arturo Brion, greeted me by saying that he, too, had been an O.F.W., having worked as a lawyer for seven years in Canada. When I asked how a nationalist candidate might fare with a vow to keep workers home, he looked confused. ''Nobody would vote for him,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The political issue is not migration but migrant safety. The formative moment in O.F.W. history, its Alamo, was the 1995 hanging of Flor Contemplacion, a Filipina maid in Singapore. Though she confessed to killing another Filipina maid and a Singaporean child, she did so in an uncertain mental state with weak legal representation; an 11th-hour witness fingered someone else. President Fidel Ramos's calls for mercy failed, and the martyred maid's coffin received a hero's welcome at home. Congressional elections followed, and the new Legislature passed what is variously called Republic Act 8042 and ''the migrant workers' Magna Carta.'' It pushed the government's responsibilities beyond migrant deployment to migrant protection.</p>
        <p>Woe now to the Filipino pol who appears not to have migrant welfare in mind. After a Filipino truck driver was kidnapped in Iraq in 2004, Arroyo not only banned all contract work there but also withdrew from the American-led military coalition. Even state visits have the tenor of bail runs. The president triumphed in Saudi Arabia last spring when King Adbullah freed more than 400 workers who had been jailed for petty crimes. But the war in Lebanon last summer threw the Arroyo government into a crisis by displacing thousands of Filipina maids. They returned home with harrowing tales of prewar abuse, including beatings and rape, endured in pursuit of salaries that averaged $200 a month. Embarrassed (and seemingly surprised), the government proposed a ''Supermaid'' program, a short-term training regimen that would lift the maids' skills and demand a doubling of their wage. Those not cringing at the name fretted that a pay raise would leave the maids displaced by Bangladeshis.</p>
        <p>While every country's migrants face risks, what makes the Philippines unique is a bureaucracy pledged to reduce them. There is no precise analog for the Overseas Workers Welfare Administration -- O.W.W.A. -- or its savvy director, Marianito Roque, who is one part international rescue worker and one part domestic fixer. A bureaucratic survivor who rose through the ranks, Roque understands the imperative of making the president look good. Christmas offered plenty of opportunity. With legions of workers coming home, Roque staged thank-you fiestas nationwide.</p>
        <p>I pictured them as sedate affairs until I arrived at a mall in Cebu City. Five thousand people pressed against police barricades, aiming cellphone cameras at a fluttering pop star who urged them to buy her music and clothes. O.W.W.A. has its own chorale, which offered the workers ''Lady Marmalade'' -- ''Voulez-vous coucher avec moi?'' -- an odd choice in a country saturated with fears of overseas adultery. Roque raffled off a mountain of rice cookers and electric fans, and the crowd responded with game-show shrieks. He caught an early-morning flight the next day and stormed through two more fiestas.</p>
        <p>When the last rice cooker had been claimed and the last voulez-vous belted out, I spotted a man grinning mischievously, as if he were in on his own private joke. An attractive woman hung on his arm with what I mistook as reunion bliss. The bliss, she happily explained, was in the pay. The man, Pepito Montero, boasted that he earned $8,000 a month on a Saudi oil rig, and a flicker of doubt must have crossed my face. His smile broadened at the chance to produce his retort -- a mass of $100 bills the size of a tennis ball.</p>
        <p>Emmet Comodas migrated to Manila before he migrated abroad. His parents, tenant farmers in the province of Leyte, died before he finished grade school, and he was handed off to an aunt in the capital, 600 miles away. She lived in a muddy squatters' camp called Leveriza. The alleys were ruled by drunks and gangs, but Emmet wore his geniality as a shield and was quick to make friends. Drawn to commerce more than to school, which he left at 16, Emmet spent much of his youth dodging traffic to sell newspapers and cigarettes. When he grew weary of his aunt's strictures, he slept on a city bridge.</p>
        <p>Among his favorite vending sites was a nearby stadium, Rizal Memorial, though without a sales license he had to sneak in early and hide before events. The canteen manager, admiring his pluck, hired him as a cook. With a bounce in his step from his first real job, Emmet was walking home to Leveriza one day when he spotted a woman, beautiful but frail, in an alley ironing clothes. He was afraid to say hello.</p>
        <p>Teresita Portagana came from a higher echelon of the Filipino poor. Her father was a farmhand in nearby Cavite province who managed to buy a few acres of coffee trees. Tita was raised on the farm, the oldest of 11 kids in a close-knit family who shared a single thatched hut. She left school after sixth grade to help her mother manage the growing clan, and when she turned 16 her father sent her to work in a Manila glove factory. She would live with an aunt and send home most of her pay.</p>
        <p>Her excitement at the prospect of city living vanished when she saw her aunt's neighborhood. Leveriza was not just crowded and dangerous; it stank. Stagnant estuaries, which doubled as sewage pits, were filled with discarded bundles of waste dubbed ''flying saucers.'' When her father learned that Tita was drawing looks from Leveriza boys, he hurried to Manila and moved her out. ''One relative in Leveriza is enough,'' he said. By then Emmet was pressing his case. Tita considered him plain-looking and ''poor as a rat,'' but his persistence carried the day. They married on the farm and moved back to Leveriza, where Emmet would be close to work. He was 23, and she had just turned 21.</p>
        <p>Similar slums were spreading across the developing world, greeting provincial migrants with welcome mats of squalor. How people survived, and at what cost, was a mystery and a concern. As Tita and Emmet were settling in, F. Landa Jocano, an anthropologist trained at the University of Chicago, moved nearby in search of answers, which eventually formed a noted book, ''Slum as a Way of Life.'' The setting of his Leveriza-like camp was predictably grim -- ''wet and muddy,'' with a ''nauseating smell'' and ''cardboard hovels'' holding six to nine people to the room. But what really stood out were the social conflicts. Despite the Filipinos' reputation for prizing social accord, husbands beat wives, gangs murdered gangs and tsismis -- gossip -- was a constant preoccupation. ''Envy, jealousy, hatred and other forms of ridicule'' coursed through the alleys, and it took a special deftness to thrive. Tita, lacking it, withdrew into herself. ''I was talkless,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Tita and Emmet had three children in four years, and two more later. Their second child. Rowena, was born seven weeks early with a heart defect that went undiagnosed for years. All they knew was that she was constantly sick. The family lived in rented shanties until Emmet won $90 on a horse race and bought a shanty of his own. It was so bug-infested that he burned the walls and rebuilt with secondhand wood. He moved to a pool-cleaning job at the stadium and sold cigarettes on the side.</p>
        <p>Still, the holes in the roof meant the children got wet on rainy nights. When she lacked money for vegetables or fish, Tita served the children rice, and when she lacked enough rice for three meals, she served two. A Sikh they called the ''boom-bay'' lent money at the standard interest rate, 20 percent per month. Emmet borrowed about $130 to open a tiny grocery store, which he planned to run as a sideline with Tita's help. The thief who robbed it during Holy Week seemed to know that they were busy with a marathon reading of the ''Pasyon,'' a 24-hour life of Christ. A few months later, Tita became pregnant with their fifth child.</p>
        <p>By then the Marcos labor decree was five years old, and the machinery was humming. Saudi Arabia was modernizing overnight. It needed roads, schools, apartments, hospitals and laborers to build them. Filipinos worked hard, spoke English and took orders. Tita and Emmet had seen the workers coming home with the Look -- leather jackets, Ray-Bans and enough gold around their necks to turn their skin yellow with a case of Saudi ''hepa.'' But most of the jobs were controlled by recruiting agencies, which charged placement fees of a month's salary or more. Only the privileged among the poor could leave.</p>
        <p>In the spring of 1980, Tita's brother Fortz took a loan from his father to try his luck in Riyadh. He had just landed when Emmet's boss asked if he wanted to do the same pool-cleaning work in Dhahran. ''Yes, yes, yes,'' Emmet said. The firm that managed the stadium had a contract there, so there were no recruiters' fees. Tita's brother Fering came the following year, and soon after, her brother Servando. Of the 11 siblings in her generation, nine either became overseas workers or married one.</p>
        <p>''First timers'' have it rough. Emmet shared a comfortable company apartment and a cook with three other Filipinos, but the loneliness was worse than anything he had known. Outside of work, there was nothing to do. Alcohol and churches were banned. Looking the wrong way at a Saudi woman was an invitation to arrest. (That is one theory behind the Ray-Bans.) Emmet paced Dhahran malls and stared at Dhahran skies, fantasizing that the planes overhead had come to take him home.</p>
        <p>Tita's loneliness was costly, too, but she had Emmet's earnings. With a monthly salary of $500, he made as much in two years in Dhahran as he did in two decades in Manila, and he sent two-thirds of it home. Tita bought better food, and she bought Rowena medicine. She bought each child a second school uniform, so she would not have to wash every night. She bought an electric fan and a television -- her habit of watching through a neighbor's window was a source of alleyway discord. Emmet, who talked to the family on cassette tapes, surprised Tita by sending one with a $100 bill inside.</p>
        <p>When Emmet got home in 1982, he gave himself a party, patched the walls and replaced the leaky roof. Then he signed another two-year contract. After his second tour, he replaced the wooden walls with cement block and added an upstairs. After his third contract, he paid the government $2,000 and got title to the land. Though neither Tita nor Emmet finished high school, all five children started college; four got degrees. Emmet, overseas paying the bills, missed every graduation. It takes a lot to move him to anger, but even now he gets furious when someone says that overseas workers leave their children to grow up without love. ''You cannot look at each other and say it's love if your stomach is empty,'' he said. ''I sacrificed!''</p>
        <p>I first met Tita and the kids in 1987, as Emmet was finishing his third contract. I had a fellowship from the Henry Luce Foundation to study urban poverty; a Leveriza nun, Sister Christine Tan, introduced us, and Tita agreed to let me move in. With Cory Aquino finishing her first year, the country was in transition, and Tita was, too. She was no longer quite so talkless. I awoke in the mornings to the blare of Tagalog news radio and once found her studying an English newspaper with a dual-language dictionary. ''What's imperialism?'' she asked. When Congress wanted a witness for a hearing on urban poverty, Sister Christine had Tita testify. Tita told me she had been asking God, ''Why are so many Filipinos poor?'' When I asked if God had answered, she laughed. ''Not yet,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Much of the credit belonged to Sister Christine, who had organized a network of prayer groups and cooperative stores and groomed Tita as a lieutenant. Tita bought and distributed 2,000 eggs a week for the group's co-op stores, placing them under a fluorescent light at night to keep the rats away. The unpaid work, undertaken in the spirit of community service, brought Tita new confidence. But so perhaps did the modest comforts made possible by Emmet's wages. By now she had a toilet.</p>
        <p>Her oldest two children spent less time mulling the meaning of life -- Rowena, still poised between sickness and health, was addicted to celebrity gossip -- and her two youngest were little boys. But Rosalie, the middle child, was on a quest. At 16, she was ambitious, sometimes brooding, beautiful and devout; while her sister squealed about movie stars, Rosalie wrote Tagalog plays about class conflict. One depicted Imelda Marcos conniving to raze Leveriza and put up a discothÃ  Jason DeParle, a senior writer for The Times, last wrote for the magazine about the aftermath of Hurricane Katrina.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jason DeParle, a senior writer for The Times, last wrote for the magazine about the aftermath of Hurricane Katrina.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
