<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Micro Comic</title>
    <meta content="Alford4.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/books/review/Alford4.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841906"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Ant Farm: And Other Desperate Situations (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E7D7123FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="697" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Micro Comic</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Micro Comic</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY ALFORD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANT FARM</p>
        <p>And Other Desperate Situations.</p>
        <p>By Simon Rich.</p>
        <p>139 pp. Random House. $12.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A collection of short-short essays on life’s little curiosities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANT FARM</p>
        <p>And Other Desperate Situations.</p>
        <p>By Simon Rich.</p>
        <p>139 pp. Random House. $12.95.</p>
        <p>In the epochal Monty Python sketch, Mrs. Premise and Mrs. Conclusion, two frowzy women at a Laundromat, are discussing that most human of all predicaments -- the fact that if you flush a parakeet down a toilet, you end up with a flock of soiled birds ''flying out of people's lavatories infringing their personal freedom.'' Mrs. Premise opines: ''It's a funny thing, freedom. I mean how can any of us be really free when we still have personal possessions.'' She then asserts that this argument is ''the whole crux of Jean-Paul Sartre's 'Roads to Freedom,' '' whereupon Mrs. Conclusion barks, ''No, it bloody isn't.'' As it turns out, Mrs. Premise recently met Sartre on holiday ''in Ibeezer'' -- Mr. S., she says, was ''a bit moody'' -- so Mrs. Conclusion suggests, ''Well, we'll give a tinkle then.'' The two women call him, and then trot off to Paris to settle their dispute.</p>
        <p>I thought of these ladies while reading Simon Rich's sweet humor collection, ''Ant Farm.'' Less because Rich's pieces tend to be written as pure dialogue and almost always spring from a ''what if?'' premise, and more because Rich, like Monty Python, favors premise over conclusion. Rich's essays tend to be very, very short -- about 200 words, a length at which many humorists are only beginning to get their conceit across. Rich cuts to the comedic chase by putting the premise in the headline. And so we find stories named ''I can only think of two scenarios where high school math would come in handy,'' ''If life were like hockey'' and ''How I imagine life in the U.S. Army (based on the commercials I've seen).'' Rich loves to end his stories on a momentous, withering realization or snippet of dialogue. An interior monologue called ''What goes through my mind when I'm home alone (from my mom's perspective)'' ends with the salvo ''I hope that when Mom comes home she asks me some very specific, humiliating questions about my changing body.'' In ''Rebellion'' -- a vignette made all the more interesting when you know that Rich is the son of the New York Times columnist and former theater critic Frank Rich -- Dad begs Simon to wear deodorant. Simon's adamant refusals (''Give the Man whatever he wants, right, Dad? ... I'm moving out! I'm going to live under the overpass!'') finally force Rich Sr. to bleat: ''Please put this on, son. You ... you carry my name.'' A torch is passed.</p>
        <p>The microscaled, high-concept humor piece seems to be in vogue with all the cool kids: see the recent book of lists from McSweeney's, ''Mountain Man Dance Moves,'' or ''The Areas of My Expertise,'' by John Hodgman. What's different about Rich is his tone and his references -- or rather, his lack thereof. You'd think that a current Harvard senior and former president of The Harvard Lampoon might serve up a hipper-than-thou shivaree of pop culture or highbrow allusions. But aside from the occasional nod to the Bible or a movie (the Bulgarian narrator of ''Pen Pal'' refers to the Disney hit ''Small Mermaid''), the stories tend toward the universal. Some of them could have been written 50 years ago.</p>
        <p>Take ''Invisible,'' for instance, in which the narrator chronicles the downside of existing in that state. He was laid off from his job as a tour guide because groups kept getting lost, and he's unappreciated as a lifeguard because his rescuees are always going on about '' 'angel this' and 'angel that.' '' (''Same thing when I was a male prostitute,'' he says.) As with some of the other stories, the fact that ''Invisible'' is only about 260 words long prevents the reader from carping about the somewhat abrupt ending. But at the same time, it would be intriguing to see what a mind supple enough to consider the unpleasantness of invisibility would come up with if it were encouraged to do so while building to a larger conclusion. Rich has got his Mrs. Premise asking some vital questions about parakeet-extinguishing and freedom. I'd love to see what would happen if he sent her to Paris.</p>
        <p>Henry Alford, a regular contributor to the Book Review, is the author of ''Municipal Bondage.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Henry Alford, a regular contributor to the Book Review, is the author of ''Municipal Bondage.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
