<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seeking Fans, Ballet Scrambles for a Killer App</title>
    <meta content="22laro" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/arts/dance/22laro.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841981"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">La Rocco, Claudia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York City Ballet</org>
        <org class="online_producer">American Ballet Theater</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E0DE1E3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1753" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seeking Fans, Ballet Scrambles for a Killer App</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Seeking Fans, Ballet Scrambles for a Killer App</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAUDIA LA ROCCO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">La Rocco, Claudia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on efforts by American ballet companies to attract younger audiences; efforts range from thematic programming to series such as Girls Night Out; various marketing efforts discussed; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE New York State Theater was positively surging at a matinee in February. Audience members played clapping games, thumping in their seats like jackhammers. Cheers and shushes erupted when the house lights dimmed. It was the New York City Ballet's annual winter performance for local students, and the energy was wildly different from that of many a sleepy matinee.</p>
        <p>Warren Betha, a student from Fort Lee High School in New Jersey who takes a variety of dance classes, said after the show that he could see connections between many techniques, but that in the end he preferred hip-hop because ''it's more alive.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Companies confront the challenge of becoming vital to a new generation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE New York State Theater was positively surging at a matinee in February. Audience members played clapping games, thumping in their seats like jackhammers. Cheers and shushes erupted when the house lights dimmed. It was the New York City Ballet's annual winter performance for local students, and the energy was wildly different from that of many a sleepy matinee.</p>
        <p>Warren Betha, a student from Fort Lee High School in New Jersey who takes a variety of dance classes, said after the show that he could see connections between many techniques, but that in the end he preferred hip-hop because ''it's more alive.''</p>
        <p>That is a verdict guaranteed to make fine arts marketing directors everywhere wince. Ballet, like opera and classical music, has a serious image problem in America, and companies are increasingly trying to combat it and attract new, younger viewers.</p>
        <p>This struggle has even reached the gates of the vaunted City Ballet. When the company opens its spring season on Tuesday, what happens onstage will be business as usual, but the packaging will be anything but, as City Ballet broadens the experiment with thematic programming that it began during the winter.</p>
        <p>Viewers may choose individual nights like ''International Balanchine'' or series like ''Girls' Night Out,'' which includes desserts and ''girl talk'' with ballerinas and has caused much eye-rolling among balletomanes.</p>
        <p>''The big concern that everyone has is that you also don't want to alienate your core audience, which has been coming for 40 years,'' said Peter Martins, the company's ballet master in chief. The jury is still out on the new system, he added, ''but not to do it, not to do anything, would be complacent.''</p>
        <p>City Ballet can ill afford complacency. The company reports that from 2001 to 2006 the percentage of seats sold by subscription dropped to 50 from 60, corresponding to a rise in single-ticket sales, to 50 percent from 40. It also reports that those who have been watching City Ballet for more than 20 years attend an average of 2.8 shows each season, but new audience members average only 1.6 performances. The core audience, which grew up during what Christopher Wheeldon, City Ballet's resident choreographer, describes as the golden years of the company and of George Balanchine's productivity, will not be the core for much longer.</p>
        <p>''We've been in rather safe territory for a while, where that slice of audience is still very supportive of the ballet,'' said Mr. Wheeldon, who concludes his residency next year. ''If you look at the number of older people at the ballet, it makes you realize that that sort of support system is perhaps going to start dwindling fairly soon.''</p>
        <p>As institutions like City Ballet tinker with existing models, Mr. Wheeldon and others envision more radical changes.</p>
        <p>Damian Woetzel, a principal dancer at City Ballet who is earning a master's degree in public administration at the John F. Kennedy School of Government at Harvard, foresees what he calls ''a day of reckoning coming very soon, when an entire generation will look at what we see as the culmination of culture and say, 'That doesn't work for us.' '' Finding what does work will take ''new generations to start influencing,'' he said, ''and to offend, in some cases.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wheeldon is perhaps ballet's biggest offender. At 33, he is the closest thing it has to Alex Rodriguez, the hyperscrutinized Yankee slugger held to the highest expectations. But A-Rod need power only one team to a ring. Mr. Wheeldon is heralded as an entire era's answer to Balanchine: a singular choreographic voice who will catapult ballet out of its creative doldrums, making it culturally vital for a new generation.</p>
        <p>Understandably leery of being crowned what he calls ''the balletic messiah,'' Mr. Wheeldon is still taking up the challenge. Morphoses/ The Wheeldon Company, which he founded in collaboration with the former City Ballet dancer Lourdes Lopez, will make its debut in August at the Vail International Dance Festival in Colorado, where Mr. Woetzel became artistic director last year. The mission of Morphoses, as stated on its Web site, morphoses.org, is to ''restore ballet as a force of innovation,'' and Mr. Wheeldon and Ms. Lopez have both expressed interest in drawing younger audiences, even at the risk of alienating longtime fans.</p>
        <p>''You want your audience to be as vibrant as the work that's being presented to them,'' Mr. Wheeldon said. ''They're a part of the experience.'' Mr. Wheeldon says he has tired of the traditional proscenium boundary between viewers and performers, which creates a feeling of ''them and us.'' Tellingly, Morphoses' first evening at Vail will feature a preview and a reception, not a premiere.</p>
        <p>Companies are increasingly playing with that boundary. The Sacramento Ballet has introduced ''Beer &amp; Ballet'' showings: for $25 viewers can sample works by resident dancers and receive a free beverage (beer, wine, soda or water). City Ballet's Web site tragiclovenyc.com -- dedicated to what is being billed as Mr. Martins's ''contemporary look'' at ''Romeo and Juliet'' -- features ''Behind the Curtain'' videos exploring the many elements that are going into the production. (In a first for City Ballet, the company is holding an open dress rehearsal of the ballet next Sunday night.) American Ballet Theater runs an ''18 to 29 Club,'' intended to bring in younger audiences and has begun a program with Payless Shoes to offer Ballet Theater shoes and accessories through the chain.</p>
        <p>Others see these efforts as mere window dressing, distractions from a deeper disconnect between ballet and American culture.</p>
        <p>''I've had a long interest in what it means to be a creative entity in an American democracy, especially when your historical vocabulary traditionally is from a European plutocracy or monarchy or however you want to say it,'' said Dorothy Gunther Pugh, the founder of Ballet Memphis. ''The whole rapid change of culture in America is going to leave these European art forms behind, and that's O.K., I guess. What we need to do is hear what the culture is saying and reflect what it is that we see, and not just what we learned inside a studio because someone told us it's very important we have straight knees and an arched foot.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Pugh's troupe, now 20 years old, looks to be thriving artistically, if its debut at the Joyce Theater this month was any indication. But regional companies face a daunting economic reality. In recent years several troupes in midsize cities have folded or cut back; Ballet Memphis has gone from 24 dancers to 14 in the last three years. This year Ms. Pugh received a $60,000 grant from the Mellon Foundation to explore the mounting operational challenges and the cultural standing of ballet companies in 21st-century America. She plans to use her findings to turn Ballet Memphis into a sort of pilot company.</p>
        <p>''It's not just about how do we market in this changing world,'' Ms. Pugh said. ''It's who are we going to be in this changing world?''</p>
        <p>Answers are urgently needed as box office and marketing pressures increasingly lead artistic directors to produce cheesy ''updates'' of classic story ballets, half-baked fusion attempts and awkward ad campaigns. Is ballet, in the rush to attract what Mr. Woetzel laughingly called ''this mythical young audience,'' compromising the very qualities that distinguish it?</p>
        <p>Regional companies are ''confronted with a system where they need to sell tickets,'' said Luca Veggetti, an Italian choreographer who often works in America. ''Otherwise they are gone.''</p>
        <p>''You have companies saying, 'We have to do Peter Pan and Dracula,' '' he added, laughing. ''What is the point? You're not like a TV program. You're supposed to raise the cultural level of your audience. I have a lot of discussions about this, especially with regional companies. They often say, 'Yes, we have to do this, even though we know it's terrible.' And I say, 'Why are you there, then?' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Veggetti acknowledged that he might be too idealistic. But a number of choreographers and dancers expressed similar views, stressing the need for more education -- for the public, certainly, but also in the ballet studio, where some feel there should be more history lessons along with the technique -- about the importance of ballet to the culture as the only meaningful way to revitalize it.</p>
        <p>This credibility gap contributes to suspicions about motivations, which often raise as many hackles as what is actually on stage.</p>
        <p>''First of all who are you attracting? The 57-year-old fathers of the girls who go to see 'The Nutcracker'?'' asked the choreographer Mark Morris, referring to American Ballet Theater's much-mocked 2002 ballet ''Within You Without You: A Tribute to George Harrison.'' ''What is this about? If it were done out of an appreciation for Mr. Harrison's music, that's one thing. But I don't think that it was.''</p>
        <p>Though Ballet Theater's artistic director Kevin McKenzie said creating something ''that resonates with people'' is never a bad thing, he dismissed the notion of pandering. ''It's always easy to criticize someone's motivations. I think it's more to the point to criticize the results.''</p>
        <p>Responding to criticism of enhanced series like ''Girls' Night Out,'' Mr. Martins said he didn't see anything wrong with a little enticement. His warning that an art form can become ''higher than thou'' and disaffect the public was echoed by several company members. ''Sometimes people take things a little too seriously,'' said Melissa Barak, a dancer and choreographer who just left City Ballet for the newly founded Los Angeles Ballet.</p>
        <p>For others, ballet is not taken seriously enough.</p>
        <p>''Ballet as a culture could use more self-reflection and really look at itself, critiquing these environments that surround the creation of these steps,'' said Emily Coates, a City Ballet alumna who is now the artistic director of the World Performance Project at Yale University, where she earned her bachelor's degree last year. ''I think that the environment itself tends to be out of step with the rest of the world in 2007.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, she added, ''dance and the performing arts need to be brought in as a crucial component of a well-rounded liberal education, and not as an entertaining reward to the 'hard stuff,' like calculus.''</p>
        <p>Audiences are not stupid, she said: ''I don't think that they need more packaging. I think that they need context.''</p>
        <p>Context is what City Ballet suggests its thematic programming offers, and that may be. But what caliber of context, and for whom? It's a question Mr. Martins and his peers will probably be wrestling with for some time to come.</p>
        <p>DANCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
