<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hyper-Articulate And Proud Of It</title>
    <meta content="22camh" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/movies/22camh.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841987"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Camhi, Leslie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bourdieu, Emmanuel</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Poison Friends (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Poison Friends (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00EFDE1E3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1080" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hyper-Articulate And Proud Of It</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hyper-Articulate and Proud of It</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE CAMHI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Camhi, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New film by French writer and director Emmanuel Bourdieu, Poison Friends, questions whether an excess of intelligence can cripple creativity; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CAN an excess of intelligence be a crippling force, creatively? That's one of the questions haunting ''Poison Friends,'' a French psychological thriller by the writer and director Emmanuel Bourdieu, opening Friday in New York. In the film, André (Thibault Vinçon), the brilliant ringleader of a band of Parisian graduate students, loves to quote a favorite dictum of the Viennese critic Karl Kraus, on why certain people write. ''Because they're too weak not to write,'' he says.</p>
        <p>Perhaps only in France could people's literary impulses appear so widespread and insistent that, according to André, they must be controlled, like a physical itch or a psychological compulsion. It's difficult to imagine a hero with a more negative view of artistic invention. But to Mr. Bourdieu, André's hypercritical approach is inspiring.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Can an excess of intelligence be a crippling force, creatively? That’s one of the questions haunting the French psychological thriller, “Poison Friends.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CAN an excess of intelligence be a crippling force, creatively? That's one of the questions haunting ''Poison Friends,'' a French psychological thriller by the writer and director Emmanuel Bourdieu, opening Friday in New York. In the film, André (Thibault Vinçon), the brilliant ringleader of a band of Parisian graduate students, loves to quote a favorite dictum of the Viennese critic Karl Kraus, on why certain people write. ''Because they're too weak not to write,'' he says.</p>
        <p>Perhaps only in France could people's literary impulses appear so widespread and insistent that, according to André, they must be controlled, like a physical itch or a psychological compulsion. It's difficult to imagine a hero with a more negative view of artistic invention. But to Mr. Bourdieu, André's hypercritical approach is inspiring.</p>
        <p>''I really like characters who are unproductive and even sometimes self-destructive, because they are so demanding of themselves and others,'' the director said. ''It's true that, literarily, André produces nothing. But he's constantly inventing dramas between his friends. So he is creative, as are many pathological liars; he turns ordinary life into theater, though there's something violent in the fact that he hasn't asked his actors for their permission.''</p>
        <p>A beguiling portrait of the vagaries of youthful camaraderie, the movie begins on the first day of classes at the Sorbonne, when Alexandre (Alexandre Steiger), a budding actor, and Eloi (Malik Zidi), the timid son of a famous writer, meet André in the lecture hall of a popular literature professor. They quickly submit to André's charisma, while he seizes on their admiration and instructs them in everything: the best way to drink coffee (with sugar), how Alexandre should get himself accepted to the Paris Conservatory (lie), which American author Eloi should study (James Ellroy) and which of their fellow students they should desire -- in particular, a fetching librarian played by Natacha Régnier. Gradually, his manipulations take a darker turn.</p>
        <p>Deferential and unassuming, Mr. Bourdieu, 42, maintains something of the air of a perpetual student. (Not many foreign directors, sitting down for an interview, will ask you to recommend an anthology of American film theory.) ''I've more than once been involved in that type of slightly dominating friendship,'' he recalled. ''I've been in Eloi's position, and I think in a way he's as much of a vampire as André. He appears to be the submissive one, but in fact he takes much more than he gives.''</p>
        <p>The character of Alexandre, he said, was modeled on a friend, the actor Denis Podalydès; they met while both were attending the elite École Normale Supérieure, cradle of Parisian intellectuals. (Mr. Bourdieu completed his graduate degree there, with a dual major in philosophy and linguistics.) Mr. Podalydès, in turn, introduced him to the French director Arnaud Desplechin, with whom he collaborated on the script for Mr. Desplechin's 1996 cult classic, ''My Sex Life  Or How I Got Into an Argument,'' another celebrated film set in the cinematically unpromising hothouse of academia.</p>
        <p>It's a world that Mr. Bourdieu has seen from the inside. As the son of Pierre Bourdieu, France's leading sociologist (known in his last years for his intense engagement with political causes), the younger Mr. Bourdieu had a front-row seat for the vivid drama of intellectual life in a country where prominent scholars maintain something of the allure of rock stars. It was while interviewing subjects for ''The Weight of the World,'' an oral history that his father compiled about the changing conditions of labor in an unfettered market, that he first realized it was possible, he says, ''to draw from the discourse of daily life something akin to literature.''</p>
        <p>Despite this background (or perhaps because of it), ''Emmanuel makes no distinction between high and popular culture,'' said Mr. Desplechin, who continues to seek the younger director's collaboration on scripts. ''He's capable of speaking equally seriously about Leibniz's philosophy and about Antonio Banderas's 'Legend of Zorro.' And that refusal to pass judgment is also in his films. Jean Renoir said that to write a screenplay you must understand that, on a certain level, everyone is right. Well, all of Emmanuel's characters have their reasons for acting as they do.''</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Bourdieu's films also explore the way a certain kind of formal intelligence can lose its footing in real life. ''Candidature'' (2001), his award-winning first film, followed the tragicomic travails of a graduate student (played by Mr. Podalydès) who applies for the job of assistant professor at a provincial university. In ''Vert Paradis'' (2003), a sociologist (Mr. Podalydès again) returns from Paris to his hometown to survey the problem of bachelorhood and becomes overly wrapped up in his research.</p>
        <p>''Emmanuel's characters always spend a great amount of intellectual and spiritual energy trying to compensate for some unnamed lack,'' Mr. Podalydès, who has also directed several of Mr. Bourdieu's plays , said by telephone from Paris. ''You'd think that would make for a very heavy psychological drama, but in Emmanuel's hands it becomes something quite droll, light and delicate.''</p>
        <p>The result is a moral tale in the tradition of Eric Rohmer, the filmmaker with whom Mr. Bourdieu says he feels the greatest affinity: hyper-articulate characters negotiating the dark undercurrents of life with a rueful, bittersweet humor.</p>
        <p>But in a France turned increasingly toward American film culture, Mr. Bourdieu's adoption of this very French form and his focus on the rarefied precincts of literary and academic life have put him on the defensive.</p>
        <p>''There's a moment in Nanni Moretti's film 'Sweet Dreams,' '' he recalled, ''when he's in a cafe and two people, one politically to the right and the other to the left, stop by one after the other and ask him if he's seen the latest movie by Don Siegel. And at a certain point he just says, 'Basta! I'm an intellectual.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bourdieu elaborated. ''People ask me, why do you always talk about this little milieu that few people know and that no one cares about?'' he said. ''Well in fact I realized that you have to play off the specificity of a locale in order to arrive at something universal. Sidney Lumet says something like that in his book 'Making Movies.' In France today, many producers, in the false hope of making money, are imitating the American model. I have the greatest respect for American film culture, but I think that's a mistake. You have to cultivate what you have that is singular, to find a common bond between people.''</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
