<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nonfiction Chronicle</title>
    <meta content="Sussman.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/books/review/Sussman.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841929"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Alpert, Stanley N</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE5D7123FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1274" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nonfiction Chronicle</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nonfiction Chronicle</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mick Sussman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sussman, Mick</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BURIED IN THE BITTER WATERS: The Hidden History of Racial Cleansing in America. By Elliot Jaspin. (Basic Books, $26.95.) Using the tools of his trade, computer-assisted reporting, Jaspin discovered a troubling demographic pattern: between 1890 and 1930, United States census data showed 260 suspect counties in which the black population appeared to fall suddenly by more than 50 percent. Jaspin ingeniously investigated the historical background of those statistical anomalies in 12 counties and found unequivocal evidence of mass racial expulsions. These incidents often began when the more familiar form of Jim Crow vigilantism, lynching, failed to satiate the mob's fury. The underlying motivation was usually economic competition. Two waves of intimidation in 1905 and 1909 that drove blacks out of Boone County, Ark., were typical. Ostensibly precipitated by crimes attributed to African-Americans, the expulsions followed closely on the arrival of an influx of unemployed black laborers. Why was this history ''hidden''? Jaspin points out that the concept of ''racial cleansing'' is of recent vintage, and wasn't understood by contemporaries, including the N.A.A.C.P., as a distinct category of persecution. His implied analogy to the Balkan ethnic cleansing campaigns of the 1990s is imprecise, since these American atrocities seem to have been more spontaneous and isolated. But Jaspin passionately defends his use of the term, and he recounts a rancorous struggle with his employers at Cox Newspapers, who eventually published only expurgated versions of the articles that are the basis of this book. For Jaspin, who was later demoted from editor to reporter, this was ''a demonstration of exactly how racial cleansings had come to be concealed in a thicket of lies, half-truths and euphemisms.''</p>
        <p>THE BIRTHDAY PARTY: A Memoir of Survival. By Stanley N. Alpert. (Putnam, $24.95.) In the 1970s, muggings in the Brooklyn neighborhood where Alpert, a federal prosecutor, grew up were so frequent that they followed a shorthand script (''Yo, lend me a dime''). The racial tensions of that era form the backdrop for Alpert's account of his ordeal as the victim of a kidnapping that took place in 1998, on the night before his 38th birthday. Grabbed at gunpoint in Greenwich Village by three toughs who demanded his A.T.M. password and took $800 from his account, Alpert was then held overnight at the apartment of an associate of the kidnappers in preparation for a half-baked scheme to compel him to withdraw $50,000 from his bank the next day. The night was by turns harrowing and farcical; his captors' friends came by to eat McDonald's takeout, smoke pot and have sex in the presence of the blindfolded, terror-stricken prisoner. Alpert remained acutely alert during his captivity, psychologically manipulating his kidnappers and noting every feature of his surroundings to help investigators should he survive. The rest of his tale, a more conventional police procedural, is something of an anticlimax, though well served by his litigator's sense for dramatic pacing and the telling detail. And throughout, Alpert wins over the reader the same way he did the kidnappers, with the force of his canny, self-assured, bighearted personality.</p>
        <p>THE END OF ALLIANCES. By Rajan Menon. (Oxford, $25.) In the early years of the cold war, the United States abandoned its traditional antipathy to formal military alliances and committed itself to defend Western Europe, Japan and South Korea. This policy was an unqualified success, but now, says Menon, a professor at Lehigh University, circumstances have changed. In the future, he predicts, the United States will probably reject strict alliances in favor of looser coalitions. Even as the Pentagon resorts to stopgap measures to maintain force levels in Iraq and Afghanistan, more than 150,000 American troops are stationed in Europe, Japan and South Korea. Some American commentators have begun to question the wisdom of providing subsidized security to some of the world's richest nations, while many people in those countries are bridling at their dependence on a military protector whose motives they increasingly distrust. Efforts to reconfigure a cold war institution like NATO for different missions, like humanitarian intervention or fighting terrorism, are misguided, Menon says; better to devise new arrangements. The alliance system is guarded by formidable bureaucracies and other vested interests, which argue that the costs are a small price to pay to avoid the uncertainties of a rupture. But Menon is a level-headed analyst, and though his prescription for an updated grand strategy is tentative, his diagnosis of the ills besetting the current one is persuasive.</p>
        <p>ONE OF THE GUYS: Women as Aggressors and Torturers. Edited by Tara McKelvey. Foreword by Barbara Ehrenreich. (Seal Press, paper, $15.95.) The photographs of Lynndie England's exploits in Abu Ghraib prison were not the first evidence of women's capacity for brutality, and sexual coercion has long been a tool of war. But the use of female soldiers to humiliate detainees sexually was a disturbing new development, provoking conflicting and sometimes disoriented reactions in the contributors to this anthology. Some of these essays, chosen by McKelvey, a senior editor at The American Prospect, suggest that superior officers' ordering enlisted women to employ these techniques could constitute a form of harassment; the women, says Aziz Huq, a human rights lawyer, are put in ''morally clouded roles, as both perpetrator and victim.'' Other writers in this volume insist the women -- ''willing and enthusiastic participants,'' according to the journalist Lila Rajiva -- were fully culpable. These issues are often obscured here by the opaque jargon of academic feminism (''vectors of patriarchal norms,'' ''racially gendered theater of subordination''); the clarity of the pieces by journalists and political activists comes as a relief. The standout essay is by Ada Calhoun, the editor in chief at Babble.com. It's about distinguishing good from bad kinds of empowerment. Calhoun reflects on a photograph of Jennifer Scala, an Abu Ghraib guard, shown carrying an obscenely titled book by Inga Muscio into a courtroom. The book, Calhoun says, incorporates ideas, in grossly degraded form, from a feminist ''zinefest'' subculture that had inspired her in her youth. Muscio is a ''fanatic,'' Calhoun writes, because she places ''political ends'' over what should be feminism's ethical touchstone, ''human decency.''</p>
        <p>PERFECT FROM NOW ON: How Indie Rock Saved My Life. By John Sellers. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $23.) Musical preferences were closely associated with status and clique among Sellers's '80s generation. So to readers of a certain age, the trajectory of his memoir could be summed up by the sequence of his (decreasingly mainstream) favorite bands, from Journey to Duran Duran to New Order to the Pixies to Pavement. The subtitle, ''How Indie Rock Saved My Life,'' is only a slight exaggeration: Sellers suggests that if he hadn't progressed beyond Journey, he might have wound up just another suburban ''meathead.'' Sellers works in the approved style of post-gonzo rock journalism, with an arch, self-deprecating, emphatic tone, digressive footnotes and ''10 best'' lists. His clowning about cheesy 1980s culture is only intermittently amusing, but whenever he immerses himself in the esoterica of alternative music the book improves. His knowledge of the subject is impressively obsessive. The central object of Sellers's very substantial enthusiasm is Guided by Voices, low-fi alt-rock purists; the climax of the book describes a night of ''giddy'' hero worship and blissful alcoholic excess spent in the company of the band's leader, Bob Pollard. A cynic might say that indie music failed to subvert the consumerism of the 1980s. After all, Sellers never really stopped identifying himself with musical brand names; he just developed gourmet taste. But those indie bands that found the sweet spot between being co-opted and being ignored served as examples of integrity and passion, helping MTV-era ironists like Sellers to grow up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New books by Elliot Jaspin, Stanley N. Alpert, Rajan Menon and John Sellers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BURIED IN THE BITTER WATERS: The Hidden History of Racial Cleansing in America. By Elliot Jaspin. (Basic Books, $26.95.) Using the tools of his trade, computer-assisted reporting, Jaspin discovered a troubling demographic pattern: between 1890 and 1930, United States census data showed 260 suspect counties in which the black population appeared to fall suddenly by more than 50 percent. Jaspin ingeniously investigated the historical background of those statistical anomalies in 12 counties and found unequivocal evidence of mass racial expulsions. These incidents often began when the more familiar form of Jim Crow vigilantism, lynching, failed to satiate the mob's fury. The underlying motivation was usually economic competition. Two waves of intimidation in 1905 and 1909 that drove blacks out of Boone County, Ark., were typical. Ostensibly precipitated by crimes attributed to African-Americans, the expulsions followed closely on the arrival of an influx of unemployed black laborers. Why was this history ''hidden''? Jaspin points out that the concept of ''racial cleansing'' is of recent vintage, and wasn't understood by contemporaries, including the N.A.A.C.P., as a distinct category of persecution. His implied analogy to the Balkan ethnic cleansing campaigns of the 1990s is imprecise, since these American atrocities seem to have been more spontaneous and isolated. But Jaspin passionately defends his use of the term, and he recounts a rancorous struggle with his employers at Cox Newspapers, who eventually published only expurgated versions of the articles that are the basis of this book. For Jaspin, who was later demoted from editor to reporter, this was ''a demonstration of exactly how racial cleansings had come to be concealed in a thicket of lies, half-truths and euphemisms.''</p>
        <p>THE BIRTHDAY PARTY: A Memoir of Survival. By Stanley N. Alpert. (Putnam, $24.95.) In the 1970s, muggings in the Brooklyn neighborhood where Alpert, a federal prosecutor, grew up were so frequent that they followed a shorthand script (''Yo, lend me a dime''). The racial tensions of that era form the backdrop for Alpert's account of his ordeal as the victim of a kidnapping that took place in 1998, on the night before his 38th birthday. Grabbed at gunpoint in Greenwich Village by three toughs who demanded his A.T.M. password and took $800 from his account, Alpert was then held overnight at the apartment of an associate of the kidnappers in preparation for a half-baked scheme to compel him to withdraw $50,000 from his bank the next day. The night was by turns harrowing and farcical; his captors' friends came by to eat McDonald's takeout, smoke pot and have sex in the presence of the blindfolded, terror-stricken prisoner. Alpert remained acutely alert during his captivity, psychologically manipulating his kidnappers and noting every feature of his surroundings to help investigators should he survive. The rest of his tale, a more conventional police procedural, is something of an anticlimax, though well served by his litigator's sense for dramatic pacing and the telling detail. And throughout, Alpert wins over the reader the same way he did the kidnappers, with the force of his canny, self-assured, bighearted personality.</p>
        <p>THE END OF ALLIANCES. By Rajan Menon. (Oxford, $25.) In the early years of the cold war, the United States abandoned its traditional antipathy to formal military alliances and committed itself to defend Western Europe, Japan and South Korea. This policy was an unqualified success, but now, says Menon, a professor at Lehigh University, circumstances have changed. In the future, he predicts, the United States will probably reject strict alliances in favor of looser coalitions. Even as the Pentagon resorts to stopgap measures to maintain force levels in Iraq and Afghanistan, more than 150,000 American troops are stationed in Europe, Japan and South Korea. Some American commentators have begun to question the wisdom of providing subsidized security to some of the world's richest nations, while many people in those countries are bridling at their dependence on a military protector whose motives they increasingly distrust. Efforts to reconfigure a cold war institution like NATO for different missions, like humanitarian intervention or fighting terrorism, are misguided, Menon says; better to devise new arrangements. The alliance system is guarded by formidable bureaucracies and other vested interests, which argue that the costs are a small price to pay to avoid the uncertainties of a rupture. But Menon is a level-headed analyst, and though his prescription for an updated grand strategy is tentative, his diagnosis of the ills besetting the current one is persuasive.</p>
        <p>ONE OF THE GUYS: Women as Aggressors and Torturers. Edited by Tara McKelvey. Foreword by Barbara Ehrenreich. (Seal Press, paper, $15.95.) The photographs of Lynndie England's exploits in Abu Ghraib prison were not the first evidence of women's capacity for brutality, and sexual coercion has long been a tool of war. But the use of female soldiers to humiliate detainees sexually was a disturbing new development, provoking conflicting and sometimes disoriented reactions in the contributors to this anthology. Some of these essays, chosen by McKelvey, a senior editor at The American Prospect, suggest that superior officers' ordering enlisted women to employ these techniques could constitute a form of harassment; the women, says Aziz Huq, a human rights lawyer, are put in ''morally clouded roles, as both perpetrator and victim.'' Other writers in this volume insist the women -- ''willing and enthusiastic participants,'' according to the journalist Lila Rajiva -- were fully culpable. These issues are often obscured here by the opaque jargon of academic feminism (''vectors of patriarchal norms,'' ''racially gendered theater of subordination''); the clarity of the pieces by journalists and political activists comes as a relief. The standout essay is by Ada Calhoun, the editor in chief at Babble.com. It's about distinguishing good from bad kinds of empowerment. Calhoun reflects on a photograph of Jennifer Scala, an Abu Ghraib guard, shown carrying an obscenely titled book by Inga Muscio into a courtroom. The book, Calhoun says, incorporates ideas, in grossly degraded form, from a feminist ''zinefest'' subculture that had inspired her in her youth. Muscio is a ''fanatic,'' Calhoun writes, because she places ''political ends'' over what should be feminism's ethical touchstone, ''human decency.''</p>
        <p>PERFECT FROM NOW ON: How Indie Rock Saved My Life. By John Sellers. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $23.) Musical preferences were closely associated with status and clique among Sellers's '80s generation. So to readers of a certain age, the trajectory of his memoir could be summed up by the sequence of his (decreasingly mainstream) favorite bands, from Journey to Duran Duran to New Order to the Pixies to Pavement. The subtitle, ''How Indie Rock Saved My Life,'' is only a slight exaggeration: Sellers suggests that if he hadn't progressed beyond Journey, he might have wound up just another suburban ''meathead.'' Sellers works in the approved style of post-gonzo rock journalism, with an arch, self-deprecating, emphatic tone, digressive footnotes and ''10 best'' lists. His clowning about cheesy 1980s culture is only intermittently amusing, but whenever he immerses himself in the esoterica of alternative music the book improves. His knowledge of the subject is impressively obsessive. The central object of Sellers's very substantial enthusiasm is Guided by Voices, low-fi alt-rock purists; the climax of the book describes a night of ''giddy'' hero worship and blissful alcoholic excess spent in the company of the band's leader, Bob Pollard. A cynic might say that indie music failed to subvert the consumerism of the 1980s. After all, Sellers never really stopped identifying himself with musical brand names; he just developed gourmet taste. But those indie bands that found the sweet spot between being co-opted and being ignored served as examples of integrity and passion, helping MTV-era ironists like Sellers to grow up.</p>
        <p>Mick Sussman produces the Books section for The New York Times on the Web.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Mick Sussman produces the Books section for The New York Times on the Web.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
