<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Comedians Lair</title>
    <meta content="22wwln--domains.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/magazine/22wwlndomains.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841964"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 04-22-07: DOMAINS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewine, Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corddry, Rob</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Winner, the (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Daily Show, the (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Stewart, Jon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E7D6113FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1036" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Comedians Lair</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Comedians Lair</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Edward Lewine</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewine, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Rob Corddry, former Daily Show fake-news correspondent who is now starring the Fox sitcom The Winner, at his rented two-bedroom bungalow in Los Angeles; he comments on such things as his morning routine, hobbies and prized possessions; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Morning routine: The day starts a little after 6:30 a.m., because after laborious effort we've gotten our baby daughter, Sloane, to wake up three minutes later than she used to. I take Sloane, and we say good morning to different things in the house. My wife, Sandra, makes the baby's breakfast, and I go to work. Also, coffee happens.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rob Corddry, former “Daily Show” fake-news correspondent and current star of the Fox sitcom “The Winner,” lives in a rented, two-bedroom bungalow in Los Angeles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Morning routine: The day starts a little after 6:30 a.m., because after laborious effort we've gotten our baby daughter, Sloane, to wake up three minutes later than she used to. I take Sloane, and we say good morning to different things in the house. My wife, Sandra, makes the baby's breakfast, and I go to work. Also, coffee happens.</p>
        <p>His hangout: In front of my computer. I write, fool around and listen to music. I don't like using the phone, so the computer is kind of my connection to my friends.</p>
        <p>How he resembles his sitcom character: The guy I play on ''The Winner,'' Glen Abbott, has double consonants in his last name like I do -- that and my hairline.</p>
        <p>His double consonants: My great-grandfather changed the name from Cordery to Corddry around the turn of the last century because his wife said it looked better on his lumber company's sign. I do think it's symmetrical with the looping ''C'' and ''y'' at the end. Very elegant.</p>
        <p>Favorite old sitcom role: Al Bundy, the dad from ''Married . . . With Children,'' because the actor who played that role, Ed O'Neill, grounded what could have been a cartoonish character in reality.</p>
        <p>Prized possession: A framed New York subway map circa 1972. It hangs in the kitchen. It was the most unsuccessful map in New York history. It isn't to scale. It is impossible to read. I love the 1970s in New York; it fascinates and terrifies me, especially 1977.</p>
        <p>What he drives: A sensible, entry-level luxury sedan, an Acura TL, because CNET and Consumer Reports told me to. I am kind of obsessed with cross-referencing.</p>
        <p>Best useless object: I have these Lonely Planet travel books. Half these places I haven't been to, but I got romantic about them at one time and bought the book. Like Shanghai. I don't remember why I thought I was going there.</p>
        <p>Favorite ''Daily Show'' memento: My ''Comm-Emmy.'' No matter how many Emmys we won, the correspondents never got a thing. So Jon Stewart and the producers were nice enough to give us statues in 2004. Technically, they aren't real. On the back it says ''commemorative.'' My fellow correspondent Samantha Bee coined the name.</p>
        <p>Favorite real-news reporter: Dan Rather, because you don't realize how much you love someone until they're gone.</p>
        <p>Possession that reminds him of himself: I got this ''Simpsons'' animation cel that mimics the Beatles Red and Blue albums. The Simpsons are looking down the stairwell, like the Beatles did, and the artist even matched the way each of the two Beatles photos was taken from a slightly different angle. That appeals to my obsessive-compulsive disorder.</p>
        <p>His other job: I write a weekly column for a Web site named SuicideGirls-.com. They fancy themselves an Internet community like MySpace, but really it's an alt-porn site with some culture thrown in. The column gives me massive, massive street cred.</p>
        <p>Always with him: ChapStick. It's in my pocket right now. There's one in my desk drawer, one in my bag, one in my car and a few in the dresser. Probably 15 have fallen behind my bed. It's become emotional for me. I just need it.</p>
        <p>Best recent gift: My wife gave me an Art Deco rocket-ship lighter. I'd seen it in an antique store and almost bought it. But when I went back the next day, it was gone. I spent the next two months pining for it, only to discover that my wife had bought it for me as a Christmas gift.</p>
        <p>Best family memento: I have this picture my dad drew. It's kind of an awkward still life of a box of fruit on really yellowed paper. He was younger than 10 when he did it, and Steve, his name, is written in block letters.</p>
        <p>Evening routine: The family eats dinner. Then my wife and I either catch up on TiVo or we perform the ancient dance of love.</p>
        <p>Hobby: Music. Just listening to it, collecting it and cross-referencing it. I love family trees, like which person was in which band. I have probably 1,000 albums.</p>
        <p>His desert-island discs: ''Abbey Road'' (the Beatles); ''Alien Lanes'' (Guided by Voices); ''Boys and Girls in America'' (the Hold Steady); any collection of Christmas music by Bing Crosby; and a Monty Python album, 'cause you need a laugh.</p>
        <p>Obsolete item he can't part with: My Hi8 video camera. I bought it when I was flat broke and barely ever used it. It's one of the first overly expensive things I ever bought and never used. Maybe I just feel guilty about having done that.</p>
        <p>Workout routine: Jumping on the treadmill for 30 to 40 minutes, two or three days in a row, and then promising I'll pick it back up, which usually takes me a month.</p>
        <p>Always in fridge: My wife always, always has a salad spinner half full of delicious salad. She spins a pretty good salad, that woman. And she grows all her ingredients in the backyard. O.K., we buy some leaves now and then.</p>
        <p>Favorite clothing item: My wife would say it's the T-shirt I go to bed in. She wants to destroy it. It has a huge hole right at chest level, in the middle of the shirt. It's falling apart, but it's the most comfortable thing I own.</p>
        <p>Household chore he's fastidious about: It is very important to have a clean coffee machine.</p>
        <p>Household chore he doesn't care about: Unballing my wet socks when I take them out of the washing machine so they dry better. But I nailed the replacing-the-toilet-paper thing, with the end of the roll on the outside like at a hotel. I nailed that.</p>
        <p>Favorite award: I won a Grammy for being a writer and performer on the audiobook of ''America.'' I did about 15 minutes of work on it. I've always said it was easy to win a Grammy, and I proved it.</p>
        <p>Next gadget: I can't wait for the iPhone to come out from Apple.</p>
        <p>Next big purchase: We're going to buy a house. The issue is whether or not my show gets picked up for another season. That will definitely affect the square footage and the bathroom-to-bedroom ratio.</p>
        <p>THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 04-22-07: DOMAINS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
