<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Money Talks</title>
    <meta content="Max.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/books/review/Max.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841918"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Mergers &amp; Acquisitions (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE6D7123FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1231" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Money Talks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Money Talks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By D. T. MAX</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Max, D T</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MERGERS &amp; ACQUISITIONS</p>
        <p>By Dana Vachon.</p>
        <p>290 pp. Riverhead Books/Penguin Group.</p>
        <p>$23.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This satirical first novel offers an insider’s look at the world of Wall Street investment banks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MERGERS &amp; ACQUISITIONS</p>
        <p>By Dana Vachon.</p>
        <p>290 pp. Riverhead Books/Penguin Group.</p>
        <p>$23.95.</p>
        <p>Dana Vachon's first novel begins with Tommy Quinn scanning the crowd gathered for the engagement party of his friend Roger Thorne. The 24-year-old casts his eyes on the investment bankers, the skinny women and their Botoxed mothers, the New York elite gathered at the Racquet &amp; Tennis Club, a ''limestone manse sitting like a sphinx on Park Avenue.'' Quinn applauds himself for being on ''the most prosperous street in the most prosperous city in the most prosperous nation that ever lived.'' Standing on the club's terrace he feels he is ''flying.''</p>
        <p>The set-up is hoary -- wide-eyed outsider comes to the vast metropolis. From it the novelist can go in two directions: he can give his character a sentimental education in big city life or he can make the world he enters so ridiculous that we can dismiss it without having to go. He can choose to be Thomas Wolfe, or Tom.</p>
        <p>At the novel's beginning it appears Vachon, himself a former investment banker, is going to give us Thomas. Quinn is sensitive: he is thinking of becoming a doctor and helping the poor -- he would already have done so if his grades had gotten him into a better medical school. He had a brother who died young. His father has never recovered from not making partner at Cravath, Swaine &amp; Moore and has become a serial joiner -- a ''great sycophantic dynamo,'' who has just become a member of his eighth country club.</p>
        <p>There, at the Fourth of July cocktail party, young Quinn meets the alluring Frances Sloan. Frances uses phrases like ''beautifully brutal'' and says ''between cradle and grave, in the end, there was nothing'' (in French, no less). She is blond and depressed, and Quinn is hooked. The tree has met its ax, Scott his Zelda. They become a couple. As her mental problems become more serious, she begins to deliberately cut herself.</p>
        <p>Quinn has not bargained on being her full-time nurse. Part of a generation of ''desperate young materialists'' he is about to start work at J. S. Spenser, a prestigious investment bank. In the bank's training program, which he wittily describes as ''affirmative action for the already affirmed,'' he meets Thorne, who is mad for sex, drugs and money and determined to drain the '00s of every drop. Thorne, a descendant of the WASP establishment, guides Quinn through the labyrinth of Spenser divisions until they find the red hot center, the mergers and acquisitions department led by Terence Mathers. ''This guy is a rock star,'' Thorne realizes. ''Let's hook it up. We've gotta get into the M&amp;A group.'' Because Mathers used to ''dog'' Thorne's sister at Princeton, they do. In the division Thorne shines and Quinn stumbles: he botches an early deal in which the firm is trying to sell off some oil fields. Thorne next draws a bead on the Latin American mergers and acquisitions team led by Manuel Oliveira Rodrigo Orjuela de Navarro. ''I think we need to rock it with Miguel,'' Thorne tells Quinn. ''In fact, I think we need to rock it with Miguel big time!''</p>
        <p>Manuel succumbs to Thorne's charms, too -- they do shots at a trendy nightclub with some Fashion Week models -- and includes him and Quinn in a conference in Cabo, where the firm has rented a resort for ''just a bit under a million dollars'' to pursue Latin America's finanical elite. Thorne relieves Manuel of his beautiful girlfriend -- ''you're such a fine babe, babe,'' he tells her -- while Quinn, ''glaringly useless even by J. S. Spenser's standards,'' tries to hold Frances' scarred hand long-distance.</p>
        <p>One night a Latin plutocrat invites the Spenser bankers to a ''Pirates of the Caribbean'' party on his yacht, to celebrate his daughter's 16th birthday. Early in the party the D.J. plays a song of homage to commemorate Manuel's kidnapped cousin, a great dancer. Shortly after, Zapatistas, initially confused with costumed guests, attack the yacht and capture Manuel too. In the middle of extensive gunplay, Quinn saves Thorne's life by dropping a ''$20,000 bottle of Champagne'' on a Zapatista aiming an Uzi in his direction. ''The Cristal crashed down on him, leaving only a mangled corpse and bloody bubbles that surged across the deck in a red tide,'' Quinn notes. He and Thorne wind up overboard and are washed up on a remote beach, eventually making their way back to civilization. Quinn and Frances are reunited.</p>
        <p>What a strange scene. It doesn't fit the book Vachon seems to be writing. If it did, then Frédéric Moreau would have run a dragoon through with a bayonet in ''Sentimental Education'' and Nick Carraway would have taken George Wilson's revolver and shot him dead by the pool. There's no reason ''Mergers &amp; Acquisitions'' shouldn't choose Tom over Thomas as a model. The absurd world of Manhattan moneymaking is always a good subject. But the scene highlights the problem ''Mergers &amp; Acquisitions'' has from the beginning. Vachon's broad comic tendency keeps intruding on the novel of manners he seems to want to write. This tonal puzzlement defeats ''Mergers &amp; Acquisitions'' long before the events on the yacht jump the shark.</p>
        <p>Quinn is, for example, throughout the book saddened by the death of his promising older brother at prep school. That's an honorable if hackneyed plot device, undercut by the number of times Vachon mentions that what killed him was an egg roll fried in peanut oil. And is it funny to have Quinn and Frances at a dinner at Cipriani in which the main comedy comes from one of the guests' being a midget? And is it really appropriate for the initials of some Latin characters to form naughty anagrams (cast your eyes back to Manuel's full name)?</p>
        <p>New York relishes novelty, and novels that convey its flavor must capture this. Does this cultural observation by Quinn feel fresh to you?: ''You could produce 90 minutes of rhesus monkeys playing Nerf football, and as long as you got the damn thing screened at Cannes people would want to know you for having done it.'' Quinn and his father shop at Brooks Brothers and he and his friends eat at Smith &amp; Wollensky and Le Bilboquet. They do cocaine in bathrooms as if the world stopped in 1985. They talk on Motorola Razrs when the guys selling fake watches on Fifth have them. Socially the '00s may be the '80s all over again, but even so, no book purporting to bring us cultural news should be set in an M&amp;A division in 2007.</p>
        <p>If Vachon's signifiers seem drawn at leisure, his prose feels hurried. The night Quinn and Frances first try to make love, Quinn says: ''The louver doors breathed seawater and night as amid the dying flowers of summer we tried again and again to climb into one another.'' Frances' skin is ''like alabaster dipped in sun.'' When ''coils of honeysuckle platinum ... escaped'' her pulled-back hairdo, they ''hung down her temples like laurels.'' I think she would forgive him these clichés -- she's hardly an original creation herself -- but I think he should promise her one thing. After they finally do consummate, he fondles ''her firm B-cup breasts.'' If the space between birth and death is really as short as Frances says it is, he at least owes her another way to put that.</p>
        <p>D. T. Max is the author of ''The Family That Couldn't Sleep: A Medical Mystery.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">D. T. Max is the author of ''The Family That Couldn't Sleep: A Medical Mystery.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
