<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Children on Demand</title>
    <meta content="Morrice.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Arts; Health; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/books/review/Morrice.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841919"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Infertility</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Babies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Artificial Insemination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pregnancy and Obstetrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Adoptions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Infertility</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Babies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Adoptions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pregnancy and Obstetrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Everything Conceivable: How Assisted Reproduction Is Changing Men, Women, and the World (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6D7123FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1336" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Children on Demand</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Children on Demand</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By POLLY MORRICE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Morrice, Polly</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVERYTHING CONCEIVABLE</p>
        <p>How Assisted Reproduction Is Changing</p>
        <p>Men, Women, and the World.</p>
        <p>By Liza Mundy.</p>
        <p>406 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $26.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>How reproductive science has transformed the path to parenthood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVERYTHING CONCEIVABLE</p>
        <p>How Assisted Reproduction Is Changing</p>
        <p>Men, Women, and the World.</p>
        <p>By Liza Mundy.</p>
        <p>406 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $26.95.</p>
        <p>At the start of this lucid, mostly approving look at how humans are tinkering with the age-old project of reproducing ourselves, Liza Mundy meets one of the British scientists whose tenacity in perfecting in vitro fertilization made possible the birth, nearly 30 years ago, of the first test-tube baby. The embryologist Robert Edwards charms her, and not just with his enduring zest for the procedure he helped invent. ''Eye hoop they all have babies!'' he declares in what Mundy, a writer for The Washington Post Magazine, calls his ''wonderfully nonestablishment, workingman's burr.'' ''What coood be better than a baby?''</p>
        <p>That rhetorical question sums up an essential principle of Mundy's book: that ''having children and loving children is an unstoppable urge; that humans, or many humans, have an overpowering need to have -- to be -- a family.'' Yet while ''Everything Conceivable'' is based on the proposition that people crave babies, it has a larger thesis to prove: that the increasingly complicated ways people are going about making babies is transforming babies and the world. Mundy seeks to make sense of assisted reproduction, a sprawling topic that now includes lesbian and single mothers who use sperm (and sometimes egg) donors, gay men who enlist surrogates and couples who ''adopt'' one of the nearly half-million frozen human embryos stored in tanks of liquid nitrogen across the United States.</p>
        <p>Until the late 1970s, the term ''assisted reproduction'' referred to a short list of infertility treatments, among them artificial insemination, with donor sperm often supplied by an anonymous medical student, and drugs that induced ovulation.</p>
        <p>Then, Edwards and his partner, the surgeon Patrick Steptoe, pulled off the delicate task of fertilizing a human egg outside the body, coaxing it into a multicelled embryo and transferring it to a woman's womb, where it implanted. The resulting birth of Louise Brown in 1978 changed everything, at least for many whose path to parenthood had been blocked by infertility, age or sexual orientation.</p>
        <p>Within a decade, men with low sperm counts could father genetic offspring by means of ICSI (intracytoplasmic sperm injection), a type of in vitro fertilization in which a sharpened pipette launches sperm into egg. A woman with aging eggs might gestate an embryo produced by her husband's sperm and a young donor's oocyte, thereby bearing his child -- or children, since in vitro pregnancies often result in multiple births. Partly as a result of the increased use of this technology, the number of twins born in the United States from 1980 to 2003 rose 75 percent. Considering the vastly broadened scope of assisted reproduction, Mundy's belief in its transformative power is unsurprising. She argues that these reproductive miracles, medicine's response to cultural shifts like later childbearing and the tendency of some men to postpone ''commitment'' (women who wait for the ideal spouse are called ''independent''), have set off what one doctor described as ''a huge social experiment.''</p>
        <p>Maybe. Consider the case of Doug Okun and Eric Ethington, whose adored twin girls were conceived with the help of a Los Angeles agency that serves the growing ranks of ''would-be gay dads.'' Following the protocol of West Coast clinics, the couple chose a young egg donor from candidates screened for looks, family health history and SAT scores: ''What are you going to do,'' Ethington says, ''get someone with a 1550, or are you going to cheat your child and get them a mom with a 1210?'' Next they contracted with a surrogate -- a married mother of four (as well as a fifth child she bore for another gay couple), with whom they would develop a deep bond -- to carry their children. In all, building the Okun-Ethington family involved two in vitro cycles, at least $100,000 and a dangerous hemorrhage by their surrogate, whose ability to deliver twins safely after having undergone five previous Caesarean sections might have been inadequately vetted. Yet the men achieved their hearts' desire, coming as close as medically possible to having children together. Read: biological children. Just as they had hoped, one daughter turned out to be Doug's genetic offspring, the other Eric's.</p>
        <p>In short, the men took an arduous, costly route -- the only one open to them -- to gain the traditional satisfaction of seeing themselves in their children's faces. On the evidence of Mundy's book, the great gift of assisted reproduction isn't just that it creates longed-for babies, but that it lets all sorts of people achieve the same goal of having genetically connected offspring. Indeed, some of the case histories here, meant to illustrate Mundy's thesis that advances in reproductive technology have thrown the world into flux, seem more useful as backup for claims that biology remains destiny, that human nature hasn't budged since the Stone Age.</p>
        <p>In Berkeley, for instance, Mundy interviews a woman who elected to become a single mother while in her 20s. This mom holds the slightly off-center view that rearing ''little teeny babies'' is probably best done outside a relationship, yet in selecting a sperm donor she first cut those who ''wildly didn't look like my family.'' And she used her donor's gametes twice, to ensure that her two children would be full siblings. (''Biology won,'' Mundy observes.)</p>
        <p>Granted, many women Mundy interviews opted for unmarried motherhood because they couldn't find men who were ready to start a family. ''I don't know why women are not marching in the streets,'' one male fertility doctor says, lamenting perceived male dithering. For these S.M.C.'s (single mothers by choice), sperm banks offer a cheaper alternative to adoption; with no waiting lists or bias against single moms, they are also a surer thing. For the record, Mundy is careful to say that ''family has never been an exclusively genetic concept.'' But some advocates of adoption may still find the overall emphasis on biological ties unsettling. A father of children conceived through sperm donation declares, ''How can you not just love them?,'' and Mundy quotes him not once but twice, as if the ability to adore and shelter children not genetically one's own is new in history.</p>
        <p>This said, much of the information in ''Everything Conceivable'' is fascinating -- and scary. Who knew that the drop in teenage pregnancies may have less to do with effective sex education than with unexplained fertility declines in young men? And the book gains considerable depth from Mundy's reportorial urge to dig into all aspects of a story. In her discussion of multiple births -- nowadays, the arrival of twins, triplets or even quadruplets no longer startles, thanks in part to assisted reproduction -- she presents meticulous evidence that twins, produced in almost half of in vitro pregnancies in the United States, face significant health risks. Triplets have even higher rates of prematurity, enduring sometimes grim side effects. Yet many fertility patients hope for a double heartbeat on their sonograms, perhaps swayed not just by the desire to complete their families without going through more in vitro cycles, but also by what Mundy calls the subtle normalization of twins, a development she believes has obscured potential problems.</p>
        <p>In the end, Mundy divides the blame for the boom in multiples among clinics that try to boost their in vitro success rates by transferring more than the recommended one or two embryos into a waiting womb, susceptible parents who consent to the procedures and pro-life interests that block human embryo research. She suggests that the government should limit how many embryos can be transferred -- indeed, that it should finally start regulating the free-for-all fertility industry, which is now so unfettered that companies producing the sugar-and-protein soup that nurtures human embryos aren't required to divulge its ingredients. State oversight would also promote controlled studies of what reproductive science has wrought, perhaps resolving the question of whether in vitro babies are different in unwelcome ways from infants created naturally. Such issues certainly deserve our attention, whether or not they are really the results of a revolution.</p>
        <p>Polly Morrice is a frequent contributor to the Book Review.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Polly Morrice is a frequent contributor to the Book Review.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
