<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>School of Hard Knots</title>
    <meta content="22funny--humor.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/magazine/22funnyhumor.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841956"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE FUNNY PAGES: II: TRUE-LIFE STORIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Knots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ashley, Clifford W (1881-1947)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Guilfoile, Kevin</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Ashley Book of Knots, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Knots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Knots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00EED7113FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="871" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>School of Hard Knots</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">School of Hard Knots</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Kevin Guilfoile</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Guilfoile, Kevin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kevin Guilfoile article on learning how to tie knots from The Ashley Book of Knots by Clifford W Ashley; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I was 36 years old and a new father when I realized I knew how to tie only one knot: the one you tie your shoes with. I could tie two knots if you count the ''double knot,'' which most seasoned mariners don't.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The author learns that getting too tied to the idea of a person can lead to trouble.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I was 36 years old and a new father when I realized I knew how to tie only one knot: the one you tie your shoes with. I could tie two knots if you count the ''double knot,'' which most seasoned mariners don't.</p>
        <p>I was never in the Boy Scouts. Growing up in central New York, I didn't live anywhere near the ocean or, for that matter, near anything you could accurately call a town. My dad had been in the Navy, and he handled all my adolescent rope-tying needs. And with that realization, panic set in. One day my son is going to have two things he needs affixed to each other with a length of rope. What was I going to do? Use the shoe-tying knot? I didn't even know what that thing was called.</p>
        <p>A few minutes on the Internet turned up the definitive resource: ''The Ashley Book of Knots.'' I clicked, and a few mornings later the mail carrier delivered a large brown box. ''I ain't luggin' this thing around all day,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Indeed, ''The Ashley Book of Knots'' was a massive, 620-page hardcover, twice as heavy and nearly as tall as our 18-month-old son. It contained descriptions and step-by-step illustrations of something like 3,900 different knots, along with history, stories and knot-related folklore. When my wife came home, it sat on the dining room table like a giant rectangular centerpiece.</p>
        <p>''How much did that cost?'' she asked.</p>
        <p>''Less than my pride,'' I told her. And my ill-fated obsession with Clifford W. Ashley began.</p>
        <p>Ashley was a circus performer and sailor who finally compiled and illustrated his lifetime repertory of hitches and binds in the 1940s. In his jacket photo he looks like an actor who might have briefly played James Bond. Handsome. Dark-haired. Tuxedo-clad.</p>
        <p>My own knowledge had always been like a rice paddy -- acres wide and ankle-deep. In college I was an American studies major, qualified for little upon graduation but schadenfreude at the failures of ''Jeopardy!'' contestants. Ashley had a love for knots and dedicated his life to cataloging every single one of them. That was how a real man lived. That was commitment. I resolved to be his apprentice.</p>
        <p>I learned the Slippery Hitch and the Fisherman's Bend. I practiced the Stevedore and the Oysterman's Stopper. I studied the Double Bastard Weaver's Knot and the Chinese Frog, which is apparently a popular fixture on Asian pajamas. I memorized filthy-sounding sailor terms like Flemish Bend, Double French Shroud, Chest Becket, Frapping Turns and Bag Lanyard.</p>
        <p>As I went, I learned that Ashley was as much a philosopher as he was an educator. ''A knot is never 'nearly right,' '' he said. ''It is either exactly right or it is hopelessly wrong, one or the other; there is nothing in between.''</p>
        <p>I also discovered I knew one more knot than previously believed: the dapper knot you've seen at the top of my neckties since first communion, which is apparently called the Four-in-Hand.</p>
        <p>Retroactively, the Four-in-Hand brought my total number of knots to 10. Ashley was my hero. I proclaimed his many virtues to family and friends, and when they seemed bored (which is to say, instantly), I would proclaim his virtues more loudly. Sharing my mentor's contempt for the ''ordinary way of lacing a shoe'' I began tying my son's laces with a complicated Bowline Cringle. Ashley had become my life coach. My Oprah.</p>
        <p>Wanting to know more of this wise knot-tier and seizer of days, I went back to an early, autobiographical chapter and reread the section in which he lists his experiences and regrets: ''I hobnobbed with butchers and steeplejacks, cobblers and truck drivers, electric linesmen, Boy Scouts and with elderly ladies who knit. ... In Boston, I halted an operation to see how the surgeon made fast his stitches. I have watched oxen slung for the shoeing, I have helped throw pack-lashings, I have followed tree surgeons through their acrobatics and examined poachers' traps and snares. But I never saw Houdini, never was present at a successful lynching and never participated in a commercial second-story venture. ...''</p>
        <p>Um, what?</p>
        <p>I read that sentence again.</p>
        <p>''But I never saw Houdini, never was present at a successful lynching. ...''</p>
        <p>Oh, I thought. Oh, no.</p>
        <p>It crossed my mind that Ashley could be joking, but some jokes reveal so much about the teller they can't be taken back. Suppose you met Henry Kissinger at a party and you said, ''You secretly bombed Cambodia!'' and Kissinger replied, ''Vee ver only kiddink.'' This was a joke like bombing Cambodia. You can't really take it back.</p>
        <p>And like that, after 10 knots and one and a half rope tricks, I closed the book on Clifford Ashley. While the ''Book of Knots'' really is an excellent reference if you need to tie down an inflatable moonwalk for the neighbor kid's backyard birthday party, Ashley himself now seemed to me something of a Flemish-bending, double-weaving bastard who'll never be anyone's Oprah.</p>
        <p>Maybe Oprah should be my Oprah. One day perhaps she'll have me on her program and I'll show her audience my Three-Ply Manrope.</p>
        <p>I'm only kidding. I quit before I found out what that is.</p>
        <p>THE FUNNY PAGES: II: TRUE-LIFE STORIES Kevin Guilfoile is the author of ''Cast of Shadows,'' a novel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Kevin Guilfoile is the author of ''Cast of Shadows,'' a novel.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
