<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Hotel Prices Rise, a Villa May Be a Bargain</title>
    <meta content="22prac" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/travel/22prac.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841948"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AFFORDABLE EUROPE | PRACTICAL TRAVELER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Higgins, Michelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Practical Traveler</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Luxury and Vacations/Vacation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E0DA113FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1169" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Hotel Prices Rise, a Villa May Be a Bargain</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">As Hotel Prices Rise, a Villa May Be a Bargain</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHELLE HIGGINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Higgins, Michelle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michelle Higgins Practical Traveler column offers advice on renting vacation villas in Europe; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVER dream of vacationing in a European villa, set on a hillside vineyard in Tuscany or on a bluff, perhaps, overlooking the Mediterranean? This may be the year to book it.</p>
        <p>Tourists in most European cities are being charged more than $200 a night for basic hotel rooms, making much larger villas more appealing. Two-bedroom villas can be reserved for as little as $1,100 a week. If two couples share the villa, that translates to about $40 a person a night. Prices for villas rise when they include concierge services, private pools and other luxuries, but in many cases they are still cheaper than hotels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Selecting among the growing number of European villas can be more daunting than making hotel reservations. Some tips for navigating your way to the Tuscan sun, or close to it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVER dream of vacationing in a European villa, set on a hillside vineyard in Tuscany or on a bluff, perhaps, overlooking the Mediterranean? This may be the year to book it.</p>
        <p>Tourists in most European cities are being charged more than $200 a night for basic hotel rooms, making much larger villas more appealing. Two-bedroom villas can be reserved for as little as $1,100 a week. If two couples share the villa, that translates to about $40 a person a night. Prices for villas rise when they include concierge services, private pools and other luxuries, but in many cases they are still cheaper than hotels.</p>
        <p>The same rules of supply and demand that dictate hotel prices also apply to villas. Popular destinations like Provence or Tuscany tend to command the highest rates. And traveling in off-season months like April, May and September can yield the best deals.</p>
        <p>Yet selecting among the growing number of villas is more daunting than making hotel reservations. The Internet has made it possible for just about anyone with a spare room to post a listing. But many villa owners do not accept credit cards and require full payment to hold a reservation. And the sheer number of villas and apartments for rent has surged in places like Spain and Portugal, which have been undergoing substantial development in the last few years.</p>
        <p>To help you get a good deal on your villa vacation, here are some guidelines.</p>
        <p>BE YOUR OWN AGENT</p>
        <p>Travelers can save money by using Web sites that put them directly in touch with villa owners rather than a booking agent. HomeAway.com, which owns several vacation rental-by-owner Web sites, including Holiday-Rentals.co.uk in London and Abritel.fr in Marseille, has an easy-to-use search feature that lets travelers quickly filter down to properties that answer their preferences -- whether for a pet-friendly villa in Turkey or a house in Burgundy with Internet access. It also lists special deals and promotions from owners trying to fill slow weeks in summer or offering discounts to early bookers.</p>
        <p>Booking on your own, of course, entails some risk. While HomeAway monitors customer feedback on rentals and typically bans properties that receive three complaints, listings are essentially advertisements, written by owners.</p>
        <p>Villas from rental agencies can cost anywhere from 5 percent to 20 percent more than rentals by owner because most owners pass on the cost of agents' commissions. But for that premium, renters also generally get a bit more quality control. Interhome (www.interhome.us), one of the largest rental agencies in Europe, with nearly 20,000 properties in 19 countries, sends staff members to inspect the properties it lists. It also has more then 60 offices in Europe that can step in to help resolve problems or even locate a new rental if necessary.</p>
        <p>STAY OUT OF THE TUSCAN SUN</p>
        <p>While many Americans aspire to the archetypical villa vacation in Tuscany or the south of France, other regions can offer comparable cultural immersion at significant savings. ''Tuscany is on our lips,'' said Tim Roney, director of worldwide sales at LaCure Villas, which specializes in luxury rentals, but Umbria, from its cuisine to its rolling agricultural countryside and medieval stone villages, offers a very similar experience ''at rates 40 and 60 percent below Tuscany prices.''</p>
        <p>In France, he said, properties in inland Provence are generally less expensive than those on the Mediterranean coast. For example, Villa d'Antibes, a nine-bedroom luxury home with a heated swimming pool and views of the bay of Cap d'Antibes near Cannes, rents for 35,940 euros a week in July and August from LaCure, or about $48,900 at $1.36 to the euro. By contrast, L'Monastère, an 11th-century monastery building with nine bedrooms, a chapel, a swimming pool and a tennis court, near Aix-en-Provence, goes for 16,200 euros ($22,000) a week.</p>
        <p>The Dalmatian Coast in Croatia, marketed by some travel companies as a new Riviera, has a Mediterranean climate and miles of beaches. The average weekly price for a four-bedroom summer rental there is $2,660 at HomeAway.com, compared with similar rentals on the Italian Riviera at $5,650 on average. ''In addition to saving a few hundred dollars on their accommodation,'' said Courtney Wylie, brand manager at Holiday-Rentals.co.uk, ''they can also save money through a cheaper cost of living.''</p>
        <p>TRAVEL IN THE OFF-SEASON</p>
        <p>Off-season in Europe doesn't always mean avoiding June, July and August. During the winter, Chamonix, France, is a draw for skiers. In summer rates go down but some lifts keep running to transport hikers, bikers and rock climbers to high-altitude adventures. For example, Chalet Villa Miremont, a three-bedroom chalet near the village center, drops to £1,000, or $2,000 at $2 to the pound, at HomeAway.com, from 1,450 to 1,650 pounds during the winter season.</p>
        <p>Of course the best deals are in the spring and fall, when the crowds are gone for good. For just $850, Bob Grundstrom, a banker from Ventura, Calif., booked a three-bedroom Tuscan villa, including housekeeping services, from Rentvillas.com for a weeklong vacation with friends last October. Shared by the two couples, the cost was just $30 a day per person. By contrast, Mr. Grundstrom, who also traveled to Rome and London during his vacation, staying in hotels and bed-and-breakfasts, didn't find anything there for less than $200 a night.</p>
        <p>''My concern was the price was so good I was afraid we'd get this shack,'' he said of the Tuscan villa. ''But we were pleasantly surprised. The place was wonderful.'' On a farm surrounded by vineyards and olive groves in a hamlet of Chianti, the villa goes for about $1,200 a week, not including housekeeping, during peak summer months.</p>
        <p>STAY SOMEPLACE NEW</p>
        <p>Owners putting property up for rent for the first time or in a new market tend to offer lower prices, said Kevin Pidduck, chief executive of Rentvillas.com, whose listings include villas in Greece and Turkey. Finding such deals ''does take a little work,'' he said. ''You either need to speak with someone or very carefully look through the inventory.'' For a list of new properties from Rentvillas.com, click on Our Featured Properties, and then Recent Additions. One recent addition, Villa Sella, a three-bedroom house with a private swimming pool in Chianti, was listed at $2,761 a week in July and August to attract clients -- about $300 less than Villa Certaldo, a comparable three-bedroom with a pool in the region. Another, Villa Amadora on Lake Maggiore, is priced at about $1,600 less than similar lake-view accommodations.</p>
        <p>Thanks to a development boom in Spain and Portugal, HomeAway.com listings by owners there have surged. Villa and apartment listings for Spain have nearly doubled, to 5,861 in January compared with those in the same month in 2005. Deals include 15 percent off a new three-bedroom villa in Alicante's Costa Blanca in June and 25 percent off a two-week rental in June, July or August of five-bedroom Casa La Cuerda, in eastern Andalusia. In Portugal, where listings more than doubled to 1,440 in January over January 2005, there are similar deals.</p>
        <p>AFFORDABLE EUROPE | PRACTICAL TRAVELER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
