<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lives of the Democrats</title>
    <meta content="Alterman.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/books/review/Alterman.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841907"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E7D7123FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1311" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lives of the Democrats</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lives of the Democrats</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC ALTERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Alterman, Eric</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>POSITIVELY AMERICAN</p>
        <p>Winning Back the Middle-Class Majority</p>
        <p>One Family at a Time.</p>
        <p>By Chuck Schumer with Daniel Squadron.</p>
        <p>274 pp. Rodale. $24.95.</p>
        <p>... AND I HAVEN'T HAD A BAD DAY SINCE</p>
        <p>From the Streets of Harlem</p>
        <p>to the Halls of Congress.</p>
        <p>By Charles B. Rangel with Leon Wynter.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 293 pp. Thomas Dunne Books/</p>
        <p>St. Martin's Press. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chuck Schumer looks at problems facing the middle class; Charles B. Rangel emphasizes the rags in his rags-to-riches story.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>POSITIVELY AMERICAN</p>
        <p>Winning Back the Middle-Class Majority</p>
        <p>One Family at a Time.</p>
        <p>By Chuck Schumer with Daniel Squadron.</p>
        <p>274 pp. Rodale. $24.95.</p>
        <p>... AND I HAVEN'T HAD A BAD DAY SINCE</p>
        <p>From the Streets of Harlem</p>
        <p>to the Halls of Congress.</p>
        <p>By Charles B. Rangel with Leon Wynter.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 293 pp. Thomas Dunne Books/</p>
        <p>St. Martin's Press. $24.95.</p>
        <p>For a politician, Representative Charles B. Rangel, Democrat of New York, turns out to be a terrific writer. But for Senator Charles E. Schumer, Democrat of New York, the opposite is true.</p>
        <p>Allow me to explain.</p>
        <p>Having slain the dragon that was Alfonse D'Amato -- the perpetually vulnerable but nevertheless previously unbeatable New York Republican -- in 1998, Chuck Schumer has grown into a full-blown political powerhouse. He racked up a 2004 re-election victory in which he received 71 percent of the vote, winning every county but one. Two years later, as chairman of the Democratic Senatorial Campaign Committee, Schumer helped organize and oversee the party's takeover of the Senate, recruiting the right candidates and helping to guide, finance and discipline their campaigns. What's more, his former aide Anthony Weiner has taken his old Congressional seat and is a putative favorite to replace the city's term-limited mayor, Michael Bloomberg, giving rise to intimations of a ''Schumer machine'' that operates at both the local and national level. Not bad for a guy consistently overshadowed by the woman politely referred to as New York's ''junior senator.''</p>
        <p>Schumer didn't get to where he is by taking unnecessary chances, and judging by his first book, ''Positively American,'' he's not eager to risk much as an author, either. Even allowing for the (soft bigotry of) low expectations one brings to a work by an active politician, this is still a bad book. Much of it reads as if it were merely a combination of hastily cobbled-together speeches and position papers, filled out with stale one-liners and homiletic pronouncements -- the kind of book made for gift giving rather than actual reading. I am, broadly speaking, politically and culturally in sympathy with Schumer's progressive politics, but finishing these 274 pages proved a chore on the order of eating a supermarket aisle's worth of Wonder Bread. (And from one New York Jew to another, Chuck, I know that's gotta hurt.)</p>
        <p>Though the first half of ''Positively American'' is presented as a political memoir, its author admits to fewer personality flaws than, say, St. Francis of Assisi had. For instance, Schumer suggests his only inspiration in politics lies in ''helping make things a little better for my parents, my friends' parents and all the families like them.'' Power? Ambition? Ego? Not Chuck. Given that even Schumer's Wikipedia entry mentions the danger he poses to anyone who accidentally finds himself between the senator and a working TV camera, his protestations test the reader's credulity beyond its breaking point.</p>
        <p>Schumer's recollections also suffer from a decided dearth of dish. Nary is heard a discouraging word about anyone, anywhere. Here again, he fails a crucial credibility test. Schumer made his way to the top of the pile in an extremely rough political heap. Who knows how many deals -- or throats -- were cut on the way? But Schumer doesn't tell any back-room stories at all. I found nothing in this book (written with Daniel Squadron) that did not feel as if it had been cleared in advance by a committee of campaign consultants. That may be wise politics, but it makes for tedious reading.</p>
        <p>As for Schumer's policy prescriptions, which take up the second half of the book -- I'm afraid the Wonder Bread metaphor works all too well here as well. Schumer has compiled one of those laundry lists of problems facing middle-class voters, problems that he believes call for ''a 50 percent solution.'' He thinks we should be 50 percent safer from terrorist attacks, our children should be exposed to 50 percent less pornography on the Internet, and our students' reading and math scores should be 50 percent higher. This may work as a slogan, but it is not, to put it mildly, an interesting philosophical argument. Who, to begin with, would oppose any of this? And why 50 percent? Why not 67 or 72? Obviously, it's a gimmick, and the real problem with poll-tested positions of this kind lies in agreeing on the means to address such issues and the likely trade-offs to be made along the way. Time and again, Schumer ignores these complications. Thus, he simply explains away the problem of raising students' scores without ''teaching to the test,'' which is inherent in the No Child Left Behind program. (What's more, he gives reviewers too-easy targets by offering solutions like -- I kid you not -- ''a Schumer box,'' to be put on all cellphone and electronic media player contracts, warning parents against porn.)</p>
        <p>Charlie Rangel's memoir -- in almost perfect contrast -- is mercifully short on laundry lists, but long on sass and spirit. Though Rangel also enjoyed the services of a co-author (in his case, Leon Wynter), ''... And I Haven't Had a Bad Day Since'' brims with brio. For instance, there's Uncle Herbert: ''There wasn't a weekend that he didn't get drunk.'' He would beat up young Charles just for fun, and then ''wash his own face with powdered chlorine bleach.'' Family members are treated sympathetically, but without sugarcoating. And much of the story is not at all pretty, including episodes of domestic violence and parental neglect.</p>
        <p>Though he recently ascended to one of the most powerful positions in Congress -- chairman of the House Ways and Means Committee, through which all revenue-raising legislation must pass -- this rags-to-riches saga emphasizes the rags. It focuses on Rangel's pre-Congressional life: his years growing up in Harlem; his experiences in the Army in Korea, where he was almost killed; his aimless period as a kind of small-time hustler in training; and, finally, his discovering his talent and opportunities, first as a lawyer and later as a political phenomenon within the well-oiled and tightly controlled Harlem machine.</p>
        <p>Rangel has included a preface, written after the elections, in which he lays out his agenda as the Ways and Means chairman. Lobbyists and committee staff members will be eager to read it. The rest of us can revel in his remarkable life story, irresistibly told. The congressman's character portraits, of the famous and not-so-famous, are sympathetically drawn and in many cases wonderfully constructed. One gets a powerful sense of place from Rangel's recollections, whether the scene is a Harlem funeral parlor, the bottom of a ravine in Korea or a negotiating session in Albany. Big personalities like Adam Clayton Powell Jr. and Nelson Rockefeller get their due, but so do Rangel's buddies from his teenage tough-guy club, called ''Les GarÃ</p>
        <p>Eric Alterman, a historian, a journalist, a blogger and the author of six books, is at work on a history of American liberalism.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Eric Alterman, a historian, a journalist, a blogger and the author of six books, is at work on a history of American liberalism.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
