<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tibetan Tea Party</title>
    <meta content="Stuart.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/books/review/Stuart.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841928"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Tibet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Buddhism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buddhism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Tibet</location>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
        <object.title class="online_producer">High Road to China, The: George Bogle, the Panchen Lama, and the First British Expedition to Tibet (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE5D7123FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="646" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tibetan Tea Party</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tibetan Tea Party</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRISTRAM STUART</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stuart, Tristram</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE HIGH ROAD TO CHINA</p>
        <p>George Bogle, the Panchen Lama, and the First British</p>
        <p>Expedition to Tibet.</p>
        <p>By Kate Teltscher.</p>
        <p>316 pp. Illustrated. Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $26.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The China trade inspired a daring encounter between the Panchen Lama and a British empire builder.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE HIGH ROAD TO CHINA</p>
        <p>George Bogle, the Panchen Lama, and the First British</p>
        <p>Expedition to Tibet.</p>
        <p>By Kate Teltscher.</p>
        <p>316 pp. Illustrated. Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $26.</p>
        <p>In 1773, patriots in Boston protested Britain's stranglehold over the tea trade by tipping 342 crates of Chinese leaves into the harbor. The British had been trying desperately to offset the costs of purchasing this valuable commodity from Canton, where China had imposed its own unfavorable trading terms. Tea was the lifeblood of the East India Company, but by the late 18th century, it had begun to drain the beast it was supposed to nourish. Kate Teltscher's marvelous new book, ''The High Road to China,'' lucidly relates how Britain tried to circumvent trade barriers by opening a back door to China through the mysterious land of Tibet.</p>
        <p>It was with this aim that in 1774 Warren Hastings, the governor of Bengal, sent his private secretary, George Bogle, to the remote Buddhist monastery of the third Panchen Lama, Lobsang Palden Yeshe. Bogle's route took him into some of the world's toughest terrain, over flooded ravines in Bhutan and across Tibet's icy plateaus. But these were the least of his obstacles: he also had to scale the daunting barriers of cultural understanding. Communication was actively hindered by agents of the Qianlong emperor in Peking, who claimed Tibet as a dependency and spurned the meddling of traders from an island of ''lonely remoteness ... cut off from the world by intervening wastes of sea.'' Besides, as the Dalai Lama's regent warned, the British were warlike and treacherous. When the Panchen Lama finally permitted Bogle to enter Tibet, he was risking relations with his Chinese overlords; he was also exposing his country to a notorious band of rascals.</p>
        <p>What could have motivated this rash invitation? While Bogle was intent on trade agreements, the Panchen Lama was eager to forge a pilgrim path to the Buddhist holy lands in India: ''I wish,'' he told Bogle, ''to have a place on the banks of the Ganges, to which I might send my people to pray.'' At the heart of Teltscher's book is the friendship that -- according to Bogle -- grew up between himself and the Panchen Lama. Despite the paucity of Tibetan sources, there is enough in Bogle's papers for Teltscher to claim that their relationship ''stands out in the history of encounters between Europeans and non-Europeans because it was neither violent nor exploitative.'' Both Bogle and the Panchen Lama ''were eager to cultivate each other, both were equally keen to learn.''</p>
        <p>Teltscher's 1995 book, ''India Inscribed,'' a study of 17th- and 18th-century British and European writing on India, emphasized how explorations of Eastern cultures, like Sir William Jones's study of Sanskrit, were carried out with the sinister aim of gaining mastery over colonial subjects. There was little room in that strict reading, inspired by the work of Edward Said, for the idea that genuine scholarly fascination could subsist as an end in itself alongside imperial ambitions. Britain's tentative position in Tibet at the time differed from its dominant role in Bengal, but ''The High Road to China'' also signals a shift in Teltscher's general attitude. Even while working for an unjust colonial machine, many individuals fostered similarly paradoxical relationships that became the channels for mutual cultural exchange.</p>
        <p>But the ironies, as Teltscher shows, run deep. Britain's ambition of opening up the Chinese market was finally realized through violence, with the Opium Wars of 1839-42 and 1856-60. Francis Younghusband, who traveled to Tibet in 1903, saw himself as Bogle's diplomatic successor even while leading a British invasion that massacred 500 Tibetans in a single encounter. Teltscher deftly laces her narrative with insights into Tibet's modern predicament, and Bogle's journey becomes a conduit for reflecting how a caffeine addiction that many of us still share was a potent force in shaping global trade.</p>
        <p>Tristram Stuart is the author of ''The Bloodless Revolution: A Cultural History of Vegetarianism From 1600 to Modern Times.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Tristram Stuart is the author of ''The Bloodless Revolution: A Cultural History of Vegetarianism From 1600 to Modern Times.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
