<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Heightened Summer Rush for Passports</title>
    <meta content="22transpassport" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/travel/22transpassport.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841941"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="IN TRANSIT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Passports</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">State Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Conlin, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Passports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Passports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Identification Devices</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">State Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E1DA113FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="548" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Heightened Summer Rush for Passports</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Heightened Summer Rush for Passports</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jennifer Conlin</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Conlin, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>State Department, citing new regulations that took effect in late January under Western Hemisphere Travel Initiative, reports 44 percent increase in passport applications over this time last year; time it takes to obtain passport has risen from four weeks to ten weeks; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>First-time travelers to Europe used to have it easy. Obtaining an American passport might take four weeks, six at the most, but the Western Hemisphere Travel Initiative now means passengers traveling to Barcelona and Athens must compete with those winging it to Jamaica and Acapulco. The result is that getting a new passport can now take up to 10 weeks. As of late January, when the new regulations went into effect, it was estimated by the State Department that 73 percent of Americans did not have passports -- a large number when you consider anyone returning by air from Canada, Panama, Mexico and most Caribbean islands now must have one to re-enter the country.</p>
        <p>''We are currently seeing a 44 percent increase in passport applications over this time last year,'' said Ann Barrett, deputy assistant secretary of state for passport services. ''The demand is a little higher than we anticipated,'' she said, adding that her office had increased the number of people manning phones, added 250 specialists and started a new facility that will eventually handle 10 million passports a year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Getting a new passport can now take up to 10 weeks. What does this mean if you need your passport expedited?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>First-time travelers to Europe used to have it easy. Obtaining an American passport might take four weeks, six at the most, but the Western Hemisphere Travel Initiative now means passengers traveling to Barcelona and Athens must compete with those winging it to Jamaica and Acapulco. The result is that getting a new passport can now take up to 10 weeks. As of late January, when the new regulations went into effect, it was estimated by the State Department that 73 percent of Americans did not have passports -- a large number when you consider anyone returning by air from Canada, Panama, Mexico and most Caribbean islands now must have one to re-enter the country.</p>
        <p>''We are currently seeing a 44 percent increase in passport applications over this time last year,'' said Ann Barrett, deputy assistant secretary of state for passport services. ''The demand is a little higher than we anticipated,'' she said, adding that her office had increased the number of people manning phones, added 250 specialists and started a new facility that will eventually handle 10 million passports a year.</p>
        <p>''If President's Day weekend and spring break are any indication of what is to come, summer will be a fiasco,'' said David J. Alwadish, chief executive of It's Easy (www.itseasypassport.com), which offers passport expediting services and is based in American Airline's new Midtown Manhattan travel center. So far, Mr. Alwadish said, the company has managed to get passports for all of its customers in time.</p>
        <p>There is an expedited government service, which costs an extra $60 on top of the $97 standard passport fee, provided the application is received at least two weeks before departure. In March, however, some travelers found it was taking up to four weeks even with the expedited service, a problem the passport agency says it has now resolved.</p>
        <p>Expediting services charge fees based on the amount of processing time. It's Easy, for example, charges $75 for 8-to-11 day processing and $179 for same-day service. That is on top of the $157 fee charged by the government for a new adult passport.</p>
        <p>Expeditors must go through the passport agency -- which gives the companies a certain number of time guaranteed slots -- hence the reason that privately fast-tracked applicants must also pay the higher government fee.</p>
        <p>''You might think that the increase in demand for passports would mean expeditors would receive more slots, but that is simply not the case,'' said Jeffrey Fine, chief executive of CIBT, which also offers expediting services. Mr. Fine said that CIBT was now selling out nearly all its slots daily.</p>
        <p>Ms. Barrett of the passport agency said: ''We allow the expeditors to come in and help out with those last minute cases, but we have to limit them because we have to keep the majority of slots available to the general American public.'' She noted that travelers can sign up for a passport at  http://travel.state.gov/passport  and check their status online a month after they apply, and after one week in the case of an expedited application. ''I would like people to plan ahead, not just for summer but for the fall and winter,'' she added.</p>
        <p>Passengers who have not received their passports 10 business days before departure should call the National Passport Information Center at (877) 487-2778.</p>
        <p>IN TRANSIT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
