<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tabloid Queen</title>
    <meta content="Senior.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/books/review/Senior.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841925"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Post</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Schiff, Dorothy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Nissenson, Marilyn</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Lady Upstairs, The: Dorothy Schiff and The New York Post (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E5D7123FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1291" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tabloid Queen</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tabloid Queen</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER SENIOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Senior, Jennifer</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE LADY UPSTAIRS</p>
        <p>Dorothy Schiff and The New York Post.</p>
        <p>By Marilyn Nissenson.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 500 pp. St. Martin's Press. $29.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ruling over the pre-Murdoch New York Post, Dorothy Schiff was a pioneer, a complex woman who was both flirt and boss, frosty heiress and labor champion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE LADY UPSTAIRS</p>
        <p>Dorothy Schiff and The New York Post.</p>
        <p>By Marilyn Nissenson.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 500 pp. St. Martin's Press. $29.95.</p>
        <p>Because she wrote a Pulitzer-winning memoir and presided over The Washington Post's evisceration of Richard Nixon, Katharine Graham is probably the best-known woman to have published an American newspaper. But long before there was Katharine Graham, there was Dorothy Schiff. From 1939 to 1976, Schiff owned The New York Post, transforming it from a money-losing broadsheet into a writerly and profitable tabloid, all while preserving the paper's liberal tilt. Unlike Graham, she didn't inherit her paper, either, but bought it outright, albeit with inherited money and at the urging of her second husband. Her romance with the paper proved far more enduring than the marriage -- and the two that followed, for that matter, and her countless love affairs, which Schiff used as both extramarital diversions and sorbet courses between spouses. (Her most famous paramour, though never confirmed, was Franklin Roosevelt.) Schiff didn't sell The Post until she was 73. A young Australian media magnate, Rupert Murdoch, bought it for $31 million and changed its ideological direction -- though not its essential New Yorkness -- forever. Or at least for the foreseeable future.</p>
        <p>Schiff's life and complicated character have all the promising elements of a terrific biography. While not exactly ''a gay byproduct of female emancipation, wearing the pants and using the vote,'' as Kenneth Tynan wrote of Katharine Hepburn -- Schiff was much too fond of showing off her legs -- she was certainly a pioneer, a complex woman who was both flirt and boss, frosty heiress and labor champion; though she rejected the feminist label, she strongly believed in the relationship between work and human integrity, hiring more women than the other newspaper bosses of her day. (When one of these reporters confessed that her job wasn't a big part of her identity, Schiff responded, ''You must have had a very happy childhood.'') She was a skinflint in a fur coat, a cloistered snob with common tastes. She once served Ed Koch a dry tuna sandwich. She once assigned an investigative article about hard-boiled eggs.</p>
        <p>All these eccentric tidbits are included in ''The Lady Upstairs,'' a scrupulously researched book that fairly spills with archival material and personal testimony. But Marilyn Nissenson, a journalist and a documentary producer, doesn't take the additional steps of synthesizing her material and taking control of it -- or, even more fundamentally, animating it. With the exception of some notable paragraphs here and there, her style is just-the-facts, whether interesting or not. Certainly, one can understand how Nissenson wouldn't want to overshadow her subject. But Dorothy Schiff -- or Dolly, as she was known -- is one of the great New York characters of the midcentury. So outsize a figure deserves a confident narrator, one willing to link arms with her readers and tell her story with nerve and verve. Instead, Nissenson paints a low-resolution portrait, unintegrated and pixelated, a scramble on a scrim.</p>
        <p>Though we're repeatedly told Schiff was a ''flirt'' and a ''coquette,'' for instance, we have only the vaguest sense of how she moved and sounded and held herself. (I had to consult Gail Sheehy's 1973 profile of Schiff to get this sense -- how she coiled up her ''long, silken legs beneath her'' on couch cushions, how she clamped a white cigarette holder to the side of her ''lusty mouth, painted Passionata pink.'') Though we learn that Schiff poured about a third of her net worth into The Post to keep it afloat in the early years, we have no idea what she was thinking or feeling as her money disappeared down this fathomless inkwell -- or what gave her the resolve to keep pouring it in. Revelations about Schiff's frailties -- her fear of flying, her early postpartum depression, her later panic attacks -- are presented in an almost offhand way, when they cry out for more comment. And Nissenson describes momentous events in timid, unvivid terms, when they should reveal something about Schiff's inner life. ''Charmed, Roosevelt saw to it that Dolly returned frequently to Hyde Park,'' she writes. ''She was flattered to be asked by the president of the United States, an astonishingly dynamic man.''</p>
        <p>Of course, the facts of Schiff's life are by any standard rich, in every sense. She was the granddaughter of the German Jewish banking magnate Jacob H. Schiff and was raised by a distant, unaffectionate mother so filled with assimilationist anxiety that she refused to let her daughter attend the debutante balls of other Jewish girls. Her husbands were appropriate for each stage of her life: the first, a playboy; the second, a cultured and politically active underachiever; the third, her Post co-editor, Ted Thackrey (as their marriage deteriorated, they went to war in their own editorial pages, arguing over Henry Wallace's commitment to anti-Communism); and the last, a businessman and Zionist, Rudolf Sonneborn, who, though unthreatened by her power, was a threat when he needed some taking care of himself. (She more or less tossed him out of her house after he'd had a stroke: ''He was supposed to look after me -- that's what he said he was going to do -- and he didn't.'') Though Schiff's only formal higher education was a year at Bryn Mawr, she read enough and tore through the world with such gusto that she developed the confidence to write her own column, Dear Reader. She took a shine to the Kennedys, socialized with the Rockefellers, enraged Robert Moses. Above all, she created a great and memorable paper, described by the cultural critic Jerry Tallmer in 1961 as ''the good indignant mama of New York City.''</p>
        <p>One would hope that this book would be, if not a coherent biography of a complicated woman, a coherent history of a newspaper. But it isn't, and for a similar reason: Nissenson has trouble reining in her reportage with well-timed analyses and finding a larger point to make about the news business. Yet she still conveys some of the ironies about The Post's rise and fall under Schiff -- how it was hurt by having a Democrat in the White House, for example, because it no longer had an administration to rail against -- and she makes it clear that private, liberal ownership of a paper doesn't always result in enlightened management: even after the surgeon general issued his warning in 1964, editors were immediately rebuked if they ''allowed a hint that there was a link between smoking and cancer to appear in the paper,'' because Schiff smoked a pack of Kools per day. Over time, Schiff's sweet tooth for gossip got the best of her, and The Post lost its ''crusading spirit.''</p>
        <p>But the tales of old-school journalism may still fill media people with longing. These were the days when The Post ran a 24-part takedown of the columnist Walter Winchell, earning itself such wonderful epithets from him as The New York Pravda, the ''pinko-stinko sheet,'' The Posterior and The N.Y. Poo. Presidential candidates came calling, looking for endorsements; the paper's liberal advocacy made a difference. And the reporters were enlivened by a sense that they were doing good in the world, going to impractical -- and today, possibly impermissible -- lengths to get a story. William Haddad, one of the paper's stars, once went to work in the construction business to confirm a rumor that cement companies were charging the city for double the cement they delivered. ''The Post then was like you wish a newspaper would be now,'' Haddad tells Nissenson, in a reminiscence that could have been Schiff's epitaph. ''You loved to go to work. I had never had much experience, so I thought that The Post was what a newspaper was. It was only later that I found out differently.''</p>
        <p>Jennifer Senior is a contributing editor at New York magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jennifer Senior is a contributing editor at New York magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
