<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The God Disillusion</title>
    <meta content="Metcalf.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/books/review/Metcalf.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841921"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Steinke, Darcey</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Easter Everywhere: A Memoir (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E5D7123FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1272" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The God Disillusion</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The God Disillusion</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN METCALF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Metcalf, Stephen</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EASTER EVERYWHERE</p>
        <p>A Memoir.</p>
        <p>By Darcey Steinke.</p>
        <p>225 pp. Bloomsbury. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In her memoir, Darcey Steinke traces her misery to spiritual rootlessness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EASTER EVERYWHERE</p>
        <p>A Memoir.</p>
        <p>By Darcey Steinke.</p>
        <p>225 pp. Bloomsbury. $24.95.</p>
        <p>I love my neighbor as I love myself -- which is to say, minimally, if at all, and in between fits of out-and-out loathing. But this is not quite the same thing as Christian charity, and one doesn't skip into heaven through a loophole. If the spirit should finally move me, and I answer the call to care for my fellow man unconditionally, the biggest challenge will be extending my newfound caritas to the religious zealots, for it is the zealots -- more than the child molesters, petro-dictators or certain on-air personalities of the Fox News persuasion -- whom I despise above all. Is it any wonder that from the Redeemer to Augustine, from Pascal to W. H. Auden, it has been the doubters, more than the believers, who have kept up religion's good name? A skeptic in this tradition, Darcey Steinke is also, in her own way, a skeptic about the virtues of the contemporary memoir, now a mostly secular genre in which every human unhappiness is trendily medicalized or assigned its origin in a topical childhood trauma. In her memoir, ''Easter Everywhere,'' Steinke has dared to ask, What if my abiding sense of misery isn't due to abuse or balky neurotransmission, but to the absence of God in my life, to an unfulfilled relationship with my own divinity, as vouchsafed to me by the Creator?</p>
        <p>This may seem a peculiar starting point for a Brooklyn it-girl novelist best known for books with titles like ''Suicide Blonde,'' but my preconceptions evaporated by about Page 3, when I became riveted by Steinke's tone, a steady, lovely, hallowed, patient, things-in-themselves hum.</p>
        <p>Steinke's father, we learn, is a Lutheran minister who moved from parish to parish during her childhood, working for a poverty-level wage. As a minister, he was devoted to good works, helping parishioners erect a do-it-yourself church in the dead of winter and tending to the elderly and infirm. But he was also, as her meticulous, and meticulously nonjudgmental, narrative demonstrates, an awkward man, overly abstracted about his own intimacies. His wife, Steinke's mother, was a former provincial beauty queen who attached too early to the local minister's son, and one of the highlights of this delicately wrought little volume is its portrait of an exhausted woman whose vanity has run up against her diminishing circumstances. As Steinke moves toward girlhood and adolescence, her mother, an itinerant and often borderline-destitute do-gooder's wife, gingerly piles up last straws. Over time, Steinke's father appears to lose his faith. Over time, Steinke's mother appears to lose her mind.</p>
        <p>Her mother does, in fact, suffer a nervous breakdown, and her father eventually abandons the church for a spell, but without ever finding a steady career to replace his ministry. Such a childhood is chockablock with potential grievances, but not one gram of score-settling poisons Steinke's memory. Instead she admires her father for having practiced his cultish, peacenik version of Lutheranism as long as he did. (Remember when a politicized Christianity meant fighting poverty and war? It's no less a touching throwback to the 1970s than Blue Nun wine, track lighting and split ends, each of which gets an amusing mention here.) Steinke doesn't even particularly ask him to have been a better father. The real issue seems to be that he infused her with religiosity without providing her with a workable theology, an intellectual framework with which to understand, or at least abide, the central contradictions of Christianity. If God exists, she asks her father, why does he allow so much suffering? ''Ah,'' he responds unhelpfully. ''The $64,000 question.''</p>
        <p>Eventually her father's commitment to his little secular diversions, to jazz and mass-market paperbacks, overtakes his already wan interest in theodicy. ''I tried to engage him in talks about God, the possibility of experiencing God not just now and then but all of the time. He'd shake his head as if I were crazy and tell me the plot of the mystery novel he was reading.''</p>
        <p>Depressives say, ''I have a condition.'' The merely unhappy say, ''Um, actually, I have a life.'' ''Easter Everywhere'' serves to re-erect a boundary between depression and unhappiness that has collapsed in recent decades; this, in turn, helps rescue a genre that has fallen prey to outlandishness and even fraud, most notoriously exemplified by James Frey and his enabler, Oprah Winfrey. Casting aside the language of biological sickness or talk-therapy self-pity for the language of spiritual sickness, a writer no longer needs to up the ante with increasingly extravagant examples of self-degradation. True, Steinke hits some of the familiar stations of the memoir cross: as a young girl, she ostentatiously reads ''Mein Kampf'' to provoke her elders; as a young woman, she finds herself drawn to boys who are ''aloof and nihilistic''; and she eventually becomes a divorced mother badly in need of her scrips. But she nails the central question -- of her memoir and perhaps of her life -- with an extraordinary quote from Simone Weil. ''One has only the choice between God and idolatry,'' Weil wrote. ''If one denies God ... one is worshiping some things of this world in the belief that one sees them only as such, but in fact, though unknown to oneself imagining the attributes of Divinity in them.'' Hence the title ''Easter Everywhere.''</p>
        <p>If you think about it, most of the tenets of the M.F.A. diploma mill, of which Steinke is a star graduate, dovetail nicely with a religious temperament that insists God is in the details, no matter how seemingly banal. This is a beautiful book, and if it loses its way toward the end, it is mostly because no pat answer would satisfy the bottomless questions that burden its author. One wishes she felt less inclined to seek such answers. Her acolyte relationship with a Catholic nun brings us back to the least satisfying solution, a generic over-concern for others so abstract its basis cannot be real love. Is suffering really the best expression of God's presence in our universe? Or are order, repose, generosity and good humor, in the face of one's own suffering, offset by an intolerance of the suffering of others?</p>
        <p>When Steinke does settle on a provisional creed, it's one of touchy-feely meta-beliefs that fail to honor the depth of her own longing. These she palms off on her daughter, and they're no more nourishing than the chocolate her father stopped her mouth with when she once asked about God's sufferance of evil. ''Everybody has their own theology'' and ''You decide what you want to believe'' sound more like an anomie hangover from the 70s than the result of grueling spiritual self-examination, and are likely to leave her own child as much of a dazed pilgrim as she was.</p>
        <p>But this book is nothing if not wise. Steinke recognizes that her feelings of spiritual rootlessness have their origin in authority -- the commanding authority her father wielded when he wore the cloth, and his utter lack of authority when he divested himself of it. The book ends with a childhood memory, of her father as he ''pulled the alb over his head, put on the white surplice with the belled sleeves, then covered his shoulders with the stole made of gold satin with red crosses embroidered on either end.'' This is oddly thrilling -- like Bruce Wayne putting on the cowl. The case ''Easter Everywhere'' makes is against this thrill, and on behalf of something more vague and semireligious, though with an opening to further attainments: by attending patiently and reverently to the truth, one withdraws the banality from all things.</p>
        <p>Stephen Metcalf is the critic at large for Slate and a frequent contributor to the Book Review.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Stephen Metcalf is the critic at large for Slate and a frequent contributor to the Book Review.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
