<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Early Retirement</title>
    <meta content="Stern.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/books/review/Stern.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841927"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Buckley, Christopher</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Boomsday (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E5D7123FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="922" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Early Retirement</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Early Retirement</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE AND MICHAEL STERN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stern, Michael; Stern, Jane</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BOOMSDAY</p>
        <p>By Christopher Buckley.</p>
        <p>318 pp. Twelve/Warner Books. $24.99.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>How to save Social Security, the Christopher Buckley way: Kill the elderly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BOOMSDAY</p>
        <p>By Christopher Buckley.</p>
        <p>318 pp. Twelve/Warner Books. $24.99.</p>
        <p>A persistent legacy of baby-boom pop culture has been the sarcastic attitude embodied by the early days of ''Saturday Night Live'': shockingly wicked derision that is at once smart and goofy. That's the voice of Christopher Buckley's ''Boomsday,'' in which ''the Ungreatest Generation'' (according to the novel's young protagonist) comes under attack by America's under-30s, a generation Buckley suggests might be called Gen-W for its all-purpose, one-word barrier to any unwelcome or annoying circumstance -- ''whatever.''</p>
        <p>The premise: Social Security is bankrupting the country. The problem: young people are stuck with bills tallied up by self-indulgent retirees playing golf and drinking gin and tonics in gated communities. The solution: financial incentives for boomers who agree to kill themselves at the age of 70 (even more if they do it at 65). To put a nice wrapper on the plan, suicide is to be known as ''voluntary transitioning.'' This radical idea is floated by a blogger, Cassandra Devine, and it pulses out of the blogosphere to become the leading issue in a presidential campaign. Cassandra, a public-relations prodigy, devises an advertising strategy to stigmatize oldsters, referring to them as ''resource hogs'' and ''wrinklies,'' and puts a positive spin on the whole idea with Norman Rockwell images of senior citizens doing themselves in. One shows a couple thumbing their noses at a frustrated Grim Reaper, the caption reading, ''We'll do it on our timetable, thanks -- not yours!''</p>
        <p>The plot thickens exponentially as battle lines are drawn and redrawn among a cast of cartoon characters that includes a handsome, skirt-chasing Massachusetts politician named Randy Jepperson; a Bible-thumping right-to-lifer from Sperm (the Society for the Protection of Every Ribonucleic Molecule); a Roman Catholic monsignor who lives in the lap of luxury by bilking widows of their fortunes; Russian prostitutes called Tolstoy and Dostoyevsky; and Cassandra's evil father, an Internet billionaire who gives the president of Yale a $15 million bribe so his dopey stepson won't be expelled. None of the characters are supposed to be lifelike, not even Cassandra, a brainy pinup who is exalted as having ''liquid, playful eyes and lips that seemed always poised to bestow a kiss'' and ''a figure that, when displayed in a bikini or thong at the resort in the Bahamas, would draw sighs from any passing male.''</p>
        <p>Most of them are connected to Yale or Harvard in some way, and it is a given in Buckley's world that such people are America's aristocrats; Jepperson is a member of the ''WASPocracy.'' Nowhere is there mention of boomers less well off than profligate retirees, and the book's rare references to the lower classes are condescending. ''I be writting with regards to my cusin who been in prison for allejedelly runing over the game wardin in his pickup,'' a constituent writes to his congressman. The book's elitism is regional as well. When campaign workers erupt in ''whoops and hollers,'' Buckley explains their vulgarity with the parenthetical ''Most of the staff was from the South.''</p>
        <p>The narrative races forward with no scene longer than a few pages, as it cuts back and forth among the oddballs and their changing alliances and evolving schemes for self-aggrandizement and the destruction of their enemies. Political addicts will enjoy moments of Washington subterfuge -- when, say, the president makes a bogus promise to Gideon Payne (known as ''Mr. Pro-Life'' for his opposition to abortion and assisted suicide) that he won't oppose a Mall memorial to 43 million unborn fetuses in exchange for Payne's support on the TATA Commission (the Commission on Transitioning and Tax Alleviation). Cynics will revel in a ''Stomach Madonna'' bit about a woman in a 17-year coma who develops a rash on her midsection in the shape of the Virgin Mary. Payne uses it as a photo op to raise money for Sperm, and when a hospice worker confesses to creating the image with benzocaine, Mr. Pro-Life declares that it was the Lord who directed the worker to undertake the dermatological hoax.</p>
        <p>''Boomsday'' echoes Kurt Vonnegut's ''Welcome to the Monkey House,'' set in a future when overpopulation drives the World Government to encourage ''ethical suicide.'' While it's not fair to measure Buckley's large-scale novel against Vonnegut's elegant short story, reading ''Boomsday'' might make you long for the days when puerile humor wasn't confused with genuine wit. Vonnegut's story is outrageous and even more ridiculous than Buckley's novel, but it's also devilishly clever and thought-provoking. The satire in ''Boomsday'' is too clever by half. As in so many of the feature-length films based on ''SNL'' skits, the caricature that is comical in small doses gets stale fast. Perhaps you find it amusing that the billionaire's motor boat appears on the cover of a publication titled Vulgar Yacht Quarterly and his sailboat is named Expensive, but page after page of such cloddish comedy can be wearying. Then again, maybe we missed the obscure irony in lines like ''When the going gets tough, the tough get blogging,'' or ''In cyberspace, everyone can hear you scream.'' The humor also includes having members of the TATA Commission come from the American Association of Expensive Estate Attorneys and the Canadian Association of Providers of Cheap but Not Altogether Reliable Pharmaceuticals. And the Massachusetts politician's campaign slogan, tailored to appeal to the Gen-W crowd, is ''Jepperson -- No Worse Than the Others.''</p>
        <p>Buckley -- whose previous novels include ''Thank You for Smoking'' and ''No Way to Treat a First Lady'' -- can come up with funny notions, but little more than that.</p>
        <p>Jane and Michael Stern's most recent book is a memoir, ''Two for the Road: Our Love Affair With American Food.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jane and Michael Stern's most recent book is a memoir, ''Two for the Road: Our Love Affair With American Food.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
