<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Work Search</title>
    <meta content="22wwln--ethicist.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/magazine/22wwlnethicist.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841965"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 04-22-07: THE ETHICIST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Search and Seizure</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Randy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/The Ethicist</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Search and Seizure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E7D6113FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="578" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Work Search</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Work Search</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Randy Cohen</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Randy Cohen Ethicist column comments on legality and propriety of routine searchers of employees' bags as they leave work; comments on whether you may overstate number of confirmed passengers when you reserve a bus for group of friends on assumption that a few will not show up (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the private hospital where I am a medical resident, security guards routinely ask to check employees' bags when we leave. After working a 24-hour shift, I just want to get home. Do employers have the right to search our bags without any probable cause?</p>
        <p>Name withheld, New York</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dilemmas involving examined bags and passengers sought.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At the private hospital where I am a medical resident, security guards routinely ask to check employees' bags when we leave. After working a 24-hour shift, I just want to get home. Do employers have the right to search our bags without any probable cause?</p>
        <p>Name withheld, New York</p>
        <p>The expert on workplace law whom I consulted confirms that your boss has the legal right to search your bag. But ethics sets a higher standard, placing a value on human dignity, something you need not relinquish on the job. Unless there has been a rash of thefts of handbag-size items that less-intrusive measures have failed to curtail, the hospital is acting badly.</p>
        <p>To search someone is to treat him as if he were untrustworthy, if not dishonest. That the hospital searches everyone mitigates this baleful effect slightly, because no employee is being singled out for special scrutiny. But to mildly humiliate many does not eradicate the sting to each.</p>
        <p>The hospital has a legitimate interest in thwarting crime, but it must do so appropriately. The heavy-handed tactic you describe should be introduced only if gentler methods fail. Have small, stealable items been locked up? Has access to them been limited? Has an effort been made to hire honest workers and treat them with the respect that encourages honesty? Have technical experts been consulted to suggest security measures that do not denigrate employees so cavalierly?</p>
        <p>Because an employer holds so much power over employees, there is an ethical duty to wield that power with restraint and to be mindful of the courtesy employees rightfully expect -- that is, not to be bullied. Or, as they put it on the big plaque over the entrance to the Measure for Measure Hospital: ''It is excellent to have a giant's strength, but it is tyrannous to use it like a giant.''</p>
        <p>I am booking a bus to take a group of friends to a political event. The bus holds 47 people. I'm thinking of confirming, say, 55 people, on the almost certain assumption that some won't show up at 5:30 on a Saturday morning as they promised. Is that ethical?</p>
        <p>name withheld, Illinois</p>
        <p>What you propose affronts both ethics and the English language -- the latter because by ''confirming'' you mean ''not confirming'' and the former because you are not being truthful to those you promise a seat on the bus.</p>
        <p>Reluctant as I am to praise the policy of airlines (seldom have so many been made so uncomfortable by so few), that industry has devised a nice solution to the overbooking problem: offer a reward to any passenger who relinquishes a seat and keep raising the value of that reward until there are seats for all who reserved them. If you overbook, you should be prepared to try something similar. Or to rent a car for the overflow. Another approach would be to confirm only 47 passengers but require a cash deposit from each that would be refunded once they boarded the bus. Or perhaps some sort of hostage deal could be worked out: a close relative is released when a passenger takes a seat. Can some stand? Ride on the roof at a discount? Use Rollerblades and a sturdy towline? With a little ingenuity you can solve this problem while still being honest with your potential passengers.</p>
        <p>UPDATE: The organizer says he ended up with one extra person: ''I sucked it up and stood for most of the ride.''</p>
        <p>THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 04-22-07: THE ETHICIST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
