<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>King of Delhi</title>
    <meta content="Harshaw.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/books/review/Harshaw.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841914"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">India</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Dalrymple, William</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Last Mughal, The. The Fall of a Dynasty: Delhi, 1857 (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E6D7123FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="832" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>King of Delhi</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">King of Delhi</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOBIN HARSHAW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Harshaw, Tobin</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE LAST MUGHAL</p>
        <p>The Fall of a Dynasty:</p>
        <p>Delhi, 1857.</p>
        <p>By William Dalrymple.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 534 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $30.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>William Dalrymple looks at Zafar, the last ruler in the Mughal dynasty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE LAST MUGHAL</p>
        <p>The Fall of a Dynasty:</p>
        <p>Delhi, 1857.</p>
        <p>By William Dalrymple.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 534 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $30.</p>
        <p>By Central Asian standards, the 19th-century Mughal emperor Bahadur Shah Zafar II had some pretty impressive bloodlines. Put it this way: If the descendants of Tamerlane and Genghis Khan had held family reunions on the same summer Sunday, Zafar would have been expected to show up at each, lamb biryani in hand. Alas, Zafar -- King of Delhi, Refuge of the Inhabitants of the World, Generous and Affectionate Killer of the Degenerate Infidels (perhaps these sound better in Persian) -- was a case study in how even the finest thoroughbreds can beget an also-ran.</p>
        <p>To be fair, the Islamic Mughal empire Zafar inherited in 1837 had been in steep decline since the death of Emperor Aurangzeb -- as pitiless a tyrant as ever had a wazir disembowled -- 130 years earlier. With no real power and a nearly bare treasury, Zafar turned inward: he was a skilled calligrapher, Sufi mystic, speaker of five languages and master of verse in two. Deep into the night, he oversaw drunken poetry competitions called mushairas.</p>
        <p>While Zafar is the title character of ''The Last Mughal,'' his life is just the thread along which William Dalrymple continues to explore a theme that has fascinated him for two decades: the utter collapse of relations between the British and the inhabitants of their Indian dominions. In his last book, the excellent ''White Mughals,'' a doomed love affair between a British civil servant and an Indian noblewoman served as an allegory for broader social unraveling. Here he tackles the most obvious example, the Great Mutiny of 1857, in which hundreds of thousands of mostly Hindu soldiers turned murderously on their British officers and inexplicably made their feeble Muslim monarch the figurehead of Asia's first great anticolonial uprising.</p>
        <p>Dalrymple excels at bringing grand historical events within contemporary understanding by documenting the way people went about their lives amid the maelstrom. His coup in researching ''The Last Mughal'' was his uncovering, deep in the National Archives of India, some 20,000 personal Persian and Urdu papers written by Delhi residents who survived the uprising.</p>
        <p>Why had historians not used these papers before? As Dalrymple explains, what really happened doesn't fit any fashionable academic dogmas: ''The stories that the collection contains allow the uprising to be seen not in terms of nationalism, imperialism, orientalism or other such abstractions, but instead as a human event of extraordinary, tragic and often capricious outcomes.''</p>
        <p>Dalrymple lets the characters tell their own tales: a 12-year-old Muslim nobleman who watched the defeated Indian mutineers and conquering British ''vying with each other as to which should carry the day in pillage or robbery''; a functionary in Zafar's court with the wonderful title of ''Keeper of the Dynastic Fish Standard of the Mughals''; and a poet who saw that the mutiny was only empowering the uneducated Indian soldiers to wipe out his humanist class, ''as the moon is engulfed by the eclipse.''</p>
        <p>As for the British, Dalrymple focuses on a few whose emotional transformations are the most idiosyncratic: the gregarious son of a poisoned British official is driven to homicidal rage in the battle to retake Delhi; the editor of the city's English-language daily becomes the leading voice in the movement to raze the capital; the wife of a senior British officer gives birth during her harrowing escape yet, almost alone among the participants, retains her sanity and humanity.</p>
        <p>Sanity, alas, is not Zafar's strong suit, at least not by the time he flees the city, only to dither on its outskirts and take refuge in the tomb of an ancestor, Humayun. This is fitting, as Humayun, the second Mughal emperor, was also more suited to poetry than politics and also lost his throne, regaining it just in time to pass it along to his remarkable son Akbar in 1556.</p>
        <p>No such fortune awaited Zafar: he was arrested, given a kangaroo trial and exiled to Burma. What blame does he deserve for the bloody fiasco? Dalrymple feels it is ''difficult to see what more Zafar could have done,'' but the details he has so painstakingly assembled tend to undermine such sympathies.</p>
        <p>Consider two events in the mutiny's first week. On May 14, upset that some Indian soldiers were defiling a beloved garden, he began ''refusing audience to all.'' This was a threat to withdraw his imprimatur from their rebellion, and the mutineers moved on. Two days later, when the rebels discovered 52 Europeans Zafar had hidden in the palace, the emperor ''wept and besought the mutineers not to take the lives of helpless women and children,'' but stepped aside as the executioners went to work.</p>
        <p>At the pivotal moment of his doomed reign, Zafar concentrated not on his role as a leader of men or on the sparing of innocent lives, but rather on his flowers. Deep in their tombs, one suspects, Humayun sympathized, Aurangzeb scoffed and Genghis Khan wept silent tears.</p>
        <p>Tobin Harshaw is an editor for the Op-Ed page of The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Tobin Harshaw is an editor for the Op-Ed page of The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
