<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amanda Cody, Mark Donohue</title>
    <meta content="22cody" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842162"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cody, Amanda Katherine (Amanda Katherine Donohue)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Donohue, Mark Avon Phillip</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03EFDD163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="390" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amanda Cody, Mark Donohue</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Amanda Katherine Cody, a daughter of Joy and Matthew Cody of Garden City, N.Y., was married yesterday to Mark Avon Phillip Donohue, a son of Phillip and Ann Donohue of Brooklyn, N.Y. John J. McKenna, a Roman Catholic deacon, officiated at St. Joseph Church in Garden City.</p>
        <p>The bride, 27, is a manager in the technology and security risk services group at Ernst &amp; Young, the accounting firm, in Manhattan. She graduated from Loyola College in Maryland. The bride's father is a senior marketing officer at Vanderbilt Capital Advisors in Manhattan. The bride's mother retired as a health and physical education teacher at Richmond Hill High School in Queens.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Amanda Katherine Cody, a daughter of Joy and Matthew Cody of Garden City, N.Y., was married yesterday to Mark Avon Phillip Donohue, a son of Phillip and Ann Donohue of Brooklyn, N.Y. John J. McKenna, a Roman Catholic deacon, officiated at St. Joseph Church in Garden City.</p>
        <p>The bride, 27, is a manager in the technology and security risk services group at Ernst &amp; Young, the accounting firm, in Manhattan. She graduated from Loyola College in Maryland. The bride's father is a senior marketing officer at Vanderbilt Capital Advisors in Manhattan. The bride's mother retired as a health and physical education teacher at Richmond Hill High School in Queens.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom, 28, is a firefighter with Engine Company 40 in Manhattan. He graduated from the State University of New York College at Potsdam. His mother retired as an early childhood teacher specialist for the New York City Board of Education in District 20 in Brooklyn, where she trained teachers. The bridegroom's father retired as a stock trader at Lehman Brothers, the investment bank in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>The couple met in 2004 at a Halloween party at a pub on the Upper East Side of Manhattan. Mr. Donohue was one of a half-dozen men who dressed as characters from Roger Hargreaves's ''Mr. Men and Little Miss'' children's book series. Mr. Donohue wore an orange suit, the signature color of his character, Mr. Tickle. He had stapled extra long sleeves to the suit so that he would have Mr. Tickle's tentaclelike arms.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cody knew one of the men in the group, Christopher Ahern, who was wearing a yellow suit, the signature color of the character Mr. Skinny. She asked him who had come up with the idea for the costumes, and he replied that it was his longtime friend Mr. Donohue.</p>
        <p>''I thought the idea was extremely creative,'' said Ms. Cody, who had improvised a doctor's costume with the last-minute purchase of a lab coat, and scrubs and a stethoscope borrowed from her roommate, a nurse.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cody struck up a conversation with Mr. Donohue and found the man in the orange suit to be ''creative, confident in his skin, unpretentious.''</p>
        <p>''She just came right up and started talking,'' Mr. Donohue remembered. ''She was funny, honest.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Tickle was touched.</p>
        <p>They spoke together until the wee hours, when the party ended.</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
