<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kurt From the Block</title>
    <meta content="22vonn" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/thecity/22vonn.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842187"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEW YORK OBSERVED"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vonnegut, Kurt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Masello, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Vonnegut, Kurt</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E5DC163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1148" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kurt From the Block</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Kurt From the Block</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID MASELLO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Masello, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Masello New York Observed essay on late novelist Kurt Vonnegut, who was his neighbor on East 48th Street in Manhattan; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE morning after Kurt Vonnegut's death on April 11, I walked past his town house, which is on East 48th Street between Second and Third Avenues. Although a cold, driving rain was falling, people had stuck folded notes and letters into the seam of the double door -- none of which, I imagined, would be readable because of the weather. A single frosted globe-lamp was lighted on the parlor floor, as if left on for the anonymous visitors. The next morning, a clear and sunny one, four bouquets of flowers were draped on the stoop's flight of steps.</p>
        <p>For years, I have lived two blocks away from Mr. Vonnegut's home, and I saw him regularly -- sitting on those front steps with Flour, his fluffy white dog, beside him or walking Flour in Dag Hammarskjold Plaza, where he sat with a cigarette on a bench and read the newspaper. (So frequent were Mr. Vonnegut's visits to the park that his wife, the photographer Jill Krementz, and his daughter Lily are seeking donations through the Turtle Bay Association to endow one of his favorite benches.) Some of the people who passed him repeatedly turned around, wondering if the man they were seeing was really who they thought he was.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the delight of his Turtle Bay neighbors, the late novelist Kurt Vonnegut could often be found on the stoop of his brownstone on East 48th Street, his dog, Flour, by his side.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE morning after Kurt Vonnegut's death on April 11, I walked past his town house, which is on East 48th Street between Second and Third Avenues. Although a cold, driving rain was falling, people had stuck folded notes and letters into the seam of the double door -- none of which, I imagined, would be readable because of the weather. A single frosted globe-lamp was lighted on the parlor floor, as if left on for the anonymous visitors. The next morning, a clear and sunny one, four bouquets of flowers were draped on the stoop's flight of steps.</p>
        <p>For years, I have lived two blocks away from Mr. Vonnegut's home, and I saw him regularly -- sitting on those front steps with Flour, his fluffy white dog, beside him or walking Flour in Dag Hammarskjold Plaza, where he sat with a cigarette on a bench and read the newspaper. (So frequent were Mr. Vonnegut's visits to the park that his wife, the photographer Jill Krementz, and his daughter Lily are seeking donations through the Turtle Bay Association to endow one of his favorite benches.) Some of the people who passed him repeatedly turned around, wondering if the man they were seeing was really who they thought he was.</p>
        <p>Even though Mr. Vonnegut and I had come to recognize each other as neighbors, I never had the courage to talk to him. Partly that was because I hadn't read his novels since college, and I figured that I needed a working knowledge of those plots to engage in an intelligent conversation.</p>
        <p>Finally, we reached the point where we nodded to each other on the street or in the park, and I would utter a quiet hello. The cigarette he would be smoking always seemed to have a long, fragile ash at its end, which more than once fell to his shirt when he nodded back. As a result, when I passed him, I'd see him quickly brushing the front of his shirt and the top of his pants, which were always dotted with small burn holes.</p>
        <p>When the Broadway star Carol Channing was performing at Feinstein's at the Regency in October 2005, I was lucky enough to attend her opening night. Among those in the audience was the actress Celeste Holm, who at one point, needing help negotiating the way back to her table, had to rest for a moment on a chair at my table.</p>
        <p>For some reason, she held my hand and we talked. I felt that I was experiencing an impossible link to history, holding the hand of one of the stars of the classic 1950 film ''All About Eve.'' I might just as well have been holding the hand of Cleopatra or suggesting the right garment for Mona Lisa to wear. But also in the audience was Mr. Vonnegut. When he walked into the room, we caught each other's eye, and I could tell that he was trying to figure out where he had seen me. Quickly, it seemed, he remembered me as his Turtle Bay neighbor, and nodded his familiar silent greeting.</p>
        <p>I loved having Mr. Vonnegut as my neighbor. Every time out-of-town friends visited, I walked them past his town house, where he had lived for decades, hoping that he would be sitting on the steps.</p>
        <p>One summer night soon after I had moved to the neighborhood, a dreadful accident occurred at Second Avenue and 49th Street; a sports car had lodged itself under the carriage of a tractor-trailer. As the assembled crowd peered at the wreck, I spotted Mr. Vonnegut. After several minutes, a young man approached me from the crowd and said: ''I know what you're looking at, and it's a lot more awesome than this accident. That is Kurt Vonnegut, isn't it?'' The stranger and I continued to gaze at the famous author while the firefighters' saws buzzed.</p>
        <p>I also remember when a fire broke out in Mr. Vonnegut's town house. According to news reports, he had apparently fallen asleep with a cigarette in hand. A neighbor across the street saw smoke curling from the top-floor window of the town house and, in the middle of the night, rang Mr. Vonnegut's bell and called the Fire Department.</p>
        <p>For months afterward, the window that had been knocked out during the fire remained boarded up with plywood. And in fact, although Mr. Vonnegut's residence was a full town house on a shady, much-coveted Manhattan block, it has always appeared less than pristine. Chinese takeout menus litter the landing, and books and papers are piled in front of windows, whose shades and curtains are uneven.</p>
        <p>MR. VONNEGUT'S block has always been my favorite block in Manhattan, not just because he lived there, but also because it was where the author E. B. White lived for decades.</p>
        <p>It's not that I thought E. B. White's ghost occupies this block or that I'd have a sighting of him through a window holding his pet dachshund, Fred, described in a 1956 essay as ''always willing to put up with being hoisted in order to gain the happy heights.'' But I do admit recently buying a reissued copy of a collection of his essays and holding the book up to the facades of his houses as I passed them, just in case some part of the author was there to see that he was still being read and published.</p>
        <p>In the case of Mr. Vonnegut, I know that he is still being read and published. Walking into the Borders store in the Time Warner Center the other day, I noticed that a display of his books had quickly been assembled, next to which was a group of young men and women, all holding copies of his novels.</p>
        <p>At the Third Avenue end of Mr. Vonnegut's block, there is an undulating office tower whose plaza contains whimsical sculptures by the artist Pamela Waters, including a 35-foot-high chessboard mounted on a windowless wall of an adjacent apartment building. A couple of times every month, a worker in a cherry picker moves one of the two-and-a-half-foot-wide disks, replicating the sequence of play in a professional match. I remember seeing Mr. Vonnegut studying the grid one day, and I have often thought that E. B. White might also have been engaged by the sculpture, had it been there when he lived on the block.</p>
        <p>Around the corner is ''Big Red Swing,'' a grand piano-scaled steel swing by Theodore Ceraldi that hangs under the arcade of an office tower. For years, I used to imagine Mr. White sitting there, pushing himself off the ground on the big red seat, Fred cradled in his arms, as he looked to ''the nameless actors who have a daily walk-on part in my play.'' Now I imagine Kurt Vonnegut there, too, Flour beside him, the two great authors and their pets in one another's company.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK OBSERVED David Masello is articles editor at Country Living magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Masello is articles editor at Country Living magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
