<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>One League Is Superior, and Don't Blame the Yankees</title>
    <meta content="22score" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/sports/baseball/22score.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842254"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="KEEPING SCORE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E6D7163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="891" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>One League Is Superior, and Don't Blame the Yankees</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">One League Is Superior, and Don’t Blame the Yankees</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN ROSENHECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenheck, Dan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Who hit better last year, Alex Rodriguez or David Wright? Carlos Beltrán or Jason Giambi? For that matter, which was a better team on the whole, the Yankees or the Mets?</p>
        <p>Fans acquainted with modern statistical evaluation may eschew traditional metrics in such debates, and compare the players' on-base and slugging percentages with the league average to make their case. But though both pairs of sluggers hit the same relative to their leagues last year, there's no doubting that the Yankees' players were more valuable. And although the teams had the same 2006 won-lost record and split their interleague games, last year's Yankees probably would have beaten the Mets comfortably had they played more games against each other.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although fans tend not to distinguish between the overall quality of the American and National Leagues, the gap between them has grown in the past two years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Who hit better last year, Alex Rodriguez or David Wright? Carlos Beltrán or Jason Giambi? For that matter, which was a better team on the whole, the Yankees or the Mets?</p>
        <p>Fans acquainted with modern statistical evaluation may eschew traditional metrics in such debates, and compare the players' on-base and slugging percentages with the league average to make their case. But though both pairs of sluggers hit the same relative to their leagues last year, there's no doubting that the Yankees' players were more valuable. And although the teams had the same 2006 won-lost record and split their interleague games, last year's Yankees probably would have beaten the Mets comfortably had they played more games against each other.</p>
        <p>The Yankees were superior because they faced a subtle but significant disadvantage: their league. Although fans tend not to distinguish between the overall quality of the American and National Leagues, the gap between them has grown larger in the past two years than at any point since the 1950s, when the N.L. integrated black players much faster than the A.L. did. According to Nate Silver of Baseball Prospectus, a typical A.L. hitter moving to the N.L. can expect to gain about 10 points of batting average and on-base percentage and 20 points of slugging percentage. A.L. pitchers switching leagues will usually have their earned run averages decrease because of the absence of the designated hitter in the N.L., but Silver calculates that the E.R.A. of an A.L. pitcher switching leagues is likely to drop by 0.25 runs more than can be accounted for by the D.H.</p>
        <p>At a team level, an average A.L. squad would probably improve its record by about 10 games if it could face N.L. competition, meaning that last year's Yankees probably would have been a 107-win juggernaut if they had played the Mets' schedule. The same is true in reverse: if the 2006 Mets had played in the A.L., they would have won only 87 games and missed the playoffs. This is about the same difference in league strength as the gap between today's N.L. and Japan's Nippon Professional Baseball.</p>
        <p>Some variation in league strength is not uncommon in baseball history, but the magnitude of today's imbalance is remarkable. The cause is straightforward: A.L. teams have spent more money on players than their N.L. counterparts. In 2005, the average N.L. team had a $71 million payroll, while the average A.L. team's was $75 million. Since then, N.L. spending has increased only slightly, to $74 million a team, while salaries in the A.L. have soared to $93 million a team.</p>
        <p>Surprisingly, the Yankees cannot be directly blamed for this trend. They are one of only two A.L. teams that have reduced their payroll since 2005. The Red Sox, often accused of imitating the Evil Empire, are not the primary culprits, either -- their $20 million increase in spending over the past two years is right around the A.L. average.</p>
        <p>Instead, it is the small- and midmarket A.L. teams that have pumped up their payrolls. The leader, believe it or not, is perennially cellar-dwelling Kansas City, which has more than doubled its $30 million payroll of 2005. The Chicago White Sox and Toronto have also added more than $30 million in salaries over the past two years.</p>
        <p>The Yankees-Red Sox rivalry may still be an underlying cause. A.L. East teams like the Blue Jays are forced to stretch their budgets if they hope to compete. The rest of the league is also indirectly pressured, because if the Yankees or the Red Sox are likely to win the wild card, a Central or West team must win its division to make the playoffs. ''One theory is that when the Yankees started spending big money to improve their team, everybody else had to chase them,'' said Bill James, a leading baseball researcher who now works for the Red Sox.</p>
        <p>It may be just as fair to finger the N.L. owners for their parsimony as it is to criticize the A.L.'s titans for their largess. Fans certainly don't factor in league strength when deciding whether to go to the ballpark or how much to spend. According to Forbes magazine, N.L. teams earn just as much revenue on average as A.L. ones do, despite their smaller payrolls, which makes them more profitable: the average N.L. franchise posted an operating income of $19.9 million in 2006, compared with $12.7 million for the A.L.</p>
        <p>There are long-term financial benefits to winning a World Series, but so much luck is involved in the playoffs that N.L. owners may not have a clear economic incentive to buy the best team possible. The optimal strategy may be simply paying for a club that is good enough to make the playoffs in the weak N.L., and hoping it gets hot at the right time to snare a title -- just like last year's 83-win St. Louis Cardinals, who would probably have been the fourth-worst team in the A.L. last year.</p>
        <p>There are many steps baseball could take to correct the imbalance if it wanted: expanding the A.L., realigning or putting in a salary floor would each help. But none of these steps are likely to take place unless the A.L.'s hapless midmarket teams can convince their N.L. counterparts to spread their wealth -- or even put sporting glory ahead of profit.</p>
        <p>KEEPING SCORE E-mail: keepingscore@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: keepingscore@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
