<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In French Vote for President, The Political Is Existential</title>
    <meta content="22france" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/world/europe/22france.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842288"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernard, Ariane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sarkozy, Nicolas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Royal, Segolene</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">France</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Royal, Segolene</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Sarkozy, Nicolas</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Le Pen, Jean-Marie</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jospin, Lionel</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Chirac, Jacques</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E7DE173EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In French Vote for President, The Political Is Existential</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In French Vote for President, Political Is Existential</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ARIANE BERNARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernard, Ariane</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, April 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Latest polls find 85 percent of French plan to support one of four leading candidates in first round of presidential election; polls show Nicolas Sarkozy with 30 percent and Segolene Royal with 23 percent as most likely contenders for runoff (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With 12 candidates running in the first round of the presidential election on Sunday, the choices made by two men drinking espresso in a cafe here seemed to sum up the dilemma for many French people: whether to vote with the heart or the head.</p>
        <p>Hakim Bensalem, 30, a telecom technician who lives in Noisy-Le-Sec, a Paris suburb, said he would not give up his ''right to express my ideas'' and would support Olivier Besancenot, a far-left candidate who hovers around 4 percent in recent polls.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first round of the election is under way, and many French people face a dilemma: whether to vote with the heart or the head.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With 12 candidates running in the first round of the presidential election on Sunday, the choices made by two men drinking espresso in a cafe here seemed to sum up the dilemma for many French people: whether to vote with the heart or the head.</p>
        <p>Hakim Bensalem, 30, a telecom technician who lives in Noisy-Le-Sec, a Paris suburb, said he would not give up his ''right to express my ideas'' and would support Olivier Besancenot, a far-left candidate who hovers around 4 percent in recent polls.</p>
        <p>He said he was not concerned that his vote for Mr. Besancenot might erode the standing of Ségolène Royal, the main candidate on the left, whom he would be ready to vote for in the runoff on May 6.</p>
        <p>''If she doesn't make it, she doesn't make it,'' Mr. Bensalem said, ''I'll chalk it up to destiny, and we'll have to deal with the right.''</p>
        <p>But his friend Mickael Gomis, 30, who also lives in Noisy-Le-Sec and is in the same line of work as Mr. Bensalem, said he would vote for Ms. Royal on Sunday. ''I'm going to vote for the biggest force of opposition possible,'' he said. ''The others, they are too small.''</p>
        <p>Weighing heavily on the minds of many voters are memories of the election of 2002, when the far-right leader Jean-Marie Le Pen edged past the Socialist candidate Lionel Jospin in the first round, depriving Mr. Jospin, the prime minister at the time, of a place in the runoff and ensuring an overwhelming victory by the incumbent, Jacques Chirac.</p>
        <p>Mr. Le Pen has come in fourth in opinion polls this year, and on Thursday Le Monde, the left-leaning newspaper, urged its readers to avoid a repeat of 2002 by choosing either Ms. Royal or the leading conservative candidate, Nicolas Sarkozy.</p>
        <p>Mathieu Doiret, an analyst at the polling group CSA, said ''French voters are caught between two tendencies: to want to affirm a narrow opinion on single-issue candidates, which has allowed Mr. Le Pen to rise, and to want to consolidate their vote around a stronger candidate.''</p>
        <p>The latest polls suggest that the head might be winning over the heart. The daily IPSOS tracking survey on Friday found that 85 percent of voters planned to support one of the four leading candidates, while in the first-round election of 2002 the top four candidates only received 60 percent of the vote.</p>
        <p>And in most recent surveys none of the eight remaining candidates breaks the 5 percent threshold, the point where the state reimburses campaign costs beyond the minimum amount. Some of those candidates in recent days have made desperate pleas to their supporters not to abandon them, with the Trotskyite candidate Arlette Laguiller asserting that she ''did not believe that Mr. Le Pen could qualify for the runoff.''</p>
        <p>Polls show Mr. Sarkozy, with 30 percent, according to IPSOS, and Ms. Royal, with 23 percent, as the two likely contenders for the runoff. François Bayrou, the centrist candidate with 18 percent in most surveys, is fighting not to be sacrificed to the recent consolidation tendencies pollsters have detected.</p>
        <p>On Friday, the last official day of the campaigning, the candidates chose striking images to make a final impression on voters before the mandatory 24 hour-blackout of television coverage and opinion polls. Mr. Sarkozy rode a horse and stopped at a bull farm in the south, Ms. Royal visited a trendy Parisian market street, while Mr. Bayrou stopped at a World War I memorial near Verdun.</p>
        <p>There is more at stake than whether Mr. Le Pen, whose support has always been underestimated, makes an appearance in the runoff.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sarkozy and Ms. Royal between them can expect only 53 percent of the vote on Sunday, according to IPSOS. If they make it into the runoff, they will need the support not only from the far-left and far-right, but also from the center -- that is, from Mr. Bayrou's supporters if he does not qualify. CSA's surveys indicate that those voters lean slightly to the right.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Sarkozy's lead in the polls does not mean that he should count on becoming the next occupant of the Élysée Palace just yet. In 1981, the incumbent president, Valéry Giscard d'Estaing, came in ahead of François Mitterrand in the first round, and seemed to have the largest reservoir of votes for the runoff. But voters' desire for change tipped the scales, and Mr. Mitterrand won.</p>
        <p>To put it mildly, Mr. Gomis has no great enthusiasm for Ms. Royal. He called her an ''an incompetent fool,'' but said he would vote for her anyway. The small-party candidates who stand no chance of being elected exist solely as a force of dissent, he added. ''Everybody knows how to complain,'' Mr. Gomis said. ''But solutions, that's something else.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
