<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Affordable Europe: Moscow</title>
    <meta content="22moscowweb" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/travel/22moscowweb.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842335"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Moscow (Russia)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/Moscow</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Moscow (Russia)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E1D61631F931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="675" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Affordable Europe: Moscow</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Affordable Europe: Moscow</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SOPHIA KISHKOVSKY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tourists on a budget face a fairly daunting hurdle when it comes to traveling cheaply in Moscow, one of the world's most expensive cities. It is all too easy to spend hundreds of dollars for a meal in Moscow, and hotels are no bargain either. Still, there are bargains to be had, even in the heart of the city.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay for Under 125 Euros</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is all too easy to spend hundreds of dollars for a meal in Moscow, and hotels are no bargain either. Still, there are bargains to be had, even in the heart of the city.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tourists on a budget face a fairly daunting hurdle when it comes to traveling cheaply in Moscow, one of the world's most expensive cities. It is all too easy to spend hundreds of dollars for a meal in Moscow, and hotels are no bargain either. Still, there are bargains to be had, even in the heart of the city.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay for Under 125 Euros</p>
        <p>Moscow's city government keeps promising a three-star hotel boom for middle-class visitors. In the meantime, there are only a handful of reasonable and comfortable options in the city center. The Prospekt Mira Hotel (Orlovo-Davydovsky per., d. 2/5, korp. 3; 7-495-741-2605, www.s-kontur.com) opened in 2006 in a quiet residential bloc near Aptekarsky Ogorod, Moscow State University's charming botanical garden. It has only nine rooms for now, at 4,000 rubles (about $150, at 26.50 rubles to the dollar -- or about 115 euros) and 4,200 rubles, and a small restaurant, but will expand to 36 rooms later this year. There is a one-time 25 percent reservation fee, or 1,000 to 1,050 rubles. Godzillas(Bolshoi Karetny per., d. 6; 7-495-699-4223; www.godzillashostel.com), an English-owned hostel that is a 20-minute walk from Red Square, is also in a renovated wing of a building. Aside from dormitory-style rooms, it offers seven private rooms, most with double beds, at 1,740 rubles. Bathrooms are shared. For a wider selection of centrally located lodgings, try Pulford serviced apartments (www.pulford.com) or Evans Real Estate (www.evans.ru).</p>
        <p>Where to Eat  Grabli, a luxury restaurateur's mass-market chain, offers Russian specialties from borscht to blini to stuffed cabbage, as well as cappuccino, tortes, parfaits and bar drinks, most at stunningly low prices, served in a free-flow cafeteria set-up. A three-story Grabli (Ulitsa Pyatnitskaya 27; 7-495-545-0830) with décor evoking Belle Époque Paris opened in 2006 two blocks from the Tretyakov Gallery. The average bill is 200 rubles. Most Moscow restaurants, even pricey ones, offer a fixed-price business lunch on weekdays, usually soup, salad, entrée and a cup of coffee or tea. It's 500 rubles at Red Square Restaurant (Red Square 1, 7-495-692-1196 or 7-495-692-5198; www.redsquare.ru) at the State Historical Museum on Red Square, and 600 rubles at Aist, one of Moscow's trendiest restaurants (Ulitsa Malaya Bronnaya 8/1; 7-495-736-9131). At Café Pushkin, a grand Moscow institution after less than a decade in operation, (Tverskoi bulvar 26a; 7-495-629-5590), it's also possible to enjoy the setting and stay within budget by sticking to tea and dessert, about 610 rubles.</p>
        <p>Where to Shop  For souvenirs, crafts stalls or stores found in most Moscow churches and monasteries are a good bet. Even the most touristy ones, like Christ the Savior Cathedral, have decent prices. At the Novodevichy Convent, a church basement shop called simply Tserkovnaya Lavka, or Church Store, offers everything from Russian scarves and black lacquer boxes (small ones can be had for 60 rubles) to icons (4,800 rubles for a large, hand-painted icon) at very reasonable prices. The nuns speak in hushed tones and expect visitors to do the same. Avoid price-gouging souvenir hawkers at the monastery gate. For classy Russian fashion, recently an oxymoron, try the Sultanna Frantsuzova chain (www.sultannafrantsuzova.com), which offers permanent discounts depending on the number of items purchased.</p>
        <p>Best Money-Saving Tip  Avoid taxis, which are notorious for price-gouging. A direct plane-to-train connection runs from Domodedovo International Airport to the Paveletsky train station for 150 rubles (a taxi often costs several thousand rubles). Soon there will be a direct link to Sheremetyevo Airport from Savyolovsky train station. The metro is crowded but much more efficient than Moscow roads or taxi drivers. A 20-ride metro pass is just 250 rubles, 60 rides for 520 rubles. Except for the Kremlin cathedrals, most Moscow churches are free and many have beautiful architecture and concert-quality liturgical singing. Well worth the 100-ruble entry fee, which is flexible, is Park Iskusstv, or Park of Arts, adjacent to the Central House of Artists on Krymsky Val. It is full of discarded monuments to Soviet leaders, from Lenin and Stalin to bushy-eyebrowed Brezhnev.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
