<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Can He Get There From Here?</title>
    <meta content="22map" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/thecity/22map.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842184"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="URBAN TACTICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Maps</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jabbour, Eddie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corbett, Rachel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Maps</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E6DC163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="986" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Can He Get There From Here?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Can He Get There From Here?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RACHEL CORBETT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Corbett, Rachel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Eddie Jabbour, marketing company co-owner and subway enthusiast who spent nearly five years designing new subway map for New York City; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was 5 p.m., and Eddie Jabbour knew that taking the subway would be faster than dealing with traffic. Cars would be backed up all the way from his office near the Empire State Building to the SoHo restaurant where he was taking an out-of-town client. But as the two descended the subway steps, his client confessed that he has always been intimidated by New York's subway system.</p>
        <p>''It's a labyrinth,'' Mr. Jabbour agreed. ''It's just a hole in the ground, and the hole is a maze.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A straphanger soldiers on in a five-year quest to revamp the 1979 subway map.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was 5 p.m., and Eddie Jabbour knew that taking the subway would be faster than dealing with traffic. Cars would be backed up all the way from his office near the Empire State Building to the SoHo restaurant where he was taking an out-of-town client. But as the two descended the subway steps, his client confessed that he has always been intimidated by New York's subway system.</p>
        <p>''It's a labyrinth,'' Mr. Jabbour agreed. ''It's just a hole in the ground, and the hole is a maze.''</p>
        <p>After they boarded the train, Mr. Jabbour tried to locate their route on the map inside the subway car. ''That's when it came to me,'' he said. ''It's the map! The map is the last vestige of the old system. If you can't read the map, you can't use the subway.''</p>
        <p>Since that day nearly five years ago, Mr. Jabbour, a 54-year-old co-owner of a marketing company, has devoted his weekends and evenings to studying old transit maps in an effort to produce one of his own. Persuading the city to adopt his new map, which he says is more stylized than the current map and therefore more accessible to non-New Yorkers, has become something of an obsession.</p>
        <p>''The map is an icon of the city; it represents New York on a certain level,'' said Mr. Jabbour, a small, restless man who was born in Bay Ridge, Brooklyn, and lives in Hastings-on-Hudson in Westchester County. ''And it takes a cryptic archaeologist to read this one. It's like the Rosetta Stone.''</p>
        <p>A self-proclaimed ''subway foamer,'' or buff, Mr. Jabbour has a passion for transit-related subjects like infrastructure, routes and track design.</p>
        <p>''It's definitely his passion,'' his 17-year-old daughter, Ellie, said of his map, adding that nearly every weekend he prints out a new version and asks her opinion on alterations she has trouble even seeing, like ''slight modulations in subway line thicknesses or color changes.''</p>
        <p>The other day, in his minimalist office, Mr. Jabbour pinned two maps to the wall, then pointed to the different renderings of the Atlantic Avenue terminal in Brooklyn, which he says is the most difficult station to represent because so many subway lines converge there. In Mr. Jabbour's map, the subway lines run parallel to one another, making the map easier to read, if slightly inaccurate. Each line is marked with a circle bearing the route's letter or number, instead of the oblong station markers used on the current map.</p>
        <p>There are other differences. Unlike the official map, Mr. Jabbour's map does not have a single line representing all the trains in a ''cluster'' route, like the 1, 2 and 3 trains in Manhattan. He used the same type font throughout, and words travel left to right, rather than diagonally, as on much of the official map. The lines bend only in 45- and 90-degree angles, to create a gridlike pattern.</p>
        <p>In the eyes of Mr. Jabbour, the New York system is too complicated to layer on information like commuter rail and bus routes, as the current map does. He would like to see a map that is singularly devoted to the subway.</p>
        <p>That map, created in 1979 by Michael Hertz (who was officially credited with the design) and John Tauranac (who was chairman of the map committee), in turn replaced the highly conceptual map created by the Italian graphic designer Massimo Vignelli. Mr. Vignelli's map was aesthetically pleasing but geographically inaccurate; it depicted Central Park as a square rather than the rectangle it is, for example, and offered riders no sense of where they would be once they left a subway station.</p>
        <p>When the current map was adopted, the subway system was decidedly unpopular. The trains were dirty, and riders associated the graffiti-covered cars with crime, often rightly so. Mr. Jabbour sees the current map as tainted by those perceptions. The subways improved dramatically in the 1990s, and in his opinion, the map needs a similarly ambitious face-lift.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jabbour's interest in subway maps began when he studied abroad in London in the mid-1970s while earning a degree in design from Syracuse University. Eager to explore the city and even get lost in it, he immediately recognized how easy it was to navigate the city's Underground. The ''tube'' map, an acknowledged masterpiece in the field, was Mr. Jabbour's main inspiration for his current project.</p>
        <p>HE planned to continue working on a hybrid of the two previous designs until he was satisfied that his mother, ''a woman from the Midwest,'' could read the map. Then, three years ago, Mr. Jabbour briefly acquired a larger audience. His name had been mentioned in a newspaper article about the design of the city's subway map, and his map was posted on foamer blogs like Live From the Third Rail. Hoping to seize the moment, he contacted the Metropolitan Transportation Authority, and to his surprise, designers from the agency agreed to meet with him.</p>
        <p>But when he showed up at the agency's Midtown offices with copies of his work, they were quick to find fault with it. According to Christopher Boylan, the transportation authority's executive director of corporate and community affairs, who recalled the meeting, the main criticism was that Mr. Jabbour's map, like Mr. Vignelli's, was artistic but geographically inaccurate.</p>
        <p>''He's a good designer and it's an interesting map,'' Mr. Boylan said. ''The design is important, but the thing we're concerned with is the best directional guidance. We design a map for use, not solely to look good, and we think it looks good.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Jabbour has since made some adjustments in his map, like removing color-coded neighborhood labels. But he refuses to shelve his project altogether.</p>
        <p>And his map is helping at least a few people navigate the system. He makes copies for anyone who asks, and he says the map is used regularly by his friends, his children and, of course, his mother.</p>
        <p>URBAN TACTICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
