<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Affordable Europe: Rome</title>
    <meta content="22romeweb" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/travel/22romeweb.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842338"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Rome (Italy)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Rome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Rome (Italy)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E0D61631F931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="611" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Affordable Europe: Rome</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Affordable Europe: Rome</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETTA POVOLEDO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rome may be steeped in history -- few other capitals can offer an equivalent array of must-see-sights spanning several millennia -- but prices have kept very much up to date (and in some cases seem to have factored in future inflationary tendencies). Budget travelers may be challenged, but there are still ways to see the city without breaking the bank.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay for Under 125 Euros</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rome may be steeped in history, but prices have kept very much up to date (and in some cases seem to have factored in future inflationary tendencies).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rome may be steeped in history -- few other capitals can offer an equivalent array of must-see-sights spanning several millennia -- but prices have kept very much up to date (and in some cases seem to have factored in future inflationary tendencies). Budget travelers may be challenged, but there are still ways to see the city without breaking the bank.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay for Under 125 Euros</p>
        <p>New hotels have tended to veer toward the high-end market, though several inexpensive bed-and-breakfasts surfaced for the Catholic Church's Jubilee year in 2000. Affordable hotel accommodations are more likely to be found in Rome's suburbs.</p>
        <p>Two recent entrants: the Ibis Roma Magliana (via Arturo Mercanti 63; 39-06 650951; www.ibishotel.com), seven and a half miles from the city center, has doubles that fluctuate from 72 to 92 euros (about $98 to $125 at $1.36 to the euro) depending on the season. Breakfast is an 8 euros a person.</p>
        <p>The Shasa Hotel Roma (via Padre Lino da Parma 1/A; 39-06-4101-633), has doubles for 120 euros, including breakfast, but it too is a hike from downtown (the name, according to its Web site, www.hotelshasa.com, means ''water in the desert''). A list of all accommodations can be found on www.romaturismo.it, run by the Rome tourist board.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat  Do as the Romans: grab a slab of pizza or a panino (sandwich) and find a picturesque spot to plop down (like the marble bench lining the wall of the Palazzo Farnese in the piazza of the same name. Word of warning: pigeons like the overhanging cornice).</p>
        <p>The tasty products at the relatively new Pan Divino (via del Paradiso 39; 39-328-948-1974), a sandwich and tapas eatery close to Piazza Navona, come from the owner's mother and local producers in a small town in the Abruzzi region. Local salamis, cheese and pickled vegetable are the sandwich mainstays, which are priced under 4 euros.</p>
        <p>The Antico Forno Roscioli (via dei Chiavari 34; 39-06-686-4045; www.anticofornoroscioli.com) isn't as ancient as its name implies (it opened in 1972 and was completely renovated in 2007) but it's a local favorite for its pizzas (priced according to slab size) and primi piatti (usually some pasta or gnocchi, tasty potato dumplings), which cost 5 euros. Come armed with patience, it's always crowded at lunchtime.</p>
        <p>Where to Shop  Each Sunday morning, bargain-hunting Romans and the city's new immigrants throng to the Porta Portese flea market in the Trastevere neighborhood, named after the 17th-century archway at one entrance. Many of the stands sell generic dime-store goods or apparel that you could pick up at any mall back home, but there's an antiques section selling everything from rusty brass keys to postcards to antique armoires. Bargains can be had as long as you're prepared to haggle. Watch your valuables: the market is where Rome's pickpockets do their best business when they aren't accidentally bumping up against you on a crowded bus.</p>
        <p>Best Money-saving Tip  Each year during Culture Week -- which this year runs from May 12 to 20 -- entrance is free to Italy's state-owned monuments, museums and archeological sites. In Rome, that includes dozens of top-notch attractions like the Colosseum and the Palatine, and museums with important art collections, like the Palazzo Barberini, the Palazzo Borghese or the Modern and the Contemporary Art Galleries.</p>
        <p>Trambus is the municipal tourist line that runs open-air double-decker buses stopping near many important monuments, from the Colosseum to the Vatican. One line specializes in Christian Rome, another in archeology (this one is especially handy because few normal buses head to the Appian Way). Routes, and prices (for example, an archeological tour costs 8 euros) are featured at www.trambusopen.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
