<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>You Better Watch Out</title>
    <meta content="pappano--bad--behavior" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Education Life Supplement" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/education/pappano.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070422T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842064"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Admissions Standards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Principals (School)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Admissions Standards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Principals (School)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E6DF1F3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1990" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>You Better Watch Out</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Conduct Unbecoming</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Laura Pappano</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pappano, Laura</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE paradox of college admissions is that, just when adolescents must present themselves as dazzlingly brilliant, thoughtful and mature, they are developmentally prone to do stupid things.</p>
        <p>That has always been true. But if stealing test answers, sneaking beers into the prom or posting a parody of your principal on MySpace used to mean taking the punishment and then forgetting about it, that's no longer the case.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Admissions offices are directing a new level of scrutiny at high school missteps.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE paradox of college admissions is that, just when adolescents must present themselves as dazzlingly brilliant, thoughtful and mature, they are developmentally prone to do stupid things.</p>
        <p>That has always been true. But if stealing test answers, sneaking beers into the prom or posting a parody of your principal on MySpace used to mean taking the punishment and then forgetting about it, that's no longer the case.</p>
        <p>It's not enough to face your principal and your parents. Now more colleges want to hear about those missteps, too.</p>
        <p>Admissions officers are directing a new level of scrutiny at student behavior. Elite colleges have always made demands about character. But with admissions offices drowning in applications (some reported double-digit increases this year), many others now have that power, too.</p>
        <p>''We don't want to import students who are immature and who are not going to approach college in a way that is appropriate,'' says Susan E. Donovan, dean of admissions at Syracuse University. This year, she says, her school received a record 20,000 applications for 3,000 freshman spots. ''It isn't any longer about admitting students who would be successful and denying those who wouldn't. It is moving into an area of selecting people who will bring something to your campus and contribute.''</p>
        <p>The Common Application, used by 320 colleges and universities, has added a discipline question for the first time this school year. Under the new rules, students and guidance counselors must disclose if students have been convicted of a crime, including a misdemeanor, or committed a school violation leading to ''probation, suspension, removal, dismissal or expulsion.''</p>
        <p>James M. Sumner, president of the Common Application membership association, says this was one of the most requested changes by members. When given a choice -- the Common App or a college's own forms -- students with discipline histories were using the Common App, he says, because it didn't ask about conduct.</p>
        <p>Colleges are free to ask about a student's run-ins with the law, but in states where juvenile records are either expunged or sealed, students may not be legally required to answer. Melissa Sickmund, a senior research associate at the National Center for Juvenile Justice, points out that unless a minor is charged as an adult and tried in a criminal court, the student can comfortably answer ''no'' to the Common App's conviction question. ''For kids, it is an adjudication,'' she says, not a conviction. Still, Ms. Sickmund says, with MySpace and search engines like Google, admissions officers can easily find out about a student's legal woes and could deny admission on the ground that the student lied on the application.</p>
        <p>Colleges want not only to offer their precious spots to students who are emotionally ready, but also to avoid admitting students who could cause trouble -- or commit a crime -- on campus.</p>
        <p>In February, a student at Boston College was stabbed following a battle with a dorm-mate over access to a dorm clothes dryer. John L. Mahoney, director of undergraduate admissions there, would not comment on the case but says that when there's a problem with a student, he returns to the application to see if anything could have tipped off a reader. ''In most cases, the answer is no,'' he says. Still, he combs applications looking for ''the slightest sign'' of trouble before granting admission.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, he tries to view run-of-the-mill lapses in an ''enlightened'' manner and focus more on what a student claims to have learned from an error rather than the error itself (hint: saying it was the teacher's fault or that everyone was doing it will sink you here). ''A student can't wear a scarlet letter the rest of their life,'' Mr. Mahoney says.</p>
        <p>Such assurances may not be so convincing, given a climate where admissions officers look for clues to differentiate among academically sound candidates. So what really counts as ''bad'' in their minds? Cheating on an exam? Streaking at a football game? Cursing out your teacher?</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, college admissions officers say they consider rule-breaking a more serious matter in junior and senior years than in 9th or 10th grade, because students are supposed to be more mature. They say any arrest raises an alarm. Cheating and plagiarizing, too, cut to the heart of a college's academic mission.</p>
        <p>Alcohol consumption is trickier. There is often a lot of drinking at the homecoming dance, allows Ann Larson, interim director of admissions at Miami University, in Ohio. She might give a nod to a student with a drinking violation who expressed regret and didn't appear to have a substance abuse problem. Still, adds Rob Durkle, director of admissions at the University of Dayton, also in Ohio, binge drinking is a concern on campuses nationwide. Students, he says, ''don't come and learn to drink, they come with proven experiences already.'' In some instances, Dayton admits freshmen with past alcohol violations but may put a strike against them (three alcohol-related strikes in three consecutive semesters draws a year's suspension).</p>
        <p>Complicating the matter is that high schools take different approaches to disciplining students. Steven Roy Goodman, a college admissions consultant in Washington, D.C., says that two seniors he is advising this year attended parties where underage drinking took place. One student was suspended for nearly two weeks, the other for a day or two. A two-week suspension senior year gets the attention of colleges.</p>
        <p>East Grand Rapids High School, a top-performing school in an affluent community in Michigan, is one of those schools ''on the strict side,'' both in disciplining students and in reporting violations to colleges, says Lawrence Fisher, associate principal and director of guidance. With a student body of about 1,000, the school issues 100 violations a year. Possessing or consuming alcohol on school grounds or at a school function will get you two days' suspension (last semester, 23 students were caught). A first offense for drugs, drug paraphernalia or inhalants will get 5 to 10 days (seven perpetrators last semester). Other offenses: swearing or yelling at teachers (nine suspensions), cheating (two) and theft (four). Even smoking on school grounds will get you a one-day suspension. Seniors must report serious discipline violations to colleges within 10 days, even after accepted -- or the school will do it for them.</p>
        <p>''The questions are getting more thorough,'' Mr. Fisher says of colleges' responses to its reports. ''We tell our kids, 'This is the direction colleges are going: They want to know just not who you are academically, but socially.' ''</p>
        <p>As a parent, Mr. Fisher appreciates this. Two years ago, the police burst into his son's dorm room at Central Michigan University and arrested his son's roommate for selling narcotics. ''I was disappointed to get that phone call,'' he says. ''I wasn't interested in him being my son's roommate.''</p>
        <p>HIGH SCHOOLS struggle with the push-pull of disciplining offending students and getting them into top colleges.</p>
        <p>The Common Application includes a section for the counselor, in essay form, to evaluate the student. It asks, for the first time this application season, about the student's discipline history. Some counselors are aggressively recounting wrongdoing, others gloss over it and omit penalty information. Parents, too, have been known to negotiate more favorable punishments for their children, including trying to have violations expunged from records.</p>
        <p>At the Nightingale-Bamford School on the Upper East Side of Manhattan, the most common violation is plagiarism. Like many private schools, Nightingale-Bamford often has a council of peers decide punishment. Plagiarism, for example, might result, for a first or second offense, in an ''F'' on the paper, a required rewrite and some period of social probation, barring the student from leaving campus during free periods. Do it a third time, says Joyce Slayton Mitchell, director of college advising, and you're ''out the door.''</p>
        <p>Her school is quicker than some to discipline, she says, especially for academic infractions. Schools with strict codes may be forced to change how they define rule-breaking, she says. In conversations with advisers at other Manhattan private schools, Ms. Mitchell says, one widely discussed approach has been adjusting what schools call a suspension, a reportable offense on the new Common Application. ''Where we might suspend them this year, next year we might call it in-house something,'' she says. ''We have to be more concerned about the language.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Mitchell, who is also author of ''Winning the Heart of the College Admissions Dean,'' says she plans to tell colleges about only discipline actions that, in her view, would affect how the student performs their first year.</p>
        <p>William Fitzsimmons, the dean of undergraduate admissions and financial aid at Harvard, admits that ''it is a very difficult job for secondary schools because they are under duress.'' But, he adds, ''if they are only willing to tell us good things,'' they do so at their peril. ''When a student comes to a place like Harvard and doesn't perform as advertised, we will go back and take a look at what the schools have said.'' Mr. Fitzsimmons says he calls counselors who write a questionable endorsement. ''Their credibility is on the line and the credibility of the whole school is on the line.''</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Krieg, a history teacher and director of college guidance at the University School of Milwaukee, a private elementary and secondary school, says she's torn, because she knows that her relationships with college admissions officers depends on ''them being able to trust me and me being able to trust them.'' Still, she admits, ''I don't want them to slam a kid because they cheated on a Latin test.''</p>
        <p>This is tender territory. Rob Koppert, director of college counseling at the Dalton School, on the Upper East Side, believes that having to explain a suspension on a college application is a useful experience for the offender.</p>
        <p>''We are counselors, we are not just people aiming to keep the record as clean as possible and be disingenuous about what they have done,'' he says. ''We think they need to take responsibility. If they can show contrition, show that they have learned something, colleges will be fair.''</p>
        <p>In a case that is now playing out in court, Justin Layshock was a senior at Hickory High School in Hermitage, Pa., last year when he posted a parody profile of his principal on MySpace before December break. When school officials confronted him, he admitted having done it. He was given a 10-day suspension and spent six weeks in the alternative education program. Mr. Layshock had been in the gifted program since second grade and earned a 1400 on his SATs.</p>
        <p>His case attracted the support of the American Civil Liberties Union of Pennsylvania, and its legal director, Witold J. Walczak. Because Mr. Layshock created the parody on his grandmother's computer -- not at school -- Mr. Walczak argues that the school violated Mr. Layshock's rights in disciplining him for speech outside of school grounds. A not unsimilar prank, in which a student in Alaska unfurled a ''Bong Hits 4 Jesus'' banner as the Olympic Torch passed, earning a 10-day suspension, got a Supreme Court hearing last month on free-speech issues.</p>
        <p>''The argument we've made is that school officials need to understand that they can't play parents,'' says Mr. Walczak. ''Teenagers do stupid things, that is almost by definition. That doesn't mean they won't grow up to be good students, productive citizens and world leaders.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Layshock had already mailed his application to St. John's University in Queens when he posted the parody and did not think he was obligated to report the incident. When he answered the question honestly on Penn State's application, however, he was told they would not process his application until he had spoken with a college administrator, he says. Ultimately, he was not accepted at the main campus, which he had sought, but at a branch. He chose instead St. John's, where he is now a freshman.</p>
        <p>He doesn't regret owning up. ''I wouldn't have felt right had I not told the truth.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 22, 2007, Sunday  An article on Page 17 of the special Education Life section today about new scrutiny of college applications for discipline violations and criminal convictions went to press before the shootings at Virginia Tech on Monday. An updated version of the article that reflects that event can be found at: nytimes.com/edlife.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 22, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article on Page 17 of the special Education Life section today about new scrutiny of college applications for discipline violations and criminal convictions went to press before the shootings at Virginia Tech on Monday. An updated version of the article that reflects that event can be found at: nytimes.com/edlife.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
