<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lower Manhattan, Higher Testosterone</title>
    <meta content="22downtown" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/22downtown.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842277"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Population</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Population</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE0DF173EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1464" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lower Manhattan, Higher Testosterone</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lower Manhattan, Higher Testosterone</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Sam</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Web site for the William Beaver House in Lower Manhattan, where the cheapest studio apartment now goes for $950,000, features a photograph of two women seductively nibbling corn on the cob. A biography of the building's mythical mascot, a martini-toting beaver-about-town, reveals that he hangs out ''where life is sleek and times are thrilling.''</p>
        <p>The sales pitch for the 47-story building, going up at the corner of William and Beaver Streets across from Delmonico's, is unabashedly capitalizing on, and perhaps perpetuating, a phenomenal population shift downtown. Men now outnumber women there by a ratio usually found in towns with all-male colleges, military bases and prisons, and in a few enclaves in Silicon Valley that have high concentrations of engineers and workers in other male-dominated fields.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Men now outnumber women in Lower Manhattan by a ratio usually found in towns with all-male colleges, military bases and prisons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Web site for the William Beaver House in Lower Manhattan, where the cheapest studio apartment now goes for $950,000, features a photograph of two women seductively nibbling corn on the cob. A biography of the building's mythical mascot, a martini-toting beaver-about-town, reveals that he hangs out ''where life is sleek and times are thrilling.''</p>
        <p>The sales pitch for the 47-story building, going up at the corner of William and Beaver Streets across from Delmonico's, is unabashedly capitalizing on, and perhaps perpetuating, a phenomenal population shift downtown. Men now outnumber women there by a ratio usually found in towns with all-male colleges, military bases and prisons, and in a few enclaves in Silicon Valley that have high concentrations of engineers and workers in other male-dominated fields.</p>
        <p>Since 2000, men, mostly between ages 25 and 44, have accounted for more than three-fourths of the population increase in Lower Manhattan. As a result, according to a special census calculation, the sex ratio there increased to 126 men per 100 women in 2005, from 101 men per 100 women in 2000. In the rest of Manhattan, and in the city over all, there were only 90 men for every 100 women.</p>
        <p>''For a normal, noninstitutional setting,'' said A. Peter Lobo, deputy director of the City Planning Department's population division, ''I would say it is among the highest sex ratios that you would see.''</p>
        <p>The census survey, coupled with interviews last week, suggests that what has driven the shift is an influx of well-heeled workaholics on male-dominated Wall Street who prefer short commutes. Nearly one-third of the residents said they walked to work.</p>
        <p>''We're seeing a lot of young professionals with very high income, young Wall Street bankers and lawyers who want to be steps from home,'' said Eric J. Deutsch, president of the Alliance for Downtown New York, a business group. ''It's still a bit of a pioneering neighborhood, and in a pioneering neighborhood you often see more single men and young couples.''</p>
        <p>The statistics come from a Census Bureau analysis of its 2005 American Community Survey that was commissioned by Planning Department demographers seeking to quantify changes to Lower Manhattan since 9/11. The demographers presented the findings last month to the Population Association of America.</p>
        <p>Because they commissioned a special tabulation, precise comparisons with other areas are difficult.</p>
        <p>The demographers eliminated group quarters like New York University and Pace University dormitories from their calculations and had to make adjustments to compare the 2000 census with the 2005 American Community Survey, but said they were confident that the samples were representative.</p>
        <p>The area studied encompassed the neighborhoods south of Canal Street, but excluded most of east Chinatown and the area between the Manhattan and Brooklyn Bridges. The area does not include neighborhoods like Chelsea and others known for high populations of gay men.</p>
        <p>''I always thought downtown had a high testosterone level, but this ratio is a surprise even to me,'' said Carl Weisbrod, Mr. Deutsch's predecessor at the Downtown Alliance and now president of Trinity Real Estate.</p>
        <p>The male majority in Lower Manhattan is even more striking considering the city's overall tilt toward women. In some neighborhoods, the ratio can be as low as 70 men to 100 women. And it is even lower in places like East New York and Brownsville in Brooklyn -- a result, researchers say, of a high incidence of murder, imprisonment, unemployment and homelessness -- and in the Rockaways, which includes neighborhoods where residents are mostly poor and others where they are disproportionately elderly.</p>
        <p>Downtown Manhattan has thrived in spite of the terrorist attack, in part because of the city's healthy financial sector and government and private subsidies to encourage people to move there after 9/11.</p>
        <p>New buildings like the William Beaver have gone up, and some office buildings have been converted to luxury residences. The number of residents in the neighborhoods studied by the city demographers surged 26 percent, to 43,650 in 2005 compared with 34,698 in 2000, according to the Census Bureau.</p>
        <p>But despite its central location, as a neighborhood, Lower Manhattan can still seem like an outpost, with fewer shopping and after-hours options than in other well-to-do parts of the city. Workers outnumber residents there 8 to 1.</p>
        <p>''I think that men may be a bit more prepared to move into a weird, slowly developing neighborhood than women are,'' said Marcus Friedman, 25, who moved downtown last fall after graduating from Brooklyn Law School. ''I know that neither me nor my roommates put a large premium on the restaurants and nightlife in the area, as we all work terrible hours, and when we go out we don't go out downtown. We value how spacious our apartment is, the amenities of our building and the excellent subway accessibility -- I work off of Times Square.</p>
        <p>''I don't mean to generalize,'' Mr. Friedman said, ''but most of the girls I am cool with have a bit more vested in their neighborhood than commute and apartment size. They would rather sacrifice one or the other to have the restaurants and bar scene that they want close by.''</p>
        <p>Lower Manhattan bars are crowded early in the evening, but they often empty out as workers head home to other parts of the city or the suburbs. Puffy's Tavern on Hudson Street began a happy hour to attract patrons with discount drinks -- from 1 to 4 a.m.</p>
        <p>Matthew Carpenter, a 38-year-old technology manager who lives in a loft on Thompson Street, agreed that ''a lot of women don't want to work the 80-hour week, so being close to work is not that important.''</p>
        <p>Wilson Lau, 32, a sales representative for a biotechnology company who lives on Nassau Street, said that he was not aware of the gender gap, but he had noticed a proliferation of cigar bars. ''I think men don't mind that there is nothing going on around in the area after 7 p.m., where women may find that more intimidating or less safe,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Susan Naci, who sells advertising for a magazine and lives in TriBeCa with her husband, said men seemed less sensitive about living close to the World Trade Center site. ''I tell my single girlfriends all the time to go out for drinks in my neighborhood because it's where all those rumored-to-exist eligible bachelors are,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Leah Hyman, who is 43 and works as a hospital volunteer, expressed a ''sort of pride'' that she lives near ground zero, adding: ''Is the preponderance of young men good or bad for women? As a single woman, I guess I should say yes -- but I need to get out more.''</p>
        <p>Generalizations are hazardous, and downtown neighborhoods are still evolving. But it is probably fair to say that families with children tend to gravitate toward Battery Park City, couples to TriBeCa and single young men to the Financial District.</p>
        <p>Even so, said Whitney G. Hess, a 24-year old designer, ''Everyone I know living below Canal Street is a woman. We all agree that we're somewhat isolated from the rest of the city, but we like it that way. The neighborhood is quiet and empty on the weeknights, but there is a lot of activity on the weekends.''</p>
        <p>By next year, according to estimates by the Alliance for Downtown New York, the number of apartments south of Chambers Street will have doubled, to 26,000, since 2000, and more than twice as many people, 46,000, will be living there.</p>
        <p>The city demographers who conducted the research, Mr. Lobo, Joseph J. Salvo and Joel A. Alvarez, said that as a result of a 46 percent surge in men 25 to 44 years old, that category's share of the downtown population grew to 51 percent in 2005 from 44 percent in 2000.</p>
        <p>They found disproportionate numbers of white, Asian and foreign-born residents. People living downtown also were more likely than other Manhattanites to have roommates who were not family members. The median household income, which jumped 20 percent from 2000 to 2005, was $98,000 -- nearly double the figure for the rest of the borough.</p>
        <p>While the number of workers in Lower Manhattan declined after 9/11, the study said it appeared that new residents continued to arrive. In 2005, 22 percent of residents there said they had been living in another apartment just one year earlier.</p>
        <p>Andrew Hacker, a political scientist at Queens College who wrote ''Mismatch: The Growing Gulf Between Men and Women,'' said that demographically speaking, ''a jump from 101 to 126 guys per 100 girls in only five years is hyper-unusual. You generally only get that kind of population leap in super-booming Arizona suburbs.</p>
        <p>''Of course,'' he added, ''New York women will tell you that, to them, it looks like 200 of them for every 100 men. But, then, they mean 'eligible' men.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
