<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>He Was Lost, And Now Reds Have Quite a Find</title>
    <meta content="22chass" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/sports/baseball/22chass.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842282"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cincinnati Reds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Cincinnati Reds</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hamilton, Josh</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEFDF173EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1648" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>He Was Lost, And Now Reds Have Quite a Find</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">He Was Lost, and Now Reds Have Quite a Find</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alex Rodriguez may have to break Barry Bonds's single-season home run record for baseball to have a more remarkable story this year than Josh Hamilton.</p>
        <p>Hamilton, a rookie, has moved into Cincinnati's starting lineup and has become the Reds' top hitter. He is batting .294 with 5 home runs and 11 runs batted in, leading the Reds in the last two categories even though he did not start a game until April 10, the eighth game of the season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cincinnati’s Josh Hamilton missed three entire seasons, 2003 through 2005, because of drug addiction. Now, he’s leading the team in batting average, home runs, and runs batted in.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Alex Rodriguez may have to break Barry Bonds's single-season home run record for baseball to have a more remarkable story this year than Josh Hamilton.</p>
        <p>Hamilton, a rookie, has moved into Cincinnati's starting lineup and has become the Reds' top hitter. He is batting .294 with 5 home runs and 11 runs batted in, leading the Reds in the last two categories even though he did not start a game until April 10, the eighth game of the season.</p>
        <p>The left-handed Hamilton hit a home run that day and another the next, then hit three more in the four games before the weekend.</p>
        <p>His performance would be impressive enough if he were an ordinary rookie, but Hamilton is proving himself in the major leagues after virtually not playing the previous four years. He missed three entire seasons, 2003 through 2005, and played in only 15 games at the Class A level last season.</p>
        <p>''He's one of the more talented guys in all of baseball,'' said Jerry Narron, the Reds' manager. ''He can throw, run, hit, hit with power. The amazing thing is he's missed three years, almost four, and he shows the plate discipline he does. He doesn't chase pitches out of the strike zone. And he has tremendous bat speed.''</p>
        <p>How does a hitter retain his bat speed while not playing for nearly four years?</p>
        <p>''I don't know,'' said Narron, a .211 hitter as a major league catcher. ''Who knows? Maybe he's lost some, but he still has a lot.''</p>
        <p>If the manager is impressed with the 25-year-old Hamilton's hitting ability, he is even more impressed with his attitude.</p>
        <p>''He's fully accountable for his past,'' Narron said. ''He makes no excuses. He regrets it and he'd like to help people in similar situations.''</p>
        <p>Hamilton missed all of those seasons because of drug addiction. He was the first player selected in the 1999 amateur draft (by Tampa Bay), but injuries and addiction undermined his progress. Major League Baseball suspended him indefinitely in February 2004, and he wasn't reinstated until last June.</p>
        <p>Although he remained a member of the Tampa Bay organization, the Devil Rays opted not to put him on their 40-man roster and prevent another team from taking him in the minor league draft last December. Who would draft a drug addict who had hardly played in years?</p>
        <p>The Reds credit Chris Buckley, their senior director of amateur scouting, for suggesting they take a chance on Hamilton.</p>
        <p>''Chris Buckley, who had followed him as an amateur, brought him to our attention,'' General Manager Wayne Krivsky said. ''Other scouts did a lot of background work.''</p>
        <p>Scott Nethery, the Reds' assistant general manager and senior director of pro scouting, recommended that the Reds elevate their position in the draft.</p>
        <p>''The Cubs were offering the third pick to anyone interested,'' Krivsky said. ''We decided to eliminate the risk instead of waiting for the 15th pick. We felt with his upside, if he had his life together, it was well worth the gamble based on the raw ability he showed over the years.''</p>
        <p>The night before the draft, after he made a deal with the Cubs, Krivsky told Narron what he had done.</p>
        <p>''His jaw dropped,'' Krivsky said. ''Little did I know that Jerry had seen him play as a kid and that his brother coached him. The day after the draft, Jerry had lunch with him and was throwing batting practice to him.''</p>
        <p>Narron's brother Johnny coached Hamilton in North Carolina 10 years ago and once asked Jerry to watch him play. Now Narron watches him play every day.</p>
        <p>Hamilton started the season on the bench but hit his way into a starting outfield spot. ''We've got four outfielders; Josh is one of them,'' Narron said. ''I'm doing what I can do to get them all playing time.''</p>
        <p>Asked if he was concerned about the possibility of Hamilton slipping, Narron said: ''I think with anyone who's been an addict of any kind, it's a day-by-day deal. I know he has his priorities right. He loves to play. He's a spiritual person. He's given himself over to the Lord.''</p>
        <p>A Tale of Two Rookies</p>
        <p>Alberto Callaspo has picked up where he left off last season, but Alex Gordon hasn't. Callaspo and Gordon are rookies: Callaspo with Arizona, Gordon with Kansas City.</p>
        <p>Gordon batted. 325 last season, his first as a professional, with 29 home runs and 101 R.B.I. while playing for Wichita of the Class AA Texas League. As the only player to win college player and minor league player of the year awards in successive seasons, the 23-year-old Gordon surprised no one by winning the Royals' third-base job this spring.</p>
        <p>But he has struggled in his first season in the majors, batting .145 with two home runs and four R.B.I. in 15 games. He has struck out 19 times in 55 at-bats.</p>
        <p>Curiously, though, he was ahead of his 2006 production in another category. He had been hit with a pitch a league-leading four times, or once every 12 at-bats. Last season, he was hit once every 30 at-bats.</p>
        <p>Callaspo, a 24-year-old switch-hitter, batted .265 while playing in 17 of the Diamondbacks' first 18 games, but that's not how he picked up where he left off. He picked up where he left off by playing multiple positions, but he has also expanded his repertory.</p>
        <p>Last year, the versatile Callaspo, a Venezuelan, started three games at second base and three at shortstop. He also played parts of two games at third base. This season he has started three games at short, one at third and six in right field.</p>
        <p>Teams Pitching Around Bonds Again</p>
        <p>The way teams pitched Barry Bonds in early games, it seemed that the walk strategy that had prevailed for four years had changed. Bonds, who hit his 739th homer yesterday, drew only six walks in his first 36 plate appearances, or 16.7 percent of the time, compared with 23.3 percent last season and 37.6 percent in 2004 (injuries limited Bonds to 52 plate appearances in 2005).</p>
        <p>In his last four games before yesterday, Bonds walked five times in 16 plate appearances, raising his season percentage to 21.2.</p>
        <p>The St. Louis Cardinals wish they had walked Bonds in the eighth inning last Wednesday. Ryan Franklin didn't walk him, and he hit a home run that tied the score. The Giants won in the 12th.</p>
        <p>Sosa Still Has Pop, but Average Lags</p>
        <p>With four home runs in his first 14 games with Texas, Sammy Sosa has demonstrated that he can still hit the long ball after a year's hiatus. But can he hit?</p>
        <p>Sosa, who batted .221 for Baltimore in 2005, entered yesterday hitting .204, but .140 (7 for 50) when he didn't hit a home run. The 38-year-old Sosa has struck out 11 times. For now, the Rangers will take the home runs and wait for other hits to follow.</p>
        <p>The Perils of Pitching</p>
        <p>Pitching can be detrimental to your health. Félix Hernández of Seattle learned that last week. Francisco Liriano learned it last September.</p>
        <p>In the space of 37 playing days, two of the best young pitchers to come to the majors in years sustained elbow injuries. Hernández, 21, was more fortunate than Liriano, 23, who needed ligament transplant surgery and will miss the season.</p>
        <p>The Mariners' medical team diagnosed Hernández's injury as a muscle strain in his elbow and forearm. They expect him to miss two or three starts.</p>
        <p>Trading Diamonds for the Diamond</p>
        <p>When Jeff Mor sneaks away from work to play baseball this summer, he won't be jeopardizing his job. He is self-employed. But for his love of the game, Mor will sacrifice a great percentage of his income during the 10-week inaugural season of the Israel Baseball League.</p>
        <p>Mor is a diamond dealer who regularly travels to the United States for two-week periods, selling diamonds he buys in Israel to other dealers and retailstores.</p>
        <p>''Playing in this league could very easily cost me in the tens of thousands of dollars,'' said Mor, a 36-year-old pitcher. ''I will suffer financially. My business will probably suffer over those two and a half months because I'll have to postpone those trips.''</p>
        <p>But ''it's not about the money,'' said Mor, whose baseball salary will be $2,000. ''Financially, it may be a negative thing for me, but you only live once and this is a big opportunity for me. It's such a thrill to be part of an historical new league. I'm not doing it for the money. I would have played for free. Baseball is a big part of my life.''</p>
        <p>And alluding to another part of his life, Mor said, ''I might be one of the first Orthodox Jews to be paid for playing baseball.''</p>
        <p>Mor, who immigrated to Israel 10 years ago, grew up in Queens, playing baseball and serving as captain of his high school softball team. In Israel, he played shortstop on the Israeli national softball team for seven years. Then came his unexpected return to baseball.</p>
        <p>''When I heard about these tryouts, I gave it a shot,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Dan Duquette, a former major league general manager and the league's director of baseball operations, watched Mor throw and a week later sent him an e-mail message telling him he had won a job as a pitcher.</p>
        <p>''I also hope to play middle infield on days when I don't pitch because I still have my defensive skills from my softball experience,'' Mor said.</p>
        <p>A resident of Bet Shemesh, a town about midway between Jerusalem and Tel Aviv, Mor will play for the Bet Shemesh Blue Sox, who will be managed by Ron Blomberg.</p>
        <p>''It's great for me,'' Mor said, ''and it's good for attendance. People have told me to let them know when I'm pitching. They said they want to come to the game.''</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
