<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Surviving a Week of Loss, And Still Having Lunch</title>
    <meta content="22lunch" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/22lunch.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842276"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Society</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Society</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Hart, Kitty Carlisle</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E0DF173EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="804" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Surviving a Week of Loss, And Still Having Lunch</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Surviving a Week of Loss, and Still Having Lunch</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC KONIGSBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Konigsberg, Eric</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As she was finishing lunch on Thursday at Swifty's, a restaurant on Lexington Avenue that functions as the clubhouse for a certain type of old-fashioned, Upper East Side woman, Lee Copley Thaw took a moment to consider the question, and then another moment.</p>
        <p>It had to do with ladies who lunch, a breed already bordering on extinction for something like 25 years. What did it mean for the fate of the whole class that two of New York society's pre-eminent women, Pat Buckley and Kitty Carlisle Hart, had passed away in the past week? Mrs. Thaw, who has been a prominent Park Avenue hostess and philanthropist for decades, was too polite to say so, but it seemed as if the question struck her as impolite.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>What did it mean for the fate of ladies who lunch that two of New York society’s pre-eminent women passed away in the past week?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As she was finishing lunch on Thursday at Swifty's, a restaurant on Lexington Avenue that functions as the clubhouse for a certain type of old-fashioned, Upper East Side woman, Lee Copley Thaw took a moment to consider the question, and then another moment.</p>
        <p>It had to do with ladies who lunch, a breed already bordering on extinction for something like 25 years. What did it mean for the fate of the whole class that two of New York society's pre-eminent women, Pat Buckley and Kitty Carlisle Hart, had passed away in the past week? Mrs. Thaw, who has been a prominent Park Avenue hostess and philanthropist for decades, was too polite to say so, but it seemed as if the question struck her as impolite.</p>
        <p>''None of us knows what we mean when we say society women,'' Mrs. Thaw, a friend of both Mrs. Buckley and Mrs. Hart, began, before starting over: ''There are all these young society beauties now.'' She turned her attention to Mrs. Buckley. ''She had a great elegance and prestige. You could say that she was almost a model of the lady of society.''</p>
        <p>In the last week, regulars at Swifty's have arrived for lunch -- and dinner -- to greet one another somberly, said a co-owner, Robert Caravaggi, who also was maître d'hôtel at the late Mortimer's, the true capital of Lunchland. ''They say, 'We lost another great lady,' '' he said.</p>
        <p>Some clarification may be in order: Kitty Carlisle Hart, who lived to see her 96th birthday, may have been a grande dame -- not to mention a doyenne -- but she herself wasn't a lady who lunched.</p>
        <p>''Kitty Carlisle was friends with them, but she was not at that lunch table,'' Elaine Stritch said over the phone from her apartment in the Carlyle Hotel. Ms. Stritch, of course, performed the song ''The Ladies Who Lunch'' in the original Broadway production of ''Company,'' in 1970. ''Kitty was a performer. She was working on numbers all the time. She was a lady who had coffee.''</p>
        <p>Stephen Sondheim, who wrote the song, said in an interview that his mother, a dress designer who often had lunch at Jack and Charlie's ''21'' (now the ''21'' Club), was the inspiration for it. ''I was just trying to describe the class my mother had some sense of belonging to,'' he said. ''My mother was not an idle lady, but she had friends who were these kinds of do-gooder, charitable-work-supporting ladies for whom lunch was a major event of the day.''</p>
        <p>Back then, in the '40s, the very notion of going out to lunch signified a leisure class ethic, Mr. Sondheim said. ''My father went to the '21' Club, but only for dinner,'' he said. ''I associate the word 'lunch' with women, hats and large menus. It really does mean something different today.</p>
        <p>''With the revival of 'Company' last year, I wonder if the audiences understood what I was talking about when the song was performed,'' he added. ''I think when people hear the word lunch, they think of C.E.O.'s.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Stritch, for her part, said extinction was unlikely. ''Oh, you can't say that, because I may sing that song again,'' she said. ''There will always be ladies who lunch. Always. And apparently they live a long time.''</p>
        <p>And not all of the song's lyrics, she pointed out, sound dated. ''Stephen Sondheim talks about them rushing around to pick up their kids,'' she noted -- ''The ones who follow the rules/ And meet themselves at the schools/ Too busy to know they're fools'' -- and working out: ''Off to the gym/ then to a fitting/ Claiming they're fat.  I'll drink to that.''</p>
        <p>''These women are everywhere still,'' Ms. Stritch said.</p>
        <p>Ann Slater, who showed up at Swifty's for lunch on Friday, said she counted both Mrs. Buckley and Mrs. Hart as ''dear, dear friends.'' She added, ''It's a shame they had to go at the same time.'' Then a favorite memory sprang to mind.</p>
        <p>''A couple of years ago I was at Yue-Sai Kan's,'' Mrs. Slater began, referring to the Chinese business tycoon. ''And Kitty was there, and I said to Bobby Short: 'Isn't Kitty beautiful? Look at her legs.' And Bobby said, 'The legs are the last to go.' ''</p>
        <p>The members of the old guard -- Mrs. Thaw and Mrs. Slater, along with Carroll Petrie and Judy Peabody, are still regulars at Swifty's, Mr. Caravaggi said -- are unpretentious. Mrs. Thaw, for instance, had on what appeared to be a Chanel suit and a gold butterfly brooch during lunch on Thursday, but she headed into the cool afternoon holding a $5 drugstore umbrella.</p>
        <p>Mr. Caravaggi volunteered that no socially prominent woman worth her caftan would actually see herself through the party-page lens.</p>
        <p>''It trivializes them,'' he said. ''Only a wannabe would call her friend a socialite.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
