<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fine Art, Shabby Package? Not in This State, Please</title>
    <meta content="22topicctCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/22topicct.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842029"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSEUMS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hughes, C J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E1D61E3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="566" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fine Art, Shabby Package? Not in This State, Please</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Fine Art, Shabby Package? Not in This State, Please</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C. J. HUGHES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hughes, C J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on restoration and upgrades planned or already under way at several art museums around Connecticut; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TIME was, a dim, cramped room was a perfectly fine place to appreciate the beauty of a Great Master's oil painting. Now, though, there's a growing expectation that the packaging -- as in the buildings that house the galleries -- should be on par artistically with its contents, according to museum directors, business analysts and architects.</p>
        <p>As a result, the state's museums have become larger, cleaner and more stylish -- an emphasis that signals more fundamental economic changes to come.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There’s a growing expectation that the buildings that house galleries should be on par artistically with the art inside.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TIME was, a dim, cramped room was a perfectly fine place to appreciate the beauty of a Great Master's oil painting. Now, though, there's a growing expectation that the packaging -- as in the buildings that house the galleries -- should be on par artistically with its contents, according to museum directors, business analysts and architects.</p>
        <p>As a result, the state's museums have become larger, cleaner and more stylish -- an emphasis that signals more fundamental economic changes to come.</p>
        <p>''Connecticut's no longer an insurance capital or a place where guns are manufactured,'' said William N. Goetzmann, a professor at the Yale School of Management who lectures on business and art and who was the director of the Museum of Western Art in Denver in the 1980s. ''So, we're looking to history and culture to define the state.''</p>
        <p>The $44 million restoration of the Yale University Art Gallery in New Haven, to better honor Louis I. Kahn's original design, is probably the state's most talked-about upgrade. Yet other renovations are equally ambitious, as in Hartford, where the Wadsworth Atheneum recently announced plans to take over the former home of The Hartford Times, which it has leased from the city.</p>
        <p>The neoclassical terra cotta 1920 building, whose facade features six tall columns, looms on Prospect Street, across the street from the Atheneum's current facility.</p>
        <p>Conversion of the now-empty building, which will begin in the late spring, will cost $15 million, said David Baxter, project director, who added that it is the museum's first expansion since 1969.</p>
        <p>When completed in the fall of 2008, the museum will have added 54,000 square feet, Mr. Baxter said. ''It's a fantastic opportunity that allows us to smartly address our most pressing need -- space,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Putting more people on the streets could also spur the neighborhood's continuing revitalization, an ancillary benefit realized by other midsize cities that are increasingly using museums as tools for urban revival, city leaders said.</p>
        <p>Since the New Britain Museum of American Art opened a 43,000-square-foot wing a year ago, attendance has more than doubled, with 70,000 people coming to admire its collection, which includes many Hudson River School paintings, said Paula Bender, a spokeswoman.</p>
        <p>Earlier this month, a complex of classrooms, studios and a library opened in the museum's former galleries, a 23,000-square-foot former mansion next door.</p>
        <p>''The changes are opening up the museum to a whole new group of people, and they're stopping here for lunch or dinner,'' said Donald A. Courtemanche, director of the New Britain Downtown District, which has worked to attract tourists since 1983.</p>
        <p>In the past, not-for-profit building booms were tied to Wall Street booms, and now, with state and federal funds all but dried up, banking money is footing an even greater share of the bills, museum directors said.</p>
        <p>To finance an imminent addition to its facility, Greenwich's Bruce Museum, for example, is likely to hit up the numerous hedge-fund firms located just blocks away, said its executive director, Peter C. Sutton.</p>
        <p>Although the museum measures 28,000 square feet, only about a quarter of that contains galleries, and with 100,000 visitors a year, those rooms can get crowded, Mr. Sutton said.</p>
        <p>When the time comes to raise funds for the multimillion-dollar project, Mr. Sutton is confident the community support will be there.</p>
        <p>''Opera, ballet and symphonies may be struggling,'' he said, ''but museums seem to be holding their own.''</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
