<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>IN THE REGION/New Jersey; Both Ultramodern and Dated</title>
    <meta content="22njzo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/realestate/22njzo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842124"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="In the Region | New Jersey"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lofts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jersey City (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martin, Antoinette</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Lofts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lofts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E2D91F3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="942" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>IN THE REGION/New Jersey; Both Ultramodern and Dated</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Both Ultramodern and Dated</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTOINETTE MARTIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Martin, Antoinette</byline>
      <dateline>JERSEY CITY</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former American Can Company factory building in Jersey City, NJ, is undergoing conversion into CanCo Lofts, offering more than 500 condominium lofts preserving best of structure's classic factory elements like soaring ceilings and interior columns; units are priced from high $200,000s to upper $600,000s and some will be ready for occupancy by fall 2007; photos (In the Region/New Jersey) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE American Can Company factory building here -- which was the birthplace of the modern American beer can -- is undergoing conversion into more than 500 condominium lofts that will retain a distinct industrial flavor, spiked with ultramodernity.</p>
        <p>The new condos will have a look that is both retro and sleek, according to architects from SBLM of Manhattan, the company hired by the developer, Coalco New York, to transform the million-square-foot Art Deco-era industrial building.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The American Can Company factory building is undergoing conversion into more than 500 condominium lofts that will retain a distinct industrial flavor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE American Can Company factory building here -- which was the birthplace of the modern American beer can -- is undergoing conversion into more than 500 condominium lofts that will retain a distinct industrial flavor, spiked with ultramodernity.</p>
        <p>The new condos will have a look that is both retro and sleek, according to architects from SBLM of Manhattan, the company hired by the developer, Coalco New York, to transform the million-square-foot Art Deco-era industrial building.</p>
        <p>Its classic factory elements, like ceilings that soar up to 24 feet and concrete columns as big around as giant redwoods, will be set off by white-lacquered kitchen cabinetry, wide-plank white-oak flooring and stone countertops in every unit, said David Nicholson of SBLM.</p>
        <p>''It has been quite fascinating working on an adaptive reuse like this,'' Mr. Nicholson said. ''The building has such strong character of its own, and we are trying to play to that, honor that, while at the same time going to the cutting edge with the apartment designs.''</p>
        <p>A separate architecture firm, LOT-EK of Manhattan, was hired to create a ''destination'' lobby at the condominium project, called CanCo Lofts. It has come up with a startling low-tech-high-tech design that combines stacked lumber used as benches and ''ceiling sculptures''; a wall decorated with industrial piping; extensive glass; and two dozen plasma television screens that will show live scenes of the Manhattan skyline as well as community news flashes.</p>
        <p>''This wall will truly be a spectacle,'' said Giuseppe Ligano of LOT-EK, describing the wall of piping as reminiscent of a Chinese screen. It will be lighted from behind so that from across the room the piping appears as stripes on an interior wall.</p>
        <p>The TV screens mounted on the wall may be viewed as art in addition to their role as instruments of communication, Mr. Ligano said. ''For one thing, they can be used creatively to repeat the view of New York, so that it seems to be everywhere in the room, or splitting it into fragments so the screens make a whole 'painting' or to produce a panorama.''</p>
        <p>In addition, five ''conversation areas'' will be created around the lumber benches, whose seating section will be wrapped in leather. The lobby will also have a mailroom, with desks for opening mail.</p>
        <p>The CanCo building is a natural haven for commuters -- nine blocks from Journal Square and a PATH station, from which passengers can reach Wall Street in less than 15 minutes. So the screens will also constantly report on weather and traffic, said Edward Yorukoff, marketing director of Coalco New York, a division of Coalco International, a diversified development company based in Russia.</p>
        <p>Coalco will open sales next month on the first 100 loft units. Construction has begun after a long phase of environmental cleanup at the property and completion of a sales lobby and model kitchens, baths and a loft space, Mr. Yorukoff said.</p>
        <p>One-, two- and three-bedroom units will be offered at prices ranging from the high $200,000s to the upper $600,000s, Mr. Yorukoff said. The apartments come with garage parking, numerous amenities and shuttle service to the PATH train.</p>
        <p>The first residents could move in by the end of the year, he said.</p>
        <p>The building, which was shut down as a can factory in the 1970s and has mostly been empty since then, is a local landmark. With its five towers, tall smokestacks and stone Deco details, the brick structure is part of a historic industrial district established by the city.</p>
        <p>The developers have picked up on the theme with a piece of artwork installed inside the sales lobby's front door: a wall-hung sculpture composed of paint cans of a type once manufactured on the site.</p>
        <p>The building's facade will be completely renovated, according to Coalco's president, Mikhail Kurnev.</p>
        <p>The lofts will be designed to be exceptionally large and roomy, he said, with period 14-foot ceilings -- 17 feet to 24 feet on upper floors -- and eight-foot-high doors, plus the oversize windows typical of old factories. The baths will have oversize showers and soaking tubs, glass mosaic tile on the walls and cove lighting.</p>
        <p>A 10,000-square-foot residents' club will feature a large fitness center, a yoga and Pilates studio and a half court for basketball. In addition, the community will offer a children's play center, screening room, pet park and pet spa, game room for billiards and video games and an event room with an outside terrace.</p>
        <p>The building's basement, formerly a rail station, will become a residents' parking garage, accessible by elevator, Mr. Kurnev said.</p>
        <p>LOT-EK, the lobby designer, is also designing a garden area outside the lobby, which will have a glass wall on the garden side. Although the setting for CanCo Lofts, situated at 50 Dey Street just off the clogged traffic artery of Tonnelle Road, is highly urban, the building is designed to offer a calm oasis to its residents, the developer said.</p>
        <p>From upper floors, the views of Manhattan and the NewJersey coast and, westward, of towns perched on rolling hills are extraordinary. From the now-gutted upper floors of one of the towers -- empty save for concrete support columns 12 feet in circumference -- the full 360-degree panorama is available.</p>
        <p>''It's a good time to shop for the view you might like to own,'' said Mr. Yorukoff, who added that prospective buyers would be allowed to take a look, if willing to don a hard hat.</p>
        <p>He said he expected the lofts to be most attractive to buyers in their 20s and 30s, probably with no children or only a toddler, who might want to use the loft space in their units as either work space or spare bedrooms.</p>
        <p>In the Region | New Jersey</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
