<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Picking Up the Pieces as the Floodwaters Subside</title>
    <meta content="22floodnjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/22floodnj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842105"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Codey, Richard J (Acting Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holl, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Emergency Management Agency</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E4DA1F3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="577" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Picking Up the Pieces as the Floodwaters Subside</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Picking Up the Pieces as the Floodwaters Subside</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN HOLL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holl, John</byline>
      <dateline>MANVILLE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Acting New Jersey Gov Richard Cody declares state of emergency after northeaster deluges region with more than nine inches of rain, causes hundreds of millions of dollars in damages and kills at least three people; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CALLING the flooding from last Sunday's storm among the worst in the state's history, Acting Gov. Richard J. Codey said the northeaster that deluged the region with more than nine inches of rain caused hundreds of millions of dollars in damage and killed at least three people.</p>
        <p>Mr. Codey declared a state of emergency on Monday as many of the state's major rivers began to flood their banks, in some cases causing devastating damage, particularly in Passaic and Bergen Counties and parts of Somerset County.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Acting Gov. Richard J. Codey of New Jersey said the storm that deluged the region with more than nine inches of rain caused hundreds of millions of dollars in damage and killed at least three people.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CALLING the flooding from last Sunday's storm among the worst in the state's history, Acting Gov. Richard J. Codey said the northeaster that deluged the region with more than nine inches of rain caused hundreds of millions of dollars in damage and killed at least three people.</p>
        <p>Mr. Codey declared a state of emergency on Monday as many of the state's major rivers began to flood their banks, in some cases causing devastating damage, particularly in Passaic and Bergen Counties and parts of Somerset County.</p>
        <p>''New Jersey clearly has received the brunt of this storm. We were in the middle of the bull's-eye,'' Mr. Codey said after an aerial tour of flooded areas on Wednesday afternoon. ''It wasn't localized. It was all over the state. Whether you were up north or south or central, you got hit, and you got hit hard, and it just wouldn't let up.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Codey has sent a letter to President Bush requesting federal aid, and representatives of the Federal Emergency Management Agency started to tour the state on Thursday afternoon to assess the damage, a process that was expected to take several days.</p>
        <p>At least three people died as a result of the storm. Niranjankumar Soni, 52, of Edison, was trapped in his car in a flooded underpass in Woodbridge. The police found Nicholas Pennucci, 79, of Bloomfield, drowned near his flooded-out car on Main Street in Belleville. And on Wednesday, the Mahwah police retrieved the body of Mary Pat Wagner, 44; she had been missing since Sunday and was believed to have accidentally driven into the Ramapo River.</p>
        <p>The New Jersey State Police said that 3,300 people had been evacuated from their homes, mainly in Passaic and Somerset Counties; most had not been permitted to return as of Thursday afternoon, with the exception of those living in Manville, in Somerset County. The state police also set up a special hot line -- 211 -- to provide safety tips and information for flood victims about insurance and financial assistance.</p>
        <p>In Manville, which is surrounded by the Raritan and Millstone Rivers, both rivers crested above the flood stage, submerging the downtown under nearly 10 feet of water. More than 600 houses were affected, making the town accessible only by boat for three days, said Mayor Angelo Corradino.</p>
        <p>By Thursday the water had receded and the cleanup had begun. Mr. Corradino said the town had suffered about $13 million in damage.</p>
        <p>The Passaic River began to rise above flood stage on Monday night, state officials said, and by Tuesday had flooded significant portions of Little Falls, Paterson and West Paterson, affecting hundreds of homes.</p>
        <p>The storm caused major delays on New Jersey Transit bus and train lines and at the local airports, including Teterboro, which was closed for two days after its runways flooded.</p>
        <p>Willowbrook Mall in Wayne was closed because of flooding, and remained closed as of Thursday. The Westfield Garden State Plaza in Paramus and the Paramus Park shopping center were closed on Monday.</p>
        <p>Kris Kolluri, the state transportation commissioner, said that at the height of the storm more than 70 roads were closed but that only one, Route 56 in Pittsgrove, was seriously damaged, with 300 feet of the highway completely washed out. He estimated damage to the state's roads at about $15 million and said that crews have been examining more than 200 bridges statewide for problems, a process that is to continue for the next three weeks.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
