<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Week of Wildfires Displaces Thousands in Georgia</title>
    <meta content="22blaze" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/us/22blaze.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842261"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Waycross (Ga)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Emergency Management Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pomerance, Rachel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Georgia</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Emergency Management Agency</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401EED6163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Week of Wildfires Displaces Thousands in Georgia</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Week of Wildfires Displaces Thousands in Georgia</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RACHEL POMERANCE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pomerance, Rachel</byline>
      <dateline>WAYCROSS, Ga., April 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wildfires around Waycross, Ga, burn 45,000 acres; more than 1,000 people are evacuated; FEMA will provide 70 percent of money for firefighting and rebuilding area; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Except for Bubba, there is not much life where the Fullards took up residence on this city's outskirts -- their mobile home razed by wildfires gnawing into 45,000 acres of South Georgia.</p>
        <p>And yet, despite the smoke-laden air and charred remains of cracked china and upside-down appliances, Bubba, the family's 6-year-old black labrador, keeps finding his way back here, resting in a ditch a few yards from where the front porch used to give him shelter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wildfires spreading gnawing into 45,000 acres have caused evacuations in South Georgia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Except for Bubba, there is not much life where the Fullards took up residence on this city's outskirts -- their mobile home razed by wildfires gnawing into 45,000 acres of South Georgia.</p>
        <p>And yet, despite the smoke-laden air and charred remains of cracked china and upside-down appliances, Bubba, the family's 6-year-old black labrador, keeps finding his way back here, resting in a ditch a few yards from where the front porch used to give him shelter.</p>
        <p>''I don't think there's anything that can be saved,'' said Christy Fullard, 33, surveying her singed property.</p>
        <p>When Ms. Fullard fled the fire on Tuesday, she grabbed pictures off the shelves on her way out. Still, many treasures are gone -- her grandmother's matching vase and lamp and the deer heads claimed by her husband, Robin, 36. Around here, she said, ''you don't get a 10-point very often.''</p>
        <p>Then there are the lost snapshots of their daughters' first accomplishments -- when Kalah crawled, Sarah rode a bike and Chelsea lost a tooth, said Ms. Fullard, who is pregnant and has shuttled between the homes of friends and relatives for shelter.</p>
        <p>''It's these little things, but then you have to stay positive, because God's not going to put any more on you than you can handle,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Abiding faith and overwhelming community support have been the cornerstones of this area during the fires, which had encompassed 45,000 acres by Saturday. ''We're going to be here for quite some time,'' said Eric Mosley, public information officer of the Georgia Forestry Commission, who said he could not estimate how long it would take to quell the fire.</p>
        <p>More than 1,000 people have been evacuated over the course of the weeklong fires, which began with a tree falling across a power line, Mr. Mosley said. It has cost the state $1.7 million.</p>
        <p>Gov. Sonny Purdue, who was touring the area on Saturday, has asked for and received FEMA assistance, which will provide 70 percent of the money for firefighting and rebuilding the area. The state will carry the rest of the cost.</p>
        <p>But for its part, the local community has stressed its self-reliance.</p>
        <p>''It's just amazing to see the community come together,'' said Carol Clarke, 48, who checked in firefighters and their equipment overnight on Friday at Ware County High School, where the parking lot has been converted into a meeting and resting spot for firefighters. ''I mean, everyone's talking about it.''</p>
        <p>Organizations like the Chamber of Commerce have pitched in, sending e-mail messages about various needs that have been forwarded around town, Ms. Clarke said.</p>
        <p>Individuals have also pitched in.</p>
        <p>Sandra Kubik, owner of the Kickin K riding stable, has helped evacuate horses to her ranch for safekeeping and asked the local TV station to notify the public of her offer.</p>
        <p>At a community meeting on Friday night, Representative Jack Kingston acknowledged the volunteers. ''Instead of having turned to Washington for answers and solutions, y'all have turned to the person next to you,'' Mr. Kingston said.</p>
        <p>A range of public officers on hand gave details about the fires and evacuations at the meeting, but much of the talk came back to faith, fellowship and gratitude to the firefighters.</p>
        <p>More than one fire chief got choked up speaking about the courage of his colleagues. ''They were so filthy'' with ash they looked as if they rolled in dirt, said Fire Chief Jimmy Brown of Ware County.</p>
        <p>''They was out there for a cause, for you and for your homes and for your timber,'' he said. ''Yes, we've lost a lot of timber, and I don't know what to say, but I know one thing. I know one thing for sure. We got a God in heaven. He's going to take care of us.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
