<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Rangers Rookies Are Providing Exuberance Amid Experience</title>
    <meta content="22rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/sports/hockey/22rangers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842306"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E3DE173EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="973" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Rangers Rookies Are Providing Exuberance Amid Experience</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Two Rangers Rookies Are Providing Exuberance Amid Experience</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <dateline>GREENBURGH, N.Y., April 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even when Rangers forward Ryan Callahan sits at his locker, he is in perpetual motion, tapping his skates or nodding his head. The manic energy he plays with is forced to idle until the next practice.</p>
        <p>Across the room, his former minor league roommate Dan Girardi goes about his after-practice routine more calmly, a steadiness evident when he steps on the ice and blends almost seamlessly into the Rangers' defense.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ryan Callahan and Dan Girardi, both 22-year-old rookies, jumped into the Rangers’ lineup during the second half of the season and became instantly indispensable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even when Rangers forward Ryan Callahan sits at his locker, he is in perpetual motion, tapping his skates or nodding his head. The manic energy he plays with is forced to idle until the next practice.</p>
        <p>Across the room, his former minor league roommate Dan Girardi goes about his after-practice routine more calmly, a steadiness evident when he steps on the ice and blends almost seamlessly into the Rangers' defense.</p>
        <p>Together, they share the low end on the Rangers' spectrum of experience. They are the counterweights to the 19-year veteran Brendan Shanahan and the 17-year veteran Jaromir Jagr. Callahan and Girardi, both 22-year-old rookies, jumped into the Rangers' lineup during the second half of the season and became instantly indispensable.</p>
        <p>''It's funny because I almost have to ask who the rookies are at this point,'' said center Matt Cullen, a nine-year veteran.</p>
        <p>Callahan made his mark in Game 3 of the Rangers' sweep in their first-round Eastern Conference playoff series against Atlanta. He scored twice in the second period of a 7-0 victory. Remarkably, he has played only 18 games for the Rangers this season, yet it was the second time he had two goals in a game. (Both were 7-0 victories, exactly a month apart.)</p>
        <p>Girardi has stood out not for any goals or assists -- he has none -- but for his ability to take on such a crucial role. He is a classic defenseman, the kind who often goes unnoticed because he makes the right play before anyone notices who had the puck.</p>
        <p>''When he came here, his first game he was really good, like he was here a long time,'' defenseman Marek Malik said. ''I thought, something is in this kid. He's really talented and he has a feeling for hockey.''</p>
        <p>It is easy to forget that Callahan and Girardi were emergency plug-ins, summoned from the Rangers' American Hockey League affiliate in Hartford to fill holes. Girardi arrived in late January, after Darius Kasparaitis was sent down. Callahan joined the team in mid-March, after Marcel Hossa injured his left knee.</p>
        <p>They immediately became part of the team's push for a playoff spot, adding spunk and fresh legs. They are occasionally sent out by their older teammates on a coffee run before a morning skate, but otherwise have blended in.</p>
        <p>''You're happy for them because you can see they're still not affected by anything,'' forward Sean Avery said. ''They're just so happy to be here and playing hockey. It hasn't become much of a business to them yet. When you play four or five years, it changes a little bit. They kind of remind you what it was like, maybe even takes a little bit of stress off you. You see how much fun they're having and you feed off of it.''</p>
        <p>Girardi was called up when the Rangers finally had enough of Kasparaitis's struggles to stay in shape and play the kind of solid defense they needed. Girardi played 12 minutes in his first game, but his ice time swelled when injuries sent Fedor Tyutin and Karel Rachunek to the injured list. Now, after 34 regular-season games, he is averaging about 19 minutes a game in the postseason.</p>
        <p>''There were some nerves there, but I tried to handle it properly, not being overexcited and running around, doing too much,'' Girardi said. ''Obviously, my first playoff series here was really special, and I take a lot from that.''</p>
        <p>Callahan played two games in December for the Rangers but was summoned back March 15. Two days later, Callahan scored twice against Boston. He has not budged from the lineup since. ''I think we bring a lot of energy, a lot of excitement,'' Callahan said.</p>
        <p>''We're real anxious to get going. I think that showed on the ice in the first round; it brings a lot of energy to the team.''</p>
        <p>Callahan, the Rangers' fourth-round draft pick in 2004, has found a home on the third line, with Cullen and Petr Prucha. Together they play a hard-charging style, heavy on speed and forechecking. At 5 feet 11 inches and 185 pounds, Callahan makes up for a lack of size with quickness and persistence.</p>
        <p>In 60 games with Hartford this season, his first as a professional, Callahan scored 35 goals, including 15 on the power play and 4 short-handed.</p>
        <p>Girardi shares a defensive pairing with Paul Mara or Tyutin. His biggest strength is making quick passes out of the Rangers' zone to the forward with the best chance of turning the possession into an offensive breakout. That is something that often takes years to develop.</p>
        <p>''He plays like a guy that's been around for a long time,'' Cullen said. ''He makes great plays and holds onto the puck and he's good defensively and he adds a lot offensively.''</p>
        <p>Girardi was passed over in two N.H.L. drafts after playing for three teams in the Ontario Hockey League. He signed with the Rangers in 2006 and has become a windfall. At 6-2, 200 pounds, he is big enough to battle well in the corners and hold off rushing forwards.</p>
        <p>In Game 1 against Atlanta, Girardi was forced into a turnover behind the Rangers' net by the veteran center Bobby Holik. The play ended in a goal by Pascal Dupuis, which cut the Rangers' lead to 4-3 in the third period. But Girardi again drew praise for how he responded.</p>
        <p>''Everybody's going to make a mistake,'' Malik said. ''So the question is, how are you going to react to it? Are you going to be thinking about it and make more mistakes, or are you going to let it go and learn from it? I think he did an awesome job playing very well after that mistake.''</p>
        <p>For another playoff round, the Rangers will turn to their rookies for more than just a coffee run.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
