<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beyond Robinson and No. 42</title>
    <meta content="22inbox-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842321"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Uniforms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DE173EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="410" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beyond Robinson and No. 42</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Sports Editor:</p>
        <p>I would have been much more impressed with major leaguers if, instead of wearing Jackie Robinson's No. 42 on the 60th anniversary of his breaking baseball's color barrier in baseball, they had each contributed $42,000 to a scholarship fund for disadvantaged youth of all races. Or perhaps donated 42 hours of their time to volunteering in the public schools.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Sports Editor:</p>
        <p>I would have been much more impressed with major leaguers if, instead of wearing Jackie Robinson's No. 42 on the 60th anniversary of his breaking baseball's color barrier in baseball, they had each contributed $42,000 to a scholarship fund for disadvantaged youth of all races. Or perhaps donated 42 hours of their time to volunteering in the public schools.</p>
        <p>Seeing all those 42s in the Monday photos struck me as a silly trivialization of what Robinson accomplished at great personal expense.</p>
        <p>Marc Burgett  Minneapolis</p>
        <p>To the Sports Editor:</p>
        <p>Give Jackie Robinson all due credit, but playing sports has been fool's gold for the black community, in particular for the young people overly impressed by the glitz of occasional superstardom and duped into shooting baskets, boxing, running and hitting balls instead of studying, learning vocational skills and otherwise developing their higher selves.</p>
        <p>It has become so obvious that sports do not build character. Mentioning some names proves the point: Ty Cobb, Mike Tyson, Pete Rose, Jose Canseco, Tonya Harding, Rafael Palmeiro, Darryl Strawberry, Barry Bonds.</p>
        <p>Robinson's true legacy, then, is by way of analogy, not direct emulation. The right message is not to bank on your athletic ability but to brave being the first of your group to enter the field of your dreams.</p>
        <p>Jeff Zorn  San Francisco</p>
        <p>To the Sports Editor:</p>
        <p>The recollections of Jackie Robinson's making it to the majors seem to overlook that he never would have made it to the majors had Branch Rickey not had the nerve to fly in the face of tradition and sign him to a Dodgers contract. Rickey also drafted Roberto Clemente, the first Hispanic to become a superstar, and created the minor league system as we know it.</p>
        <p>It seems a commemorative recognizing Rickey would not be amiss.</p>
        <p>J. Dirk Lohman  Hendersonville, N.C.</p>
        <p>To the Sports Editor:</p>
        <p>Young fans across the country held Jackie Robinson in high esteem from the beginning.</p>
        <p>Somehow, through our innocent hearts and not yet hardened prejudices and judgments, he managed to capture our imagination and fresh sense of fair play. We suspected that Robinson was a special human being facing huge challenges in a difficult era, and we simply believed in him.</p>
        <p>He was always ranked in the highest tier of our baseball heroes for all the right reasons: his talent, his character, and his real spirit and honesty.</p>
        <p>Richard Carney  Evanston, Ill.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
