<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Lives of Three Sisters, Fortune Doesn't Smile Often</title>
    <meta content="22theatreweWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/22theatrewe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842042"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Schoolhouse Theater (Croton Falls, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gold, Sylviane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Henley, Beth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kareman, Pamela Moller</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Crimes of the Heart (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Schoolhouse Theater</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07EFD61E3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="534" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Lives of Three Sisters, Fortune Doesn't Smile Often</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In the Lives of Three Sisters, Fortune Doesn’t Smile Often</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SYLVIANE GOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gold, Sylviane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sylviane Gold reviews production of Beth Henley play Crimes of the Heart, directed by Pamela Moller Kareman, at Schoolhouse Theater in Croton Falls, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The spacious yellow kitchen that provides the setting for ''Crimes of the Heart'' at the Schoolhouse Theater has seen better days. The flowered wallpaper is fading. Water stains dribble from the ceiling. And there's a cot shoved Cinderella-style into a corner.</p>
        <p>The cot belongs to Lenny Magrath, and the Cinderella analogy is not entirely gratuitous. Lenny is the homely, put-upon older sister of Meg and Babe, who in their own ways have gone to the ball -- Meg by abandoning small-town Mississippi to pursue a singing career in California; Babe by marrying a rising local politician. Lenny has been left to sleep in the kitchen and tend to their old ailing grandfather in the old ailing house.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“Crimes of the Heart,” at the Schoolhouse Theater in Croton Falls, treats playwright Beth Henley’s writing with resolute earnestness rather than crisp dispatch.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The spacious yellow kitchen that provides the setting for ''Crimes of the Heart'' at the Schoolhouse Theater has seen better days. The flowered wallpaper is fading. Water stains dribble from the ceiling. And there's a cot shoved Cinderella-style into a corner.</p>
        <p>The cot belongs to Lenny Magrath, and the Cinderella analogy is not entirely gratuitous. Lenny is the homely, put-upon older sister of Meg and Babe, who in their own ways have gone to the ball -- Meg by abandoning small-town Mississippi to pursue a singing career in California; Babe by marrying a rising local politician. Lenny has been left to sleep in the kitchen and tend to their old ailing grandfather in the old ailing house.</p>
        <p>But don't feel too sorry for her. By the time Beth Henley's Pulitzer Prize-winning comedy has run its convoluted course and all three are back in John Pollard's evocative kitchen, it's clear that Lenny will be fine. Meg and Babe are the Magrath sisters who need our sympathy.</p>
        <p>The hard-headed Meg, played here by Quinn Cassavale, has found she wasn't quite tough enough for show business; she's been getting by with a job at a pet-food factory. And the soft-headed Babe, portrayed by Sherry Stregack, has finally had it with her none-too-nice husband; she's shot him in the stomach and poured herself a glass of freshly made lemonade.</p>
        <p>So the fact is, Cheryl Orsini's Lenny doesn't have that much to worry about. Her big problem -- apart from her two sisters, of course -- is a shrunken ovary, which has made her hopelessly self-conscious around men. But it's easy to get depressed when your father walked out, your mother committed suicide, the grandfather who took you in is in the hospital, your pet horse has been struck by lightning and your obnoxious, social-climbing cousin keeps popping in the back door to remind you that your whole family is a disgrace. On your birthday.</p>
        <p>The rat-a-tat, good news-bad news rhythms of Ms. Henley's writing require, above all else, superb timing. Pamela Moller Kareman's production at the Schoolhouse tracks the fortunes of the Magrath clan with resolute earnestness rather than crisp dispatch, so some of the humor goes a little flat. ''Crimes of the Heart'' should elicit laughs, not just indulgent smiles. But the play's clever construction proves to be remarkably forgiving, and with the exception of one botched performance, the Schoolhouse is offering its audience a decent rendition of the play.</p>
        <p>Ms. Orsini is likeably hangdog as Lenny, and Ms. Cassavale does well with Meg's brassy facade. The 1980 Manhattan Theater Club production, which later moved to Broadway, introduced Peter MacNicol as the grinning, goofy young lawyer hired to defend Babe. At the Schoolhouse, Andy Place brings a similar cocky boyishness to the role. And in the secondary roles of the snooty cousin and Meg's old flame, Jillian Sanders and Simon MacLean acquit themselves honorably.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, Ms. Stregack's overdone Babe comes across as aggressively silly rather than charmingly wide-eyed, and you sort of wish Ms. Henley had left her in jail.</p>
        <p>''Crimes of the Heart,'' by Beth Henley, is at the Schoolhouse Theater, 3 Owens Road, Croton Falls, through May 6. Information: (914) 277-8477 or www.schoolhousetheater.org.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
