<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hitting the Links From the Desk</title>
    <meta content="22goods" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/business/yourmoney/22goods.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842189"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OPENERS: THE GOODS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/The Goods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Operations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Working Hours</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Working Hours</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Toys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E3DC163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="621" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hitting the Links From the Desk</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hitting the Links From the Desk</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRENDAN I. KOERNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Koerner, Brendan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN a 2005 episode of ''The Office,'' the NBC sitcom, the bored employees of Dunder-Mifflin, a fictional paper company, demonstrated their made-up sports. Two accountants battled tedium by playing Hateball, their nickname for a well-known pastime in which paper triangles are flicked across desks. A human-resources employee, meanwhile, procrastinated with Dunderball, a catch-and-throw game that pitted cubicle dwellers against one another.</p>
        <p>The hapless drones of ''The Office'' lack the ambition of the partners in Rutan G.m.b.H., a product design firm in Darmstadt, Germany. When Rutan's designers put their minds to creating a whimsical, cubicle-friendly sport, they came up with micro golf, a sophisticated game best described as marbles-meets-miniature-shuffleboard. And they built a kit, called Pit Green, that includes pebble-sized balls, clubs the length of toothpicks, a hexagonal putting green and a five-inch figurine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A German game inspires golf for the cubicle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN a 2005 episode of ''The Office,'' the NBC sitcom, the bored employees of Dunder-Mifflin, a fictional paper company, demonstrated their made-up sports. Two accountants battled tedium by playing Hateball, their nickname for a well-known pastime in which paper triangles are flicked across desks. A human-resources employee, meanwhile, procrastinated with Dunderball, a catch-and-throw game that pitted cubicle dwellers against one another.</p>
        <p>The hapless drones of ''The Office'' lack the ambition of the partners in Rutan G.m.b.H., a product design firm in Darmstadt, Germany. When Rutan's designers put their minds to creating a whimsical, cubicle-friendly sport, they came up with micro golf, a sophisticated game best described as marbles-meets-miniature-shuffleboard. And they built a kit, called Pit Green, that includes pebble-sized balls, clubs the length of toothpicks, a hexagonal putting green and a five-inch figurine.</p>
        <p>Oliver Johannson, a Rutan designer, said micro golf was inspired by Tipp-Kick, a classic German game that involves metal figures modeled after soccer players; when a player's head is tapped, his foot moves up to strike a tiny plastic soccer ball. Because many modern soccer stars spend their leisure time on the links, Mr. Johannson said, Rutan's designers decided to create a golf version of Tipp-Kick.</p>
        <p>Rutan displayed drawings of the concept at a 2004 Berlin design show sponsored by Nike. ''A lot of people called us and asked, 'Where can I buy this product?' '' Mr. Johannson said. ''And we said, 'Oh, no, this is just an idea.' ''</p>
        <p>In 2005, Rutan began working on a three-dimensional prototype of Pit Green's figurine, beginning with a rough model made from the wire that secures Champagne corks. The designers then reworked the body in foam, attaching the arms and legs with sewing needles.</p>
        <p>They quickly refined the figure's shape, giving it sleeker, artistic look. A brass gear was placed in the torso, with a space near the shoulder for a serrated stick to control the figurine's arms. Move the stick to adjust the power of the swing: draw it all the way up and then push down rapidly for a long drive, or apply just a little pressure for a one-inch putt.</p>
        <p>The designers made the figurine as durable as possible, anticipating that micro golfers would take out their frustrations on their plastic surrogates. ''It's impossible to destroy because it's got 30 percent glass fibers,'' Mr. Johannson said.</p>
        <p>Each Pit Green kit comes with four die-cast zinc clubs -- a driver, an iron, a wedge and a putter -- that screw into the figurine's hands. The tiny golf balls in the early version were hollow, said Mr. Johannson, and rolled too far when struck; they now contain small weights, to better mimic the motion of real golf balls on grass.</p>
        <p>Mr. Johansson estimated that Rutan has sold 10,000 Pit Green kits, primarily through PitGreen.com. The basic version costs 69 euros (about $94); a deluxe version, with more accessories and a souvenir micro golf magazine, costs 99 euros (about $134).</p>
        <p>To promote the product, Rutan has sponsored micro golf tournaments. At the International Furniture Fair in Cologne, Germany, in January, Mathias Ley defeated several dozen competitors to win the Pit Green League's 2007 Tee-Off Event, played on a carpeted course measuring about a tenth of an acre. Mr. Johannson calls Mr. Ley ''the Tiger Woods of micro golfers.''</p>
        <p>After spending an embarrassing number of hours honing my micro golf game, I feel almost capable of challenging Mr. Ley for that coveted title. I played several rounds in my apartment, which seemed a much more fitting locale than a cramped office. I would like to try it on an even bigger course; my hardwood floors are too fast, and my mightiest tee shots often crashed into my bedroom wall.</p>
        <p>OPENERS: THE GOODS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
