<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Building Binge For Bank Branches</title>
    <meta content="22sqft" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/realestate/commercial/22sqft.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842219"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SQUARE FEET: SPOTLIGHT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Construction and Maintenance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E6D9163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1181" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Building Binge For Bank Branches</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Building Binge for Bank Branches</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMY CORTESE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cortese, Amy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF you've ever seen a new storefront rising in your neighborhood and secretly hoped for, say, a new cafe or boutique, you might know the sinking feeling when -- almost invariably, it seems -- the business turns out to be a bank. Now, there's nothing wrong with banks, but, you might wonder: Don't we have enough branches already?</p>
        <p>Apparently not.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you’ve ever seen a new storefront and secretly hoped for, say, a new cafe, you might know the sinking feeling when the business turns out to be a bank.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF you've ever seen a new storefront rising in your neighborhood and secretly hoped for, say, a new cafe or boutique, you might know the sinking feeling when -- almost invariably, it seems -- the business turns out to be a bank. Now, there's nothing wrong with banks, but, you might wonder: Don't we have enough branches already?</p>
        <p>Apparently not.</p>
        <p>Across the country, prime real estate continues to be snatched up by bank companies, which are in the midst of a branch-building boom even as many of the companies merge. As of last year, there were some 94,559 federally insured branches in the United States, up from 92,394 in 2005, and 82,302 in 1996, according to the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation.</p>
        <p>The growth is partly a reaction to pent-up demand in this decade, when branch building slowed as bankers anticipated that their bricks-and-mortar business was giving way to the Internet, bank professionals say. But it turns out that when it comes to their money, many people still prefer the human touch.</p>
        <p>In areas like the New York metropolitan region, building has occurred at a furious pace over the last few years, even if it is now starting to cool. It's not uncommon to see four or more branches on a single city block or intersection. The region -- with about $462 billion in consumer deposits, according to the American Bankers Association -- was the seventh most active market in terms of new openings last year. (With rents having soared to $200 to $450 a square foot in prime neighborhoods, banks may be among the few possible tenants who can afford the space.)</p>
        <p>Banks elsewhere see plenty of untapped potential. Nationwide, the number of branches grew by 2.6 percent in 2006, but total consumer deposits grew even more -- by 9 percent -- according to the F.D.I.C. In recent years, banks have been following the population trends in fast-growing states like Texas, which, by F.D.I.C. tallies, had 5 of the 10 most active markets last year.</p>
        <p>But with more competitors fighting for the same markets and many of the best locations already taken, banks have had to become savvier about selecting sites for expansion. Getting it right is important: It can cost $2.5 million to $3 million to open a branch in a suburb, and up to $5 million for one in a city, according to industry experts.</p>
        <p>James Allen, the group executive vice president for retail banking at Broadway National Bank, a $1.7 billion privately owned community bank in San Antonio, has watched as credit unions and national banks have started pouring into the greater San Antonio area, which the bank has served for more than 60 years.</p>
        <p>''Ten years ago we could probably go out and pick a location based on gut,'' Mr. Allen said. But with the new competition, he added, ''the ballgame has changed.''</p>
        <p>''It's caused us to think and act smarter,'' he said.</p>
        <p>A few years ago, the bank began working with MapInfo, a software company based in Troy, N.Y., that specializes in what it calls ''location intelligence.'' Using census data and information that companies have gathered on their customers and operations, MapInfo's analytical software engine spits out color-coded maps that show where the most attractive opportunities lie.</p>
        <p>The maps can show a high-level view of a large region, like the Southwest, or can drill down to specific intersections of a city. Variables like income level, banking deposits, retail activity, small-business concentration and competition can be tracked. MapInfo's analytic tools can help banks, and retailers, to choose not only the most attractive sites, but also to understand the effect of a new branch on existing networks -- for example, whether it might cannibalize existing business. ''It allows us to add some science to the intuitive process,'' Mr. Allen said.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, for example, Broadway National was evaluating the acquisition of a smaller, local bank. It looked like a good strategic fit, but Broadway National asked MapInfo to analyze the potential of the bank's four branches and how they would affect Broadway's existing business. Based on the results, Broadway went ahead with the deal.</p>
        <p>''The data has proven to be pretty realistic,'' Mr. Allen said.</p>
        <p>Such decision-making support is especially helpful in crowded markets like Manhattan. Karen Curtin, the general manager of the branch and network management group at Wachovia, based in Charlotte, N.C., says MapInfo helped the bank's analysts identify growth areas in Manhattan. For example, the software flagged the northward march of development on the Upper West Side, where the bank added a branch at Broadway and 70th Street last July, with another at Broadway and 85th Street scheduled to open its doors this summer.</p>
        <p>In the Midwest, Amcore, a $5.3 billion regional bank, was looking to expand. At the turn of the millennium, ''we were in no-growth areas and, if we didn't expand, we'd soon be going by another name,'' says Eleanor Doar, chief marketing officer at Amcore, based in Rockford, Ill., and a unit of Amcore Financial.</p>
        <p>Amcore was doing well in suburban areas, but was missing out on the urban growth markets of Chicago, Milwaukee and Madison, Wis.</p>
        <p>Amcore began an expansion program in 2001, but the process was ''organized chaos,'' as Ms. Doar described it.</p>
        <p>''Everyone had a friend in commercial real estate with the best bank site,'' she recalled. ''We spun our wheels investigating all of these tips.'' Amcore brought in a consultant who researched potential sites by driving around neighborhoods, but the bank ended up getting into some markets too early as a result, Ms. Doar said.</p>
        <p>Amcore began working with MapInfo, which helped it rank the most lucrative markets and sites and become more focused.</p>
        <p>''Then, when we got the real estate call, we could say, 'No, that doesn't fit,' '' Ms. Doar said.</p>
        <p>Sometimes the results are counterintuitive. Broadway National Bank found what it had thought was a slam-dunk location across from the University of Texas at San Antonio and a retail area, guaranteeing heavy foot traffic. But the MapInfo recommendation was to pass. Students were not a core target for the bank, and the analysis suggested that the location was well served by two of the bank's existing branches within four to five miles of the prospective site. ''In hindsight,'' Mr. Allen said, ''the data was right and we've moved on.''</p>
        <p>Timing counts, too. Banks are often surprised to learn that being the first to enter an up-and-coming neighborhood may not always be wise. The second, third and even fourth entrants usually fare better, after the market is established, said Hal Hopson, global practice leader at MapInfo, which is being acquired by Pitney Bowes.</p>
        <p>And all those banks crammed onto one corner? Competition isn't necessarily a bad thing. In high-density markets like Manhattan, a block or two may be able to support multiple banks; there may even be a synergistic effect. Community banks, for example, often do well next to a national bank branch.</p>
        <p>''We don't mind being next to a large regional bank because we think we offer more on the customer service side,'' said Ms. Doar of Amcore.</p>
        <p>SQUARE FEET: SPOTLIGHT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
