<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Calendar Says 'Sell,' but Should You Obey?</title>
    <meta content="22fund" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/business/yourmoney/22fund.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842196"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FUNDAMENTALLY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Fundamentally</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E2DC163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="926" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Calendar Says 'Sell,' but Should You Obey?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Calendar Says ‘Sell,’ but Should You Obey?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL J. LIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lim, Paul J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFTER sending the Dow Jones industrial average to new highs last week, shareholders are about to face a seasonal challenge: investing in equities during what has historically been a frustrating six-month stretch for stocks.</p>
        <p>Whether you measure the market's performance going back to the 1980s, the 1950s, or even 1900, the worst time of the year to invest in domestic equities has been the period we're about to enter: May through October.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shareholders are about to face a seasonal challenge: investing in equities during what has historically been a frustrating six-month stretch for stocks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFTER sending the Dow Jones industrial average to new highs last week, shareholders are about to face a seasonal challenge: investing in equities during what has historically been a frustrating six-month stretch for stocks.</p>
        <p>Whether you measure the market's performance going back to the 1980s, the 1950s, or even 1900, the worst time of the year to invest in domestic equities has been the period we're about to enter: May through October.</p>
        <p>Since 1945, the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index has gained just 1.6 percent, on average, during that stretch. By contrast, the best six months for the S.&amp; P. have been the period that's coming to an end: November through April. Since the end of World War II, the S.&amp; P. 500 has shot up 7.1 percent, on average, during these months.</p>
        <p>This phenomenon has been just as strong in recent years. Since 1990, stocks have gained 7.8 percent from November to April, on average, but only 2.1 percent from May to October.</p>
        <p>Chris Orndorff, head of equity strategy at Payden &amp; Rygel, an asset manager in Los Angeles, says he doesn't usually pay much attention to seasonal differences. ''But these numbers are quite compelling,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Why such a disparity in performance? Theories abound. Jeffrey A. Hirsch, editor in chief of The Stock Trader's Almanac, says investors may be ''operating on a summer vacation schedule'' during this six-month window. He added that investors usually don't have as much money to put to work in the market in the middle of the year. By the time May rolls around, some people are done funding individual retirement accounts, and many have already spent or invested year-end bonuses.</p>
        <p>That may explain why mutual fund sales tend to slow noticeably during that six-month period. In fact, since 2000, net new inflows into domestic stock funds from November to April have been three times as big as those from May through October, according to data compiled by the Investment Company Institute.</p>
        <p>To be sure, the 1.6 percent gain for the S.&amp; P. during this stretch is only an average. In a number of midyear stretches, stocks have fared much better.</p>
        <p>From May to October of 2006, for example, the S.&amp; P. 500 advanced 5.1 percent. Though that was still below the 8.6 percent gain from November 2005 to April 2006, it was far better than the norm.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the May-to-October period has outperformed the November-to-April stretch in almost a third of the years since World War II. So it may be far too simplistic -- and risky -- to just ''sell in May and go away.''</p>
        <p>While the May-to-October window is typically frustrating, two of the best months for equities -- July and August -- fall within it. And Mr. Hirsch noted that October, which used to be considered a scary month, has turned out to be the best one for domestic stocks since 1998, on average.</p>
        <p>The fact is, ''you'd prefer not to sell in May,'' said Sam Stovall, S.&amp; P.'s chief investment strategist.</p>
        <p>Even if the broad market underperforms from May to October, most types of stocks actually do quite well during that time. Since 1990, eight of the 10 stock market sectors have posted positive returns, on average, over those six months. The only exceptions were two economically sensitive sectors: basic materials and consumer-discretionary stocks. What's more, seven of the 10 sectors actually outperformed the broad S.&amp; P. 500 during these doldrums months.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stovall says that selling stocks simply because the calendar has turned to May would be a risky form of market timing. ''If the odds are seven in 10 that stocks will rise,'' he said, ''you'd have to be pretty confident to be making this bet.''</p>
        <p>Still, with both corporate earnings and the economy slowing, it may be wise to think defensively. Amid slowing profits or a decelerating economy, the best-performing sectors tend to be defensive ones, like health care and consumer staples. The premise is simple: When times are tough, people may stop buying new cars and clothes, but they still need their drugs and toothpaste.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, health care and consumer staples are among the sectors for which investors are currently most bullish, according to a recent survey of money managers by the Russell Investment Group.</p>
        <p>And the seasonality argument would also call for overweighting these defensive parts of the market. Since 1990, these two areas have been the best-performing sectors in the May-to-October period, according to an analysis by S.&amp; P. Health care stocks have risen 5.7 percent, on average, during those six months, while consumer staples have gained 5.3 percent.</p>
        <p>By contrast, economically sensitive sectors have fared far worse. In addition to the consumer-discretionary and basic materials sectors -- which have historically lost value during this stretch -- shares of industrial companies have risen only 0.1 percent, on average.</p>
        <p>MR. ORNDORFF of Payden &amp; Rygel said that ''anytime you're in an environment where the overall economy is decelerating and earnings growth is also decelerating, it raises the risk that there might be a more significant correction than the one we saw at the end of February.''</p>
        <p>And in such an environment, he said, ''we typically like to focus on companies with more stable cash flows.''</p>
        <p>While these types of companies can be found in any number of sectors -- including some economically sensitive ones -- Mr. Orndorff said that many were typically in areas like health care and consumer staples, which don't require a strong economy in order to thrive.</p>
        <p>The seasonality argument, he said, only serves to bolster this line of thinking.</p>
        <p>FUNDAMENTALLY Paul J. Lim is a financial writer at U.S. News &amp; World Report. E-mail: fund@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Paul J. Lim is a financial writer at U.S. News &amp; World Report. E-mail: fund@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
