<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Affordable Europe: Prague</title>
    <meta content="22pragueweb" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/travel/22pragueweb.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842337"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Prague (Czech Republic)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Czech Republic/Prague</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Czech Republic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Prague (Czech Republic)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1D61631F931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="597" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Affordable Europe: Prague</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Affordable Europe: Prague</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EVAN RAIL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The City of a Hundred Spires is becoming one of Europe's top destinations, with passenger arrivals at Prague's Ruzyne Airport having doubled since 2000, according to official statistics. Those ever-increasing numbers mean that prices are among the highest in the former Eastern bloc, though a few surprising bargains have recently appeared in the Czech capital.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay for Under 125 Euros</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ever-increasing numbers of tourists mean that prices are among the highest in the former Eastern bloc, though a few surprising bargains have recently appeared in the Czech capital.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The City of a Hundred Spires is becoming one of Europe's top destinations, with passenger arrivals at Prague's Ruzyne Airport having doubled since 2000, according to official statistics. Those ever-increasing numbers mean that prices are among the highest in the former Eastern bloc, though a few surprising bargains have recently appeared in the Czech capital.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay for Under 125 Euros</p>
        <p>For years, most new hotels in Prague have followed the path charted by the city's flashy restaurants, aiming squarely for the high-end market, with prices to match. But a new generation of smaller hotels is starting to serve more budget-conscious travelers, often in locations that are better than expensive lodgings. In a building whose first written reference dates back to the early 14th century, Hotel Loreta (Loretanske namesti 8; 420-233-310-510; www.hotelloreta.cz) opened in June of 2006, with 10 double rooms right at Prague Castle, next to the Baroque facade of the Loreta pilgrimage church. In high season, doubles are 98 euros, or about $133 at $1.36 to the euro, including breakfast. Be sure to mention if you want the separable mattresses set up as one bed or two.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat  Some of the best new restaurants in Prague are also among the cheapest, especially once you get out of the crowded center. Just off the Vltava river promenade at the south end of New Town, six-month-old Noodle Bar(Plavecka 4; 420-602-370-984; www.noodle.cz) serves good Thai plates, a rarity throughout the region, at very moderate prices. The tangy and sweet phad sen mu is 105 koruna (about $5 at 21 koruna to the dollar), and a marvelous pomelo salad with crispy fried prawns and fragrant cilantro is 155 koruna. The modern, manga-inspired décor is probably chic enough for a date. Next door, year-oldOliva(Plavecka 4; 420-222-520-288; www.olivarestaurant.cz) alternates between high-end Continental and down-home comfort food: a plate of crispy garlic-lemon chicken with grilled tomatoes, olives and house-baked bread is 265 koruna. The wine list, much of which comes from the Côtes du Rhône and the Languedoc regions, has several bottles priced at 400 to 500 koruna.</p>
        <p>Where to Shop  Czech Cubist, Art Deco and Functionalist design is quickly catching on with antiques collectors. For the cream of the crop, check out the four-month-old shop Modernista (Celetna 12; 420-224-241-300; www.modernista.cz) where a walnut display case from 1936 might set you back 3,500 euros. To score a bargain, try Prague's main blesi trh, or flea market, which runs every Saturday and Sunday from 6 a.m. until 1 p.m. To get there, take tram 19 or the Metro B line to the Kolbenova stop and follow the signs. A much larger market, Bustehrad Antik (www.bustehradantik.cz), takes place every two weeks in a village 12 miles northwest of the city, with direct buses leaving from metro stations Dejvicka and Zlicin. For schedules, check www.idos.cz.</p>
        <p>Best Money-Saving Tip  Even museums can be budget-busters here: the must-see Jewish Museum (www.jewishmuseum.cz) charges 470 koruna for a full adult ticket to all Jewish sites in Old Town, as much as many locals earn in a day. However, a few great collections have regular free entry. The lovely Museum of Decorative Arts (17 listopadu 2; 420-251-093-111; www.upm.cz) is free every Tuesday from 5 to 7 p.m. The first Thursday of every month, the Museum of the City of Prague(Na Porici 52; 420-224-816-773; www.muzeumprahy.cz) has tickets for a symbolic 1 koruna. And at the National Gallery (Dukelskych hrdinu 47; 420-224-301-024; www.ngprague.cz) visitors can enter for free between 3 and 8 p.m. on the first Wednesday of every month.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
