<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A NIGHT OUT WITH: The Men Who Rouse 'Spring Awakening'; Cats in the Alley</title>
    <meta content="22nite" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/fashion/22nite.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070429T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842132"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="A Night Out With the Men Who Rouse Spring Awakening"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Columns/A Night Out With</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE2DF163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="623" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A NIGHT OUT WITH: The Men Who Rouse 'Spring Awakening'; Cats in the Alley</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cats in the Alley</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WINTER MILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Miller, Winter</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE evening began with a miscommunication. John Gallagher Jr., Jonathan Groff and Duncan Sheik of the Broadway musical ''Spring Awakening'' were sitting in a loud bowling alley. Each thought the other had suggested Harlem Lanes. In fact, no one had expressed a desire to bowl. Their publicist thought it would be cool.</p>
        <p>So they did what any self-respecting celebrities would: buck their publicist and set out in search of a decent restaurant. That couldn't be too difficult -- it was Harlem, after all. They hopped into a waiting town car and rode south to Zoma, an Ethiopian restaurant on Frederick Douglass Boulevard and 113th Street.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ethiopian food and bowling with John Gallagher Jr., Jonathan Groff and Duncan Sheik of the Broadway musical “Spring Awakening.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE evening began with a miscommunication. John Gallagher Jr., Jonathan Groff and Duncan Sheik of the Broadway musical ''Spring Awakening'' were sitting in a loud bowling alley. Each thought the other had suggested Harlem Lanes. In fact, no one had expressed a desire to bowl. Their publicist thought it would be cool.</p>
        <p>So they did what any self-respecting celebrities would: buck their publicist and set out in search of a decent restaurant. That couldn't be too difficult -- it was Harlem, after all. They hopped into a waiting town car and rode south to Zoma, an Ethiopian restaurant on Frederick Douglass Boulevard and 113th Street.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gallagher, 22, and Mr. Groff, also 22, play two young men, Moritz and Melchior, undergoing major sexual stirrings in the critically lauded musical adaptation of Frank Wedekind's 19th-century play of the same name. Mr. Sheik, 37, who composed the music, first earned his rock bona fides in the '90s with a heavy rotation on MTV.</p>
        <p>Fresh off a plane from Los Angeles, Mr. Sheik was lobbying for a glass of wine. (This was reason No. 2 for leaving the bowling alley.) In the subdued atmosphere of Zoma, Mr. Sheik suggested a bottle of sauvignon blanc. Both actors, a) beer drinkers and b) barely legal, nodded their assent. They sipped cautiously, as if by drinking they might become irrevocably adult.</p>
        <p>Two large platters of vegetables and meat over injera, a spongy flatbread, arrived. Mr. Sheik demonstrated the art of tearing injera and scooping.</p>
        <p>Talk turned to the show and spring-break audiences. ''They flash us,'' Mr. Gallagher joked. ''No, but some teenage girl asked me to marry her.'' He didn't say if he took her up on it.</p>
        <p>''Lindsay Lohan was supposed to come the other night,'' Mr. Sheik mentioned, only semi-casually.</p>
        <p>''You know her?'' Mr. Groff asked, his jaw scraping the table.</p>
        <p>''A little,'' Mr. Sheik said. ''But then her shoot ran over.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Groff was crestfallen.</p>
        <p>''This teenage girl at the stage door asked me if the two guys who do the gay scene, if they're both gay,'' Mr. Gallagher said, changing the subject to method acting, all the while not answering the question he had raised.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sheik, the elder statesman of the threesome, wore a navy anorak with Levi's and sported a scruffy brown beard. Mr. Groff had on a blue-and-white striped polo, jeans and a brown baseball cap salvaged from a failed Broadway musical. ''We got to keep our costumes because they knew there wouldn't be a road show,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gallagher wore a beige oxford with an ocher necktie and brown corduroys. The tie would reach its zenith later.</p>
        <p>By 10 p.m., fortified, and with just enough to drink to instill bravado, the guys headed back to Harlem Lanes. The Johns ordered beers.</p>
        <p>''They're going to let me win, or I'm going to fire them,'' Mr. Sheik said menacingly. Rap boomed out of the alley's speakers.</p>
        <p>''I would bowl better with some really bad classic rock,'' Mr. Gallagher insisted. All the same, he prepared for his first ball, loosening his tie and roping it across his forehead, like a bowling ninja. He cupped the ball and rolled  a gutter ball. The first of many, though he was the only one to hit his groove midway, bowling spares and strikes.</p>
        <p>At 11 p.m., the alley was shutting down.</p>
        <p>''We forgot to re-enact the scene from 'The Big Lebowski,' '' Mr. Sheik lamented.</p>
        <p>''I almost licked the ball, but I didn't know where it had been,'' Mr. Gallagher said, referring to a purple-pantsuit-clad John Turturro licking his ball before bowling.</p>
        <p>The alley shut the music off, and it was time to trade in the shoes.</p>
        <p>They came. They bowled. They floundered.</p>
        <p>A Night Out With the Men Who Rouse Spring Awakening</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 29, 2007, Sunday  A picture caption last Sunday with the Night Out column, about the composer and two stars of the Broadway show ''Spring Awakening,'' misspelled the surname of one of the actors. He is Jonathan Groff, not Goff.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 29, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>A picture caption last Sunday with the Night Out column, about the composer and two stars of the Broadway show ''Spring Awakening,'' misspelled the surname of one of the actors. He is Jonathan Groff, not Goff.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
