<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Venerable Italian's 3rd Act: Great Food, and Opera, Too</title>
    <meta content="22dineliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/22dineli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842009"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/CEDARHURST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">La Viola (Cedarhurst, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starkey, Joanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403EEDA1E3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="835" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Venerable Italian's 3rd Act: Great Food, and Opera, Too</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Venerable Italian’s 3rd Act: Great Food, and Opera, Too</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOANNE STARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Starkey, Joanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joanne Starkey reviews La Viola restaurant in Cedarhurst, NY; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THROUGHOUT its 30-year history, La Viola has been a weathervane of Long Island's taste in Italian food. When it opened in Cedarhurst in 1977, it was the kind of Italian restaurant that Long Islanders loved in that era: a formal, special-occasion spot serving continental cuisine. The restaurant was sold in the mid-1980s and later closed. In 1989, a new Viola opened with its original owners, Lino and Elsa Viola, back at the helm.</p>
        <p>The 1989 version was a casual cafe with cutting-edge pastas (like black-bean pasta with walnut sauce), a glistening antipasto array and olive oil and balsamic vinegar bottles on the tables. In 1990 all that changed, and La Viola became a leader in the family-dining trend. A few months later, after a fire, the restaurant moved several blocks away into a landmark building that had been a hotel. It remains there, with its Italian family-dining style intact. (There is a second La Viola in Syosset, which opened in 1992.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At La Viola in Cedarhurst, almost everything was delicious, and the pastas were the superstars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THROUGHOUT its 30-year history, La Viola has been a weathervane of Long Island's taste in Italian food. When it opened in Cedarhurst in 1977, it was the kind of Italian restaurant that Long Islanders loved in that era: a formal, special-occasion spot serving continental cuisine. The restaurant was sold in the mid-1980s and later closed. In 1989, a new Viola opened with its original owners, Lino and Elsa Viola, back at the helm.</p>
        <p>The 1989 version was a casual cafe with cutting-edge pastas (like black-bean pasta with walnut sauce), a glistening antipasto array and olive oil and balsamic vinegar bottles on the tables. In 1990 all that changed, and La Viola became a leader in the family-dining trend. A few months later, after a fire, the restaurant moved several blocks away into a landmark building that had been a hotel. It remains there, with its Italian family-dining style intact. (There is a second La Viola in Syosset, which opened in 1992.)</p>
        <p>The Cedarhurst spot is airy and spacious, with rooms flowing into one another. (Some can be closed on slow nights.) Diners enter through a big, old-fashioned wooden bar, which has a few tables for casual dining.</p>
        <p>The dining rooms feature wall-size mirrors, big, colorful Italian posters and watercolors of historic Cedarhurst buildings. In one room, opera reigns, with posters of various productions and photographs of stars. (The owners love music, and popular opera nights are held the first Friday of every month in an upstairs party room; the $55 price includes a four-course meal and unlimited wine.)</p>
        <p>The service staff is exceptionally friendly and spiffily decked out in white shirts and red suspenders. Yet the service is not as sharp as the look. Diners can order family-style platters serving three to four or individual plates (priced at about 60 percent of the large ones, they are also huge). To try more dishes, we chose the latter. Since most patrons order family-style, the wait staff was a bit thrown by our order. No one had a clue as to who had ordered what.</p>
        <p>But oh, what food! Almost everything was delicious, and the pastas were the superstars. If spaghetti with veal meatballs is offered as a special, order it. The meatballs were the size of baseballs but as light as air; the tomato sauce was outstanding. Equally impressive was veal cannelloni: homemade pasta covered with that wonderful pomodoro sauce. Linguine with white clam sauce was packed with flavor from its briny clams and sautéed garlic.</p>
        <p>The restaurant's pasta sauces (sold at Waldbaum's) also made star turns with the eggplant parmigiana and a dish that layered veal medallions and eggplant. Another hearty winner was a special of fork-tender lamb shank in a rich gravy, accompanied by fusilli. Broiled fillet of sole and salmon stuffed with spinach were fine choices for those with lighter appetites.</p>
        <p>All the salads made good starters. The house and tricolor both had sprightly greens and a snappy mustard vinaigrette. The Caesar was classic and far above average. Arugula topped with slices of portobello mushrooms was also splendid. Seafood salad had firm but tender morsels, but it would have been even better without the chunks of fake crabmeat.</p>
        <p>Other good openers included baked clams, whole ones covered with a sprinkle of buttery crumbs, and a noteworthy cold antipasto.</p>
        <p>Desserts are homemade and not to be missed. It was hard to choose between the warm flourless chocolate cake, the creamy tiramisù, the Italian cheesecake studded with candied fruit, the eclairs stuffed with vanilla ice cream and covered in a hot chocolate sauce, profiteroles filled with whipped cream, the creamy American cheesecake and the crunchy cannoli. My favorite, though, was a wedge of strawberry and chocolate mousse cake touted as ''low calorie'' on the menu. Although no calorie count was given -- and the restaurant could not supply one when I called later -- I managed to feel virtuous while indulging in a treat that knocked my socks off.</p>
        <p>La Viola</p>
        <p>499 Chestnut Street  Cedarhurst  (516) 569-6020  laviolarestaurant.com</p>
        <p>VERY GOOD</p>
        <p>THE SPACE -- Sprawling restaurant in a historic building. Not wheelchair accessible.</p>
        <p>THE CROWD -- Groups of friends and family members..</p>
        <p>THE BAR -- Wooden bar with a few tables. There is a list of 26 reasonably priced wines ($20 to $66).</p>
        <p>THE BILL -- Lunch entrees, $7 to $14.50. Three-course lunch, $9.95. Dinner entrees, $8.95 to $30.50 (lobster). Family-size platters, $16.75 to $65 (porterhouse for two). American Express, MasterCard and Visa are accepted.</p>
        <p>WHAT WE LIKE -- Baked clams, house salad, arugula and portobello mushrooms, Caesar salad, cold antipasto, tricolor salad, spaghetti with veal meatballs, cannelloni, linguine with clam sauce, eggplant parmigiana, veal and eggplant, stuffed salmon, broiled fillet of sole, all desserts.</p>
        <p>IF YOU GO -- Lunch: noon to 2:30 p.m. Monday through Friday. Dinner: 5:30 to 10 p.m. Monday through Saturday and 4:30 to 9:30 p.m. Sunday. Reservations for groups of eight or more only.</p>
        <p>Reviewed April 22, 2007</p>
        <p>DINING/CEDARHURST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
