<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Solo Act at the Top</title>
    <meta content="22GOVNJNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/22GOVNJ.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842102"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Golway, Terry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E4DA1F3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1356" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Solo Act at the Top</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Solo Act at the Top</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TERRY GOLWAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Golway, Terry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article, in light of serious injuries sustained in auto accident by New Jersey Jon Corzine, on unusual power that post holds; traces changes that have made governor must powerful elected official in state; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN New Jersey politics, there is the governor, and there's everybody else.</p>
        <p>There are no other statewide elected officials in Trenton competing for power and publicity. Governors appoint the state treasurer, the attorney general and county prosecutors. They have unusual control over public bodies like the Turnpike Authority. They can rewrite bills that have passed the Legislature, although the revisions are subject to legislative override.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Trenton awaits Gov. Jon S. Corzine’s return in a state where the governor’s office wields greater executive authority than any other state’s.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN New Jersey politics, there is the governor, and there's everybody else.</p>
        <p>There are no other statewide elected officials in Trenton competing for power and publicity. Governors appoint the state treasurer, the attorney general and county prosecutors. They have unusual control over public bodies like the Turnpike Authority. They can rewrite bills that have passed the Legislature, although the revisions are subject to legislative override.</p>
        <p>''It is the most powerful governorship in the country,'' said former Gov. Thomas H. Kean. ''When I was governor, my colleagues in the National Governors Association had a nickname for me: They called me Ayatollah Kean. They couldn't believe the powers I had.''</p>
        <p>One downside to such a singularly empowered office is that when a governor is incapacitated, the state's body politic loses its equilibrium. A little more than a week ago, Gov. Jon S. Corzine was critically injured in an auto accident and Senate President Richard J. Codey, a Democrat from Essex County, was once again summoned to duty as acting governor.</p>
        <p>The prognosis after a few days, however, was that Mr. Corzine would eventually recover, and Mr. Codey was not expected to initiate any major policies while Trenton waited for Mr. Corzine's return.</p>
        <p>There was a time when the state's political power brokers had little reason to adjust their calendars to accommodate the chief executive. Until 1947, New Jersey's governor was among the weakest in the country, a legacy of long-standing American suspicions of centralized power.</p>
        <p>Under the state's first Constitution, passed in a frenzy of patriotic fever in July 1776, legislators were instructed to ''elect some fit person within the Colony to be Governor.'' Ironically, the governor was also expected to serve as president of the Legislative Council -- the 18th-century version of today's State Senate. More than 225 years later, Mr. Codey is serving as both the state's chief executive, albeit temporarily, and as senate president -- and for the third time. He served in both posts for 14 months after Gov. James E. McGreevey resigned in 2004, and also during a four-day period before Mr. McGreevey took office in 2002.</p>
        <p>''The early governors were beholden to the Legislature, served one-year terms, and had no veto power,'' said Maxine N. Lurie, chairwoman of the history department at Seton Hall University in South Orange. ''It was a very weak office.''</p>
        <p>Despite those limitations, the state's first governor, William Livingston, was anything but weak. A strong patriot and propagandist who barely escaped several British raids on his home in today's Union Township during the Revolution, Livingston was particularly enthusiastic about his powers as commander in chief of the state's militia.</p>
        <p>''Livingston had been a militia general before his election, and as governor he took his role as commander in chief of New Jersey's military forces seriously,'' said Mark Edward Lender, chairman of the history department at Kean University in Union. ''He certainly contributed to the American tradition of civilian control of the military.''</p>
        <p>After Livingston died in office in 1790, New Jersey's governors were legislative figureheads until 1844, when a new Constitution allowed voters to choose a governor for a three-year term. ''But governors could not succeed themselves, and their vetoes could be overridden with a simply majority vote, so it was still a namby-pamby office,'' said Robert F. Williams, a professor at the Rutgers-Camden School of Law.</p>
        <p>Namby-pamby it remained decades into the 20th century, despite occasional protests from reformers like Woodrow Wilson, the only New Jersey governor to be elected president. Some politicians, however, apparently were satisfied with the status quo. Democrat A. Harry Moore was elected to three nonconsecutive terms in the 1920s and '30s. ''They say he used to get on the train to Trenton, look at his mail, and go home,'' former Gov. Brendan Byrne said with a laugh.</p>
        <p>With the twin emergencies of the Depression and World War II, however, demands for a stronger chief executive grew.</p>
        <p>Resisting those demands, Professor Lurie noted, was none other than Frank Hague, the legendary boss of Jersey City and Hudson County. He used the formidable powers at his disposal to thwart attempts in the early and mid-1940s to create a more powerful governor's office through constitutional change. Hague and other urban bosses had no interest in surrendering their power over patronage and appointments to a mere governor, particularly one they might not be able to control.</p>
        <p>Not coincidentally, two enemies of Hague were among the advocates for change. Governor Charles Edison, a Democrat who served from 1941 to 1944, and Republican Walter E. Edge, who had been governor from 1917 to 1919 and came out of retirement to serve again from 1944 to 1947, both tried in vain to win passage of a new Constitution. Finally, in 1947, New Jersey approved a new Constitution at the urging of Gov. Alfred E. Driscoll, a Republican who cut a shrewd deal with the Hague machine, ensuring its support for change.</p>
        <p>The new Constitution, which increased the length of term for governors to four years and allowed for re-election to a successive term, made the office what it is today -- the envy of the nation's other governors.</p>
        <p>''The Constitution of 1947 was a reaction against bosses, but it also was part of a spirit of the times,'' said the State Senate's minority leader, Leonard Lance, a Republican from Hunterdon County. ''We had just won World War II based on the strength of executives like Franklin Roosevelt and generals like Dwight Eisenhower. So the new Constitution made the governor's office into one of the strongest executives in the country.'' Senator Lance's father, Wesley L. Lance, is the last surviving delegate to the 1947 constitutional convention.</p>
        <p>New Jersey's politicians of today live with the legacy of an age that put its faith in strong executive power. Periodic calls for an elected comptroller or attorney general to serve as a check on the governor's power have inspired only inaction, though the state's voters recently approved the creation of an office of lieutenant governor beginning in 2010. The governor and Legislature also agreed to create the office of comptroller, although the position would be appointed by the governor. Even the measure that will establish a lieutenant governor was hardly designed to dilute the governor's power -- it was a reaction to the state's awkward succession law, which currently designates the Senate president as first in line to fill in for or succeed a sitting governor.</p>
        <p>''When you have all that power, you get all the credit, and all the blame,'' said former Gov. Christie Whitman, who served from 1994 to 2001. Mrs. Whitman said she believed that the greatest power she had in her arsenal was the conditional veto, which allows a governor to rewrite a bill, as long as the revisions are in the spirit of the legislation. The rewrites can be overridden, but it takes a two-thirds majority in the Legislature.</p>
        <p>Mr. Byrne, who served from 1974 to 1982, said: ''The nice thing about being governor of New Jersey is that everybody knows the governor is a powerful person, so the people know who does what. I'm happy to have it that way.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kean, who served from 1982 to 1990 and who is the last person to complete two full terms as the state's chief executive, recalled another example of his former office's wide-ranging powers.</p>
        <p>''I was trying to get a bill passed to protect wetlands, and it was stalled in the Senate because of pressure from builders,'' he said. ''Under the governor's emergency powers, I issued an executive order that stopped all building in the state. When I did that, the builders came around.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps not surprisingly, the former governors view the powers of their old job as a good thing.</p>
        <p>''You can look at an issue, decide that it's a problem you want to solve, and you don't have to worry about political rivalries,'' Mrs. Whitman said. ''That was a real strength of the office.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kean said: ''I went home every day thinking that I had really done something that day. There are very few political offices in the United States that you could say that about.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
