<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cupfuls of Creativity Season Traditional Italian</title>
    <meta content="22dinectCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/22dinect.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842035"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/GREENWICH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Solaia (Greenwich, Conn, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooks, Patricia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E0D61E3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="765" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cupfuls of Creativity Season Traditional Italian</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cupfuls of Creativity Season Traditional Italian</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA BROOKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooks, Patricia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patricia Brooks reviews Solaia restaurant in Greenwich, Conn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOLAIA, a new enoteca (wine bar) in Greenwich, is the second Italian restaurant I have visited within the last few weeks. Both have served appetizers of reasonable portions -- that is to say, small-to-moderate, not the gargantuan servings that are standard at all too many restaurants. I'd like to think this is a trend in the making, as most appetizers elsewhere are so huge they make the entrees that follow almost redundant.</p>
        <p>Not only are Solaia's starters of sensible size, they are also uniformly delicious, and there isn't a cliché among them. The short menu at Solaia (translated as ''sunny place,'' which is an odd name for a cellar location, even with its wide windows to the street) is refreshingly original. This is particularly evident in the starters, whether fried baby artichokes with Meyer lemon chips, shaved parmigiano and garlicky aioli or grape leaves wrapped around grilled goat's milk cheese with fresh herbs and marinated olives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The short menu at Solaia in Greenwich is refreshingly original.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOLAIA, a new enoteca (wine bar) in Greenwich, is the second Italian restaurant I have visited within the last few weeks. Both have served appetizers of reasonable portions -- that is to say, small-to-moderate, not the gargantuan servings that are standard at all too many restaurants. I'd like to think this is a trend in the making, as most appetizers elsewhere are so huge they make the entrees that follow almost redundant.</p>
        <p>Not only are Solaia's starters of sensible size, they are also uniformly delicious, and there isn't a cliché among them. The short menu at Solaia (translated as ''sunny place,'' which is an odd name for a cellar location, even with its wide windows to the street) is refreshingly original. This is particularly evident in the starters, whether fried baby artichokes with Meyer lemon chips, shaved parmigiano and garlicky aioli or grape leaves wrapped around grilled goat's milk cheese with fresh herbs and marinated olives.</p>
        <p>Absolutely exquisite were the stuffed squash blossoms -- two lightly battered and fried blossoms stuffed with ricotta in a delicate tomato coulis, augmented by a charred squash salad.</p>
        <p>Just as elegant was chilled spring pea soup. The bowl arrived with a ramekin of Maine crab meat salad with crispy pancetta and a black truffle vinaigrette in the center, over which the waiter poured an intensely flavored spring pea purée.</p>
        <p>Whether you order the polpette (a casserole of golf-ball-size veal-and-pork meatballs with ricotta in a light tomato sauce) or a small slab of tasty Berkshire bacon with braised mustard greens, roasted baby turnips and a fruit mostarda, you should be pleased with the results.</p>
        <p>The menu changes seasonally. One night I enjoyed quail, barbecued to a deep mahogany, served with coarse-ground polenta, radicchio and pickled mustard seeds; another time the bird was rubbed with paprika and rested on corn relish and grilled red onion slices.</p>
        <p>Your table may share, as ours did, a platter of salumi and formaggi. Again, a triumph. From a list of about 15 items, we chose culatello (dry cured ham), coppa (cured pork with black peppercorns) and cacciatorini al vino rosso (small pork salami marinated in red wine), combined with garroxta (a nutty Catalan goat's milk cheese) and Ossau Iraty (a sweet raw sheep's milk cheese from the French Pyrenees).</p>
        <p>While the entrees are more predictable, each is garnished with appetite-tweaking elements. Wild striped bass arrived with a Napoleon of eggplant caviar layered between sheaves of crisply fried eggplant rounds, with a side of yellow tomato chutney.</p>
        <p>Four pastas are on the menu. I especially liked the hand-cut pappardelle creamed with braised rabbit bits, cracked pepper, sharp green Picholine olives, tomato and fresh rosemary. Almost as luscious was the housemade ravioli stuffed with fresh veal and spinach in a Sicilian pistachio sauce.</p>
        <p>All desserts are winsome, but none matched the citrus-laced cannoli (crisp, paper thin), rich with goat's milk cheese and mascarpone, served with poached rhubarb and pistachio brittle. An ethereal pomegranate sorbet was a close second.</p>
        <p>With its nuova cucina, Solaia is an exciting addition to Greenwich's already diverse restaurant scene.</p>
        <p>Solaia</p>
        <p>363 Greenwich Avenue  Greenwich  (203) 622-6400</p>
        <p>EXCELLENT</p>
        <p>THE SPACE -- Long, low, all-white and below ground-level, with a bar and a few tables in front, a long banquette and more tables in the rear; sophisticatedly furnished with handsome wooden chairs, soft lighting, wine racks and wine case inserts in wooden tabletops. Four steps down to restaurant level; wheelchair accessibility from the restaurant's rear (call ahead).</p>
        <p>THE CROWD -- Well-dressed business foursomes, couples and office groups; an after-work gathering place. Servers are friendly, well-informed and professional.</p>
        <p>THE BAR -- A full bar, slightly separated from the rear dining area, with a comprehensive Italian wine list and a smaller list of French, American, Australian, New Zealand and South American wines. Bottle prices begin at $30; by the glass from $9 to $82.</p>
        <p>THE BILL -- Lunch: entrees, $13 to $22; three-course prix fixe lunch, $19.95. Dinner: appetizers, $12 to $14; entrees, $21 to $42; desserts, $8 to $10; chef's seven-course tasting menu, $85. Almost all credit cards are accepted.</p>
        <p>WHAT WE LIKE -- All appetizers; hand-cut pappardelle, wild striped bass, pork saltimbocca, hanger steak, housemade ravioli; all desserts, especially citrus-laced cannoli and pomegranate sorbet.</p>
        <p>IF YOU GO -- Lunch: noon to 3 p.m. Monday to Saturday. Sunday brunch: noon to 3 p.m. Dinner: 5 to 10 p.m. Monday to Thursday; 5 to 11 p.m. Friday and Saturday; 5 to 9 p.m. Sunday. Meter parking along Greenwich Avenue.</p>
        <p>Reviewed April 22, 2007</p>
        <p>DINING/GREENWICH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
