<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Playwright's Progress</title>
    <meta content="22artsnjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/22artsnj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842089"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Arts and Entertainment"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Luna Stage</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marshall, Jeanne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooks, Romaine (1874-1970)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baranauckas, Carla</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Little Beasts (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">luna stage</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500EEDB1F3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="663" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Playwright's Progress</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Playwright’s Progress</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARLA BARANAUCKAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Baranauckas, Carla</byline>
      <dateline>Montclair</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of and interview with Jeanne Marshall, playwright-in-residence and public relations director at Luna Stage in Montclair, NJ; Marshall is preparing her third premiere at Luna, drama Little Beasts, about painter Romaine Brooks; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JEANNE MARSHALL has been a storyteller most of her life.</p>
        <p>''I was a pathological liar as a child,'' Ms. Marshall said. ''So my mother said, 'You can be a con artist or a writer.' ''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As she grows into her role in the theater, Jeanne Marshall draws attention to other women’s artistic achievements.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JEANNE MARSHALL has been a storyteller most of her life.</p>
        <p>''I was a pathological liar as a child,'' Ms. Marshall said. ''So my mother said, 'You can be a con artist or a writer.' ''</p>
        <p>It's no secret that Ms. Marshall, 49, the playwright-in-residence at Luna Stage here, where she is also the public relations director, chose the second path. But for a long time she felt that she still had a bit of the con artist in her.</p>
        <p>''I didn't call myself a playwright until 'Burying Fiona,' '' she said of her comedy about life, death and family secrets that had its premiere at Luna in 1999.</p>
        <p>But it wasn't until the following year, with the premiere at Luna of her drama ''Rapture'' -- about the 17th-century composer Lucrezia Vizzana, who was a cloistered nun -- that Ms. Marshall began to feel that she actually deserved the title.</p>
        <p>Now Ms. Marshall is preparing her third premiere at Luna, the drama ''Little Beasts,'' about the painter Romaine Brooks, which runs April 26 to May 20. It is the second play in a trilogy about women in the arts who did remarkable work, although their names have been all but forgotten. The third play in the trilogy, about the actress Laurette Taylor, who played Amanda Wingfield in the original Broadway production of Tennessee Williams's ''Glass Menagerie,'' is in development.</p>
        <p>Ms. Marshall, who lives in Bloomfield, describes herself as a ''binge writer'' who might write a first draft in one sitting. She said she brought a ''sense of abandon'' to the writing process for ''Little Beasts.'' In the play she explores how memory and reality converge and diverge.</p>
        <p>''We carry with us these incredible memories,'' she said. ''But what is real?'' Those memories, real or fabricated, often make themselves known through voices in the head -- the ''little beasts'' of the title.</p>
        <p>''We create the memories that we need,'' Ms. Marshall said.</p>
        <p>In ''Little Beasts,'' which is set in the 1920s, Romaine Brooks is forced to choose between the demons from her childhood with an emotionally abusive mother and a mentally ill brother and her relationship with the salon hostess Natalie Clifford Barney -- or put another way, between memory and reality.</p>
        <p>Ms. Marshall calls the theater ''the best place to be a writer'' and urges her students in a playwriting workshop she teaches there to ''trust in the collaborative process.''</p>
        <p>''Little Beasts'' is her third collaboration with Jane Mandel, Luna's artistic director, who is directing the play. But one of the actresses in the play, Kathleen Marsh, is even more familiar with the playwright, because Ms. Marshall is her sister.</p>
        <p>As the oldest of four children, Kathleen enlisted Jeanne, their brother, Pete, and their sister Suzanne to perform in backyard play productions. Jeanne Marshall credits her mother, Reba Marie Marshall, a painter and art instructor, with nurturing her children's artistic endeavors.</p>
        <p>''She created in such a sane way that it always grounded us,'' said the playwright, whose family lived in four different states while she was in high school. ''We were encouraged to do anything that we wanted.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Marshall's mother, who lives in Newton and Fort Myers, Fla., has also painted a group of 12 portraits that will be exhibited in the Luna Stage lobby during the play's run. Called ''Many Daughters,'' the exhibition showcases her daughters and the women with whom she has a mother-daughter-like relationship.</p>
        <p>When ''Little Beasts'' has its formal opening on April 28, after two preview performances, Ms. Marshall does not expect to be nervous. She plans to be sitting in the lobby of the theater -- she does not sit in the audience unless there are unsold seats -- surrounded by her mother's paintings, listening for the audience reaction.</p>
        <p>''Something in a good play stays with you forever,'' she said, ''and that's what I want to effect in people.''</p>
        <p>''Little Beasts'' runs from April 26 to May 20 at Luna Stage, 695 Bloomfield Avenue, Montclair. Information: (973) 744-3309 or www.lunastage.org.</p>
        <p>Arts and Entertainment</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
