<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Russians Still Think Boldly</title>
    <meta content="22myers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/weekinreview/22myers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842243"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/Siberia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Russia</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Bering Strait</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Siberia</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Putin, Vladimir V</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EFD9163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="646" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Russians Still Think Boldly</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Where Russians Still Think Boldly</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN LEE MYERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Myers, Steven Lee</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHUKOTKA is at the edge of the earth, one of Russia's most remote and impoverished regions, a frozen expanse bigger than Texas, with a population that could fit in the Astrodome.</p>
        <p>Like much of Russia's Far North, the vast arc of tundra and permafrost above the Arctic Circle, it has captured the imaginations of czars and general secretaries and now a new generation of leaders. For centuries they have aspired to conquer its unforgiving isolation, often with schemes that defy the imagination.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A place of explorers, adventurers and survivors, Chukotka is one of Russia’s most remote regions, but its tiny population has some big ideas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CHUKOTKA is at the edge of the earth, one of Russia's most remote and impoverished regions, a frozen expanse bigger than Texas, with a population that could fit in the Astrodome.</p>
        <p>Like much of Russia's Far North, the vast arc of tundra and permafrost above the Arctic Circle, it has captured the imaginations of czars and general secretaries and now a new generation of leaders. For centuries they have aspired to conquer its unforgiving isolation, often with schemes that defy the imagination.</p>
        <p>The latest such scheme emerged last week with a proposal to link Chukotka to Alaska by building a 63-mile tunnel under the icy waters of the Bering Strait -- a man-made rejoining of the two continents. Pointing out that the tunnel would essentially begin and end nowhere (Chukotka has few roads, let alone railroads) misses the essential point of the Arctic's place in the Russian soul.</p>
        <p>It is a place of explorers, adventurers and survivors, of endurance, tradition and ambition. The tunnel idea evoked the grand designs the Soviet Union crafted to unlock the natural resources of Siberia by decree and, in the beginning at least, with the subjugated labor of the gulag.</p>
        <p>That legacy, clearly, lives on, but other, less pie-in-the-ice ideas are incubating in Chukotka. The World Wildlife Fund has created a project with native Chukchi hunters to protect the region's polar bears, now endangered by the threats of a changing climate and rampant poaching.</p>
        <p>In Vankarem, a tiny coastal village on the Chukchi Sea, hunters established a ''bear patrol'' last year with the intent of keeping a safe distance between villagers and the growing number of bears that come ashore as they migrate in search of their preferred environs, floating sea ice.</p>
        <p>''We would like to have every village on the migration route be involved,'' said Sergei I. Kavry, the patrol's leader, who dreams of reviving native cultural traditions that all but died under Soviet rule.</p>
        <p>It is an increasingly rare instance of Russian civic political organization -- in the Siberia of exile, no less. Such activism is viewed with increasing suspicion in Vladimir V. Putin's realm. Perhaps given Chukotka's location, nine time zones east of Moscow, the Kremlin's heavy hand seems a distant thing.</p>
        <p>No less ambitious has been the effort of Chukotka's governor, Roman A. Abramovich, to lift the region out of the poverty and desolation it found itself in after the Soviet Union collapsed in the 1990s.</p>
        <p>He is Russia's richest man, an oil tycoon turned investor who owns the Chelsea Football Club in London (where he clearly prefers to live). Since being elected governor in 2000 and reappointed by Mr. Putin in 2005, he has revived the region -- in large part with money raised by the personal income tax he pays there and two charities he has created. He has largely rebuilt Chukotka's homes and hospitals.</p>
        <p>Next up is the economy, which is still dependent on government subsidies for fuel, food and jobs because the harsh winters and only slightly less harsh summers make life in Chukotka virtually unsustainable.</p>
        <p>''The governor has a goal of making Chukotka self-sufficient within the next few years,'' his American spokesman, John A. Mann, said. ''To do that, you have to develop natural resources and bring in investments. It is not the easiest thing to do.''</p>
        <p>Certainly not. During the cold war, Chukotka was a closed border zone, bristling with military installations that are now abandoned lots filled with the rusting detritus of Soviet power. Government permission is still required before a visit, but the Arctic beckons and is, slowly, opening itself to the possibilities of a new Russia.</p>
        <p>In the middle of an overland journey across Chukotka's windswept snow and ice, two all-terrain track vehicles carrying the World Wildlife Fund's researchers to Vankarem encountered a convoy of snowmobiles headed north. Riding them were entrepreneurs with another notion: extreme tourism.</p>
        <p>THE WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
