<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After the Storm, a Sigh of Relief</title>
    <meta content="22weekliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/22weekli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842075"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coastal Erosion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dextromethorpan (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Fire Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hamptons (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Suffolk County (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Suffolk County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nowick, Lynne C (County Legislator)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stern, Steven H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Jon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saslow, Linda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/Fire Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/The Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E5DF1F3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1052" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After the Storm, a Sigh of Relief</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Week on Long Island</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA SASLOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Saslow, Linda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>The Week column; Long Island officials, despite damage to homes on Fire Island, flooding on South Shore and beach erosion in Hamptons, express relief after recent storm; Suffolk County lawmaker Lynne Nowick, citing growing incidence of teenagers overdosing on cough syrup or cold medicines containing dextromethorphan, introduces bill to ban sale of medicines to those 18 or younger; Suffolk County Legislators Steven Stern and Jon Cooper file proposal to authorize parks commissioner to identify at least five new sites for fenced-in dog runs in county parks; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The word most often used by Long Island officials after last Sunday's storm was ''lucky.'' Though beaches were eroded and some homes were seriously damaged, they agreed: It could have been much worse.</p>
        <p>As Jim Callahan, commissioner of the Nassau County Office of Emergency Management, put it, ''The storm went further west than had been predicted, and we didn't get the brunt of rain and winds.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The word most often used by Long Island officials after last Sunday’s storm was “lucky.” Though beaches were eroded and some homes were seriously damaged, they agreed: It could have been much worse.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The word most often used by Long Island officials after last Sunday's storm was ''lucky.'' Though beaches were eroded and some homes were seriously damaged, they agreed: It could have been much worse.</p>
        <p>As Jim Callahan, commissioner of the Nassau County Office of Emergency Management, put it, ''The storm went further west than had been predicted, and we didn't get the brunt of rain and winds.''</p>
        <p>The areas most affected in Nassau, Mr. Callahan said, were villages that were flooded by seawater; they included Bayville, Centre Island, Freeport and Island Park.</p>
        <p>The county's emergency operations center, which opened at 10 a.m. on the day of the storm, was staffed by people from 20 local, state, county and federal agencies.</p>
        <p>''We provided a generator for the Centre Island Police Department and pumps in Bayville,'' Mr. Callahan said. ''We set up three shelters in response to a voluntary evacuation in Bayville and Centre Island, but only a few people showed up. Similarly, we set up an evacuation center in Valley Stream for residents of Long Beach and Island Park, but no one came.</p>
        <p>''Overall, it turned out to be a very good exercise, in the event a hurricane ever comes.''</p>
        <p>In Suffolk County, Fire Island suffered the most damage, according to Joe Williams, commissioner of the county's Office of Emergency Management. In Davis Park, ''there are between six and eight homes that are in jeopardy of falling down and may not be able to be lived in again,'' he said.</p>
        <p>There was also considerable flooding on the South Shore, particularly in Lindenhurst and Amityville, and beach erosion in the Hamptons, but no evacuations were ordered.</p>
        <p>Mr. Williams, like many others, expressed relief, adding, ''It's not what it could have been.''</p>
        <p>The Island's parks were also spared the devastation that had been anticipated.</p>
        <p>Scott Fish, director of engineering for the Long Island region of the State Office of Parks, Recreation and Historic Preservation, said the worst damage was at Orient Beach State Park, where four sections of the entrance road caved in and needed immediate attention. Heckscher and Captree State Parks also suffered heavy erosion, and Robert Moses State Park lost some beach frontage, but the problems there were less urgent, he said.</p>
        <p>The biggest problem on the Island's state roads was at the Wantagh State Parkway, which was closed Sunday afternoon because of flooding. It reopened at 4:30 p.m. on Monday.</p>
        <p>Eileen Peters, a spokeswoman for the State Department of Transportation, said traffic was diverted to the Meadowbrook Parkway to the west and the Robert Moses Causeway to the east for Monday morning's rush.</p>
        <p>Curbing Cough Syrup Misuse</p>
        <p>A growing incidence of teenagers' overdosing on cough syrup or cold medicines containing dextromethorphan (DXM) has prompted the introduction of a bill in the Suffolk County Legislature to ban the sale of the medicines to those 18 or younger.</p>
        <p>Legislator Lynne C. Nowick of Saint James sponsored the bill, with the support of 12 other legislators. Over-the-counter medicines containing DXM include Robitussin and Coricidin.</p>
        <p>Ms. Nowick said that cases of Long Island teenagers being taken to the hospital after overdosing on the medicines tripled from 2000 to 2006.</p>
        <p>''Based on statistics from the Long Island poison control, there were 40 reported cases in 2000, of which 20 necessitated hospitalization,'' she said. ''In 2006, that number jumped to 76, with 62 hospitalizations.''</p>
        <p>DXM is a cough suppressant found in more than 100 cold remedies. Taken in excess, it can accelerate a person's heart rate and cause hallucinations.</p>
        <p>The County Legislature was to conduct a public hearing on the bill on Tuesday; it could come to a vote as early as May 15. If it is approved, businesses that intentionally sell the medications to anyone 18 or under would be subject to fines, with the amounts suggested at $500 for a first offense and up to $750 for each subsequent offense.</p>
        <p>In 2004, State Senator Dean G. Skelos of Rockville Centre introduced a bill to make it a Class B misdemeanor statewide for any retailer to sell two or more containers of medications containing DXM to people under 18. The bill has been held up in the Assembly.</p>
        <p>Ms. Nowick said that while she applauded Senator Skelos for his proposed legislation, ''I don't believe it goes far enough, because kids can go from one counter to another and find ways to buy more than one container of these medications.''</p>
        <p>A Call for More Dog Runs</p>
        <p>Suffolk County's lone dog run will have lots of company if a legislative proposal to add more public runs in county parks wins approval next month.</p>
        <p>On April 11, County Legislators Steven H. Stern of Huntington and Jon Cooper of Lloyd Harbor filed a proposal to authorize the county parks commissioner to identify at least five new sites in the next 120 days that would become fenced-in areas of two to five acres where dogs could run free.</p>
        <p>Currently, the only enclosed dog run in Suffolk is at West Hills County Park in Huntington. Runs are planned at another two parks, Blydenburgh County Park in Hauppaugue and Coindre Hall Park in Huntington. Five county parks allow dogs to be walked on a leash no longer than six feet.</p>
        <p>Nassau County, in contrast, has four fenced-in dog runs at county parks; another park allows dog walking.</p>
        <p>''With tens of thousands of park acres and 600,000 dog owners in the county, it is outrageous to have only one dog run,'' Mr. Cooper said. ''Dog owners now come all the way from Montauk to use the dog run in Huntington.''</p>
        <p>The county hopes to add new runs that will be more evenly spread out, he said.</p>
        <p>The one remaining question is how to define a fenced-in run, Mr. Cooper said. ''Can we use a natural barrier like bushes or water?''</p>
        <p>Suffolk County's parks commissioner, Ronald F. Foley, said the anticipated cost of building a dog run was between $15,000 and $20,000, mostly for fencing. He said that he had not yet considered using natural borders, but added that ''trees are not much of a barrier.''</p>
        <p>''There is a definite need for such areas,'' Mr. Foley said. But each run has to be selected properly, he added, ''in recognition of the unique characteristics of the specific park and its location.''</p>
        <p>THE WEEK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
