<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When The Group Is Wise</title>
    <meta content="22carey" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Health; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/weekinreview/22carey.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842240"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Virginia</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cho Seung-Hui</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Alameddine, Ross Abdallah</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0D9163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1133" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When The Group Is Wise</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">When the Group Is Wise</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BENEDICT CAREY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carey, Benedict</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SEUNG-HUI CHO seemed indifferent to every small act of human kindness, any effort to connect.</p>
        <p>According to classmates of Mr. Cho, the Virginia Tech killer, one student made several attempts to speak to him, even after reading his frightening writings. Mr. Cho's suitemates, and some teachers, too, made an effort to engage him. And there were undoubtedly others. Maybe they signaled their openness with a slight nod, a friendly widening of the eyes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The tragedy in Blacksburg, Va., illustrates how human social groups, whether in classrooms, boardrooms or dormitories, are in fact exquisitely sensitive to a threat in their midst.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SEUNG-HUI CHO seemed indifferent to every small act of human kindness, any effort to connect.</p>
        <p>According to classmates of Mr. Cho, the Virginia Tech killer, one student made several attempts to speak to him, even after reading his frightening writings. Mr. Cho's suitemates, and some teachers, too, made an effort to engage him. And there were undoubtedly others. Maybe they signaled their openness with a slight nod, a friendly widening of the eyes.</p>
        <p>Those acts of genuine decency failed to prevent Mr. Cho's rampage on Monday. But the tragedy in Blacksburg, Va., illustrates how human social groups, whether in classrooms, boardrooms or dormitories, are in fact exquisitely sensitive to a threat in their midst, and act in ways both conscious and unconscious to test how dangerous it is. Take a step back, and the peer group can be seen as a single organism that recoils from a threat, then sends out feelers, in the form of overtures from its members, to gauge whether danger is imminent or might be reduced.</p>
        <p>The Blacksburg case suggests just how this process typically works, and highlights its strengths as well as its limits in preventing a crisis.</p>
        <p>After this shooting (and most school and workplace rampages, big and small), forensic experts quickly and properly cautioned that no profile of a rampage killer exists. Most predatory killers score very highly on the most rigorously tested measure to predict violence, the so-called psychopathy checklist; but many who do not commit crimes also score high.</p>
        <p>Yet out in the world, no one uses questionnaires or diagnostic manuals to check out a stranger or an acquaintance. People read the other person's body language, tone of voice; they read between the lines of what is said. They absorb most of this information instantly, unconsciously, and often accurately, studies suggest. And they sometimes get the creeps -- for reasons they might not be able to explain right away.</p>
        <p>The evidence that this happened over the months and years before the shooting in Blacksburg is now abundant. After hearing Mr. Cho read one of his sinister poems in a creative-writing class, dozens of his classmates did not show up the next time the class met, so as to avoid the young man, according to the teacher. This is what most human social groups do, when they collectively register a threat: they move away, socially and often literally.</p>
        <p>The thousands of years that early humans lived in small, fragile kin groups helped shape their instinct for social distancing, anthropologists say. A person who steals, who lies or who incites fights is a direct threat not only to those lured into confrontations but also to the coherence and ultimate survival of the group itself.</p>
        <p>''Social stigma is rooted in part in a concern for social predictability,'' said Robert Kurzban, a psychologist at the University of Pennsylvania. ''One thing that's crucial in groups, particularly small groups, is cooperation, and if someone is unpredictable, they don't cooperate or coordinate well and represent a group threat. So people look out for such individuals.''</p>
        <p>To guard against a real threat, this instinct is naturally conservative. It flags as potentially threatening many people who aren't, as millions of people living with mental illness have experienced firsthand.</p>
        <p>In some ancient societies and religious communities, the rules that guided how to manage a person thought to be dangerous were very explicit, said David Sloan Wilson, an evolutionary biologist at the State University of New York at Binghamton and the author of ''Evolution for Everyone.'' Bad gossip, followed by a rebuke, then ostracism. Each stage sets in motion more isolation. This escalating discipline protects the community but is also intended to bring about a change of heart in the outcast.</p>
        <p>Finally, if such a change isn't forthcoming, there is expulsion. ''For some nomadic cultures, it was as simple as saying, 'O.K., you go this way, we're going that way,' '' Dr. Wilson said.</p>
        <p>Modern societies are -- blessedly, for most people -- far more tolerant. Their justice systems are less likely to be swayed by hearsay, or claims of possession and superstition. People perceived as threatening have some civil rights, and as the Virginia Tech case showed, the authorities are limited in what they can do if a person of interest hasn't actually made threats or attacks.</p>
        <p>Still, the peer group is tracking the person carefully and, deliberately or not, doing its own tests for a threat.</p>
        <p>For some 20 years, Lawrence Palinkas, a professor of social work at the University of Southern California, has studied the social networks that form like crystals among work teams who spend the winter together in scientific missions in Antarctica. The groups, which range in size from a dozen people to nearly 200, very often have at least one outcast. That person may be simply unlucky, picked on by influential people central to the group. But often the person helps define the identities of those who make up the group's core.</p>
        <p>''It's a stable situation, because in a way that isolated person helps define a group; people look at him and can say, 'I'm not like him, someone who doesn't fit in,' '' Dr. Palinkas said.</p>
        <p>It often happens, Dr. Palinkas has found, that another group member makes an investment and helps reel the outcast back in. But this is much more likely to succeed when the main group is a cohesive one, like a team or work crew with a tightly bound inner core, Dr. Palinkas said. ''If it's a group that is split into factions, diffuse, not well integrated, then it is very hard to integrate the isolates,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Large college campuses tend to be tolerant, fluid, self-enclosed societies, where almost anyone can find a niche. The peer group around Mr. Cho, even as he avoided direct eye contact, seemed to be extending a tentacle now and then, to see if the young man was ready to find his own place. The student who tried to talk to Mr. Cho in English class, Ross Alameddine, made several attempts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cho ignored every one, and many more from others who were less patient.</p>
        <p>Debate will undoubtedly continue about what could have, or should have, been done by university officials, campus police officers or the Virginia mental health system. Teachers will have their say, as will administrators.</p>
        <p>But it is clear from interviews that many of Mr. Cho's peers knew in their guts the danger the young man presented. They sent up alarms, even while watching him. They kept their distance, as a natural protective instinct.</p>
        <p>And through the spirit of people like Mr. Alameddine, who would become one of the random shooting victims, they continued to send out feelers: small human invitations that, in the shadow of what was to come, now look very large indeed.</p>
        <p>THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
