<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Corzine's Rehab Could Free Him For Policy Issues</title>
    <meta content="22polsnjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/22polsnj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842103"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON POLITICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chen, David W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E4DA1F3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="860" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Corzine's Rehab Could Free Him For Policy Issues</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Corzine’s Rehab Could Free Him for Policy Issues</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David W. Chen</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chen, David W</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Chen On Politics column, in light of injuries sustained in car accident and necessary rehab, holds New Jersey Governor Jon Corzine could be spared from fulfilling ceremonial and political duties and spend more time immersing himself in state's business; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GIVEN the extent of Gov. Jon S. Corzine's injuries, it appeared unlikely late last week that he would be resuming his hectic schedule as the state's chief executive officer anytime soon.</p>
        <p>It could be weeks. It could be months. It could be a year before he would be able to fill his daily calendar once again with the events, ceremonial meetings and the political dinners that can keep a New Jersey governor regularly traveling from one corner of the state to another.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>TRENTON.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GIVEN the extent of Gov. Jon S. Corzine's injuries, it appeared unlikely late last week that he would be resuming his hectic schedule as the state's chief executive officer anytime soon.</p>
        <p>It could be weeks. It could be months. It could be a year before he would be able to fill his daily calendar once again with the events, ceremonial meetings and the political dinners that can keep a New Jersey governor regularly traveling from one corner of the state to another.</p>
        <p>But maybe, for Mr. Corzine, and the people of New Jersey, restricting his ability to fulfill many of his ceremonial and political duties might not be such a terrible thing.</p>
        <p>Perhaps, Mr. Corzine may be afforded a rarity for most politicians these days: more time to immerse himself in the state's business, to thumb through arcane policy papers and budget documents, and to come up with new policies and ideas.</p>
        <p>After all, there is no shortage of pressing and complicated issues demanding attention.</p>
        <p>Just this past week, the State Commission of Investigation accused a state subsidy program for hospitals of being riddled with fraud and waste to the tune of tens of millions of dollars in losses each year. The state's labor commissioner told legislators that the state's fund for unemployment benefits has dropped to only $260 million from $3.1 billion five years ago, because of past practices of siphoning money away to help balance the budget.</p>
        <p>And the state treasurer, Bradley I. Abelow, testified before the Assembly's budget committee about accounting practices used in the state pension fund prior to the Corzine administration.</p>
        <p>People tend to forget that a big part of the governor's job description is performing ceremonial or constitutional functions. That means waving to residents at parades on Main Street, delivering speeches to trade associations, reading to children in schools and libraries.</p>
        <p>Then there is the sheer volume of political commitments. As the only elected statewide official, at least until the office of the lieutenant governor is created, the governor is also the titular head of his or her party. There are always county chairmen and chairwomen to appease, new mayors to meet, national candidates to raise money for. Not to mention the endless opportunities for political dinners on any given evening.</p>
        <p>Since the medical experts were saying late last week that Mr. Corzine would have limited mobility for some time, he could decline requests that might have been impolite for him to reject before.</p>
        <p>If so, he might be able to turn his full attention to the central issues that he cares deeply about, like the leasing of toll roads, a new school financing formula or universal health care.</p>
        <p>''As the governor is rehabilitating, I believe he will be in charge,'' said William G. Dressel Jr., executive director of the New Jersey State League of Municipalities, and a 30-year veteran of Trenton politics. ''In fact he will probably have more time to spend on policy with the less demanding schedule he will have.''</p>
        <p>In a typical election year for the Legislature -- like 2007 -- almost half of a governor's time could be spent on political activities like fund-raisers and postdinner rallies, said Carl Golden, a former spokesman for Governors Thomas H. Kean and Christie Whitman.</p>
        <p>Another 20 percent, perhaps, could be devoted to ceremonial activities with a dash of policy, like a ribbon-cutting event at a local school that also happens to mention an educational goal. That does not leave much time for the nitty-gritty of state business, and focusing on policies and legislative initiatives, Mr. Golden said.</p>
        <p>''He can conduct business without being distracted by something like, 'I have to leave this budget meeting because I have to meet with six county chairmen in Cape May,' '' he said. ''But he has to be careful, as he does that, to not create a perception that he's ceding some of the power of the office.''</p>
        <p>Consider, for instance, Governor Corzine's packed schedule on April 12, the day of his auto accident on the Garden State Parkway.</p>
        <p>First, he attended the funeral of a Federal Bureau of Investigation agent in Pottstown, Pa. Then he brokered a peace between two rival Democratic camps in Hackensack. Then, he had two events in Atlantic City, including a speech to members of the New Jersey Conference of Mayors. Last up was a meeting at Drumthwacket between the former talk-show radio host Don Imus and the Rutgers women's basketball team.</p>
        <p>Of all those events, you could argue that the only one he had to attend was the funeral. For the Bergen County announcement, perhaps he could have dispatched Assemblyman Joseph Cryan, the state Democratic party chairman? For the others, perhaps a cabinet official or other surrogate, like Mr. Codey, may have sufficed?</p>
        <p>Of course, Corzine administration officials may be reluctant to rely too much on Mr. Codey. While Mr. Corzine and Mr. Codey have been allies on many issues since Mr. Corzine took office in January 2006, it does not make political sense for the Corzine camp to give the New Jersey public even more of a reason to love Mr. Codey, the state's most popular politician.</p>
        <p>ON POLITICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
