<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Affordable Europe: St. Petersburg</title>
    <meta content="22stpeteweb" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/travel/22stpeteweb.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842339"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">St Petersburg (Russia)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/St. Petersburg</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">St Petersburg (Russia)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E0D61631F931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="560" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Affordable Europe: St. Petersburg</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Affordable Europe: St. Petersburg</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD J. LEVY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ignore all those tales of nouveau riche fat cats guzzling Champagne in gilded hotels. Many of St. Petersburg's glories -- wondrous architecture, enchanting canals and an enveloping sense of history -- are free or relatively cheap. The city even deploys young English-speaking guides in the historic center in the summer to help tourists, at no charge. Grumpy Communist apparatchiks, they are not.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay for Under 125 Euros</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many of St. Petersburg’s glories  wondrous architecture, enchanting canals and an enveloping sense of history  are free or relatively cheap.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ignore all those tales of nouveau riche fat cats guzzling Champagne in gilded hotels. Many of St. Petersburg's glories -- wondrous architecture, enchanting canals and an enveloping sense of history -- are free or relatively cheap. The city even deploys young English-speaking guides in the historic center in the summer to help tourists, at no charge. Grumpy Communist apparatchiks, they are not.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay for Under 125 Euros</p>
        <p>Like the length of the day here in this former imperial capital, hotel rates fluctuate sharply. Prices soar in the summer, when a good bet is Nevsky Mayak (7-812-272-2342; www.nmhotel.ru/eng/index.html). Unmarked and tucked away in a courtyard near the city's main boulevard, Nevsky Prospect, it has 12 rooms and a fetching little lobby. The rooms are small and nothing fancy, but clean. In high season, they start at 2,500 rubles, or about $96, at 26.50 rubles to the dollar. In the off-season, relatively upscale hotels can be affordable, like the Petro Palace Hotel (7-812-571-3006; www.petropalacehotel.com) and the Hotel Pushka Inn (7-812-312-0913; www.pushkainn.ru), both of which are ideally situated near Palace Square and the enormous St. Isaac's Cathedral. Rooms at both are as low as 2,500 rubles in the winter.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat  Brush aside Brezhnev-era notions about the paucity and quality of Russian food. It is not hard to find surprisingly tasty, affordable meals in St. Petersburg, beginning with the ubiquitous blini kiosks run by companies like Teremok, where a freshly made cheese blini is about 40 rubles. For classic Russian food, theTolstiy Fraerpub offers well-prepared favorites for under 250 rubles, from beef stroganoff to dumplings. Vodka arrives the Russian way: room temperature in a beaker, with chilled glasses and a plate of snacks that includes smoked fish and an addictive dried black bread with the flavor of croutons. There are five locations, one very close to the Hermitage Museum, at 1 Kirpichny Pereulok (7-812-314-5921).</p>
        <p>Where to Shop  Take the subway -- no matter what you do, at 14 rubles, it shouldn't be missed, with endless escalators that descend into charming, unsubway-like stations. Get off at the Udelnaya stop, where on Sundays the city's largest open-air flea market takes place. It's both a market with traditional vendors and a sprawling garage sale, as people spread out blankets and offer all sorts of treasures, knickknacks and junk. If you are looking for Soviet and other historic memorabilia, this is the place, but be leery of fakes. That supposed war veteran who just sold you his medals may have also sold the same ones last week.</p>
        <p>Best Money-Saving Tip  With its czarist-era palaces and monuments and boulevards, St. Petersburg is a wonderful city for wandering. But if you find those Cyrillic signs daunting, Peter's Walking Tours (www.peterswalk.com) offers all sorts of jaunts, typically at only 400 rubles a person, with some focused on themes like the Communist legacy, the Siege of Leningrad or Dostoyevsky. The tours typically last three or four hours, and have the feel of an informal stroll with a friend. The young guides speak excellent English and know not only the history behind the major sites, but also the city's nooks and crannies. When your legs get tired, head over to the Beloselsky-Belozersky Palace at 41 Nevsky Prospect, where splendid classical music concerts are regularly held, with tickets as low as 125 rubles.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
