<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What to Do While Awaiting That N.F.L. Call</title>
    <meta content="22colliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/22colli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842015"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE ISLAND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arena Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New England Patriots</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Dragons</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davey, Rohan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kilgannon, Corey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New England Patriots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E6D91E3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="837" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What to Do While Awaiting That N.F.L. Call</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">What to Do While Awaiting That N.F.L. Call</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Corey Kilgannon</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kilgannon, Corey</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONDALE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Corey Kilgannon The Island column on Rohan Davey, former New England Patriots player who is starting quarterback for Arena Football League's New York Dragons; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF the idea of being a professional quarterback in New York sounds glorious and glamorous, you should have seen Rohan Davey last Sunday afternoon after the New York Dragons game at the Nassau Coliseum.</p>
        <p>The Dragons -- Long Island's team in the Arena Football League -- lost a last-second heartbreaker to the Colorado Crush after Mr. Davey, the Dragons' starting quarterback, threw an interception in the final seconds. The Dragons had closed a 12-point halftime deficit and trailed by 1 with 27 seconds left when Mr. Davey spotted a receiver streaking toward the end zone. But his pass was picked off, and the Dragons lost, 49-48, dropping their record to 1 win and 5 losses and all but dashing their playoff hopes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If the idea of being a professional quarterback in New York sounds glorious, you should have seen Rohan Davey last Sunday after the New York Dragons game at the Nassau Coliseum.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF the idea of being a professional quarterback in New York sounds glorious and glamorous, you should have seen Rohan Davey last Sunday afternoon after the New York Dragons game at the Nassau Coliseum.</p>
        <p>The Dragons -- Long Island's team in the Arena Football League -- lost a last-second heartbreaker to the Colorado Crush after Mr. Davey, the Dragons' starting quarterback, threw an interception in the final seconds. The Dragons had closed a 12-point halftime deficit and trailed by 1 with 27 seconds left when Mr. Davey spotted a receiver streaking toward the end zone. But his pass was picked off, and the Dragons lost, 49-48, dropping their record to 1 win and 5 losses and all but dashing their playoff hopes.</p>
        <p>Four of Mr. Davey's 25 completed passes yielded touchdowns, but he also threw three interceptions. He told reporters he was to blame, and he went back out onto the field to sign autographs.</p>
        <p>There have been higher points in Rohan Davey's career -- starring in big-time college bowl victories, dominating the N.F.L.'s European league and collecting two Super Bowl rings from his three years with the New England Patriots -- but there he was last week in Uniondale, sitting and scowling and scribbling his name for fans, seated next to Sparky the Dragon, the team's fire-snorting mascot.</p>
        <p>He was in a better mood on Monday after working out at XSport, a snazzy fitness center in the Roosevelt Field mall that serves as the Dragons' gym. He settled his 6-foot-2-inch, 245-pound frame into a couch near the gym's spacious hair salon.</p>
        <p>''You ever been in a gym where you can get your hair done?'' joked Mr. Davey, who emigrated from Jamaica at age 8 and grew up in Florida.</p>
        <p>Arena football may not be on your radar screen, and it certainly wasn't on Mr. Davey's until he signed with the Dragons recently. The team's many talented players are still learning the indoor game, he said.</p>
        <p>Each team uses eight players at a time, and the field is 50 yards long. Reading the defense is different, he said, and since the field is boxed in by nets and sideboards, so is the depth perception and judgment of the pass coverage. The pass patterns are short and quick so the quarterback has to make a shorter drop into the pocket and release the ball quickly. As Mr. Davey stood to demonstrate this, several people stopped their stationary stair-climbing and skiing and watched him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Davey took up football his sophomore year of high school and went on to star at Louisiana State University, where he became M.V.P. of the Sugar Bowl and the most prolific passer in school history. In Europe, he led the Berlin Thunder to the World Bowl and was voted the league's offensive M.V.P. in 2004. With the Patriots, he backed up Tom Brady, the two-time Super Bowl M.V.P. But he saw little playing time and was replaced by the veteran Doug Flutie. After a stint with the Arizona Cardinals, he was signed by the Dragons in October to fill in for Aaron Garcia, the team's standout quarterback, who broke his leg last season.</p>
        <p>At the Coliseum last Sunday, there were more seats empty than occupied, but those who braved the weather were having a great time. Young fans clamored at the sideboards to slap hands with the players. Section 224 behind the end zone is known as the Dragon Zone, where a group of hardcore fans wear orange hard hats and go by nicknames from tailgating barbecues, including BBQ, Biscuit, Brisket and Beans.</p>
        <p>Stewart Slattery, 45, and his son Brian, 16, of Mount Sinai, sat in the front row, after buying $15 tickets and moving down to seats on the 10-yard line, where players slammed into (and sometimes over) the boards directly in front of them.</p>
        <p>Brian, a lineman for Mount Sinai High School, said he became a fan after playing a video game, Arena Football: Road to Glory.</p>
        <p>It is not exactly like playing in front of 90,000 people in college bowls or even large crowds in Europe, and game results rarely make the evening news or the major newspapers. However, Mr. Davey emphasizes, for a professional athlete approaching 30, it is better to be on the field for an arena team than perpetually pacing the sidelines for a Super Bowl squad.</p>
        <p>''It's not the same thing as the N.F.L.,'' he said, ''but it's still football and I'm out there playing. I still get jacked up for these games.''</p>
        <p>He is certainly not leading a Joe Namath lifestyle. His working-class pay, his Oyster Bay apartment and his red minivan are all provided by the team. He has yet to get into Manhattan. His observations so far about Long Island include the abundance of pizza parlors, bagel shops, aggressive drivers and A-type personalities.</p>
        <p>''The N.F.L. is still something I'm hoping for, but I just have to focus on playing here for now,'' he said. ''I'm not sitting on the bench anymore -- I can't afford to.''</p>
        <p>THE ISLAND E-mail:theisland@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail:theisland@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
