<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nets Open The Playoffs The Way They Did the Season</title>
    <meta content="22nets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/sports/basketball/22nets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842311"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Toronto Raptors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Toronto Raptors</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Carter, Vince</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jefferson, Richard</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E2DE173EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="807" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nets Open The Playoffs The Way They Did the Season</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nets Open the Playoffs the Way They Did the Season</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eligon, John</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO, April 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Over the past few days, the Nets have made a habit of referring to the playoffs with the cliché ''the second season.'' But in 48 minutes Saturday, they proved that they believed the message.</p>
        <p>With a 96-91 victory over the third-seeded Toronto Raptors in Game 1 of their first-round Eastern Conference playoffs series, the sixth-seeded Nets stole home-court advantage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vince Carter scored 16 points, but shot only 5 of 19. Richard Jefferson compensated by making 11 of 21 shots and scoring a game-high 28 points to lead the Nets to victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Over the past few days, the Nets have made a habit of referring to the playoffs with the cliché ''the second season.'' But in 48 minutes Saturday, they proved that they believed the message.</p>
        <p>With a 96-91 victory over the third-seeded Toronto Raptors in Game 1 of their first-round Eastern Conference playoffs series, the sixth-seeded Nets stole home-court advantage.</p>
        <p>More important, they were beaming with confidence.</p>
        <p>As winners of five games in a row, the Nets were looking for that consistency, not the erratic play that earned them a 41-41 record in the regular season. They began that regular season with a victory over the Raptors.</p>
        <p>''This is a veteran ball club,'' said Jason Kidd, who had 8 points, 15 assists and 10 rebounds. ''The regular season is over with. We're starting 0-0. We felt very confident coming into this series because of the way that we did end the season, so hopefully we can just build on that.''</p>
        <p>The Nets now enter Game 2 of this best-of-seven series on Tuesday night knowing that they can win even when Vince Carter is out of sync in front of his former home fans.</p>
        <p>Carter scored 16 points, but shot only 5 of 19 and was limited to 33 minutes because of foul trouble. The small forward Richard Jefferson compensated by making 11 of 21 shots and scoring a game-high 28 points.</p>
        <p>The reserve forward Bostjan Nachbar added 16 points, including a crucial 3-pointer with 2 minutes 43 seconds remaining that extended the Nets' lead to 87-83.</p>
        <p>The Raptors had cut a 13-point deficit at the start of the fourth quarter to 1 with less than three minutes left.</p>
        <p>Many of the Raptors' fans wore red shirts as part of the team's postseason campaign -- even though the Nets wore red road uniforms. That did not go unnoticed by Jefferson.</p>
        <p>''The biggest shock for us was how much support we got from Toronto fans,'' Jefferson said with a smile. ''I think that was exciting, the fact that they all came out and wore red to show us a lot of love.''</p>
        <p>The fervor of the already boisterous Toronto crowd was compounded by Carter's presence. Once the Raptors' franchise player, Carter now brings out anger in fans who feel he gave up on the team shortly before he was traded to the Nets in 2004. A couple of fans wore bibs bearing Carter's No. 15. They held various signs and shouted insults.</p>
        <p>It might not be a coincidence that Carter missed six of his first seven shots and had only 7 points through three quarters. Early in the second half, Carter picked up his third and fourth fouls in a span of 10 seconds. He sat out the final 9:33 of the third quarter.</p>
        <p>But with his mother, Michelle, watching calmly from the front row behind one of the baskets, Carter made a couple of crucial plays in the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>The Raptors used a 12-2 run that began four minutes into the fourth quarter to narrow the Nets' lead to 1 point. Carter's two free throws accounted for the Nets' only points during that stretch.</p>
        <p>Carter, who made five free throws and scored 9 points in the fourth, later made a driving layup to extend the Nets' lead to 7 points with 1:21 to play.</p>
        <p>That got his mother, who had been the subject of some of the fans' heckling, to break from her stoic demeanor, clapping and yelling words of encouragement.</p>
        <p>''I was ready to play, playoffs atmosphere, coming back here to play,'' Carter said. ''It is always great; the welcome is always exciting.''</p>
        <p>The Nets answered the Raptors' run with a 7-1 spurt. The Nets did not look rattled, despite the crowd and the feisty young Raptors, who already had their Atlantic Division regular-season championship banner hanging from the rafters.</p>
        <p>The Nets failed to capture that banner, mostly because they lost 12 games in which they entered the fourth quarter with a lead.</p>
        <p>''You're always interested as to what might transpire in the first playoff game, particularly on the road,'' said Rod Thorn, the Nets' president. ''They made a great comeback in the fourth quarter; game could've gone either way. It's nice that we closed it out.''</p>
        <p>The Nets remain a long way from regaining the swagger they took into this season. They once had aspirations of winning the conference and even the N.B.A. title.</p>
        <p>For now, they will look with smiles upon their longest winning streak since a 14-game run that ended April 8, 2006.</p>
        <p>''The last few games before the playoffs, we strapped it down and played pretty good basketball,'' said Nets center Mikki Moore, who had 9 points and 7 rebounds. ''I knew we were going to take that momentum into the playoffs. Everybody on our team is concentrating, and they're focused.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
