<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pattiann McAdams, Aaron Russell</title>
    <meta content="22mcadams" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/fashion/weddings/22mcadams.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842146"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">McAdams, Pattiann</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Russell, Aaron</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E0DF163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="268" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pattiann McAdams, Aaron Russell</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pattiann McAdams, Aaron Russell</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pattiann McAdams and Aaron Russell were married on Monday at Heartbreak Hill during the Boston Marathon. The ceremony was led by Kathy C. Byrnes, the bridegroom's mother, who was granted permission to officiate by the Commonwealth of Massachusetts. Yesterday, the Rev. Peter K. Meehan, a Roman Catholic priest, performed a religious ceremony at the Church of Our Lady of the Rosary in New York.</p>
        <p>The couple will be known as Mr. and Mrs. McAdams-Russell.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pattiann McAdams and Aaron Russell were married on Monday at Heartbreak Hill during the Boston Marathon. The ceremony was led by Kathy C. Byrnes, the bridegroom’s mother, who was granted permission to officiate by the Commonwealth of Massachusetts. Yesterday, the Rev. Peter K. Meehan, a Roman Catholic priest, performed a religious ceremony at the Church of Our Lady of the Rosary in New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pattiann McAdams and Aaron Russell were married on Monday at Heartbreak Hill during the Boston Marathon. The ceremony was led by Kathy C. Byrnes, the bridegroom's mother, who was granted permission to officiate by the Commonwealth of Massachusetts. Yesterday, the Rev. Peter K. Meehan, a Roman Catholic priest, performed a religious ceremony at the Church of Our Lady of the Rosary in New York.</p>
        <p>The couple will be known as Mr. and Mrs. McAdams-Russell.</p>
        <p>The bride, 33, is the president of the online division at Avon Products in New York. She graduated from the College of New Rochelle. She is a daughter of William McAdams of Boynton Beach, Fla., and the late Annmarie McAdams.</p>
        <p>The bride's father retired as a New York City sanitation worker. Her mother was the payroll clerk at Mamaroneck High School in Mamaroneck, N.Y.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom, 34, is the executive director of the Donald and Paula Smith Family Foundation, a nonprofit organization that sponsors public policy debates in New York. He is also studying for a law degree at Fordham. In August, he is to become an associate specializing in state and local tax law at the New York office of Morrison &amp; Foerster, a San Francisco law firm. He graduated from the State University at Albany and received a master's in computer information systems from Baruch College and another in economics from New York University.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom's mother, who lives in New York, is a teacher of English and of students with disabilities at Frederick Douglass Academy II in New York. His father, Robert Russell of Frankfurt, is a social worker in Germany.</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
