<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Conflicts Arise, Lawyers May Be a Source</title>
    <meta content="22deal" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/business/yourmoney/22deal.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842197"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DEALBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/DealBook</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E2DC163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="773" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Conflicts Arise, Lawyers May Be a Source</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">When Conflicts Arise, Lawyers May Be a Source</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INVESTMENT bankers are often singled out in this space over their conflict-ridden ways. Yet when it comes to deals and conflicts, another group always seems to get off scot-free: the lawyers.</p>
        <p>Perhaps it's time to stop giving them a pass.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When it comes to deals and conflicts, another group always seems to get off scot-free: the lawyers. Perhaps it’s time to stop giving them a pass.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INVESTMENT bankers are often singled out in this space over their conflict-ridden ways. Yet when it comes to deals and conflicts, another group always seems to get off scot-free: the lawyers.</p>
        <p>Perhaps it's time to stop giving them a pass.</p>
        <p>For bankers, being conflicted is almost an understandable cost of doing business: Wall Street has always been a push-the-envelope culture, driven by a brutish chase for outsize fees and bragging rights. It has become routine to hear about a bank playing both sides of a deal, competing against its own client or doing something else that doesn't sound exactly kosher.</p>
        <p>Now consider who allows these bankers to get out of line so regularly.</p>
        <p>The lawyers, who are supposed to be the grown-ups among bank advisers -- and bankers do at times seem like children, judging by some of the stories about conference calls run amok -- often look the other way. Or worse, the lawyers themselves help cultivate a thicket of conflicting interests.</p>
        <p>It probably shouldn't come as a surprise. Take a look at the top 10 prominent law firms involved in the world of mergers and acquisitions. Who are their highest-fee-paying clients? Investment banks and private equity firms, of course.</p>
        <p>Just look at the deal that was the subject of my last column, the sale of the Tribune Company to Samuel Zell. Two of the banks working for Tribune -- Merrill Lynch and Citigroup -- also provided financing to Mr. Zell, and they stand to make more in fees from the debt than Mr. Zell paid for the entire deal.</p>
        <p>Among the lawyers advising Tribune that told the board this was acceptable were Sidley Austin and Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher &amp; Flom, which represented a special committee. And who, you might ask, is one of Sidley Austin's biggest clients? Merrill Lynch. And Skadden's? Why, Citigroup.</p>
        <p>Spokeswomen for Skadden and Sidley declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Having Wall Street firms as their biggest clients is de rigueur for law firms.</p>
        <p>Simpson Thacher &amp; Bartlett's biggest clients are JPMorgan Chase, Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Company and the Blackstone Group, which often leaves Simpson advising multiple parties in a deal.</p>
        <p>One of the biggest clients of Sullivan &amp; Cromwell -- far and away -- is Goldman Sachs. Davis Polk &amp; Wardwell works for Morgan Stanley. Wachtell, Lipton, Rosen &amp; Katz counts Apollo Management and Lazard among its bigger clients. The list goes on.</p>
        <p>Law firms that often advise public companies on sales also advise investment banks and buyout firms on other deals. One day they are advocating for an investment-banking client to perhaps push the envelope, and the next day they are working for a corporate client that should probably push back on such a practice. But their work the day earlier often creates a sense of normalcy about what is considered acceptable practice -- called ''market'' in industry parlance -- leaving them less likely to raise a red flag.</p>
        <p>It starts to make sense that all the right questions are not being asked in this incestuous, six-degrees-of-separation world.</p>
        <p>That's not to say that the lawyers are somehow conspiring against their client with investment banks or private equity firms, or violating professional ethics rules governing conflicts. Like Wall Street banks, they say they have impenetrable Chinese walls.</p>
        <p>But they may not be pressing hard enough against practices like staple financing or ''go shops'' that are used as replacements for auctions. That is because, in part, the lawyers have been responsible for helping to push such practices when they are working on the other sides of deals for their Wall Street and private equity clients.</p>
        <p>IT'S a situation that mirrors Wall Street, where the banks' biggest clients have become private equity firms -- doling out $10 billion in annual fees. As a result, however, it has in some cases perverted the sale process for public companies. Investment banks, indebted to their private equity clients, often run auctions that invariably seem to benefit their own clients over strategic buyers.</p>
        <p>And let's be completely frank: private equity is winning these auctions not just because it is more aggressive than strategic buyers.</p>
        <p>Last month, Vice Chancellor Leo E. Strine Jr. of the Delaware Court of Chancery found that Netsmart Technologies had sold itself in a $115 million buyout to some private equity firms without even seeking interest from strategic buyers.</p>
        <p>That was a situation where the bank may have been at fault.</p>
        <p>Even so, legal advisers need to police the boardroom more forcefully. And while lawyers often ask the questions, maybe the board should doing the same.</p>
        <p>DealBook also has a newsletter and a Web site, nytimes.com/dealbook, that is updated continuously when markets are open.</p>
        <p>DEALBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
