<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Why the British Killed King Leer</title>
    <meta content="22isherwood" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/weekinreview/22isherwood.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070429T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842242"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="IDEAS &amp; TRENDS: COMEDY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Monty Python</org>
        <org class="online_producer">BBC America</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01EFD9163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1040" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Why the British Killed King Leer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Why the British Killed King Leer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES ISHERWOOD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Isherwood, Charles</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's embarrassing to admit now, but there was a time in my life when I preferred the cheesy antics of ''The Benny Hill Show'' to the more rarefied silliness of ''Monty Python's Flying Circus.'' This pre-adolescent era of jolly tastelessness is long distant, I'm happy to say. But the news that BBC America has decided to remove ''The Benny Hill Show'' from its roster, in the belief that his brand of comedy reflected an ''older Britain,'' according to a company publicist, gave me a pang nonetheless.</p>
        <p>Growing up in the Bay Area in the 1970s, I watched ''Benny Hill'' on weekend nights on a local independent station. The lateness of the hour and the show's presence on a commercial channel were central to its appeal. ''Monty Python'' was telecast on the PBS station, firmly associated in my mind with the endless, ponderous serials my parents insisted on watching in favor of, say, ''Laverne &amp; Shirley.'' (This was in that benighted era when most suburban houses boasted but a single set for family viewing.) And I think ''Benny Hill'' had the added attraction of appearing as a lighthearted appetizer for my real passion of the time, a resplendently lurid Australian soap opera set in a women's prison called ''Prisoner: Cell Block H.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most TV comedy can be Americanized. Not the silly-walking men.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's embarrassing to admit now, but there was a time in my life when I preferred the cheesy antics of ''The Benny Hill Show'' to the more rarefied silliness of ''Monty Python's Flying Circus.'' This pre-adolescent era of jolly tastelessness is long distant, I'm happy to say. But the news that BBC America has decided to remove ''The Benny Hill Show'' from its roster, in the belief that his brand of comedy reflected an ''older Britain,'' according to a company publicist, gave me a pang nonetheless.</p>
        <p>Growing up in the Bay Area in the 1970s, I watched ''Benny Hill'' on weekend nights on a local independent station. The lateness of the hour and the show's presence on a commercial channel were central to its appeal. ''Monty Python'' was telecast on the PBS station, firmly associated in my mind with the endless, ponderous serials my parents insisted on watching in favor of, say, ''Laverne &amp; Shirley.'' (This was in that benighted era when most suburban houses boasted but a single set for family viewing.) And I think ''Benny Hill'' had the added attraction of appearing as a lighthearted appetizer for my real passion of the time, a resplendently lurid Australian soap opera set in a women's prison called ''Prisoner: Cell Block H.''</p>
        <p>''Benny'' and ''Monty'' were essential poles of British television comedy as imported to America in the 1970s, and they represented distinct strains of British humor. Both derived their sketch formats in part from the rowdy tradition of the music hall. But ''Benny Hill'' stayed closer to its populist roots, with its relentless parade of naughty innuendoes and physical comedy. ''Monty Python'' mixed juvenile raillery with decidedly more analytical kinds of comedy, reflecting the Oxbridge smarty-pants satire of ''Beyond the Fringe'' and even the influence of European absurdist theater. A celebrated skit on ''Monty Python'' riffed with a mock-straight face on the notion of silly walks. Benny Hill just walked silly, period, usually at high speed, to the accompaniment of cheesy pop music, and in drooling pursuit of a buxom lass wearing a very short skirt.</p>
        <p>Benny's twinkling, elbow-in-the-ribs leer and naughty-boy grin underscored the double entendres in case you had slipped into a coma. By contrast, the stiff posturing toffs played by the cast of ''Monty Python'' gave nary a wink at the camera. The contained universe of the gag was rarely violated by any suggestion that the performers were in on the joke. Highbrow and lowbrow isn't quite the right distinction, since much of the ''Monty Python'' comedy beautifully blended both, but it's close enough, and touches on the general and uneasy-making class distinctions that mark British culture to this day: ''Masterpiece Theater'' on the one hand, ''EastEnders'' on the other.</p>
        <p>From an American perspective, both ''Benny Hill'' and ''Monty Python'' were unusual in being imported directly and appearing outside the frame of network television, which then ruled the landscape. In the 1970s, British sitcoms like ''Til Death Us Do Part'' and ''Steptoe &amp; Son'' were reformatted by Norman Lear as ''All in the Family'' and ''Sanford and Son,'' both of which became huge hits. But there was no translating Benny Hill, just as there was no way to Americanize ''Monty Python.''</p>
        <p>The expansion of the cable landscape in the last 20 years has meant that American audiences have access to a lot more British comedy than before, not just the ones deemed translatable, or suitable for PBS audiences, or with the mass appeal to justify full-scale syndication. ''Absolutely Fabulous'' was a breakthrough draw for Comedy Central, back when Jon Stewart and Stephen Colbert had not yet perfected their smirks. ''Little Britain'' and other comedies of recent vintage can be seen with ease.</p>
        <p>But all this access may help dilute what's specifically British -- or specifically American -- in popular comedy. What I mourn most about the banishment of Benny on the Yank version of the Beeb is not the access to the show itself, but the waning of the truly indigenous entertainment it symbolized.</p>
        <p>''Benny Hill'' took hold in America precisely because we had nothing like it; its lewd comedy and rampant childishness never really had an equivalent on American TV. Hard as it may be to believe today, when the gross-out antics of ''Jackass'' scarcely raise a cultural watchdog's eyebrow, popular culture of the 1960s and 1970s was pretty prudish, with Goldie Hawn's innocent gyrations on ''Laugh-In'' about as naughty as things got on commercial television.</p>
        <p>As the BBC lost its chartered right to British eyeballs over the decades, rival networks flooded the market with sitcoms and dramas from the United States, and now lots of British TV is either American imports or imitations thereof. Meanwhile, American producers returned to Mr. Lear's reformatting formula, both for the hugely popular contest shows like ''American Idol'' and ''Big Brother'' and for comedy, too. NBC turned the Ricky Gervais comedy ''The Office,'' a mock documentary about cubicle drones, into a vehicle for another ''Daily Show'' alumnus, Steve Carell.</p>
        <p>The changeover for BBC America is being billed as an attempt to update the programming to reflect what's current in British television. But what's current in British television increasingly resembles what's current in American television. ''Wire in the Blood'' is apparently a crime show about a forensic psychologist, something along the lines of the sprawling ''CSI'' phenomenon. The news release announcing the end of Benny ballyhooed the arrival of a teenage soap opera called ''Hollyoaks,'' which sounds a lot like ''Dawson's Creek.'' What's ''Footballers' Wives'' but ''Desperate Housewives'' with hotter guys and tackier outfits?</p>
        <p>This is probably unavoidable. The truth is, entertainment formulas are always being ripped off, repeated and recycled with different degrees of artistry. And even shows that disappear from the TV landscape can have a subterranean influence on writers and producers years later. Come to think of it, my beloved ''Prisoner: Cell Block H,'' which seemed such a delicious oddity back in the day with its malevolent lesbian guards and hard-edged violence, didn't evaporate entirely either. It returned on super-respectable HBO, decades later, in an all-male version called ''Oz.'' Benny may be leaving BBC America, but his leer will surely live on to inspire the imaginations of happily juvenile-minded writers and performers for some time to come.</p>
        <p>IDEAS &amp; TRENDS: COMEDY</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 29, 2007, Sunday  A photograph caption last Sunday accompanying an article about British television comedy misspelled the surname of an actor in ''Little Britain.'' He is David Walliams, not Williams.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 29, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>A photograph caption last Sunday accompanying an article about British television comedy misspelled the surname of an actor in ''Little Britain.'' He is David Walliams, not Williams.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
