<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Free Will and Virginia Tech</title>
    <meta content="l22brooks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842229"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E4D9163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="816" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Free Will and Virginia Tech</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''The Morality Line'' (column, April 19):</p>
        <p>David Brooks makes the point about choice and responsibility: The killings at Virginia Tech happened at a moment ''when background forces stop and individual choice'' begins.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''The Morality Line'' (column, April 19):</p>
        <p>David Brooks makes the point about choice and responsibility: The killings at Virginia Tech happened at a moment ''when background forces stop and individual choice'' begins.</p>
        <p>Not all troubled people act out violent fantasies; despite his apparent illness, Seung-Hui Cho made a choice in his soul somewhere along the line.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, we as a society also have choices, including what kinds of weapons we allow in the marketplace that are easily available to the troubled when they make wrong choices -- and that is our responsibility.</p>
        <p>Diana Holdsworth  Norwalk, Conn., April 19, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>David Brooks is right to suggest that any account of Seung-Hui Cho's actions will have to assume that he made choices and exercised some degree of self-control in making them. But choices and self-control are complex processes with many underlying contributory factors -- physiological, psychological and social.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brooks laments the loss of free will in this explanatory mix, but what would we gain by adding it, other than a false sense of closure that some one person is morally to blame? How will this help us prevent similar actions in the future?</p>
        <p>Dave Hilditch  St. Louis, April 19, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>David Brooks's columns about the marvels of biology and evolution in explaining human behavior have been eye-opening. Yet he is wrong to dismiss the role of gun laws when it comes to the impact of violent actions.</p>
        <p>One wonders why President Bush, who often speaks of the sanctity of life, has done so little to help protect our lives from gun violence.</p>
        <p>Chris Homan  Washington, April 19, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In arguing for a return to individual choice, free will and moral responsibility as we try to ponder the inexplicable behavior of Seung-Hui Cho, David Brooks misses the point. Whether Mr. Cho's actions were determined by social forces outside his control or whether he had free will and was responsible for his behavior does not help us avert future tragedies.</p>
        <p>In either case, he was a severely disturbed individual in need of help. We -- his peers, his parents, his college, his world -- had sufficient warning to intervene so as to protect others from his rage, irrespective of its source, as well as to protect him from himself.</p>
        <p>Ferne Traeger  New York, April 19, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is a psychoanalyst.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>David Brooks argues that ''individual choice and moral responsibility'' need to be ''closer to the center'' of the debate about Seung-Hui Cho's massacre at Virginia Tech. In doing so, he wisely acknowledges the evidence that some behavior is driven by forces that know no such control.</p>
        <p>What also must be debated is the moral responsibility of social systems to protect society from Mr. Cho and Mr. Cho from himself. These systems failed, largely because of barriers to treating his mental illness.</p>
        <p>They included laws that protected his rights against involuntary commitment and precluded college officials from discussing his situation with his parents.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the community mental health system to which he was directed is broken.</p>
        <p>Virginia has a severe shortage of acute-care mental hospital beds and waiting lists for mental health care. People with schizophrenia, bipolar disorder and other serious mental illnesses cannot get the care they need and often go to prison as a result. Where is the morality in that?</p>
        <p>Mary Beth Pfeiffer  Stone Ridge, N.Y., April 19, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is the author of ''Crazy in America: The Hidden Tragedy of Our Criminalized Mentally Ill.''</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>David Brooks presents the dilemma between holding people morally accountable for their actions and the evidence of neuroscience that free will is only an illusion. But the ability of some people to rise above oppressive families and cultures to achieve great things represents a good practical substitute for free will.</p>
        <p>Euclid, Newton, Darwin and Einstein all demonstrate the existence of some quality in humans that enables them to break free of the past and of their surroundings. We should remember them whenever we are tempted to think that someone's failings, moral or otherwise, are fated.</p>
        <p>Bill Hibbard  Stoughton, Wis., April 19, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I agree with David Brooks when he says we need to ''reconstruct some self-confident explanation for what happened at Virginia Tech that puts individual choice and moral responsibility closer to the center.''</p>
        <p>But Seung-Hui Cho made such a choice. He chose to exercise his constitutional right to arm himself, and defend himself from what he perceived as his nemesis, a morally responsible action in his mind.</p>
        <p>What we have not done is to construct a barrier to prevent such deluded people from taking advantage of the Second Amendment.</p>
        <p>Larry Maxcy  Yucca Valley, Calif., April 19, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
