<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Affordable Europe: Istanbul</title>
    <meta content="22istanbulweb" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/travel/22istanbulweb.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842331"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Istanbul (Turkey)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey/Istanbul</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Istanbul (Turkey)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E1D61631F931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="638" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Affordable Europe: Istanbul</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Affordable Europe: Istanbul</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH SHERWOOD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sure, Turkey lopped off several zeroes from its currency (the lira) in 2005, but that doesn't mean that dining on meze or hobnobbing with sultans has gotten cheaper. If anything, it's just the opposite. Istanbul has emerged as one of Europe's hottest centers of chic, with the designer boutique hotels, flashy night life and cosmopolitan price tags to match. Luckily, pockets of this former Byzantine capital -- from lesser-known markets to trendy new restaurants -- are dedicated to preserving pre-devaluation bargains, as when $1 was worth more than one million Turkish liras.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay for Under 125 Euros</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Istanbul has emerged as one of Europe’s hottest centers of chic, with the designer boutique hotels, flashy night life and cosmopolitan price tags to match.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sure, Turkey lopped off several zeroes from its currency (the lira) in 2005, but that doesn't mean that dining on meze or hobnobbing with sultans has gotten cheaper. If anything, it's just the opposite. Istanbul has emerged as one of Europe's hottest centers of chic, with the designer boutique hotels, flashy night life and cosmopolitan price tags to match. Luckily, pockets of this former Byzantine capital -- from lesser-known markets to trendy new restaurants -- are dedicated to preserving pre-devaluation bargains, as when $1 was worth more than one million Turkish liras.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay for Under 125 Euros</p>
        <p>Armchair archaeologists and style mavens alike will go for the Hotel Nomade (Divanyolu Caddesi, Ticarethane Sokak 15; 90-212-513-8172; www.hotelnomade.com), a contemporary-style crash pad that's spitting distance from the Hagia Sofia, Roman cisterns and other millenniums-old monuments of the former Constantinople. Outfitted with flat-screen TVs and wireless Internet access, the 16 (admittedly smallish) rooms were revamped a few years ago by the French designer Dan Beranger, who brightened up the angular minimalist surfaces with colorful fabrics and blond wood furnishings. But the real highlight is the view from the rooftop terrace. If you can tear your eyes away from the free cheeses and rich Turkish yogurt, you'll have a commanding view of the Bosphorus and the city's sublime minarets. Doubles from 85 euros, or $116 at $1.36 to the euro, with breakfast.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat  The two-year-old Peradoxin the bohemian Tunel district (Sofyali Sokak 11, 90-212-245-7610; www.peradox.com.tr) revels in contradictions. Although it's housed in a 19th-century town house, the industrial-chic interior oozes with up-to-the-minute designs. The crowd is young and stylish, but the food is an old-school mix of mezze, skewered meats, lamb casseroles, grilled fish, baked rice pudding and fiery raki, the anise-flavored national drink. And despite its tony vibe, prices are starving-artist friendly. Two-course, prix fixe menus are 10 new Turkish liras, or $7.22 at 1.41 new liras to $1 (lunch); three dinner menus are 15 to 20 new liras. Two people can eat three courses à la carte for 60 new liras.</p>
        <p>Where to Shop  Istanbul's Grand Bazaarteems with 4,000-odd stalls hocking every tea set and carpet imaginable. It also teems with smooth-talking salesmen skilled at fleecing travelers with a smile and a glass of free tea. More low-key -- and lower priced -- are the Sunday flea markets, where merchants don't face the pressure of paying annual rents in gold. In the Ortakoy district, the waterfront streets brim with turquoise jewelry, scarves, silks, samovars, calligraphy, blown glass and paintings. Recent finds include large ceramic fragments illustrated with dervishes and harem girls (5 to 10 new liras) and cushion covers embroidered with Ottoman prints (5 new liras).</p>
        <p>You'll find much more than prayer beads in the courtyard east of Beyazit Mosque, where old men sell vintage cigarette lighters, antique foreign coins, retro watches, military medallions, old fountain pens, forgotten electronics and other curios. And bring your bargaining gloves: prices in flea markets are always negotiable.</p>
        <p>Best Money-Saving Tip  One word: Sultanahmet. This old quarter, in the heart of historic Istanbul, has an abundance of cultural treasures that don't cost a coin-- from the Egyptian Obelisk to the walls of the Roman hippodrome. Must-sees include theSuleymaniye Mosque (Prof. Siddik Sami Onar Caddesi; 90-212-522-0298), built 450 years ago atop the city's highest hill by Istanbul's great architect Mimar Sinan to immortalize the most powerful Ottoman sultan, Suleyman the Magnificent. Despite its age, the structure still inspires awe with its massive central dome, surrounding sea of smaller domes and pencil-thin minarets. Also free are the 500-year-old Beyazit Mosque (Beyazit Square, 90-212-519-3644), one of the city's oldest Ottoman mosques, and the iconic Sultanahmet Mosque (Meydani Sokak 17, 90-212-518-1319), revered for its harmonious proportions and intricately painted interiors. (Mosques are closed to tourists at prayer times.)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
