<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Hamptons, Ahead of the Crowds</title>
    <meta content="22beachliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/22beachli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842005"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hamptons (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Medina, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Upstate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Long Island/Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Luxury and Vacations/Vacation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/The Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Hamptons (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505EEDA1E3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="982" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Hamptons, Ahead of the Crowds</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In the Hamptons, Ahead of the Crowds</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER MEDINA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Medina, Jennifer</byline>
      <dateline>AMAGANSETT</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on spending off-season at rental house in Hamptons, NY; notes Hamptons are becoming year-round getaway for those drawn by quiet and beauty; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS the renters of Hamptons summer shares are making their final plans for the coming season, the five members of our house will be getting ready to say goodbye. We didn't sip piña coladas on the deck; we nursed glasses of port and fed the fireplace. Instead of packing bathing suits, we brought thick sweaters and woolly caps.</p>
        <p>Renting a cottage off-season, from September through May, was my friend's idea; I said yes without giving it much thought. Though I had lived in New York for several years, I had never been to the Hamptons in the summer. Mostly, I was convinced it was not worth the money or the headache to get out there in July. This, my friend informed me, would be the perfect solution: I would satisfy my California-native craving for sand and sea and avoid the madness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The off-season offers pleasures that summer visitors are denied.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS the renters of Hamptons summer shares are making their final plans for the coming season, the five members of our house will be getting ready to say goodbye. We didn't sip piña coladas on the deck; we nursed glasses of port and fed the fireplace. Instead of packing bathing suits, we brought thick sweaters and woolly caps.</p>
        <p>Renting a cottage off-season, from September through May, was my friend's idea; I said yes without giving it much thought. Though I had lived in New York for several years, I had never been to the Hamptons in the summer. Mostly, I was convinced it was not worth the money or the headache to get out there in July. This, my friend informed me, would be the perfect solution: I would satisfy my California-native craving for sand and sea and avoid the madness.</p>
        <p>My friend was right. On one of the first weekends of spring, I could walk out our back door to the shore a few yards away and find myself all alone, with the waves making the loudest sound I had heard since arriving that Friday evening.</p>
        <p>To hear some who live on the East End tell it, the Hamptons are becoming a year-round getaway for many like us who are drawn by the quiet, the beauty, the ease of it.</p>
        <p>''The Hamptons in the winter used to be a ghost town -- you could fire a cannon down Main Street and nobody would have noticed,'' said Rick Hoffman, regional vice president for the Corcoran Group in Southampton, who became a winter renter himself in 1990. ''Now people are investing in premium properties and want to get real use out of their homes, so they are there all the time.''</p>
        <p>Because there is a more active community year round, he said, ''people are more interested in renting.'' Roughly a third of the houses available in summer can be rented in the off-season, according to real estate agents. Demand has risen in recent years as more restaurants and shops have stayed open, but still, only about 30 to 50 percent of the houses available are actually rented, Mr. Hoffman said.</p>
        <p>Winter rentals are ''definitely at a discount,'' he said, though ''I can't tell you an exact formula.''</p>
        <p>The real pleasures of renting in the off-season have nothing to do with money, as I was reminded on the afternoon in March when a seal made its way to the sand just in front of our cottage. One of our housemates who spotted it ran to call the rest of our group, and the animal soon drew a small group of admirers. In summer, the seal would likely be farther north; the crowds on the beach then surely would have scared it off, or worse.</p>
        <p>In some ways, though, the starkest example of how spring is different can be found in town. The shops that line the streets of East Hampton, like Scoop, Coach and DKNY, are filled with the same sort of high-end merchandise one would find in summer. But when they are getting rid of leftover winter stock, it's possible to find bargains. As a bonus, there's space on the sidewalk to walk a dog or take a toddler on a tricycle ride.</p>
        <p>Although many restaurants close during the off-season, reopening on Easter or Memorial Day, others, like Robert's Restaurant in Water Mill, choose to stay open just for the weekends, taking advantage of the reduced schedule.</p>
        <p>''This is the one time where you are really going to see friends, go surfing on the beach, do the things that make you like it out here,'' said Kelly Krieger of Sag Harbor, who works part time as a hostess at Robert's. ''This is the time we can actually have some fun. When the summer comes all we can do is work and deal with short tempers.''</p>
        <p>There are times, however, even in the off-season, when crowds seem to gather. On one Saturday night we headed to the Laundry, the East Hampton bistro much favored by critics. BMWs and SUVs were cheek by jowl in the parking lot.</p>
        <p>We had 8 o'clock reservations, but the hostess took nearly 15 minutes to seat us, giving us a chance to listen in on several conversations at the bar. (Each of the five couples seemed to be talking about real estate.)</p>
        <p>Once seated, we found the back dining room as crowded as the parking lot. I was literally bumping elbows with the woman at the next table, and it was almost impossible to hear my friend across from me. Blessedly, by the time our food came, the earlier diners had cleared out.</p>
        <p>Most of the joys of the off-season were quieter, smaller ones. As one friend pointed out, he has no idea where the sun rises and sets in relation to his Brooklyn apartment; he hardly even knows what time those things happens. But in Amagansett, he can point out exactly where the sun will set as spring days grow longer.</p>
        <p>I thought about that as I boarded the ferry in Port Jefferson, heading back to Bridgeport, Conn. On that side of the Long Island Sound, too, I could find the quiet rocky beaches of Madison. I could wander into the R. J. Julia bookstore in Guilford or drive over to Lenny and Joe's Fish Tale in Madison for fried cod and chips.</p>
        <p>It was Sunday evening, with the sun just turning the sky hints of magenta. Somehow, I was not lamenting the passing of the weekend, as I might have in summer. Instead, I looked out from the top deck, where I stood alone, zipping up the neck of my down coat. Even as I tied my scarf and pulled down my hat, I was thinking of spring weekends to come. Summer would be here soon. I could never have the deck to myself then.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
