<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>STREET LEVEL -- Downtown Brooklyn; In Big Mac Country, Gilded Age Yearnings</title>
    <meta content="22stre" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/thecity/22stre.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842177"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Street Level | Downtown Brooklyn"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Gage &amp; Tollner (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tgi Friday's</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bleyer, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7DC163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="713" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>STREET LEVEL -- Downtown Brooklyn; In Big Mac Country, Gilded Age Yearnings</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Big Mac Country, Gilded Age Yearnings</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER BLEYER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bleyer, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Street Level column on landmark building at 372 Fulton Street in Downtown Brooklyn, which once housed Gage &amp; Tollner restaurant; restaurant closed on Valentine's Day 2004 and was replaced with TGI Friday's, which closed nearly a month ago; several restaurateurs reportedly are considering renting space; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE lunch crowd coursed along Fulton Street Mall in Downtown Brooklyn on Tuesday afternoon, a river of people bundled up in trench coats and athletic jackets. Some scurried toward the nearby Dallas BBQ restaurant. Others clutched takeout bags from White Castle. The line inside a corner pizza shop stretched almost to the sidewalk.</p>
        <p>A few passers-by cast quick glances at a brownstone wedged amid the cellphone stores and the fast-food joints. Its ground floor most recently housed a T.G.I. Friday's restaurant, which closed abruptly nearly a month ago. Now, behind the locked wooden revolving door was the darkened interior of what had previously been Gage &amp; Tollner, the Brooklyn culinary establishment that opened in 1879.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Since the old-school Brooklyn restaurant Gage &amp; Tollner closed in 2004, many residents have been hoping for a worthy replacement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE lunch crowd coursed along Fulton Street Mall in Downtown Brooklyn on Tuesday afternoon, a river of people bundled up in trench coats and athletic jackets. Some scurried toward the nearby Dallas BBQ restaurant. Others clutched takeout bags from White Castle. The line inside a corner pizza shop stretched almost to the sidewalk.</p>
        <p>A few passers-by cast quick glances at a brownstone wedged amid the cellphone stores and the fast-food joints. Its ground floor most recently housed a T.G.I. Friday's restaurant, which closed abruptly nearly a month ago. Now, behind the locked wooden revolving door was the darkened interior of what had previously been Gage &amp; Tollner, the Brooklyn culinary establishment that opened in 1879.</p>
        <p>Deniz Su, a 36-year-old restaurant manager, pressed her nose to the plate-glass window to appraise the elegant dining room. With the marble slab bar and gaslight fixtures, it took only a slight reach of the imagination to picture the space full of men in top hats and women in whalebone corsets.</p>
        <p>Ms. Su, who lives in Park Slope, the neighborhood where she grew up, recalled her mother's taking her to Gage &amp; Tollner when she was younger to celebrate special occasions like graduations. ''It was a classic,'' Ms. Su said. ''It was one of those places with career waiters who would pull out the chair for you and say, 'Young lady, you're so beautiful.' ''</p>
        <p>Like others who noticed the recent vacancy in the building, 372 Fulton Street, which is a designated city landmark, Ms. Su hoped that a business befitting its rich history might move in. ''How many McDonald's and Wendy's do you need?'' she said. ''I think another old-school chop house should come give Peter Luger a run for its money.''</p>
        <p>Gage &amp; Tollner closed on Valentine's Day 2004, a casualty of paltry business in an area dominated by downscale retailers, and inconvenient to adjacent brownstone neighborhoods. Still, many lamented its loss. Gone were the lobster Newburg and the venison pot pie, along with the well-preserved remnants of 19th-century New York amid which generations of affluent seafood and steak fanciers had dined.</p>
        <p>When T.G.I. Friday's opened in the space seven months later, there was further outcry from some who thought that a casual American-fare chain did not befit such an esteemed location. T.G.I. Friday's made an effort to recast the restaurant, bringing in a jukebox and television sets and serving up chicken wings and stuffed potato skins. But try as it did, the outlet was ultimately unsuccessful at the location.</p>
        <p>''Business was bad,'' said Larry Abrams, the property manager for the T.G.I. Friday's franchisee group that operated the restaurant. ''It could have used more signage to let people know we were there, but we couldn't, partially because of the landmark restrictions. It was good for preservation, but not good for attracting attention.''</p>
        <p>Not long after T.G.I. Friday's vacated the site last month, local bloggers began chattering cheerfully about what they would like to see take its place. The author of the blog 110livingston.net, which is aimed at future residents of the condo taking shape at the former home of the city's Board of Education, wrote that ''we can only hope something more appropriate goes in at this landmarked interior -- like maybe Gage &amp; Tollner?''</p>
        <p>Gage &amp; Tollner seems unlikely to return. But it is possible that another sophisticated restaurant could rent the space. Faith Hope Consolo, chairwoman of the retail division of Prudential Douglas Elliman real estate, said she was considering the site on behalf of a French brasserie with several outlets in Manhattan. ''I think they're looking for a more upscale restaurant there,'' Ms. Consolo said of the site's owners.</p>
        <p>A ''for rent'' sign with a telephone number hangs on the outside of the building. The real estate agent who answered declined to be quoted by name or to identify his company but said that several restaurateurs were considering renting the space.</p>
        <p>In the opinion of Ms. Consolo of Douglas Elliman, whoever takes over the building will most likely complement the restaurant's aesthetic details with high-minded food, a change that she predicts will be echoed around Downtown Brooklyn as the area becomes more residential. ''People have a different taste bubble from what's existed before,'' she said. ''Everybody has had enough of McDonald's.''</p>
        <p>Street Level | Downtown Brooklyn</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
