<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Historical Mayhem, Set to Music</title>
    <meta content="22artsctCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/22artsct.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842033"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Westport Country Playhouse</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gold, Sylviane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stein, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kander, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ebb, Fred (1933-2004)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barre, Gabriel</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">All About Us (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Westport Country Playhouse</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E0D61E3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="760" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Historical Mayhem, Set to Music</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Historical Mayhem, Set to Music</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SYLVIANE GOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gold, Sylviane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sylviane Gold reviews Westport Country Playhouse production of musical All About Us, book by Joseph Stein, music by John Kander, lyrics by Fred Ebb and directed by Gabriel Barre; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Is there anything that can't be saved by Eartha Kitt?</p>
        <p>Sheathed in a shimmering red dress and wearing a feathered purple turban, she slinks onstage at the Westport Country Playhouse to issue a somber warning: ''There's gonna be rain, rain, rain, rain, rain, rain, rain, rain, rain.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The latest stab at adapting Thornton Wilder’s “The Skin of Our Teeth,” at the Westport Country Playhouse, still falls a bit short.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Is there anything that can't be saved by Eartha Kitt?</p>
        <p>Sheathed in a shimmering red dress and wearing a feathered purple turban, she slinks onstage at the Westport Country Playhouse to issue a somber warning: ''There's gonna be rain, rain, rain, rain, rain, rain, rain, rain, rain.''</p>
        <p>Believe it. Ms. Kitt, the 80-year-old show business legend, plays an Atlantic City fortuneteller named Esmeralda, working her hands and her brows and her knees -- not to mention her voice -- to alert humanity to the coming Flood. (Or had you forgotten that New Jersey is in that Bible story?)</p>
        <p>At the same time, she's demonstrating that there is indeed a good reason for ''All About Us,'' the musical version of Thornton Wilder's apocalyptic comedy ''The Skin of Our Teeth'' that runs at Westport through April 28.</p>
        <p>Until Ms. Kitt unleashes her incomparable hooch act, it's not exactly clear why the musical theater royalty responsible for ''All About Us'' -- the author of ''Fiddler on the Roof,'' Joseph Stein, and the songwriters behind ''Cabaret'' and ''Chicago,'' John Kander and Fred Ebb -- felt so strongly about this material that they shaped it into a musical in 1999 and then kept revisiting it.</p>
        <p>The Wilder play, a bubbly mash of anachronism, absurdity and high purpose, follows the archetypal Antrobus family through the march of human history, from the Ice Age to the Flood to an all-consuming modern war. Constructed as a play within a play, ''The Skin of Our Teeth'' was being called a vaudeville from its premiere, in 1942. And with self-conscious actors commenting on the play as they act in it and with backstage mayhem spilling over into the audience's view, it does seem to have the kind of double vision that allows characters to sing.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, parables create a distance that undercuts the emotional intimacy that grounds a musical. By necessity, the Antrobus clan is generic. George has invented the wheel and the alphabet; Maggie is his loyal wife; their children, Henry and Gladys, are forever squabbling. Their saucy maid, Sabina, is the eternal Other Woman. While it's easy to see why Mr. Stein, Mr. Kander and Mr. Ebb were tempted by the musical possibilities of ''The Skin of Our Teeth,'' it's also easy to see why they have had so much trouble with it.</p>
        <p>They called their first adaptation ''Over and Over,'' but when it faltered in tryout, they shelved it and began again. Retooled as ''The Skin of Our Teeth,'' it was revised once more, as ''All About Us.'' Its current incarnation was nearly complete when Mr. Ebb died, in 2004, and as Ms. Kitt's rollicking number indicates, the show is getting closer. But it's not there yet.</p>
        <p>Paradoxically, the reason for this is embedded in the ''Rain'' number as well: Esmeralda is not a major character. She shows up to predict bad weather and then disappears until it's time for a reprise. In ''All About Us,'' too many of the best musical numbers belong to characters on the periphery of the story.</p>
        <p>Eric Michael Gillett and Drew Taylor, who play a pair of at-risk woolly mammoths in Ann Hould-Ward's loopy costumes, harmonize endearingly about getting ''Warm.'' The quartet playing Socrates, Homer, Plato and Moses close the Ice Age section with ''A Discussion,'' a terrific Kander-Ebb patter song that puzzles over the show itself: ''I rehearsed it and I read it and I even read an edit/But if you believe I got it you were wrong.'' And the most characteristic Kander-Ebb tune, a sly, misanthropic, indelible ditty called ''Nice People,'' is the anthem for Carlo Alban, playing the bad seed, Henry.</p>
        <p>This isn't to say that the show's stars don't get their opportunities. As Mr. Antrobus, Shuler Hensley, the Tony-winning Jud Fry of the Broadway revival of ''Oklahoma!'' sings a comic ode to the wheel; Yvette Freeman's Mrs. Antrobus delivers the ballad of the wronged wife, ''He Always Comes Home to Me''; and Cady Huffman, reprising a bit of her Tony-winning ''Producers'' turn as Sabina, seduces Mr. Antrobus with the lilting ''You Owe It to Yourself.'' But even with these fine moments, ''All About Us,'' directed by Gabriel Barre, never achieves the critical mass that transforms a collection of discrete numbers into an all-embracing universe. That is, until Ms. Kitt arrives with her gloom-and-doom weather report and miraculously brightens the sky.</p>
        <p>''All About Us,'' by Joseph Stein, with music by John Kander and lyrics by Fred Ebb, is at the Westport Country Playhouse, 25 Powers Court, through April 28. Information at (203) 227-4177 or westportplayhouse.org.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
