<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From the Foxhole</title>
    <meta content="books22" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Education Life Supplement" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S.; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/education/edlife/books22.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842057"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7DF1F3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1226" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From the Foxhole</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From the Foxhole</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Charles McGrath</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgrath, Charles</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A NICE little profit center in education publishing these days, when Teach for America and similar programs are plopping untested teachers into inner city schools, is the foxhole memoir, a first-person account of what it's really like there in the trenches. The gold standard is probably ''Educating Esmé: Diary of a Teacher's First Year,'' which is still selling briskly in paperback after five years and has spawned an Esmé industry -- six more books by Esmé Raji Codell.</p>
        <p>Written in diary form, like most of the foxhole genre, ''Educating Esmé'' is a record of a year teaching fifth grade in Chicago, and its most distinguishing feature is an almost manic perkiness. Nothing fazes Ms. Codell, except the principal, the moronic Mr. Turner, who stares at her breasts and, for petty bureaucratic reasons, refuses to let her call herself Madame Esmé.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Where the principals are muddle headed, field trips are few and all the children are below average.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A NICE little profit center in education publishing these days, when Teach for America and similar programs are plopping untested teachers into inner city schools, is the foxhole memoir, a first-person account of what it's really like there in the trenches. The gold standard is probably ''Educating Esmé: Diary of a Teacher's First Year,'' which is still selling briskly in paperback after five years and has spawned an Esmé industry -- six more books by Esmé Raji Codell.</p>
        <p>Written in diary form, like most of the foxhole genre, ''Educating Esmé'' is a record of a year teaching fifth grade in Chicago, and its most distinguishing feature is an almost manic perkiness. Nothing fazes Ms. Codell, except the principal, the moronic Mr. Turner, who stares at her breasts and, for petty bureaucratic reasons, refuses to let her call herself Madame Esmé.</p>
        <p>Ms. Codell is a self-cultivated eccentric -- the kind of teacher who likes to dress up in costumes and wear roller skates in class, and who renames the subjects so that science becomes ''Mad Scientist Time'' and social studies turns into ''Time Travel and World Exploring.'' Not surprisingly, some older colleagues find her intensely irritating, and even complain that her room is ''overstimulating'' -- proof, Ms. Codell says, that ''they are totally jealous because I have the most insanely beautiful classroom ever, of all time.''</p>
        <p>And yet, unless she is as self-deluded as she is annoying, Ms. Codell is a very effective teacher -- and her book even suggests that a certain degree of self-delusion may not be such a bad thing. It makes for happier reading.</p>
        <p>Two new foxhole memoirs, ''Man Overboard: Confessions of a Novice Math Teacher in the Bronx'' and, coming out this summer, ''The Great Expectations School: A Rookie Year in the New Blackboard Jungle,'' are by writers who suffer from the opposite problem: a not-unjustified sense of failure and inadequacy.</p>
        <p>As he constantly reminds his readers (and presumably his students), Ric Klass, the author of ''Man Overboard,'' is a graduate of M.I.T. and Harvard Business School who had several successful careers before taking a job as a math teacher at a school he calls Central Bronx High. He thought he could make a difference. Reading between the lines, one guesses that Mr. Klass is probably about as good a teacher as he is a writer, which is to say competent, a little corny, not quite as entertaining as he thinks he is. But in many ways he never even gets a chance. His classroom turns out to be afflicted with collective attention deficit disorder, with students constantly jumping up, wandering around, shouting, fighting, stealing one another's stuff. That's when they bother to come to school at all; for many, attendance is only slightly more reliable than homework compliance.</p>
        <p>Mr. Klass is also weighed down with paperwork, harassed by niggling administrators and so discouraged by his students' lack of effort that as the book progresses, you watch him sink into despair and start to throw in the towel. More and more of his diary entries are simply copies of reports to the security department complaining about disruptive behavior. He concludes that as many as 80 percent of the children at Central Bronx High are essentially write-offs -- doomed not by lack of ability but by behavioral and attitude problems and nonexistent work habits.</p>
        <p>Mr. Klass's biggest failing is discipline -- or ''classroom management,'' to use the professional jargon. That, along with poor bulletin-board presentations, also proves to be the downfall of Dan Brown, author of ''The Great Expectations School.'' Mr. Brown (who can probably count on selling thousands of extra copies to readers confusing him with the Dan Brown who used to teach at Exeter before turning to theological thrillers) is a recent graduate of the New York University film school who went into teaching after Hollywood failed to make him an offer, and found himself, after just a summer of training, in a fourth-grade classroom at Public School 85 in the Bronx. He's an appealing and sympathetic figure with a seemingly genuine talent for teaching (a supervisor says he has the ''gene''), and yet he, too, finds himself in charge of a class that is always on the verge of chaos, even violence, and in which failure quickly becomes the norm.</p>
        <p>CLASSROOM management, it turns out, is both a gift (some teachers at P.S. 85 seem to have been born knowing how to control unruly 10-year-olds) and a learnable skill. But it's hardly a boost to Mr. Brown's confidence when he discovers that his class includes many of the biggest troublemakers in the grade, and that there are very few resources, besides meaningless detentions, to deal with the worst of them, some of whom are clearly disturbed. There are some heartwarming high points as the year goes on, but many more low ones, and, like so many of his colleagues, Mr. Brown begins to suffer from a nearly constant, low-grade depression. His health tailspins, he loses his girlfriend and one day becomes so angry he puts his fist right through the blackboard.</p>
        <p>Like Central Bronx High, P.S. 85 is afflicted with pettifogging bureaucrats, and yet most of the faults seem forgivable, as the place is so clearly under siege and staffed by so many others who, in Mr. Brown's account, emerge as little short of heroic. If Mr. Klass's conclusion is that the fight is practically lost by the time children turn up at Central Bronx, what you conclude about P.S. 85 and schools like it is that the system has begun to fail underprivileged children even before they reach middle school.</p>
        <p>In practically all the foxhole memoirs there is a common villain: standardized testing, which the authors agree has been so overemphasized that it is now an obstacle to the very education it was supposed to measure. And there is a common, if nearly impossible, remedy as well: smaller classes, more resources. Mr. Klass stumbles on this partly by accident when he is asked to take over a group of special ed students and discovers that they do much better than his other classes, simply because he can give them more time.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Brown the discovery comes a year later, when, after being essentially put on probation by P.S. 85, he lands a job at Collegiate, one of New York's elite private schools. Here there are no tests, or even grades, until middle school, and he concludes that the main difference between it and his previous school is not just the bells and whistles afforded by a $27,000 yearly tuition, but simply a sense of community, in which everyone, from the administration down, comes to know and care about everyone else.</p>
        <p>It sounds too good to be true, of course. For all we know, there is a disgruntled, shell-shocked first-year teacher somewhere on the Upper East Side, so overburdened with parent-teacher conferences, with field trips to Tuscany, with students begging for extra homework that he or she is already working on ''Tilapia in the Lunchroom: My Year in Hell.''</p>
        <p>EDUCATING ESMÉ: DIARY OF A TEACHER'S FIRST YEAR  By Esmé Raji Codell (Algonquin Books; paperback)</p>
        <p>THE GREAT EXPECTATIONS SCHOOL: A ROOKIE YEAR IN THE NEW BLACKBOARD JUNGLE  By Dan Brown (Arcade; hardcover)</p>
        <p>MAN OVERBOARD: CONFESSIONS OF A NOVICE MATH TEACHER IN THE BRONX  By Ric Klass (Seven Locks; paperback)</p>
        <p>BOOKS Charles McGrath is a writer at large at The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Charles McGrath is a writer at large at The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
