<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Aide Has One Focus In Trenton: Corzine</title>
    <meta content="22shea" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/22shea.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842293"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Shea, Tom</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Codey, Richard J</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E6DE173EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1589" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Aide Has One Focus In Trenton: Corzine</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Governor Is Sidelined, but His Chief of Staff Keeps Pulling the Strings</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN; Ronald Smothers contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chen, David W</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, April 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As acting governor, Richard J. Codey has been the public face replacing Jon S. Corzine since his devastating car accident, surveying flood damage by helicopter and assembling a task force on campus security as a response to the Virginia Tech shootings.</p>
        <p>But for legislators, lobbyists and other key officials, New Jersey's locus of political power is still the same man who was helping Mr. Corzine navigate state government even before he landed in the intensive care unit: Tom Shea, the chief of staff.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For legislators, lobbyists and other key officials, New Jersey’s locus of political power remains with Tom Shea, the top aide to Gov. Jon S. Corzine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As acting governor, Richard J. Codey has been the public face replacing Jon S. Corzine since his devastating car accident, surveying flood damage by helicopter and assembling a task force on campus security as a response to the Virginia Tech shootings.</p>
        <p>But for legislators, lobbyists and other key officials, New Jersey's locus of political power is still the same man who was helping Mr. Corzine navigate state government even before he landed in the intensive care unit: Tom Shea, the chief of staff.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shea, 40, a New Jersey native who has worked on three presidential campaigns and in the White House political shop, has been close to Mr. Corzine since serving as communications director in his successful 2000 run for the United States Senate. Many here in the state capital see Mr. Shea as the governor's political alter ego and the only person who can act as his conscience and carry out his political wishes.</p>
        <p>And so, over the last week, as Mr. Corzine lay in critical condition, unable to speak and, until Friday afternoon, breathing with the help of a ventilator, Mr. Shea has been shuttling between the State House here and Cooper University Hospital in Camden. He has convened his usual morning staff meetings -- plus a special one last Sunday night on pressing issues -- and sat in on conferences Mr. Corzine normally would have had with department heads and local officials.</p>
        <p>He has been talking to Mr. Codey once or twice a day.</p>
        <p>''There is no question that at the end of the day Tom is making the decisions, because anyone who is working there knows that the governor is going to recover and Tom is the prime minister,'' said James P. Fox, a good friend of Mr. Shea's who served in the same post under former Gov. James E. McGreevey. ''He is one of the most powerful chiefs of staff I have ever seen.''</p>
        <p>But William L. Gormley, who retired in February after three decades in the State Senate, described Mr. Shea as ''the exact opposite of Al Haig,'' recalling the former secretary of state who declared, ''I'm in control here'' after the 1981 assassination attempt on President Ronald Reagan. ''He doesn't talk,'' Mr. Gormley said of Mr. Shea, ''and he's incredibly disciplined.''</p>
        <p>Admirers in Trenton and in Washington say that Mr. Shea is smart, calm and loyal, caring only about Mr. Corzine's agenda, not taking himself too seriously and therefore never viewed as a threat or a rival to the governor.</p>
        <p>Others, though, say privately that Mr. Shea has not done enough to reach out to legislators or lobbyists, reinforcing the suspicion that the administration's soul belongs to aloof out-of-towners from New York and Washington. A profoundly political animal, he shows marginal interest in public policy; of nearly two dozen people interviewed in the past week, not one could identify a single issue or cause about which Mr. Shea seemed especially committed, other than his boss.</p>
        <p>''He's playing poker for Jon Corzine all the time, and he's not going to give you any information, period,'' said Mr. Gormley, a Republican from Atlantic County who worked closely with Democrats and Republicans. ''Of all of the chiefs of staff I have ever dealt with, I have never found one more focused on the individual well-being of his boss. His job is to protect Jon Corzine, period.''</p>
        <p>Never, however, has Mr. Shea's role been as vital as now, with Mr. Corzine possibly weeks or even months from being in any physical or mental shape to govern effectively.</p>
        <p>With one hand, Mr. Shea must push the Corzine agenda on everything from universal health care to the possible lease of the New Jersey Turnpike. With the other, he must accommodate Mr. Codey, a popular fellow Democrat and occasional rival of Mr. Corzine's, in an awkward political minuet of uncertain duration.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shea declined to be interviewed for this article. But according to Corzine aides and lawmakers, Mr. Shea has managed the current crisis involving Mr. Corzine -- or ''my guy,'' as Mary Beth Cahill, a veteran Democratic strategist, says Mr. Shea has long called the governor -- much as he would any other high-stress, sleep-depriving situation. Meeting with key players one on one. Delegating details to staff members. And monitoring every minute on his BlackBerry.</p>
        <p>The day after Mr. Corzine's accident, Mr. Shea had a rare news conference to introduce Mr. Codey, who is also the Senate president, and to promise that the business of the state would continue. Since then, he has stayed behind the scenes, where he generally prefers to be.</p>
        <p>''At first I think it was very awkward for him,'' Mr. Codey said, ''because he's got someone he admires and loves who's critically injured, and I understand the sensitivity for the time being that I'm taking his job.''</p>
        <p>William G. Dressel Jr., executive director of the New Jersey State League of Municipalities, expressed concerns about how a prolonged absence by Mr. Corzine would affect thorny issues like eminent domain.</p>
        <p>''Someone has to emerge in the leadership of the senior staff to pick up that mantle and advance the thinking of Corzine,'' he said. That should be Mr. Shea, Mr. Dressel said, but then a worried look came over his face as he added, ''But his major concern now seems to be monitoring the governor's health on a daily basis.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Shea, more big-picture strategist than micromanager, gives his three deputy chiefs of staff -- Maggie Moran, Patti McGuire and Jeanine LaRue -- a lot of autonomy, said Anthony Coley, Mr. Corzine's communications director. He is also a man of few words; his e-mail messages often consist of one word, or even one letter (''K,'' as in O.K., is a standard one).</p>
        <p>The fifth of eight children of a factory worker father and a mother who worked in the local Catholic church, Mr. Shea grew up in Mays Landing, in Atlantic County, and worked his way through what is now known as the College of New Jersey.</p>
        <p>He worked in Trenton briefly after graduation, serving as deputy director of appointments and chief of staff for the General Service Administration under Gov. Jim Florio.</p>
        <p>''He was very, very savvy at a young age, and he had the ability to think strategically about how political appointments would impact the political structure,'' recalled Kurt P. Shadle, who, as Mr. Florio's director of appointments, was Mr. Shea's boss. ''Frankly, he kept us from making mistakes or stepping on toes.''</p>
        <p>After working on Bill Clinton's 1992 presidential campaign in Michigan, Mr. Shea worked for Harold Ickes, an adviser to Mr. Clinton, in the White House before joining Mr. Corzine's 2000 campaign, in which the candidate's personal wealth, estimated at several hundred million dollars, was a major issue.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine prevailed, and Mr. Shea was his chief of staff in Washington until mid-2004, when he became the Florida state director for Senator John F. Kerry's unsuccessful presidential campaign.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shea rejoined Mr. Corzine for the 2005 governor's race, and it was a nasty battle. First, Mr. Corzine was attacked for having provided, and then forgiven, a $470,000 mortgage to a former companion, who is also the president of a major state workers' union. Then, Mr. Corzine's ex-wife publicly criticized him, saying he had let his family down.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Corzine won, and he has told aides and friends that he could not have done it without Mr. Shea. So by the end of 2005, Mr. Shea was among the top aides to whom Mr. Corzine, a former co-chairman of the investment bank Goldman Sachs, gave gifts of $5,000 to $25,000.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Corzine has waged battles big andsmall, administration aides said, he can be heard bellowing, ''Tom!'' several times a day. Mr. Shea travels frequently by the governor's side, which is unusual for chiefs of staff, though the night of the accident, he was waiting at Drumthwacket, the governor's mansion in Princeton, where Mr. Corzine was scheduled to broker a meeting between Don Imus, the radio host, and the Rutgers women's basketball team he had insulted on the air.</p>
        <p>''Tom doesn't get spooked,'' said Eric Shuffler, a former top aide to Governor McGreevey and to Mr. Codey, who has also written speeches for Mr. Corzine. ''He's not one of these people who says, 'We have to cut a deal because people are upset or the press is beating us up.' Tom is not afraid to stick to his guns.''</p>
        <p>At times, Mr. Shea can give the impression that he is bored in meetings, according to several administration officials and other New Jersey Democrats. He uses his BlackBerry so regularly that a skit during an annual dinner for journalists and politicos last year featured a reporter acting as Mr. Shea, typing madly on the device, saying not a word.</p>
        <p>Lisa P. Jackson, the state's environmental commissioner, recalled one meeting with the governor last fall involving a complicated issue, in which Mr. Shea spent most of the time playing his favorite BlackBerry game, BrickBreaker.</p>
        <p>Ms. Jackson said she was annoyed, until suddenly Mr. Shea put his BlackBerry down, and offered a concise summary and cogent proposal. ''He may need to keep his fingers busy, but his mind is right with you,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Every few months, there are reports in the local press that Mr. Shea may leave the administration and move to the Fort Lauderdale, Fla., area, where he owns property. Maybe even run for Congress.</p>
        <p>But not, friends and others say, so long as Mr. Corzine needs him.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
