<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Run First, Then Look At Earnings</title>
    <meta content="22mark" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/business/yourmoney/22mark.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842193"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E2DC163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="509" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Run First, Then Look At Earnings</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Run First, Then Look at Earnings</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONRAD DE AENLLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">De Aenlle, Conrad</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE stock market enters the week a bit higher than it was two months ago, and far higher than many investors are likely to have expected after share prices plunged in late February. One market watcher thinks that this is a good time to try to learn lessons from the episode.</p>
        <p>For that strategist, Jonathan Golub, of JPMorgan Asset Management, the decline is fodder for a crash course in anthropology more than finance or economics. He advised traders to get in touch with the primitive hominid that lurks within them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The recovery in share prices has been aided by strong earnings reports. But such a favorable ratio is the norm, and not as rosy as it seems, according to an analyst.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE stock market enters the week a bit higher than it was two months ago, and far higher than many investors are likely to have expected after share prices plunged in late February. One market watcher thinks that this is a good time to try to learn lessons from the episode.</p>
        <p>For that strategist, Jonathan Golub, of JPMorgan Asset Management, the decline is fodder for a crash course in anthropology more than finance or economics. He advised traders to get in touch with the primitive hominid that lurks within them.</p>
        <p>''We're wired to make decisions not as people who went to Harvard Business School but as cavemen,'' Mr. Golub said. ''The world is more evolved, but the decision making is not.''</p>
        <p>We may dress better than our primitive ancestors, but we respond to danger in the same way. ''We're descendants of people who ran first and then evaluated the situation,'' Mr. Golub said. ''The people who evaluated things rationally didn't pass on their genes.''</p>
        <p>The growling animal two months ago sounded like a bear to many investors, who explained its rampage only after they had gotten out of its way. The causes offered for the sudden drop were quite lame, he said: a recession prediction that was attributed to Alan Greenspan, the former Federal Reserve chairman, but that Mr. Greenspan denied making; and orders for durable goods that appeared weak because of soft aircraft orders, a notoriously volatile figure.</p>
        <p>''We got freaked out,'' Mr. Golub said. That occurs more often than many investors realize, he said. Another drop, steeper than the recent one, at some point this year would not be out of the ordinary, he cautioned.</p>
        <p>The recovery in share prices has been aided by strong earnings reports. About two-thirds have beaten analysts' estimates, and Mr. Golub expects more of the same as corporate results continue to roll in this week.</p>
        <p>But such a favorable ratio is the norm, he pointed out, and not as rosy as it seems. ''If you see a number close to 50-50,'' with as many companies missing estimates as beating them, he warned, ''it would not be positive for the market.''</p>
        <p>Analysts' tendency to lowball earnings estimates is a corollary of the law of the jungle that governs market panics, Mr. Golub explained. Analysts are overly cautious because no one wants to stray too far from the herd, he said. (Better to be wrong with others than to be wrong alone.)</p>
        <p>DATA WATCH -- More mixed signals are expected from the housing market. Existing-home sales are forecast in a Bloomberg News poll of economists to show a decline to an annual rate of 6.41 million units in March from 6.69 million in February; that report is due on Tuesday. The next day, sales of new homes are predicted to come in at an 8.9 million rate, up from 8.48 million.</p>
        <p>The report on orders for durable goods, also on Wednesday, is estimated to show a gain of 2.5 percent in March after a 1.7 percent gain in February.</p>
        <p>MARKET WEEK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
