<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Melissa Epstein, Jason Mills</title>
    <meta content="22Epstein" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/fashion/weddings/22Epstein.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842148"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Epstein, Melissa Jill (Melissa Jill Mills)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mills, Jason Scott</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E0DF163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="422" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Melissa Epstein, Jason Mills</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Melissa Epstein, Jason Mills</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Melissa Jill Epstein, the daughter of Gail Epstein of Poughkeepsie, N.Y., and Paul Epstein of Hopewell Junction, N.Y., was married yesterday to Jason Scott Mills, the son of Bonnie Mills and Gerald Mills of Yucaipa, Calif. The Rev. Margaret Duttera, a Lutheran minister, officiated at the Adamson House in Malibu, Calif.</p>
        <p>The bride and bridegroom, both 32, were Marine captains. She left active duty in 2006 after four years; he in 2004 after five years. They met in February 2004 in Iraq, where they were serving as Marine prosecutors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Melissa Jill Epstein, the daughter of Gail Epstein of Poughkeepsie, N.Y., and Paul Epstein of Hopewell Junction, N.Y., was married yesterday to Jason Scott Mills, the son of Bonnie Mills and Gerald Mills of Yucaipa, Calif. The Rev. Margaret Duttera, a Lutheran minister, officiated at the Adamson House in Malibu, Calif.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Melissa Jill Epstein, the daughter of Gail Epstein of Poughkeepsie, N.Y., and Paul Epstein of Hopewell Junction, N.Y., was married yesterday to Jason Scott Mills, the son of Bonnie Mills and Gerald Mills of Yucaipa, Calif. The Rev. Margaret Duttera, a Lutheran minister, officiated at the Adamson House in Malibu, Calif.</p>
        <p>The bride and bridegroom, both 32, were Marine captains. She left active duty in 2006 after four years; he in 2004 after five years. They met in February 2004 in Iraq, where they were serving as Marine prosecutors.</p>
        <p>The bride is a litigation associate at Gibson, Dunn &amp; Crutcher, a law firm in Los Angeles. She graduated from the State University of New York at Binghamton and received her law degree from Columbia. Before joining the Marines in 2002, she was a prosecution lawyer for a year at the International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia in The Hague.</p>
        <p>Her father is a lawyer in Beacon, N.Y. Her mother is an assistant county attorney in Poughkeepsie for Dutchess County.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom is an associate in labor and employment law at the Los Angeles office of Morgan, Lewis &amp; Bockius, a Philadelphia law firm. He graduated from the University of California, San Diego, and received his law degree from the University of Minnesota.</p>
        <p>His mother is a mediator for the court system of San Bernardino County, Calif. His father works out of Bloomington, Calif., as a truck driver for Roadway Express.</p>
        <p>''Besides her physical beauty, what struck me about Melissa was how intelligent she is,'' Mr. Mills said of his early conversations with Ms. Epstein. ''Despite having so much going for her, she's a very modest person.''</p>
        <p>They traveled extensively throughout Al Anbar Province -- sometimes together, sometimes separately -- to conduct investigations and litigate court-martial proceedings.</p>
        <p>''We were stationed together at the same office,'' Ms. Epstein said. ''It was a very stressful environment, and in those situations you get to know somebody quite well.''</p>
        <p>They learned they both liked Jon Stewart, Stephen Colbert, food and running, and they exercised together on the base.</p>
        <p>They discovered they shared a liberal political bent. ''That's not the norm in the Marine Corps,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But they didn't go on a date until shortly after returning to the United States from Iraq in the fall of 2004.</p>
        <p>''It's against protocol to date in a combat theater,'' she said. ''Besides, neither of our minds were in that place. We were very focused on the mission. And frankly,'' she added, ''camouflage is not the most attractive look for everyone.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
