<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Turn Left at [Your Name Here]</title>
    <meta content="22CImiller" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/opinion/nyregionopinions/22CImiller.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842178"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Names, Geographical</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Streets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Stuart</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Names, Geographical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Names, Geographical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DC163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="832" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Turn Left at [Your Name Here]</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Turn Left at [Your Name Here]</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Miller</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Miller, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by Stuart Miller holds New York City's commemorative street sign process wastes money, is too frequently driven by kitsch or politics and does little to pay tribute to those who deserve it (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHO on this list doesn't belong?</p>
        <p>Jane Jacobs, longtime Greenwich Village resident who influenced urban planning in New York for several generations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Too many streets are cluttered with signs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHO on this list doesn't belong?</p>
        <p>Jane Jacobs, longtime Greenwich Village resident who influenced urban planning in New York for several generations.</p>
        <p>Al Jolson, king of Broadway for three decades.</p>
        <p>Humphrey Bogart, Upper West Side native who became a film icon.</p>
        <p>Florry Burrell, Girl Scout troop leader and school aide at Public School 13 in Queens.</p>
        <p>Those four were among the 122 people and organizations honored by the City Council in 2006 with a ''street co-naming'' -- those street signs that don't make maps but clutter up corners -- and while Florry Burrell may have been a wonderful person and a neighborhood fixture, her inclusion reveals a process that wastes money, is too frequently driven by kitsch or politics, and does little to pay tribute to those who deserve it.</p>
        <p>Last week, a City Council committee rejected a proposal to name a Brooklyn street after controversial advocate Sonny Carson. This may provoke a re-evaluation of this flawed, well-meaning system, but the truth is that it's a reminder of how rare it is that any name submitted by a community board ever fails to win approval. As the Council prepares to vote next month on the 52 names that passed muster, perhaps it should instead debate whether these street signs serve any real purpose.</p>
        <p>The commemorative street sign was born decades ago but for most of its life, additions were made only periodically and haphazardly.</p>
        <p>After 9/11, the co-naming of New York began in earnest: amid the clamor to honor victims, the Council decided that each spring and fall it would co-name dozens of blocks at a time. (Honorary signs once had blue backgrounds but the new ones are green, matching regular street signs.)</p>
        <p>A few household names are added each year, like the longtime New Yorkers Gilda Radner and Katharine Hepburn. Frederick Douglass and Malcolm X are also worthy but already have streets named after them in Harlem -- so why lionize them again with a sign at Chambers and West Streets and 97th Street in Queens, respectively? And why co-name streets for Bob Marley and Pope John Paul II? Adding famous people with tenuous connections to the city further dilutes the system.</p>
        <p>Most honorees are simply beloved community members. With no standards, however, co-naming borders on cronyism. Take, for example, Richard Addeo, memorialized at Edward Curry and South Avenues on Staten Island. According to the Council's description, Mr. Addeo supported the local Y.M.C.A. and March of Dimes; he also ran a well-respected electrical contracting company and gave Staten Island politicians rides in his private jet and jobs to their family members.</p>
        <p>Like Florry Burrell, Mr. Addeo could easily be venerated by the local organizations he helped. Instead those community groups prompt council members to spend the city's time and money on these street signs.</p>
        <p>Those who died tragically are the other major recipients of co-naming. It's too late to debate whether all the 9/11 victims need their own streets when they'll also have a major memorial at ground zero. But this nice gesture starts a slippery slope, as does recognizing victims like Genesis Regalado, an 11-year-old killed in a drive-by shooting in Queens, or Karl Feldman, who died at 19 from cancer. Remembering each New Yorker whose life ended too soon will quickly use up every street in the city.</p>
        <p>Not only are there too many signs, but they are ultimately useless, since they provide no explanation of who these people were and why they were so honored. The section of Queens Boulevard named for Sharon Rivers and Caprice Bush, struck down by a car, fails as a warning if no one knows their story. All each sign does is please a handful of family and friends.</p>
        <p>There is a simple solution to this problem, but it would require politicians to turn down their constituents. Instead of honoring 75 to 100 people a year, the Council should set a limit of, say, a dozen. (Those shut out can be given kudos on a locally sponsored honor roll.) This way they'd have to honestly debate their decisions and choose only those who genuinely earned co-naming.</p>
        <p>The money saved on those street signs could be used instead on historical plaques telling the stories of the deserving dozen. With fewer names, it would be possible to call attention to those plaques -- children studying New York City could even learn about these people and go on class trips to those blocks.</p>
        <p>Today, people walk down Florry Burrell Way (52nd Avenue at 94th Street in Queens) and Elizabeth Jennings Place (Park Row at Beekman Street in Manhattan) in ignorance or apathy -- just as they walk along Albee Square and Jay Street and hundreds of others without understanding their history.</p>
        <p>The best solution would be not only to honor the crème de la crème like Jennings -- the brave woman who, a full century before Rosa Parks, set off the protest and a lawsuit that allowed blacks to ride New York City's buses -- but to do it right.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor Stuart Miller is the author of ''The 100 Greatest Days in New York Sports.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Stuart Miller is the author of ''The 100 Greatest Days in New York Sports.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
