<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Adopted Child Is a Riddle. Now I Have a Clue.</title>
    <meta content="22love" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/fashion/22love.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842131"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MODERN LOVE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Babies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Adoptions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Babies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Adoptions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E2DF163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1808" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Adopted Child Is a Riddle. Now I Have a Clue.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Adopted Child Is a Riddle. Now I Have a Clue.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NONA MARTIN STUCK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stuck, Nona Martin</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BY our own clear-eyed assessment, my husband and I sprang from relatively shallow ends of our respective gene pools. Had we chosen to try to overcome our infertility and produce our own children, they most likely would have had crooked teeth and bad tempers and been as myopic as moles.</p>
        <p>Instead, we adopted three of the loveliest, brightest and most interesting people I know. And the three women responsible for our good fortune have remained strangers, largely unaware of how they have enriched our lives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A meeting with the birth mother provides answers, and also some questions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BY our own clear-eyed assessment, my husband and I sprang from relatively shallow ends of our respective gene pools. Had we chosen to try to overcome our infertility and produce our own children, they most likely would have had crooked teeth and bad tempers and been as myopic as moles.</p>
        <p>Instead, we adopted three of the loveliest, brightest and most interesting people I know. And the three women responsible for our good fortune have remained strangers, largely unaware of how they have enriched our lives.</p>
        <p>Our fourth adoption began just like the others. Domestic and private, it required, in addition to a lawyer, a social worker to ensure once again that we were suitable candidates for parenthood. She was also responsible for conducting the interview with the birth mother and was, in effect, a state-sanctioned go-between in what had always been for us an anonymous affair.</p>
        <p>But times were changing. The previously locked doors of adoption information were swinging open, and what had once been considered a shameful secret by many was increasingly seen as a loving choice.</p>
        <p>So it was that the social worker one day asked me whether I had ever wanted to meet one of my children's birth mothers.</p>
        <p>''Oh, God, yes!''</p>
        <p>''Well,'' she continued, ''this one is interested in meeting you. Do you want me to arrange it?''</p>
        <p>I was stunned into an uncharacteristic silence. Meeting the birth mother had not even been presented as a possibility in our other adoptions. Always, though, I had wondered about them, worried about them, imagined conversations with them. I knew they were young, between 15 and 19, and unmarried. And I assumed they were as frightened and uncertain about the future as I would have been in their situation.</p>
        <p>On a Friday morning in mid-September, the social worker called to tell me that a meeting had been set up for the following Wednesday at a coffee shop in a small town an hour's drive away.</p>
        <p>When I shared the news with my husband, he was less than enthusiastic. While supporting my decision to meet the woman, he wanted no part in the meeting. ''Too much raw emotion'' was how he put it. Even talking about it made him uneasy.</p>
        <p>I, on the other hand, was twitchy with anticipation. My children were 8, 6 and 3, and their personalities were emerging before my eyes like quick-developing photographs. Watching these transformations, I had begun to have a sense of their biological mothers as I have of the characters in my favorite books, never actually seen but unmistakable in their particularity.</p>
        <p>Where had these surprises in disposition and style originated? Where was the adult version of that one's smile, another's playful confidence with strangers, his perfect pitch, her gift for mimicry? Were there other children, brothers and sisters with the same endearing traits and annoying habits? And would knowing the answers be a blessing or a curse?</p>
        <p>On the day of our meeting, I chose my outfit as carefully as I ever had for a date. As I drove, I let my thoughts drift to those other three women. They were in my mind often, especially at the milestones of my children's lives: the first haircuts, steps taken, words spoken; as training wheels came off their bikes and as braces went on their teeth; on each first day of school, and at every soccer game and piano recital. At birthday celebrations I experienced a vague unease, as if I had forgotten to invite a close relative.</p>
        <p>I remembered precisely where I was and what I'd been doing at the moment I received each phone call bringing the news of the birth. Surely their memories of those hours were more intense than mine. Yet did they observe those anniversaries? I could only imagine, and I did.</p>
        <p>When the coffee shop came into view, I resisted the urge to drive past and had to rely on deep breathing to maintain my composure as I parked the car. Getting out, I caught sight of myself in the side mirror and saw that sprigs of my hair were sticking up at goofy angles and my mascara was smudged, but it was too late for repairs.</p>
        <p>Inside, a very pregnant woman sitting alone in a booth rose to shake my hand. She asked about my drive, laughing nervously when I mispronounced her name. By the time the waitress had refilled our coffee cups, the awkwardness had passed and we were interrupting each other, eager to tell and know everything.</p>
        <p>She was in her late 20s, divorced and raising two preschoolers on her own. A lapsed Catholic, she maintained she was still under the sway of what she had been taught.</p>
        <p>Sensing I was in favor of abortion rights, she looked directly at me and said, ''I really am pro-choice, and my choice is to have this baby.'' And then, with conviction and regret, she added: ''But I can't raise it. I can't single-parent another child. I just can't.''</p>
        <p>We traded pictures and stories of our children. I told her I felt fortunate to have held all three of my children within their first 24 hours. About the births of her son and daughter, she said: ''Those first few minutes after they're born are amazing. They look right at you, as if they already know who you are.''</p>
        <p>As we prepared to leave, she took my hand. ''My mother and sister will be there for me, to help and all, but I don't think I can be there for this baby, not in the way I was with my others.'' She looked near tears, but went on. ''I want him to have somebody right from the beginning.''</p>
        <p>Finally we said our goodbyes, and I drove home in a rich sensory fog of baby lust and the giddiness of this new relationship.</p>
        <p>Three months later she called me, not to announce a birth but to explain that a satisfactory fetal stress test had stamped the O.K. on an induced labor. The holidays were fast approaching, and neither of us wanted the delivery to fall on a day ideally devoted to celebration with our other children, hers and mine. My husband again declined to join us, promising instead to arrive the next day to drive our new baby and me home.</p>
        <p>I reached the hospital in midafternoon, anticipating an all-nighter. I carried along magazines, a pillow and the tiny needlepoint stocking I was trying to finish for Christmas. I had just unwrapped a skein of yarn when I heard my name called. I looked up to see the face of a young woman who was clearly the birth mother's sister.</p>
        <p>''Would you like to come into the birthing suite?'' she asked.</p>
        <p>I hadn't expected to be summoned until after the delivery but followed her along the hall and into the dimly lighted room. There I found the birth mother, propped on pillows, smiling, but well into the hard work of late labor. Her dark red hair was tangled, and sweat beaded her forehead and upper lip.</p>
        <p>Her mother stood at the bedside, a damp washcloth and basin at the ready. It was she who motioned me nearer. We waited through a strong contraction, then the four of us joined hands, and within minutes our boundaries seemed to dissolve and we began the work for which we had gathered.</p>
        <p>My memory of the next three hours is as clear as any I hold, and as otherworldly as if from a dream. The delivery and the minutes following remain in my mind more impression than distinct images. I remember cutting the umbilical cord, and then I was holding the baby, and he was, just as she had promised, looking into my eyes.</p>
        <p>Someone was crying, then everyone was crying, and my attention was once again drawn to the woman in the bed. A nurse lifted the child from my arms, explaining that he would need to be weighed and have the routine newborn blood tests in the nursery. She left the room, and I slipped back into my place, an integral member of this group of smiling, weeping women.</p>
        <p>''You're not Catholic, are you?'' the grandmother asked sheepishly.</p>
        <p>''No, I'm Presbyterian.''</p>
        <p>''But you're not one of those, you know, who wait until they're teenagers to baptize them?''</p>
        <p>''No,'' I assured her. ''Definitely infant baptism.''</p>
        <p>She slumped with relief.</p>
        <p>''A month at the most, just after the holidays,'' I said. ''Don't worry, he's safe.''</p>
        <p>A tension that I hadn't been aware of seemed to evaporate and we all laughed and began to talk at once, about Christmas and gifts and food, about almost everything but babies.</p>
        <p>AFTER a while the birth mother reached for my arm, and I steadied her as she slipped gingerly from the bed. She moved toward the bathroom, leaning against me a little, and as she turned, she gave my hand a squeeze. ''I'm fine,'' she assured me, and closed the door.</p>
        <p>When she emerged she was fully dressed. She had combed her hair and put on lipstick, and only the redness of her eyes and the huskiness of her voice gave her away. ''I think I would like to go home now,'' she said, looking past me to where her mother and sister were standing.</p>
        <p>''You're leaving?'' Even I could hear the quaver in my words. ''Are you sure?''</p>
        <p>She nodded.</p>
        <p>My mind raced with unasked questions. I suddenly needed to know everything, not only about her family and history but the histories of the other three birth mothers, whom I had never met. Somehow, in the intensity of our shared experience, I had combined them and made her the repository for the secrets of all their lives. As foolish as it seemed, I wanted her to tell me that they would be O.K. as well.</p>
        <p>As we made our way along the hall, we attempted to fill the awkward space with generic goodbyes. There were no assurances about keeping in touch. We knew we wouldn't. As the elevator doors were closing, I thought of the baby and my pulse quickened, but I knew it was more than the thrill of new motherhood.</p>
        <p>There was now a person and a past where only a fantasy had been, and in the years ahead I would come to appreciate the importance of this connection. I would watch my child's intense response to music, be enchanted by his smile, stand in awe of his feisty determination, and I'd know the origin of these characteristics.</p>
        <p>And I could choose, when the time was right, to share this story, his story, with him. For the moment, though, it was with a silent ''thank you'' to the mother I knew and those I didn't that I turned back, headed for the nursery and my son.</p>
        <p>E-mail: modernlove@nytimes.com</p>
        <p>MODERN LOVE Nona Martin Stuck, an essayist who is writing a novel, lives in Columbia, S.C.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Nona Martin Stuck, an essayist who is writing a novel, lives in Columbia, S.C.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
