<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Democracy's Often Quirky in Town Where 'Rockwell Meets the Sopranos'</title>
    <meta content="22towns" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/22towns.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842284"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OUR TOWNS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Our Towns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Putnam County (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EEDF173EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="882" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Democracy's Often Quirky in Town Where 'Rockwell Meets the Sopranos'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Democracy’s Often Quirky in Town Where ‘Rockwell Meets the Sopranos’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER APPLEBOME</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Applebome, Peter</byline>
      <dateline>PUTNAM VALLEY, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Tony Soprano wanted to get away from it all on this year's first episode, where did he go?</p>
        <p>He came to beautiful Lake Oscawana here in Putnam Valley, where they shot the lakeside scenes in the episode where Tony visited his sister Janice and brother-in-law Bobby, played the world's nastiest game of Monopoly and got an AR-10 machine gun as a birthday present.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>People look at politics in the scenic hideaway of Putnam Valley as if pondering a head-on car crash.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Tony Soprano wanted to get away from it all on this year's first episode, where did he go?</p>
        <p>He came to beautiful Lake Oscawana here in Putnam Valley, where they shot the lakeside scenes in the episode where Tony visited his sister Janice and brother-in-law Bobby, played the world's nastiest game of Monopoly and got an AR-10 machine gun as a birthday present.</p>
        <p>It's surely coincidence that at a real-world gathering on the same lake just a few weeks earlier, one resident described the town as ''Norman Rockwell meets the Sopranos.'' Others might vote for ''Twin Peaks'' as the better model.</p>
        <p>Still, whatever your reference point, people look at politics in this scenic Putnam County hideaway just north of Westchester as if pondering a head-on car crash -- watch the collision or turn your eyes away? It's mostly small potatoes, centering on local development issues and the town supervisor's hiring his girlfriend as his secretary, but it's a reminder that grass-roots democracy isn't necessarily any more edifying than the big-time version.</p>
        <p>So at the town hall on Wednesday night, there was Anthony J. Bondi Jr. in his long black robe, cross and black ponytail as an archbishop of the Holy Orthodox Catholic and Apostolic Church of America (and a member of the local ethics board) lecturing the Putnam Valley town supervisor, Sam Davis.</p>
        <p>He accused Mr. Davis of demeaning and insulting him and all Orthodox Christians and went on: ''The people of Putnam Valley may be patient and kind, but we are not stupid. We gave you a very long rope, and you, sir, are hanging yourself.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis, a former science teacher and chiropractor serving his first term,  hair tied back in his ponytail, listened politely and then responded, ''If you look into your soul, I think you'll find more bigotry than you'll ever find in mine.'' Things went on in that vein until people from the audience started shouting, ''Take it outside,'' as if a fistfight rather than plain old verbiage was the logical finale.</p>
        <p>The next morning Mr. Davis took time off from discussing local politics to mosey back to the same boardroom, where he was arraigned on a trespassing charge stemming from a dispute with a local landowner while on county business. He said it was political harassment.</p>
        <p>Whatever the alignment now, some say things here have been contentious almost from the beginning, when the town was founded as Quincy in 1839 and then changed its name within a year because of unhappiness with the town's namesake, President John Quincy Adams.</p>
        <p>One theory on the town's contrary nature is that it stems from the large and shallow deposits of magnetite, magnetic iron, that may be throwing everyone a bit off-kilter. A more probable one is that it's so contrary because it's so diverse, an isolated farming and mining community that drew urban émigrés with its lakes and the raffish tourism economy of the '30s and '40s (it had 23 bars in the 1940s) and now has contemporary offshoots of both those strains, plus a strong coterie of environmentalists and artists who were Mr. Davis's strongest supporters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis, a Democrat, was elected by 44 votes in November 2005, to the astonishment of almost everyone in the town of about 11,000. He ran as a staunch environmentalist, a position that was not viewed by all as motherhood and apple pie.</p>
        <p>''The original concept was 'Hereafter, if you want to build anything in Putnam Valley, it's going to be a teepee; if you want plumbing it's going to be a hole in the ground; do not use phosphates when you beat your laundry to death on the rocks in the creek; and don't cut down anything bigger than a blade of grass,' '' said Anne Spoonhour, a justice court clerk.</p>
        <p>With his narrow surprise victory and antidevelopment stance, Mr. Davis would have been a big target even if he hadn't hired his girlfriend as his secretary. He said he already offered the job to three others and made sure it was wholly legal, but it did give his opponents a club to beat him with. A year and a half later, both sides are still swinging. The town board censured him, citing an appearance of impropriety. He sued them. His suit was thrown out this month, allowing both sides to claim victory. His opponents cited the dismissal of the suit. He cited the finding that there was no ethics violation. Now they're battling over court costs.</p>
        <p>All of this doesn't even touch on the other main narrative of the Davis era, the role of John Zarcone, a tough-talking attorney and a powerful Republican, viewed by many as an intimidating, bullying pro-development presence. Mr. Davis was viewed as one of the few people willing to take him on, a role that became less important for now when Mr. Zarcone was arrested this month and charged with cocaine possession and threatening to kill his wife. He said he was entering a rehabilitation center but was innocent of the charges.</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis seems likely to run again, saying Putnam Valley does have its idiosyncrasies, but that the campaign against him had parallels elsewhere. ''This was all about winning at any cost,'' he said. ''Just like politics at the national level.''</p>
        <p>OUR TOWNS E-mail: peappl@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: peappl@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
