<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Should It Be So Hard to Tally Votes Fairly?</title>
    <meta content="22colweWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/22colwe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842052"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Voting Machines</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ciber Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lombardi, Kate Stone</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EED61E3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="807" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Should It Be So Hard to Tally Votes Fairly?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Should It Be So Hard to Tally Votes Fairly?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATE STONE LOMBARDI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lombardi, Kate Stone</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kate Stone Lombardi column on impasse over what type of voting machines Westchester County will use in 2008 presidential election; state's 2005 Election Reform and Modernization Act requires that counties choose their machines from state-approved list; state has not yet approved any machines because contract with Ciber Inc, which was testing new models, has been suspended; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH the 2008 presidential campaign already making headlines, the question is how Westchester is going to vote. I mean that literally -- not whether the county will vote Democratic or Republican, but actually how will those votes be cast, on what kind of machinery?</p>
        <p>Federal law mandates that the old lever-style machines be replaced. It's up to our two county election commissioners, both political appointees, to choose the new electronic equipment on which Westchester residents will cast their ballots. But what we're getting, and when we're getting it, is completely up in the air, dependent on forces well beyond local control.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Is a presidential election really the right time to be asking citizens to acquire new voting skills?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH the 2008 presidential campaign already making headlines, the question is how Westchester is going to vote. I mean that literally -- not whether the county will vote Democratic or Republican, but actually how will those votes be cast, on what kind of machinery?</p>
        <p>Federal law mandates that the old lever-style machines be replaced. It's up to our two county election commissioners, both political appointees, to choose the new electronic equipment on which Westchester residents will cast their ballots. But what we're getting, and when we're getting it, is completely up in the air, dependent on forces well beyond local control.</p>
        <p>One thing election officials agree on -- forget 2007 for the new machines; it's not going to happen. And if the new equipment is ready for 2008, some people are wondering if it should be used. Is a presidential election really the right time to be asking citizens to acquire new voting skills?</p>
        <p>The seeds of the current impasse were planted just after the contested 2000 presidential election (think butterfly ballots and hanging chads). In 2002, Congress passed the Help America Vote Act, which required that punch-card and lever machines be replaced and set new standards for running elections. It sounds straightforward enough. But putting the new law in place in New York has been problematic, to say the least.</p>
        <p>''I've heard it referred to as the 'Hinder America Vote Act,' because it's raised more problems than it solved,'' said Marion S. Sinek, a former president of the League of Women Voters of New York State and now an adviser to Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton.</p>
        <p>Ms. Sinek recently addressed the League of Women Voters of New Castle to talk about the conversion to electronic voting, the pros and cons of different types of machines and the political morass surrounding the issue.</p>
        <p>Each state had to comply with the 2002 federal voting law, Ms. Sinek said. New York's legislature, never known for acting with dispatch, finally passed the Election Reform and Modernization Act in 2005. The state law is considered one of the most stringent in the country. It has tough auditing standards, requires what is called a voter-verified paper trail and mandates that voting machine vendors put the software codes of their machines into escrow to help detect hacking.</p>
        <p>The law also specifies that election commissioners in each county select their own voting machines, so voters in Westchester may be voting on equipment different from that used in Putnam. Nor are all electronic voting machines created equal.</p>
        <p>It's easy to get lost in the alphabet soup of acronyms of the different models. You've got D.R.E.'s and P.B.O.S.'s The first are direct-recording electronic machines; a voter touches a screen, and the vote is recorded. P.B.O.S.'s are precinct-based optical scanners; a voter marks a paper ballot, which is then scanned by an electronic machine.</p>
        <p>The League of Women Voters favors the optical scanners, because they say it is easier to recount and verify votes and the machines are less prone to security flaws. But proponents of the direct-recording devices argue that they are easier to use, particularly for the disabled.</p>
        <p>Which way will Westchester election commissioners go? Right now, they can't go anywhere. State law requires that counties choose their machines from a state-approved list. But the state hasn't approved any machines yet. Why? Because New York suspended its $3 million contract with Ciber Inc., the laboratory that was testing the new models, after federal officials found deficiencies in its practices.</p>
        <p>Lee K. Daghlian, a spokesman for the New York State Board of Elections, said the board would soon put out a request for proposals for a new testing company. In the meantime, the Justice Department has sued the state for failing to comply with earlier deadlines in the federal voting act. The new machines were supposed to be certified by May 7, with the counties making their choices and reporting back to the state by May 11. Mr. Daghlian said he hoped to be able to provide counties with a list of certified machines ''some time in the fall.''</p>
        <p>Carolee C. Sunderland, the county's Republican election commissioner, said she was frustrated with the current state of affairs.</p>
        <p>''Westchester won't be in compliance, but it's not because of anything the county, the board or the people have done,'' Ms. Sunderland said. ''The state has been so far behind. We're going to have to look at what's best for the voters. And we know in the computer world, what's new now is old by the time you get it a month from now.''</p>
        <p>While Westchester waits, reports of malfunctioning machines and more contested elections are coming in from states that have already converted to electronic voting. ''So much has happened to erode people's confidence,'' Ms. Sinek said, ''people need to know that their votes will be counted.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
