<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Say It Loud. Improvise. Keep 'Em Guessing.</title>
    <meta content="22wong" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/weekinreview/22wong.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842224"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WORLD: THE RIDDLE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Shiite Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Arabs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arabs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shiite Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Mahdi Army</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Sadr, Moktada Al-</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E4D9163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1466" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Say It Loud. Improvise. Keep 'Em Guessing.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Say It Loud. Improvise. Keep ’Em Guessing.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WONG; Hosham Hussein contributed reporting for this article.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wong, Edward</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MOKTADA AL-SADR'S power is felt from Baghdad to the Beltway even when he has vanished from sight.</p>
        <p>For the last month, from a secret location, the young Shiite cleric has fanned the flames of Iraqi nationalism and anti-American sentiment, a sure path to popularity in his frightened, frustrated land.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Anti-Americanism is Moktada al-Sadr’s lifeblood. Still, he doesn’t want to go too far.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MOKTADA AL-SADR'S power is felt from Baghdad to the Beltway even when he has vanished from sight.</p>
        <p>For the last month, from a secret location, the young Shiite cleric has fanned the flames of Iraqi nationalism and anti-American sentiment, a sure path to popularity in his frightened, frustrated land.</p>
        <p>He organized a protest that drew tens of thousands of people to the Shiite holy city of Najaf to demand an end to the American military presence. They burned American flags and chanted, ''Death to America!'' Then, last week, he withdrew his six cabinet ministers from the government, complaining that it was not doing enough to rid the country of the Americans.</p>
        <p>But press his aides for concrete details of a timetable to present to the Americans, and the picture becomes murkier. They say they want the Americans out. But not just yet.</p>
        <p>''In order to drive out the occupation, we need to build up the security forces; then we can have a timetable,'' said Abdul Mehdi Mutairi, one of Mr. Sadr's top political officials, as he smoked at his desk inside the main Sadr office in Baghdad, his television tuned to an Iranian-financed satellite network. He was referring to the Iraqi government's largely Shiite army and police, which by all accounts could not yet control Iraqi violence on their own.</p>
        <p>The gap between Mr. Sadr's public oratory and his actions shows that he, as much as any American or Iraqi official, is captive to the fact that there is no easy path to securing Iraq's future. He does have a starkly plain vision -- a centralized Islamist Iraq ruled by nationalist Shiites who are distanced from, if not openly hostile to, the United States. But he also has a problem all too familiar to the Bush administration: he does not know exactly how to realize his vision, given the complexities of the conflict.</p>
        <p>He has become a great improviser, the Miles Davis of the war.</p>
        <p>He publicly courts anti-American Sunni nationalists while his Mahdi Army militia kills Sunni Arabs. He denounces Shiite groups backed by Iran while he is said to be hiding in Iran and taking instructions from clerics there. He promotes Shiite unity while Mahdi fighters battle other Shiite groups in cities across the south, as they did this month in Diwaniya.</p>
        <p>There is even widespread talk that he has ordered an elite wing of the Mahdi Army, known as the Thahabiya, or Golden Unit, to assassinate rogue militiamen from his own organization.</p>
        <p>Last week, as his allies quit the cabinet, he said he could no longer work with the government. But he left his 30 legislators in the Parliament.</p>
        <p>A secular senior Iraqi official said Mr. Sadr's thinking was in constant evolution, groping for a workable strategy for the war.</p>
        <p>''The Sadrists, I've said all along, operate on a Hezbollah model,'' the official said, referring to the nationalist Lebanese Shiite group that has successfully fought Israel. ''But Hassan Nasrallah is much more sophisticated than Moktada al-Sadr. Mookie is a reflection of the rough world of Iraqi Shia, and Hassan Nasrallah is a reflection of the sophisticated world of Lebanese Shia.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps nothing is more surprising than the fact that Mr. Sadr's attitude toward the Americans actually reflects a degree of ambivalence.</p>
        <p>Anti-Americanism is the basis of his unflagging popularity. More than any other Iraqi politician, he is willing to recognize, validate and capitalize on the refusal of large segments of the Shiite population, especially the poor and dispossessed, to buy into any government that has the support of the Americans. It is one of the most vexing problems for the Americans, since President Bush's whole strategy rests on the premise that formerly oppressed Shiites will work with the Americans.</p>
        <p>''How can we accept the fact that our country is taken over or occupied, especially since we've seen nothing from the occupier but destruction for four years, and they've succeeded only in planting sectarian strife?'' Mr. Mutairi said.</p>
        <p>''Our priority is to drive the occupation from the country,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But there is an unacknowledged dependence by Mr. Sadr on the Americans themselves.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Sadr's aides criticized Prime Minister Nuri Kamal al-Maliki last week for refusing to set a timetable for American withdrawal, Mr. Sadr himself has not come forward with deadlines. (The Democrats in Congress have taken a stronger stand.)</p>
        <p>One leading Sadr legislator, Bahaa al-Aaraji, said the Americans should stay no longer than two more years. But like Mr. Mutairi, he insisted that the Iraqi security forces had to be well-trained before the Americans left.</p>
        <p>In other words, beneath all his fiery talk, Mr. Sadr seems to understand that the Shiite-dominated security forces -- which include many recruits from his militia -- still need training and equipment from the Americans to take on the relentless Sunni militants in the widening civil war. The horrific bombings in mostly Shiite areas of Baghdad on Thursday, which killed at least 171 people, underscored the fears of some Shiites that they are perhaps farther than ever from defeating the Sunni-led insurgency.</p>
        <p>That might help explain why Mr. Sadr, despite his chest-beating, has also pulled his punches on President Bush's new Baghdad security plan, and in the process has drawn some less-than-enthusiastic comments from members of his fractious militia.</p>
        <p>When President Bush said this winter that he was sending nearly 30,000 more troops to Iraq, Mr. Sadr said through his aides that he would comply with the plan. He ordered his militia to lie low. There has since been a drop in death squad killings, and American military commanders attribute some of it to Mr. Sadr's orders. Meanwhile, the Americans have continued to arrest militiamen and raid safehouses.</p>
        <p>Some Mahdi Army commanders are all too aware of the awkward situation.</p>
        <p>''Take for example something that happened in the Orfeli area of Sadr City,'' said Abu Tiba, who leads 30 to 40 men in the Sadr City slum. ''The Americans recently tried to arrest a Mahdi Army commander named Abu Ali. The Americans couldn't find the commander, so they arrested two civilians instead. We were very angry, but we didn't do anything because we have orders to be quiet, not to attack.''</p>
        <p>''We're never afraid,'' he said. ''We have all our weapons. We're ready, we're just awaiting orders.''</p>
        <p>The endless stream of Sunni-built car bombs, and the inability of the Americans to stop them, has also tested the patience of Sadr officials. ''It's on its way to failure,'' Mr. Mutairi said of the security plan.</p>
        <p>One of the biggest threats to the plan is the possibility that as the bombings continue, Shiite militiamen will step up their killings of Sunni Arabs, plunging the capital back into a cycle of sectarian revenge.</p>
        <p>Should that happen, it would expose once again another glaring contradiction in Mr. Sadr's policies -- his attempts to ally with anti-American Sunni Arabs even as his militiamen slaughter them.</p>
        <p>During the mass protest in Najaf on April 9, Sadr officials brought in a few conservative Sunni Arabs in a show of cross-sectarian unity. But the violence on the ground, especially in Baghdad, where Shiite militias have driven Sunni Arabs from entire neighborhoods, suggests that Mr. Sadr is just paying lip service to Sunni-Shiite harmony.</p>
        <p>Just as complicated is Mr. Sadr's relationship with Iran. Like many prominent Shiite leaders, Mr. Sadr has kept close ties to Iran, and the Americans have said he has been in hiding there during the current troop buildup. Yet, Mr. Sadr's main distinction from his greatest Shiite rival, Abdul-Aziz al-Hakim, the leader of the Supreme Council for the Islamic Revolution in Iraq, is that his father, a powerful cleric, stayed inside Iraq to oppose Saddam Hussein while Mr. Hakim's family fled to Iran and founded the Supreme Council there.</p>
        <p>Because of that, Mr. Sadr has a much greater popular base here than Mr. Hakim or any other Shiite politician. Mr. Sadr's rivalry with Mr. Hakim has been the greatest threat to Shiite unity. It has often exploded in violence, as it did in the clashes in Diwaniya this month, and is fueled by widely-held suspicions that Mr. Hakim is Iran's favorite among the various Shiite leaders.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mutairi said that an alliance with Iran had limited appeal for Mr. Sadr.</p>
        <p>''Speaking on a religious level, it's possible,'' he said. ''But the Sadrists are a nationalist movement. We reject the interference of any country. We don't want Iran's problems to be settled on our land.''</p>
        <p>A few minutes later, a suicide car bomb exploded on a crowded boulevard nearby, killing at least 13 people and rattling the windows in Mr. Mutairi's office.</p>
        <p>Someone was settling their problems in Mr. Sadr's backyard. Whoever it was, he, like everyone else, had issues with Mr. Sadr's vision for Iraq.</p>
        <p>THE WORLD: THE RIDDLE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
