<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Surge of Vitality In Downtown New Rochelle</title>
    <meta content="22topicweWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/22topicwe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842046"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="URBAN RENEWAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Rochelle (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Trump Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marszalek, Diana</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805EED61E3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="612" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Surge of Vitality In Downtown New Rochelle</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Surge of Vitality in Downtown New Rochelle</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANA MARSZALEK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marszalek, Diana</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on beginnings of revitalization of downtown New Rochelle, NY; five higher-end restaurants have opened and five others are planned, residential developments include Trump condominium tower and 140,000 square feet of retail space is scheduled to open in fall; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE recent opening of five higher-end restaurants in downtown New Rochelle, including a grill owned by the Yankees pitcher Mariano Rivera, is giving local leaders confidence that the city's long-range plan for revitalizing the area is starting to take shape.</p>
        <p>''The restaurant scene often is the real vanguard of urban renewal,'' Mayor Noam Bramson said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE recent opening of five higher-end restaurants in downtown New Rochelle, including a grill owned by the Yankees pitcher Mariano Rivera, is giving local leaders confidence that the city’s long-range plan for revitalizing the area is starting to take shape.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE recent opening of five higher-end restaurants in downtown New Rochelle, including a grill owned by the Yankees pitcher Mariano Rivera, is giving local leaders confidence that the city's long-range plan for revitalizing the area is starting to take shape.</p>
        <p>''The restaurant scene often is the real vanguard of urban renewal,'' Mayor Noam Bramson said.</p>
        <p>Five other restaurants are planned for downtown, and the growing number of such establishments comes during construction of several downtown residential developments, including a Trump condominium tower that will bring 185 units, priced at up to $1.6 million, and 140,000 square feet of retail space to the area. It is scheduled to open in the fall.</p>
        <p>That tower, a second apartment building, Avalon, with 588 units, scheduled to open this summer, and other downtown projects that are in the works will yield about 2,000 new residences. Some of the projects, most notably the mixed-use, one million-square-foot LeCount Square, will bring retail and office space to boot.</p>
        <p>Local leaders are hoping that the Trump and Avalon openings will spark a revival in a downtown that has been ailing for about 50 years.</p>
        <p>''We're optimistic that when the critical mass expands in the spring and fall, we'll begin to see a turn in retail,'' the city manager, Charles B. Strome III, said.</p>
        <p>In addition, the lure of the large developments is expected to pay off elsewhere in the city, in smaller-scale areas like the once vibrant Main Street, Mr. Strome said.</p>
        <p>Small-business owners downtown say that despite the threat of competition, they, too, are ready for change in an area that has been plagued for too long by vacant storefronts, an abundance of dollar stores and a bad rap stemming from bouts of club-related and other crime.</p>
        <p>''We need someone to come in here and bring the lady into town again, because that's who I need,'' said Robert Kaessinger, co-owner of the Curtain Shop. ''And they're not going to come here until we get new stores.''</p>
        <p>City officials say that while developments like the Trump space may lure big-name retailers, their goal is to improve business for small Main Street establishments -- many of which serve New Rochelle's ethnic population -- and not price them out of the market.</p>
        <p>''There is a place for 99-cent stores in New Rochelle, but we don't want a Main Street dominated by them,'' Mr. Bramson said.</p>
        <p>Though cabaret and nuisance laws have reduced club-related crime (in fact, the now defunct Palladium nightclub may be turned into a 20-story condominium building), some investors remain wary about downtown. That may have been exacerbated by a melee on April 8 at the New Roc City entertainment complex in which hundreds of youths, many from New York City, clashed with the police.</p>
        <p>Geoffrey Gold, a 43-year-old investment manager from Larchmont, said that while he might look to New Rochelle for office space in the future, there was still work to be done before he made that decision.</p>
        <p>''I'm increasingly impressed by the improvement in downtown New Rochelle,'' Mr. Gold said. ''Working there is a thought to explore more definitively in the future. But I'm unsure about the prospects at the moment.''</p>
        <p>That is not surprising to city officials, who say they are about halfway through what Mayor Bramson calls ''the most dramatic physical and economic transformation in New Rochelle's modern history.''</p>
        <p>The ultimate success, Mr. Bramson said, will be based on the city's tenet of managing growth wisely, considering everything from parking, traffic and wastewater management to preserving green space. He also stressed that preserving the suburban nature of New Rochelle outside the downtown, by limiting lot sizes and taking other measures, was also a goal.</p>
        <p>URBAN RENEWAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
