<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Good Luck Charm With Ideas of Its Own</title>
    <meta content="22POSS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/fashion/22POSS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842134"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="POSSESSED"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jewels and Jewelry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Englander, Nathan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E1DF163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="638" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Good Luck Charm With Ideas of Its Own</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Good Luck Charm With Ideas of Its Own</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID COLMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Colman, David</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE is writing, and there is rewriting. But is there a difference?</p>
        <p>In the last 10 years or so, fiction and memoir have gradually (and sometimes uneasily) blurred so thoroughly as to become a new genre. Surely an anthology of the form -- ''The Decade of Wishful Thinking'' -- is in the offing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The novelist Nathan Englander and the amulet that goes against everything he stands for intellectually.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE is writing, and there is rewriting. But is there a difference?</p>
        <p>In the last 10 years or so, fiction and memoir have gradually (and sometimes uneasily) blurred so thoroughly as to become a new genre. Surely an anthology of the form -- ''The Decade of Wishful Thinking'' -- is in the offing.</p>
        <p>Though many have tried, few have taken on this fictional genre as cleverly and thoughtfully as Nathan Englander, who is making his debut as a novelist this month with ''The Ministry of Special Cases'' (Knopf). The book, which details the dismal effects of trying to apply Liquid Paper to life, takes place in 1970s Argentina during the ''Dirty War,'' when suspect citizens were disappeared, identities erased and ethnic traditions blotted out.</p>
        <p>Yet in his own small way, Mr. Englander is waging his own dirty (or let's say smudgy) war with the vestiges of his Orthodox Jewish childhood on Long Island. ''I don't do anything with organized religion,'' said Mr. Englander, who is boyish at 37. ''I'm totally secular. I'd call myself an atheist if I wasn't so afraid of going to hell.''</p>
        <p>You can take the boy out of the orthodoxy, but you can't take orthodoxy out of the boy.</p>
        <p>So while Mr. Englander sees himself as an outsider, he is not free to wander off. Rather, it is as if he is locked in a kind of orbit around the Jewish self, pulled in by the gravity of the past but trying with his own centrifugal force to veer off on his own. The effect, whether you are talking to or reading him, is like some wryly observant moon, an eye-in-the-sky cross between Kafka and Shecky Greene.</p>
        <p>For example, his idea of getting away from his childhood was moving to Jerusalem for five years. There in 1999, just after the publication of ''For the Relief of Unbearable Urges,'' his book of short stories, he found an object that gave a bit of shine to his beliefs or, rather, to his lack of them.</p>
        <p>He was wandering nervously through Mea Shearim, perhaps the oldest and most strictly Orthodox section of the Jewish quarter (''You're always made to feel out of your element in that neighborhood,'' Mr. Englander said), when he came on an old man making traditional amulets.</p>
        <p>Intimidated yet charmed -- ''He wasn't making these things for tourists,'' he said -- he bought what he calls a general-purpose good-luck charm, made of what looks to be tin or zinc. It bears the image of a man etched with the sefirot, the 10 divine attributes, and the legend ''Ein Sof,'' the kabbalah term for the infinite substance of creation (or for God himself, depending on the context).</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Englander bought it almost defiantly as a souvenir, he is superstitious, and today the amulet, along with three ancient Jewish and Islamic charms for diverting the evil eye, is the only decoration in his bedroom.</p>
        <p>But ''under no circumstances,'' he stated unwaveringly (sort of), does the religiosity of the object appeal to him. Rather, it is the beautiful and humble humanity of it and of the man and shop whence it sprang.</p>
        <p>''I don't seek solace in it,'' he said. ''It's a really special find. I've never seen anything like it. They don't sell it at the Jerusalem candle store on Main Street.''</p>
        <p>But even if Mr. Englander has dedicated himself to the New Yorkers' religion of books, he cannot deny that the amulet has a strong pull. ''It goes against everything I stand for intellectually,'' he said.</p>
        <p>If only he could be positive. ''I am so desperate to live in a black and white world,'' he said. ''At the same time I am obsessed with the whole world being gray.''</p>
        <p>So, memento or pentimento? Perhaps so blurred together as to be a genre of its own.</p>
        <p>POSSESSED</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
