<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ADMISSIONS</title>
    <meta content="strategy22" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Education Life Supplement" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/education/strategy22.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842071"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="STRATEGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Admissions Standards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tuition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E5DF1F3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="702" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ADMISSIONS</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Admissions</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Samantha Stainburn</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stainburn, Samantha</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nowhere to go in the fall? Keep applying. Call it late decision.</p>
        <p>THE REALITY</p>
        <p>Bad application choices (oops, Barnard is not a safety school) can result in the unthinkable: nowhere to go to college in the fall, or nowhere you want to go. ''Every year we get reports from our school counselors of panicked students who have not gotten into the colleges of their choice,'' says David Hawkins, director of public policy for the National Association for College Admission Counseling. Other students come down with senioritis, and the college they planned to attend won't take them (see Page 16 for how this can happen). Still others need to rethink their options because their lives have changed: you can't go to school in California if a sick parent needs you in New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nowhere to go in the fall? Keep applying. Call it late decision.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nowhere to go in the fall? Keep applying. Call it late decision.</p>
        <p>THE REALITY</p>
        <p>Bad application choices (oops, Barnard is not a safety school) can result in the unthinkable: nowhere to go to college in the fall, or nowhere you want to go. ''Every year we get reports from our school counselors of panicked students who have not gotten into the colleges of their choice,'' says David Hawkins, director of public policy for the National Association for College Admission Counseling. Other students come down with senioritis, and the college they planned to attend won't take them (see Page 16 for how this can happen). Still others need to rethink their options because their lives have changed: you can't go to school in California if a sick parent needs you in New York.</p>
        <p>Luckily, colleges get rejected, too. Fewer admitted applicants than desirable may reserve places. Institutions also experience ''summer melt'': in June and July, students cancel for a host of reasons, including the shock of that first tuition bill.</p>
        <p>So colleges may be interested in applicants after May 1, the day most enrollment deposits are due.</p>
        <p>HOW TO</p>
        <p>Where do you find colleges with room late in the game? A good source is the annual Space Availability Survey on the admissions association Web site, www.nacacnet.org, as of May 7. Last year, 186 four-year colleges, including the University of Pittsburgh, Fordham and Mills College, reported slots. The list, dominated by private colleges accepting 50 to 85 percent of applicants, is updated until August.</p>
        <p>Not all colleges respond to the survey, so call the admissions office. Important: Your mom cannot make these calls. ''The student must take ownership over the situation,'' says Dennis Craig, vice president for admissions at Purchase College, part of the State University of New York. Colleges are wary of late applicants, he says; parental involvement ''gives us even less confidence.''</p>
        <p>When an admissions officer gives you the go-ahead, send everything regular applicants submit plus a statement explaining how you ended up in your predicament. Expect to hear in a matter of days to a few weeks.</p>
        <p>CAVEATS</p>
        <p>While most colleges with space also have financial aid and housing available, they have less of it. Students who slide into college in July may find that the courses they had wanted to take are filled.</p>
        <p>But the biggest danger of applying at the last minute is the TKTS phenomenon, experienced by those queuing up for cut-rate theater tickets at the last minute: you will probably get a seat if you stand in line long enough, but you may not like the show.</p>
        <p>If the best you can find is a college you think you can stomach for just one year -- or if you're still looking because of lackluster academics -- consider a community college, where you can more cheaply earn academic credits that will transfer to a four-year college. Or take a year off to work, travel or do community service. Admissions officers like students who have had such experiences, says Carlton Surbeck, director of admissions at Goucher College, in Baltimore. ''Their focus is good, and they assimilate beautifully when they come to college.''</p>
        <p>SUCCESS RATE</p>
        <p>If your academic qualifications exceed those of students on a wait list, the college will admit you first. ''While I hope to get a sense of whether there will be a good match between the student and the institution, the platform is all academic,'' Mr. Surbeck says. Special talents or the ability to pay your own way might help normally, but they matter less for late applicants.</p>
        <p>''At that point, the composition of the class is pretty much developed,'' he says. ''There are already some great singers and volleyball players, and we've probably generated the revenue we need out of tuition.''</p>
        <p>Colleges may accept late applications even though they are full, as extra insurance against summer melt. But statistically, it's more difficult to get in late than if you had applied during the regular season. For example, last year, about 70 applicants vied for admission to Goucher after May 1. The college typically admits 67 percent of students who apply on time, but only 30 percent of late applicants.</p>
        <p>STRATEGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
