<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Designs From Japanese Life, Detailed With Vigor</title>
    <meta content="22artsweWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/22artswe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842041"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Vassar College</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Genocchio, Benjamin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chikanobu (1838-1912)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Vassar College</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904EFD61E3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="679" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Designs From Japanese Life, Detailed With Vigor</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Designs From Japanese Life, Detailed With Vigor</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BENJAMIN GENOCCHIO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genocchio, Benjamin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Benjamin Genocchio reviews retrospective of woodcut prints by Japanese artist Chikanobu at Vassar College; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the more splendid offerings in Hudson River Valley museums this spring is ''Chikanobu: Modernity and Nostalgia in Japanese Prints,'' a robust survey of the work of a once popular but now largely forgotten Japanese printmaker from the Meiji period. It is the kind of exhibition where even if you don't know anything about Japan or Japanese printmaking you can still bliss out on the designs.</p>
        <p>The Meiji period (1868-1912) was a time of great change in Japan. The emperor was reinstated as ruler and society underwent rapid westernization. These changes are reflected throughout this impressive collection of some 60 works, touring to Vassar College from Scripps College in Claremont, Calif. It is also, from what I can gather, the first retrospective of Chikanobu's work in the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Frances Lehman Loeb Art Center at Vassar College is showing a robust survey of the work of a once popular but now largely forgotten Japanese printmaker from the Meiji period.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of the more splendid offerings in Hudson River Valley museums this spring is ''Chikanobu: Modernity and Nostalgia in Japanese Prints,'' a robust survey of the work of a once popular but now largely forgotten Japanese printmaker from the Meiji period. It is the kind of exhibition where even if you don't know anything about Japan or Japanese printmaking you can still bliss out on the designs.</p>
        <p>The Meiji period (1868-1912) was a time of great change in Japan. The emperor was reinstated as ruler and society underwent rapid westernization. These changes are reflected throughout this impressive collection of some 60 works, touring to Vassar College from Scripps College in Claremont, Calif. It is also, from what I can gather, the first retrospective of Chikanobu's work in the United States.</p>
        <p>Popular printmaking in Japan is closely associated with the ukiyo-e tradition, color woodblock prints mass-produced in the 18th and 19th centuries reflecting the enthusiasms of the common people. By the end of the 19th century the movement had gone into a decline, largely because of lower standards of workmanship and repetitiveness. Chikanobu (1838-1912) sought to reinvigorate the tradition.</p>
        <p>Chikanobu's prints owe much to the traditions of Japanese popular woodblock printing, in particular the use of flat planes and decorative patterning, along with a conventional choice of subjects -- actors, courtesans, famous sites and beautiful women. But he also branched out, his prints reflecting Western art conventions and also picturing current events, like Saigo's Rebellion in 1877 by the traditionalist samurai warriors against the Meiji government.</p>
        <p>The show's opening room contains several prints reflecting the growing westernization of Japanese society during the Meiji period. Figures are routinely depicted in Western dress, while in one of the larger, more elaborate prints here, ''Great Horses at Ueno Park's Shinobazu Pond Illustrated'' (1884), we see the Japanese emperor and others enjoying the spectacle of an Ascot-like horse race.</p>
        <p>Concentrated chemical dyes for printing on paper came into use in Japan during the Meiji period, along with many other forms of Western influence. This gives Chikanobu's prints eyeball-burning intensity, a powerfully intense and saturated look, in contrast to the flatter, more subtle matte finish of traditional ukiyo-e prints.</p>
        <p>The process of making woodblock prints is complex, and is usually collaborative. The artist's original outline drawing is cut by a specialized engraver on a block of wood from which a printer makes several outline proofs. The artist then paints parts of each proof with a single color from which new blocks (one for each color) are cut and then used one at a time for printing up the image.</p>
        <p>While Chikanobu's printer was in charge of applying the colors to the blocks in the proper tones -- a complicated task requiring years of experience -- the superb designs by Chikanobu are what give the prints their vigor. His drawing is beyond reproach, while the prints themselves have an energy and freshness that is immediately engaging -- a result of the artist's bold willingness to treat his themes with originality and flair.</p>
        <p>Chikanobu's innovations are best conveyed in a series of imaginative prints from the late 1890s depicting life in and around the Shogun's palace in Edo (Tokyo) before the Meiji restoration. These prints, in the middle room of the exhibition, often contrast a focused, detailed foreground scene of figures with more subtle, vaguely defined spatial areas in the background as to suggest a dreamy past. An example is ''Chiyoda Outer Palace: Sanno Festival'' (1897), in which a castle and figures loom almost dreamily in the background.</p>
        <p>Later in life Chikanobu returned to more conventional subjects, reviving themes of warriors and portraits of beautiful women. He also produced scenes based on Kabuki plays. Perhaps his more experimental prints didn't sell, or perhaps he tired of innovation. We don't know, for like much else in the life and career of this talented printmaker, information is only now beginning to come to light.</p>
        <p>''Chikanobu: Modernity and Nostalgia in Japanese Prints,'' Frances Lehman Loeb Art Center, Vassar College, 124 Raymond Avenue, Poughkeepsie, through May 13. (845) 437-5632 or www.fllac.vassar.edu.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
