<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Affordable Europe: Vienna</title>
    <meta content="22viennaweb" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/travel/22viennaweb.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842340"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Vienna (Austria)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Austria/Vienna</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Vienna (Austria)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E0D61631F931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="561" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Affordable Europe: Vienna</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Affordable Europe: Vienna</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH WILDMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the inner ring -- the First District -- of this Hapsburgian city, prices can feel frustratingly high. The key to low-cost Vienna is to step beyond the tourist paths of the pedestrian Graben and venture into the neighborhoods where the Viennese actually live.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay for Under 125 Euros</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The key to low-cost Vienna is to step beyond the tourist paths of the pedestrian Graben and venture into the neighborhoods where the Viennese actually live.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the inner ring -- the First District -- of this Hapsburgian city, prices can feel frustratingly high. The key to low-cost Vienna is to step beyond the tourist paths of the pedestrian Graben and venture into the neighborhoods where the Viennese actually live.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay for Under 125 Euros</p>
        <p>Along with its woeful omission from the rosters of low-cost airline destinations, Vienna lags far behind the rest of Europe in opening inexpensive hotels -- but in the Second and Seventh Districts you'll find recent entries that have brought design to the city. At the Falkensteiner Hotel am Schottenfeld (Schottenfeldgasse 74; 43-1-526-5181; www.falkensteiner.com), breakfast, free Wi-Fi access in the lobby, and a small fitness center are bundled with rooms closer to current European design standards (111 euros, or $148 at $1.36 to the euro) than many in the city. At the recently renovated Mercure Imlauer Nestroy (Rotensterngasse 12; 43-1-211-400; www.mercure.com), near the Augarten in the Second District, a 15-minute walk from Stephansplatz, doubles can be found for as low as 99 euros, with Wi-Fi.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat  Schleifmühlgasse, a small side street in the increasingly cool Fourth District, has several great spots for hearty inexpensive fare. At tiny Acht Ein Halb (Schleifmühlgasse 20; 43-1-585-6323) fresh pastas and risottos are a bargain at 8 euros, joined by restaurant-made desserts (under 5 euros) and a well-edited wine list. At the nearby cozyBreakfast Club (Schleifmühlgasse 12-14; 43-581-2692; www.thebreakfastclub.at), frühstück, or breakfast, is served all day. With American-style portions, this means brunch: two eggs sunny side up, served with grilled zucchini, bread and jam, and coffee are only 4.90 euros, and imaginative omelets and waffles with Nutella hardly ever break the 6-euro mark. Everything is fresh, organic and fair trade. The cheapest food of all, of course, is street food. For everything from light bites to hearty breakfasts, the Naschmarkt is your best bet. Asian stalls sell take-out stir fry and at Cafe Deli (Naschmarkt Stand 421-436; 43-1-585-0823), Turkish-influenced breakfasts draw a jumble of young Viennese every Saturday.</p>
        <p>Where to Shop  Vienna's least expensive and most bizarre knickknacks can be found in the Naschmarkt (it's just outside the Kettenbrückengasse metro stop) every Saturday morning where a hundred or so weathered characters sell everything from forlorn damaged Torah scroll covers to porcelain dolls and postcards from soldiers serving in the World Wars. One of the best stalls is the Button Lady, a cubicle filled with a boggling display of antique buttons, many sold in original packs of four or six or eight for the equivalent of just a few dollars a piece. At Combinat(Museumsplatz 1, Burgasse exit: 43 -6991-2008920; www.combinat.at) young designer lines like the Austrian Pitour, created by Maria Oberfrank (a Helmut Lang veteran), the Hungarian design group Artista, and the German Claudia Güdel's collection for men present limited-clothing collections that won't overwhelm wallets.</p>
        <p>Best Money-Saving Tip  This city of music is satisfyingly accessible: tickets to the opera (www.wiener-staatsoper.at) are available online beginning one month before performance day (book early, as many seats belong to season ticket holders); the least expensive are day-of standing-room tickets (3.50 euros) for opera fans patient enough to get there early and wait in line. Classical concerts at the Musikverein(where conductors like Daniel Barenboim drop in to conduct) are available for as little as 4 euros, with tickets available online (www.musikverein.at).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
