<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Search for Yield Leads Some Back to Bonds</title>
    <meta content="22bond" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/business/yourmoney/22bond.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070429T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842192"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SUNDAY MONEY: INVESTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE3DC163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1255" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Search for Yield Leads Some Back to Bonds</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Search for Yield Leads Some Back to Bonds</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. HERSHEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hershey, Robert D Jr</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR generations, turmoil in the stock market has driven investors to bonds. Not only are bonds less subject to price gyrations, but they also provide more income as you sit out the equity storm. Particularly in foul weather, some bonds belong in virtually every portfolio, many financial advisers say.</p>
        <p>''I believe that's an absolutely essential thing to do,'' said John C. Bogle, founder of the Vanguard Group and now a securities researcher and author. ''Your bond position should equal your age -- or maybe your age minus 10 years. So if you're 70, you should have 60 percent bonds.'' Mr. Bogle, who advocates a low-risk approach to investing, clearly favors low-cost mutual funds as a sensible way to hold a diverse portfolio containing both stocks and bonds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stock buyers appear to be searching for havens that focus on dividend income and those that have portfolios of bonds as well as stocks, an analyst said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR generations, turmoil in the stock market has driven investors to bonds. Not only are bonds less subject to price gyrations, but they also provide more income as you sit out the equity storm. Particularly in foul weather, some bonds belong in virtually every portfolio, many financial advisers say.</p>
        <p>''I believe that's an absolutely essential thing to do,'' said John C. Bogle, founder of the Vanguard Group and now a securities researcher and author. ''Your bond position should equal your age -- or maybe your age minus 10 years. So if you're 70, you should have 60 percent bonds.'' Mr. Bogle, who advocates a low-risk approach to investing, clearly favors low-cost mutual funds as a sensible way to hold a diverse portfolio containing both stocks and bonds.</p>
        <p>Although there was a brief stampede into Treasury securities -- and out of riskier bonds -- after stocks dived in late February, there was no mass migration into bonds. ''Typically, investors aren't going to rush into bonds unless there is a fairly broad agreement'' that stocks have entered a bear market, said Jeff Tjornehoj, a senior research analyst at Lipper.</p>
        <p>Other specialists say that whether bonds benefit when stocks slump depends on circumstance. When stocks hit a bottom in early 2003, the Federal Reserve smiled on bond investors by aggressively cutting interest rates to spur a sluggish economy.</p>
        <p>With stocks now recovering from their February drop -- the Dow Jones industrial average reached a record high last week -- and with inflation a greater concern than an economic slump, the Fed seems unlikely to cut rates anytime soon.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Tjornehoj added that many stock buyers did appear to be ''putting on the risk brakes'' and searching for havens like mutual funds that focus on dividend income and those that have portfolios of bonds as well as stocks. During March, investors pulled $1.4 billion from funds investing in emerging-market equities, a high-risk category.</p>
        <p>One reflection of investors' appetite for yield was the record-setting $5.5 billion raised in the February start-up of a closed-end fund, Eaton Vance Tax-Managed Global Diversified Equity Income.</p>
        <p>Scott Berry, bond fund analyst at Morningstar, says that while he has detected no major shift in assets recently, several months of outflows from some funds investing in Treasury securities ''came to a grinding halt once the stock market slipped.'' Perhaps the stock market's volatility was ''keeping people in bonds who may have thought of switching to stocks,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Oddly, polar opposites in quality -- long-term government bonds, mainly gilt-edged Treasuries, and high-yield, or junk, corporates were the best-performing categories in January and February. But while junk has remained at the top of the taxable fixed-income heap, with a 3.5 percent advance through Wednesday, Treasuries faded in March. This year through Thursday, short-term Treasuries gained 1.5 percent, while long-term Treasuries were last among taxable bond sectors, with a gain of 1.24 percent, according to Morningstar.</p>
        <p>''Typically, if you see a flight to quality, money is coming out of junk,'' Mr. Berry said. ''But that hasn't been the case. The default numbers are staying low and demand stays high. Until we see some defaults, to show that there's more risk there, returns will probably hold up pretty well.''</p>
        <p>Still, there has been some widening of spreads, the yield difference among bonds of different quality. Junk bonds were returning 2.7 percentage points more than the 10-year Treasury bond days before the Dow Jones industrial average plummeted 416 points on Feb. 27; the spread is now more than 3 points.</p>
        <p>Some bond funds have suffered a bit from the turmoil in the mortgage market. For example, the $1.6 billion Fidelity Mortgage Securities fund has slipped to the ''back of the pack,'' Mr. Berry said, because of some lower-quality holdings -- but there are no funds focused mainly on subprime loans and thus exposed to a major level of defaults. This year through Thursday, Fidelity Mortgage Securities had a return of 1.2 percent. Funds investing in Government National Mortgage Association, or Ginnie Mae, bonds or other federal agency securities carry virtually no credit risk because these bonds have implicit federal backing, Mr. Berry said, and have remained almost entirely unscathed.</p>
        <p>Investors considering new commitments to bonds may well look to high-quality municipals, specialists say.</p>
        <p>''Yields are very attractive compared to taxable bonds,'' observed Robert MacIntosh, co-director of municipal investments at Eaton Vance, with investors in municipal bonds getting fatter returns from longer maturities.</p>
        <p>In other words, the yield curve for these bonds slopes upward, unlike the partially inverted situation in Treasury bonds, which offers little incentive to commit for longer periods. Indeed, the municipal curve has never inverted. That is because enormous demand from money market funds for the shortest of tax-exempt maturities keeps those rates relatively low. At the same time, rates are reliably higher for longer-term maturities, with banks, insurance companies and mutual funds each tending to focus their buying on separate segments of the maturity spectrum. Individuals buy in all market segments, usually holding their bonds to maturity.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tjornehoj was upbeat about the prospects for municipal bonds. ''I think they're going to put up, through the rest of this year, numbers that are very respectable compared to their corporate and government peers,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. MacIntosh of Eaton Vance agreed, though he cautioned that there was not much yield benefit these days from buying bonds of lesser quality. The political winds also seem to favor municipals. While no one is predicting imminent action, municipals could benefit if the Democrats seemed likely to win the White House as well as Congress next year, and if current chatter about reversing the Bush administration's tax cuts became a policy priority. Higher income taxes would make tax-free bonds more desirable.</p>
        <p>Also subject to changes in tax law is the fate of many relatively new bond funds that are meant to be free of the alternative minimum tax.</p>
        <p>Investors may also want to see whether the Supreme Court accepts a case brought by a Kentucky couple challenging the practice by states of exempting their own bonds while taxing those of other states. If all municipal bonds were treated the same, the myriad of state-specific bond funds would become obsolete.</p>
        <p>As for bonds of emerging markets, which have been outstanding performers in recent years, most now seem fairly expensive despite a widening of spreads, specialists say.</p>
        <p>''Is it time to say it's as good as it's going to get?'' Mr. Tjornehoj wondered. ''I think that emerging-market debt is probably going to be rather volatile this year.''</p>
        <p>If you're considering closed-end bond funds, many of which are trading at a discount to portfolio value, keep in mind that these are generally leveraged with borrowings and could be particularly hurt if inflation worries prompted the Fed to resume raising short-term interest rates.</p>
        <p>But if the Fed lowered rates instead, closed-end funds would benefit from their lower-cost borrowings, Mr. MacIntosh said.</p>
        <p>WHETHER or not the stock market is swooning, Mr. Bogle said, bonds are worth holding. He contended, though, that most bond funds are too expensive -- from both sales charges and annual expenses -- and that bond exchange-traded funds, which are priced throughout the day, encourage speculative behavior that undermines long-term performance.</p>
        <p>''The point is not that bonds are a good bet to do better than stocks,'' Mr. Bogle said, though they do outperform them in perhaps a quarter of 10-year periods. ''But they give you some protection, an anchor to windward, that makes you less apt to make foolish moves when we get a big stock-market decline.''</p>
        <p>SUNDAY MONEY: INVESTING</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 29, 2007, Sunday  An article last Sunday about investing in bonds referred imprecisely to the Federal Reserve's cutting of interest rates early in this decade. The Fed began cutting rates in early 2001 and finished in mid-2003; it did not start the cuts in early 2003.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 29, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about investing in bonds referred imprecisely to the Federal Reserve's cutting of interest rates early in this decade. The Fed began cutting rates in early 2001 and finished in mid-2003; it did not start the cuts in early 2003.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
