<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Opening a Courthouse, Overdue and Over Budget</title>
    <meta content="22courthouse" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/22courthouse.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842256"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Bronx (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E6D7163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1010" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Opening a Courthouse, Overdue and Over Budget</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Opening a Courthouse, Overdue and Over Budget</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY WILLIAMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Williams, Timothy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani and other officials dug ceremonial shovels into the ground in the summer of 2001 to mark the start of construction of a new Bronx courthouse, the building was projected to be finished in less than four years and to cost $325 million.</p>
        <p>Almost six years and $400 million later, the state's largest courthouse, the Bronx County Hall of Justice, is scheduled to open next month featuring the latest technology and sleek architecture.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After six years and $400 million, the state’s largest courthouse is scheduled to open next month in the Bronx.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani and other officials dug ceremonial shovels into the ground in the summer of 2001 to mark the start of construction of a new Bronx courthouse, the building was projected to be finished in less than four years and to cost $325 million.</p>
        <p>Almost six years and $400 million later, the state's largest courthouse, the Bronx County Hall of Justice, is scheduled to open next month featuring the latest technology and sleek architecture.</p>
        <p>Among the highlights of the building are a translucent glass and aluminum facade that has been certified bomb-proof, courtrooms equipped with video monitors to allow defendants to watch their trials from jail cells if necessary, and a design that allows sunlight to reach every courtroom.</p>
        <p>But the building, which stretches for two city blocks along 161st Street, remains incomplete and is mired in controversy. Its 200-space underground garage has been declared unsafe after inspectors discovered its ceiling had bowed. G. Oliver Koppell, a councilman from the Bronx, has called for an investigation of the entire project.</p>
        <p>''The thing is way over budget and there are many construction defects,'' Mr. Koppell said. ''There absolutely has to be an inquiry.''</p>
        <p>But the agencies most heavily involved in managing the construction, the state's Dormitory Authority and the state's Office of Court Administration, say the delays and cost overruns have been unavoidable, given the ambitious scope of the project.</p>
        <p>Ronald Younkins, chief of operations for the Office of Court Administration, said that not long after the August 2001 groundbreaking ceremony, the project's low bidder was disqualified because of suspected mob ties.</p>
        <p>Later, soil at the site was found to have been contaminated with petroleum.</p>
        <p>Bad weather and other problems also caused some delays.</p>
        <p>''On many public projects, there often are problems and delays, and on this one, we had a couple right from the get-go,'' Mr. Younkins said.</p>
        <p>Paul Burgdorf, a spokesman for the Dormitory Authority, which provides financing and construction services to various state institutions, said the problem with the building's garage appears to be the result of a contractor's mistake, rather than a design flaw.</p>
        <p>While the courthouse is scheduled to open during the last week of May, the garage's ceiling needs major repair work, officials said, which will further add to the project's cost.</p>
        <p>The hall of justice, which is located in a section of the South Bronx dominated by courthouses, is meant to help relieve overcrowding caused by an increase in the number of civil and criminal cases in the city.</p>
        <p>For the past two decades, the Bronx County Courthouse, at 161st Street and the Grand Concourse, and the Bronx Family/Criminal Courthouse, a few blocks east on 161st Street, have each held the borough's criminal cases once the criminal courthouse ran out of room.</p>
        <p>Space remained tight even after some of the Bronx borough president's offices and most of the Bronx district attorney's offices moved out of the county courthouse during the past decade, and a building to house the Bronx Housing Court opened on the Grand Concourse in 1997.</p>
        <p>As a result, some courtrooms in the older buildings were divided to make two. Offices were also turned into courtrooms. Now, the Bronx County Courthouse, which had 28 courtrooms when it was built in 1933, has 63, which is still not enough.</p>
        <p>Once the new hall of justice opens, courtrooms in the two older courthouses will be refurbished, and many of the rooms will be returned to their original size, officials said.</p>
        <p>''This is going to give us a chance to decompress and make sure each room is suitable for a court -- and not in somebody's former office,'' Mr. Younkins said.</p>
        <p>With its green tinted glass and aluminum front, the new courthouse dominates a streetscape of concrete and mortar structures that house government offices a few blocks from Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>It is nine stories tall with two underground levels in addition to the garage, has 47 large courtrooms and a total of about 800,000 square feet, making it one of the largest courthouses in the United States.</p>
        <p>An earlier design for the hall of justice called for a 30-story skyscraper with a day care center and retail shops at ground level and a street running through the complex. After the 1995 bombing of the Alfred P. Murrah Federal Building in Oklahoma City, however, designers essentially started from scratch.</p>
        <p>Fred Wilmers, project director for Rafael Viñoly Architects, which designed the building, said the firm had sought to build a structure that was welcoming rather than intimidating.</p>
        <p>''These buildings have traditionally been like fortresses,'' Mr. Wilmers said. ''We look to change that perception. The transparency is sort of figurative, but there is some in the literal sense as well.''</p>
        <p>The building's glass wall, which subtly changes color as it rises from street level in two different patterns, has been described as resembling a stretched-out accordion.</p>
        <p>At street level, the windows are opaque for privacy and security; they become clearer at the top.</p>
        <p>The glass was tested at a blast simulator at the White Sands Missile Range in New Mexico to ensure it could absorb the shock waves of a bomb blast.</p>
        <p>Each window is laminated and held together by a plastic inner layer that was then glued into the frame with silicone so that the glass will not shatter or fly out.</p>
        <p>Throughout the building, security was made a priority. A street designed to run through the complex has been converted into a pedestrian walkway.</p>
        <p>The windows in the building's lobbies and in the judges' chambers are bullet-resistant, and the loading dock, mail room and public plaza have all been built with bomb-resistant material.</p>
        <p>Because of security concerns, it is unclear whether a rooftop rock garden will ever be open to the public.</p>
        <p>Eight courtrooms have flat-screen video monitors and video systems to enable witnesses to testify from remote locations, allow inmates to watch from the building's holding cells, or give inmates the possibility of making their preliminary trial appearances from Rikers Island instead of having to be bused to the courthouse.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
