<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Affordable Europe: Paris</title>
    <meta content="22parisweb" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/travel/22parisweb.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842336"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Paris (France)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Paris (France)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE1D61631F931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1028" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Affordable Europe: Paris</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Affordable Europe: Paris</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELAINE SCIOLINO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The euro is so high these days that it has even become an issue in the presidential campaign in France: Nicolas Sarkozy, the conservative candidate for president, has vowed to lobby to lower its value against the dollar if he wins the election in May. But until that happens, creative thinking is in order for visitors on a budget.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay for Under 125 Euros</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The euro is so high these days that it has even become an issue in the presidential campaign in France. For visitors on a budget, this means creative thinking is in order.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The euro is so high these days that it has even become an issue in the presidential campaign in France: Nicolas Sarkozy, the conservative candidate for president, has vowed to lobby to lower its value against the dollar if he wins the election in May. But until that happens, creative thinking is in order for visitors on a budget.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay for Under 125 Euros</p>
        <p>Buying and renovating small apartments for investment became a cottage industry in Paris long ago. There is a flood of apartments to rent, which keeps the market competitive (an average of 100 to 170 euros a night, or about $135 to $230 at $1.36 to the euro). Apartments can be viewed online and usually rent for a week or more, with cleaning service included depending on the length of the stay. I know a couple who rent a sun-filled, two-bedroom, fifth-floor apartment in the Marais decorated with Indian paintings, Italian prints and Persian kilims for about 1,200 euros a week (agent fee included).</p>
        <p>Among the agencies that offer rental apartments: Rental France (the owner is Pascal Zytomirski, 33-6-14-65-09-33; www.rentalfrance.com), RothRay (Ray Lampard and Mono Roth, 33-1-48-87-13-37; www.rothray.com) and Paris Address (Xavier Fouquerand, 33-1-43-20-91-57; www.parisaddress.com).</p>
        <p>If you want a residence hotel with apartment living but hotel service, try the Hotel Residence Henri IV at 50, rue des Bernardins near the Panthéon and the Sorbonne in the Fifth Arrondissement (33-1-44-41-31-81, www.residencehenry4.com). All rooms accommodate two to four guests and have marble mantels, molded ceilings and kitchenettes that can be hidden away during the day.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat  If you're down, out, hungry and adventurous, tryLe Taïs Restaurant/Bar at 129, boulevard de Ménilmontant in the 11th Arrondissement on a Friday or Saturday evening. A plate of Algerian couscous made with vegetables and lamb comes with a beer or a glass of wine (2.50 to 5 euros). The best thing about Le Taïs is not the food but the crowd: chic young Parisians, artists, Arab-Parisians. Arrive early. The place fills up by 8:30. Then head down Rue Oberkampf, which is dotted with bars that have live music.</p>
        <p>For a memorable, traditional bistro meal, try Le Clou, (132, rue Cardinet, 33-1-42-27-36-78; www.restaurant-leclou.fr), in the 17th Arrondissement. At 32 euros for a three-course meal, it is not cheap. But it is one-star cooking at no-star prices. Specializing in seasonal dishes from the Poitou-Charentes region in central-west France (where the Socialist presidential candidate Ségolène Royal is regional president), Le Clou might offer a home-made foie gras or blood sausage to start, followed by grilled tuna with ratatouille or a rack of veal in a ginger and lemon balm sauce and its signature frozen nougat.</p>
        <p>Where to Shop  For one-stop shoppers who need to bring home a lot of useful gifts that say ''Paris,'' head to one of the city's five La Vaissellerieporcelain and crystal shops. The Web site, www.lavaissellerie.fr, gives an idea what is offered -- from plastic trays with Paris scenes to terrines for making foie gras. The best bargains fill bins outside. I especially like the jewel-colored, pleated breakfast bowls and the colored bistro glasses for 1.50 euros. A cousin recently bought 12 white Limoges dinner plates, salad plates and soup bowls for half what they would cost in New York. The service is warm; the gift-wrapping is included.</p>
        <p>Worried about breakage on the trip back home? Wrap your purchases in 1.50-euro bistro-style cotton dishtowels and napkins from Toto. There are several locations, including 7, place de la Madeleine in the Eighth Arrondissement and 34, rue St.-Placide in the Sixth.</p>
        <p>Paris is loaded with consignment clothing shops for women. My favorite is the Chercheminippes designer shop (111, rue du Cherche Midi; 33-42-22-53-76), where it is not impossible to find an Armani jacket and pants for 150 euros. If there's nothing that day, try its home furnishings consignment shop next door (with an odd number of cordial glasses, for example, for 1 euro each). Down the street at No. 102 is its ready-to-wear shop, which offers designers like Kenzo and Agnès b. Its shops for men and children are less interesting.</p>
        <p>At Les Dépôts Rive Gauche boutiqueat nearby 62, rue Vaneau in the Seventh Arrondissement, you'll find the delightful owner, Olga Boughanmi. Second-hand Hermès scarves run 95 to 125 euros depending on their condition. (A new Hermès scarf at the duty-free shop in the Paris airport costs 224 euros.)</p>
        <p>Best Money-Saving Tip  There are so many things to do free in Paris that an entire book in French has been written on the subject: ''Paris-0-Euro.'' For music lovers, check the churches. The Val de Grâce church in the Fifth Arrondissement, for example, offers a free classical music and organ concert at 7 p.m. on the first Saturday of each month; the Madeleine Church in the Eighth Arrondissement offers free organ and choral concerts two or three Sundays a month at 4 p.m.</p>
        <p>For the last 10 years, a group of hard-core dancers have gathered on the Seine every evening from mid-May through September. They do the tango, salsa and rock-swing. Free lessons start at 7:30 p.m. (a hat for tips is passed), followed by dancing until midnight. It all happens at Square Tino Rossi at 9, quai St.-Bernard in front of the University of Paris at Jussieu just a few steps from the Cathedral of Notre-Dame (''Paris Danses en Seine,'' tangoargentin-eric.site.voila.fr/page3.html).</p>
        <p>The iconic restaurant Taillevent has one of the best wine cellars in the world, and every Saturday from 10 a.m. to 6:30 p.m. it offers a free tasting. Visit the www.taillevent.com and click on ''Les Caves Taillevent,'' then ''Nos Prestations'' and then ''Les Dégustations'' for information (in French only) on the schedule and theme of the tasting.</p>
        <p>As for museums, forget the big expensive national ones like the Louvre and visit the free permanent collections of the city-run ones, including the Petit Palais, the Musée Carnavalet and the Cognacq-Jay. The small ones, too, like the homes of Victor Hugo and Honoré de Balzac, are also free.</p>
        <p>If you're in a romantic mood, pick up a copy of the paperback ''The Best Places to Kiss in Paris.'' A user-friendly guide.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
