<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Just About Letter Perfect</title>
    <meta content="22dinenjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/22dinenj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842087"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/AUDUBON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Alphabet Soup (Audubon,  NJ, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cook, Karla</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04EEDB1F3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="822" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Just About Letter Perfect</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Just About Letter Perfect</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KARLA COOK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cook, Karla</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Karla Cook reviews Alphabet Soup restaurant in Audubon, NJ; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHIMSY is nice in a name, and in a restaurant's décor, but whimsy on the plate can be even better. When accompanied by flawless execution, it moves a restaurant into a higher realm, as it does at Alphabet Soup, an upscale addition to the edible landscape in south-central New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Jayson Grossberg, 34, the chef and co-owner with his wife, Alix, 33, found cooking after he was prevented by illness from pursuing his first love, drumming. As he tells it, a friend of a friend knew someone in the kitchen of the legendary French chef Jean-Louis Palladin at his restaurant in Washington. Mr. Grossberg signed on in 1992, at the age of 19, to work for no pay. ''I can still smell that kitchen,'' he said longingly. He studied at the Culinary Institute of America, then worked at Mesa Grill and Bolo in Manhattan, among other places.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At Alphabet Soup in Audubon, whimsy and flawless execution move the restaurant into a higher realm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHIMSY is nice in a name, and in a restaurant's décor, but whimsy on the plate can be even better. When accompanied by flawless execution, it moves a restaurant into a higher realm, as it does at Alphabet Soup, an upscale addition to the edible landscape in south-central New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Jayson Grossberg, 34, the chef and co-owner with his wife, Alix, 33, found cooking after he was prevented by illness from pursuing his first love, drumming. As he tells it, a friend of a friend knew someone in the kitchen of the legendary French chef Jean-Louis Palladin at his restaurant in Washington. Mr. Grossberg signed on in 1992, at the age of 19, to work for no pay. ''I can still smell that kitchen,'' he said longingly. He studied at the Culinary Institute of America, then worked at Mesa Grill and Bolo in Manhattan, among other places.</p>
        <p>Mr. Grossberg went into catering, seeking more control over his schedule and pace; he and Alix were looking for space for that business when they happened upon the site of Alphabet Soup. They opened the 50-seat restaurant in May 2006.</p>
        <p>The menu lists three courses and 16 items. We tamped our hunger with rolls that had a nice crumb and a slightly sassy flavor; they were served hot, with softened butter garnished with sea salt.</p>
        <p>Acorn squash soup, with its touch of chive and its truffle-sweet potato ravioli (since replaced with a diver scallop and frizzle of smoked bacon) won over even a skeptic. Diver scallops, in combination with brussels sprouts and grapes and flavored by saffron, were delicately prepared, artistically presented and so delicious that it was hard to share them. Foie gras was similarly luscious, with its pairing of raw and cooked apple. The duck confit was the best I've had. Risotto, too, was masterful, its bits of tomato sweetened by mascarpone and shrimp.</p>
        <p>Main dishes posed difficult choices: venison, strip steak, salmon, bass (on one night), cod (on another night), lamb or veal? And the components: huckleberries, trumpet mushrooms, cranberry, lime, barley, black grapes, lemon-soy.</p>
        <p>Though there is one salad (winter lettuces with avocado, bacon and pistachio), there's no plant-based main dish; Mr. Grossberg says the menu is tightly focused because he has a small kitchen, he wants every dish to reach its potential, and these are the dishes that sell best.</p>
        <p>They didn't disappoint. Flavors were vivid and balanced. Sauces linked the parts to the whole beautifully. Meats and seafoods were impeccably cooked, though portions edged toward retro-size.</p>
        <p>Roasted venison approached alchemy with maple-sweet potato purée, mushrooms, the occasional huckleberry, spinach, baby carrots and candied pecans. The seared and slow-roasted strip steak, at $38 the high mark on the menu, was luscious, but after a few bites of beef, I was ready for the trumpet mushrooms and spinach served alongside, and would have liked more of them. Roasted veal rose to a new level with its pickled beets, black grapes and wild mushrooms, all joined with lemon-thyme jus.</p>
        <p>Three fish dishes -- salmon, bass and cod -- were outstanding as well. The salmon, sautéed to a crunch outside in a blend of olive oil and duck fat, then slow-roasted to melting inside, echoed the restaurant's color scheme with beautifully arranged cranberries, carrots and marinated confit of endive. Bass and cod were lighter but no less luscious, with accoutrements of cucumber and avocado, plus a poached leek and a basil-spinach pistou.</p>
        <p>But it was the roasted lamb that pulled me in, with its barley, a Persian homage of apricots and the asparagus of spring.</p>
        <p>Two desserts stood out: the hot apple-huckleberry crumble and the lemon tart, a minor miracle of freshness. Simple, elegant and saucy, it was practically perfect.</p>
        <p>''When I think about music and food, I think about Miles Davis,'' says Mr. Grossberg. ''He could play five notes in five minutes, and that was all that was necessary. I'm not even close to where I want to be.''</p>
        <p>When he gets there, I hope I can eat at his restaurant.</p>
        <p>Alphabet Soup  34 West Merchant Street  Audubon  (856) 310-0605  www.alphabetsoupnj.com</p>
        <p>EXCELLENT</p>
        <p>THE SPACE -- Small and delightful, with gray walls, red upholstery and whimsical touches. Complete wheelchair access.  THE CROWD -- Ranging from well dressed to casual, in jeans and T-shirts; some children. Efficient servers.  THE BAR -- Bring your own.  THE BILL -- Starters, $12 to $16. Main dishes, $27 to $38. Desserts, $7. (Neither American Express nor Discover cards are accepted.)  WHAT WE LIKE -- Everything: duck confit, foie gras, diver scallops, risotto, squash soup, venison, veal, lamb, steak, salmon, bass, cod, lemon tart, apple-huckleberry crumble.  IF YOU GO -- Open Wednesday to Sunday, 5:30 to 10 p.m. Reservations recommended on weekends. Adequate street parking along the canal that runs along the railroad tracks, and extra on the street. A municipal parking lot is down the block.  Reviewed April 22, 2007</p>
        <p>DINING/AUDUBON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
