<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gym Shorts</title>
    <meta content="quizquestions" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Education Life Supplement" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842065"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="POP QUIZ: PHYSICAL EDUCATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Physical Education and Training</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E6DF1F3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="941" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gym Shorts</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Less gym, more pounds. A coincidence? Judith Rink, a phys ed expert at the University of South Carolina, thinks not, and predicts a new respect for P.E. ''There has been so much public attention to the obesity issue,'' she says, ''decreasing P.E. time is probably not politically correct for schools to do anymore.'' She cites some legislative ''bright lights'': South Carolina has mandated at least 150 minutes of physical activity a week in elementary schools; California has announced incentive grants to hire about 1,100 new gym teachers. Two dozen states use the Praxis exam to certify phys ed teachers. The questions below, from the Educational Testing Service's practice exams, show what it takes. Answers are on Page 32.</p>
        <p>1. It is reputed that Milo of Greece lifted a newborn bull onto his shoulders each day until the bull became fully mature. Milo followed what two principles of modern muscle strength and endurance conditioning?  a. progression and overload  b. variable resistance and overload  c. frequency and progression  d. intensity and retention</p>
        <p>2. Which of the following sports is considered to have originated in the United States and not been adapted from similar games from other countries?  a. baseball  b. basketball  c. football  d. golf</p>
        <p>3. In the late 1800s, the greatest influence on the direction of physical education came from individuals with a background in which of the following?  a. medicine  b. professional sport  c. intercollegiate sport  d. the military</p>
        <p>4. Which of the following best describes the effect of sports participation on personality?  a. Players are not affected in a predictable way.  b. Players who pursue individual sports become more introverted.  c. Players who participate in team sports become more extroverted.  d. Players tend to become more individualistic.</p>
        <p>5. Which of the following lists the usual developmental order of play stages through which children progress in United States society?  a. competitive, cooperative, introspective, parallel  b. cooperative, competitive, parallel, introspective  c. introspective, parallel, cooperative, competitive  d. parallel, cooperative, competitive, introspective</p>
        <p>6. In its most rudimentary form, which of the following locomotor skills generally appears last in a young child's repertory of movements?  a. galloping  b. skipping  c. hopping  d. jumping</p>
        <p>7. Heavy resistive training, such as strenuous weight training, should be avoided in early childhood because of the potential development of:  a. inflexible joints  b. epiphyseal separations  c. elongated ligaments  d. calcium deposits</p>
        <p>8. Which of the following statements best characterizes most children between ages 5 and 8?  a. They are in the egocentric stage.  b. They choose leaders spontaneously from among themselves.  c. They are primarily concerned with following the rules.  d. They begin to create strategies and mentally test their abilities.</p>
        <p>9. Which of the following statements best characterizes most children between ages 8 and 11?  a. They have lost their strong egocentric tendencies.  b. They have a strong social need, especially at the higher age range.  c. They have a desire to participate in parallel play.  d. They feel more comfortable as part of a large group than a small group.</p>
        <p>10. In children age 5 through 9, the largest gender difference is generally evident in which of the following?  a. standing height (or stature)  b. overarm throwing velocity and distance  c. standing long-jump distance  d. sprint running speed and duration</p>
        <p>11. Using various body parts to volley a balloon or a lightweight ball will best enhance skill for which of the following sports?  a. basketball and soccer  b. basketball and tennis  c. volleyball and soccer  d. volleyball and tennis</p>
        <p>12. Based on the speed of the runners, which of the following is the generally accepted strategy used in setting up a pursuit relay team?  a. fastest, second fastest, third fastest, slowest  b. second fastest, third fastest, slowest, fastest  c. third fastest, slowest, fastest, second fastest  d. slowest, fastest, second fastest, third fastest</p>
        <p>13. When performing an overhand serve in volleyball, the player should:  a. contact the ball with a cupped or open hand  b. contact the ball with the arm bent  c. serve the ball off a bounce  d. shift weight to the back foot as the ball is contacted</p>
        <p>14. When dribbling a soccer ball in a restricted space, the player should attempt to do all of the following except:  a. keep the ball close to the feet  b. stay in a slightly crouched position  c. use body feints and changes of speed  d. use only the dominant foot for better control</p>
        <p>15. The correct racing posture of a swimmer, cyclist or downhill skier minimizes the effect of:  a. lift  b. propulsion  c. turbulence  d. gravity</p>
        <p>16. Which of the following activities is most aerobically demanding in relation to kilocalories burned per hour?  a. bowling  b. volleyball  c. walking  d. cross-country skiing</p>
        <p>17. To lose one pound of fat a week, a person would theoretically need a weekly caloric deficit of approximately:  a. 1,500 calories  b. 3,500 calories  c. 5,500 calories  d. 7,500 calories</p>
        <p>18. After maturity, which of the following generally increases due to the aging process?  a. maximum heart rate  b. vital capacity  c. body fat  d. body height</p>
        <p>19. Eighty percent of Americans will suffer from lower back pain. The primary cause of this condition is:  a. car accidents  b. muscular imbalance of the trunk  c. falls  d. osteoporosis</p>
        <p>20. The primary reason for including protein in the human diet is to provide:  a. material for building and repairing body tissue  b. an energy reserve in the body  c. vitamins and minerals for growth  d. readily available energy for bodily functions</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Less gym, more pounds. A coincidence? Judith Rink, a phys ed expert at the University of South Carolina, thinks not, and predicts a new respect for P.E. ''There has been so much public attention to the obesity issue,'' she says, ''decreasing P.E. time is probably not politically correct for schools to do anymore.'' She cites some legislative ''bright lights'': South Carolina has mandated at least 150 minutes of physical activity a week in elementary schools; California has announced incentive grants to hire about 1,100 new gym teachers. Two dozen states use the Praxis exam to certify phys ed teachers. The questions below, from the Educational Testing Service's practice exams, show what it takes. Answers are on Page 32.</p>
        <p>1. It is reputed that Milo of Greece lifted a newborn bull onto his shoulders each day until the bull became fully mature. Milo followed what two principles of modern muscle strength and endurance conditioning?  a. progression and overload  b. variable resistance and overload  c. frequency and progression  d. intensity and retention</p>
        <p>2. Which of the following sports is considered to have originated in the United States and not been adapted from similar games from other countries?  a. baseball  b. basketball  c. football  d. golf</p>
        <p>3. In the late 1800s, the greatest influence on the direction of physical education came from individuals with a background in which of the following?  a. medicine  b. professional sport  c. intercollegiate sport  d. the military</p>
        <p>4. Which of the following best describes the effect of sports participation on personality?  a. Players are not affected in a predictable way.  b. Players who pursue individual sports become more introverted.  c. Players who participate in team sports become more extroverted.  d. Players tend to become more individualistic.</p>
        <p>5. Which of the following lists the usual developmental order of play stages through which children progress in United States society?  a. competitive, cooperative, introspective, parallel  b. cooperative, competitive, parallel, introspective  c. introspective, parallel, cooperative, competitive  d. parallel, cooperative, competitive, introspective</p>
        <p>6. In its most rudimentary form, which of the following locomotor skills generally appears last in a young child's repertory of movements?  a. galloping  b. skipping  c. hopping  d. jumping</p>
        <p>7. Heavy resistive training, such as strenuous weight training, should be avoided in early childhood because of the potential development of:  a. inflexible joints  b. epiphyseal separations  c. elongated ligaments  d. calcium deposits</p>
        <p>8. Which of the following statements best characterizes most children between ages 5 and 8?  a. They are in the egocentric stage.  b. They choose leaders spontaneously from among themselves.  c. They are primarily concerned with following the rules.  d. They begin to create strategies and mentally test their abilities.</p>
        <p>9. Which of the following statements best characterizes most children between ages 8 and 11?  a. They have lost their strong egocentric tendencies.  b. They have a strong social need, especially at the higher age range.  c. They have a desire to participate in parallel play.  d. They feel more comfortable as part of a large group than a small group.</p>
        <p>10. In children age 5 through 9, the largest gender difference is generally evident in which of the following?  a. standing height (or stature)  b. overarm throwing velocity and distance  c. standing long-jump distance  d. sprint running speed and duration</p>
        <p>11. Using various body parts to volley a balloon or a lightweight ball will best enhance skill for which of the following sports?  a. basketball and soccer  b. basketball and tennis  c. volleyball and soccer  d. volleyball and tennis</p>
        <p>12. Based on the speed of the runners, which of the following is the generally accepted strategy used in setting up a pursuit relay team?  a. fastest, second fastest, third fastest, slowest  b. second fastest, third fastest, slowest, fastest  c. third fastest, slowest, fastest, second fastest  d. slowest, fastest, second fastest, third fastest</p>
        <p>13. When performing an overhand serve in volleyball, the player should:  a. contact the ball with a cupped or open hand  b. contact the ball with the arm bent  c. serve the ball off a bounce  d. shift weight to the back foot as the ball is contacted</p>
        <p>14. When dribbling a soccer ball in a restricted space, the player should attempt to do all of the following except:  a. keep the ball close to the feet  b. stay in a slightly crouched position  c. use body feints and changes of speed  d. use only the dominant foot for better control</p>
        <p>15. The correct racing posture of a swimmer, cyclist or downhill skier minimizes the effect of:  a. lift  b. propulsion  c. turbulence  d. gravity</p>
        <p>16. Which of the following activities is most aerobically demanding in relation to kilocalories burned per hour?  a. bowling  b. volleyball  c. walking  d. cross-country skiing</p>
        <p>17. To lose one pound of fat a week, a person would theoretically need a weekly caloric deficit of approximately:  a. 1,500 calories  b. 3,500 calories  c. 5,500 calories  d. 7,500 calories</p>
        <p>18. After maturity, which of the following generally increases due to the aging process?  a. maximum heart rate  b. vital capacity  c. body fat  d. body height</p>
        <p>19. Eighty percent of Americans will suffer from lower back pain. The primary cause of this condition is:  a. car accidents  b. muscular imbalance of the trunk  c. falls  d. osteoporosis</p>
        <p>20. The primary reason for including protein in the human diet is to provide:  a. material for building and repairing body tissue  b. an energy reserve in the body  c. vitamins and minerals for growth  d. readily available energy for bodily functions  POP QUIZ: PHYSICAL EDUCATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
