<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LIVING IN/Beacon, N.Y.; A Makeover in Progress, and Modern Art, Too</title>
    <meta content="22livi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/realestate/22livi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842119"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Living In | Beacon, N.Y."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Beacon (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brenner, Elsa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Upstate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Dutchess</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Beacon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Dutchess County (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE3D91F3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1669" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LIVING IN/Beacon, N.Y.; A Makeover in Progress, and Modern Art, Too</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Makeover in Progress, and Modern Art, Too</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELSA BRENNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brenner, Elsa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Living In article on Beacon, NY; maps; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Emma Dewing and her husband, Kanoa Baysa, who had been renting an apartment in Williamsburg, Brooklyn, decided to buy a home last year but realized they couldn't afford the size they needed in New York City, they refocused their search on towns strung along the commuter rail lines running north from Manhattan.</p>
        <p>They felt priced out of Westchester and Putnam Counties, too. So, setting their sights ever northward, Ms. Dewing, a stay-at-home mother, and Mr. Baysa, a sculptor and builder of stage sets, found Beacon, a formerly hard-pressed town 60 miles north of New York City in southern Dutchess County, on Metro-North Railroad's Hudson line south of Poughkeepsie.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Beacon, the ruins of hat-making, brick and carton factories are being reincarnated as artists’ lofts and once-boarded-up storefronts have reopened as boutiques.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Emma Dewing and her husband, Kanoa Baysa, who had been renting an apartment in Williamsburg, Brooklyn, decided to buy a home last year but realized they couldn't afford the size they needed in New York City, they refocused their search on towns strung along the commuter rail lines running north from Manhattan.</p>
        <p>They felt priced out of Westchester and Putnam Counties, too. So, setting their sights ever northward, Ms. Dewing, a stay-at-home mother, and Mr. Baysa, a sculptor and builder of stage sets, found Beacon, a formerly hard-pressed town 60 miles north of New York City in southern Dutchess County, on Metro-North Railroad's Hudson line south of Poughkeepsie.</p>
        <p>There, the ruins of hat-making, brick and carton factories are being reincarnated as artists' lofts; once-boarded-up storefronts have reopened as trendy boutiques; and an abandoned industrial building reopened four years ago as a shrine to modern art, Dia:Beacon.</p>
        <p>The town, with 14,000 people on 4.8 square miles, still bears the scars of a prolonged economic downturn that started in the mid-1950s. There were periods several years ago, said Sgt. Gary Fredericks of the Beacon police force, when drug traffic thrived along the milelong stretch of Main Street.</p>
        <p>Today, the storefronts there give more encouraging signs of life. And within walking distance of them -- tucked between the 1,500-foot-high Mount Beacon and the corrugated eastern shore of the Hudson River -- is a housing stock of single-family bungalows, Cape Cods, modest colonials and ranches on tidy lots.</p>
        <p>Beacon seemed made to order for Mr. Baysa and Ms. Dewing, who several months ago paid $245,000 for a 1920s three-bedroom Arts and Crafts-style bungalow with a fenced-in backyard ideal for their son, Ikaika Baysa, who is 17 months old.</p>
        <p>They aren't the only ones. Beacon, known among other things for being the longtime home of the folk singer Pete Seeger, is a quirky town that lures creative types -- many on limited budgets -- who shy away from more conventional suburbs.</p>
        <p>The population reflects a mix of income levels, races and ages. According to Census Bureau figures from 2005, nearly 61 percent of Beacon residents are white non-Hispanic; almost 20 percent are black; and just under 17 percent are Hispanic.</p>
        <p>Jim Svetz, the co-owner of a Main Street coffee shop called the Muddy Cup, said that on a typical Sunday afternoon a wide variety of residents -- everyone from local teenagers to newly arrived young married couples to old-time parishioners from the Star of Bethlehem Baptist Church down the street -- make themselves comfortable in his shop.</p>
        <p>The town has been growing, but the growth has been spasmodic. In addition to the 300,000-square-foot Nabisco carton manufacturing factory that became Dia:Beacon, there may also ultimately be a waterfront conference center and park called Long Dock Beacon. Ned Foss, one of the developers, estimated the cost of the project at $75 million and said it would include a 166-room hotel, among other things. He said the project was still in the design phase.</p>
        <p>But another project, the Beacon Cultural Foundation, which made it to fruition in 2003, filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection last year, perhaps sounding a note of caution for entrepreneurs like Mr. Foss. Looking back on the episode, Sam Yanes, the group's director, has said that the $4.25 million it paid for its site, the former Beacon High School, was too high. In the end, he added, the foundation was unable to meet energy costs.</p>
        <p>The school district has since repossessed the building but has not yet decided what to do with it, said Ann Marie Quartironi, a business administrator for the district, adding that artists are still working in the spaces that the cultural foundation created in former classrooms.</p>
        <p>The economic uncertainty is a concern for people like Charlotte Guernsey, an artist and real estate broker who owns land and several buildings in the city. She feels that development isn't happening fast enough. In addition to the failed cultural foundation, Ms. Guernsey points to what she considers an eyesore on Main Street, opposite her office: an abandoned factory with punched-out windows.</p>
        <p>Its owner, a holding company called Beacon Terminal Associates, has a number of similar old factory buildings. David Lloyds, the company's vice president, said it was working with the state Department of Environmental Conservation to determine the extent of contamination on the properties, with the goal of redeveloping them as residences.</p>
        <p>He would not say what kind of contamination might be present on the properties, although the early-20th-century hat-making industry was known for its use of mercury to shape the felt used in hats. ''It's a long process to redevelop a site, especially old industrial sites,'' he said.</p>
        <p>What You'll Find</p>
        <p>Beacon's boosters, like Mayor Cara-Lou Gould, note that economic ups and downs are no indication of failure and aren't imperiling a slow but steady improvement. In the first half of the 1900s, when factories were booming, she claimed, Beacon was among the country's most vigorous small cities.</p>
        <p>She is quick to emphasize the unspoiled atmosphere, pointing out that unlike other similar places, Beacon has not been overrun with Mercedes sedans, McMansions and other symbols of suburban affluence.</p>
        <p>In fact, there are residents who feel that such symbols are already too plentiful. Karen Gowan, a grants analyst for the Ford Foundation in Manhattan who moved here nine years ago, said that in some ways it was already overcrowded.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gowan, 47, who owns a small gatehouse and commutes to Grand Central Terminal, says that on weekday mornings, parking is hard to find at the Beacon station.</p>
        <p>''And for my taste,'' she added, ''there are more McMansions going up than I'd like to see. They're cropping up and spoiling what was the more modest appeal of Beacon when I first moved here.''</p>
        <p>But that appeal is still very much in evidence downtown along Main Street, where rental apartments with tie-back curtains and plants in their windows sit atop storefronts. On the blocks bordering the long commercial strip, the streets are lined with close-set single-family and multifamily wood-frame and vinyl-clad homes built during the last century.</p>
        <p>Farther out, toward Mount Beacon, landowners have bought large areas, carved out new roads in the hills, renovated and rented out older buildings, and built new structures. On one hilly road overlooking the river, grand Victorians once occupied by factory owners and managers are still very much lived in.</p>
        <p>What You'll Pay</p>
        <p>The 2000 census found 5,406 rental and ownership units in Beacon, and a density of 2,892 people per square mile. The same census found a density of 5,416 in White Plains, Westchester's county seat.</p>
        <p>On the east end of Main Street, an industrial building has been turned into 14 rental apartments, with studios for $1,250 a month and two-bedrooms for $1,650 and up.</p>
        <p>The units appeal to tenants like Arben Gasi, 27, and Olivier Lagarde, 34, engineers who work for I.B.M. in nearby Fishkill and find the building reminiscent of city residences in the southern French city of Toulouse, where they used to live.</p>
        <p>But most apartments in older buildings cost several hundred dollars a month less, said Janet Gerlach of Hedgestone Realty Group.</p>
        <p>Through the first quarter of this year, there were 59 houses listed for sale and 28 sold, said Santo Tambone of the Mid Hudson Multiple Listing Service. By comparison, in all of 2002, 82 homes sold, he said.</p>
        <p>A two-bedroom, one-bath colonial is listed for $229,900; a three-bedroom, two-and-a-half-bath Dutch colonial for $469,900; and a four-bedroom colonial with five full and two half baths for $1.199 million.</p>
        <p>The median sold price for a single-family house as of the end of April was $272,000, according to Mr. Tambone. For the whole of last year, the median was $300,000. And five years ago, it was $177,500.</p>
        <p>What to Do</p>
        <p>For Ms. Dewing and Mr. Baysa, Beacon's major draw is its cultural offerings, not least Dia:Beacon, Riggio Galleries (named in honor of Louise and Leonard Riggio, donors of $30 million). There is also the Tallix Art Foundry, a sculpture facility that has produced the Franklin D. Roosevelt and the Korean War Memorials, among other works.</p>
        <p>The Howland Cultural Center in the city, in a Victorian building on the National Register of Historic Places, is used for concerts, recitals, plays and poetry readings. Also, Main Street has private galleries, including bau, an artists' collective, and Hudson Beach Glass, which demonstrates glassblowing.</p>
        <p>For residents like Patty Scecina, who moved to Beacon last fall and teaches fifth grade in Garrison, the outdoor activities -- hiking on Mount Beacon and boating on the waterfront -- are also a plus. In the evening, the restaurants and pubs offer live music. Ms. Scecina's two grown sons are among the performers. ''Beacon's small-city atmosphere is an especially good place for an older single like myself,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The Schools</p>
        <p>The Beacon City School District has almost 3,200 students in three elementary schools, one middle school and a high school.</p>
        <p>SAT averages from last spring were 478 on the verbal portion and 506 on the math section, versus state averages of 493 and 510. Of last year's 258 graduates, 103 are attending four-year colleges and universities, 129 are at two-year colleges, 5 joined the military and 21 have other jobs, said Edward Mancari, principal of Beacon High School.</p>
        <p>The Commute</p>
        <p>For daily commuters to Grand Central Terminal, express trains from Beacon to Midtown Manhattan keep the ride under an hour and 20 minutes. A monthly ticket, if bought on the Web, is $314.58. Round-trip tickets during peak hours are $28.98.</p>
        <p>The History</p>
        <p>Beacon was settled in 1709 as the villages of Matteawan and Fishkill Landing. The town was named for the signal fires set on Mount Beacon during the Revolution.</p>
        <p>During the 1800s, Beacon was a hat-making center.</p>
        <p>Going Forward</p>
        <p>Because it is evolving out of a slump, Beacon has real estate bargains. But for the same reason, such investments are uncertain. Also, movies and discount shopping are 20 minutes away in Poughkeepsie.</p>
        <p>Living In | Beacon, N.Y.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
