<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Red Sox Reliever Finds A Role in an Old Rivalry</title>
    <meta content="22redsox" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/sports/baseball/22redsox.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842307"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Beckett, Josh</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rodriguez, Alex</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3DE173EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="876" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Red Sox Reliever Finds A Role in an Old Rivalry</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Red Sox Reliever Finds A Role in an Old Rivalry</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, April 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The dramatic at-bat that never happened was Jonathan Papelbon against Alex Rodriguez. Rodriguez was standing in the on-deck circle when Papelbon retired Bobby Abreu and enabled the Boston Red Sox to silence the Yankees, 7-5, on Saturday. The mighty Rodriguez did not get the chance to face the mighty Papelbon.</p>
        <p>But the dramatic at-bat that did happen came in the seventh inning when Hideki Okajima, the other Japanese pitcher on the Red Sox, faced Jason Giambi with the potential tying runs on base. Okajima had replaced Josh Beckett, who had surrendered Alex Rodriguez's run-scoring single and made things tenser at Fenway Park.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Josh Beckett, who was touched for four runs in the first two innings, wound up surrendering five runs on nine hits in six and two-thirds innings to help the Red Sox win on Saturday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The dramatic at-bat that never happened was Jonathan Papelbon against Alex Rodriguez. Rodriguez was standing in the on-deck circle when Papelbon retired Bobby Abreu and enabled the Boston Red Sox to silence the Yankees, 7-5, on Saturday. The mighty Rodriguez did not get the chance to face the mighty Papelbon.</p>
        <p>But the dramatic at-bat that did happen came in the seventh inning when Hideki Okajima, the other Japanese pitcher on the Red Sox, faced Jason Giambi with the potential tying runs on base. Okajima had replaced Josh Beckett, who had surrendered Alex Rodriguez's run-scoring single and made things tenser at Fenway Park.</p>
        <p>Okajima is still a bit of an unknown to Giambi and the Yankees as a left-handed reliever with a decent fastball, a nifty curveball and a nice changeup. His fastball rarely exceeds 88 miles an hour, but if Okajima is precise with spotting his pitches, he can be very effective.</p>
        <p>Giambi discovered how tricky Okajima can be when he missed a 2-2 fastball and killed the rally. After Okajima filled in for a resting Papelbon on Friday and notched a save, he came back about 20 hours later and notched another critical out. Later, Okajima sounded as if he were born for this rivalry.</p>
        <p>''When I'm facing a batter, I don't think who he is and what his name is,'' Okajima said through an interpreter. ''I just think about the pitches I have to throw.''</p>
        <p>An animated Beckett might have been louder than any fans after Okajima struck out Giambi. Beckett had pitched six and two-thirds draining innings, but no matter how hard he pumped his fastballs to Rodriguez (and they ranged from 95 to 98 m.p.h.), he could not retire him in the seventh. So Beckett stewed in the dugout and pounded a water cooler, until Okajima rescued him.</p>
        <p>''You never want to have somebody else clean up your mess for you,'' Beckett said.</p>
        <p>With the Yankees and the Red Sox playing a nationally televised game that started at 3:54 p.m., about three hours later than normal, everything seemed to be moving in slow motion. It was a day where the plodding Red Sox had two bunt singles and a sacrifice bunt. It was a day where Manny Ramírez danced around a ball that bounced off the left-field wall and slithered through his legs. That was actually the correct play.</p>
        <p>But it was also a day when David Ortiz did a Rodriguez imitation with a home run, a double and four runs batted in. Ortiz said that he was not motivated to try to match what Rodriguez, his good friend, was doing, and said that he was just ''trying to do the job.''</p>
        <p>Ortiz's two-run homer against Jeff Karstens gave the Red Sox a 7-4 lead in the fourth. The only thing surprising about it was that it did not come later in the game, as Ortiz's important hits often do.</p>
        <p>''It's all the time,'' said Terry Francona, the Red Sox' manager. ''That's why he's here. That's why he is who he is.''</p>
        <p>Still, it was also a game in which Beckett's resurgence was important. The Yankees peppered Beckett for four runs on five hits in the first two innings. When Beckett becomes too reliant on fastballs, he can get into trouble. Aside from some early off-speed pitches to Rodriguez, Beckett was throwing a lot of fastballs.</p>
        <p>But, even though Beckett said that he did not change his pitching style after two dismal innings, Francona said that Beckett rebounded in part because he threw his breaking pitches for strikes. After Rodriguez doubled to open the third and Ramírez danced around the ball in left, Beckett retired 14 of the next 15 batters while using his entire repertory of pitches. He has won his first four starts.</p>
        <p>''I don't think that Josh had his greatest stuff,'' Red Sox third baseman Mike Lowell said. ''That's the mark of a guy who is maturing. When your stuff is not that good, that's when you have to grind it out.''</p>
        <p>Beckett defeated the Yankees in the clinching game of the 2003 World Series with the Florida Marlins, but he has never pitched well against them in the regular season. When Beckett was drubbed for a career-worst nine runs by the Yankees last August, he threw too many fastballs.</p>
        <p>''That was one of those days where you don't find anything,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Beckett said that he never thought about last August, but Ortiz did. That was when the Yankees swept five games from the Red Sox and buried them.</p>
        <p>''The last time we played them, they just killed us,'' Ortiz said. ''Now we've got to show everybody we've got a better team.''</p>
        <p>This time, the Red Sox have a chance for a sweep when Daisuke Matsuzaka, the heavily hyped pitcher from Japan, makes his first start against the Yankees on Sunday night.</p>
        <p>Who would have had expected Okajima to have influenced two games against New York before Matsuzaka even appeared in one? Okajima is quickly becoming a cult hero at Fenway, where he received a standing ovation after saving Beckett and saving the Red Sox.</p>
        <p>''It's nice to see him respond to the Yankees-Red Sox and all that,'' Francona said. ''It's nice to see that.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
