<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What's in the Air At Graduation?</title>
    <meta content="toss22" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Education Life Supplement" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/education/edlife/toss22.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842072"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="COMMENCEMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E5DF1F3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="378" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What's in the Air At Graduation?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Commencement: What’s in the Air at Graduation?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTINE LAGORIO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lagorio, Christine</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN 1912, for the first time, midshipmen graduating from the United States Naval Academy were awarded officers' hats at commencement. No longer in need of their midshipmen caps, they spontaneously lobbed them into the air.</p>
        <p>Graduates -- military and otherwise -- have engaged in mass captosses ever since.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The tradition of mass cap-tosses has spawned creative commencement-day displays.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN 1912, for the first time, midshipmen graduating from the United States Naval Academy were awarded officers' hats at commencement. No longer in need of their midshipmen caps, they spontaneously lobbed them into the air.</p>
        <p>Graduates -- military and otherwise -- have engaged in mass captosses ever since.</p>
        <p>The tradition has spawned creative commencement-day displays. Harvard graduate students coordinate in advance what to throw, so it varies each year depending on student ''whims and ingenuity,'' says Marvin Hightower, a spokesman.</p>
        <p>Other universities have tossing traditions. More than a decade ago some ''ingenious students figured out that tortillas fly like Frisbees when tossed,'' says Jim Drnek, associate dean of students at the University of Arizona. The practice has been called racist by the area's Hispanics and American Indians and dangerous by the administration.</p>
        <p>''They do hurt, especially when they are dried a bit,'' Mr. Drnek says. One year a dough disk hit the president, Peter Likins, in the face.</p>
        <p>Until his retirement last summer, Mr. Likins campaigned vehemently against tortilla tossing. He implemented robe searches in 2004, but the ceremony was particularly rowdy. Daniel Hornung, who graduated that year, likens the toss to a drunken food fight: ''It is a mess, especially when people start throwing them off the ground and they are torn and dirty.'' Mr. Likins threatened to cancel ceremonies if the throws didn't stop.</p>
        <p>Last spring, every graduate and guest was searched upon entry. About 3,000 tortillas, sometimes in bulk quantities, were confiscated from purses and diaper bags (unopened packages were donated to a community food bank). Even so, hundreds of tortillas flew. ''They sort of cemented it as a tradition by telling us not to do it,'' Mr. Hornung says. ''No one wants to be the class not throwing them.''</p>
        <p>CHRISTINE LAGORIO</p>
        <p>THINGS THEY'VE TOSSED</p>
        <p>UNIVERSITY OF ARIZONA  Tortillas (pictured above)</p>
        <p>HARVARD  Condoms labeled ''safe sex'' in Latin; rubber chickens sans flu (School of Public Health)  Pipe-cleaner halos, devil's horns (Divinity School)  False teeth, inflatable toothpaste tubes (School of Dental Medicine)  Inflatable sharks, wooden gavels (Law School)  Construction tape, rulers (Graduate School of Design)</p>
        <p>COLUMBIA  Faux CliffsNotes (the college)  Inflated surgical gloves (College of Physicians and Surgeons)  Newspaper confetti (Graduate School of Journalism)</p>
        <p>MILWAUKEE SCHOOL OF ENGINEERING  Hardhats (carefully!)</p>
        <p>COMMENCEMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
