<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Life Of the After-Party</title>
    <meta content="22andre" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/fashion/22andre.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842133"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Graffiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nightclubs and Cabarets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DF163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1080" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Life Of the After-Party</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Life of the After-Party</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIA CHAPLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chaplin, Julia</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANDRÉ SARAIVA, the slight 35-year-old graffitist and night-life entrepreneur, showed up at the Emmanuel Perrotin gallery in the Marais on a recent Saturday night in his trademark impossibly skinny jeans and a navy Thom Browne peacoat.</p>
        <p>He had come by for the opening of a show of works by the Belgian conceptual artist Wim Delvoye. It was just a few nights post-Fashion Week and Mr. Saraiva had spent the week throwing boozy after-parties for his friends Marc (as in Jacobs), Stefano (as in Pilati, the Yves Saint Laurent designer) and Nicolas (Ghesquiere, as in Balenciaga) at Le Baron and Paris Paris, his perennially packed nightclubs. Nevertheless, he looked more than ready to greet another sunrise.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>André Saraiva is painting the town red, but he has a history of painting the town, literally.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANDRÉ SARAIVA, the slight 35-year-old graffitist and night-life entrepreneur, showed up at the Emmanuel Perrotin gallery in the Marais on a recent Saturday night in his trademark impossibly skinny jeans and a navy Thom Browne peacoat.</p>
        <p>He had come by for the opening of a show of works by the Belgian conceptual artist Wim Delvoye. It was just a few nights post-Fashion Week and Mr. Saraiva had spent the week throwing boozy after-parties for his friends Marc (as in Jacobs), Stefano (as in Pilati, the Yves Saint Laurent designer) and Nicolas (Ghesquiere, as in Balenciaga) at Le Baron and Paris Paris, his perennially packed nightclubs. Nevertheless, he looked more than ready to greet another sunrise.</p>
        <p>He worked the rooms of the converted 17th-century mansion -- one of France's most-watched galleries for emerging artists -- with verve, plying through the hipster elite with a squeeze of the arm and a kiss on both cheeks for everyone.</p>
        <p>''I love this,'' said Mr. Saraiva, deviating from the meet and greet to inspect an intricate pencil drawing. ''It's by Gelitin. An art collective from Austria. They did an amazing installation at Art Basel this year.''</p>
        <p>It used to be that the most dialed-in international party promoters held events in Los Angeles during Oscar week, St.-Tropez or the Hamptons in August, and over New Year's in Punta del Este or maybe St. Bart's. But all that seems hopelessly passé.</p>
        <p>Now the contemporary-art craze has rearranged the sociopolitical map of destination desire and mobilized a new class of bohemian jet-setters, who flit between art fair and biennial and crave a gritty after-party. Mr. Saraiva is their man on the ground.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, Mr. Saraiva and his partner in Le Baron and Paris Paris, Lionel Bensemoun (whose father is a casino owner), were approached by two Le Baron habitués, Mr. Perrotin and the director of Art Basel Miami Beach, Sam Keller, about giving late-night parties during the fair. So they set up for the week in a kitschy karaoke club in the basement of the Shelborne hotel on South Beach and packed it with dewy art stars and gallerists.</p>
        <p>Now the ''Le Baron party'' is a staple on the art fair circuit, taking over dive bars during the Frieze in London, the Armory Show in New York City, Art Basel, and this June the Venice Biennale. (There are no invitations, but the coordinates are traded at gallery booths and openings.)</p>
        <p>''It is great to have one of us organizing nightclubs which actively involve artists and give the art world a late-night home,'' said Mr. Keller, who called Mr. Saraiva and Mr. Bensemoun social ''alchemists.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Saraiva is also a partner in the Hôtel Amour with Thierry Costes, of the Costes hotel and restaurant family; the Beatrice Inn in New York; and, with the industrial designer Marc Newson, a branch of Le Baron in Tokyo. He was born in Sweden but was brought up in Paris, and as a teenager began tagging the streets with his trademark ''Mr. A,'' a stick figure with a winking eye and a top hat.</p>
        <p>Mr. Saraiva, who had blue paint on his boots, said he still goes on late-night graffiti missions, dressed incognito in a suit, when in Tokyo or Hong Kong. But he refrains in Paris because he is on probation, having been caught so many times over the years.</p>
        <p>More recently, he did ''Love Graffiti,'' a project where, for $2,500, he'd spray-paint the name of a lover in big bubble letters at an address of the customer's choosing. But the cognoscenti know him as the guy who runs Black Block, a boutique in the contemporary-art space Palais de Tokyo that sells knickknacks like black toilet paper and a vase shaped like an army tank.</p>
        <p>Mr. Saraiva, who is soft-spoken and flirtatious, seems to know almost everyone in the international fashion-art orbit. New acquaintances instantly become confidants. If he sees artists standing awkwardly on the sidelines of one of his clubs or at an art opening, he'll swoop in, bestow them with a drink and lead them by the wrist to the safety of a V.I.P. room or a clutch of interesting people. A bond is formed.</p>
        <p>''André has a MySpace quality,'' said Olivier Zahm, the editor of the magazine Purple Fashion. ''He makes friends instantly and then his new friends become your friends. It's a big magic.''</p>
        <p>All of which seems to serve him well in a world based on social alliances, the bartering of cool and a plumped-up contact list. ''I don't have to buy art,'' Mr. Saraiva said. ''My friends just give me work.''</p>
        <p>In return -- he says he has pieces by Dash Snow, Dan Colen and Sophie Calle -- he lets the artists stay at the Hôtel Amour and drink free at his clubs. ''So it works out,'' he said. Part of his charm is that he avoids many of the tackier tricks of the club trade. ''We have no bankers backing us,'' Mr. Saraiva said. ''We don't use p.r.'' His places have a certain punk glamour, with worn red carpets and upholstery that is covered with beer stains and cigarette burns, as if to ward off those with platinum credit cards and collagen lips.</p>
        <p>At Le Baron in Paris, a former strip club, artists are employed as doormen and D.J.'s. Fashion models are turned away, as are soccer stars and bankers.</p>
        <p>''Mostly, models are cheesy and stupid,'' Mr. Saraiva said. ''They show up with tacky men who think they are kings of the world because they have a driver and expensive clothes. A guy that looks like a bum is more likely to get into one of my places.''</p>
        <p>But there must have been models in his clubs during Fashion Week? Mr. Saraiva smiled mischievously. ''Yes, but those ones are our friends.''</p>
        <p>Which seems to also be the thinking behind the Beatrice Inn, the musty basement bar in the West Village in New York that is nearly impossible to get into if your hair is overly blow-dried or you appear to have more than $100 in your pocket.</p>
        <p>On this Saturday evening, Mr. Saraiva was supposed to fly to Tokyo, where he and Mr. Newson were to be the hosts of a birthday blowout for a member of Phoenix, the experimental French rock band, at Le Baron there. But he missed his plane.</p>
        <p>''I'll go tomorrow,'' Mr. Saraiva said with a shrug. Then he hopped onto his red Vespa and zoomed off into the night.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
