<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Repaying Alexander Hamilton</title>
    <meta content="NJpaterson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/opinion/nyregionopinions/NJpaterson.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842101"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="New Jersey"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">National Parks, Monuments and Seashores</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Paterson (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Falls (Paterson, NJ)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/National Parks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">National Parks, Monuments and Seashores</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Hamilton, Alexander</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E5DA1F3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="612" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Repaying Alexander Hamilton</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Repaying Alexander Hamilton</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial supports effort to designate and preserve historic Great Falls district of Paterson, NJ, as national park</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Walk through the historic Great Falls district of Paterson and you will get a feel for what life was like in the early days of industrial America. There's the ''raceway,'' for example, a gradually sloping set of canals on three levels. As the water dropped from one level to another, it turned giant wheels that provided power to the mills.</p>
        <p>A few of the factories still remain, with their numerous windows that provided essential light during a time when artificial lighting was hard to come by. Some of the space has been converted into artists' housing and office suites, including one for a podiatrist and another for a dentist, and a few light manufacturers are using portions of the buildings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New Jersey members of Congress are trying to persuade the federal government to designate Paterson’s historic manufacturing district as a national park. And for good reason.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Walk through the historic Great Falls district of Paterson and you will get a feel for what life was like in the early days of industrial America. There's the ''raceway,'' for example, a gradually sloping set of canals on three levels. As the water dropped from one level to another, it turned giant wheels that provided power to the mills.</p>
        <p>A few of the factories still remain, with their numerous windows that provided essential light during a time when artificial lighting was hard to come by. Some of the space has been converted into artists' housing and office suites, including one for a podiatrist and another for a dentist, and a few light manufacturers are using portions of the buildings.</p>
        <p>There is also the site of the ''bull mill'' where bulls harnessed to a wheel walked in a circle to generate additional power. The mill provides a glimpse into an almost forgotten element of the early industrial city: its quasi-rural atmosphere. Livestock roamed the streets, and farmland was just beyond the downtown area.</p>
        <p>The district's signature feature is the so-called Great Falls of Paterson, the spectacular 77-foot waterfalls; east of the Mississippi it is second largest in volume to Niagara Falls. If you walk on the pathway to the promontory overlooking the falls, the chasm to the north would make you think you are in rural Maine rather than in one of New Jersey's poorest, most rundown cities.</p>
        <p>It is this 118-acre historic manufacturing district that a group of Paterson natives and residents, prominent American historians and all 15 New Jersey members of Congress are trying to persuade the federal government to designate as a national park. And for good reason: Alexander Hamilton, a founding father who became the nation's first Treasury secretary, established what Ron Chernow, author of an acclaimed 2004 Hamilton biography, calls the model for America's industrial cities. In Congressional testimony last month, Mr. Chernow lamented how the country does a much better job in telling its political history than ''the no less stirring saga of our economic development.''</p>
        <p>But national park designation for the district is a tough sell, despite Paterson's glorious early history of textile and silk mills, steam engine factories, the Holland Boat submarine and the Colt Gun Mill. The National Park Service says it is already telling the story of industrial America, primarily in Lowell, Mass., where the state's powerful Congressional delegation helped win national park designation even though Lowell lacked Paterson's historical significance. And the Bush administration argues there is not enough money to maintain existing national parks, much less acquire new ones.</p>
        <p>Certainly money is tight, although Paterson's advocates are asking for a modest initial appropriation of no more than $10 million. But a great nation needs to do more than pay for war and commemorate its battlefields and majestic beauty. It needs also to recognize an area that was truly significant in making the nation the economic and capitalist power that it is today.</p>
        <p>Paterson's story is more complex than the story of presidents whose grand estates are now national parks. Paterson flourished as an industrial beacon, but it then declined and has long suffered hard times. But peaks and declines are an important part of the country's history, and the story of the manufacturing era of early America, in which men born to no great wealth built major industries, deserves to be told in the city where it started.</p>
        <p>An additional benefit of designating Paterson as a national park is that it may well help bring the city back to some semblance of its better days. That would be an appropriate way to repay Hamilton for his contribution to America's greatness.</p>
        <p>New Jersey</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
