<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Ocean of Opportunity</title>
    <meta content="22boss" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/business/yourmoney/22boss.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842202"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OFFICE SPACE: THE BOSS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/The Boss</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Careers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Human Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">General Maritime Corporation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E1DC163EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="797" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Ocean of Opportunity</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Ocean of Opportunity</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER C. GEORGIOPOULOS; As told to Claudia H. Deutsch.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Deutsch, Claudia H; Georgiopoulos, Peter</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I'VE had people ask me whether, had one of my ancestors shortened the name from Georgiopoulos to something like George, I would have wound up in the traditional role of Greek shipping magnate. A better question might be, if I hadn't grown up in the United States, where everything seems possible, would I have even tried?</p>
        <p>The funny part is, when I was growing up, I never thought of myself as Greek. My family has been in the United States since the 1800s, I've got blond hair and blue eyes, and like most American kids, I liked only plain foods like hamburgers and steak.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“When I was growing up, I never thought of myself as Greek. My family has been in the United States since the 1800s,” said Peter C. Georgiopoulos, chief executive, General Maritime.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I'VE had people ask me whether, had one of my ancestors shortened the name from Georgiopoulos to something like George, I would have wound up in the traditional role of Greek shipping magnate. A better question might be, if I hadn't grown up in the United States, where everything seems possible, would I have even tried?</p>
        <p>The funny part is, when I was growing up, I never thought of myself as Greek. My family has been in the United States since the 1800s, I've got blond hair and blue eyes, and like most American kids, I liked only plain foods like hamburgers and steak.</p>
        <p>And I certainly wasn't Mr. Achievement. I didn't even much like school. I was a smart kid and a good test taker, so I got into the Bronx High School of Science, but I was never better than a C+ student there. I was a happy-go-lucky kid who, when I thought about a career at all, figured I'd be a rock star.</p>
        <p>I had to do something when I graduated high school, so I went to Fordham University, partly because it was an easy commute from our Bronx home. I majored in business, but truthfully, it bored me.</p>
        <p>My dad was a successful maritime lawyer, and a lot of his clients were rich, glamorous Greek shipping tycoons whose lifestyles really appealed to me. When I graduated, one of them offered me a job in Athens, in his chartering department. One day, after I'd been there about two years, he asked me if I'd decided what I wanted to do with the rest of my life. I said I wanted to start my own shipping company.</p>
        <p>That's when culture clash really hit. In America, you get the sense you can do anything you want. That's not true in Greece, and he was really offended. He called my father, and said: ''Who does your son think he is? Does he think this is easy?'' And my father, for some reason, sided with him and yelled at me.</p>
        <p>I was surprised that my father didn't back me up, but my reaction was, ''I'll show them!'' So I left Greece and went to Dartmouth for an M.B.A.</p>
        <p>Back then, a lot more doors were open to people with American last names. In 1985, when I graduated, a Wall Street recruiter actually told me that, with a last name like Georgiopoulos, I'd have trouble getting an investment banking job.</p>
        <p>But I did get a job at Drexel Burnham. I didn't really like investment banking; I still wanted to be my own boss. But I made a lot of money, and met a lot of people. And it was a time when a lot of shipping partnerships had formed in Norway to take advantage of tax laws. In the '90s, Norway changed its tax laws, and the partnership shares plummeted. I figured we could buy the ships they owned.</p>
        <p>I tried to persuade some of the Greek ship owners I knew to go in on it with me, but their reaction was, ''If this is such a good deal, why wouldn't the Norwegians do it themselves?'' These guys would have left a $20 bill sitting on the floor because no one else had picked it up.</p>
        <p>So I got some hedge funds to put up money, and we started buying ships, selling them, then using the profit to buy some more. By 1997 I had investors coming to me, asking me to take their money to do this.</p>
        <p>That's how General Maritime was born. We took it public in 2001, and by 2003 we were the fourth-largest tanker company in the world. That was when everyone started referring to me as the Greek shipping tycoon. And people would make comparisons to Aristotle Onassis and such. I've never actively played the role -- but I don't try to discourage it.</p>
        <p>I'm proud to be Greek. I got married two years ago, and my wife converted to Greek Orthodox. I was named after my grandfather, Peter Constantine, because that's the Greek custom. We're going to have a son in July, and I plan to name him after my father, Constantine Peter. And while I still like plain foods best, I've learned to like, and even to cook, Greek foods, too.</p>
        <p>But I never forget that, if I hadn't been brought up American, I might never have made it so big in a classic Greek career.</p>
        <p>PETER C. GEORGIOPOULOS  Chief executive, General Maritime Corporation</p>
        <p>HOME  Greenwich Village, with weekend forays to a farm in Millbrook, N.Y.</p>
        <p>HOBBIES  Bird shooting in the fall, reading and 'generally being lazy' other times.</p>
        <p>FAVORITE VACATION SPOT  The Greek Isles, on a chartered boat.</p>
        <p>OFFICE SPACE: THE BOSS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
