<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Affordable Europe: Berlin</title>
    <meta content="22berlinweb" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/travel/22berlinweb.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842334"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Berlin (Germany)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany/Berlin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Berlin (Germany)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E1D61631F931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Affordable Europe: Berlin</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Affordable Europe: Berlin</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRETCHEN LANG</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BERLIN is the home of good deals. Eighteen years after the fall of the Berlin Wall, the city's depressed economy has kept prices down, and transportation and food are generally more reasonable than in other large European capitals. The city's 20th-century history is visible everywhere to the hardy walker, and there are plenty of green spaces where you can relax and grab a quick kebab or currywurst for lunch.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay for Under 125 Euros</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eighteen years after the fall of the Berlin Wall, the city’s depressed economy has kept prices down, and transportation and food are generally more reasonable than in other large European capitals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BERLIN is the home of good deals. Eighteen years after the fall of the Berlin Wall, the city's depressed economy has kept prices down, and transportation and food are generally more reasonable than in other large European capitals. The city's 20th-century history is visible everywhere to the hardy walker, and there are plenty of green spaces where you can relax and grab a quick kebab or currywurst for lunch.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay for Under 125 Euros</p>
        <p>Finding a cheap hotel in Berlin is easy. Finding something cheap and nice is tougher. One budget possibility is the Albrechtshof in Mitte. (Albrechtstrasse 8; 49-30-308-860; www.albrechtshof-hotels.de.) Up a side street from the river, right in the heart of town, Albrechtshof has a clean, cheerful foyer, a cozy bar and a cafe with a cool, flower-filled inner courtyard. Doubles go for 152 euros (about $205 at $1.36 to the euro), but on weekends the price is 122 euros, depending on availability. Down a green side street in Charlottenburg, the Bleibtreu (Bleibtreustrasse 31; 49-30-884-740; www.bleibtreu.com) gives easy access to the swank shops on Kurfürstendamm and the funky, more colorful neighborhood around Savignyplatz. A little spare, the hotel nevertheless provides a calm, clean environment using natural woods and fibers in muted tones. Rooms offer wireless DSL connections, there are a steam room, a masseuse on call and a popular bar and deli offering healthy snacks. Doubles start at 121 euros. Children under 12 stay free.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat  Street food, like the Turkish döner kebab, a sandwich of lamb or veal stuffed into sesame bread with salad, usually costs around 2.50 euros. Or try Berlin's famous currywurst, a grilled sausage smothered in ketchup and curry powder, for about the same price. Stands are everywhere.</p>
        <p>Don't miss the latest Berliner fad -- Sunday brunch. Many cafes offer all-you-can-eat buffets for less than 10 euros per person. Try Frida Kahlo (Lychener Strasse 37; 49-30-445-7016), a Mexican restaurant in the trendy Prenzlauer Berg neighborhood (about 8.50 euros a person). Further west, Die Zwölf Apostel (Bleibtreustrasse 49; 49-30-312-1433, next to the Savignyplatz S-Bahn station) is a bit more expensive but a good value for the huge selection of Italian salads, hearty German meat dishes and slices of stone-oven pizza. (About 15 euros a person including a hot drink and a glass of prosecco. Children are 7.50 euros. Reservations on Sunday are a must.)</p>
        <p>Where to Shop  For citywide deals, visit in January or July. Clothing stores slash prices up to 60 percent during their seasonal clearance sales.</p>
        <p>Best Money-Saving Tip  Easy-on-the-wallet choices include a walk along the Spree River. With renovations to the river walls now mostly complete, this pleasant stroll takes you past some of the city's important landmarks and modern architecture. If it's too cold or rainy to walk, take your guidebook and jump on the fast train line that runs above the city and takes in many of the same sights. Or head for the Sony Center, worth a visit in itself for its soaring futuristic architecture. English language movies are only 4.50 euros on Tuesdays. And if you plan to hit a few museums, consider buying a three-day SchauLust pass, available at hotels and city museums for 15 euros.</p>
        <p>Finally, Berlin can seem exhausting at times, but the peace of the country is just a 25-minute train ride from Mitte. Take the S1 to Schlachtensee for a 4.20 euro round trip. Take your bathing suit and a towel. Schlachtensee, a narrow lake surrounded by woods, is a treasure in the southwestern outskirts of the city. Get off the train and cross the road to the free sunbathing lawn. Turn left and walk 10 minutes to reach the boathouse, where you can rent a rowboat for a lazy outing. Or turn right and walk for 20 minutes to reach the Alte Fischerhütte beer garden where you can sit at picnic tables and eat sausages or roast chicken and drink vats of German beer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
