<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tennis In a Parking Lot</title>
    <meta content="sport22" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Education Life Supplement" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/education/edlife/sport22.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842070"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="COMMUNITY COLLEGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Scholarships and Fellowships</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grading of Students</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Admissions Standards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Scholarships and Fellowships</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Scholarships and Fellowships</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E5DF1F3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2535" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tennis In a Parking Lot</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tennis in a Parking Lot</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robert Andrew Powell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Powell, Robert Andrew</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANTHONY CLARKE played his high school basketball for Holy Cross in Queens, in one of the more competitive athletic conferences in the country. He's used to dribbling and shooting in front of an audience. Now, a few years later, in his sophomore season at Broward Community College, Mr. Clarke has adapted to the sound of silence.</p>
        <p>During warm-ups for a recent away game at Miami-Dade College, Mr. Clarke and his fellow Seahawks run a layup drill in a cavernous and largely empty gym. I walk in without having to buy a ticket, which I couldn't get away with even in high school. Immediately before tipoff, as the last notes of the national anthem fade, I count 33 fans in the yellow plastic bleachers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Juco sports may be unsung, but players can get a boost to the next level. Isn’t that what junior college is all about?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANTHONY CLARKE played his high school basketball for Holy Cross in Queens, in one of the more competitive athletic conferences in the country. He's used to dribbling and shooting in front of an audience. Now, a few years later, in his sophomore season at Broward Community College, Mr. Clarke has adapted to the sound of silence.</p>
        <p>During warm-ups for a recent away game at Miami-Dade College, Mr. Clarke and his fellow Seahawks run a layup drill in a cavernous and largely empty gym. I walk in without having to buy a ticket, which I couldn't get away with even in high school. Immediately before tipoff, as the last notes of the national anthem fade, I count 33 fans in the yellow plastic bleachers.</p>
        <p>''You just have to motivate yourself,'' says Mr. Clarke, 20, of the turnout, which is fairly typical at this level of college sports.</p>
        <p>Soon enough, the Miami-Dade Sharks are leading 20-3, a rout that prompts me to focus on the sounds of the game. Without cheerleaders -- or cheers, for that matter -- I hear the squeak of sneakers. There's a percussive pop when a passed ball lands in waiting hands and a groan after a steal attempt backfires, leading to an easy basket for the other team.</p>
        <p>''Look inside you, Ryan!'' shouts Bob Starkman, head coach at Broward, a two-year college just outside Fort Lauderdale, Fla. ''Carlos, go where we just told you!'' Every word Mr. Starkman says is audible across the court. It's shockingly intimate, like watching a command performance.</p>
        <p>''Match up, match up, match up,'' Mr. Starkman exhorts his players. ''Match! Up!''</p>
        <p>College sports conjure up images of tailgate parties and boosters and, at the highest level, championship tournaments on national television -- not commuter schools whose students have day jobs and children waiting at home. Intercollegiate athletics at junior colleges (jucos, as they're known in sports vernacular) are largely anonymous, followed mostly by recruitniks and other talent obsessives. There's an ice hockey team hidden at Erie Community College in Buffalo, basketball at Lawson State Community College in Birmingham, Ala., and fast-pitch softball at the College of Southern Idaho.</p>
        <p>Even the most successful football teams play under the national radar, in bowl games like the Graphic Edge Printing Bowl in Cedar Falls, Iowa, or the Zions Bank Top of the Mountains Bowl in Salt Lake City. The Blinn Buccaneers in Texas won the junior college national championship last year in the Pilgrim's Pride Bowl, playing in front of about 5,000 fans. Revenues from the entire season didn't come close to offsetting the costs of fielding the team.</p>
        <p>But juco sports aren't exactly intramural activities.</p>
        <p>Community colleges like Blinn (for football) and Indian Hills in Iowa (basketball) are established powers feeding talent to the Division I level of the National Collegiate Athletic Association. The Jayhawk Community College Conference in Kansas is another basketball hotbed. Among community college alumni who have gone on to professional sports are Albert Pujols of the St. Louis Cardinals, who played for Maple Woods Community College, in Missouri; the Carolina Panthers wide receiver Steve Smith, who attended Santa Monica Junior College, in California, and Ben Wallace of the Chicago Bulls, who attended Cuyahoga Community College, in Ohio.</p>
        <p>In some ways, the juco transfer tradition echoes the typical academic transfer: students hope to improve grades that are too low for university admissions or to strengthen skills for a sweeter offer from a prestigious four-year institution.</p>
        <p>Greg Hinze, the athletic director at Blinn, is blunt: ''We provide an opportunity to those kids who don't meet N.C.A.A. academic requirements, to enable them to continue academic careers. Whether right or wrong, a lot of them wouldn't go to college if athletic avenues weren't available to them.''</p>
        <p>But if the job of a community college is to ''fill the gap,'' in the words of Willis Holcombe, president of Broward Community College, it is just not that simple when athletes are involved.</p>
        <p>In a report last year by two professors at Western Carolina University, 88 community college presidents in six states were questioned on the role of intercollegiate athletics at two-year colleges. They concurred that sports can foster community and school pride, diversify the student body and bolster enrollment, though there were complaints that recruits were often ''poorly prepared academically,'' denting a school's reputation.</p>
        <p>The presidents, who headed colleges both with and without sports programs, disagreed significantly on one point: whether competitive sports teams support their core mission.</p>
        <p>FINDING Broward Community College is a challenge. Its general location, inside a complex called the South Florida Education Center, is easy enough to pinpoint. But it's not so easy to differentiate Broward from the other schools on the campus. Sharing acres of parking lots and traffic speed bumps with the community college are a branch of Florida Atlantic University, a branch of the University of Florida, a technology center and the main campus of Nova Southeastern University.</p>
        <p>At Broward, men can play baseball and basketball, while women can choose among basketball, softball, volleyball and tennis.</p>
        <p>Hunting for the tennis team, I find six players and a coach on a set of concrete courts that are in a parking lot, of course; the parking crunch is recurring front-page news in the student paper. Broward's tennis team won a national championship last year, its third title in four years. The four women who graduated took scholarships, to Nova Southeastern, the University of Miami and the University of California, Santa Barbara. A row of small steel signs hanging on a chain-link fence lists tennis all-Americans back to 1983. Also honored are all the individual national champions, four in 1990 alone.</p>
        <p>I sit in one of two small aluminum bleachers. Alyona Tsutskova launches into a game of doubles with three teammates. A couple years ago, she played doubles in a tournament at Roland Garros, the famous stadium in Paris. She held an international ranking then, and it looked like tennis would open the world to her. She lived at a residential tennis academy in Miami, half a world away from her native Ukraine. She dreamed of turning professional. Then she hurt her back.</p>
        <p>Now, at 21, her goals are more modest. She wants a scholarship to play tennis at a Division I college. First, she needs to improve her grades -- she is studying business administration after years of being singularly focused on tennis. Then she needs to get the attention of a Division I coach somewhere.</p>
        <p>''Everyone here has had some time when they had to face reality,'' says LeTrone Mason, the coach. Mr. Mason is sitting next to me on the bleachers, winding a spongy grip onto Ms. Tsutskova's backup racket. ''They don't get down, because they know the level of tennis here is still good, and they know I can help them get to the next level.''</p>
        <p>Money is tight at Broward, as it is at almost every junior college. The National Junior College Athletic Association, the governing body everywhere but California, which operates its own system, advises member schools to ''justify your athletic department.'' Athletic directors are steered to forms that show how to list the number of conference titles won, the number of players who have advanced to Division I programs and other accomplishments.</p>
        <p>Junior college athletic departments, like many at four-year institutions, do not receive public funds. But with hardly any collecting revenue from television or radio rights, merchandise or tickets, teams don't pay for themselves. Cash is needed to travel to away games, to outfit the players, to maintain the facilities and to hire coaches.</p>
        <p>At Broward, student activity fees finance the sports. The fee, about $5 a credit hour, is set by a board made up of students, who want the lowest fees possible, and administrators, who generally favor extracurricular activities.</p>
        <p>''We try to encourage them to be ecumenical in their thinking,'' says Dr. Holcombe. ''Even though the average age of our students is 28, a lot of students come to us right out of high school. These students are 19 or 20 years old, and a number of them want to have some kind of normal campus life.''</p>
        <p>What constitutes a ''normal campus life'' varies greatly. While Broward's parking lots and concrete classrooms are about as physically attractive as a strip mall, the campus of Tyler Junior College offers leafy landscaping and on-campus housing for up to 600 students. Tyler's team, in football-rich Texas, plays in a dedicated stadium. At halftime during home games, the Tyler Apache Band marches across the field, accompanied by the Apache Belles, the college's precision dance team since 1947.</p>
        <p>''Tyler is turning into a first-choice college for some kids,'' says Mike Marquis, head coach of its men's basketball team. ''Kids are coming here over some four-year institutions just because it's so nice.''</p>
        <p>Modesto Junior College in California fields teams in 21 sports, serving 400 athletes from a student population of more than 18,000. The football and baseball teams are very competitive, says the athletic director, William Kaiser. A tight end on Modesto's football team went on to play for the University of Utah on scholarship. Other athletes have had their tuition picked up by less prominent colleges, such as the University of Mary in Bismarck, N.D.</p>
        <p>While juco coaches have no problem luring strong players for football, basketball and baseball, less mainstream sports present challenges rarely seen in Division I. For example, and in large part to comply with Title IX legislation, Modesto fields a golf team that is stocked with middle-aged women who are taking a few academic units just so they can play golf.</p>
        <p>''People say, 'How come our teams are always old women?' '' Mr. Kaiser says. ''I tell them it's because old women are the only ones we can find to play. Few high schools in the area are feeding us younger players.''</p>
        <p>Anthony Clarke, the basketball player from Queens, wound up at Broward after playing in a high school tournament in South Florida and warming to the palm trees and sunny weather. Without the grades or court skills to interest a four-year college, he still realized his dream of playing college ball, and on scholarship, too. Coach Starkman, who hails from New York and remains connected to the city game, lured Mr. Clarke and four other New Yorkers. His team ended the season with a winning record, 18-13.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clarke assesses his athletic potential realistically. ''I don't hope to play for a Division I school necessarily,'' he says. ''I just want to play the most competitive basketball I can.''</p>
        <p>Last year, 29 athletes from various Broward teams moved on to Division I or II schools with scholarships.</p>
        <p>The talent pipelines that flow between two-year colleges and Division I programs are well established. Big-time schools often urge academically challenged recruits to attend a community college to get grades up to admissions standards. Coaches at the two-year colleges, in turn, can use these relationships to get their players to the next level. Kevin Ferguson, a wide receiver who signed with Texas A&amp;M out of high school, redshirted at Blinn last season. Colby Renfro, a linebacker on the A&amp;M spring football roster, is a Blinn transfer.</p>
        <p>But the system is sometimes corrupted. Pick a year at random and you can find some scandal: 2003, St. Bonaventure (for admitting a junior college basketball player with only a welding degree); 1994, Baylor University (for rigging test scores of five junior college basketball recruits). Last year, coaches at Barton County Community College, in Great Bend, Kan., were sentenced to jail time for paying players for outside work they didn't perform and for sanitizing transcripts.</p>
        <p>Such examples are the exception. Of some 530 members of the junior college association, 16 are on probation for various violations. An association spokesman says it randomly audits players' transcripts (1.75 G.P.A. required first semester, then 2.0) and for eligibility. Athletes must be enrolled full time and can play only two years.</p>
        <p>More than a few players have used two-year colleges as a mere way station. The superstar wide receiver Chad Johnson, of the Cincinnati Bengals, came out of high school in Florida lacking the grades to play for Division I powers like Florida State or Miami. His focus, he once told ESPN, was football -- ''The academic part wasn't important to me.'' After washing out at a small university in Oklahoma, he landed at the two-year Santa Monica College. There, with the personal oversight of his head coach, his grades rose enough to get him accepted at Oregon State, where he played just a year before turning pro.</p>
        <p>Most student athletes get an extra assist, from coaches who try to keep them on task and from dedicated academic advisers. Broward athletes who are at risk of falling behind are also required to attend study halls, Dr. Holcombe says. They graduate and transfer out with better rates than nonathletes (38 and 23 percent compared with 22 and 18 percent, of students enrolled in fall 2003).</p>
        <p>Anthony Clarke says he attends two to three classes a day, taking five to six classes a semester. His major is liberal arts. ''It's fair,'' he says of the workload. ''Obviously, any school you go to you have to study to pass. Nobody's giving me my grades.''</p>
        <p>A JUMBO jet descending into the Fort Lauderdale airport roars above the tennis court, drawing Coach Mason's eyes skyward. ''Looks like we beat the rain,'' he says, no doubt tempting the clouds to open. As thick gray clouds hover, he explains that to build a competitive tennis team he is forced to recruit beyond the community B.C.C. serves.</p>
        <p>By the very nature of the college -- the student body turns over every two years -- the success of the tennis team goes largely unnoticed.</p>
        <p>He looks locally first, though he reserves two roster spots each season for international players, the maximum allowed by national rules. The local players tend to be a harder sell.</p>
        <p>In letters to prospective team members, he will offer to pay tuition, room and board, which admittedly isn't much: about $70 a credit for Florida residents, $242 for out-of-state students. A limited number of athletes are lodged at apartments rented by the college. He will also spell out the advantages of a college education, emphasizing how Broward can be a steppingstone to a Division I school.</p>
        <p>''I pitch them in letters and in phone calls,'' says Mr. Mason, who aspires to set up his own tennis academy. ''I tell them we've won national championships and this and that, but most of them I don't hear back from again. Everyone has this misconception about community college tennis -- that it's not good, that they're better than that. But I'm telling you, our team could have beat a lot of Division I teams last year.'' Last month, it did just that, winning a scrimmage against Seton Hall of New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Fat rain drops now dot the green concrete courts, and Mr. Mason calls practice, excusing his team from conditioning drills. Scurrying over to the bleachers, the players zip their rackets into vinyl covers and grab their plastic jugs of drinking water. Saying quick goodbyes, they dart off to the parking lot. National champions at a commuter school, racing to their cars.</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY COLLEGE Robert Andrew Powell is author of ''We Own This Game: A Season in the Adult World of Youth Football.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Robert Andrew Powell is author of ''We Own This Game: A Season in the Adult World of Youth Football.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
