<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Drying Out After a 'Tale of Two Storms'</title>
    <meta content="22weekctCN-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842319"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rell, M Jodi (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holtz, Jeff</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maker, Elizabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spiegel, Jan Ellen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E1DE173EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="710" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Drying Out After a 'Tale of Two Storms'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF HOLTZ, ELIZABETH MAKER and JAN ELLEN SPIEGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Maker, Elizabeth; Holtz, Jeff; Spiegel, Jan Ellen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Connecticut Gov M Jodi Rell seeks federal disaster relief in wake of northeaster; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the state bailed out, dried out and put things back where they belonged after last week's northeaster, it was clear that location was everything in determining how communities fared.</p>
        <p>''I would call it a tale of two storms,'' said Wayne Sandford, the deputy commissioner of the State Department of Emergency Management and Homeland Security, who helped coordinate storm response from the Hartford Armory. ''In western Connecticut it's a flooding issue, and in eastern Connecticut it's a wind issue.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the state bailed out, dried out and put things back where they belonged after last week's northeaster, it was clear that location was everything in determining how communities fared.</p>
        <p>''I would call it a tale of two storms,'' said Wayne Sandford, the deputy commissioner of the State Department of Emergency Management and Homeland Security, who helped coordinate storm response from the Hartford Armory. ''In western Connecticut it's a flooding issue, and in eastern Connecticut it's a wind issue.''</p>
        <p>The southwestern part of the state got most of the rain -- up to 8 inches was reported -- causing rivers to overflow and closing scores of roads. In midwest Connecticut, sandbags were used to reinforce the Long Meadow Pond dam in Bethlehem after water started flowing over the top, threatening Bethlehem, Woodbury and Southbury.</p>
        <p>''We haven't had this kind of flooding experience in probably 25 years,'' said Raymond G. Baldwin, the first selectman of Trumbull, where the Pequonnock River overflowed. He said he would not be surprised if the damage was ''well over $1 million.''</p>
        <p>Among the major rivers that overflowed were the Housatonic, Still, Saugatuck, Norwalk, Quinnipiac, Farmington, Naugatuck, Mill, Rooster and Connecticut. Surges of runoff from the heavy rains and snow to the north continued to flow downstream.</p>
        <p>''The Still River is running like rapids,'' Gov. M. Jodi Rell said after touring the western part of the state on Monday. ''I have never seen that much water coming out of the Still River, and I've been here 35 years.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Rell, who was seeking federal disaster relief, called the situation ''devastating'' after seeing propane tanks drifting down street near Jensen's Mobile Home Park in Danbury.</p>
        <p>Bill Jacquemin, the director and chief meteorologist at the Connecticut Weather Center in Danbury, said flooding of that magnitude occurred in the state ''once every 25 years.''</p>
        <p>''Because of the wet fall and winter we had, the ground was completely filled with water,'' he said. ''There wasn't room for any more rain to fit between the soil.''</p>
        <p>Over 18 hours, starting at noon Sunday, as much as 7.7 inches of rain fell in Brookfield, 7.3 inches in New Hartford and 6.8 inches in Stamford.</p>
        <p>At midweek, the Housatonic was as high as eight feet over flood stage at the Stevenson Dam on the border between Derby and Monroe, and the Connecticut River was at least seven feet over in Hartford and Middletown, the Weather Center said.</p>
        <p>In New Milford, the Housatonic looked like a swirling sea of chocolate syrup from Veterans Memorial Bridge, which was closed to traffic. Pedestrians could watch errant objects being swept downstream: footballs, soccer balls, folding chairs, giant tree limbs.</p>
        <p>As of Wednesday afternoon, part of Route 7 was still underwater and three other town roads were closed indefinitely, said Michael Zarba, the city's public works director.</p>
        <p>He estimated it would cost $150,000 ''just to get the roads back to being passable,'' but he could not say how much it would cost for other repairs -- ''fix the curbs, the parks that were devastated, everything else.''</p>
        <p>''It's sort of mind-boggling,'' he said.</p>
        <p>New Milford's deputy police chief, Norbert Lillis, said the town had set up a shelter at the local center for teenagers, but only two people had showed up. ''Everyone else went to stay with family or friends,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Coastal areas on Long Island Sound fared a little better than expected because of slightly lower winds, which held down tidal surges. Still, Fairfield, Westport and other coastal communities had to evacuate some residents near the beaches.</p>
        <p>In eastern Connecticut, the wind took down dozens of electrical wires, poles and trees, which were especially vulnerable because of the rain-soaked ground. While some 50,000 customers lost power throughout the state, the worst of it was in the east.</p>
        <p>''You could literally draw a line down the middle of the state,'' said Mitch Gross, a spokesman for Connecticut Light and Power.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jacquemin warned that the state could face even more trouble with flooding this summer if the amount of water in the ground remained high and another storm hit.</p>
        <p>''All of our dams could get a real test in mid- to late summer,'' he said.</p>
        <p>JEFF HOLTZ, ELIZABETH MAKER and JAN ELLEN SPIEGEL</p>
        <p>THE WEEK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
