<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Who Should Fix the Chimney In a Brownstone Co-op?</title>
    <meta content="22qa" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842121"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Q &amp; A"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Q and A</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2D91F3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="649" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Who Should Fix the Chimney In a Brownstone Co-op?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAY ROMANO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q. We live in a co-op in a 100-year-old brownstone with several apartments on four floors. The fireplace in the apartment on the first floor appears to have a leak in the chimney so that fumes escape into the adjacent apartment and the common area. The owner has agreed to stop using the fireplace until it is fixed. Who should pay for this repair?</p>
        <p>A. ''The first step in solving this problem is to determine what is wrong and how it can be fixed,'' said Howard Schechter, a Manhattan co-op lawyer. He said that under most proprietary leases, anything visible in the apartment (other than standard heating equipment like radiators) is the shareholder's responsibility and anything behind the walls, floor or ceiling (with the exception of electrical wiring and certain plumbing connections) is the co-op corporation's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q. We live in a co-op in a 100-year-old brownstone with several apartments on four floors. The fireplace in the apartment on the first floor appears to have a leak in the chimney so that fumes escape into the adjacent apartment and the common area. The owner has agreed to stop using the fireplace until it is fixed. Who should pay for this repair?</p>
        <p>A. ''The first step in solving this problem is to determine what is wrong and how it can be fixed,'' said Howard Schechter, a Manhattan co-op lawyer. He said that under most proprietary leases, anything visible in the apartment (other than standard heating equipment like radiators) is the shareholder's responsibility and anything behind the walls, floor or ceiling (with the exception of electrical wiring and certain plumbing connections) is the co-op corporation's.</p>
        <p>Under most proprietary leases, the co-op is responsible for all ''equipment and apparatus'' in the building, he said, unless the responsibility is specifically passed on to the shareholder. ''Under this typical language, a chimney probably would be the responsibility of the co-op,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The more difficult question, he said, is whether the co-op board has the authority to refuse to do the repair and to direct the owner to repair the chimney himself or stop using the fireplace.</p>
        <p>''It might be argued that the board may exercise its business judgment on whether to make the repair,'' he said. ''I have been unable to find a case in which a court has been asked to rule on this precise question, but there is a good chance that the board will be required to perform the repair and cannot use the business judgment rule to avoid it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schechter said that before positions get too entrenched, it probably makes sense to have an engineer or architect determine what is wrong. ''It is usually best to know how much you are talking about to repair a problem before becoming overly concerned with who has to pay,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Can a Landlord Ask For Personal Information?</p>
        <p>Q. I have been asked to submit an affidavit giving the names and relationship of everyone who lives in my apartment. Not only does this seem unusual, since I have never been asked for this before, but they also want my Social Security number. Must I submit this information if I am a rent-stabilized tenant?</p>
        <p>My building was sold two years ago to a company that is now asking about tenants' interest in being bought out. Could this personal information help them get rid of me?</p>
        <p>A. ''The New York City Housing Maintenance Code provides that upon the landlord's request, the tenant must submit an affidavit setting forth the names and relationship of all occupants residing within an apartment," said Alan Kucker, a Manhattan real estate lawyer who represents landlords. "And a landlord will usually request a Social Security number so that the interest on the tenant's security deposit is properly attributed."</p>
        <p>Since the building changed hands two years ago, and since the tenant apparently had not provided a Social Security number to the former landlord, it is understandable that the new owner is requesting it. But there is at least one court case that holds that a tenant has no legal obligation to provide a Social Security number to a landlord.</p>
        <p>So, Mr. Kucker said, while the letter writer must provide the affidavit the landlord is asking for, it may be possible to withhold the Social Security number. If the tenant does so, however, there is a possibility that the landlord could try to force the issue by taking the tenant to court.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kucker said that as long as the tenant had not violated the lease or the rent stabilization law, the landlord should not be able to evict her based on the information being requested.</p>
        <p>JAY ROMANO</p>
        <p>Q &amp; A</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
