<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hoping to Curb Drug Trade at a Housing Complex, the Newark Police Move In</title>
    <meta content="22newark" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/22newark.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842274"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Newark (NJ)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E0DF173EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="566" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hoping to Curb Drug Trade at a Housing Complex, the Newark Police Move In</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hoping to Curb Drug Trade at a Housing Complex, the Newark Police Move In</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREEM FAHIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fahim, Kareem</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, April 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One man, in all seriousness, asked whether President Bush was here.</p>
        <p>Here is Pennington Court, a public housing project in Newark's East Ward. And the man's question was not totally unreasonable, given what he and other residents saw in the courtyard early Saturday: police officers on horseback, on motorcycles and in a helicopter, along with a mobile police tower that can lift a watchful officer up to 24 feet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Police officers will remain in the courtyard of an East Ward housing project indefinitely, 24 hours a day, trying to edge out the dealers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One man, in all seriousness, asked whether President Bush was here.</p>
        <p>Here is Pennington Court, a public housing project in Newark's East Ward. And the man's question was not totally unreasonable, given what he and other residents saw in the courtyard early Saturday: police officers on horseback, on motorcycles and in a helicopter, along with a mobile police tower that can lift a watchful officer up to 24 feet.</p>
        <p>The arrival of the officers was part of an eight-month investigation into the illegal narcotics trade at the housing project, conducted by the Newark police, the federal Drug Enforcement Administration and others. Knocking on doors before the sun rose on Saturday, the police made 21 arrests. In recent days, they also arrested Simmied Tut, 41, whom officials called the ringleader of the local drug trade.</p>
        <p>The drug raid, which also targeted narcotics distributors in Pennsylvania, was named after Mr. Tut and the housing project where the police said he ran his business: Operation King and His Court.</p>
        <p>If the snappy name conjured images of yet another inner-city drug raid, officials said this one was different: Most important, the police officers will remain in the courtyard indefinitely, 24 hours a day, trying to edge out the dealers.</p>
        <p>A page of mug shots -- of men arrested in the raid, and men who are still wanted -- was passed around the basketball court as if it were a celebrity magazine.</p>
        <p>''They got Abdul? The fat one?'' said one woman in her 50s, referring to Abdul Oliver, who is known as Butch and who the police allege was Mr. Tut's second in command. The woman, who refused to give her name, tapped a grill next to her. ''This is his barbecue,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In the summer, residents said, the dealers cook for some of the 260 families living here, and give the children money for ice cream. And when Carlos Denizac and his family dress up and go to church, three times a week, the dealers are respectful, he said, momentarily moving their trade out of the family's view.</p>
        <p>But for every resident who spoke of the drug dealers' largess, there were others who talked about how bad the situation had become. Even Mr. Denizac said he welcomed the police presence. The question for him, and others, was how long the officers would stay at the Court, as the complex of three-story red brick buildings is known.</p>
        <p>''We're not going to walk away until it's done,'' said Garry F. McCarthy, Newark's police director, who promised in January, after announcing the formation of a new narcotics squad, that he would reclaim parts of the city from drug dealers.</p>
        <p>To go with the police presence, the Newark Housing Authority has begun cleaning up Pennington Court, whitewashing graffiti-filled hallways. The strategy is in many ways a throwback to New York City's ''model block'' program, which Mr. McCarthy presided over in the late 1990s in the Washington Heights neighborhood.</p>
        <p>Pennington Court is not the most dangerous of Newark's housing projects, and is surrounded by the residential streets and industrial pockets of the city's Ironbound district. But the drug trade in the Court is stubborn, and the dealers have more staying power than the police, some residents said.</p>
        <p>''The drugs are like cockroaches,'' said Maritza Felix, who said she had served jail time on drug-related charges. ''You're not going to get rid of them.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
