<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Is Finger of Blame Unfairly Pointed At One Group?</title>
    <meta content="22hockey" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/sports/hockey/22hockey.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842267"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY: SUNDAY SHOOTOUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Pittsburgh Penguins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Islanders</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Pittsburgh Penguins</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Yashin, Alexei</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Malkin, Evgeni</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E2DF173EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="959" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Is Finger of Blame Unfairly Pointed At One Group?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Is Finger of Blame Unfairly Pointed at One Group?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF Z. KLEIN and KARL-ERIC REIF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Jeff Z; Reif, Karl-Eric</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is always plenty of blame to go around when a team loses in the playoffs. This postseason, some of that blame has been directed at Russian stars: Ilya Kovalchuk of Atlanta, Alexei Yashin of the Islanders, even the Pittsburgh rookie Evgeni Malkin.</p>
        <p>In the 1970s and '80s, North American coaches, team officials and commentators routinely criticized European players in general for being soft and lacking the character needed for the rugged Stanley Cup playoffs. Although that point of view is rarely heard today, it still has its proponents, like the CBC commentator Don Cherry (who is also working for NBC).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is always plenty of blame to go around when a team loses in the playoffs. This postseason, some of that blame has been directed at Russian stars: Ilya Kovalchuk, Alexei Yashin, and Evgeni Malkin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is always plenty of blame to go around when a team loses in the playoffs. This postseason, some of that blame has been directed at Russian stars: Ilya Kovalchuk of Atlanta, Alexei Yashin of the Islanders, even the Pittsburgh rookie Evgeni Malkin.</p>
        <p>In the 1970s and '80s, North American coaches, team officials and commentators routinely criticized European players in general for being soft and lacking the character needed for the rugged Stanley Cup playoffs. Although that point of view is rarely heard today, it still has its proponents, like the CBC commentator Don Cherry (who is also working for NBC).</p>
        <p>During this season's opening-round series against Buffalo, Yashin was demoted to the fourth line by Islanders Coach Ted Nolan, and his ice time was cut sharply. As the team captain, and as a player accused of underperforming during his years with Ottawa, Yashin was singled out for criticism. He scored no points as the Islanders lost in five games.</p>
        <p>Kovalchuk was also criticized when the Thrashers were swept by the Rangers. He had only one goal and one assist in the four-game series, but no Thrasher scored more than 3 points.</p>
        <p>Malkin was rapped for not scoring a goal in the Penguins' five-game loss to Ottawa, though he had four assists, which was good for a tie for second best in club scoring.</p>
        <p>Whether nationality has anything to do with the criticism of Kovalchuk, Yashin or Malkin is not clear. Mark Gandler, a player agent born in Russia with degrees from there and from New York University and Columbia, said that any bias on the part of commentators came from team officials.</p>
        <p>''Journalists get their information from the coaches,'' Gandler said by telephone. ''If there is any prejudice, it's from the coaching.</p>
        <p>''Many coaches are more comfortable with North American players who are 'safer,' but there are plenty of Russian players, European players, who can play defense, kill penalties -- there are lots of them over there -- but what's scouted, and drafted, the contracts in North America go to the skill players, not the plumbers, so when you need a defensive player, or an 'energy' player, you wind up going to the Canadian because it's a skewed group.''</p>
        <p>Gandler, the founder of International Sports Advisors and the representative for several Russian players, including Yashin, said: ''Russian players, like North American players, are doing the best they can. They sacrifice the body; they all want to win. But it's a team game. You can't put it all on any one player. I frankly do not see any difference whatsoever between Russian, Canadian, Finnish players. No difference at all.''</p>
        <p>Gandler said that Yashin joined the Islanders ''when the team was in complete disarray -- since then, they've made the playoffs five out of six years.''</p>
        <p>But Igor Kuperman, another prominent Russian involved in the business side of the game, says there is no longer bias against Russian players.</p>
        <p>''Those days are long gone,'' said Kuperman, who worked in the front office in Winnipeg and Phoenix from 1991 to 2004 and was an assistant general manager for the 2002 Russian Olympic team. ''I don't believe that's the case, and even if that was the case, if they're really strong athletes, they'd have to battle through it.''</p>
        <p>Kuperman, now a vice president at an international sports statistics company, said that the corps of Russian players in the N.H.L. as a whole was not as strong as it once was. ''After Alexander Ovechkin and Malkin, there aren't that many really good newcomers,'' he said. ''Russians don't really have the leading role in the N.H.L. anymore.''</p>
        <p>Kuperman said that any criticism for Russian players was probably not unfair. ''I'm not a believer in that at all,'' he said. ''Valid or not, they still have to plug away. There are absolutely no excuses.''</p>
        <p>World Championship in Works</p>
        <p>The International Ice Hockey Federation announced Friday that it would stage an expanded European club championship tournament, called the Champions Hockey League, starting in 2008-9. The federation president, René Fasel, also said that plans were being made with the N.H.L. to have the winner and perhaps the runner-up of that competition play an N.H.L. challenger for the world club championship. Those games would take place in late September 2009.</p>
        <p>The Champions Hockey League format, similar to that of soccer's European Champions League, would involve the champions of 16 of Europe's smaller hockey-playing nations in a preliminary stage. At a later stage, the playoff and regular-season champions of the six top nations enter the competition.</p>
        <p>The federation operated a similar champions league from 1996 through 2000, but underfunding and low television interest caused its demise. The new competition, however, will distribute a guaranteed $14 million to participating clubs, with an additional $830,000 going to the winner.</p>
        <p>Fasel said in the announcement that discussions with the N.H.L. for a world club championship were at an advanced stage. ''We believe that together with our partner N.H.L. we have a concept for an annual September showdown,'' Fasel said. ''Also, this competition would carry a substantial financial reward.''</p>
        <p>Usual Suspects Missing</p>
        <p>Of the five teams to reach the postseason most frequently in N.H.L. history, none qualified for the playoffs this spring. The St. Louis Blues, who have made the playoffs in 34 of their 39 years (a rate of 87 percent), missed the cut this season. So did Montreal (75 of 89, 84 percent), Philadelphia (31 of 39, 79 percent), Edmonton (21 of 27, 78 percent) and Boston (62 of 82, 76 percent).</p>
        <p>The team with the highest playoff-appearance rate to make this season's playoffs was the Buffalo Sabres, who have reached the postseason 27 times in their 36 seasons, a rate of 75 percent.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY: SUNDAY SHOOTOUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
