<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Renewal in the Sound</title>
    <meta content="LIsound" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842014"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island Sound</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E7D91E3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="678" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Renewal in the Sound</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial credits government at all levels, advocacy groups and private citizens for improving water quality in Long Island Sound; holds much remains to be done and there is never quite enough money for job</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some people refer to Long Island Sound as the Urban Sea, which by itself is enough to make you nervous. Since colonial days, humans in great numbers have gravitated to its coastal habitats, bringing housing, commerce, recreation and, inevitably, pollution. An estimated 20 million people live within a 50 mile drive of its shores, and 400 years after the first European explorers came to trade with the Indians, people are still moving to the coast, eating up open space, trampling wildlife habitats and paving over land in ways that reduce nature's capacity to filter and clean contaminated runoff.</p>
        <p>The remarkable thing is that the Sound is doing as well as it is; though hemmed in by the densest population area in America, this 110-mile-long body of water has, against all odds, remained one of America's great estuaries, still very much at risk but by no means gasping for life the way Chesapeake Bay is. Water quality has improved, osprey and striped bass, among other species, have made dramatic recoveries, rivers have been opened to provide fish passage and there have even been tiny improvements in restoring wetlands. Credit belongs to governments at all levels, advocacy groups and private citizens; indeed, the entire enterprise is as good an example of regional cooperation as one is likely to find.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Some people refer to Long Island Sound as the Urban Sea, which by itself is enough to make you nervous. Since colonial days, humans in great numbers have gravitated to its coastal habitats, bringing housing, commerce, recreation and, inevitably, pollution. An estimated 20 million people live within a 50 mile drive of its shores, and 400 years after the first European explorers came to trade with the Indians, people are still moving to the coast, eating up open space, trampling wildlife habitats and paving over land in ways that reduce nature's capacity to filter and clean contaminated runoff.</p>
        <p>The remarkable thing is that the Sound is doing as well as it is; though hemmed in by the densest population area in America, this 110-mile-long body of water has, against all odds, remained one of America's great estuaries, still very much at risk but by no means gasping for life the way Chesapeake Bay is. Water quality has improved, osprey and striped bass, among other species, have made dramatic recoveries, rivers have been opened to provide fish passage and there have even been tiny improvements in restoring wetlands. Credit belongs to governments at all levels, advocacy groups and private citizens; indeed, the entire enterprise is as good an example of regional cooperation as one is likely to find.</p>
        <p>But much remains to be done and there is never quite enough money for the job. Water quality in the Sound's urbanized western end remains only fair to poor; the lobster harvest remains perilously low; some tidal marshes are turning into mud flats, for reasons not entirely clear; and water temperature is rising, distressing not only the lobsters but other fish species.</p>
        <p>The main culprit, though not the only one, is nitrogen from urban and agricultural runoff and from the many municipal sewage treatment plants that empty their partially-treated wastewater in the Sound and its tributaries. Nitrogen, useful as fertilizer on land, is fatal to water bodies, where it stimulates the growth of bacteria and algae and robs the water of oxygen.</p>
        <p>In 1994, after considerable prodding from the federal Environmental Protection Agency, New York and Connecticut approved a comprehensive cleanup plan, and, in 1998, set a goal of reducing by 58.5 percent the nitrogen reaching the Sound from waste treatment plants in about 80 communities along the Sound and in New York City.</p>
        <p>The results, so far, have been impressive -- a 25- to 30 percent reduction in nitrogen, roughly speaking, a figure that is sure to improve once an agreement struck last year between New York City and Albany to upgrade four plants along the East River kicks in. These plants produce nearly half the nitrogen that enters the Sound, and it is not stretching things to say that failure to live up to this agreement, which will cost the city at least $700 million, could ruin the entire effort.</p>
        <p>Backsliding by the city would also gravely insult the local communities that, at considerable cost, have tried to reduce their own contribution to the problem. Norwalk and Stamford have been particularly aggressive in upgrading their treatment plants, as have some communities in Nassau County. Westchester, which was lagging behind the others, has become much more active under the leadership of a regional group with a jawbreaking name, The Long Island Sound Watershed Intermunicipal Council, which among other creative ideas is trying to set up a stormwater utility company with the power to raise taxes to retrofit older treatment plants.</p>
        <p>Congress could also help. Two bills approved in recent years await full funding. One is the Long Island Sound Restoration Act, which authorizes $40 million a year over 5 years in matching grants to help modernize treatment plants. The other is the Long Island Sound Stewardship Act, which President Bush signed last October and which provides $25 million a year in matching funds for the acquisition of open space essential to the health of the Sound. Funding these programs would provide not only a financial but psychological boost to the local communities to whom the cleanup job has largely been entrusted.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
