<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Composer Who's Weathered Some Tempests of His Own</title>
    <meta content="22peoplectCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/22peoplect.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842028"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE CREATIVE LIFE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Trio Solisti (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moravec, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shattuck, Kathryn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Depression (Mental)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Depression (Mental)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Moravec, Paul</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E1D61E3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="716" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Composer Who's Weathered Some Tempests of His Own</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Composer Who’s Weathered Some Tempests of His Own</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHRYN SHATTUCK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shattuck, Kathryn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of and interview with Pulitzer Prize-winning composer Paul Moravec, whose work Tempest Fantasy will be performed by Trio Solisti at Westport Arts Center; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THREE years after he won the 2004 Pulitzer Prize for ''Tempest Fantasy,'' the composer Paul Moravec described that meditation on Shakespeare's ''Tempest'' as ''a joyous piece, an optimistic piece that follows the trajectory of Prospero's story.'' It was, he suggested, an allegory for his own life.</p>
        <p>Of course Prospero, sent off to die with his daughter on a remote island, endured no small amount of suffering and hardship before living happily ever after.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The composer Paul Moravec talks about his battle with depression.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THREE years after he won the 2004 Pulitzer Prize for ''Tempest Fantasy,'' the composer Paul Moravec described that meditation on Shakespeare's ''Tempest'' as ''a joyous piece, an optimistic piece that follows the trajectory of Prospero's story.'' It was, he suggested, an allegory for his own life.</p>
        <p>Of course Prospero, sent off to die with his daughter on a remote island, endured no small amount of suffering and hardship before living happily ever after.</p>
        <p>Ay, there's the rub.</p>
        <p>''Coming back from depression, I identified with Prospero and his melancholy and his downcast state,'' Mr. Moravec said. ''Through the power of imagination he improves his condition, and so that's what I did as a composer.''</p>
        <p>On Friday at 8 p.m., ''Tempest Fantasy,'' a 30-minute, five-part work for violin, cello, piano and clarinet, will be performed by Trio Solisti, for whom it was originally conceived, with the clarinetist Alan Kay, in the final concert of the Westport Arts Center's Composers Project. Mr. Moravec will discuss his life and work in a preconcert lecture at 7:30. (Several of Mr. Moravec's works will also be performed in Manhattan at Merkin Hall on April 25 and, from April 30 through May 3, as part of the Contemporary Music Festival at the Mannes school of music, where he is composer in residence).</p>
        <p>As curator of the inaugural season of Westport's Composers Project, Mr. Moravec dissected a range of contemporary composers, from John Corigliano and Fred Hersch to Tania León and Ben Allison, and placed them within the context of their traditions.</p>
        <p>Though he has often been lumped with the so-called new tonalists, who have forsaken dissonant avant-gardism in favor of more traditional harmonies, Mr. Moravec doesn't quite buy that assessment. ''The term 'new tonalist' is a little outdated simply because of the passage of time,'' he said. ''It had more relevance a few decades ago, when late modernism was dying or even dead. For my work, I regard the term only as a point of departure before considering each composition on a case-by-case basis.''</p>
        <p>''As a composer, I try always to make beautiful things, and I use whatever techniques and materials are useful for the particular composition at hand,'' he said. ''Some of those materials are atonal or nontonal, but the overall harmonic context of my music derives from the tonal tradition, which after all is the lingua franca of Western music -- essentially, Monteverdi to the Beatles and beyond.''</p>
        <p>Born in Buffalo and reared in the New York region, Mr. Moravec earned a bachelor's at Harvard and a doctorate in music at Columbia, after which he taught at Harvard, Columbia, Dartmouth and Hunter College while accumulating fellowships from the American Academy in Rome, the National Endowment for the Arts, the Rockefeller Foundation and the American Academy of Arts and Letters. But severe depression marked the stages of his life and reached its apex about the time he ended his term at Dartmouth in 1995. Diagnosed with clinical depression, he underwent electroshock therapy.</p>
        <p>''Afterward, it forces you to focus your attention in ways that might not have been required,'' he said of the treatment. ''I had to basically reinvent my career and my life.''</p>
        <p>In March 2005, emboldened by his Pulitzer as a testament to his functionality, Mr. Moravec publicly revealed his illness for the first time on National Public Radio and at a Bay Area fund-raiser for the severely mentally ill. ''In essence, I came out,'' he said, ''speaking about something very personal, in part because I hoped to help overcome the stigma that attaches to mental illness.''</p>
        <p>Despite the strains of his illness, Mr. Moravec long considered himself prolific. He is even more so now, he said, having composed nearly 90 works for orchestra, chamber ensemble, chorus and film, with an oratorio and an opera -- his first -- in the works. He also holds a professorship at Adelphi University on Long Island, and will be the composer in residence at the Institute for Advanced Study in Princeton for the 2007-8 academic year.</p>
        <p>''I don't know what the alternative reality would have been had I not undergone treatment,'' he said. ''We all get depressed from time to time, but the suffering from clinical depression is unimaginable.''</p>
        <p>''I guess I'm proof,'' he added, ''that you can get help and go on. ''</p>
        <p>THE CREATIVE LIFE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
