<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Poetry Lovers, Coming Through (For) the Rye</title>
    <meta content="22colctCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/22colct.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842048"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Haven (Conn)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atticus Bookstore and Cafe (New Haven, Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hochswender, Woody</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut/New Haven</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Haven (Conn)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506EED61E3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="762" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Poetry Lovers, Coming Through (For) the Rye</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Poetry Lovers, Coming Through (for) the Rye</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WOODY HOCHSWENDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hochswender, Woody</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Woody Hochswender column on popularity of weekly poetry readings this month at Atticus Bookstore and Cafe in New Haven, Conn, in honor of National Poetry Month; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YOU'VE heard of singing for your supper. This is about rhyming for your bread.</p>
        <p>Every Friday this month, which is National Poetry Month, the Atticus Bookstore and Cafe in New Haven has been inviting poets to recite a poem aloud -- theirs or someone else's -- in exchange for a free loaf of bread.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>You’ve heard of singing for your supper. This is about rhyming for your bread.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YOU'VE heard of singing for your supper. This is about rhyming for your bread.</p>
        <p>Every Friday this month, which is National Poetry Month, the Atticus Bookstore and Cafe in New Haven has been inviting poets to recite a poem aloud -- theirs or someone else's -- in exchange for a free loaf of bread.</p>
        <p>And you thought you couldn't make any dough with poetry.</p>
        <p>On a recent Friday, there was no shortage of hungry bards. Some came from area high schools or Yale University, which looms stony and gothic across the street. They read everything from Dante to Dr. Seuss. A steady stream of poets, many of whom had that perfect lean, impecunious look, straggled up to the podium, rang a little pushbell, then gave and received nourishment.</p>
        <p>Haley Keane, 16, a student at Newtown High School and Educational Center for the Arts, recited her own poem, ''White Girls'' -- ''White girls/With pretty curls/Little dogs that squeak/Diamond encrusted/Bulletproof vested/Stiletto wearing/Cellphone bearing/White girls'' -- kind of a spiky ode to the Paris Hilton-Ashley Olsen-Britney Spears set.</p>
        <p>There was quite a lot of youthful angst, harsh words about corporate America and free verse visions of apocalypse and gloom, the kind of poetry that makes the hairs on the back of your neck do the lambada.</p>
        <p>From Emily Oliver, 18, who also attends Newtown High:</p>
        <p>A dead earth will still twirl on its axis</p>
        <p>It will follow a path around the sun</p>
        <p>After it's suffocated under the</p>
        <p>Dark, dead weight of the New American dream.</p>
        <p>Then there was a ''team'' poem, ''Stanford and Brown,'' about anxiety of college admissions, recited alternately by Ms. Oliver and Samuel Cunningham, 18, of Wilbur Cross High School:</p>
        <p>We regret to inform you we cannot offer you admission this year.</p>
        <p>We regret to inform you your poetry did not catch our ear.</p>
        <p>We did not hear your pleas, your sighs, or your screams.</p>
        <p>We regret to inform you we found another kid with a pocketbook bursting at the seams.</p>
        <p>While poets recited, there were the occasional sounds of silverware crashing and coffee cups clattering in the cafe. The audience applauded politely after each reading.</p>
        <p>Jennifer Drury, 32, a middle-school English teacher from Hamden, recited her composition ''The Book of Ruth.'' When memory failed in spots, she got prompting from the subject of the poem, Ruth Carruth (whose name, it should be noted, contains an internal rhyme).</p>
        <p>''Yes, I am that Ruth,'' Ms. Carruth said. ''It's one of my favorite poems.''</p>
        <p>As night fell, a tall, ascetic-looking young man in a shabby herringbone tweed coat and black beret, looking like a character out of Dostoyevsky, began to recite at length, from memory, in Italian:</p>
        <p>Spesse fiate vegnonmi a la mente</p>
        <p>Le oscure qualità ch'Amor mi dona</p>
        <p>Or something like that. This was, in case you forgot, Sonnet 16, from Dante's ''La Vita Nuova.'' For the man who read it, Martin Devecka, 23, a doctoral student in Renaissance literature at Yale, reciting medieval poetry from memory is a mere bagatelle -- for which he received a baguette. ''I'm hungry,'' he said, as he accepted his cranberry loaf. And he looked it.</p>
        <p>His was not the only non-English offering. A dark-haired woman declaimed, lyrically, in Spanish, from ''Romance Sonámbulo,'' by Federico García Lorca. The reader, Jennifer Roberts, was one of several Yale law students in attendance. In fact, the room was crawling with future litigators.</p>
        <p>Paul Beaton, 30, a student at the law school and the school of environmental studies and forestry, read a timely selection from ''A Shropshire Lad'' by A. E. Housman (''Loveliest of trees, the cherry now/Is hung with bloom along the bough ''). Regan Kirk, 19, another first-year law student, read Robert Frost's ''Acquainted With the Night.''</p>
        <p>Looking on with evident satisfaction was Charles J. Negaro, the owner of the bookstore and the Chabaso Bakery, which donated the bread. ''I'm not sure I ever appreciated poetry before like I did here today,'' he said. Asked if poetry sold well in his store, Mr. Negaro replied, ''No, not really.''</p>
        <p>The store just likes to sponsor unusual fun events, he said. On Election Day, they gave bread to anyone who voted.</p>
        <p>The last of the bread-for-poetry readings is this Friday, with open reading from 8 a.m. on, and a formal reading at 7 p.m. by a distinguished group of poets, including Vivian Shipley, the editor of The Connecticut Review, and Marilyn Nelson, the former state poet laureate.</p>
        <p>''It made them happy,'' Mr. Negaro said of the poets. ''They recited a poem, I gave them a loaf of bread, and they were so happy.''</p>
        <p>E-mail:conn@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail:conn@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
