<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Fresh Start for the Stanhope</title>
    <meta content="22Deal1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/realestate/22Deal1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842113"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BIG DEAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theaters (Buildings)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playhouse 91 (NYC Theater)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Stanhope Hotel (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Buildings Department (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Full Gospel New York Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barbanel, Josh</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swig, Kent M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/The Big Deal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E5D91F3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1476" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Fresh Start for the Stanhope</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Fresh Start for the Stanhope</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSH BARBANEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barbanel, Josh</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Newly renovated Stanhope Hotel, now luxury co-op building being marketed by address, 995 Broadway, has opened doors to prospective buyers of its 26 apartments; Buildings Dept revokes preliminary approval given in 2006 to developer Kent Swig that would have allowed him to piggyback nine-story condominium on top of two prewar six-story tenements at 201 West 92nd Street and 200 West 93rd Street; 316 East 91st Street, known as Playhouse 91 and home to Off Broadway theater companies, will continue to function as theater; building was sold on April 2 to Full Gospel New York Church, which says it has plans to renovate structure and rent it out as theater for foreseeable future; photos (Big Deal column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS April showers taper off and the spring real estate season unfolds, there is new hope for the developers of the project that until recently was known as the Stanhope, the former Stanhope Hotel just across Fifth Avenue from the Metropolitan Museum of Art.</p>
        <p>Now, just in time for the year's peak selling season, the property -- where the duplex penthouse is priced at $47.5 million, and a 4,200-square-foot half-floor apartment on a lower floor starts at $10.25 million -- has undergone a marketing makeover. It is now being marketed by its address, 995 Fifth Avenue, and two large, luxuriously finished model apartments have been created on the fifth floor, connected by an elegant lobby of wood and intricately carved stone floors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just in time for the year’s peak selling season, the property just across Fifth Avenue from the Metropolitan Museum of Art has undergone a marketing makeover.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS April showers taper off and the spring real estate season unfolds, there is new hope for the developers of the project that until recently was known as the Stanhope, the former Stanhope Hotel just across Fifth Avenue from the Metropolitan Museum of Art.</p>
        <p>Now, just in time for the year's peak selling season, the property -- where the duplex penthouse is priced at $47.5 million, and a 4,200-square-foot half-floor apartment on a lower floor starts at $10.25 million -- has undergone a marketing makeover. It is now being marketed by its address, 995 Fifth Avenue, and two large, luxuriously finished model apartments have been created on the fifth floor, connected by an elegant lobby of wood and intricately carved stone floors.</p>
        <p>The model apartments -- one traditional with deep plaster moldings, the other with a modern twist -- were designed to solve one of the tricky marketing problems that has bedeviled the project since it was approved for sale in the fall of 2005. This was the fear that the small rooms and eight-foot ceilings of the Stanhope Hotel, designed by Rosario Candela in 1926, would not measure up to the standards of other prewar co-ops that surround it.</p>
        <p>''People have been waiting to see the finished project and take a test drive,'' said Beth Fisher, a senior managing director at the Corcoran Sunshine Marketing Group.</p>
        <p>The apartments, which went on display last week, have interiors by the British architect John Simpson, and interior decorating and design by Eric Cohler. The old dropped ceilings of the Stanhope have been pulled down, beams unveiled, ceiling plate exposed and decorated in layers of plaster panels and molding to create a sense of depth and spaciousness. Ceilings top out at nine feet in the center of most rooms.</p>
        <p>The project, developed by the Extell Development Company, went through the unusual step of shutting down its off-site sales office last year when sales stalled after only a few of the 26 apartments in the 17-story building had gone into contract. Rather than cutting prices, ranging from about $2,800 to $3,000 a square foot, the developers hurried to complete the model apartments.</p>
        <p>But while they installed huge mahogany entry doors and granite and marble counters at 995 Fifth Avenue, the market has not stood still. Ask Kathy Sloane, a broker at Brown Harris Stevens, who has been marketing a competing building, at 823 Park Avenue, near 75th Street, another prewar building that, like the Stanhope, was gutted down to the bare walls and rebuilt.</p>
        <p>Last month, Ms. Sloane, the top selling broker at Brown Harris Stevens for the last three years, sold 6 condominiums of a total of 12 at 823 Park, with a combined sticker price of $59.6 million. One buyer combined three lower-floor apartments to create an apartment with more than 7,000 square feet of space and a 4,000-square-foot rear garden, she said. Two full-floor apartments are still listed at just over $12 million each.</p>
        <p>''We sold them without an office, without a model apartment, and we broke all price records on Park Avenue,'' she said. ''We sold the building based on location, the fact that they were condominiums, and our personal reputations.''</p>
        <p>Unlike those at 823 Park Avenue, the apartments at the Stanhope are co-ops, but operate without many of the restrictive rules used by traditional co-ops to reject many buyers, like an elaborate board approval process. This was done because the land under the Stanhope is leased, rather than owned, though the developers say they negotiated fixed rental terms covering the next 150 years, to avoid uncertainty.</p>
        <p>Now, Ms. Fisher said, brokers have begun showing the units at 995 Fifth to a list of would-be buyers who wanted to wait until the model apartments were available.</p>
        <p>Contracts for several apartments were out for signing as of late last week, she said, and one prospective buyer inquired about buying a complete model apartment, including the furniture, rugs and artwork.</p>
        <p>Piggyback Condo Faces a Legal Setback</p>
        <p>KENT SWIG, one of the biggest players in the condominium conversion market, has been dealt a setback in an imaginative plan to piggyback a new nine-story condominium on top of two prewar six-story tenements at Amsterdam Avenue and West 92nd and West 93rd Streets.</p>
        <p>After issuing a preliminary approval of the plan last year, the city's Buildings Department ordered an audit, and on April 12 revoked its approval, after receiving complaints from West Side elected officials and tenants in both buildings, who hired an engineer to critique the plans.</p>
        <p>Although a final work permit had never been issued and work had not begun, a red banner proclaims ''Stop Work Order Exists on the Property'' on the Buildings Department's Web site. Kate Lindquist, a Buildings Department spokeswoman, issued a statement saying that there were ''several outstanding objections'' involving both building code and zoning issues.</p>
        <p>''We have been working closely with the community and the applicant to address all concerns surrounding this project,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In the past, many tenant groups have complained that the Buildings Department paid scant attention to their complaints about condo conversions, but in this case, the tenants said the balance was shifting.</p>
        <p>The tenants' association in the two buildings even sent a thank-you letter to the Manhattan borough commissioner. ''We are extremely grateful that the D.O.B. has finally reached the correct result concerning the proposed construction plans for our buildings,'' it said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Swig is a principal in Terra Holdings, the parent company of Brown Harris Stevens and Halstead Property, two large real estate brokerages. He also runs Swig Equities, a development company that is converting two large rental projects to condominiums: the Sheffield on West 57th Street and 25 Broad Street.</p>
        <p>Mr. Swig said that the revocation was not unusual and that steps were being taken to meet the Buildings Department's concerns. ''From what I understand, it is part of the normal review process,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Rather than converting and expanding the two existing buildings. Mr. Swig and his partners proposed that the new nine-story condo would legally be a separate building. It would share elevators and stairs with the existing buildings but would be supported by steel columns that passed through and around them. The two buildings, 201 West 92nd Street and 200 West 93rd Street, would remain as rentals. They have 134 apartments, most of them occupied and about two-thirds with tenants protected by rent-stabilization and rent-control laws.</p>
        <p>Assemblywoman Linda B. Rosenthal, who represents the area and has been working with tenants to halt the development, said the proposal was framed this way to get around a wrinkle in state law. She said that the existing buildings qualify as tenements and that state law sets a height limitation for tenements, preventing new construction if it was part of the same buildings.</p>
        <p>An engineer hired by the tenants, Richard Herschlag, reviewed the plans and argued that the new building was not independent of the old buildings and could not be built without causing dangerous conditions in them.</p>
        <p>The roofs of buildings are the new frontiers of development,'' Ms. Rosenthal said, adding, ''We can't ignore the health and safety of current residents.''</p>
        <p>Playhouse 91 Gets a Reprieve</p>
        <p>AS the residential real estate boom roars through Manhattan, driving up prices for buildings and land, it has had an unfortunate side effect: the closing of a number of small Off Broadway theaters.</p>
        <p>Last June, Playhouse 91, the home to smaller companies like Light Opera of Manhattan, went dark to make way for redevelopment, but now the theater, at 316 East 91st Street, appears to have won a temporary reprieve.</p>
        <p>When the sale of the 299-seat, 50-foot-wide white-brick theater closed on April 2, it turned out that the buyer was not a condo developer, but a huge Pentecostal church, the Full Gospel New York Church, based in Queens.</p>
        <p>The church paid $7.25 million for the playhouse, and while the church officials mull future development, they said they hoped to lease it out as a theater for the foreseeable future.</p>
        <p>''We are at the preliminary stages, and the architects and planners are looking into what is possible,'' said the Rev. David Kim, an associate pastor of what is also known as the Promise Church. ''The plans now are to renovate it as a theater and lease it out.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kim said that the church, which was once in Midtown, had no plans to move its main building back to Manhattan. The Full Gospel church now has two separate sanctuaries in College Point, Queens, seating a total of 3,000 worshipers. He said the congregation, which holds services in Korean and Spanish, has 4,000 members and is affiliated with the Assemblies of God, a large Pentecostal denomination.</p>
        <p>Playhouse 91 was built in a former stable and icehouse in 1980 and was home to the Riverside Shakespeare Company and the Jewish Repertory Theater.</p>
        <p>BIG DEAL E-mail: bigdeal@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: bigdeal@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
