<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Military Cites 'Negligence' in Aftermath of Iraq Killings</title>
    <meta content="22haditha" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/world/middleeast/22haditha.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070424T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842291"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Haditha (Iraq)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Von Zielbauer, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Huck, Richard A (Maj Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davis, Stephen W (Col)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Marine Corps</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E7DE173EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="908" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Military Cites 'Negligence' in Aftermath of Iraq Killings</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Military Cites ‘Negligence’ in Aftermath of Iraq Killings</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL von ZIELBAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Von Zielbauer, Paul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Military investigation finds senior Marine Corps commanders in Iraq showed routine disregard for lives of Iraqi civilians that contributed to willful failure to investigate killing of 24 unarmed Iraqis in Haditha; criticizes Marine division commander Maj Gen Richard A Huck and regimental commander Col Stephen W Davis (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A military investigation has found that senior Marine Corps commanders in Iraq showed a routine disregard for the lives of Iraqi civilians that contributed to a ''willful'' failure to investigate the killing of 24 unarmed Iraqis by marines in 2005, lawyers involved in the case said.</p>
        <p>The report, completed last summer but never made public, also found that a Marine Corps general and colonel in Iraq learned of the killings within hours that day, Nov. 19, 2005, in the town of Haditha, but failed to begin a thorough inquiry into how they occurred.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A military investigation found that the Marine Corps chain of command in Iraq engaged in “willful negligence” in failing to investigate an attack by marines that killed 24 unarmed Iraqis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A military investigation has found that senior Marine Corps commanders in Iraq showed a routine disregard for the lives of Iraqi civilians that contributed to a ''willful'' failure to investigate the killing of 24 unarmed Iraqis by marines in 2005, lawyers involved in the case said.</p>
        <p>The report, completed last summer but never made public, also found that a Marine Corps general and colonel in Iraq learned of the killings within hours that day, Nov. 19, 2005, in the town of Haditha, but failed to begin a thorough inquiry into how they occurred.</p>
        <p>The 130-page report, by Maj. Gen. Eldon A. Bargewell of the Army, did not conclude that the senior officers covered up evidence or committed a crime. But it said the Marine Corps command in Iraq was far too willing to tolerate civilian casualties and dismiss Iraqi claims of abuse by marines as insurgent propaganda, according to lawyers who have read it.</p>
        <p>''All levels of command tended to view civilian casualties, even in significant numbers, as routine and as the natural and intended result of insurgent tactics,'' General Bargewell wrote in his report, according to two people who have read it. ''Statements made by the chain of command during interviews for this investigation, taken as a whole, suggest that Iraqi civilian lives are not as important as U.S. lives, their deaths are just the cost of doing business, and that the Marines need to get the job done no matter what it takes.''</p>
        <p>The killings in Haditha, in Anbar Province, began with a roadside bombing that killed one American marine and wounded two. Several marines then began methodically killing civilians in the area, eventually going door to door in the village and killing women and children, some in their beds, according to a Naval criminal investigation.</p>
        <p>General Bargewell's report, completed at the request of Lt. Gen. Peter W. Chiarelli, the day-to-day commander of American forces in Iraq at the time, did not focus on the killings themselves, but rather on commanders' handling of the aftermath.</p>
        <p>The Washington Post published details of the report's findings on Saturday. Spokesmen for the Marine Corps declined to comment, citing hearings for the three enlisted marines charged with murder in the case and for four officers charged with dereliction of duty for failing to ensure a proper investigation.</p>
        <p>General Bargewell's report was said to have found what it called ''inattention and negligence, in certain cases willful negligence,'' among Marine officers who reported the civilian deaths immediately up their chain of command in ways that the report said were ''untimely, inaccurate and incomplete.''</p>
        <p>It is critical of the Marine division commander, Maj. Gen. Richard A. Huck, and the regimental commander, Col. Stephen W. Davis, for fostering a perception that civilian Iraqi lives were not as important as American lives and for failing to investigate the civilian deaths in Haditha, lawyers who read the report said.</p>
        <p>Lawyers for the four officers charged with dereliction of duty -- a lieutenant colonel, two captains and a first lieutenant -- disagreed Saturday with the report's conclusions about them.</p>
        <p>''Colonel Chessani, Colonel Davis and General Huck all viewed this -- and still do -- as a legitimate combat action,'' said Brian J. Rooney, a civilian lawyer for Lt. Col. Jeffrey R. Chessani, who was relieved of his command and is the highest-ranking officer known publicly to be punished in the Haditha matter. ''That same night and the next morning Colonel Chessani reported up the chain of command what he had learned about the attacks,'' including that marines had killed civilians. ''I don't know how that's untimely, accurate and incomplete.''</p>
        <p>The Bargewell report, which was recently declassified, also established that junior officers, including a captain who issued a news release on the episode that blamed a roadside bomb planted by insurgents for most of the deaths, knew from the beginning that marines had killed the civilians, the lawyers said.</p>
        <p>The captain, Jeffrey S. Pool, told General Bargewell's investigators that he was given reports from battalion commanders that accurately described the marines' killing of civilians, said lawyers who read the report. But Captain Pool said he issued a news release blaming insurgents for the deaths because he believed that the killings were ultimately a direct result of the roadside bombing of the marines, the lawyers said.</p>
        <p>''The way I saw it was this,'' Captain Pool told two colonels questioning him, according to a lawyer who read the report to a reporter. ''A bomb blast went off, or was initiated, that is what started, that is the reason they're getting this, is a bomb blew up, killed people. We killed people back, and that's the story.'' (Since the investigation, the captain has been promoted to major and is again working as a public affairs officer in Anbar Province.)</p>
        <p>Lawyers for the four officers charged with failing to properly investigate the civilian killings blame the inaccurate news release for creating the false perception that the Marine Corps chain of command had covered up the killing of civilians. But one lawyer also said that the captain's thinking reflected that of his superiors, who believed that civilian casualties, though regrettable, were an inevitable part of war.</p>
        <p>''That's the rubric that the whole division was operating under,'' the lawyer said. The report, he said, came to a similar conclusion. ''It just was the culture of the Marine Corps,'' he said, paraphrasing the report, ''to think that the Iraqis' story was propaganda, and didn't investigate.''</p>
        <p>THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 24, 2007, Tuesday  An article on Sunday about a military report that found that senior Marine Corps commanders had contributed to a ''willful'' failure to investigate the killing of 24 unarmed Iraqis by marines in the town of Haditha in 2005 misstated a word in a quotation from Brian J. Rooney, a lawyer for an officer punished in the Haditha matter. Mr. Rooney said his client, Lt. Col. Jeffrey R. Chessani, had promptly reported what he knew about the killings and ''I don't know how that's untimely, inaccurate and incomplete.'' He did not say ''untimely, accurate and incomplete.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 24, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article on Sunday about a military report that found that senior Marine Corps commanders had contributed to a ''willful'' failure to investigate the killing of 24 unarmed Iraqis by marines in the town of Haditha in 2005 misstated a word in a quotation from Brian J. Rooney, a lawyer for an officer punished in the Haditha matter. Mr. Rooney said his client, Lt. Col. Jeffrey R. Chessani, had promptly reported what he knew about the killings and ''I don't know how that's untimely, inaccurate and incomplete.'' He did not say ''untimely, accurate and incomplete.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
