<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Affordable Europe: Amsterdam</title>
    <meta content="22amsterdamweb" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/travel/22amsterdamweb.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842326"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Amsterdam (Netherlands)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands/Amsterdam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Amsterdam (Netherlands)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE2D61631F931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="581" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Affordable Europe: Amsterdam</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Affordable Europe: Amsterdam</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GISELA WILLIAMS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Amsterdam still harbors a strong bohemian and laid-back spirit, which means affordable options rarely found in other European capitals, from well-priced restaurants to free cultural events. And it's an easy city to navigate, thanks to its small size and the efficient Amsterdam Tourist Board (www.amsterdamtourist.nl), which, in contrast to some, is actually tourist-friendly.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay for Under 125 Euros</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Amsterdam still harbors a strong bohemian and laid-back spirit, which means affordable options rarely found in other European capitals, from well-priced restaurants to free cultural events.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Amsterdam still harbors a strong bohemian and laid-back spirit, which means affordable options rarely found in other European capitals, from well-priced restaurants to free cultural events. And it's an easy city to navigate, thanks to its small size and the efficient Amsterdam Tourist Board (www.amsterdamtourist.nl), which, in contrast to some, is actually tourist-friendly.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay for Under 125 Euros</p>
        <p>The common complaint about Amsterdam's budget hotels is that they're either too remote, or too close to the noisy Central Station. One exception is the family-owned 36-room Hotel Aalborg(Sarphatipark 106; 31-20-676-0310; www.aalborg.nl). Newly renovated, the hotel is the middle of the Pijp neighborhood, a lively area filled with young students, artists and an international mix of affordable restaurants. It's also two blocks from the excellent Albert Cuyp market, where 300-plus stalls offer bargains on everything from furniture to Dutch delicacies. Double rooms start at 69 euros, about $94 at $1.36 to the euro, including breakfast.</p>
        <p>Share Your Tips | Read Tips</p>
        <p>Where to Eat  Don't be put off by the word ''squat'': Amsterdam's squat restaurants -- volunteer-run kitchens in formerly abandoned buildings -- offer a cheap way to break bread with the city's creative underclass. Many are exceptionally well run and clean, and draw a festive crowd. The food tends to be vegan and organic, and some places even offer beer, wine and live music. The best part, however, is the price: a two- to three-course meal runs about 6 euros. Two of the city's most popular squat restaurants are De Peper in the former Netherlands Film Academy (Overtoom 301; 31-20-412-2954; www.depeper.org), which serves organic vegan dishes like spring beans over brown rice with roasted miso onions; and Einde van de Wereld (31-20-419-0222; www.eindevandewereld.nl), housed in a floating barge docked on Java Island.</p>
        <p>If you're still nervous about eating in a squat, or need some meat with your dinner, try the Belgica (Kleine-Gartmanplantsoen 25; 31-20-535-3290; www.belgica.nu), a new brasserie where a good beef stew or bowl of mussels with excellent Belgian frites won't set you back more than 8 or 10 euros.</p>
        <p>Share Your Tips | Read Tips</p>
        <p>Where to Shop  Remember when shopping for vintage clothing was fun and cheap? That's still true at shops like Laura Dols (Wolvenstraat 6 and 7; 31-20-624-9066; www.lauradols.nl), a favorite among the thrift-store cognoscenti. It has two locations on Wolvenstraat: No. 7 carries cocktail dresses from the '40s, '50s and '60s, many under 100 euros, as well as a handsome selection of vintage tuxedos and dinner jackets. No. 6, across the street, has bed linens, fur coats and dressy children's clothes. Also popular with fashion stylists is Lady Day (Hartenstraat 9; 31-20-623-5820; www.ladydayvintage.com). For vintage furniture and couture, head to Cornelis Johannes (Willemsparkweg 67; 31-20-616-0184; www.cornelisjohannes.nl). The inventory changes frequently, so you never know if might find a Mies van der Rohe chair, a Mobach ceramic lamp or a classic Chanel suit.</p>
        <p>Share Your Tips | Read Tips</p>
        <p>Best Money-Saving Tip  Dozens of free concerts are being held in Amsterdam this year, from large-scale raves to classical music performances -- all part of the city's annual arts festival. Events for this year's ''Feel the Rhythm'' theme can be found at www.amsterdammusicdance.com. If you're looking to just chill, bike over to Strand West, probably the city's hippest urban beach. It's free to suntan alongside the beautiful locals on the wide sandy beach, but it'll cost you to buy a drink at the chic indoor lounge.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
