<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Red Sox Pound Yankees' Soft Spot</title>
    <meta content="22yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/sports/baseball/22yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842309"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ortiz, David</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rodriguez, Alex</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Beckett, Josh</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Cabrera, Melky</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jeter, Derek</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE3DE173EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1047" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Red Sox Pound Yankees' Soft Spot</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Red Sox Pound Yankees’ Soft Spot</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, April 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chien-Ming Wang threw 55 pitches on Saturday. Mike Mussina threw 30. Even Carl Pavano played catch.</p>
        <p>The problem for the Yankees was that none of their pitches counted. All of those starters are on the disabled list. Three everyday players -- the injured Hideki Matsui and the banged-up Johnny Damon and Jorge Posada -- were also not starting at Fenway Park.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees, or what was left of them, were no match for the Boston Red Sox, who overwhelmed starter Jeff Karstens on Saturday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Chien-Ming Wang threw 55 pitches on Saturday. Mike Mussina threw 30. Even Carl Pavano played catch.</p>
        <p>The problem for the Yankees was that none of their pitches counted. All of those starters are on the disabled list. Three everyday players -- the injured Hideki Matsui and the banged-up Johnny Damon and Jorge Posada -- were also not starting at Fenway Park.</p>
        <p>The Yankees, or what was left of them, were no match for the Boston Red Sox, who overwhelmed Jeff Karstens in a 7-5 victory. It was the Yankees' second loss this weekend, and they will face Daisuke Matsuzaka on Sunday as they try to avoid a sweep.</p>
        <p>''Our goal right now is to try to stay as close as possible,'' said Damon, who grounded out as a pinch hitter in the ninth inning. ''Hopefully we can win tomorrow night, but it's not the season if we don't. Our team is going to be all right.''</p>
        <p>The last time the teams met here, the Yankees swept a five-game August series to all but seal the American League East title. Wang and Mussina started games then, as did three other pitchers no longer with the team. Karstens had yet to make his major league debut.</p>
        <p>He made his first start of this season on Saturday after a stint on the disabled list with elbow stiffness. Manager Joe Torre said the Yankees knew Karstens might not be sharp after only one rehab start, but they had no better options.</p>
        <p>''They asked me if I thought I was ready, and I did,'' Karstens said. ''I thought I was ready.''</p>
        <p>He lasted four and one-third innings, allowing seven runs on nine hits and two walks. David Ortiz doubled in two and drove in two more with a homer, looking a bit like the Yankees' Alex Rodriguez.</p>
        <p>With a double and a run-scoring single, Rodriguez lifted his average to .379. He now has 31 runs batted in, matching his personal best for any month. The total is just four shy of tying Juan González's April record, set in 1998, and it is the most by a Yankee in any month since Roger Maris drove in 32 in July 1961.</p>
        <p>But for the first game since last Sunday, Rodriguez did not hit a home run. He was on deck when the game ended as Bobby Abreu, representing the tying run, flied to deep center off closer Jonathan Papelbon.</p>
        <p>''Bobby hit the ball right on the screws,'' Rodriguez said. ''Somewhere along the lines, I thought I was going to get a chance.''</p>
        <p>Instead, the Yankees trudged off with a loss, despite scoring twice in the first and second innings against Josh Beckett. Rodriguez doubled to lead off the third, but Beckett retired 14 of the next 15 hitters, mixing his pitches better to stifle the Yankees.</p>
        <p>Jason Giambi struck out twice against Beckett, both times looking, and later fanned with two men on against the left-hander Hideki Okajima. Beckett's pitching line was spotty -- six and two-thirds innings, nine hits and four earned runs -- but he struck out seven. He became the first pitcher in the majors with four victories.</p>
        <p>''That's the best I've seen him look with his breaking ball and changeup, no doubt, since he came to the American League,'' Giambi said. ''That's why he's off to such a good start.''</p>
        <p>Beckett complemented those pitches by pumping fastballs that still reached 98 miles an hour in the seventh inning. Karstens is much different, a soft tosser who must keep the ball down to survive.</p>
        <p>His velocity was fine, Torre said, and his stuff looked good. But he was up in the strike zone too much, and a walk to Kevin Youkilis in the fourth inning was critical.</p>
        <p>Torre had pulled the infield back, sacrificing a run on a ground out to clear the bases and allow Karstens to challenge Youkilis with two outs and Ortiz on deck. But Karstens walked Youkilis to bring up Ortiz.</p>
        <p>''I thought there were a couple of pitches that were close, but they were probably balls,'' Karstens said. ''He's got a good eye; what can I do? I could have just put it over the plate a little more to take my chances with him instead of Big Papi.''</p>
        <p>In hindsight, that would have been a better idea. Ortiz blasted a home run down the right-field line to turn a one-run Boston edge into a commanding 7-4 lead that Beckett and three relievers would not lose.</p>
        <p>Now the Yankees will turn their attention to Matsuzaka while relying on Chase Wright to hold down the Red Sox. Wright beat Cleveland on Tuesday in his first career start above Class AA. A start at Fenway will be another kind of test, although watching two games here has not deterred him.</p>
        <p>''I really haven't heard too many bad things,'' Wright said. ''They told me what to expect when I'm out there warming up in the bullpen before the game. It gets pretty intense out there.''</p>
        <p>Matsuzaka is still a mystery to the Yankees, who bid $33 million for the right to negotiate with him but fell well short of Boston's $51 million bid. The players will study tape of him on Sunday, but for now, their exposure has been limited to highlights.</p>
        <p>Damon said the Yankees should focus on one or two pitches, not the eight Matsuzaka might offer. Derek Jeter said he had no idea what awaits.</p>
        <p>''I haven't seen a thing,'' Jeter said. ''I've heard he's good.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Center fielder Johnny Damon, who rested a sore back and hamstring, said he would start Sunday. But Manager Joe Torre said Jorge Posada's bruised left thumb was too swollen for him to return this weekend. Posada's replacement, Wil Nieves, is 0 for 24 dating to 2002 and has been removed from the lineup in each of his four starts this season.  Hideki Matsui (hamstring) went 1 for 3 in his second rehab game for Class A Tampa yesterday. He is scheduled to rejoin the team on Monday.  Carl Pavano, who is on the disabled list with a mild elbow strain, threw off flat ground on Saturday, but Torre said Pavano still felt discomfort. Chris Britton was optioned to the minors to make room for Jeff Karstens.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
