<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Starting With Little Bunt, Offense Goes a Long Way</title>
    <meta content="22beltran" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/sports/baseball/22beltran.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842279"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Atlanta Braves</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Reyes, Jose</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EFDF173EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="667" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Starting With Little Bunt, Offense Goes a Long Way</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Starting With Little Bunt, Mets’ Offense Goes a Long Way</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Long before the long balls soared toward the construction cranes at the new stadium rising behind the outfield fence, the Mets began to beat the Braves yesterday with only a little bit of a hit at sunny old Shea Stadium.</p>
        <p>It was a leadoff bunt single in the first inning by José Reyes that seemed to discombobulate Chuck James, Atlanta's starting pitcher, in what became a 7-2 Mets victory. James looked surprised by the bunt, a small spark that ignited a big explosion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A leadoff bunt single in the first inning by José Reyes seemed to discombobulate Chuck James, Atlanta’s starting pitcher, in what became a 7-2 Mets victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Long before the long balls soared toward the construction cranes at the new stadium rising behind the outfield fence, the Mets began to beat the Braves yesterday with only a little bit of a hit at sunny old Shea Stadium.</p>
        <p>It was a leadoff bunt single in the first inning by José Reyes that seemed to discombobulate Chuck James, Atlanta's starting pitcher, in what became a 7-2 Mets victory. James looked surprised by the bunt, a small spark that ignited a big explosion.</p>
        <p>When James's hurried throw skipped past first baseman Craig Wilson, Reyes kept going and slid headfirst into second. He moved to third on a fly ball by David Wright and scored on an infield single to deep second base by Carlos Beltrán, the first of Beltrán's four hits.</p>
        <p>''Reyes sets the tone for us,'' Manager Willie Randolph said. ''His energy is infectious. When we score first, we usually win.''</p>
        <p>That first-inning scratch run gave the Mets a lead they never squandered.</p>
        <p>''After I missed the first pitch, I thought, I'm going to put one down and see what happens,'' Reyes said. ''Make the people on defense nervous and throw the ball quick. If I put it in the right place and I run, I'm going to be safe.''</p>
        <p>Reyes later hit a home run, as did the backups Ramón Castro, who started at catcher, and Damion Easley, who played second base. Beltrán did not hit one over the fence, but he managed another single, a double and a triple. He has nine hits in his past 14 at-bats and is 15 for his last 28, and he has raised his batting average to .385.</p>
        <p>Until now, Beltrán has been known as a warm-weather hitter who does better on the road than at home. But with temperatures in the 70s yesterday, he said he felt comfortable.</p>
        <p>''When it's cold, you don't sweat,'' Beltrán said. ''Today was a great day. You sweat, it's sunny. It's baseball weather right here.''</p>
        <p>Beltrán's excellent start has been overshadowed by the torrid one for the Yankees' Alex Rodriguez, but Beltrán is taking the lack of attention in stride. ''Talk about me, don't talk about me,'' Beltrán said. ''They should talk more? I don't care. Talk about what you feel like.''</p>
        <p>He smiled as he said those words and added that he was pleased to talk about Reyes, who raised his average to .368 by going 3 for 5. Beltrán noted the importance of Reyes's leadoff bunt.</p>
        <p>''Reyes is the guy who makes us go,'' Beltrán said. ''Every time he gets to first base, we have a chance to score a run. He can turn it into a triple. This is how we've been playing the game.''</p>
        <p>There was plenty of credit to go around on a day when the Mets outhit the Braves by only 11-10 but got theirs earlier and at key moments. Castro, subbing for Paul Lo Duca, and Easley, in for José Valentín, made Manager Willie Randolph look prescient.</p>
        <p>''I love our lineup -- we're long,'' Randolph said before the game, holding out his hands and moving them apart. After the game, he praised his subs by saying, ''My guys prepare themselves and they came through with big knocks.''</p>
        <p>Castro, who has three home runs in 16 at-bats this season, is a veteran who accepts his role and relates well to the pitchers. After yesterday's game, Castro's average stood at .353. During an injury-plagued 2006, he batted .238.</p>
        <p>''It's all here, mental,'' Castro said, pointing a finger to his head. ''I let my abilities take care of business. I feel better physically. I'm not thinking too much.''</p>
        <p>Coming into the game, the Mets' team batting average, .298, was the best in the major leagues. They raised it to .299.</p>
        <p>''We can score by stealing bases,'' said Easley, reflecting on bunt singles and home runs and everything in between. ''We don't always need the big fly. This is probably the most-balanced lineup I've ever played in.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
