<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Affordable Europe: Brussels</title>
    <meta content="22brusselsweb" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/travel/22brusselsweb.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842327"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brussels (Belgium)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Belgium/Brussels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Belgium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brussels (Belgium)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE2D61631F931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="592" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Affordable Europe: Brussels</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Affordable Europe: Brussels</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN BILEFSKY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Home to the European Union and NATO, Brussels is flush with big-spending bureaucrats in Armani suits. That has pushed up prices everywhere, from monthly rents to moules frites. Luckily, Europe's political capital still suffers from an inferiority complex, which means certain things remain affordable, like Belgium antiques and the 450 varieties of homegrown beer (strawberry brews, anyone?), some of which cost about 1 euro.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay for Under 125 Euros</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Europe’s political capital suffers from an inferiority complex, which means certain things remain affordable, like Belgium antiques and the 450 varieties of homegrown beer (strawberry brews, anyone?), some of which cost about 1 euro.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Home to the European Union and NATO, Brussels is flush with big-spending bureaucrats in Armani suits. That has pushed up prices everywhere, from monthly rents to moules frites. Luckily, Europe's political capital still suffers from an inferiority complex, which means certain things remain affordable, like Belgium antiques and the 450 varieties of homegrown beer (strawberry brews, anyone?), some of which cost about 1 euro.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay for Under 125 Euros</p>
        <p>Thanks to the city's revolving door of diplomats with fat wallets, Brussels hotels can be expensive. One bargain -- at 95 euros, or $127 at $1.36 to the euro, for a double -- is the Hotel Mozart(rue du Marché aux Fromages 23; 32-2-502-6661; www.hotel-mozart.be). Disregard the kebab stands outside and the failed attempt to replicate the grandeur of the Hapsburg court and focus instead on the Grand Place -- one of the world's most beautiful squares -- just a few steps away. For a more intimate alternative, try the booking agency Bed &amp; Brussels (32-2-646-0737, www.bnb-brussels.be), which offers inexpensive rooms (starting at 46 euros) in guesthouses run by Belgians or, just as often, multilingual foreigners.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat  Brussels may have 30 Michelin-star restaurants, but money-conscious foodies need not worry. There are plenty of outstanding and affordable restaurants. One standout isLes Brassins(rue Keyenveld 36; 32-2-512-6999; www.lesbrassins.com), a brasserie that serves 50 different brews along with Belgian classics like carbonnades flamandes (beef stew cooked with beer) and stoemp (puréed potatoes and vegetables served with meat or sausage, with a mustard sauce) for less than 11 euros. Moules frites for under 20 euros can be savored at the 80-year-old Aux Armes de Bruxelles(rue des Bouchers 13; 32-2-511-5550, www.armebrux.be) and the more upmarket but equally traditional restaurant Vincent (rue des Dominicains 8-10; 32-2-511-2607; www.restaurantvincent.com). The Belgians claim to have invented French fries, and one of the best friteries, or French fry stands, can be found in Place Jourdan, a square not far from the European Union's headquarters. A euro buys a cone of frites and a choice of 12 sauces, including Cognac mayonnaise.</p>
        <p>Where to Shop  Bargain hunters should look no further than the Place du Jeu de Balle, a flea market in the oldest quarter of Brussels, the working-class but quickly gentrifying Marolles. There's everything from pink flamingos to retro cinema chairs to reproductions of paintings by Belgian artists like René Magritte. The surrounding streets -- Rue Blaes and Rue Haute -- are peppered with a quirky (some say kitschy) mix of antique furniture shops, galleries and cafes. A highlight is L'Instant Présent (rue Blaes 136; 32-2-513-2891), a photography shop that sells framed black-and-white pictures of India, South America and Brussels for as little as 30 euros. Chic designer shops, not all of them overpriced, are scattered along Rue Antoine Dansaert near the bourse. And one of the best places to buy chocolate is Pierre Marcolini ( rue des Minimes 1; 32-2-514-1206; www.marcolinichocolatier.com), where an assortment of 33 chocolates, including truffles and dark chocolate, costs 16.50 euros.</p>
        <p>Best Money-Saving Tip  For one of the most pleasant (and cheapest) escapes in Brussels, take a stroll or bike ride in the Bois de la Cambre, a 300-acre park on the edge of the city. The park, which has a lovely swan-filled lake in its center, was once a favorite horse-riding spot of Queen Marie-Henriette, wife of the Belgian king, Leopold II. Today, it remains a popular escape for the equestrian set, as well as for nature lovers. You can rent a bike for 13 euros a day at Provelo (www.provelo.be).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
