<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Heat Outdone by Running of Deng and the Bulls</title>
    <meta content="22bulls" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/sports/basketball/22bulls.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842316"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Chicago Bulls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Miami Heat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Miami Heat</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Chicago Bulls</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Deng, Luol</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wade, Dwyane</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wallace, Ben</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Riley, Pat</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E1DE173EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="891" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Heat Outdone by Running of Deng and the Bulls</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Heat Outdone by Running of Deng and the Bulls</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, April 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Luol Deng slashed to the basket, all speed and stealth, undaunted by the championship pedigree of the Miami Heat.</p>
        <p>His teammate Andres Nocioni barreled straight to the basket, and the Chicago rookie Thabo Sefolosha did not merely defend Miami's Dwyane Wade, he gift-wrapped Wade early. And the Bulls' Ben Gordon calmly made his clutch free throws.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>All afternoon of this entertaining first game of the Eastern Conference playoffs, the Chicago Bulls attacked the Heat, grabbing rebounds, racing on the fast break and forcing fouls.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Luol Deng slashed to the basket, all speed and stealth, undaunted by the championship pedigree of the Miami Heat.</p>
        <p>His teammate Andres Nocioni barreled straight to the basket, and the Chicago rookie Thabo Sefolosha did not merely defend Miami's Dwyane Wade, he gift-wrapped Wade early. And the Bulls' Ben Gordon calmly made his clutch free throws.</p>
        <p>Throughout this entertaining first game of their Eastern Conference playoff series, the precocious Bulls attacked the aging Heat, grabbing rebounds, racing on the fast break and forcing Miami to commit frustrating fouls.</p>
        <p>When Wade's 3-point attempt to tie the score in the final 12 seconds fell short, Chicago had held off a spirited Miami charge and claimed a 96-91 victory at the United Center. Youth was served -- even if it was only the first course.</p>
        <p>Deng was the difference in this rematch of last season's first-round series, which the Heat won in six games en route to its first N.B.A. title. Deng, a rangy third-year small forward, led all scorers with 33 points. He opened the game with a salvo (12 first-quarter points) and finished just as convincingly (with 9 fourth-quarter points).</p>
        <p>''The past two years we're definitely a lot more mature,'' said Deng, who turned 22 last week. ''Just being in the playoffs, you're more confident than before. The first year, I was hurt. Last year was my first playoffs, and I was a little bit more nervous than I was tonight.''</p>
        <p>The Bulls were far from rattled, as they were in their season-ending loss to the Nets that dropped them into the fifth seeding and a matchup with Miami, the Southeast Division winner. Twice, the Heat overcame a 9-point deficit to draw to a point behind.</p>
        <p>But ahead by 92-91 with 23 seconds left, the Bulls -- young and old -- did not fold. One crucial tip on an offensive rebound from the veteran Ben Wallace sent the ball to Deng and on to Gordon, who was fouled and made both free throws.</p>
        <p>When Wade, his aggressiveness hampered by his dislocated left shoulder, missed a 3-pointer with 11.9 seconds left, he sealed Miami's defeat. Despite Miami Coach Pat Riley's advice to Wade to bank the shot, Wade said later that he did not have the angle to do so.</p>
        <p>''I had a good look, just came up a little short,'' he said. ''We're still confident with Game 2. We know we did a lot of things wrong. Also, we know we had a lot of stupid fouls. All we can do is learn from our mistakes.''</p>
        <p>Heat center Shaquille O'Neal watched the end from the bench, having fouled out with 3 minutes 19 seconds to play.</p>
        <p>He was on his way to a dominating game in the first half, scoring 17 points by relying on his trademark jump hooks.</p>
        <p>But he quickly picked up four fouls in the second half. His fifth and sixth fouls -- he was called for blocking when he was looking for a charge -- were irritating to him because his heel was in the restricted area on the circle for both, which would make it harder for him to draw a call.</p>
        <p>It was Nocioni, giving up 100 pounds on his drive, who forced O'Neal's sixth foul. O'Neal said he thought that Nocioni flopped.</p>
        <p>''It's just unfortunate that people fall for that,'' O'Neal said.</p>
        <p>O'Neal's coach stuck up for him.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to make excuses,'' Riley said, ''but he has size-22 shoes and he can't get out of the box like most of us can.''</p>
        <p>O'Neal said: ''Even if I did have the back of my foot on the line, the ref that made the call was not in position to make that call. I'm just saying there's got to be consistency. We've got to get the same respect, the same call.''</p>
        <p>The Bulls had a ready response: Point guard Kirk Hinrich, also saddled with fouls, played only eight minutes through the first three quarters. He guarded Wade on the last play, forcing him to go left.</p>
        <p>The Heat left Chicago after the game to return to Miami for two days of practice before coming back here Tuesday for Game 2. O'Neal is convinced the Heat will rebound, he said, because of ''the veterans that we have, all the situations and the drama we've been through.''</p>
        <p>Wade, who finished with 21 points, will be watching film on Deng, whom he defended, and Sefolosha, the 6-foot-7 rookie from Switzerland, who foiled him in the first half and limited him to 3-of-9 shooting. The Bulls outrebounded the Heat by 46-33, led by Wallace's 14, and had 25 fast-break points to Miami's 4.</p>
        <p>''We were able to hold them off,'' Bulls Coach Scott Skiles said. ''I'm more concerned with the way we coughed up a 9-point lead and put ourselves in that position.</p>
        <p>''Our guys are always going to battle, and we were fortunate enough to make good plays in the end.''</p>
        <p>Deng was making most of them. In the four games against Miami this season -- three of them Chicago victories -- and in last year's series, he averaged only 10 points.</p>
        <p>''He's grown,'' Riley said. ''He had a monster game. Any time they needed something, he was making plays.''</p>
        <p>Skiles said: ''He's the kind of guy I don't have to worry about. He's low maintenance.''</p>
        <p>And now Deng is Miami's problem.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
