<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Corzine's Wild Ride</title>
    <meta content="22NJkitman" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/opinion/nyregionopinions/22NJkitman.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842098"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Seat Belts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Speed Limits and Speeding</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kitman, Jamie Lincoln</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Motoring</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Speed Limits and Speeding</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seat Belts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seat Belts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E5DA1F3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="816" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Corzine's Wild Ride</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Corzine’s Wild Ride</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jamie Lincoln Kitman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kitman, Jamie Lincoln</byline>
      <dateline>Nyack, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by automobile magazine editor Jamie Lincoln Kitman on automobile accident involving New Jersey Gov Jon Corzine; comments on excessive speed at which SUV was traveling and fact that Corzine was not wearing seat belt (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHILE Gov. Jon Corzine lies in a hospital bed, his bones broken and shattered, the hearts of all right-thinking people must go out to him.</p>
        <p>Still, for those of us who spend our days thinking and writing about cars, there is so much more to consider about the circumstances of this accident and about the stark truths of the highway, which have once again been revealed and which will, if experience is any guide, once again be ignored.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Why an S.U.V., high speed and no seat belt don’t mix.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHILE Gov. Jon Corzine lies in a hospital bed, his bones broken and shattered, the hearts of all right-thinking people must go out to him.</p>
        <p>Still, for those of us who spend our days thinking and writing about cars, there is so much more to consider about the circumstances of this accident and about the stark truths of the highway, which have once again been revealed and which will, if experience is any guide, once again be ignored.</p>
        <p>Much has already been said about the excessive speed, 91 miles per hour, that the governor's Chevrolet Suburban, a large and heavy sport utility vehicle driven by a state trooper, was traveling just seconds before the accident occurred, this according to an onboard crash data recorder or ''black box'' retrieved from the wrecked vehicle.</p>
        <p>Car companies do not make much of it, but such devices are now routinely installed in new cars, in part as a hedge against litigious accident victims. For as Governor Corzine's driver, Robert Rasinski, now knows, there's nothing like scientific proof of illegal speed to knock holes in one's accident reconstruction story. Indeed, the device's impartial capitulation of the facts has forced the state police to amend an earlier assessment, that speed was not a factor in this terrible accident.</p>
        <p>The very act of going 26 miles over the posted speed limit would lose many drivers their licenses, even if a near fatal wreck had not occurred. To say that traveling 91 miles per hour on the winding and often congested Garden State Parkway at dusk is a lousy idea is to state the obvious. To say that the meeting the governor was racing to attend -- Don Imus's rehabilitative session with the Rutgers women's basketball team -- wasn't worth the risk, much less the ''emergency'' the law requires before allowing state officials to exceed the speed limit, similarly goes without saying.</p>
        <p>To observe, too, that not wearing your seat belt is unwise further iterates the obvious. Failure to wear seat belts is illegal in every state except New Hampshire. But like Diana, Princess of Wales, who would surely have lived had she been belted in the rear seat of her large Mercedes sedan, the governor sealed his own fate -- and undoubtedly multiplied the extent of his injuries.</p>
        <p>Clearly, people who don't wear seat belts are inviting needless injury. Why do they do this? Surely the governor does not subscribe to the indefensible point of view that one is better being thrown from the car than being belted in as tightly as possible. Interestingly, the American automobile industry actually broadcast this macho sawhorse as recently as the 1960s, when it was fighting pending mandatory restraint regulations, even though its own research as far back as the 1930s had proven the contrary. Old disinformation campaigns die hard, it's true, but it's difficult to believe the governor didn't know better.</p>
        <p>More probably, like many accident victims before him, he imagined himself immune to harm. We can leave it to the sociologists and psychologists to describe what it is about wealth, power and privilege that lead many chauffeured occupants to reject their safety belts. More relevant to the rest of us -- and quite possibly a factor here -- is the deeply entrenched myth in our country that three-ton S.U.V.'s offer their occupants some extra measure of protection.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of thousands of New Jerseyans transport themselves and their loved ones in hulking S.U.V.'s like the one the governor was nearly killed in, thinking they are doing themselves a favor, when in fact they are just as likely to be killed on the road as anyone else. In single-vehicle crashes -- accidents where no other vehicle is involved -- S.U.V. drivers are more likely to die. What the S.U.V. giveth, it may also taketh away.</p>
        <p>That's because while big V-8 engines may make S.U.V.'s like the governor's as fast as some sports cars, high centers of gravity and excessive weight make these trucks more unwieldy, especially in avoidance maneuvers, than the most pedestrian sedans. Their tendency to roll over more readily than cars has been thoroughly documented. And, as the governor's experience illustrated, all the weight in the world doesn't help an unbelted occupant.</p>
        <p>A big part of the problem has been the auto industry's insistence on marketing the S.U.V.'s bulk as a selling point. If you really love your spouse and children, you will arm them with all the weight you can afford. But the truth is, if you really love them, you'll make sure they wear their seat belts.</p>
        <p>Governor Corzine, when he is back on the job, and other state officials, along with all New Jerseyans, might do well to take this opportunity to also consider the safety advantages of balanced, low-to-the-ground, proper automobiles. There are plenty to choose from.</p>
        <p>Our elected officials may be above some laws, but they'll never be above the laws of physics.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor Jamie Lincoln Kitman, a lawyer, is the New York bureau chief for Automobile Magazine and the United States editor for Top Gear, a British magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jamie Lincoln Kitman, a lawyer, is the New York bureau chief for Automobile Magazine and the United States editor for Top Gear, a British magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
