<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After a Makeover, A Promising Start</title>
    <meta content="22dineweWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/22dinewe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842044"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/PLEASANTVILLE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Strega (Pleasantville, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reed, M H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Strega</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EFD61E3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="857" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After a Makeover, A Promising Start</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After a Makeover, a Promising Start</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By M. H. REED</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reed, M H</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>M H Reed reviews Strega restaurant in Pleasantville, NY; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFTER being closed for three months for renovation, Strega reopened in February to an enthusiastic clientele who clearly see the place as providing the only show in town. And given its location -- at a four-corners intersection away from the business center of Pleasantville -- it just may be.</p>
        <p>The restaurant's expansion and redecoration is delightful. Rusticated walls contrast with a lush bronze curtain separating the original dining area from the corner entrance, once closed but now in use. Soft lighting, pretty tiles, a newfound roominess -- all add class to this restaurant, clearly popular and a natural for a weekend night date. That's when the bar is crammed with customers happily awaiting a table, and the crowd becomes more jovial as the evening progresses. It's a party.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After being closed a short time for renovation, Strega in Pleasantville still needs some cosmetic refinishing and the food needs some attention as well.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFTER being closed for three months for renovation, Strega reopened in February to an enthusiastic clientele who clearly see the place as providing the only show in town. And given its location -- at a four-corners intersection away from the business center of Pleasantville -- it just may be.</p>
        <p>The restaurant's expansion and redecoration is delightful. Rusticated walls contrast with a lush bronze curtain separating the original dining area from the corner entrance, once closed but now in use. Soft lighting, pretty tiles, a newfound roominess -- all add class to this restaurant, clearly popular and a natural for a weekend night date. That's when the bar is crammed with customers happily awaiting a table, and the crowd becomes more jovial as the evening progresses. It's a party.</p>
        <p>Some cosmetic finishing is still needed -- like outside siding, more evenly distributed tables, a better-marked entrance. But at the moment, there is little that interferes with the enjoyment of the new paint and polish.</p>
        <p>The business end of a restaurant -- the food -- needs some attention as well. While the young kitchen adjusts its offerings, diners may find some efforts uneven. One evening's blunder may be another's triumph. Except when the kitchen was taxed, on weekends it seemed, many dishes fulfilled their promise.</p>
        <p>Those waiting at the bar for a table can share a starter of fried calamari, a mountain of tender, crisp rings and, our favorite, tentacles. The bland tomato dipping sauce needed spark.</p>
        <p>A few interesting items come from the antipasto section. A white bean dish called fantasia (pronounced fan-tah-SEE-ah, we were told) was in fact a down-to-earth, delectable mix of tender cannellini, chopped shrimp, fresh parsley and a dressing of fruity olive oil. Light crepes (crespelle) wrapped ricotta, the dish laved with meltingly delicious béchamel and Gorgonzola. A tasty egg and cheese flan (sformatino) topped a salad of wild arugula.</p>
        <p>Salads with generous amounts of greens sometimes arrived with too little dressing. But the shaved fennel and apple salad, with toasted walnuts and clean-flavored cider vinaigrette, was nicely balanced, as was a plain mix of crisp, chopped romaine (called cesare, though not the classic Caesar salad). Sliced beet salad had only a modicum of beets, arugula taking over the plate.</p>
        <p>Baring the extreme saltiness in a couple of dishes -- the salinity in the pasta water, I suspect -- pastas were all worth trying. Gnocchi with sweet, thick Gorgonzola sauce; and ridged, quilled garganelli with wild mushrooms and truffle oil in mascarpone sauce were rich, creamy knockouts. More sober yet as appealing were maccheroni alla chitarra, a square spaghetti-like pasta teamed with sausage ragù; meaty tagliatelle Bolognese; and simply prepared bucatini with chopped tomato, onions and pancetta. For those diners with special dietary needs, whole wheat pasta and brown rice pasta are available on request.</p>
        <p>As in other courses, when timed carefully, entrees were also winning. Braised beef short ribs could not have been more flavorful. And a thick filet mignon sautéed with good balsamic vinegar melted in the mouth. On the other hand, in a sloppy dish called straccetti the hacked scraps of beef were overdone and tough.</p>
        <p>A gentle sweet-hot sauce of pink peppercorns and a dash of moscato made a star of ordinary shrimp. Juicy and cooked perfectly, medallions of chicken were nicely served by a simple sauce of garlic, firm green olives and soft grape tomatoes. The right timing for salmon has yet to be worked out.</p>
        <p>The same julienne of colorful vegetables came with most entrees, but the combination was so successful that no one objected to the repetition.</p>
        <p>Desserts were mostly sweet and bland -- profiteroles, ricotta cheesecake -- with a napoleon perhaps the best choice.</p>
        <p>Prices are a little high for some of the wobbly opening days' efforts, but Strega has lots of energy and is a handy destination not only for a date but also for neighbors wanting a special meal away from the kitchen.</p>
        <p>Strega</p>
        <p>2 Broadway  at Route 141 and Bedford Road  Pleasantville  (914) 769-4040</p>
        <p>GOOD</p>
        <p>THE SPACE -- Lovely, larger and redecorated dining areas done in rustic Mediterranean style. Outside dining planned for warm weather. High-decibel level at peak moments, especially on weekends. Two shallow steps at the entrance limit easy wheelchair access.</p>
        <p>THE CROWD -- Adult diners in neat, casual dress.</p>
        <p>THE BAR -- Long, pretty copper-topped bar with a few tables. Lively and loud on weekends. Mostly Italian wines in a broad price range. (We were informed that the list was being revised. )</p>
        <p>THE BILL -- Main dishes, $21 to $35; pasta entrees, $18 to $21.</p>
        <p>WHAT WE LIKE -- Fennel salad, chopped romaine salad, fried calamari, fantasia of beans and shrimp, crespelle with cheese, spaghetti alla chitarra, gnocchi with Gorgonzola sauce, bucatini amatriciana, garganelli with mascarpone sauce, chicken with tomato and green olives (special), short ribs with wild mushroom ragù, filet mignon balsamico, shrimp with pink peppercorns.</p>
        <p>IF YOU GO -- Dinner only, Tuesday to Thursday, 5:30 to 10 p.m.; Friday and Saturday, 5:30 to 11 p.m. Reservations necessary on weekends. Valet parking on Friday and Saturday.</p>
        <p>Reviewed April 22, 2007</p>
        <p>DINING/PLEASANTVILLE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
