<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mamaroneck Grasps for Way to Avoid a Repeat</title>
    <meta content="22weekweWC-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842302"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mamaroneck (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Army Corps of Engineers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitaker, Barbara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gruen, Abby</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marszalek, Diana</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DE173EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="768" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mamaroneck Grasps for Way to Avoid a Repeat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA WHITAKER; ABBY GRUEN and DIANA MARSZALEK contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marszalek, Diana; Gruen, Abby; Whitaker, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Village officials and residents of Mamaroneck, NY, meet with Army Corps of Engineers to discuss ways to prevent repeat of flooding that occurred after recent heavy rain; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After some neighborhoods in Mamaroneck flooded in a heavy rain on March 2, village officials and residents met with the Army Corps of Engineers to discuss ways to prevent a repeat.</p>
        <p>''Then we got zonked again,'' Mayor Philip Trifiletti said Tuesday after more than seven inches of rain fell in the village in last week's northeaster, flooding basements, closing roads and leaving merchants lamenting their lack of flood insurance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After some neighborhoods in Mamaroneck flooded in a heavy rain on March 2, village officials and residents met with the Army Corps of Engineers to discuss ways to prevent a repeat.</p>
        <p>''Then we got zonked again,'' Mayor Philip Trifiletti said Tuesday after more than seven inches of rain fell in the village in last week's northeaster, flooding basements, closing roads and leaving merchants lamenting their lack of flood insurance.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trifiletti said the Army Corps developed a plan nearly 30 years ago for dealing with flooding in the area, but while some elements were put in place, some were not, because of cost or other reasons.</p>
        <p>''What I've said is, we have to start looking at the other parts of the plan,'' he said. ''With all the change and development where there is no longer impervious land, water ends up in our village.''</p>
        <p>Peggy Jackson, of Harbor Heights, one of the citizens who participated in the Army Corps talks, said her house, which is near the Mamaroneck River, has flooded three times since 2004, twice in the last six weeks. The Sheldrake River also runs through Mamaroneck.</p>
        <p>''Probably, overdevelopment hasn't helped us,'' she said. ''Lots of permeable ground has been lost, but it could also be a freak of nature.''</p>
        <p>The county's planning commissioner, Jerry Mulligan, said his office had begun putting together a countywide summit on flooding. ''The initial focus will try to get people on the same page as to why we're in the situation we're in,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But, he cautioned, ''there is no silver bullet.''</p>
        <p>He noted that each community has its own land-use regulations, and development pressures sometimes resulted in the choices that had adversely affected the watershed.</p>
        <p>Residents throughout the county spent the week bailing out, drying out and trying to put things back where they belong.</p>
        <p>Pupils at the Mamaroneck Avenue School, many of whom live in the hard-hit Washingtonville area, returned to class Wednesday only to be shuttled to temporary classrooms at the high and middle schools. The 620 students, some of whom had taken refuge with their families at a shelter in the high school, returned to school Thursday after electricity was restored.</p>
        <p>In downtown Rye, most businesses reopened by midweek, except those unfortunate enough to back onto the Blind Brook. About a dozen were without power for days.</p>
        <p>''This is devastating,'' said Dennis Noskin, the owner of a small office building on Elm Street, as he watched a pipe gush water out of his basement.</p>
        <p>He said he had escaped damage in the early March storm. ''This time, the water picked up the asphalt of my parking lot and threw it around like giant pancakes,'' he said.</p>
        <p>For Sam Moy, 58, of Rye, the owner of Fong's Laundry on Elm, the scene was all too familiar.</p>
        <p>''I spent lots of money putting in all new equipment and electricity after the last flood'' in March, he said. ''Insurance doesn't cover that. We moved everyone's clothes up to the second floor, so they are O.K., but I had eight feet of water in my basement again.''</p>
        <p>At Ruby's Oyster Bar and Bistro on Purchase Street, the owner, Jim Sullivan, said he had six feet of water in his basement. ''We are just outside the flood zone, so we don't have flood insurance,'' he said. ''We lost all of our product, worth $30,000 to 40,000, plus four days of business, plus $20,000 of equipment, plus the cost of the cleanup.''</p>
        <p>The bridge over the Blind Brook at Central Avenue was closed, the asphalt buckled and large gaps visible in the supports. At a brown colonial on Central Avenue, just over the bridge, a five-foot sinkhole had opened in the front yard along the foundation. As a sump pump poured water out of the basement, a television and sofa cushions were piled outside.</p>
        <p>''The pressure from the flood pushed open the basement window and water poured in to the ceiling,'' said the owner, Victoria Cerami. ''My new $12,000 generator was moved five feet on its concrete pad.''</p>
        <p>Her son, Matthew Breitel, 17, a junior at Rye High School, and four friends, all barefoot or in sandals and covered with mud, were helping to clean out the basement.</p>
        <p>''The water in the street was up to my knees, and I found my mom in the basement screaming because the basement window had blown in,'' Matthew said. ''Our basement was full of water, and the backyard was a pond. Our neighbor's large playset had landed in my trampoline.''</p>
        <p>ABBY GRUEN and DIANA MARSZALEK contributed reporting.</p>
        <p>THE WEEK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
