<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>And the Sand Won't Burn Your Feet</title>
    <meta content="22beachnjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/22beachnj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842083"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kocieniewski, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00EFDB1F3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="899" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>And the Sand Won't Burn Your Feet</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">And the Sand Won’t Burn Your Feet</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID KOCIENIEWSKI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kocieniewski, David</byline>
      <dateline>CAPE MAY</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on springtime along New Jersey Shore, before crowds show up; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SPRING announces its arrival in vibrant and unmistakable ways along the Jersey Shore. In Belmar, the sound of bagpipes and the ruckus of the annual St. Patrick's Day parade signal winter's unofficial end, whatever the thermometer may say. Down in May's Landing, rowing crews in sleek sculls begin to dot the frigid waters of Absecon Bay and Lake Lenape. And in Cape May, the brilliant colors of the annual tulip festival (this year on April 28 and 29) are an unmistakable sign that the resort is shaking off the cricks and cobwebs of seasonal slumber.</p>
        <p>In the weeks that follow, as beach towns ramp up for the coming onslaught, visitors have a chance to experience the shore in such a relaxed way that those who have been there in summer might mistake it for a mirage. Crowds are sparse or nonexistent. Room rates are lower. And until Memorial Day, most towns forgo that bane of summer down the Shore: beach tags.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The pre-summer at the Jersey Shore offers its own share of attractions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SPRING announces its arrival in vibrant and unmistakable ways along the Jersey Shore. In Belmar, the sound of bagpipes and the ruckus of the annual St. Patrick's Day parade signal winter's unofficial end, whatever the thermometer may say. Down in May's Landing, rowing crews in sleek sculls begin to dot the frigid waters of Absecon Bay and Lake Lenape. And in Cape May, the brilliant colors of the annual tulip festival (this year on April 28 and 29) are an unmistakable sign that the resort is shaking off the cricks and cobwebs of seasonal slumber.</p>
        <p>In the weeks that follow, as beach towns ramp up for the coming onslaught, visitors have a chance to experience the shore in such a relaxed way that those who have been there in summer might mistake it for a mirage. Crowds are sparse or nonexistent. Room rates are lower. And until Memorial Day, most towns forgo that bane of summer down the Shore: beach tags.</p>
        <p>With fewer people around and more relaxed rules, spring getaways offer easier access to what makes the Shore the Shore: its sprawling beaches. Some permit you to ride a horse or walk a dog before the summer season officially begins on Memorial Day. A spring getaway also allows visitors to appreciate that resort towns are more than just places to spread a beach towel; they are real communities with year-round residents and some charms that don't bloom until the summer weather fades.</p>
        <p>Without the hordes of tourists, ''you can stand in the middle of the street and have a 20-minute conversation,'' said Ken McAlpine, a travel writer and author of the book ''Off Season,'' about East Coast beach towns.</p>
        <p>''In the summer you couldn't even get across that street,'' he said. ''There's more of a sense of humanity, because it's not overrun with humanity.''</p>
        <p>In Cape May, for instance, summer throngs transform the Victorian neighborhoods into a bustling carnival of gingerbread houses and canopied surrey bicycles. But in spring, the streets have a tranquillity befitting Cape May's quaintness. Most of the miniature golf courses and fudge shops are shuttered until late May. Restaurants and stores are either closed or on limited schedules. Some of those that operate year round, like the Blue Pig at Congress Hall, keep a fireplace blazing to help burn off the chill.</p>
        <p>Cape May's hospitality businesses and its industrious Mid-Atlantic Center for the Arts have devised an assortment of activities: family treasure hunts, teas, mansion tours, even a haunted-house tour by trolley.</p>
        <p>Those who wander a bit, however, can find more unusual sites and even enduring natural treasures.</p>
        <p>A short drive from Cape May's Boardwalk, Cape May Point is one of the nation's best-known bird-watching destinations. Each April and May, it attracts thousands of visitors who want to witness the return flights of the red knot, the Louisiana water thrush, yellow-throated warbler and hundreds of other species. The New Jersey Audubon Society's Northwood Center offers guided tours, cruises and a variety of educational programs. The nearby Higbee Beach Wildlife Management Area also has two observation towers and miles of birding trails running through its 900 acres.</p>
        <p>About 20 miles north in Wildwood, where the streets on a March weekend were so deserted that the traffic lights were operating in blink mode, the seasonal desolation is a kind of spectacle unto itself. While the town often swells to 250,000 people on summer weekends, in springtime it offers a case study in depopulation for photographers, painters and travelers who crave solitude. There are miles of abandoned beaches, lonely boardwalks and an empty amusement park. Wildwood's business strip, built in the so-called Doo-Wop style of the 1940s and '50s, is a virtual ghost town of unoccupied motels, their plastic palm trees shuddering in the stiff spring breeze.</p>
        <p>One business that operates year-round, Montego Bay Resort in North Wildwood, offers an oasis for parents desperate to burn off their children's excess energy: an indoor water park. For a $10 admission fee, kids can romp in a heated pool, two-story water slide and hot tub while their parents unwind at the poolside bar.</p>
        <p>But a Jersey Shore getaway will always be about the beaches.</p>
        <p>At Island Beach State Park, a 95-mile drive north from Cape May, off-season regulations allow visitors to ride horses along the beach (between Oct. 1 and April 30). It's strictly bring-your-own; the park doesn't have horses available for rent, and travelers must call ahead to make reservations because a limited number of riders are allowed at one time.</p>
        <p>At Cape May Point, the sun's lower trajectory in the off season helps Sunset Beach live up to its name with a spectacular twilight display of blue, violet and metallic orange hues. A popular spot for sunbathers and quartz collectors in the summer, it's a laid-back haven for couples, kite-fliers and photographers in spring.</p>
        <p>On Sunset Beach, Caroline Peterson of Mahopac, N.Y., who was visiting Cape May in March to watch her niece in a cheerleading competition, said she had been so pleasantly surprised by the scenery and solitude that she planned to return.</p>
        <p>''I kind of groaned at the thought of going to New Jersey in the cold,'' said Ms. Henderson, who had set up a tripod to photograph the blazing sunset. ''But it's been so peaceful and beautiful that I want to come back with my husband before the crowds get here.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
