<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yes, It's All About Music, But Leave the iPods Home</title>
    <meta content="22theaterctCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/22theaterct.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842034"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Long Wharf Theater</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gold, Sylviane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cale, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Orlandersmith, Dael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edelstein, Gordon</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Blue Album, The (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Long Wharf Theater</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E0D61E3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="549" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yes, It's All About Music, But Leave the iPods Home</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Yes, It’s All About Music, but Leave the iPods Home</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SYLVIANE GOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gold, Sylviane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sylviane Gold reviews Long Wharf Theater production of David Cale and Dael Orlandersmith play The Blue Album, directed by Gordon Edelstein; Cale and Orlandersmith star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It seems unlikely that the iPod generation will ever be able to tell the kinds of stories that David Cale and Dael Orlandersmith recount and enact in ''The Blue Album,'' the sharply written, beautifully performed vignettes and character sketches that run through April 29 at Long Wharf Theater's Stage II.</p>
        <p>In the new world of the iPod, you create your own musical universe. In the older world of ''The Blue Album,'' listening to music means joining a tribe. Although its locales range from punk-era London to Harlem in the '50s to Malibu in 1960, and its characters include a Polish Holocaust survivor, a rape victim and a Dolly Parton fan, the play is more than a well-chosen anthology of bits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It seems unlikely that the iPod generation will ever be able to tell the kinds of stories that David Cale and Dael Orlandersmith recount and enact in “The Blue Album.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It seems unlikely that the iPod generation will ever be able to tell the kinds of stories that David Cale and Dael Orlandersmith recount and enact in ''The Blue Album,'' the sharply written, beautifully performed vignettes and character sketches that run through April 29 at Long Wharf Theater's Stage II.</p>
        <p>In the new world of the iPod, you create your own musical universe. In the older world of ''The Blue Album,'' listening to music means joining a tribe. Although its locales range from punk-era London to Harlem in the '50s to Malibu in 1960, and its characters include a Polish Holocaust survivor, a rape victim and a Dolly Parton fan, the play is more than a well-chosen anthology of bits.</p>
        <p>Of course, the production imposes a visible structure on the work, with Neil Patel's indigo-blue dream-box of a set and the moody wash of Jennifer Tipton's lighting. But it's the writing itself that weaves the various pieces together, with a subtle but unmistakable backbeat about the ways in which music can seep into a life, the ways in which it can create a community.</p>
        <p>Ask Mr. Cale's flamboyantly gay Trevor, who comes into the record store where David, also played by Mr. Cale, works, to buy ''Liza With a Zed.'' Ask Ms. Orlandersmith's Yiddish-accented Herman, who has a melancholy barstool encounter with Billie Holiday. Or her Al, a sputtering uptown geezer who has to take ''two damned trains'' to get down to an impossible-to-find club in Greenwich Village -- ''Why the hell didn't Nina Simone play the damned Apollo?,'' he wants to know.</p>
        <p>Part of the pleasure of watching ''The Blue Album'' comes from the mix-and-match way the writer-performers trade places and personas. There's no way to know for sure who wrote what, who lived what. It's a pretty good bet that Mr. Cale drew ''5th Street'' from his own life -- in it, a woman assails two gay men looking out the window of their apartment with a homophobic tirade -- and that Ms. Orlandersmith experienced the excruciating moment portrayed in ''Bellagio (2003),'' in which ''a perfumed, well-dressed, well-read'' writer in Italy is mistaken for a servant. But she's the one telling the Fifth Street story, and he's the one acting in the Bellagio episode.</p>
        <p>The play's 22 ''tracks,'' as they are called in the program, emerged from what sounds very much like a ''let's put on a show'' collaboration among Mr. Cale and Ms. Orlandersmith, who are playwrights, performers and East Village neighbors, and Gordon Edelstein, who heads the Long Wharf and who commissioned and directed ''The Blue Album.'' Mr. Edelstein writes in his program note that they discarded ''thousands of pages'' during the two years they worked on it. The 90 minutes that remain, laced with snatches of song by Mr. Cale, play like theatrical chamber music.</p>
        <p>To be sure, the show might benefit from a tad more pruning -- ''Side 2'' feels a little heavier than it should. But as Mr. Cale and Ms. Orlandersmith spin their platter, they create yet another musical community at Long Wharf. Just take off your iPod and listen.</p>
        <p>''The Blue Album,'' by David Cale and Dael Orlandersmith, is at Long Wharf Theater's Stage II, 222 Sargent Dr., New Haven, through April 29. Information at (203) 787-4282 or longwharf.org.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
