<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Skipping Along to a Victory, Pérez Goes Without Walks</title>
    <meta content="22mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/sports/baseball/22mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842310"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Atlanta Braves</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pérez, Oliver</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2DE173EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="854" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Skipping Along to a Victory, Pérez Goes Without Walks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Skipping Along to a Victory, Mets' Pérez Goes Without Walks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shpigel, Ben</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Oliver Pérez has this superstition about foul lines. He avoids them. Ever since he was a Little Leaguer in Mexico, where he was warned not to step on the fresh chalk, Pérez has skipped over foul lines on his way to and from the mound.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, as he did in his last start after he was removed for walking seven before sunset, the skip can look a little incongruous. But on days like yesterday, when he struck out nine Atlanta Braves, walked none and, in a remarkable stretch, threw 20 consecutive strikes, Pérez could have been mistaken for dancing off the field.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Oliver Pérez struck out nine Atlanta Braves, walked none and, in a remarkable stretch, threw 20 consecutive strikes to lead the Mets to a victory on Saturday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Oliver Pérez has this superstition about foul lines. He avoids them. Ever since he was a Little Leaguer in Mexico, where he was warned not to step on the fresh chalk, Pérez has skipped over foul lines on his way to and from the mound.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, as he did in his last start after he was removed for walking seven before sunset, the skip can look a little incongruous. But on days like yesterday, when he struck out nine Atlanta Braves, walked none and, in a remarkable stretch, threw 20 consecutive strikes, Pérez could have been mistaken for dancing off the field.</p>
        <p>When he was removed in the seventh inning of the Mets' 7-2 victory at Shea Stadium, Pérez jogged briskly toward the dugout to a standing ovation from the sun-drenched crowd of 55,143. He tipped his cap and, as soon as he entered the dugout, embraced the pitching coach Rick Peterson.</p>
        <p>''It was a very important game for me and for the team,'' Pérez said. ''When you have a game like that, you have to feel happy.''</p>
        <p>He was not the only one. Joe Smith defused a dangerous situation in the seventh, striking out Andruw Jones with the bases loaded to end the inning. The reserves Ramón Castro and Damion Easley hit home runs, and Carlos Beltrán had his second four-hit game in three days, falling a home run shy of the cycle.</p>
        <p>In his past six games, Beltrán is hitting .536 (15 for 28) with nine runs batted in. His average has rocketed to .385 from .270.</p>
        <p>''What can I say?'' Beltrán said. ''I'm just looking for pitches to drive, and it just seems that every ball I'm hitting is finding the hole. God is letting me start like this.''</p>
        <p>Such brilliance is almost expected these days from Beltrán. But from Pérez? In his last start, April 11, he walked seven Phillies in two and two-thirds innings and was booed off the mound.</p>
        <p>And yet his pitching line, to those who were not among the largest crowd to see a Mets-Braves game at Shea, could have been deceiving: two runs and nine hits, including five over his final one and two-thirds innings that threatened to cut into the Mets' big lead. But to understand Pérez's performance yesterday, other factors must be considered.</p>
        <p>Rain pushed Pérez's scheduled start from Wednesday, allowing him to throw two extra bullpen sessions with Peterson and to correct a mechanical flaw that hindered his control during his last start. He was not bringing his knee up to his chest as he prepared to throw, causing him to open his body and miss his target.</p>
        <p>''He needed to get back into his rhythm,'' Manager Willie Randolph said. ''And he did.''</p>
        <p>Throwing a fastball that reached 96 miles an hour, Pérez accomplished some feats yesterday that would have pleased a control specialist like his teammate Tom Glavine. After a ball that evened the count at 2-2 to the No. 2 hitter, Édgar Rentería, in the first inning, Pérez did not throw another one until an 0-2 pitch to Kelly Johnson, the Braves' leadoff hitter, with two outs in the third.</p>
        <p>''I had no idea,'' Castro, the catcher, said. ''I knew he was good, but I didn't know he was that good. Wow.''</p>
        <p>Of his first 30 pitches, only 5 were balls. Pérez threw a ball on the game's first pitch to Johnson -- who struck out all four times he faced Pérez -- then did not fire a first-pitch ball to any of the next 13 hitters. He left after throwing 98 pitches, 72 for strikes.</p>
        <p>If anything, Randolph said, Pérez was throwing too much around the plate.</p>
        <p>''If he used his off-speed pitches more, maybe he could have pitched a complete game,'' Randolph said. ''But I'm just nitpicking there.''</p>
        <p>Braves right fielder Jeff Francoeur, who struck out twice against Pérez, said: ''I've never, ever seen him have the pinpoint accuracy that he did today. His fastball definitely looked harder today, and he was throwing his slider wherever he wanted.''</p>
        <p>Pérez threw a shutout against the Braves in September. In Atlanta on April 6, in his first start of the season, he allowed one run and walked none in seven innings.</p>
        <p>The problem, as it always is with Pérez, is developing consistency, not being consistently erratic. He and the Mets seemed confident that yesterday's outing could have long-lasting effects.</p>
        <p>''We know what Tommy and Duque can give us,'' Castro said of Glavine and Orlando Hernández. ''But if Oliver pitches like this, and Johnny Maine does, too, then we could be real tough.''</p>
        <p>The mild-mannered Pérez seemed more animated from the outset, and he thumped his glove after big strikeouts. But he saved his best for the end, when Randolph came for him in the seventh. On his way toward the dugout, Pérez slowed down briefly before leaping about 3 feet over the foul line.</p>
        <p>''A little too much,'' Castro said playfully. ''But he deserved it.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>David Wright, who batted second for the final two weeks of spring training, hit there yesterday and went 0 for 4.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
