<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Israel and Palestinians Trade Fire in Gaza and West Bank</title>
    <meta content="22mideast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Education" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/world/middleeast/22mideast.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842289"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Beit Lahiya (Israel)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Gaza Strip</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Al Qaeda (Terrorist Group)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Islamic Jihad</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Gaza Strip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Gaza Strip</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Israel</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Al Qaeda</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E7DE173EF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="862" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Israel and Palestinians Trade Fire in Gaza and West Bank</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Israel and Palestinians Trade Fire in Gaza and West Bank</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ISABEL KERSHNER; Taghreed El-Khodary contributed reporting from Beit Lahiya, Gaza.</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, April 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Israeli and Palestinian clashes leave up to six Palestinians dead; actions include Israeli airstrike against Islamic Jihad cell that launched three rockets from Gaza Strip into Israel; extremists believed to be linked to Al Qaeda bomb and set fire to American International School in Beit Lahiya north of Gaza City; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A sharp escalation of Israeli-Palestinian violence in the West Bank and Gaza left up to six Palestinians dead and culminated in an Israeli airstrike into Gaza, officials said.</p>
        <p>In a separate episode, about a dozen masked Palestinians bombed and set fire to the American International School in Beit Lahiya, north of Gaza City, before dawn on Saturday, school officials and Palestinian security officials said. The attack caused extensive damage, but no injuries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>About a dozen masked Palestinians bombed and set fire to the American International School, causing extensive damage, but no injuries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A sharp escalation of Israeli-Palestinian violence in the West Bank and Gaza left up to six Palestinians dead and culminated in an Israeli airstrike into Gaza, officials said.</p>
        <p>In a separate episode, about a dozen masked Palestinians bombed and set fire to the American International School in Beit Lahiya, north of Gaza City, before dawn on Saturday, school officials and Palestinian security officials said. The attack caused extensive damage, but no injuries.</p>
        <p>The officials said that the attackers, believed to be Islamic extremists subscribing to the ideology of Al Qaeda, placed several explosive devices at the school. The principal's office and the cafeteria on the first floor of the two-story building were badly burned, and computers were stolen, the officials said.</p>
        <p>Early in the day in the West Bank, Israeli troops killed Muhammad Said Abed, 22, in the village of Kufr Dan, near Jenin. An army spokeswoman said that Palestinians had thrown an explosive device and repeatedly fired at the soldiers, who were on a routine operation. The soldiers identified a man standing on the roof of a house ''holding a long rifle,'' the spokeswoman said, and shot him. Witnesses in the village told Reuters that Mr. Abed, a member of the Palestinian security forces, had not been involved in the fighting.</p>
        <p>Hours later, an Israeli special unit killed three Palestinians traveling in a car in the Jenin refugee camp, Israeli and Palestinian officials said. The Israeli Army spokeswoman said that the men had fired first and that two rifles and a rocket-propelled grenade were found in the car.</p>
        <p>Palestinian medical workers reported that a 17-year-old Palestinian girl was also shot dead in Jenin. The Army was checking those reports.</p>
        <p>On Saturday evening, three Qassam rockets were launched from the Gaza Strip into Israel, according to the army. One hit a house in the Israeli town of Sderot, close to the Gaza border, and six civilians were treated for shock, the Army said. Two rockets landed in open areas.</p>
        <p>The Army confirmed that it then carried out an airstrike against the cell that launched the rockets. The militant Islamic Jihad group, which claimed responsibility for the rocket attack, said that one of its men was killed in the airstrike. But reports in the Palestinian news media said the man killed was a civilian bystander.</p>
        <p>Nabil Abu Rudeineh, an aide of the Palestinian president, Mahmoud Abbas, called the Israeli actions ''dangerous aggression'' that could cause instability ''at a time when the Palestinian Authority is making great efforts to maintain a truce.''</p>
        <p>The school blast happened around 5 a.m. on a day when the building was closed for the weekend. Two night guards said the militants tied their hands and initially kept them on the premises before allowing them to move out of danger. According to one of the guards, Atef al-Beheisi, the masked men told him, ''We are the organization of Al Qaeda in Palestine, and our swords will be directed at the throats of the infidels.''</p>
        <p>The second guard, who fearing for his safety asked not to be identified and who was at another entrance of the school, said the intruders identified themselves to him as being part of the ''Army of Islam.''</p>
        <p>In recent months, a wave of bombings by people suspected of being Islamic radicals has been directed against Internet cafes, pharmacies, music stores and other recreational centers in the Gaza Strip. Last weekend, an explosion damaged a Christian bookstore in Gaza City.</p>
        <p>The American International School in Gaza was established as a local private enterprise and opened shortly before the outbreak of the second intifada in September 2000. It promotes American-style education and received $160,000 this year from the State Department to finance scholarships for needy students, according to Micaela Schweitzer-Bluhm, a spokeswoman at the United States Consulate in Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>The school, which charges $2,000 to $4,000 a year, is beyond the means of most Gazans, and as a result it is not profitable. There are 150 students enrolled at the school, which has a teaching staff of 30, all local Palestinians. The last foreign staff members left about a year ago because of the deteriorating security situation.</p>
        <p>Several hours after Saturday's attack, the current principal, Ribhi Salem, said: ''I am still in a state of shock. How could any Palestinian think it is in the Palestinian interest to carry out such a barbaric act?''</p>
        <p>Dr. Eyad Sarraj, a well-known psychiatrist in Gaza and the chairman of the board of the school, said: ''This is a clear attack against our country. It is designed to make everybody afraid. This school offers a distinguished education, but they want the students to be illiterate. This is against Islam.''</p>
        <p>Though privately run, the school falls under the supervision of the Palestinian Authority Education Ministry, which is controlled by Hamas. The United States defines Hamas as a terrorist organization and refuses to deal with the Hamas ministers in the Palestinian government.</p>
        <p>But the Palestinian deputy minister of education, Muhammad Abu Shkeir, said in a telephone interview from Gaza that his ministry ''cooperates fully with the American School, as with all international institutions.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
