<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Less Provocative,But No Less Dysfunctional</title>
    <meta content="22theaternjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/22theaternj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842090"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siegel, Naomi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finn, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapine, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saint, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Falsettos (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">George Street Playhouse</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Finn, William</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Lapine, James</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EEDB1F3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="513" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Less Provocative,But No Less Dysfunctional</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Less Provocative, but No Less Dysfunctional</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NAOMI SIEGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Siegel, Naomi</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Naomi Siegel reviews George Street Playhouse production of William Finn and James Lapine musical Falsettos, directed by David Saint; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Reunions with old friends are fraught with danger. Will the magic still be there, or has time, with its corrosion of content and context, damaged the connective tissue?</p>
        <p>I pondered those questions as I settled into my seat for the production of ''Falsettos'' that ends the season at the George Street Playhouse in New Brunswick. The Tony Award-winning William Finn and James Lapine musical, which opened on Broadway 15 years ago, was in reality a reworking and patching together of two earlier one-act musicals: ''The March of the Falsettos,'' written in 1981, and ''Falsettoland,'' from 1990.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A family works through its problems musically in “Falsettos,” at George Street Playhouse in New Brunswick.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Reunions with old friends are fraught with danger. Will the magic still be there, or has time, with its corrosion of content and context, damaged the connective tissue?</p>
        <p>I pondered those questions as I settled into my seat for the production of ''Falsettos'' that ends the season at the George Street Playhouse in New Brunswick. The Tony Award-winning William Finn and James Lapine musical, which opened on Broadway 15 years ago, was in reality a reworking and patching together of two earlier one-act musicals: ''The March of the Falsettos,'' written in 1981, and ''Falsettoland,'' from 1990.</p>
        <p>''Falsettos'' was seen as provocative enough to be commercially risky when it first appeared. Marvin's conflicted odyssey from conventional husband and father to out-of-the-closet gay man -- accompanied by his lover, Whizzer, his ex-wife, Trina, their pre-adolescent son, Jason, and Trina's new psychiatrist husband, Mendel -- was not an easy voyage for audiences. (And let's not forget the ''lesbians from next door,'' Dr. Charlotte and her partner, Cordelia.)</p>
        <p>''Falsettos'' struggled to find its niche; some ticket buyers were uncomfortable watching a stage portrayal of two men in an explicit physical relationship, or hearing the angst of family dysfunction blasted raucously throughout the nonstop musical score (the opening ''Four Jews in a Room Bitching'' sets the tone), or confronting the specter of AIDS as a social reality.</p>
        <p>Segue to 2007 and a theater scene that has few boundaries and a diminished capacity to shock. George Street, under the able direction of its artistic director, David Saint, has mounted a funny, touching ''Falsettos'' that almost succeeds in covering the fault lines in the work. Visually stunning -- Beowulf Boritt's setting, inspired by Keith Haring, is great fun -- and wonderfully cast, the show swings broadly in mood. While reveling in its ethnic shtick about the Jewish-American family, it mines poignancy to the point of heartbreak as Marvin's own family comes apart at the seams. Overlong at two and a half hours, overstuffed and, at times, overwrought, ''Falsettos'' could use a good editor, most notably in the more repetitious, less well-crafted Act I. Yet no one can deny the quiet power of Act II's tender ending and its message of nonjudgmental, open-hearted love.</p>
        <p>As musical director, Joshua Salzman has elicited musically rewarding performances from the talented ensemble. Michael Winther ricochets explosively between selfish and selfless as he captures Marvin's desperate desire to have it all. Liz Larsen is deeply affecting as Trina, the woman left behind, whose struggle to understand her husband's defection pushes her into the loving arms of her rather smarmy (and unprofessional) shrink, played with no holds barred by Mark Nelson. In the role of Jason, young Malcolm Morano is a sheer delight. Rounding out the cast are the handsome, musically gifted Colin Hanlon in the role of Whizzer and the team of Anne L. Nathan and Sarah Litzsinger as Charlotte and Cordelia.</p>
        <p>Reunions with old friends are fraught with danger. This time, the risk is worth taking.</p>
        <p>''Falsettos'' is at George Street Playhouse, 9 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick, through May 6. Information: (732) 246-7717 or www.gsponline.org.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
