<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dream Catchers</title>
    <meta content="merrow" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Education Life Supplement" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842062"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="COMMUNITY COLLEGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vocational Training</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E6DF1F3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="4352" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dream Catchers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By John Merrow</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Merrow, John</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MATTERS were simpler 100 years ago, when junior colleges were created to prepare deserving students for the final two years of a university. In fact, the very first public junior college, in Joliet, Ill., was set up in a high school, as the equivalent of grades 13 and 14.</p>
        <p>Community colleges today do far more than offer a ladder to the final years. They train the people who repair your furnace, install your plumbing, take your pulse. They prepare retiring baby boomers for second or third careers, and provide opportunities for a growing number of college-age students turning away from the high cost and competition at universities. And charged with doing the heavy remedial lifting, community colleges are now as much 10th and 11th grade as 13th and 14th.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MATTERS were simpler 100 years ago, when junior colleges were created to prepare deserving students for the final two years of a university. In fact, the very first public junior college, in Joliet, Ill., was set up in a high school, as the equivalent of grades 13 and 14.</p>
        <p>Community colleges today do far more than offer a ladder to the final years. They train the people who repair your furnace, install your plumbing, take your pulse. They prepare retiring baby boomers for second or third careers, and provide opportunities for a growing number of college-age students turning away from the high cost and competition at universities. And charged with doing the heavy remedial lifting, community colleges are now as much 10th and 11th grade as 13th and 14th.</p>
        <p>It's a long to-do list on a tightening public purse. Two-year colleges receive less than 30 percent of state and local financing for higher education, according to the American Association of Community Colleges. Yet they are growing much faster than four-year colleges and universities, enrolling nearly half of all undergraduates. That's 6.6 million students. Add those taking just a course or two, and the total reaches some 12 million.</p>
        <p>Kay M. McClenney, director of the annual Community College Survey of Student Engagement, calls America's two-year colleges ''today's Ellis Island,'' because they serve a disproportionate number of immigrants, first-generation citizens and minorities.</p>
        <p>While filming a documentary for PBS, ''Discounted Dreams: High Hopes and Harsh Realities at America's Community Colleges,'' my colleagues and I visited dozens of classrooms across the country and met with hundreds of students whose stories reveal the possibilities and limitations of community colleges.</p>
        <p>On these pages are four of the students -- and the dreams they are chasing.</p>
        <p>MIDLIFE, STARTING OVER  The wait list for nursing programs can be years long. Brian Bullas 'won the lottery.'</p>
        <p>It says something about Brian Bullas that he participated, twice, in Hawaii's Ironman Triathlon -- a 140-mile endurance course suitable for only the most fit and the most driven. You might not know that about Mr. Bullas by watching him on the job, mixing drinks on the working side of the bar at the Marine Room, a clubby, candlelit restaurant with floor-to-ceiling windows overlooking San Diego harbor.</p>
        <p>''I probably see 300 sunsets a year out these windows,'' he said one recent dusk, jovial and relaxed. ''I've been medicating people for 26 years, and now I'll finally get to do it the right way.''</p>
        <p>At 51, he is determined to redefine himself. With his wife working days, bartending seemed a logical career choice when his son was small. Today, he has a different view. ''As good as it's been, bartending has been a pretty stagnant job,'' he said. ''I think I can give more to myself and to my family and to society by trying a new career that I think I'm going to be good at.''</p>
        <p>After graduating from San Diego City College next month and passing the licensing exam, Mr. Bullas will be a registered nurse. He will be in great demand, because the country desperately needs nurses. The national shortfall, of about 6 percent, is particularly acute in California. A 2006 report by the Hospital Association of Southern California estimates that the state currently needs 22,500 registered nurses and predicted a shortage of 116,000 by 2020. Two-year institutions train some 60 percent of the nation's new nurses.</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Bullas says he ''won the lottery'' when he was able to start classes. He did get lucky: three of four applicants to City's nursing program are accepted but are immediately placed on a waiting list. There just isn't enough room.</p>
        <p>''They're qualified, we tell them they're qualified, but then they have to go off and flip burgers or tend bar or do whatever, until their number comes up,'' says Terrence Burgess, the college president. ''It's not uncommon up and down the state to have wait lists that go two and three years out.'' He adds, ''We refer to it as our five-year plan.'' That is, considering the prerequisites, which most applicants need to take, and at least a year on the waiting list, a nursing education can easily take half a dozen years.</p>
        <p>For colleges, granting nursing degrees is a losing proposition. Classes require expensive equipment and must be small. They can cost three times as much as a chalk-and-talk class, Mr. Burgess says, but the state pays the college the same per-student rate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bullas chose this route because City's nursing classes are scheduled for the convenience of working adults and because the cost is low.</p>
        <p>Community colleges attract a lot of men and women like Brian Bullas. In a study conducted by ACT Inc. and the American Association of Community Colleges, more than 35 percent of students indicated that changing careers was the major reason they were taking classes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bullas already has a degree in sociology from the University of San Diego, where he played varsity baseball. He was drafted by the Oakland A's but played only in the minors and Canada, he says, before turning to restaurant work and bartending. The road to where he is today has been a triathlon of classwork and clinical and personal responsibilities -- eight hours two days a week at the hospital and two in the classroom; four or five nights, eight hours a night, at the Marine Room. ''I have a couple of days where I carpool kids to school, do the shopping, and help out with homework when I can with my son,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The stress, just getting through it, shows in his face. It helps that his wife (''a saint'') has a good job managing a health club. ''I do keep in contact with her to let her know where I am and what I'm doing,'' he said, laughing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bullas has studied in a parking lot, waiting for his son at baseball or basketball or water polo; he does schoolwork behind the bar when it's slow. ''They let you know that you should have a book in your car at all times,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He is a focused learner who furiously takes notes during a demonstration of an IV pole. Afterward, he goes up to the teacher to ask questions.</p>
        <p>He thinks about that day when he will enter a patient's room for the first time on his own. ''I know I'm going to have support,'' he said. ''But I also know that the patient's life is in my hand, and I want to be sure I've done my homework.''</p>
        <p>LIFELONG LEARNING  What 'Salsa Dancing' taught a hairstylist, besides rhythm.</p>
        <p>A t a strip mall in Joliet, an hour's drive southwest of Chicago, 19-year-old Stacey Jurgens spends long days on her feet styling hair. One evening a week, she escapes to the cavernous, faded banquet hall of an old hotel, now part of Joliet Junior College. ''I love Latin music, the beats and the rhythm,'' she said. ''Dancing to the music sets me free.''</p>
        <p>Her classmates, none as accomplished on the dance floor as she, include a 51-year-old store manager whose wife drags him there and a construction company manager and his girlfriend, who wanted to try something new. ''Salsa Dancing'' meets six times and costs $74.</p>
        <p>This is Ms. Jurgens's fourth evening class. ''I took a beginner salsa class with my dad,'' she said, ''and that was so much fun I signed up for 'Hip-Hop Dancing' and 'Advanced Salsa.' '' Ms. Jurgens is participating in what community college catalogs call continuing education or, in the latest jargon, lifelong learning. At Cuyahoga Community College, in Cleveland, students play simulated versions of classic game shows in ''Game Show Fun'' or learn to ''connect'' in ''Conversations That Matter.'' One flight down from the dance class in Joliet, six women attempt to master the art of decorating cookies; a few doors away a chef teaches other adult students how to make hors d'oeuvres.</p>
        <p>Critics say such courses divert institutional energy and attention away from the college's essential missions. ''If the community wants adult education, most community colleges say, 'We'll do that.' If the community wants cooking courses, they say, 'We'll do that,' '' says Michael W. Kirst, an emeritus professor of education at Stanford and director of the Bridge Project, a nonprofit organization seeking to get more low-income and minority students to college. ''Before long they get to the point where they now do almost anything and everything a community wants, but none of it very well.''</p>
        <p>What he calls ''mission creep,'' Kay McClenney, of the Community College Survey of Student Engagement, calls ''comprehensive mission.'' Continuing ed can be a profit center that supports items shortchanged in public financing, like the library or gym. It's good community politics, too, she says. ''Therefore, you will find community colleges operating wineries and golf courses and doing a whole lot of contractual training for employers,'' she says. ''They end up offering wine-tasting classes and charging a boatload of money for them.''</p>
        <p>Thom Price, dean of community and economic development at Joliet, says that the most profitable noncredit offerings are not personal development like ''Salsa Dancing'' but professional development, the work force training requested by local businesses.</p>
        <p>Ms. McClenney could be thinking of City College of San Francisco's one-day wine workshops, including ''France and Italy vs. California'' ($40) and ''Basics for Beginners'' ($40). Noncredit continuing education contributes more than $350,000 to City's budget each year, says Robert Gabriner, its vice chancellor.</p>
        <p>Wine tasting makes sense in a wine region, and Excel class makes sense anywhere. But Ms. McClenney draws the line at ''Great Ghost Stories'' and ''Game Show Fun.'' ''There are places where you have to exercise judgment. We shouldn't offer classes in 'How to Bet on Horse Races,' but I know a community college that did.''</p>
        <p>Stacey Jurgens has found a community at her dance classes. ''They just bring people together, and they're a great way to meet new people,'' she said. Did she mean a boyfriend? ''Probably,'' she said, laughing. ''But not as good as church. I have a boyfriend, a musician who loves to dance, and I met him at church.''</p>
        <p>After graduating from high school, Ms. Jurgens went to commercial beauty school. Inspired by her mother, who is now attending Joliet full time to become an X-ray technician, Ms. Jurgens enrolled in an evening class in entrepreneurship. ''It's opened my eyes to the kind of things I could do.''</p>
        <p>She could see herself, now, for example, opening a hair salon.</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY COLLEGE</p>
        <p>A HARSH REALITY  Krystal Jenkins failed and failed and failed math, and then failed again.</p>
        <p>Math 096 covers a lot in a short time, mostly 9th- and 10th-grade material eight hours a week for six weeks. ''You can't afford to miss a class,'' George McCormack, who teaches it at LaGuardia Community College, in Queens, warned his students as the intersession intensive revved up early last year. ''This is a demanding course, there's no question about it.''</p>
        <p>Krystal Jenkins, now 20, knew he was telling the truth. She had already failed remedial math three times with three different teachers, but until she passed basic algebra, she could not take courses in her major.</p>
        <p>Ms. Jenkins has always wanted to be a veterinarian. Even after having a baby as a high school sophomore and settling for a G.E.D., she did not give up on the dream. ''I've always loved animals,'' she said. ''I feel I was put on earth to be a vet, and my daughter is my motivation.''</p>
        <p>So she decided on this different approach: a concentrated course. ''If I do not pass,'' she said. ''I probably will stop going to school.''</p>
        <p>According to the most recent federal statistics, 42 percent of public community college freshmen take remedial courses. Experts insist the number is vastly higher, because data collection is spotty. At LaGuardia and Joliet Junior College, for example, 80 percent of new students must take at least one catch-up course in math, reading or writing, based on a placement test. At LaGuardia, only about 46 percent make it through in reading, 41 percent in math. Remedial students can take the same course over and over until they pass, get discouraged and quit, or run out of money.</p>
        <p>LaGuardia offered Ms. Jenkins a chance to fulfill her dream. It will admit anyone with a diploma or equivalent and has a strong program for veterinary technicians, the animal world's equivalent of a nurse. But vet tech is math-heavy. Becoming an actual vet requires a bachelor's degree and four years at a school of veterinary medicine.</p>
        <p>After a few classes, Ms. Jenkins was feeling confident. She seemed to be doing better, with a 72 on her first big test. ''I'd say it's 90 percent sure that I will pass this time,'' she said. ''I'm very determined to pass the class. That's why I come every morning on time. No matter how tired I am, I still wake up and come to school.''</p>
        <p>But she left the midterm exam early, feeling frustrated. ''I really didn't understand the questions and I couldn't really get the answers, so basically I kind of guessed, guessed most of them.'' She said she hadn't been able to study the night before because she was exhausted.</p>
        <p>Nor had she gone to her teacher for help.</p>
        <p>''I don't have other time, the extra time to go study, and sit down and review my notes and stuff,'' she said. ''I'm on my feet seven-and-a-half hours a day.'' In addition to doing her job checking groceries, Ms. Jenkins had to travel close to three hours a day -- from home in the Bronx to school to work and back, usually after 10:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>Like many other community college students, Krystal Jenkins is a full-time parent with a full-time job and a full-time course load. She is close to the edge financially. She shares a small two-bedroom apartment with her parents, her boyfriend, her 4-year-old daughter, a gerbil and a cat. And she is behind academically.</p>
        <p>Kay McClenney, of the Community College Survey of Student Engagement, calls remedial education ''job one'' for two-year colleges. Yet 79 percent of remedial classes are taught by part-time faculty, according to a new study published in Research in Developmental Education.</p>
        <p>In my visits to remedial classrooms around the country, I saw students wearing headphones, text-messaging and reading nonclass material during class time. On one occasion a class that began with 20 students had only six after the break. Most of the teachers told me they had not been trained to work with at-risk students. They were biology or English majors and, in one case, a college's full-time Webmaster.</p>
        <p>Classrooms like these do not surprise Nancy Shulock, who studies community colleges. A professor at Sacramento State University, she says two-year colleges ''are trying to do remediation on the cheap.''</p>
        <p>Her analysis: ''They don't have the money, and they don't have the money because society thinks that it is cheap. It's a circular logic that's not going to get us out of this box.''</p>
        <p>Mike Kirst of Stanford calls for more accountability. ''We don't know exactly how many students they take who could have succeeded with better teaching.'' He cites what economists call the churn model, in which success is unrewarded and failure unpunished. ''As long as the number of students coming in the front equals the number of students dropping out the back door and side door, their enrollment and full-time equivalence is the same, whether they're advancing and graduating or flunking out.'' Because demand is high, he says, ''there is really no incentive to spend a lot of the money to serve these students with special counselors and trained teachers.''</p>
        <p>Fewer than half of the remedial classes at LaGuardia are taught by full-time faculty. But Mr. McCormack, Ms. Jenkins's teacher, is full time and trained in remedial education. He earned his doctorate in mathematics education at Teachers College at Columbia University and has been teaching math at LaGuardia for four years. Ms. Jenkins called him the best teacher she had had. He moved easily around Ms. Jenkins's classroom, urging students to ask questions and solve problems.</p>
        <p>On the day of her final, Krystal Jenkins was nowhere to be found. We discovered her at her apartment that afternoon. She had skipped the exam. ''It all came crashing down,'' she said. ''The whole semester I've been doing so much at one time, and I couldn't deal with it anymore. I just wasn't strong enough to handle it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McCormack allowed her to take the test several days later. Still she did not pass, though 25 of the 31 students enrolled did well enough to move on. Ms. Jenkins dropped out of LaGuardia. Expecting her second child at the end of May, she now works at an Old Navy store and says she still owes the college $2,035.</p>
        <p>What happened here? Should Ms. Jenkins have been counseled into making a more realistic career choice? Would a different approach to instruction have made the material stick?</p>
        <p>Professor Shulock admits the obvious but asks for understanding: ''Community colleges are unprepared to teach the unprepared,'' she says, ''but who is doing it better?''</p>
        <p>LaGuardia, which is part of the City University of New York, won the MetLife Foundation Community College Excellence Award for 2006, for innovative programs for underserved students. It is one of 13 colleges and universities cited as an ''Institution of Excellence'' by the Policy Center on the First Year of College. Among various services, it provides free tutoring at math labs.</p>
        <p>Gail Mellow, the president, offers this explanation: ''We have lots of innovations but no resources to bring them to scale. If we get half of the students like Krystal through, given our resources, that's amazing.''</p>
        <p>This semester, LaGuardia started a pilot program to try to bring in -- for special tutoring, advising and evaluations -- students who have failed remedial math more than once. Only students who are doing adequately in other courses are being contacted (those with an overall G.P.A. of 2.0 -- 70, all told).</p>
        <p>The focus is on math, says Cindy Freidmutter, vice president for external and community affairs, because it's an anxiety-producing ''stumbling block.'' Many remedial students have been away from classroom math for some time and need a refresher, she says; others, like Krystal Jenkins with her G.E.D., missed out on years of basic high school math.</p>
        <p>Ms. Jenkins, who said she had a G.P.A. of 2.9, could have benefited from the new initiative. She said she visited the counseling office two or three times. ''I got a little card telling me I had to come in, so I went in with a list of classes I wanted to take, and they just said O.K.'' Did anyone discuss her plans or ask how she was doing? ''No,'' Ms. Jenkins said, simply.</p>
        <p>''She did not make it,'' Ms. Mellow says, ''but many do, and they are heroes.'' It's a matter of taking advantage of resources and making time for study. ''Krystal would never be able to make it through remedial math if she couldn't dedicate at least 15 hours a week of work at home.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Mellow says she does not favor interfering with what educators call ''the right to fail.'' LaGuardia caps the number of times a student can take college-level courses at two. But like most community colleges, it does not restrict the number of times a student can take a developmental course.</p>
        <p>''Who are we to say a student shouldn't keep on trying?'' Ms. Mellow says.</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY COLLEGE</p>
        <p>THE SMART TRANSFER  How to graduate from N.Y.U. (or Amherst or Stanford) at half the cost.</p>
        <p>Reshma Tharani, 21, is part of a new breed of community college student: right out of high school, determined to save money, knowledge able about the ways of the system.</p>
        <p>She expects to graduate next month from New York University, prepared to teach either special education or elementary school. N.Y.U. is one of the nation's most expensive colleges (tuition, room and board come to around $50,000 a year), but she has managed to pay a fraction of that.</p>
        <p>Her strategy: she lived at home, worked part-time jobs, including telemarketing, and paid less than $2,000 a semester at Nassau Community College on Long Island.</p>
        <p>I found Ms. Tharani in her classroom at Public School 3 in Greenwich Village, where she is a student teacher. A half-dozen second and third graders were taking turns reading a story. After each one read aloud, she asked questions, trying, she later explained, ''to make sure they were really comprehending what they were reading.''</p>
        <p>She had always intended to go to a four-year college but waffled on which one. ''So I decided to go to community college and take care of my prerequisites and get my first degree.''</p>
        <p>She took some of her requirements during summer and winter breaks to allow time, she said, to ''take some psychology and math classes I was really interested in'' during the school year.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tharani's parents came to the United States from India about 40 years ago. They met and married here and now own a wholesale clothing business. Ms. Tharani is the first in her family to attend college. In that, she resembles 39 percent of community college students. Her younger brother goes to Boston College.</p>
        <p>''As the tuition has been going up more steeply in four-year institutions, community colleges are an increasingly attractive alternative for savvy kids who want to save money, '' says Prof. Nancy Shulock, of Sacramento State University. ''They know what they need, know how to get it, and don't need a lot of the student services community colleges are struggling to provide students. They can get through in two or three years and transfer.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Tharani saw an academic counselor regularly. ''There were lines, but I always managed to see the same woman,'' she said. She took only courses that the Nassau counselor said N.Y.U. would accept for credit, but, just to be sure, she double-checked with N.Y.U.</p>
        <p>A favorite professor suggested she apply for a scholarship from the Community College Transfer Opportunity Program, designed to attract transfers from 13 area community colleges to the Steinhardt School of Culture, Education and Human Development at N.Y.U. Ms. Tharani graduated cum laude from Nassau and won $20,000 a year for her junior and senior years.</p>
        <p>A number of prestigious private institutions encourage transfers. Richard H. Shaw, dean of admissions at Stanford, calls community college transfer applicants mature and interesting candidates. Every year Stanford has 1,400 to 1,600 applicants for about 70 openings in the junior class. This year 26 percent of those accepted came from community colleges, he says.</p>
        <p>Amherst aggressively recruits community college transfers, says Thomas H. Parker, its dean of admissions and financial aid. The Jack Kent Cooke Foundation provides scholarships of up to $30,000 a year to transfer students. One of this year's 38 recipients is attending Amherst. The foundation is also doling out almost $7 million in grants -- to Amherst, Mount Holyoke, Bucknell, Cornell, the University of Michigan, the University of North Carolina, the University of Southern California and the University of California, Berkeley -- ''to more effectively reach out to high-achieving community college students.''</p>
        <p>But access to the high end is not necessarily a shoo-in. In a 2006 report, the Cooke Foundation found that the number of community college students entering the most competitive institutions had declined (from 10.5 percent in 1984 to 5.7 percent in 2002 at private colleges and from 22.2 to 18.8 percent at public ones).</p>
        <p>Depending on what measures are used, only about 35 percent to 50 percent of potential transfers make it, according to a Department of Education study. A major hurdle is simple confusion. ''A student could be ready to transfer to one institution,'' Ms. Shulock says. ''Then your life circumstances change and you move, only to find that the requirements are different at another college.'' In many states, transferring credits is hit or miss. Unless a two-year college has an articulation agreement that makes a university comfortable with the material covered in its courses, transfer students are not likely to enjoy full credit for their efforts.</p>
        <p>In California, Ms. Shulock says, ''we do not have one standardized set of courses that a community college student can take and know they are transfer-ready to any of the 23 Cal State campuses or the 10 University of California campuses.''</p>
        <p>Where state policy makers have intervened and created incentives, transfer rates are higher. For example, in Florida, students with associate's degrees are automatically admitted to one of the 11 state universities. Apparently, it works: according to David Armstrong, the chancellor of Florida's community colleges, 71 percent of students hoping to transfer actually do; an additional 4 to 6 percent transfer into private or out-of-state colleges. Programs to draw community college transfers have also been developed at the State University of New York, the University of Virginia, the University of California at Davis and the University of Michigan.</p>
        <p>There is a certain paradox when two-year colleges educate savvy students like Reshma Tharani. If more college-ready students begin their postsecondary careers at community colleges, transfer rates will improve. Community colleges will be doing what they were established to do -- except some of those most in need of the stepladder will be turned away.</p>
        <p>When the number of applicants becomes overwhelming, says George R. Boggs, president of the American Association of Community Colleges, ''the students who register last are turned away, and that's usually first-generation and economically poorer individuals who do not know how to navigate the system.''</p>
        <p>He adds, ''It will be a real test of the will of state policy makers to be sure the doors remain open to those who seek a community college education.''</p>
        <p>So how does Ms. Tharani compare her two experiences? ''I had great professors at both places,'' she said, ''but at Nassau I never had any huge classes, where no one knows your name. And when I hear friends talking about all the loans they'll have to pay back, it makes me feel even better about my decision.''</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY COLLEGE John Merrow reports on education for ''The NewsHour With Jim Lehrer'' and is a visiting scholar at the Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching. Carrie Glasser, Shae Isaacs and David Wald contributed reporting for this article.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">John Merrow reports on education for ''The NewsHour With Jim Lehrer'' and is a visiting scholar at the Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching. Carrie Glasser, Shae Isaacs and David Wald contributed reporting for this article.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
