<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Grange Hall, Preservation vs. Development</title>
    <meta content="22coynenjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/22coynenj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842092"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="JERSEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Meyersville (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaufman, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Coyne, Kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E6DA1F3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="860" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Grange Hall, Preservation vs. Development</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At Grange Hall, Preservation vs. Development</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Kevin Coyne</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Coyne, Kevin</byline>
      <dateline>Meyersville</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kevin Coyne Jersey column on scene at Grange Hall No 188 in Meyersville, NJ, as residents and planning board officials discuss hamlet's land-use ordinances; Bill Kaufman, architect who has purchased property in middle of town, wants to build pedestrian-friendly residential 'eco-village'; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE last grange left in Morris County, Meyersville Grange No. 188, lost its farmers decades ago but has persisted as a social organization and, perhaps more important, as an ideal about what residents believe life should look like in these rolling hills beside the Great Swamp.</p>
        <p>The grange hall is about the size and shape of a country schoolhouse, with knotty pine walls and a pressed-tin ceiling, and it backs up onto the national wildlife refuge, almost 8,000 acres where the main residents are otters and egrets, foxes and herons. One recent evening the hall's long tables were already laid with bowls and ladles for a scheduled soup and pasta competition, but the 100 people who filled the rows of folding chairs had something more pressing on their minds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As residents in Meyersville, N.J., try to balance preservation against development, the questions that are raised have become more complex.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE last grange left in Morris County, Meyersville Grange No. 188, lost its farmers decades ago but has persisted as a social organization and, perhaps more important, as an ideal about what residents believe life should look like in these rolling hills beside the Great Swamp.</p>
        <p>The grange hall is about the size and shape of a country schoolhouse, with knotty pine walls and a pressed-tin ceiling, and it backs up onto the national wildlife refuge, almost 8,000 acres where the main residents are otters and egrets, foxes and herons. One recent evening the hall's long tables were already laid with bowls and ladles for a scheduled soup and pasta competition, but the 100 people who filled the rows of folding chairs had something more pressing on their minds.</p>
        <p>''How many people are really concerned about the future of Meyersville?'' asked Tom Behr, chairman of the local zoning board, and every hand went up.</p>
        <p>Meyersville is a hamlet within Long Hill Township that radiates out from a tiny, incongruous traffic circle: a church and graveyard, a pair of restaurants, a convenience store that closes at 5:30, an antiques shop, a few houses from the 18th century and many more from the late 20th. All the open space in the neighboring refuge makes it easy for residents here to forget they are living in the nation's most densely populated state, just 20 miles down the Gladstone Line from Newark.</p>
        <p>''This has always been more rural in feeling, even if not in reality,'' said Cecilia Cilli, a 37-year resident who recently organized a citizens' group called Meyersville411 in response to a retail and residential development proposal she fears may change that. ''It's a very special place, and we know how vulnerable it is.''</p>
        <p>With the Great Swamp on one side and a wooded ridge on the other that separates it from the rest of Long Hill, Meyersville has always felt like an island, better fortified against the developers who brought town houses and shopping strips to Valley Road on the other side of town. ''But the pressure from all the surrounding communities is squeezing this one, and it's going to burst,'' said Bill Kaufman, who has an architectural firm in Millington, another section of Long Hill. His purchase last year of a pair of properties in the middle of Meyersville, totaling around two acres, set the hamlet buzzing more loudly than it had since a failed attempt to build town houses in the same spot almost 20 years ago.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaufman, 40, has submitted no plans yet, but enough people were worried about what might happen that the planning board arranged the meeting to discuss what protections the township's land-use ordinances did, and did not, offer against any future development.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaufman sat quietly in the back of the grange hall, listening as the residents discussed the holes in the township's master plan -- a self-described environmentalist uncomfortably cast as an agent of the sprawl he says he opposes, an object lesson in how difficult it is to imagine new ways of using land in a state with so little of it left.</p>
        <p>To him, Meyersville would make a perfect spot for what he called a pedestrian-friendly residential ''ecovillage'' of an undetermined size, with environmentally friendly building materials and an artificial marsh to treat the wastewater. ''It's a hamlet that would provide an opportunity to reduce the effects of sprawl,'' said Mr. Kaufman, who likes to quote Thomas Jefferson and is particularly fond of the word ''sustainable.''</p>
        <p>To the residents, though, a couple of nice stores or restaurants may be fine, but more housing sounds too much like Valley Road, on the other side of the ridge. ''I don't want to see any changes, really -- I want to go back,'' said Gus Schmidt, 77, who lives in a house his father built, and whose mother, Mary, 95, will soon be presented with an 85-year membership pin from Grange No. 188. '' 'Changes' to me means more of everything -- more traffic, more people.''</p>
        <p>Current zoning, though, would not prevent a chain drugstore, say, from leveling the early-closing convenience store or an auto-repair garage from replacing the antiques shop, as Len Hamilton, a member of the planning board, explained to the crowd. ''I think we wouldn't at all like what could happen to Meyersville under the master plan ordinance we have,'' Mr. Hamilton said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaufman finally stood and addressed the crowd, though he hadn't planned to. ''We've been on your side since Day 1, fighting against the desecration of our environment,'' he said, and the way he spoke seemed to soothe some fears.</p>
        <p>But the questions raised by his ideas for Meyersville, like the questions raised in communities all over New Jersey struggling to balance preservation against development, seemed more complex than ever. Everybody agreed to meet again in two weeks, to talk about it some more.</p>
        <p>And the grange hall -- with its fading photos of past masters and its blue and gold ''1950 Grangerettes Champions'' banner and its framed charter dating to 1909 -- seemed as good a place as any to try to figure out how the future should look.</p>
        <p>JERSEY E-mail: jersey@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: jersey@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
