<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bluetooth Plays Matchmaker: M3, Meet MP3</title>
    <meta content="22BLUETOOTH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/automobiles/22BLUETOOTH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842094"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Automobile Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wireless Communications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Bluetooth Special Interest Group</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE6DA1F3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1161" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bluetooth Plays Matchmaker: M3, Meet MP3</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bluetooth Plays Matchmaker: M3, Meet MP3</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN R. QUAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Quain, John R</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FEW people get behind the wheel alone anymore. Many drivers wouldn't dare pull away from the curb without their cellphone, iPod or P.D.A. -- mobile devices essential to life on the move, though not necessarily designed for use in cars.</p>
        <p>To make the devices better, less distracting driving companions, more carmakers and electronics companies are using Blue-tooth technology, which wirelessly connects phones to a headset or to the car's sound system. Bluetooth is becoming the wireless standard in vehicles, and it has ambitions far beyond hands-free cellphone use.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The use of wireless technology to make mobile devices into less distracting companions is growing, and it has ambitions beyond hands-free cellphones.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FEW people get behind the wheel alone anymore. Many drivers wouldn't dare pull away from the curb without their cellphone, iPod or P.D.A. -- mobile devices essential to life on the move, though not necessarily designed for use in cars.</p>
        <p>To make the devices better, less distracting driving companions, more carmakers and electronics companies are using Blue-tooth technology, which wirelessly connects phones to a headset or to the car's sound system. Bluetooth is becoming the wireless standard in vehicles, and it has ambitions far beyond hands-free cellphone use.</p>
        <p>The benefit of Bluetooth is that it frees the hands of a driver talking on the phone, though it does not address the larger problem of diverted attention while holding a conversation. It allows users to leave a Bluetooth-equipped cellphone in a pocket or purse and still make and receive phone calls, either with a cordless headset or by using speakers and a microphone built into the vehicle.</p>
        <p>In addition, the voice-activated dialing with today's cellphones can be used through a microphone in the car's headliner with the driver's hands on the wheel.</p>
        <p>One inspiration to use wireless Bluetooth devices in cars was the enactment of hands-free cellphone laws across the country.</p>
        <p>''The laws did help with the visibility and awareness of Bluetooth,'' said Mike Foley, executive director of the Bluetooth Special Interest Group, a nonprofit trade group.</p>
        <p>California, Connecticut, New Jersey, New York and Washington, D.C., have all passed laws mandating the use of hands-free systems for cellphone calls. Municipalities from Florida to Utah have similar laws.</p>
        <p>Named for a 10th-century king credited with uniting warring factions of Denmark, Norway and Sweden, Bluetooth was designed to allow devices to communicate across distances of 30 feet or less.</p>
        <p>Today, every major cellphone maker includes this radio-frequency technology. And there is a wide variety of rechargeable Bluetooth headsets available from companies like Jabra, Logitech, Motorola, Nokia and Sony Ericsson. Many, however, are not designed strictly for motorists. When the headsets lose their power, for example, users often have to wait until they are at the office or home to recharge the device.</p>
        <p>One exception is Plantronics's Discovery 665 Bluetooth Headset, which costs $150 and comes with a folding cigarette lighter charger. The tiny in-ear Discovery also uses a digital signal processor to reduce road and wind noise.</p>
        <p>Not everybody is comfortable driving with something stuck in their ear, so some automakers are offering Bluetooth as part of integrated systems. BMW, DaimlerChrysler, Ford, Honda, Nissan and Toyota offer Bluetooth in some models. The factory-installed systems allow drivers to take a call with the push of a button, like a speaker phone, while the system automatically mutes the car's sound system.</p>
        <p>One notable laggard in Bluetooth adoption has been General Motors, which has favored its own wireless OnStar system. Only G.M.'s Cadillac STS has Bluetooth, but that may be about to change. G.M. ''is developing Bluetooth in a wide range of products,'' said Pete Barkey, a company spokesman. He declined to provide a timetable for its introduction in other models.</p>
        <p>Other carmakers and consumer electronics companies are looking to expand Bluetooth's wireless possibilities.</p>
        <p>''The original scenario was purely hands-free operation,'' said Mr. Foley, the trade group executive. ''Now it's pretty common to be able to synchronize a phone's contacts with the car setup.'' This allows drivers to dial a number simply by saying the person's name. They can also see who's calling on the vehicle's stereo display.</p>
        <p>More cellphones, music players and headsets are also supporting Bluetooth's Advanced Audio Distribution Profile (A2DP), which allows devices to play stereo music through a car's sound system without wires. Several Samsung phones can play music this way, for example, and iPod owners can purchase adapters like the Jabra A125s. The $60 add-on plugs into the dock connector on an iPod to make the Bluetooth connection.</p>
        <p>Companies that support Bluetooth said there would be more wireless abilities coming in new cars. Ford, for example, is introducing Sync in 13 new models this fall. Using Microsoft software, the Sync system makes extensive use of Bluetooth, including coupling it with basic voice recognition for hands-free dialing commands like, ''Call JQ at work.'' The system also uses Bluetooth to stream music from similarly equipped phones or portable music players. Sync's robotic voice can even read incoming text messages aloud to the driver.</p>
        <p>Microsoft and the Bluetooth alliance foresee additional abilities in the future, including using a cellphone's Internet connection to download local restaurant or hotel information to a car's navigation system. Nick Hunn, chief technology officer of Ezurio, a wireless technology company based near London, said his company was already working with the automotive industry on Bluetooth toll systems, which would obviate the need for E-ZPass-style boxes.</p>
        <p>Bluetooth's ability to tap into a vehicle's diagnostic computer may prove more immediately practical. According to Martin Thall, general manager of Microsoft's automotive business, the Sync software has that ability now, although Ford has not put it to use. He said he believed that Bluetooth could be used to not only discover a problem with, say, a car's transmission, but also be used to download a quick software fix without ever raising the hood. Weekend mechanics already use devices like the $200 Bluetooth-enabled ElmScan 5 Wireless to read diagnostic codes via a car's on-board diagnostics plug.</p>
        <p>The problem with Bluetooth, however, is that making an initial connection between devices can be cumbersome and frustrating if they cannot readily find each other.</p>
        <p>''Bluetooth doesn't always work,'' said David Jurgensen, an automotive consultant with Keystone Motors, a Volvo dealership in Berwyn, Pa. Even with basic cellphone communications, he said, Bluetooth connections will sometimes fail or drop calls, depending on the model of phone. ''But when it works, it's phenomenal.''</p>
        <p>Contributing to those problems is that cellphones have different and sometimes inscrutable software settings. Consumers often waste time clicking through menus on their phones only to discover that once they have found the right setting, the device they are trying to connect to has powered off.</p>
        <p>An update to the Bluetooth specification was announced last month to alleviate that headache. New software should let users click an ''add headset'' option, for example, to connect a phone, said Mr. Foley, and it should be available by the end of the year. Mr. Foley and Mr. Thall of Microsoft see Bluetooth eventually also reaching into the back seat. Hand-held game consoles could wirelessly connect to a network for multiplayer contests or to stream video to multiple screens, for example. But to handle such tasks, Bluetooth will need another upgrade, which is already under way.</p>
        <p>The next release of Bluetooth is expected late next year, according to Mr. Foley, who said it would use a speedier connection known as ultrawideband. Current Bluetooth transmitters can send information at up to 3 megabits a second; the next wideband version will bump that up to a maximum of 480 megabits a second. That's enough to handle video phone calls, games and music.</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
