<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At the Top of the Heap</title>
    <meta content="guidance--counselor22" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Education Life Supplement" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/education/edlife/guidancecounselor22.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842060"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GUIDANCE COUNSELOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Scholarships and Fellowships</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">SAT (College Admission Test)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Equal Educational Opportunities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">SAT (College Admission Test)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">SAT (College Admission Test)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tuition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Equal Educational Opportunities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Scholarships and Fellowships</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Scholarships and Fellowships</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">College Board</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE7DF1F3FF931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1566" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At the Top of the Heap</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At the Top of the Heap</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Louise Tutelian</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tutelian, Louise</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT has a nice ring to it, doesn't it? ''National Merit Scholar.'' Don't even think about it unless you can test in the top 1 percent, have earned spectacular grades and demonstrated leadership potential.</p>
        <p>So lofty is the designation that you don't even have to win it to bask in its glow. Letters of commendation, which go to students who don't make it past the early rounds, can pave the way to honors programs and internships. Semifinalists get their names in hometown papers. Finalists are courted by well-known universities, which publicize how many winners they have nabbed for each incoming class.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>8,200 high school students who didn’t sleep in on a Saturday morning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT has a nice ring to it, doesn't it? ''National Merit Scholar.'' Don't even think about it unless you can test in the top 1 percent, have earned spectacular grades and demonstrated leadership potential.</p>
        <p>So lofty is the designation that you don't even have to win it to bask in its glow. Letters of commendation, which go to students who don't make it past the early rounds, can pave the way to honors programs and internships. Semifinalists get their names in hometown papers. Finalists are courted by well-known universities, which publicize how many winners they have nabbed for each incoming class.</p>
        <p>''In the absence of any other program that's so highly recognized and broad-based, most schools are using it as the marker of an exceptional student,'' says Rod Oto, associate dean of admissions and director of student financial aid at Carleton College, in Northfield, Minn. Carleton admitted 99 National Merit Scholars to a freshman class of 500 this past fall.</p>
        <p>The National Merit Scholarship Corporation, the nonprofit organization that administers the program, is sending out notices through June to the top dogs, the 8,200 high school seniors who have successfully navigated a complicated, highly competitive contest that is about as opaque as the college admissions process itself. These four truths may shed some light.</p>
        <p>1. THE PSAT ISN'T JUST FOR JUNIORS ANYMORE.</p>
        <p>The score on the PSAT/National Merit Scholarship Qualifying Test -- and that score alone -- determines who gets to move up the food chain. The test, at least the one that counts, is taken in October of a student's junior year as a practice run for the SAT (the ''P,'' after all, is for preliminary). But to get a jump on the competition, many sophomores now take run-up tests for the run-up test. If an early score -- 200 or above -- suggests they have a shot at a scholarship, they prep in earnest.</p>
        <p>In fact, the College Board, which administers the PSAT/NMSQT, actively encourages younger students to take this 11th-grade test to get them ''thinking about college.'' About 140 school districts in eight states pay for their sophomores, freshmen and even eighth-graders to do so. Almost 43 percent of 10th graders, 10 percent of ninth graders and 2 percent of eighth graders took the PSAT in 2005.</p>
        <p>Impressed by a College Board presentation on the information educators can glean from PSAT results, the Centerville School District, near Dayton, Ohio, opened the test to the district's seventh, eighth and ninth graders in October, and more than 300 took it. ''Once kids hit high school, they have very limited time to prepare for these tests,'' says Karen Bryan, who coordinates gifted services for the district. ''This is a way to give them practice before they get too busy.'' The district also offers a semester-long elective through its English departments to test-prep 9th and 10th graders.</p>
        <p>Josh Bornstein, executive director of The Princeton Review's Northern New Jersey office, says the number of students taking PSAT prep courses has doubled in the Northeast and on the West Coast.</p>
        <p>This is not good news to guidance counselors like Robert Sweeney, who is ''concerned by the number of 10th graders taking the test.'' He says that about 70 percent of 10th graders take the PSAT at his school, Mamaroneck High School in suburban New York. Six Mamaroneck students have attained National Merit Scholar status in the past five years.</p>
        <p>''I don't see any reason to prep for the PSAT,'' he says, ''because of all the time and energy being taken away from courses, activities and living their lives.'' He advocates treating it only as a baseline from which to gauge how much to study for the real test, the SAT.</p>
        <p>Will scads of prepping improve your chances of becoming a semifinalist? That depends on whether you ask the prep company (a lot) or the test company (not much). The College Board knows only that performance improves with repeated takings. When the PSAT is first taken sophomore year, junior-year scores improve (on average, 3.3 points in reading, 4.4 in math and 4.1 in writing). But it's not clear whether that's because students are more familiar with the test or because they have had an additional year of learning.</p>
        <p>2. IT'S EASIER IN NEW MEXICO. (SO MOVE?)</p>
        <p>''It's kind of a secret on how you go from one level to the next,'' says Francine E. Block, a private admissions consultant in Holland, Pa. ''You can't predict.''</p>
        <p>It's safe to say that the same superlatives that tip the scales in college admissions also sway National Merit judges, a panel of admissions officers and high school guidance counselors.</p>
        <p>The PSAT is only the starting gate. Semifinalists have to submit grades, SAT scores (which should match the excellence of the PSAT), evidence of extracurricular activities and community involvement, an essay and a recommendation from the school principal.</p>
        <p>But whether you live on the densely populated Northeastern seaboard or on the grassy plains makes a difference.</p>
        <p>To maintain a national balance, the number of semifinalists from each state is proportional to the number of its graduating seniors. That makes it easier for top students in underpopulated states to move up in the competition. New Yorkers who took the test in October, for example, had to score 221 out of 240, while a student in New Mexico got by with a 211 score and in Nevada a 209, according to Elaine Detweiler, a National Merit Scholarship Corporation spokeswoman.</p>
        <p>Sally Rubenstone, a former Smith College admissions officer and co-author of ''Panicked Parents' Guide to College Admissions,'' has seen the fireworks: ''You don't want to be around a mom from Mamaroneck who has just found out her daughter missed the cutoff with a score of 216 while her niece in Nevada with a 214 was in by a mile.''</p>
        <p>3. AWARDS ARE PALTRY, BUT THE RIDE CAN BE FREE.</p>
        <p>There are actually three types of scholarship. All finalists compete for a one-time award of $2,500 from the National Merit Scholarship Corporation. Until this year, only those 2,500 winners had the right to call themselves National Merit Scholars.</p>
        <p>But for the first time this year winners in two secondary categories can claim the title, tripling the number of students carrying the distinction. Company-sponsored scholarships (usually $500 to $2,500) go to 1,100 finalists who are related to employees, who reside in the company's town or who have career plans the company wants to support. College-sponsored scholarships ($500 to $2,000) go to 4,600 finalists who have identified a participating college as their first choice. Students can defer making that call until spring, allowing time to compare what various colleges are offering.</p>
        <p>The scholarship amounts have not exactly kept pace with the cost of college, but even contenders can reap rewards.</p>
        <p>Non-Ivy and large state schools are most likely to court finalists and to buttress a merit award with significant institutional aid, says Mark Kantrowitz, publisher of FinAid.org and co-author of ''FastWeb College Gold: The Step-by-Step Guide to Paying for College.''</p>
        <p>For example, finalists who make the University of Tulsa their first choice are eligible for full tuition and room and board -- a package totaling $112,000 over four years. Sixty-four freshmen received the full ride last fall from Tulsa. ''National Merit finalists are in huge demand,'' says David Hamby, a Tulsa spokesman. ''They have their choice of schools. We work with these students to show them what we can offer, and the financial piece is a part of that.''</p>
        <p>Bradley University, in Peoria, Ill., offers free tuition; the University of Southern California covers at least half. Arizona State University, which touts its ''meteoric rise in National Merit Scholar ranking'' on its Web site (it's now No. 8), tempts finalists from Arizona with $12,500 a year and offers up to $21,500 for out-of-state students -- cash and energy that the student newspaper earlier this semester suggested might better be spent on academics.</p>
        <p>4. MINORITIES STILL LOSE OUT.</p>
        <p>The program has come in for its share of criticism. With this school year, the entire University of California system has withdrawn from sponsoring National Merit Scholarships. The concern was the program's over-reliance on a single test score for eligibility and its under-representation of minority students, who on average score lower on standardized tests than do white students. The National Merit Scholarship Corporation does not provide the racial breakdown of scholars, but Patrick Hayashi, a former associate president of the U.C. system, has studied the scores. He says that 99.7 percent of black, Hispanic and American Indian students do not make it past the first cutoff.</p>
        <p>To critics who blame the National Merit Scholarship program for the lack of minority scholars, Ms. Detweiler says, ''The test is the messenger. It is reporting the difference in achievement levels in different groups. It is not the cause of the differences. We firmly believe that energies and attention should be put toward eliminating the differences, not killing the messenger.''</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, acknowledging a problem, the corporation offers a parallel program for African-American students. The National Achievement Scholarship of $2,500 goes to 700 finalists; 100 additional students get company-sponsored awards.</p>
        <p>Some universities supplement these, too -- Florida Atlantic University, for example, gives Achievement Scholars $3,000 a year; $4,000 goes to Hispanic high scorers named by the College Board's National Hispanic Recognition Program. That program offers no monetary award, but it lets colleges know which students have earned the designation.</p>
        <p>GUIDANCE COUNSELOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
