<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Affordable Europe: Copenhagen</title>
    <meta content="22copenhagenweb" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/22/travel/22copenhagenweb.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842329"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E1D61631F931A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="474" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Affordable Europe: Copenhagen</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Affordable Europe: Copenhagen</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH SHERWOOD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prisbillig -- that's the Danish word for cheap. Unfortunately, it's a word seldom heard in this Nordic city. One culprit is the powerful krone (or weak dollar). Another is the city's skyrocketing style quotient. An explosion of high-end hangouts and high-style buildings by name-brand architects -- including Daniel Libeskind, Jean Nouvel, Zaha Hadid, Henning Larsen and Norman Foster -- have helped make the Danish capital one of the planet's 10 most expensive cities.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay for Under 125 Euros</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ranked among the world’s most expensive cities, Copenhagen doesn’t advertise its bargains.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prisbillig -- that's the Danish word for cheap. Unfortunately, it's a word seldom heard in this Nordic city. One culprit is the powerful krone (or weak dollar). Another is the city's skyrocketing style quotient. An explosion of high-end hangouts and high-style buildings by name-brand architects -- including Daniel Libeskind, Jean Nouvel, Zaha Hadid, Henning Larsen and Norman Foster -- have helped make the Danish capital one of the planet's 10 most expensive cities.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay for Under 125 Euros</p>
        <p>The rooms at the Absalon Hotel(Helgolandsgade 15; 45-33-24-22-11; www.absalonhotel.dk) may be a beige mix of bland carpeting and floral fabrics. But its unbeatable location -- in hip Vesterbro and just steps from Central Station and the Tivoli amusement park -- puts the Absalon a cut above its lower-cost competitors. Throw in extras like Wi-Fi and breakfast, and you have the makings of a decent Danish deal. For travelers on a very tight budget, the hotel's annex (simpler rooms, shared bathrooms) is an even better value. Doubles in the annex start at 790 kroner, about $144 at 5.6 Danish kroner to $1, or 106 euros (the Internet rate is 710 kroner). Standard hotel doubles start at 1,360 kroner (Internet rate, 1,195 kroner).</p>
        <p>Where to Eat  Why seek out French fare in Scandinavia? Because the gastronomic philanthropists at Les Trois Cochons (Vaernedamsvej 10; 45-33-31-70-55; www.cofoco.dk) are executing it with zest -- and thrift. Housed in a former butcher shop (you can still spy the checkerboard tile floors and window-pane cabinets), this two-year-old nouveau bistro offers impeccable three-course meals for just 250 kroner. The seasonal menu, which changes monthly, recently included French-infused Danish dishes like halibut in mussel broth, beef with mushrooms in red-wine sauce, and roasted suckling pig with carrots, onions and mustard.</p>
        <p>Where to Shop  Don't be fooled by the Italian name. Vero Moda (Ostergade 7-9; 45-33-15-88-15; www.veromoda.com) -- Copenhagen's answer to budget retailers like H&amp;M and Zara -- is thoroughly Danish. Racks brim with bright tops, slim jeans and other trendy fashions for nightclubbers and hipsters who are making do without Daddy's trust fund. (''Sell more at lower prices'' is the store's philosophy.) This year's spring collection unfurls retro-chic 1950s styles that would make Tuesday Weld and Audrey Hepburn proud. Must-haves -- all for under $100 -- include black ruffled corsage dresses (199.95 kroner), scoop-neck baby-doll dresses (259.95 kroner) and shiny silvery purses (129.95 kroner).</p>
        <p>Best Money-Saving Tip  Follow the sound of camera clicks to Copenhagen's most photographed celebrity: the statue of the Little Mermaid. She sits on a rock just offshore from Langeline, a harborside street next to the rampart-surrounded Kastellet. Across town, in the Norrebro district, join the picnickers and sunbathers at the leafy expanses of Assistens Kirkegaard. The picturesque cemetery holds the graves of the Mermaid's creator, Hans Christian Andersen, and the existentialist philosopher Soren Kierkegaard. And neither charges a dime.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
