<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ex-Aide Says Gonzales Discussed Firings</title>
    <meta content="17attorneys" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/washington/17attorneys.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840936"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Justice Department</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Gonzales, Alberto R</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Sampson, D Kyle</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E7D9113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="641" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ex-Aide Says Gonzales Discussed Firings</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ex-Aide Says Gonzales Discussed Firings</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID JOHNSTON; Eric Lipton contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnston, David</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The former top aide to Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales has told Congressional investigators that Mr. Gonzales was ''inaccurate,'' or ''at least not complete'' in asserting that he had no role in the deliberations about individual United States attorneys who were later dismissed, a Democratic senator said Monday.</p>
        <p>The statements by D. Kyle Sampson, the former chief of staff to Mr. Gonzales, during an interview with investigators on Sunday, were made public as the Senate Judiciary Committee postponed a hearing that had been scheduled for Tuesday in which Mr. Gonzales was to appear to defend his actions in the dismissals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The attorney general’s assertions about his involvement were “not complete,” his former top aide told Congressional investigators.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The former top aide to Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales has told Congressional investigators that Mr. Gonzales was ''inaccurate,'' or ''at least not complete'' in asserting that he had no role in the deliberations about individual United States attorneys who were later dismissed, a Democratic senator said Monday.</p>
        <p>The statements by D. Kyle Sampson, the former chief of staff to Mr. Gonzales, during an interview with investigators on Sunday, were made public as the Senate Judiciary Committee postponed a hearing that had been scheduled for Tuesday in which Mr. Gonzales was to appear to defend his actions in the dismissals.</p>
        <p>Senator Patrick J. Leahy, the Vermont Democrat who is the committee's chairman, and Senator Arlen Specter of Pennsylvania, its senior Republican, delayed the hearing until Thursday because of the shooting rampage at Virginia Tech.</p>
        <p>In his interview, Mr. Sampson said under oath that Mr. Gonzales took part in discussions last fall about David C. Iglesias, who was removed as the United States attorney in New Mexico, as well as in a June 2006 meeting that addressed concerns about Carol C. Lam, the United States attorney ousted from her job in San Diego, said Senator Charles E. Schumer, Democrat of New York. Mr. Sampson made similar statements in public testimony to the Judiciary Committee on March 29, but appeared to offer more specifics in the interview.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schumer, who has led the Senate inquiry into the Justice Department's ouster of eight federal prosecutors, said that Mr. Sampson's testimony raised new questions about the accuracy of Mr. Gonzales's previous statements, most recently in testimony released Sunday in advance of the Senate hearing, that he had not taken part in deliberations about individual prosecutors designated for removal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gonzales said in an interview with NBC News on March 26 that he did not recall a White House meeting held in the fall. White House officials confirmed the meeting and that President Bush raised concerns at it about a lack of aggressive voter-fraud investigations in three states, including New Mexico.</p>
        <p>''I don't remember that conversation,'' Mr. Gonzales said in the NBC interview. ''During the process there may have been other conversations about specifically about the performance of U.S. attorneys. But I wasn't involved in the deliberations as to whether or not a particular United States attorney should or should not be asked to resign.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schumer said Monday that Mr. Sampson recalled that in early March, Mr. Gonzales had told him about the White House conversation -- the first time, Mr. Sampson said, that he learned of the president's concern. Mr. Sampson's lawyer, Bradford A. Berenson, declined to comment on the interview.</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Schumer, Mr. Sampson said he believed Mr. Gonzales had attended a June 2006 meeting in which Ms. Lam's removal was discussed. Another official, William W. Mercer, the acting associate attorney general, recalled with greater certainty that Mr. Gonzales was at the meeting, Mr. Schumer said.</p>
        <p>A Justice Department spokesman, Brian Roehrkasse, said there was nothing new in the information Mr. Schumer attributed to Mr. Sampson. He said that Mr. Gonzales's role in discussions about Mr. Iglesias and Ms. Lam had been previously disclosed; that Mr. Gonzales's statements about his lack of recollection about the White House meeting were accurate; and that his accounts of it to Mr. Sampson and others were based on what others had told him, not on his own memory.</p>
        <p>The House Judiciary Committee also moved Monday to expand its investigation, notifying the Justice Department that it was seeking to interview the current United States attorneys from Minnesota, New Mexico, Pennsylvania and Wisconsin.</p>
        <p>One House official said the committee wanted to learn about the February 2006 appointment of Rachel K. Paulose as the United States attorney in Minnesota, particularly the reasons for her move from a post at the department's headquarters.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
