<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AT&amp;T Drops Offer to Invest In Italian Phone Company</title>
    <meta content="17tele" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/business/worldbusiness/17tele.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840963"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">At&amp;t Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Olimpia (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Telecom Italia</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pirelli Spa</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">America Movil</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sylvers, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Italy</location>
        <org class="online_producer">AT&amp;T Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Telecom Italia Spa</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E0D9113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="467" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AT&amp;T Drops Offer to Invest In Italian Phone Company</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">AT&amp;T Drops Offer to Invest in Italian Phone Company</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SYLVERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sylvers, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>MILAN, April 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>AT&amp;T wi</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT&amp;T on Monday withdrew its offer to buy a stake in the company that controls Telecom Italia, the largest Italian telecommunications company, for about two billion euros, or $2.7 billion.</p>
        <p>In a terse statement, AT&amp;T did not give any reason for the decision to pull back its offer to buy a third of the controlling company, Olimpia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT&amp;T is said to have been dissuaded by the intense political pressure in Italy against a sale to a foreign company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT&amp;T on Monday withdrew its offer to buy a stake in the company that controls Telecom Italia, the largest Italian telecommunications company, for about two billion euros, or $2.7 billion.</p>
        <p>In a terse statement, AT&amp;T did not give any reason for the decision to pull back its offer to buy a third of the controlling company, Olimpia.</p>
        <p>But a person who had been briefed on the negotiations but was not authorized to comment on them publicly said AT&amp;T had been dissuaded by the intense political pressure in Italy against a sale to a foreign company.</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T's withdrawal came against the backdrop of an extended Telecom Italia shareholders' meeting on Monday, called to elect a new board and approve last year's financial results. The meeting ran late into the evening as investors lined up for a chance to question management.</p>
        <p>Pirelli, which controls Olimpia, had been in exclusive talks with AT&amp;T and America Móvil, which was also negotiating to buy a one-third stake in Olimpia.</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T will now be able to negotiate with other companies while it tries to work out an accord with America Móvil, the largest cellphone company in Latin America.</p>
        <p>America Móvil said it had not yet decided whether to follow AT&amp;T or continue talking with Pirelli, Reuters reported.</p>
        <p>Telecom Italia has attracted several potential buyers in the last six months, but the only concrete offer came on April 1 from AT&amp;T and America Móvil, which announced their offer to Olimpia at the same time though they were formally acting separately. AT&amp;T owns 9 percent of America Móvil.</p>
        <p>The announcement that the two foreign companies were negotiating to buy control of Telecom Italia set off a wave of objections in Italy by politicians who said the company had strategic importance to the country and should not fall into foreign hands. Although Prime Minister Romano Prodi said he would not step in to block the sale, he and several of his ministers said they hoped that an ''Italian solution'' could be found.</p>
        <p>Had its offer been accepted and approved, AT&amp;T could have gotten, for a relatively modest investment, a strong foothold in Italy's corporate market and an expanded presence in Germany, France and the Netherlands -- countries where Telecom Italia has been building broadband Internet businesses.</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T already sells telecommunications services to some of Europe's largest companies and provides services in Europe for American-based companies.</p>
        <p>Intesa Sanpaolo, a leading Italian bank, said Monday that it might buy a stake in Olimpia.</p>
        <p>The Telecom Italia shareholders' meeting gained particular attention because of the sale negotiations and also because the former chairman, Guido Rossi, resigned two weeks ago after clashing with Pirelli's chairman, Marco Tronchetti Provera, over strategy.</p>
        <p>More than 350 shareholders registered for the meeting, compared with 75 last year, a Telecom Italia spokesman said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
