<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cuomo Says State May Be First to Curb College Lenders</title>
    <meta content="17cuomo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840969"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cuomo, Andrew M (Atty Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Confessore, Nicholas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E7D8113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="592" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cuomo Says State May Be First to Curb College Lenders</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS CONFESSORE; Jonathan D. Glater contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Confessore, Nicholas</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, April 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Atty Gen Andrew M Cuomo and leaders of State Legislature unveil bill that would make New York first state to establish tough new restrictions on relationship between colleges and companies that make tuition loans to their students; legislation, which is expected to pass, would apply to financial institutions offering student loans to New York residents going to colleges in state (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Attorney General Andrew M. Cuomo and leaders of the Legislature unveiled a bill on Monday that state officials said would make New York the first state to establish tough new restrictions on the relationship between colleges and the companies that make tuition loans to their students.</p>
        <p>The legislation would bar lenders from sharing revenue from student loans with colleges, a much criticized practice that has been at the heart of recent investigations by Mr. Cuomo and federal officials into the student-loan industry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Attorney General Andrew M. Cuomo and leaders of the Legislature unveiled a bill on Monday that state officials said would make New York the first state to establish tough new restrictions on the relationship between colleges and the companies that make tuition loans to their students.</p>
        <p>The legislation would bar lenders from sharing revenue from student loans with colleges, a much criticized practice that has been at the heart of recent investigations by Mr. Cuomo and federal officials into the student-loan industry.</p>
        <p>It would also forbid lenders to offer gifts to school officials or name them to corporate advisory boards in exchange for those officials' recommending the companies to students seeking financial aid. Officials serving on such boards would be barred from receiving payments for doing so.</p>
        <p>The measure, which is considered likely to pass because of the support of leaders in both houses, puts New York at the forefront of states in regulating the college loan industry. Attorneys general in California, Ohio, Connecticut and Minnesota have also begun to investigate relationships between lenders and colleges but have yet to propose legislation.</p>
        <p>''Lenders that are being recommended by the colleges are all too often being recommended because they're in the best interest of the college rather than being in the best interest of the student,'' Mr. Cuomo said.</p>
        <p>He appeared Monday with Joseph L. Bruno, the Senate majority leader, and Sheldon Silver, the speaker of the Assembly, who both promised quick passage of the legislation. The Assembly will hold a hearing on the bill next week, Mr. Silver said, to ensure that it ''is thoughtful, it's tough'' and does not create ''unintended consequences.''</p>
        <p>The legislation would apply to financial institutions offering student loans to New York residents going to colleges in the state and would take effect 30 days after passage. Out-of-state lenders engaging in the same kinds of conduct can already be prosecuted under the state's general business law, Mr. Cuomo said.</p>
        <p>Separately, lawyers in the attorney general's office said they had expanded the investigation of practices in the student-loan industry over the weekend, sending out 13 subpoenas or formal letters seeking information from loan companies on their business practices.</p>
        <p>Among the recipients, according to the lawyers, were JP Morgan Chase, Bank of America, Sun Trust, Wells Fargo, Wachovia, Access Group and the College Board, which sponsors the SAT exam.</p>
        <p>Seven colleges and the State University of New York system have already agreed to abide by the new rules as part of settlements they reached earlier this year with Mr. Cuomo's office. Two financial institutions, Citibank and Sallie Mae, have reached settlement agreements with the attorney general's office and have agreed to the new code of conduct.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Mr. Cuomo also announced details of a settlement with a third lender, Education Finance Partners, based in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>Education Finance will adopt the new code of conduct, contribute $2.5 million to a fund devoted to educating college-bound students about their loan options and end its revenue-sharing arrangements with universities. As part of earlier settlement agreements, St. John's University and Fordham University have already agreed to pay back students who took out Education Finance loans that earned money for the colleges under such agreements.</p>
        <p>More than 100 colleges and lenders remain under investigation by the attorney general, who has sought to identify other examples of conduct that he considers improper, including making payments to colleges in exchange for high output of loans, giving cash or stock to financial-aid administrators and paying for the administrators' travel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
