<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>City Releases Work Records For Officer Who Died</title>
    <meta content="17borja" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/nyregion/17borja.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840965"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dust</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Respiratory Diseases</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Borja, Cesar A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chan, Sewell</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Respiratory Diseases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Emphysema</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Emphysema</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Respiratory Diseases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Emphysema</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Borja, Cesar A</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E0D9113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="688" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>City Releases Work Records For Officer Who Died</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">City Releases Work Records for Officer Who Died</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SEWELL CHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chan, Sewell</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Search of New York City files concerning Cesar A Borja, police officer whose death from lung disease was held as example of medical problems affecting thousands of ground zero workers and volunteers, finds no record that he worked in Lower Manhattan until Dec 24, 2001, more than three months after attacks; family has not maintained that he worked at ground zero before December 2001 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A search by the city of its files concerning Cesar A. Borja, the New York City police officer whose death from lung disease was held up as an example of the medical problems affecting thousands of ground zero workers and volunteers, found no record that he worked in Lower Manhattan until Dec. 24, 2001, more than three months after the 9/11 attack.</p>
        <p>The records show that Officer Borja worked for several hours in Brooklyn, near the East River waterfront, on the evening of Sept. 13, 2001, two days after the disaster, during his regular work shift.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A police officer whose death was used as an example of medical problems affecting ground zero workers did not work in Lower Manhattan until December 2001, city records show.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A search by the city of its files concerning Cesar A. Borja, the New York City police officer whose death from lung disease was held up as an example of the medical problems affecting thousands of ground zero workers and volunteers, found no record that he worked in Lower Manhattan until Dec. 24, 2001, more than three months after the 9/11 attack.</p>
        <p>The records show that Officer Borja worked for several hours in Brooklyn, near the East River waterfront, on the evening of Sept. 13, 2001, two days after the disaster, during his regular work shift.</p>
        <p>Officer Borja, 52, died on Jan. 23 this year, hours before his eldest child, Ceasar, attended the State of the Union address to publicize the plight of workers who responded to the World Trade Center attack. The officer had received a diagnosis of pulmonary fibrosis, a rare chronic lung disease that his family believes was caused by exposure to toxic substances in Lower Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Several news organizations reported that Officer Borja had rushed to ground zero after the twin towers fell, but The New York Times reported on Feb. 13 that according to the officer's own records, he did not work a formal shift in Lower Manhattan until Dec. 24, 2001. By then, much of the site had been cleared and the fire in the remaining pile had been declared extinguished.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the city's Law Department released 55 pages of records concerning Officer Borja, in response to requests by The Times and other news organizations under the state's Freedom of Information Law.</p>
        <p>Among the documents that had not been previously released were eight pages from a handwritten command log maintained at the police tow pound in College Point, Queens, where Officer Borja was assigned.</p>
        <p>The command log lists Officer Borja as one of five officers from the pound who worked at Adams and Plymouth Streets, at the Brooklyn end of the Manhattan Bridge, from 6:50 p.m. to 11 p.m., during his regular work hours on Sept. 13, 2001.</p>
        <p>In a February interview, Officer Borja's wife, Eva, recalled that her husband had said he worked in Brooklyn shortly after the attack. The family has not maintained that he worked at ground zero before December 2001.</p>
        <p>The records released yesterday also include a table listing Officer Borja's overtime claims from Sept. 11, 2001, to April 28, 2002. Each entry is given a four-digit code according to the type of overtime claimed. According to the table, Officer Borja did not claim paid overtime for work outside the borough to which he was assigned -- Queens -- until Dec. 24, 2001.</p>
        <p>Both the log and the table note that Officer Borja repeatedly filed for World Trade Center-related overtime, but there is no indication that the overtime was for work at ground zero. The attack had put the city, state and federal governments on high alert, and almost the entire Police Department was mobilized for extra duty for weeks after the disaster.</p>
        <p>The records also include three weeks of roll-call records. The roll calls show Officer Borja working his regular shift, 2:37 to 11 p.m., on Sept. 11, 2001; a different shift, 6 p.m. to 2:23 a.m., on the three following days; and a 12-hour shift, 6 p.m. to 6 a.m. on Sept. 15, a Saturday, which was one of his regular days off. According to the roll calls, Officer Borja took the next week off for vacation before returning to his regular schedule on Sept. 24.</p>
        <p>The city also released 16 assignment sheets yesterday showing that Officer Borja did shifts as part of a ''World Trade Center recovery detail'' around ground zero between Dec. 24, 2001, and April 27, 2002.</p>
        <p>The records show that Officer Borja was one of 35,006 police employees who submitted their names to an ''exposure database'' created by the Police Department's medical division. But officials said the database did not indicate where the employees were stationed on the day of the attack.</p>
        <p>Ceasar Borja, the officer's son, declined to comment yesterday on the newly released records. The officer's widow, Eva, did not respond to a phone message left at her home.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
