<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tax Credit Seen as Helping More Parents</title>
    <meta content="17poor" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/us/17poor.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840939"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tax Credits, Deductions and Exemptions</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eckholm, Erik</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Brookings Institution</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E7D9113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="593" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tax Credit Seen as Helping More Parents</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tax Credit Seen as Helping More Parents</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIK ECKHOLM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eckholm, Erik</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New report finds that more than one in six taxpayers in 2004 received Earned Income Tax Credit, highlighting its growing role in bolstering incomes of struggling low-income parents; amount of credit for low-income parents reaches zero as their incomes hit $38,000; many economists and poverty experts call for equal tax treatment for childless adults and noncustodial fathers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>More than one in six taxpayers in 2004 received the Earned Income Tax Credit, highlighting its growing role in bolstering the incomes of struggling low-income parents, according to a new report.</p>
        <p>The federal credit, which offers tax refunds this year of up to $4,716 for a parent with two children who makes $12,000 to $15,000, has emerged as one of the largest aid programs for the working poor. The amount of the credit for such parents gradually declines, reaching zero as their incomes hit $38,000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>More than one in six taxpayers in 2004 received the Earned Income Tax Credit, highlighting its growing role in bolstering the incomes of struggling low-income parents, a report found.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>More than one in six taxpayers in 2004 received the Earned Income Tax Credit, highlighting its growing role in bolstering the incomes of struggling low-income parents, according to a new report.</p>
        <p>The federal credit, which offers tax refunds this year of up to $4,716 for a parent with two children who makes $12,000 to $15,000, has emerged as one of the largest aid programs for the working poor. The amount of the credit for such parents gradually declines, reaching zero as their incomes hit $38,000.</p>
        <p>Annual federal payments under the program total nearly $40 billion, compared with $25 billion for the revamped welfare program, and all tax-credit money goes directly to the recipients.</p>
        <p>But childless adults and noncustodial fathers receive little from the earned income credit; their maximum benefit this year will be $428 and begins phasing out at an annual income of $7,000. Many economists and poverty experts are calling for more generous tax treatment of these groups, too, in part to increase the financial rewards of work for single black men, who have high rates of unemployment and incarceration.</p>
        <p>Covering 2000 to 2004, the study shows the importance of the tax credit as a buffer for families in periods of economic downturn and stagnating wages, said Elizabeth Kneebone, the author of the report, which was released yesterday by the Brookings Institution.</p>
        <p>''For workers who faced job losses or reduced hours, it played an important role in bridging the gap until the next rise in the economic cycle,'' Ms. Kneebone, a researcher at the institute, said in a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>The number of people receiving the credit rose to 21.7 million in 2004 from 18.8 million in 2000, a period of economic sluggishness, Ms. Kneebone said. Payments averaged $1,834 in 2004, the last year for which data are complete.</p>
        <p>At least 19 states and three local governments, including New York City, San Francisco and Montgomery County, Md., offer similar credits against state and local taxes.</p>
        <p>The number of recipients was especially high in economically distressed cities, with payments going to 41 percent of taxpayers in Jackson, Miss.; 37 percent in El Paso; and 34 percent in Hartford. But over all, the report found, more people in suburbs than cities filed for the credit, reflecting the geographic sprawl of the working poor.</p>
        <p>For those whose incomes are too low to require payment of taxes, the earned income credit is paid as a cash refund. Since a change in the law in 2001, many of these same parents have also benefited from refunds of the standard child deduction of $1,000.</p>
        <p>First adopted in the 1970s, the earned income credit was expanded significantly in the 1990s and has played a crucial supporting role in welfare overhaul, helping to make work more profitable for mothers who were pushed into low-paying jobs from cash welfare.</p>
        <p>According to a report in March 2006 by the Center on Budget and Policy Priorities, the tax credit last year, added to recipient earnings, lifted more than four million people above the official poverty line and was ''the nation's most effective antipoverty program for working families.''</p>
        <p>Reflecting a growing consensus among poverty experts, who say the changes in welfare together with the tax credit increased employment among single women but did little for struggling single men, the United States Conference of Mayors in a report in January called for a major increase in the tax credit for single, childless low-wage workers.</p>
        <p>Millions of adults, the report said, ''are working hard and 'playing by the rules' but not getting ahead.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
