<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Critic's Choice: New DVD's</title>
    <meta content="17dvd" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/movies/homevideo/17dvd.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840916"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Critics Choice"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/DVD and Video</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E4DA113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1139" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Critic's Choice: New DVD's</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New DVDs</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dave Kehr</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kehr, Dave</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bedazzled</p>
        <p>Of all the film versions of ''Faust'' I've encountered, my favorites are the 1926 silent masterpiece by F. W. Murnau -- a reasonably close adaptation of the Goethe play -- and Stanley Donen's 1967 ''Bedazzled,'' which is Goethe by way of the great Oxbridge comedians Peter Cook and Dudley Moore. The setting is London in the Swinging Sixties, though nothing much is swinging around the Wimpy Bar where Stanley Moon (Mr. Moore) is working as a fry cook.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stanley Donen’s 1967 “Bedazzled” updates “Faust” in a comic way. Also, a reissue of the horror film “Phantasm” and the Fritz Lang western, “The Return of Frank James.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bedazzled</p>
        <p>Of all the film versions of ''Faust'' I've encountered, my favorites are the 1926 silent masterpiece by F. W. Murnau -- a reasonably close adaptation of the Goethe play -- and Stanley Donen's 1967 ''Bedazzled,'' which is Goethe by way of the great Oxbridge comedians Peter Cook and Dudley Moore. The setting is London in the Swinging Sixties, though nothing much is swinging around the Wimpy Bar where Stanley Moon (Mr. Moore) is working as a fry cook.</p>
        <p>His Marguerite, renamed Margaret and played by the great comic actress Eleanor Bron, is an intensely bored waitress in the same establishment, though when she mechanically relays orders to Stanley -- ''one cheeseburger, one portion fries'' -- he hears angels singing.</p>
        <p>Still too shy to speak to her after six years, Stanley decides to hang himself from a water pipe in his sad little flat, a cue for Mr. Cook's Mephisto, working under the uninspiring earthly pseudonym George Spiggott, to make a tempting offer. In exchange for his soul, Stanley will get seven wishes, one of which is bound to unite him with his true love.</p>
        <p>Or so Stanley hopes. The lean, aristocratic Mr. Cook and the tiny, proletarian Mr. Moore, who began performing together in 1960 with the comedy troupe Beyond the Fringe, have a richly ambivalent relationship in ''Bedazzled.'' Although George fools him every time out, finding the hidden loophole in each of Stanley's elaborately detailed wishes, they become friends and confidants. Stanley opens up to him, and the lonely Lucifer responds.</p>
        <p>Spiggott takes Stanley on a tour of his own workaday world: he operates out of a dodgy nightclub with peeling crimson walls, where he scratches records and tears out the last pages of murder mysteries, two of the irritatingly effective ways he gets people to take the Lord's name in vain. Spiggott complains as lavishly as any midlevel drone about his arrogant, eccentric boss and the lousy help he's saddled with. His assistants, the Seven Deadly Sins, include Raquel Welch as a go-go girl named Lilian Lust and Barry Humphries, out of his Dame Edna drag, as a mincing personification of Envy.</p>
        <p>All the while, Mr. Cook, who wrote the screenplay, endlessly spouts quotable lines with a dry, absurdist quality (''the Garden of Eden was a boggy swamp just south of Croydon -- you can see it over there'') that clearly left an impression on the up-and-coming humorists who later became the Monty Python troupe.</p>
        <p>Each of Stanley's wishes becomes the premise for another satirical sketch -- Stanley as a pompous Scottish intellectual, a gyrating rock star, the world's richest man and a few even more surprising variations -- enlivened and lent an unexpected emotional core by the rapport between Mr. Cook and Mr. Moore.</p>
        <p>Mr. Donen made his name as a director of musical comedies in the early 1950s (''Singin' in the Rain,'' directed with Gene Kelly, remains the most famous), but by the '60s he had moved into romantic comedies, bringing his gift for stylized décor and graceful, dancing dialogue with him. In a decade replete with remarkable satires -- ''Dr. Strangelove'' comes to mind -- ''Bedazzled'' remains one of the finest, a film both of lightness and purpose, stocked with some very big laughs. (20th Century Fox Home Entertainment, $19.98, not rated)</p>
        <p>Phantasm</p>
        <p>The indie horror film ''Phantasm'' came out of nowhere in 1979 and immediately established Don Coscarelli, its director, as one of the most original voices in the genre. An unpredictable mix of boy's adventure, gothic horror and science fiction, ''Phantasm'' follows the quest of Mike (Michael Baldwin), a teenager whose parents died in a car accident, to uncover the mysteries of the Morningside mausoleum, a sinister institution presided over by a gaunt, threatening figure the film identifies only as ''The Tall Man'' (Angus Scrimm).</p>
        <p>What Mike really is investigating, of course, are the mysteries of sex and death, as they open up for an anxious adolescent. With its labyrinthlike sets, resentment of authority figures and family drama (Mike is now worried that his older brother, played by Bill Thornbury, is preparing to leave him too), Mr. Coscarelli's film bears comparison with that masterpiece of moviemaking from the subconscious, William Cameron Menzies's feverish ''Invaders From Mars'' (1953).</p>
        <p>Anchor Bay Entertainment, fulfilling its mission of becoming the Criterion Collection of genre pictures, has reissued ''Phantasm'' in a handsome new widescreen transfer, along with two other films by Mr. Coscarelli -- ''Survival Quest'' (1989) and a new cut of the 1994 sequel ''Phantasm III: Lord of the Dead.'' ($19.98, R)</p>
        <p>The Return of Frank James</p>
        <p>Westerns may not seem the most natural genre for Fritz Lang, the Vienna-born director best known for paranoid thrillers like ''Dr. Mabuse, der Spieler'' (1922) and ''The Big Heat'' (1953). But like many German-speakers who grew up with the western novels of Karl May, Lang was fascinated by the American West, and began shooting home movies of the Western landscape almost as soon as he arrived in the United States. (Selections from his 16-millimeter films can be downloaded free at the University of Wyoming's American Heritage Center, ahc.uwyo.edu/onlinecollections/digital/lang/motionpictures.htm.)</p>
        <p>''The Return of Frank James,'' Lang's first western, was a sequel to one of 20th Century Fox's big hits of 1939, Henry King's ''Jesse James,'' starring Tyrone Power (also newly available from Fox), and carries over several cast members and characters from the earlier film, including Henry Fonda as Frank. But Lang quickly makes the movie his own, focusing on the revenge theme that runs through much of his Hollywood work.</p>
        <p>Fonda shifts easily between his patented aw-shucks manner and the steely focus of a man obsessed, as Frank sets out to settle his score with Bob Ford (John Carradine), the former associate who shot Jesse James in the back. The film's most impressive sequence is a long, slow pursuit through a rocky landscape, as Frank pursues Bob's brother; the epic compositions and deliberate pacing give the scene the mythic gravity of Lang's 1924 adaptation of the ''Nibelungen'' saga. A fine transfer from Fox preserves the glow of George Barnes's Technicolor photography. (Fox Home Entertainment, $14.98, not rated)</p>
        <p>Also Out Today</p>
        <p>THE LAST KING OF SCOTLAND -- Kevin Macdonald directs Forest Whitaker in an Oscar-winning performance as the Ugandan dictator Idi Amin. (Fox Home Entertainment, $29.99, R)</p>
        <p>NOTES ON A SCANDAL -- An aging teacher (Judi Dench) conceives a dangerous fixation on a younger colleague (Cate Blanchett) in Richard Eyre's adaptation of Zoe Heller's novel. (Fox Home Entertainment, $29.99, R)</p>
        <p>NOT JUST THE BEST OF 'THE LARRY SANDERS SHOW' -- Some online fans of Garry Shandling's acerbic sitcom about a talk show host are fuming over Sony's decision to release only 23 episodes from the series's second through fifth seasons. But the four-disc set does come with eight hours of new bonus material. (Sony Pictures Home Entertainment, $49.95, not rated)</p>
        <p>Critics Choice</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
