<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Don Imus And Free Speech</title>
    <meta content="l17imus" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840976"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E6D8113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="520" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Don Imus And Free Speech</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Everybody Hates Don Imus'' (column, April 15):</p>
        <p>Frank Rich and others who raise ''free speech'' or First Amendment guarantees to argue that Don Imus should not have been fired are misguided.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Everybody Hates Don Imus'' (column, April 15):</p>
        <p>Frank Rich and others who raise ''free speech'' or First Amendment guarantees to argue that Don Imus should not have been fired are misguided.</p>
        <p>I'm far from a First Amendment expert, but I do know that the First Amendment's prohibition applies to the government, which cannot establish laws that may act as a ''chill'' on free expression. In this situation, no government body acted in violation of Mr. Imus's rights.</p>
        <p>The familiar response to the ''chilling'' argument is that the answer to free speech is more free speech. I agree. And that's exactly what happened here. After Mr. Imus's remark, there was an avalanche of free speech against it. It worked.</p>
        <p>The great thing about ''more free speech'' is that speakers and listeners can learn and discern -- and in some cases, take action. Some of that action is internal: ''I'm never going to talk that way. It hurts people.'' Some action is external: ''I'm going to call CBS and ask them to fire Don Imus.''</p>
        <p>So Mel Gibson can still say whatever he wants. So can Don Imus, Rush Limbaugh and Ann Coulter. That personal consequences may follow free speech (like losing your job or learning not to say vicious things) doesn't violate the Constitution. That is a result of more free speech.</p>
        <p>Lauren Gardner  Cleveland Heights, Ohio  April 15, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As a longtime guest on the Imus show, Frank Rich tries to mitigate his complicity in Don Imus's bigotry by suggesting that the movie ''Borat'' and the TV show ''South Park'' have gotten a free pass from the bigotry police. But there's a huge difference between Don Imus and the others.</p>
        <p>''Borat'' and ''South Park'' use bigotry to make fun of bigotry. So we laugh at ourselves. Don Imus's bigotry has no irony. It invites us to sneer at its victims. It's raw, the bar stool variety, with the only humor involved being our own attempt to laugh away the discomfort it causes.</p>
        <p>To use a '60s analogy, it's the difference between Lenny Bruce and Lester Maddox.</p>
        <p>Leonard Steinhorn  Washington, April 15, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Shock Talk Without Apologies'' (column, April 14):</p>
        <p>Robert Wright gauges the pulse of the Muslim American community perfectly.</p>
        <p>Muslim Americans are chagrined by the dubious and selective moral fervor demonstrated by the detractors of Don Imus's sexist-racist comments. As Mr. Wright so eloquently points out, when Ann Coulter, speaking about Muslims, opined after 9/11 that America should ''invade their countries, kill their leaders and convert them to Christianity,'' the silence was deafening.</p>
        <p>Ms. Coulter is not alone. Certain conservative commentators use gutter language with complete impunity in their TV and radio programs or newspaper columns to denounce Muslim Americans for the crime of being Muslims.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wright is correct in his observation that Muslim American-bashing continues unabated because the five million to seven million Muslim Americans do not have a muscular organization like the N.A.A.C.P. to protect and promote their interests.</p>
        <p>Fakhruddin Ahmed  Princeton Junction, N.J.  April 14, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
