<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yahoo Strikes Ad Deal With More Papers</title>
    <meta content="17search" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/technology/17search.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840955"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Yahoo Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Helft, Miguel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Yahoo Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2D9113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="547" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yahoo Strikes Ad Deal With More Papers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Yahoo Strikes Ad Deal With More Papers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIGUEL HELFT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Helft, Miguel</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, April 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Yahoo announces broad deal with publishers representing 264 newspapers to sell national advertising across their Web sites; it may be clearest sign to date of company's efforts to extends its advertising platform beyond panoply of Yahoo sites; Yahoo's deal with newspapers is extension of agreement announced in November with smaller group of publishers; it also represents vote of confidence for Yahoo's revamped search advertising technology, which company unveiled earlier in year (M)d</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a flurry of deal making over the last few days, Google and Yahoo, two giants of the online advertising business, are set to encroach on each other's turf even more aggressively than before.</p>
        <p>On Monday, Yahoo announced a broad deal with publishers representing 264 newspapers to sell national advertising across their Web sites. It may be the clearest sign to date of the company's efforts to extend its advertising platform beyond the panoply of Yahoo sites.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Yahoo announced a broad deal with publishers representing 264 newspapers to sell national advertising across their Web sites.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After a flurry of deal making over the last few days, Google and Yahoo, two giants of the online advertising business, are set to encroach on each other's turf even more aggressively than before.</p>
        <p>On Monday, Yahoo announced a broad deal with publishers representing 264 newspapers to sell national advertising across their Web sites. It may be the clearest sign to date of the company's efforts to extend its advertising platform beyond the panoply of Yahoo sites.</p>
        <p>The move follows Google's announcement on Friday of its plans to acquire DoubleClick for $3.1 billion, a bold move into the market to deliver display and graphical advertising to Web sites. It is a business that Yahoo dominates, and one in which Google -- the leader in search-based text advertisements -- has failed to gain much traction.</p>
        <p>''They are both trying to extend their influence and business opportunities beyond their own properties,'' said Stewart Barry, an analyst at ThinkEquity Partners.</p>
        <p>Yahoo's deal with newspapers is an extension of an agreement announced in November with a smaller group of publishers. It also represents a vote of confidence for Yahoo's revamped search advertising technology, which the company unveiled earlier this year.</p>
        <p>Under the deal, newspapers will use Yahoo's search technology on their Web sites and share revenue generated from the ads that Yahoo places alongside search results. Both Yahoo officials and outsiders have said recently that the technology, referred to internally as Project Panama, has improved Yahoo's ability to place relevant ads in front of users, and therefore generate more revenue from search advertising.</p>
        <p>Additionally, newspapers will be able to sell local advertisements on certain Yahoo properties, and their articles will appear on Yahoo's news, finance and sports Web sites.</p>
        <p>Those newspapers in the consortium that currently use DoubleClick's technology to deliver graphical ads on their sites will gradually move to Yahoo's system.</p>
        <p>The earlier agreement was largely limited to cross-selling employment classified advertisements.</p>
        <p>And in recent months, members of the newspaper consortium, which initially included the MediaNews Group, Hearst, Belo, E. W. Scripps and others, have recruited other chains, including the McClatchy Company and Media General. They are hoping that the broader alliance with Yahoo will help struggling newspaper companies increase online revenues.</p>
        <p>''It's an important step in the transformation of the newspaper industry,'' said Robert W. Decherd, chairman and chief executive of Belo.</p>
        <p>Yahoo made its first significant foray into the business of selling graphical ads outside its own network in an alliance with eBay last May. The company described the new agreement as the next step in that strategy.</p>
        <p>''We are very interested in aligning not with everyone, but on a selective basis with publishers that have a quality audience where there is an alignment with Yahoo's audience,'' said Hilary Schneider, a Yahoo senior vice president.</p>
        <p>Google's planned acquisition of DoubleClick and Yahoo's deal with newspapers place the two companies increasingly at the nexus between advertisers and online publishers.</p>
        <p>''Both companies are looking to get to as large a scale as they can so their advertisers have the broadest reach possible,'' said Bill Gross, chairman and chief executive of Idealab, which incubates and finances new technology ventures and was a pioneer in the search advertising business. ''And everyone is looking to lock up as many publishers as possible.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
