<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sure, Times Have Changed, But Optimism Stays in Style</title>
    <meta content="&amp;17crye" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/arts/music/17crye.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840905"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Cryer, Gretchen</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Ford, Nancy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E5DA113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="533" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sure, Times Have Changed, But Optimism Stays in Style</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sure, Times Have Changed, but Optimism Stays in Style</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Love is rare/And life is strange/Nothing lasts/And people change'' go the lyrics of ''Old Friend,'' the most memorable song by Gretchen Cryer (lyrics) and Nancy Ford (music) from their 1978 show, ''I'm Getting My Act Together and Taking It on the Road.'' To hear it sung by its creators, who are performing an anthology of their theater music at 59E59 Theaters, is to be stirred by a pop avowal of friendship through thick and thin that has no expiration date.</p>
        <p>Simply by showing up, Ms. Cryer and Ms. Ford, who until recently hadn't performed together for three decades, prove the song's truth. In the final verse the narrator imagines that she and her pal (a man with whom she enjoys a long-term platonic relationship) will meet years hence (at the age of 62) and travel the world together. Ms. Cryer and Ms. Ford are now closer to 72: point doubly taken.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The plucky but guarded optimism behind their feminist songs of 1978 now sound poignant, even quaint.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Love is rare/And life is strange/Nothing lasts/And people change'' go the lyrics of ''Old Friend,'' the most memorable song by Gretchen Cryer (lyrics) and Nancy Ford (music) from their 1978 show, ''I'm Getting My Act Together and Taking It on the Road.'' To hear it sung by its creators, who are performing an anthology of their theater music at 59E59 Theaters, is to be stirred by a pop avowal of friendship through thick and thin that has no expiration date.</p>
        <p>Simply by showing up, Ms. Cryer and Ms. Ford, who until recently hadn't performed together for three decades, prove the song's truth. In the final verse the narrator imagines that she and her pal (a man with whom she enjoys a long-term platonic relationship) will meet years hence (at the age of 62) and travel the world together. Ms. Cryer and Ms. Ford are now closer to 72: point doubly taken.</p>
        <p>The anthology, ''Getting Their Act Together Again!,'' is not a sequel to their 1978 hit. Among its 21 songs, which chronologically survey a collaboration that has lasted more than three and a half decades, only six come from their blockbuster, which opened at the Public Theater, then moved to Circle in the Square Downtown for a three-year run and has enjoyed countless regional productions.</p>
        <p>''I'm Getting My Act Together and Taking It On the Road'' triumphed at the moment when the winds of feminist self-determination were whistling through American pop culture. The year it opened, Jill Clayburgh, Hollywood's designated symbol of ascendant second-wave feminism, was a bankable star with her movie ''An Unmarried Woman.'' Then the wind changed.</p>
        <p>Most of the other best songs from ''Together Again'' -- ''Smile,'' ''Dear Tom'' and ''Strong Woman Number'' -- describe the exhilaration, challenges and disappointments facing women who abandon the demeaning subservience of the perky housewife role to strike out on their own. Hearing them sung in the age of the lap dance and the boob job makes their plucky but guarded optimism sound poignant, even quaint. The songs from a musical about Eleanor Roosevelt, especially ''If I Could Make a Difference,'' share the attitude of cheerleading determination.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cryer, who does the majority of the singing, and Ms. Ford, who plays the piano, harmonizes and takes several lead vocals, are exemplars of the spirited but polite keyboard-based 1970s folk-pop that refuses to despair. The show is quintessentially Midwestern in tone and attitude. (The women met at DePauw University.) Cute, tidy epigrams with hospital corners are tucked into Ms. Cryer's straightforward, anecdotal lyrics. Their song ''The News,'' which counters tabloid headlines with its reassuring observation that ''one hundred million men did not kill a model today,'' is as resolutely chipper as anything from ''The Sound of Music.''</p>
        <p>When Ms. Cryer adopts the simpering persona of a wife who coos to her husband in the baby-doll tones of what she calls ''a lunatic child,'' you sense for a moment an untapped reserve of sarcasm and bitterness behind the good manners. Ms. Cryer and Ms. Ford are too nice and commercially sensible to dig any deeper.</p>
        <p>''Getting Their Act Together Again!'' continues through Friday at 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, Manhattan; (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
