<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Storm Leaves a Toll of Flooding and Hardship</title>
    <meta content="17storm" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/nyregion/17storm.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="EDITORS' NOTE APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070419T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840992"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blackouts and Brownouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Northeastern States (US)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcfadden, Robert D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blackouts and Brownouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E1D8113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1265" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Storm Leaves a Toll of Flooding and Hardship</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Storm Leaves a Toll of Flooding and Hardship</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. McFADDEN; Reporting was contributed by Ken Belson, Bill Finley, Abby Gruen, John Holl, Tina Kelley, Maureen Seaberg, Nate Schweber, Ronald Smothers, Jan Ellen Spiegel and Barbara Whitaker.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcfadden, Robert D</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Northeaster of '07 continues its assault on New York region, forcing evacuation of thousands from flooded homes, disrupting travel, closing schools and trailing a wake of rising rivers, gouged beaches, power failures and widespread damage; at least nine deaths in five states are attributed to storm that stalled over Northeast; 7.57 inches of rain in Central Park on April 15 make it city's second-wettest day since record keeping began in 1869; Northern New Jersey and Westchester County are among hardest hit areas; public officials warn of continuing power outages and commuter headaches; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The storm destined for the books as the northeaster of '07 continued its assault on the New York region and the Northeast yesterday, forcing the evacuation of thousands from flooded homes, disrupting travel, closing schools and trailing a wake of rising rivers, gouged beaches, power failures and widespread damage.</p>
        <p>The awesome storm, which swamped New York City and other locales on Sunday with record rains, punishing winds and heavy snows that recast northern landscapes, stalled over the Northeast yesterday. But forecasters said it had lost its punch and would churn to oblivion over the Atlantic today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The northeaster continued to wreak havoc on Monday, but forecasters said it had lost its punch and would churn into oblivion over the Atlantic by Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The storm destined for the books as the northeaster of '07 continued its assault on the New York region and the Northeast yesterday, forcing the evacuation of thousands from flooded homes, disrupting travel, closing schools and trailing a wake of rising rivers, gouged beaches, power failures and widespread damage.</p>
        <p>The awesome storm, which swamped New York City and other locales on Sunday with record rains, punishing winds and heavy snows that recast northern landscapes, stalled over the Northeast yesterday. But forecasters said it had lost its punch and would churn to oblivion over the Atlantic today.</p>
        <p>At least nine deaths in five states were attributed to the storm. There were no immediate estimates of its damage, which seemed likely to run into the hundreds of millions of dollars. And it was not over. While coastal flooding was receding in most areas, rivers were still rising, swollen by the runoff of record rains. Public officials warned of continuing and widespread power problems and commuting headaches.</p>
        <p>''The storm may be over, but it will take time to recover,'' the Westchester County executive, Andrew J. Spano, said last night. He urged drivers to use mass transit, asked residents and business owners to document damage with photographs and receipts to support claims for federal assistance, and warned of unscrupulous contractors, fraudulent charities, fake inspectors and other scam artists.</p>
        <p>As the rain continued falling, 223 more flights were canceled at the area's three major airports, on top of Sunday's 600. Scores of roads were closed, many commuter trains ran late or not at all, evacuees spent the night in shelters, and thousands of low-lying homes along rivers in New Jersey, New York and Connecticut were flooded or in danger of flooding today or tomorrow. The acting governor of New Jersey declared a state of emergency.</p>
        <p>The Boston Marathon was run in a drizzle. But power was still out at 328,000 homes and businesses in nine states from Maryland to Maine. New York officials told of major erosion at Jones Beach, Robert Moses State Park and beaches in Montauk on Long Island. Westchester County schools were closed for the day. Airlines and commuter lines struggled to resume their schedules, but are expected to do better today.</p>
        <p>And meteorologists profiled an astounding storm: 7.57 inches of rain in Central Park on Sunday made it the city's second-wettest day since recordkeeping began in 1869; other rain records were set in Philadelphia, Newark, Trenton, Baltimore, Washington and Bridgeport, Conn.; 26 inches of snow hit Tupper Lake, N.Y., and winds were clocked at 72 miles an hour in Milton, Mass., 81 m.p.h. in Cape Elizabeth, Me., and 156 m.p.h. at Mount Washington in New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>For millions, it was a tough day of coping -- of watching floodwater pour into homes on the Raritan River in New Jersey from New Brunswick to Bound Brook and in the Westchester suburbs of Mamaroneck and New Rochelle, of sleeping in a shelter or an airport, of towing a car and watching a refrigerator float by, of getting to work despite flooded roads and erratic trains, of waiting for power or a water pump or just something to hope for.</p>
        <p>''We lost everything,'' Gloria Martinez, 75, one of 300 Mamaroneck, N.Y., residents who were driven from their homes and spent the night in a shelter at a high school, sobbed in Spanish to Gov. Eliot Spitzer as she sat amid a few plastic bags that held her possessions. It had been only hours since the water had risen to her shoulders and forced her from her apartment.</p>
        <p>The governor took her hand, but there was little he could say to her.</p>
        <p>Later, speaking to reporters on a tour of the damaged area, Mr. Spitzer said Mamaroneck had been one of the hardest-hit places in the state. National Guard troops had been called in overnight to assist in the evacuations of 60 to 70 flooded homes.</p>
        <p>''Just the magnitude of the devastation is always shocking and hard to absorb,'' the governor said. ''When you see the folks, you see the devastation in their eyes.''</p>
        <p>Roads along rivers in Westchester County were severely disrupted by flooding. Portions of the Saw Mill, Bronx River and Hutchinson River Parkways were closed, and traffic slowed to a crawl on roads that were open. In Croton-on-Hudson, the Croton River spilled over its banks, and half of the parking lot at the commuter train station was under water.</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, acting Gov. Richard J. Codey said in Trenton that 1,400 residents were evacuated from homes along the Raritan River, mainly in Bound Brook and Manville. David A. Robinson, the state climatologist, said the river crested at 38.5 feet at midafternoon, 10.5 feet above flood stage.</p>
        <p>While most of New Jersey's rivers -- the Ramapo, the Passaic, the Delaware and others -- had not overflowed, the Raritan was expected to continue rising today and tomorrow, said Capt. Jerome Hatfield of the state police emergency management office.</p>
        <p>Mr. Codey said that sections of 54 roads in New Jersey had been closed because of flooding, but that the interstate highways were all open. He called the storm the second-worst in state history, after Tropical Storm Floyd in 1999, and said it had dropped more rain than any storm since 1882.</p>
        <p>Hoboken became an island as roads surrounding the city flooded, in some cases up to three feet, submerging cars, basements and parking lots.Classes were canceled in dozens of school districts in New Jersey, as well as at Bergen Community College, and the New Brunswick and Piscataway campuses of Rutgers University.</p>
        <p>In Connecticut, where up to eight inches of rain fell, rivers overflowed in sections of Westport, Fairfield and Trumbull. In Bridgeport, the Pequonnock River sent water gushing into basements, parks and roadways.</p>
        <p>Besides 43,000 customers without power in Connecticut, utilities reported power failures all over the Northeast: 10,000 households and businesses in the New York area, 55,000 in upstate New York, 40,000 in New Jersey, 30,000 in Maryland, 50,000 in Pennsylvania, 46,000 in New Hampshire, 17,000 in Maine, 25,000 in Vermont and 12,000 in Massachusetts. For many, there were no firm predictions on when power would be restored.</p>
        <p>On Long Island, roads and schools were open. Flooding occurred along canals in Seaford and Freeport, and several homes were heavily damaged in the Davis Park community on Fire Island.</p>
        <p>Travel was a frustration for thousands. The Port Authority of New York and New Jersey reported two-hour flight delays at La Guardia Airport and three hours at Newark Liberty International Airport, but none during the day at Kennedy Airport. Amtrak said downed trees and flooding had delayed service between Washington and Boston, and some long-distance trains were canceled.</p>
        <p>Across the New York region, commuters ran into problems.</p>
        <p>Metro-North reported delays of up to 60 minutes on its Harlem Line, with shorter and scattered delays on its New Haven and Hudson Lines. The Long Island Rail Road reported 30- to 45-minute delays across the board, affecting 90 percent of its city-bound riders. In the evening, 17 trains were canceled. New Jersey Transit reported delays of up to 30 minutes on trains in and out of Pennsylvania Station, and up to 60 minutes on bus lines.</p>
        <p>In one of the few bright reports of a gloomy day, ferries on 17 New York Waterway routes operated normally. ''Flooding may disrupt roads and tracks,'' said Patrick Smith, a spokesman, ''but a little water never stopped a boat.''</p>
        <p>Editors' Note:  April 19, 2007, Thursday  A picture on the front page of The Metro Section on Tuesday with an article about flooding caused by the recent northeaster showed an antiques shop in Ridgefield, Conn., being washed away. The wood siding at the far left of the pink building was out of alignment because the picture was retouched by a Times staff member who took the picture, but who is not a staff photographer. He altered it because a flash created a white spot on the picture when he shot it through the window of a train. Also, the retouching tool left a round circle on the building's window at right.</p>
        <p>Times policy forbids the manipulation of any photograph. Had editors been aware of the manipulation and seen the original picture, they would have either published the picture with the blemish or not used it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Editors' Note: April 19, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>A picture on the front page of The Metro Section on Tuesday with an article about flooding caused by the recent northeaster showed an antiques shop in Ridgefield, Conn., being washed away. The wood siding at the far left of the pink building was out of alignment because the picture was retouched by a Times staff member who took the picture, but who is not a staff photographer. He altered it because a flash created a white spot on the picture when he shot it through the window of a train. Also, the retouching tool left a round circle on the building's window at right.</p>
        <p>Times policy forbids the manipulation of any photograph. Had editors been aware of the manipulation and seen the original picture, they would have either published the picture with the blemish or not used it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
