<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Opening Eyes to a Slowly Dimming World</title>
    <meta content="17adco" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/business/media/17adco.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840960"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Names, Organizational</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Departments and Agencies</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, David Cay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/World Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Alzheimer's</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Alzheimer's Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Names, Organizational</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alzheimer's Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E0D9113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="916" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Opening Eyes to a Slowly Dimming World</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Opening Eyes to a Slowly Dimming World</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE L. LEVERE</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US House to vote on bill that clarifies law barring for-profit companies from using names that sound like official government agencies (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Alzheimer's Association is introducing its first paid campaign, intended to educate the American public about the disease that threatens to overwhelm the Medicare system as the baby boom population ages.</p>
        <p>The campaign, by two agencies, includes $8 million worth of magazine and online advertising, a new Web site (actionalz.org) and initiatives by local association chapters. The goal is to persuade five million Americans to become ''champions'' in the fight against Alzheimer's, one for every person who now has the disease.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Alzheimer’s Association is introducing its first paid campaign, intended to educate the American public about the disease.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Alzheimer's Association is introducing its first paid campaign, intended to educate the American public about the disease that threatens to overwhelm the Medicare system as the baby boom population ages.</p>
        <p>The campaign, by two agencies, includes $8 million worth of magazine and online advertising, a new Web site (actionalz.org) and initiatives by local association chapters. The goal is to persuade five million Americans to become ''champions'' in the fight against Alzheimer's, one for every person who now has the disease.</p>
        <p>The campaign was praised by experts in the disease, one of whom said it would help the Chicago-based association catch up with other groups' educational efforts.</p>
        <p>The association ''has fundamentally been interested in supporting scientific research and looking for a cure, and they've therefore been behind in public education,'' said Dr. Kenneth Minaker, chief of the geriatric medicine unit at Massachusetts General Hospital.</p>
        <p>''We're delighted they're turning their energies to this huge need,'' he added, ''and expect they will do a very good job.''</p>
        <p>Angela Geiger, vice president for constituent relations for the association, said it has primarily ''focused on care and support for people going through the disease as well as research.''</p>
        <p>''It is time for us to step up our efforts to educate the public to do something now,'' she added.</p>
        <p>Alzheimer's ''has escalated into an epidemic,'' Ms. Geiger said, citing statistics showing that a new diagnosis is made every 72 seconds and that by 2050, 16 million Americans will have the disease.</p>
        <p>''It will overwhelm Medicare in less than 25 years unless scientists find a way to cure or prevent it,'' Ms. Geiger said.</p>
        <p>The campaign is vital, she added, because most Americans are ignorant about Alzheimer's. A survey released by the association yesterday found that although almost half of Americans say they know someone who has the disease, 94 percent said they do not know much about it.</p>
        <p>Nearly 9 out of 10 Americans do not know it is a leading cause of death, the survey showed. But Alzheimer's is the seventh leading cause of death, according to the Centers for Disease Control, developing in one in eight people after age 65 and one in two after age 85.</p>
        <p>Each of the three print ads in the campaign, created by TG Madison of Atlanta, features a blurry sepia photograph of a person with Alzheimer's over which is superimposed text in bold type, some in purple, the association's official color. (The people shown in the campaign are models.)</p>
        <p>One ad depicts a man holding his chin in his hand and says, ''Someone suffering from Alzheimer's will lose the ability to form thoughts, remember simple words and ultimately communicate. You can be their voice. Alzheimer's is the seventh leading cause of death in the United States. It's time to speak up.''</p>
        <p>Another ad says: ''Many Alzheimer's sufferers will slowly lose control of their bodies. They need you to move their cause forward.'' The third ad says: ''As their brains continue to shrink, people with Alzheimer's will feel trapped in their own minds. They need you to open everyone else's.''</p>
        <p>The ads urge readers to ''take action against Alzheimer's. Go to actionalz.org,'' a site created by Undisclosed Location, an agency in Chicago.</p>
        <p>John Carter, executive creative director of TG Madison, said his agency wanted the ads to be ''a little bit in your face. We wanted readers to sit back and think there really is a big problem, that something needs to be done. The visuals illustrate the emotions of what Alzheimer's sufferers go through.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Geiger said the value of the media used in the campaign is $8 million, but the association's actual spending is less. TG Madison negotiated discounts for the nonprofit, particularly with Time Warner magazines and Web sites. Previous campaigns for the association ran as public service ads, on a pro bono basis.</p>
        <p>The print ads are running in magazines like AARP The Magazine , Newsweek, Parade and Time. There are also online ads on Web sites like AOL.com, MSN.com, oprah.com and prevention.com.</p>
        <p>The campaign also includes a traveling photography and video exhibit featuring more than 30 celebrities. Among them are David Hyde Pierce, Dick Van Dyke, Peter Gallagher, Kate Burton and Olympia Dukakis.</p>
        <p>Also, Ch. Felicity's Diamond Jim, the dog that won the 2007 Westminster Dog Show, is featured in the exhibit; the English springer spaniel, known colloquially as James, does therapy work with Alzheimer's patients. All the celebrities wear purple clothes that bear the word ''voice,'' ''move'' or ''open.''</p>
        <p>''I hope the campaign will raise awareness of what the disease is, what the threat is, so people will put pressure on Congress'' to increase financing, said Mr. Hyde Pierce, a member of the association's board who has testified in Washington and is the campaign's spokesman.</p>
        <p>David Shenk, author of ''The Forgetting: Alzheimer's: Portrait of an Epidemic,'' said that many ''researchers are very optimistic they can make very significant progress against the disease in the near future. There is a window of opportunity here. It is so depressing the federal government is not stepping up to the plate.''</p>
        <p>He also suggested the campaign could help dispel the taboo that surrounds discussion of the disease.</p>
        <p>''We're talking about a subject that is still in many respects taboo to discuss,'' he said. ''It's a terrifying disease, most people don't understand it very well. We're naturally afraid of things we don't understand. The better people can understand Alzheimer's, the better are our chances of breaking through the taboo.''</p>
        <p>ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
