<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fight Seen For ABN; Stock Soars</title>
    <meta content="17bank" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/business/worldbusiness/17bank.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840997"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abn Amro</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Barclays Bank Plc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Werdigier, Julia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands/Amsterdam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Amsterdam (Netherlands)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">ABN AMRO Holding NV</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Barclays Plc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E0D8113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="934" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fight Seen For ABN; Stock Soars</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Fight Seen for ABN; Stock Soars</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIA WERDIGIER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Werdigier, Julia</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, April 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Shares of ABN Amro soar on prospect of bidding war for largest Dutch bank; rise creates difficulties in completing merger deal with Barclays, its preferred partner and possibly its last chance to avoid breakup of company (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The prospect of a bidding war for ABN Amro sent its shares soaring on Monday, making it more difficult for the company, the biggest Dutch bank, to seal a merger deal with its preferred partner, Barclays, and reject an unusual overture from a group of three European banks.</p>
        <p>Rijkman W. J. Groenink, ABN Amro's chief executive, is racing to reach an agreement with John Varley, his counterpart at Barclays, before Wednesday, when a month of exclusive talks between them ends.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The prospect of a bidding war for ABN Amro is making it difficult for the bank to seal a merger deal with its preferred partner, Barclays.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The prospect of a bidding war for ABN Amro sent its shares soaring on Monday, making it more difficult for the company, the biggest Dutch bank, to seal a merger deal with its preferred partner, Barclays, and reject an unusual overture from a group of three European banks.</p>
        <p>Rijkman W. J. Groenink, ABN Amro's chief executive, is racing to reach an agreement with John Varley, his counterpart at Barclays, before Wednesday, when a month of exclusive talks between them ends.</p>
        <p>Some analysts said that a merger with Barclays, which would be one of ABN Amro's last chances to avoid a breakup, is looking increasingly unlikely after ABN Amro's shares surged 5.7 percent, to about 35.5 euros, or $48.18, in Amsterdam Monday. Analysts expect that Barclays could afford to pay 35 euros for each ABN Amro share.</p>
        <p>''The current share price is quite high for Barclays and is above what we expect it is willing to pay,'' said Dirk Peeters, an analyst at KBC Securities in Belgium.</p>
        <p>Analysts said that ABN Amro's rising share price could force Barclays to walk away, which could leave Barclays exposed as a takeover target itself. The high price could also help it fend off a possible rival bid by Royal Bank of Scotland, Banco Santander Central Hispano and Fortis by seeking its own deep-pocketed partners.</p>
        <p>Either way, the takeover battle is already one of the most unusual in European financial services. A merger with Barclays would make the final entity the biggest in banking, with ABN Amro's market value Monday reaching 68.3 billion euros, or $92 billion. If that deal does not work out, talks with the rival group would be the first involving an approach by a consortium of lenders, each eyeing a different part of ABN's business.</p>
        <p>Such group efforts are more common among private equity firms, which may team up to buy a company and then sell off parts or else allow each member to focus on a separate part of the business. That approach is almost unheard-of in financial services, where institutions are in fierce competition with each other for size and market share.</p>
        <p>The idea of splitting up ABN Amro was first voiced this year by the Children's Investment Fund, an activist hedge fund investor that owns less than 3 percent of ABN Amro. Mr. Groenink rejected the idea and told shareholders to vote against it at the company's annual general meeting on April 26. He argued that a breakup would damage the remaining operations and possibly hurt the company's credit ratings.</p>
        <p>Yet, a breakup is exactly what the group led by Royal Bank of Scotland and advised by Merrill Lynch has in mind. Royal Bank is Britain's second-largest bank, behind HSBC Holdings; Banco Santander is Spain's largest bank; and Fortis is a Belgian banking group. On Friday, they asked ABN Amro to open discussions about a takeover. They expect to hear back from ABN Amro on Tuesday about a possible meeting.</p>
        <p>The group of banks would be able to pay more for ABN Amro than Barclays because each one of them would take only that part of ABN that fitted best with its businesses and could generate the most cost savings.</p>
        <p>''A consortium could pay more because they can justify higher premiums because everyone is picking out the things they want, making synergies more likely,'' said Thomas Rothaeusler, an analyst at Bank Sal. Oppenheim in Frankfurt.</p>
        <p>Also, ABN Amro would be easier to digest for a group splitting the bill rather than Barclays paying alone.</p>
        <p>If successful, the group approach may set a precedent for further acquisitions in the banking industry, fund managers said.</p>
        <p>''Everyone is looking for the best synergies possible, picking the businesses they like,'' said Marc van de Weijenberg, a fund manager at SNS Asset Management in the Netherlands. ''This is quite new for the banking industry.''</p>
        <p>Fred Goodwin, chief executive of Royal Bank of Scotland, who led an expansion into America that included the acquisition of Charter One Financial for $10.3 billion in 2004, has his eyes set on ABN Amro's American business, including LaSalle Bank.</p>
        <p>Santander would profit from ABN Amro's Brazilian business, Banco Real, and Banca Antonveneta in Italy because they would provide a diversification of revenue at a time when growth in the home market is slowing.</p>
        <p>Fortis, Belgium's biggest financial services company, would take on ABN Amro's Dutch business to create a tight banking network in the region.</p>
        <p>A team bid would result in far greater cost savings than one by Barclays, analysts said. Royal Bank and Santander could generate 2.56 billion euros in expense savings compared with 1.44 billion euros by Barclays, according to Jean-Pierre Lambert, an analyst at Keefe, Bruyette &amp; Woods in London.</p>
        <p>Some analysts also said that there was the possibility of more bidding groups emerging. Bank of America, ING, Bank of Montreal and HSBC could all profit from buying parts of ABN Amro and could team up in any possible formation, Mr. Lambert said.</p>
        <p>ABN Amro, with 4,600 branches in 53 countries, is an attractive target not only because it has businesses in areas like India and Brazil that are growing faster than Europe but also because its share price has been underperforming its peers. ABN Amro's shares jumped more than 20 percent in the month since it announced takeover talks with Barclays.</p>
        <p>Barclays' shares, meanwhile, rose 1.7 percent, to 756 pence, in London Monday. Analysts said Barclays could attract potential bidders like JPMorgan Chase and Bank of America, which could use Barclays's investment banking arm to help its efforts to build such a business in Europe.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
