<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Day in Court for Queens Home-Care Aide</title>
    <meta content="17homecare" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/nyregion/17homecare.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840993"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Home Health Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minimum Wage</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Overtime</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Long Island Care at Home</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Labor Department (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Coke, Evelyn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minimum Wage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Supreme Court</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E1D8113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="886" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Day in Court for Queens Home-Care Aide</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Day in Court for Queens Home-Care Aide</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Steven</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Supreme Court hears arguments in case of Evelyn Coke, 73-year-old home-care worker from Queens, who seeks to overturn Labor Department's regulation exempting home-care aides employed by third-party companies from federal minimum wage and overtime protections; Coke was employed by Long Island Care at Home; all agree that home-care workers hired directly by individuals are exempt from those protections; several justices show little sympathy for Coke's position; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was Evelyn Coke's first trip to the United States Supreme Court, and for the 73-year-old home-care aide from Corona, Queens, it was certainly eventful, the last step in a five-year battle.</p>
        <p>In a case in which Ms. Coke is the sole plaintiff, her lawyers sought to persuade the nine justices that she -- and the nation's 1.4 million other home-care aides -- should not be exempt from federal minimum wage and overtime protections.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bush and Bloomberg administrations oppose the lawsuit, arguing that protection for home-care aides could cause government spending to soar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was Evelyn Coke's first trip to the United States Supreme Court, and for the 73-year-old home-care aide from Corona, Queens, it was certainly eventful, the last step in a five-year battle.</p>
        <p>In a case in which Ms. Coke is the sole plaintiff, her lawyers sought to persuade the nine justices that she -- and the nation's 1.4 million other home-care aides -- should not be exempt from federal minimum wage and overtime protections.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Coke has faced considerable resistance. The Bush and Bloomberg administrations oppose her lawsuit, arguing that government spending on home care for the elderly and infirm will soar if the Supreme Court rules that home-care aides are protected by minimum wage and overtime laws.</p>
        <p>After her son pushed her into the ornate courtroom in her wheelchair on Monday, Ms. Coke listened intently to the arguments.</p>
        <p>''I hope they try and help me because I need help bad,'' said Ms. Coke, who is too ill to work, with kidney problems so serious that she has dialysis treatments three times a week.</p>
        <p>Ms. Coke filed her lawsuit because she was angry that she sometimes worked 70 hours a week -- washing, bathing and cooking in elderly clients' homes -- without, she said, ever receiving time-and-a-half pay for overtime.</p>
        <p>Her lawyer, Craig Becker, urged the Supreme Court to overturn a Labor Department regulation issued by the Ford administration in 1975 exempting home-care aides employed by third-party companies from federal minimum wage and overtime coverage; her suit argues that the regulation clashes with the intent of Congress.</p>
        <p>But several justices showed little sympathy for that view. Justice Antonin Scalia pushed Ms. Coke's lawyer, asking why the court should not defer to the expertise of the Labor Department.</p>
        <p>The central question in the case is whether home-care aides hired by companies, as Ms. Coke was, should be exempt from labor protections. All sides agree that home-care aides hired directly by the elderly or infirm are exempt from those protections.</p>
        <p>The case has drawn close attention from the health care industry. The nation's largest health care union, the Service Employees International Union, is paying Ms. Coke's legal fees, hoping that a victory for her will raise pay for hundreds of thousands of home-care aides. But the Home Care Council of New York City and other health care groups filed briefs opposing Ms. Coke, worried that a victory for her would significantly increase their payroll costs.</p>
        <p>In its brief, the Bloomberg administration argued that a victory for Ms. Coke could require the federal, state and city governments, which together finance home care through Medicaid, to pay $250 million more a year to the 60,000 home-care aides who work in the city.</p>
        <p>In July 2004, the United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit in Manhattan ruled for Ms. Coke, concluding that the Labor Department had acted improperly in issuing its 1975 regulation.</p>
        <p>The home-care company that Ms. Coke sued, Long Island Care at Home, appealed the case, asking the Supreme Court to overturn that ruling.</p>
        <p>Ms. Coke said she was paid $7 an hour in 2001, when she last worked for Long Island Care at Home, before she became disabled, first because she was hit by a car and later because of kidney problems.</p>
        <p>MaryAnn Osborne, Long Island Care's vice president, said the company now paid its aides $8 to $11 an hour, meaning that with overtime premium pay they would earn $12 to $16.50 an hour.</p>
        <p>In 1974, Congress amended the Fair Labor Standards Act to extend minimum wage and overtime protections to maids, cooks and other domestic service workers. But the amendments exempted baby sitters and workers who provided companion services for the elderly and infirm.</p>
        <p>In issuing final regulations in 1975 to flesh out the amendments, the Labor Department adopted two seemingly contradictory regulations. One stated that home-care aides would be exempt only when they worked in a private home ''of the person by whom he or she is employed.'' The other regulation stated that home-care workers employed by third-party employers other than the family would be exempt from minimum wage and overtime coverage.</p>
        <p>In subsequent years, the Labor Department has treated the broad exemption as the operative one.</p>
        <p>The justices interrupted Mr. Becker repeatedly as he sought to argue that the judiciary should not defer to the Labor Department, on the ground that a broad exemption clashed with Congress's intent.</p>
        <p>''It could not have been Congress's purpose, when amendments were explicitly designed to extend coverage, to at the same time contract coverage,'' Mr. Becker said, noting that before the 1974 amendments were enacted, home-care aides employed by companies had minimum wage and overtime protections.</p>
        <p>He argued that coverage provisions were to be read broadly and exemptions narrowly.</p>
        <p>But H. Bartow Farr, who represented Long Island Care at Home, responded that the Labor Department ''was the agency chosen by Congress to do the work of defining and delimiting the exception.''</p>
        <p>Justice Stephen G. Breyer voiced concern that if Ms. Coke prevailed, sons and daughters who hired home-care aides for their parents might have to pay far more for the services. ''If you win this case,'' he said, ''it seems to me suddenly there will be millions of people who will be unable to do it and hence, millions of sick people will move to institutions.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
