<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wall Street Journal Wins 2 Pulitzer Prizes; History of Civil Rights Reporting Also Wins</title>
    <meta content="17pulitzer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070419T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840996"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pulitzer Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cartoons and Cartoonists</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wall Street Journal</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Times</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Birmingham News</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Times</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Herald</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Oregonian (Newspaper)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boston Globe</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlanta Journal-Constitution</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">La Weekly (Newspaper)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Daily News</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Associated Press</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sacramento Bee (Newspaper)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Newsday</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Forelle, Charles</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bandler, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maremont, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stecklow, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Andrea</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blackledge, Brett J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weiss, Kenneth R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcfarling, Usha Lee</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Loomis, Rick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cenziper, Debbie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Savage, Charlie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tucker, Cynthia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gold, Jonathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Browne, Arthur</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Evans, Heidi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weintraub, Beverly</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Balilty, Oded</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Byer, Renee C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Handelsman, Walt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Gene</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klibanoff, Hank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccarthy, Cormac</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lindsay-Abaire, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Applegate, Debby</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wright, Lawrence</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trethewey, Natasha</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Coleman, Ornette</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradbury, Ray</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Coltrane, John (1926-67)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Razmi, Jahangir</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cartoons and Cartoonists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E0D8113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="3043" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wall Street Journal Wins 2 Pulitzer Prizes; History of Civil Rights Reporting Also Wins</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE and JAMES BARRON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q; Barron, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pulitzer Prize winners are announced; Wall Street Journal wins two--one for public service for bringing about widespread change in corporate America with uncovering of unethical practices of business executives for series of articles by Charles Forelle, James Bandler, Mark Maremont and Steve Stecklow--and one for international reporting for series of articles about adverse effects of industrial development in China; New York Times reporter Andrea Elliott wins for feature writing; Boston Globe reporter Charlie Savage wins for national reporting; Birmingham News of Alabama reporter Brett J Blackledge wins for investigative reporting; Los Angeles Times reporters Kenneth R Weiss, Usha Lee McFarling and Rick Loomis win for explanatory reporting; Miami Herald reporter Debbie Cenziper wins for local reporting; staff of The Orgeonian wins for breaking news; Cynthia Tucker of Atlanta Journal-Constituion wins for commentary; LA Weekly restaurant reviewer Jonathan Gold wins for criticism; prize for editorial writing goes to Arthur Browne, Heidi Evans and Beverly Weintraub of The New York Daily News; Oded Balilty of Associated Press wins for breaking news photography; Renee C Byer of The Sacramento Bee wins for feature photography; Walt Handelsman of Newsday wins for editorial cartooning; Gene Roberts and Hank Klibanoff (The Race Beat) win for history; Cormac McCarthy (The Road) wins for fiction; David Lindsay-Abaire (Rabbit Hole) wins for drama; Debby Applegate (The Most Famous Man in America; The Biography of Henry Ward Beecher) wins for biography; Lawrence Wright (The Looming Tower: AL-Qaeda and the Road to 9/11) wins for general nonfiction; Natasha Trethewey (Native Guard) wins for poetry; Ornette Coleman (Sound Grammar) wins for music; Pulitzer board also announces two special citations: one to science fiction writer Ray Bradbury for his prolific and deeply influential career and one to jazz saxophonist John Coltrane for his iconic centrality to history of jazz; Jahangir Razmi will be credited for 1980 Pulitzer for spot news photography; his name was withheld at time out of concern for his safety; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Wall Street Journal won the Pulitzer Prize for public service yesterday for uncovering the unethical practices of business executives who had rewarded themselves millions of dollars by backdating stock options. The articles, by Charles Forelle, James Bandler, Mark Maremont and Steve Stecklow, have led to the federal investigation of more than 130 companies, and at least 70 top executives have lost their jobs.</p>
        <p>In awarding The Journal its highest journalistic honor, the Pulitzer Prize Board said the paper had brought about ''widespread change in corporate America.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Wall Street Journal won the Pulitzer Prize for public service yesterday for uncovering the unethical practices of business executives who had rewarded themselves millions of dollars by backdating stock options. The articles, by Charles Forelle, James Bandler, Mark Maremont and Steve Stecklow, have led to the federal investigation of more than 130 companies, and at least 70 top executives have lost their jobs.</p>
        <p>In awarding The Journal its highest journalistic honor, the Pulitzer Prize Board said the paper had brought about ''widespread change in corporate America.''</p>
        <p>The Journal also won the Pulitzer Prize for international reporting, for a series of articles about the adverse effects of industrial development on China. The Journal was the only newspaper to win more than one award. The New York Times won the feature writing prize for a series called ''An Imam in America,'' written by Andrea Elliott, that focused on Sheik Reda Shata, the leader of a mosque in Brooklyn, and his struggle to reconcile Muslim tradition with American life. Ms. Elliott told colleagues in a newsroom ceremony that the Muslim community had at times been so difficult to penetrate that she felt she was covering ''the no one will talk to me beat.''</p>
        <p>The Boston Globe won for national reporting for articles by Charlie Savage documenting that President Bush had quietly disregarded portions of more than 750 laws enacted by Congress through ''signing statements'' that asserted that he had the power to bypass certain legal provisions because they conflicted with his interpretation of the Constitution.</p>
        <p>In the investigative reporting category, Brett J. Blackledge of The Birmingham News of Alabama won for ferreting out nepotism, cronyism and corruption within the state's two-year-college system. The prize for explanatory reporting went to The Los Angeles Times for a series called ''Altered Oceans,'' by Kenneth R. Weiss, Usha Lee McFarling and Rick Loomis, examining how industrialized society had altered the basic chemistry of the seas.</p>
        <p>The Miami Herald won for local reporting for articles by Debbie Cenziper for ''House of Lies,'' revealing that developers had received millions of dollars to build housing projects that they never delivered on.</p>
        <p>The staff of The Oregonian won in the breaking news reporting category for its coverage of the ordeal of the Kim family, which was lost for nearly nine days in Oregon.</p>
        <p>Cynthia Tucker, a columnist for The Atlanta Journal-Constitution, won the prize for commentary for what the Pulitzer board cited as ''her courageous, clear-headed columns.'' Jonathan Gold, a restaurant reviewer for LA Weekly, won the prize for criticism for what the board called his ''zestful'' writing.</p>
        <p>The prize for editorial writing went to Arthur Browne, Heidi Evans and Beverly Weintraub of The Daily News of New York for ''compassionate and compelling'' editorials about workers at ground zero whose health problems had been neglected. The Pulitzer for breaking news photography went to Oded Balilty of The Associated Press for a photo of a Jewish woman defying Israeli security forces. The Pulitzer for feature photography went to Renée C. Byer of The Sacramento Bee for a photo of a single mother and her young son as he died of cancer. Walt Handelsman of Newsday won the Pulitzer for editorial cartooning. No newspaper or single topic dominated the awards, administered by Columbia University.</p>
        <p>Sig Gissler, administrator of the Pulitzer Prizes, said the board changed the ''beat reporting'' category to ''local reporting'' this year to honor a subject that, he said, was ''the lifeblood of newspapers and is becoming more so.''</p>
        <p>In the Pulitzer Prizes for the arts, Gene Roberts and Hank Klibanoff won the prize for history for their book ''The Race Beat,'' about coverage of the civil rights movement. This is the first Pulitzer for Mr. Roberts, 74, who covered civil rights for The New York Times and presided over the winning of 17 Pulitzer Prizes in his 18 years as the editor at The Philadelphia Inquirer.</p>
        <p>Cormac McCarthy won the prize for fiction for ''The Road,'' David Lindsay-Abaire won the drama award for ''Rabbit Hole,'' and Debby Applegate won the biography prize for ''The Most Famous Man in America: The Biography of Henry Ward Beecher.'' The prize for nonfiction went to Lawrence Wright for ''The Looming Tower: Al-Qaeda and the Road to 9/11.'' Natasha Trethewey won the poetry prize for ''Native Guard.'' The prize in music went to Ornette Coleman for ''Sound Grammar.''</p>
        <p>The Pulitzer board also announced two special citations: one to the science fiction writer Ray Bradbury, the other to the jazz saxophonist John Coltrane. The board praised Mr. Bradbury's ''prolific and deeply influential career.'' It said Mr. Coltrane, who died in 1967, had ''masterful improvisation, supreme musicianship and iconic centrality to the history of jazz.''</p>
        <p>The board also confirmed a footnote to the Pulitzer for spot news photography that was awarded in 1980 for a photograph of a firing squad in Iran. The photographer's name was withheld out of concern for his safety. But The Wall Street Journal, in an article last December, named the photographer as Jahangir Razmi, and the citation from 1980 will be changed to give Mr. Razmi credit.</p>
        <p>HISTORY  GENE ROBERTS and HANK KLIBANOFF</p>
        <p>''The Race Beat: The Press, the Civil Rights Struggle, and the Awakening of a Nation''  Mr. Roberts, left, pulled in Mr. Klibanoff -- a fellow Southerner who is now a managing editor at The Atlanta Journal-Constitution -- to work on the book because ''like me, he thought it was a story that needed to be told.''</p>
        <p>''My span in journalism now covers a bit over 50 years,'' said Mr. Roberts, a journalism professor at the University of Maryland, who covered civil rights for The New York Times, ''and I never encountered a story quite like this one. It was long-running, it had emotional impact and it was probably the most important domestic story of the 20th century.''</p>
        <p>FINALISTS ''Middle Passages: African American Journeys to Africa, 1787-2005'' by James T. Campbell; ''Mayflower: A Story of Courage, Community, and War'' by Nathaniel Philbrick.</p>
        <p>BIOGRAPHY  DEBBY APPLEGATE</p>
        <p>''The Most Famous Man in America: The Biography of Henry Ward Beecher''  Ms. Applegate started looking into Beecher's life nearly 20 years ago, when she was a sophomore at Amherst College and was asked to put together an exhibition on notorious alumni. (Beecher graduated in 1834.) ''I came from a very evangelical community,'' she said, and ''I had never seen a religious figure who was so funny, irreverent, open minded and open hearted.''</p>
        <p>FINALISTS ''John Wilkes: The Scandalous Father of Civil Liberty,'' by Arthur H. Cash; ''Andrew Carnegie'' by David Nasaw.</p>
        <p>FICTION  CORMAC McCARTHY  ''The Road''  The famously reclusive Mr. McCarthy, 73, won for his devastating chronicle of a father and son walking alone across a post-apocalyptic America, cold, dark and strewn with corpses and ash. In her review in The New York Times,, Janet Maslin wrote, '' 'The Road' would be pure misery if not for its stunning, savage beauty.'' It is Mr. McCarthy's 10th novel.</p>
        <p>FINALISTS ''After This'' by Alice McDermott; ''The Echo Maker'' by Richard Powers.</p>
        <p>GENERAL NONFICTION  LAWRENCE WRIGHT  ''The Looming Tower: Al-Qaeda and the Road to 9/11''  Mr. Wright, 59, a staff writer for The New Yorker, spent five years investigating four principal characters he used to tell the story of the Sept. 11 terrorist attacks: Osama bin Laden; Ayman al-Zawahiri, Mr. bin Laden's chief lieutenant; John P. O'Neill, the former head of F.B.I. counterterrorism in New York, who died in the World Trade Center attack; and Prince Turki al-Faisal, the former head of Saudi Arabia's intelligence agency.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wright said he was rejected repeatedly for a journalist's visa to enter Saudi Arabia, so he instead went there as a mentor to young reporters. ''It was extremely beneficial that nobody thought of me as a reporter,'' he said. ''It was the best piece of bad luck I ever had.''</p>
        <p>Finalists ''Crazy: A Father's Search Through America's Mental Health Madness'' by Pete Earley; ''Fiasco: The American Military Adventure in Iraq'' by Thomas E. Ricks.</p>
        <p>DRAMA  DAVID LINDSAY-ABAIRE  ''Rabbit Hole''  Having built a reputation as a writer of absurdist comedies, Mr. Lindsay-Abaire, 37, surprised theatergoers with a sober, naturalistic portrait of an upper-middle-class family paralyzed by grief after the accidental death of their 4-year-old son.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lindsay-Abaire said the idea for the play was inspired by the advice of a teacher who told him he should write about what he fears the most. Of losing a child, he said, ''this is real fear, profound fear.''</p>
        <p>FINALISTS ''Orpheus X'' by Rinde Eckert, ''Bulrusher'' by Eisa Davis, and ''Elliot, a Soldier's Fugue'' by Quiara Alegría Hudes.</p>
        <p>POETRY  NATASHA TRETHEWEY  ''Native Guard''  In her third volume of poetry, Ms. Trethewey, the daughter of a black mother and white father, takes inspiration from the life of her mother and the history of Mississippi, where the poet was born. The title poem tells the story of a soldier who served in one of the first all-black regiments in the Union Army.</p>
        <p>Ms. Trethewey, 40, teaches creative writing at Emory University in Atlanta.</p>
        <p>FINALISTS ''The Republic of Poetry'' by Martin Espada; ''Interrogation Palace: New &amp; Selected Poems 1982-2004'' by David Wojahn.</p>
        <p>MUSIC  ORNETTE COLEMAN  ''Sound Grammar''  Mr. Coleman, the 77-year-old jazz saxophonist and composer, won for ''Sound Grammar,'' a live album by his most recent quartet, recorded in 2005.</p>
        <p>Elastic and bracing, with two acoustic basses and much collective improvisation, the music harks back to the 1960s records that made him famous. ''I'm tearing and I'm surprised and happy -- and I'm glad I'm an American,'' he said. ''And I'm glad to be a human being who's a part of making American qualities more eternal.''</p>
        <p>FINALISTS ''Grendel'' by Elliot Goldenthal; ''Astral Canticle'' by Augusta Read Thomas.</p>
        <p>PUBLIC SERVICE  THE WALL STREET JOURNAL  The Wall Street Journal was honored for what the Pulitzer Prize Board called ''its creative and comprehensive probe into backdated stock options for business executives,'' as a result of which more than 70 executives, including some chief executives, have been fired or have quit and 10 have been criminally charged. ''It was like an incredibly well-hidden secret in corporate America,'' said Mark Maremont, who reported and wrote the articles along with Charles Forelle, James Bandler and Steve Stecklow.</p>
        <p>FINALISTS The Birmingham News, in Alabama; The Washington Post.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL REPORTING  THE WALL STREET JOURNAL  The Pulitzer jury honored the newspaper for its ''sharply edged reports on the adverse impact of China's booming capitalism on conditions ranging from inequality to pollution.''</p>
        <p>The Journal detailed the costs of virtually unrestrained growth in China, where an entire industrial revolution has been condensed into the span of a single lifetime.</p>
        <p>One report detailed the dismantling of the cradle-to-grave social safety net that once ensured people's basic needs. Another highlighted the courage of a blogger who called for a boycott of the real estate market, tapping into widespread resentment of developers and their government backers.</p>
        <p>Another article recounted the efforts of a village doctor to rally farmers against a chemical factory dumping toxic waste into a river.</p>
        <p>FINALISTS The staff of The Los Angeles Times; Anthony Shadid of The Washington Post.</p>
        <p>NATIONAL REPORTING  CHARLIE SAVAGE  The Boston Globe  The judges lauded Charlie Savage, a 31-year-old Washington correspondent, for a series of articles about President Bush's efforts to expand presidential power through ''signing statements,'' technical legal documents that act as instructions to the executive branch.</p>
        <p>Mr. Savage showed how the president had used some 150 signing statements to assert the right to disregard parts of more than 750 laws, including a law banning torture.</p>
        <p>''For a while, The Globe was out there alone talking about these things, and the paper showed courage in continuing, before people began to react,'' Mr. Savage said.</p>
        <p>FINALISTS Maurice Possley and Steve Mills of The Chicago Tribune; Les Zaitz, Jeff Kosseff and Bryan Denson of The Oregonian, in Portland, Ore.</p>
        <p>INVESTIGATIVE REPORTING  BRETT J. BLACKLEDGE  The Birmingham News  Mr. Blackledge, 43, won for his work exposing extensive corruption and cronyism in Alabama's network of 26 two-year colleges and training schools.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blackledge's reporting has led to the chancellor's dismissal and to a move by the governor to ban the hiring of any state legislator by any of the colleges.</p>
        <p>FINALISTS Ken Armstrong, Justin Mayo and Steve Miletich of The Seattle Times; Michael J. Berens, Julia Sommerfeld and Carol Ostrom of The Seattle Times; Lisa Chedekel and Matthew Kauffman of The Hartford Courant.</p>
        <p>FEATURE WRITING  ANDREA ELLIOTT  The New York Times  Ms. Elliott, 34, who began writing about the Muslim experience in America in 2005, was honored for a series of articles on Sheik Reda Shata, an Egyptian-born imam who came to Brooklyn to preside over a mosque. The articles illustrated the highly charged challenges the imam faced as both prayer leader and, increasingly, a community leader.</p>
        <p>''When Islamic traditions clash with American culture, it is imams who step forward with improvised answers,'' Ms. Elliott wrote. ''Outside the mosque, many assume the public roles of other clergy, becoming diplomats for their faith.''</p>
        <p>FINALISTS Christopher Goffard of The St. Petersburg Times; Inara Verzemnieks of The Oregonian.</p>
        <p>BREAKING NEWS REPORTING  THE OREGONIAN  The staff of The Oregonian in Portland won for its coverage of a family that disappeared in the Oregon mountains during a blizzard.</p>
        <p>The Pulitzer judges commended the paper's ''skillful and tenacious'' coverage, which detailed how mistakes had slowed the search for the father as he wandered the snowy terrain in search of help. The mother and two daughters were found alive after nine days in the family car; the father was later found dead of hypothermia.</p>
        <p>FINALISTS The staff of The Courier-Journal, Louisville, Ky.; the staff of The Denver Post.</p>
        <p>EXPLANATORY REPORTING  KENNETH R. WEISS, USHA LEE McFARLING and RICK LOOMIS  The Los Angeles Times  The Pulitzer committee lauded the reporters Kenneth R. Weiss and Usha Lee McFarling, and the photographer Rick Loomis, for ''richly portrayed reports on the world's distressed oceans.'' The reports, in a series called ''Altered Oceans,'' described waters devolving into primeval seas dominated by slime.</p>
        <p>''We are despoiling our nests on a global scale,'' said Mr. Weiss, 49.</p>
        <p>FINALISTS The staff of The New York Times; Joanne Kimberlin and Bill Sizemore of The Virginian-Pilot, Norfolk, Va.</p>
        <p>LOCAL REPORTING  DEBBIE CENZIPER  The Miami Herald  Debbie Cenziper's exposé into waste and negligence at Miami-Dade County's housing agency became important quickly. She spent months tracking developers who got sweetheart deals from the county and residents who waited years for homes that never arrived.</p>
        <p>The response to her series surprised her. ''I was writing about a voiceless and vulnerable minority, and you wonder if anyone cares,'' she said. ''But in this case, Miami stepped up.'' Housing officials lost their jobs, developers were arrested and some residents are finally getting homes.</p>
        <p>FINALISTS The staff of The Boston Globe; Fred Schulte and June Arney of The Baltimore Sun.</p>
        <p>COMMENTARY  CYNTHIA TUCKER  The Atlanta Journal-Constitution  Ms. Tucker, The Atlanta Journal-Constitution's editorial page editor, was honored for ''her courageous, clear-headed columns that evince a strong sense of morality and persuasive knowledge of the community.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Tucker, 52, has been a columnist with The Journal-Constitution for more than 20 years and was a finalist in the same category in 2004 and 2006.</p>
        <p>''You really never know if you're having any influence in this business, but I would like to think that I did,'' she said.</p>
        <p>FINALISTS Ruth Marcus of The Washington Post; Joe Nocera of The New York Times.</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL WRITING  ARTHUR BROWNE, BEVERLY WEINTRAUB and HEIDI EVANS  The Daily News  The Daily News of New York was honored for a series of ''compassionate and compelling'' editorials taking aim at city, state and federal agencies for neglecting ground zero workers who developed extensive health problems after Sept. 11.</p>
        <p>The editorial campaign helped persuade New York lawmakers to pass a bill compensating ground zero workers.</p>
        <p>FINALISTS Jane Healy of The Orlando Sentinel; Sebastian Mallaby of The Washington Post.</p>
        <p>CRITICISM  JONATHAN GOLD  LA Weekly  Mr. Gold, LA Weekly's restaurant critic, is a cult figure among diners who follow him into the culinary nooks and crannies of the city he grew up in. His food interests vary widely. He might write that the corn dogs at Disneyland are the best he has ever had, or suggest that a tasting menu at the luxe Valentino is one of the best meals in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>FINALISTS Christopher Knight of The Los Angeles Times; Mark Swed of The Los Angeles Times.</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL CARTOONING  WALT HANDELSMAN  Newsday  Mr. Handelsman, 50, who won his first Pulitzer Prize in 1997, has been an editorial cartoonist for Newsday since 2001. This year was the first in which electronic submissions for editorial cartooning were accepted, and Mr. Handelsman submitted 10 animation pieces that average one minute in length.</p>
        <p>FINALISTS Mike Thompson of The Detroit Free Press; Nick Anderson of The Houston Chronicle.</p>
        <p>BREAKING NEWS PHOTOGRAPHY  ODED BALILTY  The Associated Press  Mr. Balilty, who is based in Jerusalem, won for what the judges called ''his powerful photograph of a lone Jewish woman defying Israeli security forces as they remove illegal settlers in the West Bank.''</p>
        <p>Santiago Lyon, director of photography for The Associated Press, said, ''It's a fantastic image from one of our most talented photographers.''</p>
        <p>FINALISTS The staff of The Associated Press; Michael Bryant of The Philadelphia Inquirer.</p>
        <p>FEATURE PHOTOGRAPHY  RENÉE C. BYER  The Sacramento Bee  Ms. Byer won for what the Pulitzer judges called ''her intimate portrayal of a single mother and her young son as he loses his battle with cancer.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Byer said she spent a year photographing the mother, Cyndie French, and her son, Derek Madsen, who was 11 when he died.</p>
        <p>''When someone says, 'My child has cancer,' it's almost overwhelming for people, so they turn away rather than becoming more compassionate, and if this can bring some compassion, I think that's very important,'' she said, adding that she had stayed in touch with Ms. French.</p>
        <p>FINALISTS Mary F. Calvert of The Washington Times; Gary Coronado of The Palm Beach Post.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 19, 2007, Thursday  An article on Tuesday about this year's Pulitzer Prize winners included outdated information from the Pulitzer board in some copies about the prize for editorial writing. After awarding it to the editorial board of The Daily News in New York, the Pulitzer board updated its Web site to note that it was won by only three writers from the paper: Arthur Browne, Heidi Evans and Beverly Weintraub. The article also referred incompletely in some copies to the reporters for The Wall Street Journal who contributed to the newspaper's prize for public service. In addition to Charles Forelle, James Bandler and Mark Maremont, Steve Stecklow worked on the project about the unethical practices of business executives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 19, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article on Tuesday about this year's Pulitzer Prize winners included outdated information from the Pulitzer board in some copies about the prize for editorial writing. After awarding it to the editorial board of The Daily News in New York, the Pulitzer board updated its Web site to note that it was won by only three writers from the paper: Arthur Browne, Heidi Evans and Beverly Weintraub. The article also referred incompletely in some copies to the reporters for The Wall Street Journal who contributed to the newspaper's prize for public service. In addition to Charles Forelle, James Bandler and Mark Maremont, Steve Stecklow worked on the project about the unethical practices of business executives.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
