<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Three Southern Women in Their House of Blues</title>
    <meta content="17blos" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/theater/reviews/17blos.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840927"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Emergency Theater (Theater Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zinoman, Jason</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halfnight, Ashlin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pines, Kate</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edgerly, Corrine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myers, Liz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccabe, Jennifer</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Mud Blossom (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Mud Blossom (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E2DA113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="452" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Three Southern Women in Their House of Blues</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Three Southern Women in Their House of Blues</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON ZINOMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinoman, Jason</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jason Zinoman reviews Emergency Theater production of Ashlin Halfnight play Mud Blossom, directed by Kate Pines; Corrine Edgerly, Liz Myers and Jennifer McCabe star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Is Ashlin Halfnight for real? With a name that inspires thoughts of things going bump in the night and a résumé that includes stints as a folk musician, minor league hockey player, Harvard undergraduate and New York International Fringe Festival playwright, Mr. Halfnight sounds like a character in a macabre and slightly unbelievable play. The truth is, he only wrote one.</p>
        <p>Death always seems to be right around the corner in ''Mud Blossom,'' Mr. Halfnight's brooding drama about a scarred family of three generations of Southern women trying to keep despair at bay in a cruel world in which no one wants to give a helping hand.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ashlin Halfnight offers a brooding drama about a scarred family of three generations of Southern women.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Is Ashlin Halfnight for real? With a name that inspires thoughts of things going bump in the night and a résumé that includes stints as a folk musician, minor league hockey player, Harvard undergraduate and New York International Fringe Festival playwright, Mr. Halfnight sounds like a character in a macabre and slightly unbelievable play. The truth is, he only wrote one.</p>
        <p>Death always seems to be right around the corner in ''Mud Blossom,'' Mr. Halfnight's brooding drama about a scarred family of three generations of Southern women trying to keep despair at bay in a cruel world in which no one wants to give a helping hand.</p>
        <p>In this Emergency Theater Project production, Camille (Liz Myers), a depressed teenager who dreams of Quebec, whispers dark secrets to her imaginary friend and writes poems about death. ''Mud Blossom'' can seem like a familiar coming-of-age play, and in some ways it is. Luckily, there is a more interesting dynamic at work between Camille's playful grandmother, Gongi (Corinne Edgerly), and her rigid mother, June (Jennifer McCabe), sparring partners who seem, respectively, younger and older than their ages.</p>
        <p>There has been no man in the house since June's husband committed suicide, which haunts the family in ways that are both obvious and less so. The air in this rickety old farmhouse, represented by a skeletal wooden frame, is thick with secrets. Mr. Halfnight, who has a gift for foreshadowing, hints at them with a finesse that is rare for a new writer.</p>
        <p>Kate Pines's naturalistic staging, though not helped by set and costume designs that lack a sense of place, gives a solid platform for these three actresses, who are more convincing as relatives than as poor Southerners.</p>
        <p>Ms. McCabe plays June with a steely spirit and dry eyes. She can't find a job, and in her struggles to support her family, all joy seems to have left her body. Her daughter comes home with a black eye and is increasingly distant, while outside a killer is on the loose, drawing his victims out of their houses by playing the sounds of a crying baby. ''If you hear the sound of a baby crying,'' reports the news anchor on the radio, ''do not go out to investigate it.''</p>
        <p>The play, which wallows a bit in despair, has the mood of a blues song, and the events of the past seem much more prominent than the actions of the present or the hopes of the future. Early on a gloomy Camille says that she just wants to find ''one good person.'' It turns out to be not so easy.</p>
        <p>''Mud Blossom'' continues through April 28 at Walkerspace, 46 Walker Street, SoHo; (212) 352-3101.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
