<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Corzine Could Be Walking In 3 Months, Doctors Say</title>
    <meta content="17corzine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/nyregion/17corzine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840970"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Codey, Richard J (Acting Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kocieniewski, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E7D8113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="700" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Corzine Could Be Walking In 3 Months, Doctors Say</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Corzine Could Be Walking in 3 Months, Doctors Say</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID KOCIENIEWSKI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kocieniewski, David</byline>
      <dateline>CAMDEN, N.J. April 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Gov Jon S Corzine undergoes third operation for severe leg fracture he suffered in traffic accident on April 12; doctors expect him to be able to walk without crutches in three to six months; say that because he is still on ventilator and unable to speak, he remains at risk of developing life-threatening complications; Richard J Codey, president of State Senate, is serving as acting governor (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Jon S. Corzine on Monday underwent his third operation for the severe leg fracture he suffered in a traffic accident last week, and doctors said afterward that they expect him to be able to walk without crutches in three to six months.</p>
        <p>But the governor -- still breathing with the help of a ventilator and unable to speak -- remains at risk of developing life-threatening complications like pneumonia or infection, the doctors said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>But Gov. Jon S. Corzine of New Jersey remains at risk of developing life-threatening complications like pneumonia or infection.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Jon S. Corzine on Monday underwent his third operation for the severe leg fracture he suffered in a traffic accident last week, and doctors said afterward that they expect him to be able to walk without crutches in three to six months.</p>
        <p>But the governor -- still breathing with the help of a ventilator and unable to speak -- remains at risk of developing life-threatening complications like pneumonia or infection, the doctors said.</p>
        <p>''He's not out of the woods yet,'' said Dr. Steven E. Ross, head of the trauma division at Cooper University Hospital here, where Mr. Corzine has been treated since the accident.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine, 60, has been in critical condition and on heavy doses of pain medication since Thursday evening, when he broke his left femur, 12 ribs, a lower vertebra and his breastbone and collarbone in a crash on Garden State Parkway.</p>
        <p>Dr. Robert F. Ostrum, the surgeon who has conducted all three operations on Mr. Corzine's leg and is Cooper's director of orthopedic trauma, said that the wound -- which occurred when the broken femur punctured his thigh twice -- does not appear to need any more surgery. The governor was able to move all four limbs when doctors asked, ''a good sign that all the muscles and nerves are working,'' Dr. Ostrum added.</p>
        <p>In a separate procedure on Monday using a local anesthetic, doctors inserted a drainage tube on the right side of Mr. Corzine's chest to remove fluid that had accumulated around his lungs. It is similar to the tube placed on the left side in a brief procedure Sunday. Dr. Ross said that Mr. Corzine would stay on the ventilator until his medication is reduced to a point where he can tolerate the pain of breathing on his own.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine's aides have said they hope he can resume his official duties by later this week. But doctors cautioned that breathing with broken ribs can be extremely painful, so they are unable to predict when the governor will be able to handle a reduction in his medication.</p>
        <p>''A lot of that is going to depend on his ability to tolerate pain,'' Dr. Ross said.</p>
        <p>With Mr. Corzine in a state of semiconsciousness, Richard J. Codey, the president of the State Senate, is serving as acting governor.</p>
        <p>At a briefing here, Dr. Ross reiterated his expressions of confidence that the governor had suffered no brain damage. A CT scan shortly after the accident found no structural brain injury, and nurses have since been monitoring Mr. Corzine's neurological functioning using the Glasgow Coma Scale. Dr. Ross said Mr. Corzine was rated at 11 out of 13, which he said is the highest a patient can score while on a breathing tube.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine was injured as his two-car caravan, red lights flashing, traveled from Atlantic City to Drumthwacket, the executive mansion in Princeton. He was running late for a meeting with the radio personality Don Imus and members of the Rutgers University women's basketball team.</p>
        <p>As the governor's Chevrolet Suburban was traveling a few miles north of the Atlantic City Expressway, the driver of a red pickup truck lost control of his vehicle while pulling to the side of the road, setting off a chain reaction that sent Mr. Corzine's sport utility vehicle slamming into a guard rail. The state police have not yet released their full report on the accident or the information, including the rate of speed, contained in a black box mounted in the vehicle. No charges have been filed against any drivers involved in the crash.</p>
        <p>The governor, who was in the front passenger seat and apparently not wearing a seat belt, was thrown past the second row of seats into the back of the Suburban. The state trooper who was driving, Robert Rasinski, and an aide to Mr. Corzine, Samantha Gordon, who was riding in the back seat, sustained minor injuries. They were both wearing seat belts, officials said.</p>
        <p>Despite his injuries, Mr. Corzine was able to describe the crash when he was admitted to the hospital.</p>
        <p>''He recalled some details when he first arrived,'' Dr. Ross said. ''Whether he will remember after being in intensive care, I don't know."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
