<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Back From Oblivion, Little-Heard Opera Gets Spotlight</title>
    <meta content="17fran" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/arts/music/17fran.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840924"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">American Symphony Orchestra</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Schreker, Franz</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E2DA113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="675" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Back From Oblivion, Little-Heard Opera Gets Spotlight</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Back From Oblivion, Little-Heard Opera Gets Spotlight</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the start of the 1920s, the Austrian composer Franz Schreker was a respected professor at the Berlin Hochschule and the celebrated composer of influential operas, including ''Der ferne Klang,'' which enjoyed enormous success at its 1912 premiere in Frankfurt.</p>
        <p>By the mid-1940s Schreker was almost forgotten. Only in recent years have his operas and concert works started making a comeback. On Sunday afternoon at Avery Fisher Hall, the conductor Leon Botstein, leading a strong cast, the Concert Chorale of New York and the American Symphony Orchestra, gave a concert performance of ''Der ferne Klang,'' which many consider a seminal work of 20th-century opera. It seemed so in this gripping performance, the first of any Schreker opera in the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The orchestra gave a gripping performance of “Der ferne Klang,” the first of any Franz Schreker opera in the United States, at Avery Fisher Hall on Sunday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At the start of the 1920s, the Austrian composer Franz Schreker was a respected professor at the Berlin Hochschule and the celebrated composer of influential operas, including ''Der ferne Klang,'' which enjoyed enormous success at its 1912 premiere in Frankfurt.</p>
        <p>By the mid-1940s Schreker was almost forgotten. Only in recent years have his operas and concert works started making a comeback. On Sunday afternoon at Avery Fisher Hall, the conductor Leon Botstein, leading a strong cast, the Concert Chorale of New York and the American Symphony Orchestra, gave a concert performance of ''Der ferne Klang,'' which many consider a seminal work of 20th-century opera. It seemed so in this gripping performance, the first of any Schreker opera in the United States.</p>
        <p>The neglect of Schreker is explained in part by the persecution his work suffered during the Nazi era. Born to a Jewish father, he died in 1934, at nearly 56, and for the next decade, his work was barred from German concert halls.</p>
        <p>The other factor is that Schreker's music straddled styles in a way that exasperated many composers and critics. That he never chose sides in the aesthetic battle of his time and drew from multiple influences -- post-Wagnerian chromatic harmony, Impressionism, a Straussian affinity for orchestral sonorities, shocking Expressionism and more -- led to the charge that his music lacked originality. Today the stylistic variety of his music seems bracing evidence of an undogmatic creative mind.</p>
        <p>With a libretto by the composer, the opera tells a grimly simple story. Grete, the beleaguered daughter of a drunken, retired minor official in a small town, yearns to run off with her boyfriend, Fritz, an aspiring composer. But Fritz, obsessed by an artistic search for the ''ferne Klang'' -- some distant sound that he hears only in his imagination -- sets off on his own.</p>
        <p>Ten years later Fritz encounters Grete in a lavish bordello on the Gulf of Venice and denounces her. In the final act his new opera is performed and deemed a failure; five years later, on his deathbed in his lonely study, Fritz, miserable with regret, is reconciled with the forgiving Grete.</p>
        <p>Below its melodramatic surface the opera teems with sensuality. The searching energy and harmonic restlessness of the music eerily capture Fritz's intangible quest to discover a transcendent musical sound. As the opera opens, over a taut pedal tone and shimmering string harmonies in the orchestra, an ominous theme struggles to emerge from the lower depths, like some new take on the opening of Wagner's ''Siegfried.'' Impressionistic whole-tone scales and Straussian polychordal harmony infiltrate the textures as well. In the first tense conversation between Grete and Fritz, Schreker's ability to write conversational yet subtly lyrical vocal lines is immediately striking.</p>
        <p>In Act II, at the garish dance hall, Schreker comes across as the Austrian Charles Ives. Voices of young women at the seashore, men in pursuit, a band playing intoxicating waltzes, frenzied dance music and more are heard simultaneously. Yet, through the unsettling sound collage, the bitter and poignant encounter between Grete and the condemning Fritz take center stage.</p>
        <p>The opera's two daunting lead roles were sung by impressive young artists. Yamina Maamar, an attractive German soprano with a cool, gleaming voice, triumphed as Grete. Robert Künzli brought urgency, stamina and a husky tenor voice to Fritz. There were several strong male singers in double roles, including Weston Hurt, Marc Embree and Ryan MacPherson. The mezzo-so prano Gloria Parker, as Grete's aggrieved mother and later a tough-skinned barmaid, was another standout.</p>
        <p>Mr. Botstein brought sure dramatic pacing and fiery commitment to his account of this thick and complex score for a huge orchestra, sizable chorus and large cast. Ideally, a conductor should shade and inflect the orchestral music better than Mr. Botstein did. At times he let the volatile orchestra cover the singers with an indistinct din of sound.</p>
        <p>Still, all credit to him for bringing this opera to attention. How can the Metropolitan Opera, which has given us such negligible works as Alfano's ''Cyrano de Bergerac,'' overlook this arresting masterpiece?</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
