<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Intimacy and Sentiment Leave and Then Return</title>
    <meta content="17oliv" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/arts/music/17oliv.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840913"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Knussen, Oliver</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E4DA113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="401" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Intimacy and Sentiment Leave and Then Return</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Intimacy and Sentiment Leave and Then Return</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD HOLLAND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holland, Bernard</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Oliver Knussen's ''Requiem: Songs for Sue'' at Zankel Hall on Friday night remembered both his wife and the kind of horizontal, heart-on-sleeve melodic style that the rest of the evening seemed studiously to avoid. Mr. Knussen's musical language here stretches beyond old ideas of tonal agreement and weights its ensemble sound toward winds and keyboard instruments, elements that are anything but Romantic.</p>
        <p>Intimacy and sentiment, on the other hand, returned these four songs in three languages to Mahler or Schumann, leaving them far from the worlds of Magnus Lindberg, Olivier Messiaen and Julian Anderson, also represented on Friday. The soprano Susan Narucki, whose true ear and musical sophistication keep her busy deciphering and projecting post-Mahlerian vocal music, worked hard to match the work's strong feelings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The deft Mr. Knussen led the extraordinary Zankel Band in a program of Magnus Lindberg, Olivier Messiaen and Julian Anderson on Friday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Oliver Knussen's ''Requiem: Songs for Sue'' at Zankel Hall on Friday night remembered both his wife and the kind of horizontal, heart-on-sleeve melodic style that the rest of the evening seemed studiously to avoid. Mr. Knussen's musical language here stretches beyond old ideas of tonal agreement and weights its ensemble sound toward winds and keyboard instruments, elements that are anything but Romantic.</p>
        <p>Intimacy and sentiment, on the other hand, returned these four songs in three languages to Mahler or Schumann, leaving them far from the worlds of Magnus Lindberg, Olivier Messiaen and Julian Anderson, also represented on Friday. The soprano Susan Narucki, whose true ear and musical sophistication keep her busy deciphering and projecting post-Mahlerian vocal music, worked hard to match the work's strong feelings.</p>
        <p>Mr. Knussen conducted the Zankel Band in this and everything else. He is deft at his job and had in front of him an extraordinary collection of talent, sprinkled with veterans of the new-music world but mostly young players.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lindberg's ''Corrente'' and Mr. Anderson's ''Book of Hours'' are happy to stand in one place and change before our eyes. ''Corrente'' develops its energy from trills, repeated notes and tremolos, which alter and interweave in unstable patterns of movement, growing in force, layer by layer. If ''Requiem: Songs for Sue'' is like a vehicle with a destination, ''Corrente'' is like a generator bolted down, going nowhere but getting stronger with each surge of juice.</p>
        <p>''Book of Hours'' has the same fixed flavor but is probably more like a crowd scene in its effect, as if someone had pointed a camera at a milling intersection and left it to accumulate what might pass by. A recurring theme is a major scale that struggles to make its way upward. Undulating tones are like visual waves of heat. At the end comes a long cadenza for electronically manipulated sound, beginning with radio static and gaining force and depth, as the live instruments have already done.</p>
        <p>Different from these pieces -- indeed, different from any other music -- was Messiaen's ''Oiseaux Exotiques,'' with Peter Serkin playing the piano part splendidly. This banging, brittle, shrieking celebration of life, with tidbits of exotic birdcall imitations thrown in, made the rest of a substantial evening seem incidental.</p>
        <p>Like Berlioz, Messiaen seems to have descended from a spaceship. He came from nowhere and forgot to take his music with him when he left.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
