<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Bands, Different on the Surface but With Quite a Few Shared Ideas</title>
    <meta content="17clou" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/arts/music/17clou.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840912"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Pop</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Rock Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rock Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E4DA113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="594" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Bands, Different on the Surface but With Quite a Few Shared Ideas</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Two Bands, Different on the Surface but With Quite a Few Shared Ideas</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATE CHINEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chinen, Nate</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''These days it's hard to tell what's outside from what's in my mind,'' sang Craig Minowa of Cloud Cult at the Mercury Lounge on Sunday night. He was delivering a line from the band's gently psychedelic new single, ''Chemicals Collide.'' His lyrics described a sort of commingling -- of essences or enzymes, or maybe both -- between romantic partners. He made chemistry sound like a mystical act.</p>
        <p>By coincidence, a similar idea had cropped up in the preceding set, by a group called Young Galaxy. The song in that case was ''The Alchemy Between Us,'' and it built to a deliberate climax. But its message of connection, sung in octaves by Stephen Ramsay and Catherine McCandless, felt confidential and vaguely spiritual.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The bands share a fascination with the laws of attraction,and both proselytize the art of letting go. And eachplayed a strong show on Sunday, though not without brushing up against limitations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''These days it's hard to tell what's outside from what's in my mind,'' sang Craig Minowa of Cloud Cult at the Mercury Lounge on Sunday night. He was delivering a line from the band's gently psychedelic new single, ''Chemicals Collide.'' His lyrics described a sort of commingling -- of essences or enzymes, or maybe both -- between romantic partners. He made chemistry sound like a mystical act.</p>
        <p>By coincidence, a similar idea had cropped up in the preceding set, by a group called Young Galaxy. The song in that case was ''The Alchemy Between Us,'' and it built to a deliberate climax. But its message of connection, sung in octaves by Stephen Ramsay and Catherine McCandless, felt confidential and vaguely spiritual.</p>
        <p>Though different on the surface, Cloud Cult and Young Galaxy share a fascination with the laws of attraction, and both bands proselytize the art of letting go. Each has a solid new album and the makings of an identifiable approach. And each played a strong show on Sunday, though not without brushing up against limitations.</p>
        <p>Cloud Cult, from Minneapolis, was the more upbeat of the two. Along with the standard instrumentation of guitar, bass and drums, the band featured a cellist and a violinist, as well as two action painters. Adding to the bohemian vibe, one painter doubled on trumpet and the other was Connie Minowa, Mr. Minowa's wife.</p>
        <p>The show was heavy on material from ''The Meaning of 8,'' a cryptic new release on Mr. Minowa's Earthology label. Most of the songs sounded sharp as Mr. Minowa sang them in his high and reedy voice. But the band's influences often came across clearly enough to be a distraction. ''Chain Reaction'' (there's that chemistry theme again) had the orchestral-pop flourishes and obscure vulnerability of a Flaming Lips song. ''Please Remain Calm'' was one of several tunes evocative of Modest Mouse. A Neil Young reference crept in, too.</p>
        <p>As influences go, Young Galaxy, based in Montreal, is even more transparent. Mr. Ramsay has expressed his abiding admiration of Fleetwood Mac, and most of the songs on Young Galaxy's self-titled debut album (scheduled for release next week) strike a balance between dreamy and downcast. It was much the same on Sunday night, though the band's guitars-and-keyboards wash was more invigorating in performance.</p>
        <p>Ms. McCandless and Mr. Ramsay both have deep singing voices and favor the darker tonalities within them. And while their songs occasionally flirt with head-bobbing tempos, Young Galaxy is most at home in a slow-drag mode. ''Lazy Religion'' and ''Wailing Wall'' sounded great in all their languid glory, and ''Swing Your Heartache,'' the band's first single, was even better.</p>
        <p>''It's time for you and I to face the signs and realize that living's a battle,'' Mr. Ramsay and Ms. McCandless sang together, with a kind of serenity. ''Living's a battle!'' several other band members agreed emphatically, projecting without microphones. By the time the song's steady crescendo came to a halt, the band had hammered home the theme of facing facts and carrying on.</p>
        <p>Cloud Cult offered much the same advice in ''Take Your Medicine,'' the highlight of its set. Inspired, like much of Cloud Cult's music, by the death of the Minowas' infant son, the song's lyrics suggested a scrap of hard-earned wisdom. And Mr. Minowa sang them earnestly, while strumming an acoustic guitar:</p>
        <p>You can take it in stride  Or you can take it right between the eyes  Suck up, suck up  And take your medicine  It's a good day, it's a good day  To face the hard things.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
