<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Imus's Longtime Sidekick Joins Other Pinch-Hitters</title>
    <meta content="17mcco" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/arts/television/17mcco.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840917"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">CBS Corp</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Imus, Don</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E4DA113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="607" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Imus's Longtime Sidekick Joins Other Pinch-Hitters</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Imus’s Longtime Sidekick Joins Other Pinch-Hitters</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACQUES STEINBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinberg, Jacques</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Regular listeners of Don Imus got a surprise yesterday when they tuned in ''Mike and the Mad Dog,'' the show that is temporarily replacing ''Imus in the Morning'' in the aftermath of its host's firing last week. For four hours yesterday morning, Mike Francesa and Christopher Russo (the ''Mad Dog'') were joined on the air by Charles McCord, Mr. Imus's longtime news reader and principal sidekick, who is apparently continuing in that role.</p>
        <p>Karen Mateo, a spokeswoman for CBS Radio, which owns WFAN in New York, the flagship for both ''Imus'' and ''Mike and the Mad Dog,'' said yesterday that ''Mr. McCord's status with the station is unchanged.'' In other words, Mr. McCord was scheduled to be back again this morning, as Mr. Francesa and Mr. Russo continue to pinch-hit for at least the next two weeks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Charles McCord, Don Imus’s longtime news reader, is apparently continuing in that role and time slot without him at CBS Radio.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Regular listeners of Don Imus got a surprise yesterday when they tuned in ''Mike and the Mad Dog,'' the show that is temporarily replacing ''Imus in the Morning'' in the aftermath of its host's firing last week. For four hours yesterday morning, Mike Francesa and Christopher Russo (the ''Mad Dog'') were joined on the air by Charles McCord, Mr. Imus's longtime news reader and principal sidekick, who is apparently continuing in that role.</p>
        <p>Karen Mateo, a spokeswoman for CBS Radio, which owns WFAN in New York, the flagship for both ''Imus'' and ''Mike and the Mad Dog,'' said yesterday that ''Mr. McCord's status with the station is unchanged.'' In other words, Mr. McCord was scheduled to be back again this morning, as Mr. Francesa and Mr. Russo continue to pinch-hit for at least the next two weeks.</p>
        <p>For more than three decades, Mr. McCord read the news alongside Mr. Imus, often at the top of the hour, and engaged in a running back-and-forth with him throughout his broadcast. The two men often spoke on the air of having spent hours on the phone the previous evening, talking about whatever might be going on in the news or their personal lives, at least partly as grist for the show. Mr. McCord also wrote a fair amount of comedy for the show, including satiric monologues performed by others imitating the voices of the Rev. Jerry Falwell and Jack Nicholson.</p>
        <p>Yesterday Mr. McCord read the news as he always does. But afterward, everything else was different, as if he were the lone easy chair in a living room in which all the other furniture had been removed. Mr. Russo and Mr. Francesa, whose afternoon show on WFAN is entirely sports-driven, spent several minutes early in yesterday's show denouncing both CBS Radio and MSNBC (which used to simulcast ''Imus'') for dumping Mr. Imus so abruptly last week over his racially and sexually disparaging comments on April 4 about the Rutgers women's basketball team.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCord had been on that day's broadcast but had not participated in the brief exchange about the Rutgers team, which was primarily between Mr. Imus and the show's executive producer, Bernard McGuirk, who had described the team in similarly crude remarks. Yesterday Mr. McCord suggested that Mr. Imus's dismissal did not befit someone of his longtime tenure and stature in broadcasting.</p>
        <p>And then, after a few minutes, Mr. Russo changed the subject entirely. He engaged both Mr. Francesa and Mr. McCord on the matter of Marco Scutaro's two-out, walk-off home run against Mariano Rivera of the Yankees, which gave the Oakland A's a come-from-behind victory on Sunday.</p>
        <p>In lieu of the newsmaker interviews with politicians and journalists that were a staple of the Imus format, Mr. Francesa and Mr. Russo spoke yesterday with Rick DiPietro, the goalie for the New York Islanders, who had returned to the team for a playoff game Saturday after a recent concussion.</p>
        <p>An excerpt from yesterday's show:</p>
        <p>Mr. Russo: ''I know the doctors cleared you, Rick. Mentally and physically -- forget mentally -- physically were you 100 percent for that game two, maybe about 85/90, and you got through it?''</p>
        <p>Mr. DiPietro: ''I felt all right. There was obviously a little bit of rust.''</p>
        <p>Westwood One, which had syndicated the ''Imus'' show to 60 affiliates around the country, said yesterday that 33 had broadcast ''Mike and the Mad Dog'' yesterday and would do so at least for this week; the remainder of the stations substituted other shows, some local.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCord did not respond to several messages left for him yesterday, and in recent days, at his home in New Jersey.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
