<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Soft-Lensed 'Memories,' But a Life From Within</title>
    <meta content="17orph" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/arts/music/17orph.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840914"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Orpheus Chamber Orchestra</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E4DA113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="387" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Soft-Lensed 'Memories,' But a Life From Within</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Soft-Lensed ‘Memories,’ but a Life From Within</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD HOLLAND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holland, Bernard</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mendelssohn's B minor Sinfonia at Carnegie Hall on Saturday night showed why Orpheus continues to be our joy and our despair. The piece is in two parts, the first an adagio of twisting, turning harmonic originality, the second a busy, fast-moving allegro. Orpheus, a small orchestra famous for what it doesn't have (a conductor), produced at the start a near-breathtaking, bass-driven sonority -- well tuned, single-minded in its mutual concentration and just plain beautiful to hear.</p>
        <p>When Mendelssohn demanded more notes, rapid execution and precise togetherness, you heard the price that had been paid: admirable coordination at the beginning and end of phrases, but a kind of impressionistic haze in between, as if individual string players each had their own minutely different takes on what togetherness means.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In its Saturday performance of Mendelssohn’s B minor Sinfonia, the orchestra produced a near-breathtaking, bass-driven sonority that was beautiful to hear.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mendelssohn's B minor Sinfonia at Carnegie Hall on Saturday night showed why Orpheus continues to be our joy and our despair. The piece is in two parts, the first an adagio of twisting, turning harmonic originality, the second a busy, fast-moving allegro. Orpheus, a small orchestra famous for what it doesn't have (a conductor), produced at the start a near-breathtaking, bass-driven sonority -- well tuned, single-minded in its mutual concentration and just plain beautiful to hear.</p>
        <p>When Mendelssohn demanded more notes, rapid execution and precise togetherness, you heard the price that had been paid: admirable coordination at the beginning and end of phrases, but a kind of impressionistic haze in between, as if individual string players each had their own minutely different takes on what togetherness means.</p>
        <p>This is what Orpheus is, and we might as well stop complaining about it. The welcome and the suspect in its music-making are part of the same thing. The orchestra is like a friend we want to keep around, bad habits notwithstanding. Ingram Marshall's new ''Orphic Memories'' before intermission appealed to everything good about these players; its gently rolling music, exquisitely colored and articulated, seemed almost site-specific.</p>
        <p>''Orphic Memories'' relies on lovely string sound and talented wind players. Orpheus has them. Soft-lensed as this music appears, its life comes from within, in subtle rhythmic variation of the moving parts. The language would not have seemed all that strange in turn-of-the-20th-century France or Edwardian England, although Debussy might not have understood those repeated-note Minimalisms.</p>
        <p>With its old-fashioned speech and rhetoric, ''Orphic Memories'' makes a broad target for anti-reactionary pioneers espousing new languages spoken in new ways. Mr. Marshall confounds them with the quality and the thoughtfulness of his music, which is neither defiant nor submissive, just comfortable. This is an exceptionally successful piece.</p>
        <p>Gil Shaham brought his own exceptional abilities to the Beethoven Violin Concerto after intermission. He is everything a virtuoso in the Romantic tradition should be. The slow movement is better served, I think, with more restraint and dignity and fewer headlong melodic surges. I also think the orchestra would have sounded more poised had it been able to constrain the soloist's freewheeling style and not pant in pursuit of it. Mr. Shaham's Beethoven is a matter of taste -- not mine -- but he is quite a player.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
