<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Learning About Choices From Those We Honor</title>
    <meta content="17nyc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/nyregion/17nyc.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840991"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NYC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Names, Geographical</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Streets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carson, Sonny (1936-2002)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Quinn, Christine C (Council Speaker)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vann, Albert (Councilman)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haberman, Clyde</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/NYC</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Names, Geographical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Robinson, Jackie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E1D8113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="766" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Learning About Choices From Those We Honor</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Learning About Choices From Those We Honor</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE HABERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Haberman, Clyde</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Clyde Haberman column opposes measure before City Council to rename street in Bedford-Stuyvesant for late black activist Sonny Carson, calling him flatout racist; supports move by Speaker Christine C Quinn to strip Carson's name from omnibus street-naming bill because of his history of unabashed bigotry; notes that Councilman Albert Vann, who put Carson on list, says that he made powerful contributions to community despite his flaws (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last week's big name in race relations was Don Imus. This week we have Sonny Carson. We're not exactly working with a gorgeous mosaic here.</p>
        <p>Mr. Imus needs no introduction. Mr. Carson's name may not ring all bells. More on him in a moment. But first let us note the celebration of racial justice that took place on Sunday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Baseball players who wore Jackie Robinson’s No. 42 this week reminded us that it once was, and still is, possible for Americans to heed their better angels on matters of race.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Last week's big name in race relations was Don Imus. This week we have Sonny Carson. We're not exactly working with a gorgeous mosaic here.</p>
        <p>Mr. Imus needs no introduction. Mr. Carson's name may not ring all bells. More on him in a moment. But first let us note the celebration of racial justice that took place on Sunday.</p>
        <p>Baseball players, including those representing New York, wore Jackie Robinson's No. 42 to honor the day 60 years ago when he ended white dominion over the major leagues. Obviously, their small act did not heal the wounds of centuries. But it was not an empty ''Kumbaya'' moment. The athletes' gesture served as a reminder that it once was, and still is, possible for Americans to heed their better angels on matters of race.</p>
        <p>At the same time, we had Don Imus, and now the ghost of Sonny Carson.</p>
        <p>Mr. Carson, who died in 2002 at 66, was (take your pick) a black activist, a community advocate, an over-the-top radical, a onetime thug who went to prison on a kidnapping conviction with roots in a murder case, an antidrug crusader and a flat-out racist. ''All of the above'' would be a reasonable choice. But the last entry in his CV is what's at issue.</p>
        <p>Responding to accusations of anti-Semitism, he once said: ''I'm antiwhite. Don't limit my antis to just one group of people.'' Indeed, Mr. Carson was a renaissance bigot. He proved that in 1990 when he led a boycott of Korean-owned delis in heavily black neighborhoods. His slogan, carried on picket signs, was ever so subtle: ''Don't shop with people who don't look like us.''</p>
        <p>The question now before a City Council committee is whether a fellow like that deserves a street named for him. Community Board 3 in Brooklyn, preferring to focus on Mr. Carson's antidrug work and other campaigns, says yes. It wants to call a stretch of Gates Avenue in Bedford-Stuyvesant ''Sonny Abubadika Carson Avenue.'' Its wish is part of an omnibus street-naming bill that the Council's Parks and Recreation Committee will consider on Thursday.</p>
        <p>The Council has long been accused of spending too much time doling out street names, typically to honor local big shots or police officers and firefighters who died on the job. That pattern holds with the 53 changes proposed in the latest omnibus bill. It includes prominent names like Jerry Orbach, Percy E. Sutton, Alvin Ailey and Robert Merrill. And Sonny Carson.</p>
        <p>For the Council's speaker, Christine C. Quinn, his presence on the list shows that street-naming is not the joke some take it for. ''It's government saying that someone deserves the prestige,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Think, Ms. Quinn said, of what future generations might make of lawmakers who ''voted to honor a man who was committed to a discriminating message against whites; what does that say about the values of the City Council at that time?''</p>
        <p>Given Sonny Carson's ''history of unabashed bigotry,'' she wants his name stripped from the bill. ''At some point, you have to have standards,'' she said. She also admits, however, to stepping into uncharted legal territory. The Council's lawyers are puzzling over how to go about abandoning the Sonny side of the street.</p>
        <p>Watching from the sidelines is Councilman Albert Vann of Brooklyn, who put Mr. Carson on the list. Sure, Sonny Carson was no ''paragon of virtue'' and said ''some hateful things,'' Mr. Vann said. But he also made ''some powerful contributions to the community.''</p>
        <p>As he sees it, ''each local community has a right to have streets named after people they think meant something to that community.''</p>
        <p>Hmm. What if some neighborhood wished to create a Don Imus Street? Mr. Imus, for all his foul words, has done plenty of good, including raising money to help children with cancer. What if people in Ozone Park, Queens, asked for a John J. Gotti Way? The late mobster was regarded as a patron saint by some in that part of town.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vann acknowledged that he might have a problem with those changes. Most New Yorkers probably would.</p>
        <p>But then, the councilman asked, what about existing street names? ''There are a lot of streets in my community named after slaveholders,'' he said. ''So I guess we'd have to start renaming all the streets. I don't know where this thing stops.''</p>
        <p>Hmm again. On that one, he had a point.</p>
        <p>Maybe instead of naming streets we could all just wear No. 42. Why not on our sleeves? It seems like a much safer way to reach those better angels of ours.</p>
        <p>NYC E-mail: haberman@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: haberman@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
