<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Advocate Of the War Explores Its Impact</title>
    <meta content="17free" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/arts/television/17free.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840925"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Public Broadcasting Service</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Perle, Richard N</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E2DA113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="960" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Advocate Of the War Explores Its Impact</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Advocate of the War Explores Its Impact</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALESSANDRA STANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stanley, Alessandra</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Richard N. Perle can sleep at night.</p>
        <p>If ''The Case for War: In Defense of Freedom'' is any guide, this former chairman of the Defense Policy Board who so fiercely lobbied for the invasion of Iraq enjoys the deep, flannelly slumber of infants and the well medicated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Richard N. Perle, the former chairman of the Defense Policy Board, admits neither mistakes nor regrets on his support of the war, and nothing can shake him of his complacency.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Richard N. Perle can sleep at night.</p>
        <p>If ''The Case for War: In Defense of Freedom'' is any guide, this former chairman of the Defense Policy Board who so fiercely lobbied for the invasion of Iraq enjoys the deep, flannelly slumber of infants and the well medicated.</p>
        <p>In an hourlong, first-person tour of his thinking, Mr. Perle admits neither mistakes nor regrets. The war is not even his main concern. Instead, Mr. Perle, a leading neo-conservative, uses much of tonight's segment of the weeklong PBS series ''America at a Crossroads'' to argue that the United States should foment regime change in Iran, regardless of what Iran and other nations think.</p>
        <p>''There's got to be some advantage to being a superpower,'' Mr. Perle tells Patrick J. Buchanan, the conservative columnist who worked with Mr. Perle in the Reagan administration.</p>
        <p>''This sounds like the Neo-Comintern,'' Mr. Buchanan replies, looking more than a little aghast. ''I mean, the Soviet Union, that was their idea.''</p>
        <p>Viewers worried that a video diary by Mr. Perle could be too one-sided and self-serving should relax. Like the unreliable narrator in a novel, Mr. Perle exposes himself by omission and indirection. ''The Case for War'' is not very persuasive about American policy. Instead it is a fascinating study in rationalization, a lighter, less repentant version of ''The Fog of War,'' Errol Morris's documentary about Robert S. McNamara.</p>
        <p>As Elizabeth Jensen reported in The New York Times earlier this month, Bush administration critics were suspicious of the entire 11-part series about the world after 9/11, especially the portion turned over to Mr. Perle. The Corporation for Public Broadcasting, which administers federal money to public television and radio, has long been under pressure by the White House to include more conservative voices. (The corporation's chairman, Kenneth Y. Tomlinson, was forced to resign in November 2005 after it was revealed that he had monitored the political leanings of some guests on PBS.)</p>
        <p>It didn't help that Brian Lapping, the British producer who first proposed a film about Mr. Perle, turned out to be his friend. Mr. Lapping later recused himself from the project.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perle's journey is a tour of the world as he sees it. It includes a trip to a girls' school in Kabul, Afghanistan, and an outdoor market, the kind of blinkered V.I.P. visit usually reserved for first ladies. (Mr. Perle notes that the Taliban is still active in southern Afghanistan without acknowledging that it is also on the rise.) In Moscow he reminisces about his days in the Reagan administration battling the ''evil empire'' during a visit with the former Soviet dissident Natan Sharansky outside Lefortovo Prison, where Mr. Sharansky was interrogated 30 years ago.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Perle takes an even more remote skip down memory lane to Los Angeles and his alma mater, Hollywood High, where the halls are lined with the names of famous students like Tuesday Weld, and where Mr. Perle says he first learned to distrust Hollywood liberals.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perle links today's antiwar demonstrators -- the film includes snippets of Martin Sheen and Jessica Lange speaking out against the president -- to the Hollywood leftists who were soft on Stalinism in his youth.</p>
        <p>He leaves out any discussion of the Vietnam War, perhaps because he didn't serve in it.</p>
        <p>Iraq also has little room on his agenda, which could explain why the producers insisted that Mr. Perle attend an antiwar demonstration at the Washington Monument and face his most impassioned critics.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perle is shown in a tweed jacket, weaving his way confidently through the crowd, debating veterans and angry mothers of dead servicemen. When a march organizer calmly argues that the Iraq war is neither just nor necessary and should be ended, Mr. Perle listens, then waves his hand toward the rows and rows of boots placed on the ground to represent each fallen soldier. ''I don't believe that's fair to them,'' he says.</p>
        <p>Afterward, Mr. Perle says he sympathizes with the mourning relatives, adding, ''But I believe the case for intervening in Iraq was and remains valid.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Perle was less adamant in a Vanity Fair article in November titled ''Neo Culpa.'' Mr. Perle blamed the administration's incompetence for the mismanagement of the occupation, but admitted, in hindsight, that the rush to topple Saddam Hussein was too hasty. ''Could we have managed that threat by means other than a direct military intervention?'' Mr. Perle said in the article. ''Well, maybe we could have.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Perle makes no such admission in ''The Case for War,'' and nothing and no one can shake him of his complacency, not Richard C. Holbrooke, former American ambassador to the United Nations, nor Abdel Bari Atwan, editor of Al Quds al Arabi, a London-based newspaper, who angrily says that the occupation of Iraq has revived and empowered Al Qaeda.</p>
        <p>When Simon Jenkins, a former editor of The Times of London, warns about British and Soviet failures in Afghanistan, Mr. Perle looks heavy-lidded and even a bit bored.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perle comes alive in a hotel room in Dubai, beaming as he listens to a young Iranian dissident who recently escaped and wants the West to help overthrow the government of President Mahmoud Ahmadinejad. Mr. Perle listens and nods intently, even though the young man speaks in Farsi. Mr. Perle doesn't need the translator to know that his protégé is speaking of freedom, tyranny and insurrection.</p>
        <p>At that moment Mr. Perle is as rapt as an opera buff at the opening night of ''Parsifal.'' He may not understand the words, but he loves the music.</p>
        <p>America at a Crossroads  The Case for War: In Defense of Freedom</p>
        <p>On most PBS stations tonight (check local listings).  Phil Craig and Brook Lapping Productions, executive producers; Mick Gold, producer.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
