<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Trial on Long Island, Priest Defends Hiring of Worker Who Later Abused Teenagers</title>
    <meta content="17diocese" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/nyregion/17diocese.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840971"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">East Meadow (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Raphael Church (East Meadow, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haggerty, Thomas (Rev)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maiello, Matthew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lambert, Bruce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Roman Catholic Church</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E7D8113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="657" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Trial on Long Island, Priest Defends Hiring of Worker Who Later Abused Teenagers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At Trial on Long Island, Priest Defends Hiring of Worker Who Later Abused Teenagers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE LAMBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lambert, Bruce</byline>
      <dateline>GARDEN CITY, N.Y., April 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Opening statements are made in civil trial over sexual abuse at St Raphael's Roman Catholic Church in East Meadow, NY; two victims, man and woman, accuse Rev Thomas Haggerty, pastor, of neglecting background checks when hiring Matthew Maiello as youth ministry director; Maiello later served two years in prison for statutory rape of two victims and two other teenagers from parish; defense lawyer says neither Haggerty nor church was responsible for Maiello's conduct; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As a civil trial over sexual abuse at a Roman Catholic church began on Monday, the lawyer for the two victims who filed the lawsuit accused the pastor of neglecting background checks in hiring the youth ministry director who committed the abuse.</p>
        <p>The employee, Matthew Maiello, later served two years in prison for the statutory rape of the two victims and two other teenagers from the parish.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The pastor of a Roman Catholic church was accused of neglecting background checks in hiring the youth ministry director who committed sexual abuse.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As a civil trial over sexual abuse at a Roman Catholic church began on Monday, the lawyer for the two victims who filed the lawsuit accused the pastor of neglecting background checks in hiring the youth ministry director who committed the abuse.</p>
        <p>The employee, Matthew Maiello, later served two years in prison for the statutory rape of the two victims and two other teenagers from the parish.</p>
        <p>''Who let the beast loose to run free through the flock of Father Thomas Haggerty, picking his victims at will?'' the lawyer, Michael G. Dowd, said in his opening statement in State Supreme Court here, referring to the pastor, whom he later called as his first witness.</p>
        <p>Brian R. Davey, the lawyer defending Father Haggerty; the parish, St. Raphael's Roman Catholic Church of East Meadow; and the Diocese of Rockville Centre, said neither the pastor nor the church was responsible for Mr. Maiello's conduct. Mr. Maiello, 33, is also a defendant, but he is not contesting the lawsuit and did not have a lawyer make a statement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dowd said the defendants, ''through their carelessness, negligence and recklessness,'' had failed to safeguard the youths entrusted to their care. But Mr. Davey, in his opening statement, said, ''Father Tom did not know that Matthew Maiello was a criminal.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Davey also disputed the claims of the plaintiffs -- a man and a woman who are now in their early 20s -- that they suffered post-traumatic stress disorder and other psychological scars from the abuses, which started when they were 15 and lasted three years.</p>
        <p>''Anybody can say, 'I have nightmares, I'm depressed, I'm in fear for my life,' '' he said, promising to share evidence that the plaintiffs had rebounded and ''flourished'' in their schools, jobs and community activities.</p>
        <p>The young man who is suing won promotions in his workplace and in his volunteer work for a local fire department, Mr. Davey said, and the young woman made dean's list, earned a perfect 4.0 average and was elected class president at college.</p>
        <p>On the stand, Father Haggerty acknowledged that when he hired Mr. Maiello, he did not verify Mr. Maiello's claim of being near completion of a college degree, which was false. Mr. Dowd noted that Mr. Maiello's Molloy College transcript showed he had failed some courses, including Bible, ''but got an A in the psychology of women, one of his few A's.'' Father Haggerty testified that had he seen that record earlier, he would not have hired Mr. Maiello.</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Maiello's résumé emphasized his youth work at St. Edward the Confessor Church in Syosset, Father Haggerty conceded that the pastor there said he did not remember Mr. Maiello. He also acknowledged that Mr. Maiello had no special training in music or liturgy.</p>
        <p>What Mr. Maiello had going for him, Father Haggerty said, was several months as the director of the rock music Mass at St. Raphael's, ''a very good voice'' and popularity with the parishioners. Father Haggerty said he had also relied on recommendations from another priest at St. Raphael's who had recruited Mr. Maiello for the rock Mass, and from a priest at a Catholic high school.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dowd also accused Father Haggerty of failing to supervise Mr. Maiello, ignoring complaints from parishioners about his conduct and ignoring ''bizarre'' behavior, like his claiming to have a series of terminal illnesses. But Mr. Davey contended that Father Haggerty was given ''no specific information'' that Mr. Maiello was committing crimes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dowd said that Mr. Maiello was given an office in a ''remote'' part of the convent that Father Haggerty ''never once'' visited. One victim ''lost her virginity in the basement of the convent of St. Raphael's,'' he said, adding that other sexual encounters occurred on the principal's desk, in the auditorium, behind the stage curtain, under the stairs, in the church basement and in the pews.</p>
        <p>Father Haggerty is scheduled to return to the witness stand on Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
