<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Former Fordham Law Dean To Lead New Ethics Panel</title>
    <meta content="17ethics" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/nyregion/17ethics.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840956"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ethics Commission (NYS)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Commission on Public Integrity (NYS)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spitzer, Eliot (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feerick, John D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Fordham University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Feerick, John D</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E2D9113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="576" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Former Fordham Law Dean To Lead New Ethics Panel</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Former Fordham Law Dean to Lead New Ethics Panel</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, April 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov Eliot Spitzer appoints John D Feerick chairman of New York State's Ethics Commission; he will also be chairman of new Commission on Public Integrity, which will combine existing ethics and lobbying commissions in Sept 2007; Feerick, former dean of Fordham University School of Law, has been chairman of special commission that recommended overhaul of process for selecting judges; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer appointed John D. Feerick on Monday to become the state's top ethics enforcer, turning to one of the elder statesmen of New York's legal community to lead an overhaul of ethics oversight.</p>
        <p>Mr. Feerick, 71, will immediately become chairman of the state's Ethics Commission, and in September, he will assume the same job at a new Commission on Public Integrity that will combine the existing ethics and lobbying commissions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>John D. Feerick has been appointed the state’s top ethics enforcer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer appointed John D. Feerick on Monday to become the state's top ethics enforcer, turning to one of the elder statesmen of New York's legal community to lead an overhaul of ethics oversight.</p>
        <p>Mr. Feerick, 71, will immediately become chairman of the state's Ethics Commission, and in September, he will assume the same job at a new Commission on Public Integrity that will combine the existing ethics and lobbying commissions.</p>
        <p>The new commission springs from ethics legislation that was one of Mr. Spitzer's earlier priorities, but its birth in negotiations behind closed doors met with skepticism from government watchdog groups, who see some problems remaining and new ones being created.</p>
        <p>The governor, however, has selected a widely respected man to lead the new commission -- a man who, as he put it, ''has held every position, chaired every commission.''</p>
        <p>''My mind immediately turned to the one individual who is pre-eminent among all new Yorkers in standing for the principles of integrity in government,'' Mr. Spitzer said, adding that he ''begged and pleaded'' with Mr. Feerick to take the post, ''not something I'm terribly good at, perhaps.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Feerick was dean of the Fordham University School of Law from 1982 to 2002, and before that worked for two decades at the law firm of Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher &amp; Flom. Since 2003, he has been the chairman of a special commission that recommended an overhaul of the process for selecting judges.</p>
        <p>Most relevant to his new role, though, is his chairmanship in the late 1980s of a commission on government integrity whose work was widely lauded but also largely ignored.</p>
        <p>''They had all these terrific recommendations on campaign finance, on ethics, they basically looked at corruption in state government and made all these recommendations that were never enacted,'' said Rachel Leon, executive director of Common Cause New York, a nonpartisan advocacy group financed by dues and contributions. ''It's a tale of what's wrong in Albany. They had a blueprint that nobody ever followed. Hopefully, this is another chance.''</p>
        <p>A number of concerns linger for good-government groups about the nascent Commission on Public Integrity. Among other things, the governor will choose the majority of the members of the new commission, giving a single official greater sway over the new commission than anyone had over previous panels.</p>
        <p>Perhaps more worrisome is that ethics issues related to the Legislature will remain under the purview of the Legislative Ethics Committee, a separate panel that discloses little of its work to the public. As the number of lawmakers either indicted or investigated seems to proliferate, legislative leaders have fought to keep ethics matters entirely in their own hands.</p>
        <p>Also remaining unresolved is the future of David Grandeau, the executive director of the Temporary State Commission on Lobbying, whose job will disappear when the new commission comes into being. Mr. Grandeau is seen as a rare enforcer in the capital, and also one who has made a number of enemies.</p>
        <p>Asked if Mr. Grandeau would have a future in the Public Integrity Commission, Mr. Feerick said during a brief news conference that his immediate focus was on taking over the existing Ethics Commission. He offered few details of his agenda.</p>
        <p>''I promise my best effort to this position,'' Mr. Feerick said. Referring to his previous work on government integrity, he said that in some respects, ''I am returning to the area where I spent three years of my life.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
