<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stomach Pain Slows One of the Favorites</title>
    <meta content="17run" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/sports/othersports/17run.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841052"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MARATHON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Boston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Boston Marathon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Boston (Mass)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Kastor, Deena</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E0D7113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="784" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stomach Pain Slows One of the Favorites</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Kastor’s Plans Are Upset by Stomach Pain</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK LITSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Litsky, Frank</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, April 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Deena Kastor had one race plan for fairly decent weather and one for the stinging wind and rain that affected the Boston Marathon on Monday. She did not plan for stomach cramps halfway through the race, which reduced Kastor, a favorite, into a fifth-place finisher.</p>
        <p>A 34-year-old Californian, Kastor was making her Boston debut a year after setting the American record, 2 hours 19 minutes 36 seconds, in London.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a race slowed by unkind weather, Deena Kastor ran the slowest of her nine career marathons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Deena Kastor had one race plan for fairly decent weather and one for the stinging wind and rain that affected the Boston Marathon on Monday. She did not plan for stomach cramps halfway through the race, which reduced Kastor, a favorite, into a fifth-place finisher.</p>
        <p>A 34-year-old Californian, Kastor was making her Boston debut a year after setting the American record, 2 hours 19 minutes 36 seconds, in London.</p>
        <p>But in a race slowed by unkind weather, she ran 2:35:09 on Monday, the slowest of her nine career marathons by more than five minutes.</p>
        <p>Lidiya Grigoryeva of Russia won the women's race in 2:29:18 and collected $100,000. Kastor, in addition to a six-figure appearance fee, earned $14,000. She also received $25,000 for winning the concurrent United States women's championship.</p>
        <p>''I had a really bad day and it is definitely a letdown, but the marathon throws things like this at you every time,'' she said. ''You just have to deal with what the cards give you every day. It was disappointing to prepare for four months and then this, but this was something out of my control. I can't be too hard on myself.''</p>
        <p>In recent days, Kastor talked of running hard from the start. But when the weather forecast turned from bad to worse, her coach, Terrence Mahon, changed the plan.</p>
        <p>''He said if the headwinds are strong, I should be very conservative and not take the brunt of the wind,'' Kastor said. ''Let someone else do the work.''</p>
        <p>In that headwind, no one in the pack of six leaders, including Grigoryeva, wanted to do it.</p>
        <p>''I was surprised running behind Deena,'' Grigoryeva said. ''She struggled downhill.''</p>
        <p>The splits for Miles 7-12 were 6:11, 6:03, 6:24, 6:23, 6:02 and 6:08 -- an incredibly slow pace for elite runners.</p>
        <p>''It felt like eight-minute miles,'' Kastor said. ''It was painfully slow.''</p>
        <p>Then came the turning point for Kastor.</p>
        <p>''I was optimistic until my stomach became upset,'' she said. ''I was suffering for a mile before I stopped. I was hoping the feeling would go away, but it didn't, so I stopped running and went to a portable bathroom. There was a TV camera on me, and I hoped it wasn't live. I must have lost two minutes. When I came out, I could see one girl in front of me, but not the lead pack.</p>
        <p>''Before I got sick, I was thinking about making a move at Mile 16 or 17, and if not then, then coming off Heartbreak Hill at 21 miles. Except for the cramps, nothing was bothering me out there, and there was never a chance I would drop out.''</p>
        <p>Kastor said that she had fully expected to win.</p>
        <p>''I knew coming in here that the competition would be great and I could conquer it,'' she said. ''That wasn't the case today. We marathoners can get pretty hard on ourselves, but I felt I had the drive to push forward and the will to win the race. So I'm definitely disappointed knowing I was good enough to come here and win this race. I'm disappointed that didn't happen.</p>
        <p>''Usually, you can learn a lesson from a marathon. I'm not taking anything away from this one. There was no learning experience. A fifth-place finish is a fifth-place finish.''</p>
        <p>Grigoryeva, like Kastor, had never run here before, and their postrace assessments reflected who won and who didn't.</p>
        <p>''I thought the course would be more difficult,'' Grigoryeva said through an interpreter.</p>
        <p>For Kastor, it was tough enough.</p>
        <p>''The course is extraordinarily difficult,'' she said. ''It's all uphill or downhill. I don't think any part is flat. But I like it. I'll be back.''</p>
        <p>OTHER WINNERS -- The push-rim wheelchair winners were from Japan: Masazumi Soejima in the men's race (1:29:16) and Wakako Tsuchida in the women's (1:53:30). Ernst Van Dyk of South Africa, the men's winner the six previous years, hit a large pothole, emerged with two flat tires and finished third in 1:37:10.  The masters' winners were 43-year-old Oleg Strijakov of Gainesville, Fla., and Russia among the men (2:28:55) and 44-year-old Heidy Lozano of Houston among the women (2:56:03).  Abebe Mekonnen, 43, of Ethiopia, the 1989 men's overall champion, finished in 2:44:12. Keizo Yamada, 79, of Japan, the 1953 winner, finished in 4:24:07.</p>
        <p>MARATHON IN SPACE -- The NASA astronaut Sunita Williams completed her version of the Boston Marathon -- more than 210 miles above Earth.</p>
        <p>''I'm done! Woo hoo!'' Williams told Mission Control in Cape Canaveral, Fla., after running 26.2 miles on a treadmill at the international space station.</p>
        <p>The 41-year-old Williams, who is known as Suni, unofficially finished in 4:23:46 as the station traveled over Russia. (AP)</p>
        <p>MARATHON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
