<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Start Has Been Tough, And the Owner Hasn't</title>
    <meta content="17chass" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/sports/baseball/17chass.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841015"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Steinbrenner, George M 3d</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Cashman, Brian</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E7D7113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="890" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Start Has Been Tough, And the Owner Hasn't</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Start Has Been Tough, and Steinbrenner Hasn’t</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here is another sign that George Steinbrenner is no longer the tempestuous owner he once was: Marty Miller and Dana Cavalea have yet to be booted out the door at Yankee Stadium and dispatched to an unemployment line in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>Miller and Cavalea are in charge of the strength and conditioning program for the highly paid Yankees players. On the job for less than a month of the regular season, the two men have watched the Yankees accumulate more injuries than some teams do in, say, half a season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Had a general manager in the first 30 years of George Steinbrenner’s reign made the moves that Brian Cashman did, he might already be gone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here is another sign that George Steinbrenner is no longer the tempestuous owner he once was: Marty Miller and Dana Cavalea have yet to be booted out the door at Yankee Stadium and dispatched to an unemployment line in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>Miller and Cavalea are in charge of the strength and conditioning program for the highly paid Yankees players. On the job for less than a month of the regular season, the two men have watched the Yankees accumulate more injuries than some teams do in, say, half a season.</p>
        <p>Miller and Cavalea remain on the job if for no other reason than Brian Cashman appointed them. He is the general manager who has been handed greater control over the Yankees' operation than any of the multitude of his predecessors in the Steinbrenner regime. Cashman wanted it that way, and he understood the perils of being in such a position of authority.</p>
        <p>The question is whether Steinbrenner can still summon enough anger to jettison Cashman if he feels his trust is misguided and misplaced. Had a general manager in the first 30 years or so of Steinbrenner's reign made the move that Cashman did, and had similar results, he might already be gone, along with the offending new strength coaches.</p>
        <p>It is possible, of course, that Steinbrenner does not know the full extent of the early-season injuries, that three-fifths of his starting pitching rotation (four-sixths if you count the first replacement) are on the disabled list. And the season is only two weeks old. Two-thirds of the outfield has also been afflicted, with Johnny Damon missing a few games with a strained calf muscle and Hideki Matsui taking an early turn on the D.L. with a strained hamstring.</p>
        <p>Now, none of these injuries -- which also include Chien-Ming Wang's bad hamstring, Mike Mussina's bad hamstring, Carl Pavano's forearm stiffness and Jeff Karstens's elbow stiffness -- may be the result of the team's new strength and conditioning program. But years ago, that never stopped the old Steinbrenner from acting like the old Steinbrenner.</p>
        <p>In 1984, for example, Dave Righetti, the Yankees' left-handed closer, cut his left index finger on the bullpen water cooler and went on the disabled list for 15 days. The day after the mishap, Jerry McNertney, the bullpen coach, was banished to the minor leagues.</p>
        <p>The Yankees have new strength and conditioning coaches because Cashman fired Jeff Mangold, who had held the job since 1998. This act has become tiresome for the 52-year-old Mangold. He had previously held the job for five seasons, from 1984 through 1988, was let go because the Yankees felt they had endured too many injuries, then was brought back. Now he's gone again.</p>
        <p>Mangold learned shortly after last season that he wouldn't be back this season, but he has not talked about the reason and declined to do so yesterday.</p>
        <p>''They just felt it was time for a change,'' Mangold said in a telephone interview from his home in Oakland, N.J.</p>
        <p>''I just wasn't rehired. I don't want to get into it. It doesn't make sense for me to. It was their decision to make, and I have to move on from there.''</p>
        <p>Cashman didn't want to talk about the change, either.</p>
        <p>''I made the decision,'' he said, ''but I don't want to speak to the reason in fairness to everyone involved, the people who are here and those who aren't.''</p>
        <p>Cashman didn't say it, but he and his aides apparently felt that the Yankees had encountered a lot of injuries in recent seasons and they didn't feel that Mangold had been as focused on his job as much as he should have been.</p>
        <p>As for Miller, a 34-year-old native of Niagara Falls, N.Y., he was not allowed to address his new job yesterday because, the Yankees said, Cashman doesn't permit him to speak to reporters.</p>
        <p>Miller does have a title, director of performance enhancement, that is appropriate for his new-wave type of conditioning, but not all of the players have adapted to his approach.</p>
        <p>Some players, in fact, have their own trainers and follow the methods those trainers employ. Considering the salaries that players are paid these days, the teams would seem to have reason to expect that their conditioning regimen would be adhered to by the players. But that's a matter for the clubs and the union to debate.</p>
        <p>Mangold wouldn't talk about Miller and his methods. When the conversation turned to the recent rash of injuries, Mangold said, ''I don't want to express my thoughts publicly on what has happened.''</p>
        <p>Given the spate of injuries, especially to the four starting pitchers, Mangold could have said a lot but didn't. But here's what he could have noted: The major leagues, according to records compiled by the commissioner's office, have 20 starting pitchers on the disabled list.</p>
        <p>The Yankees represent 20 percent of that number. No other team has more than two starting pitchers disabled.</p>
        <p>But Mangold didn't say any of that. Those are my words and my research. Cashman said yesterday that injuries were up this year and that on opening day, the disabled list had a population 30 percent greater than a year ago and 30 percent greater than the average number over the past four years.</p>
        <p>But only the Yankees have four starting pitchers on the disabled list.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
