<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sabres Capitalize on Power Play to Go Up in Series</title>
    <meta content="17islanders" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/sports/hockey/17islanders.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841050"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Buffalo Sabres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Buffalo Sabres</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Islanders</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Briere, Daniel</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E1D7113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="775" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sabres Capitalize on Power Play to Go Up in Series</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sabres Capitalize on Power Play to Go Up in Series</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONDALE, N.Y., April 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Buffalo Sabres, flashy and frenetic, are hard enough to stop with five skaters and a good goaltender. An opponent that sends two players to the penalty box -- at the same time, no less -- can expect to pay a steep price.</p>
        <p>With Islanders defensemen Tom Poti and Marc-André Bergeron serving penalties midway through the second period, Buffalo center Daniel Brière scored what proved to be the winning goal Monday night in the Sabres' 3-2 victory against the Islanders at Nassau Coliseum.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With two Islanders defensemen serving penalties midway through the second period, Buffalo center Daniel Brière scored the winning goal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Buffalo Sabres, flashy and frenetic, are hard enough to stop with five skaters and a good goaltender. An opponent that sends two players to the penalty box -- at the same time, no less -- can expect to pay a steep price.</p>
        <p>With Islanders defensemen Tom Poti and Marc-André Bergeron serving penalties midway through the second period, Buffalo center Daniel Brière scored what proved to be the winning goal Monday night in the Sabres' 3-2 victory against the Islanders at Nassau Coliseum.</p>
        <p>Buffalo leads the best-of-seven Eastern Conference first-round playoff series, 2-1.</p>
        <p>''They're making it tough for us,'' Islanders right wing Trent Hunter said. ''They're causing a lot of pressure.''</p>
        <p>Islanders left wing Ryan Smyth, who seemed to be in front of Buffalo goaltender Ryan Miller all game, scored with eight seconds remaining in the second period to cut the Islanders' deficit to one. But they could not tie the score.</p>
        <p>Game 4 will be played here Wednesday, with Game 5 scheduled for Friday in Buffalo.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes you get momentum, and sometimes it's taken away,'' Islanders Coach Ted Nolan said of the way Buffalo responded in the third period.</p>
        <p>After Islanders center Randy Robitaille was called for tripping with 1 minute 34 seconds remaining, angry fans in the capacity crowd of 16,234 hurled plastic beer bottles and white playoff hand towels onto the ice. Play had to be stopped for a few minutes.</p>
        <p>''They pay to watch good hockey and not to have the officials take over,'' Smyth said.</p>
        <p>If the Islanders are to have a chance in this series, which was considered a mismatch, they need to put more pressure on the Sabres, who outshot them by 35-22. In the third period, the Islanders trailed by only a goal but were outshot, 17-2.</p>
        <p>''Down by a goal in the playoffs, that's unacceptable,'' Robitaille said. ''We have to come out with a little more desperation the next time.''</p>
        <p>The Islanders were 0 for 4 on power plays. Two of them came during a scoreless first period, when the Islanders hit Miller in the head twice with long-range slap shots. They are 1 for 11 with a man advantage in the series.</p>
        <p>The Islanders foiled the Sabres in the first period with persistent forechecking, keeping the game scoreless. But Buffalo, which led the N.H.L. in goals this season, scored twice in 3 minutes 21 seconds during the second period to hush the boisterous crowd in the Islanders' first home playoff game since 2004.</p>
        <p>Buffalo forward Adam Mair started a rush by knocking Hunter off the puck in the Sabres' zone. Defenseman Henrik Tallinder then carried the puck up the ice and dropped a pass to center Chris Drury near the boards.</p>
        <p>Drury spotted Mair cruising up the right wing and threaded a cross-ice pass to him. Mair reached the puck in time to knock it past Islanders goaltender Rick DiPietro at 5:17 into the second period.</p>
        <p>Thomas Vanek soon gave the Sabres a 2-0 lead. He tried to stuff the puck between DiPietro's right skate and the goal post. Although Vanek lifted his arms in celebration, play continued as if DiPietro had kept the puck from crossing the goal line.</p>
        <p>''I was trying to do whatever I could to keep it out,'' DiPietro said.</p>
        <p>Play was then stopped for a lengthy video review. Vanek was awarded his first goal of the playoffs at 8:38, and the crowd went silent.</p>
        <p>Nolan said that Vanek's shot did not cross the goal line in any replays he saw.</p>
        <p>''Unless the National Hockey League has a different angle that we can't see,'' Nolan said.</p>
        <p>Only 74 seconds later, Hunter cut the deficit to one, taking a pass from Smyth and muscling a shot that was hard enough to trickle past Miller.</p>
        <p>But the Islanders fell behind by two goals again after Poti and Bergeron each received penalties at 11:59. Moments after Bergeron slashed Maxim Afinogenov, Poti whacked Afinogenov with a high stick and received a double minor, putting him in the penalty box for four minutes.</p>
        <p>''Maybe two minutes,'' Nolan said. ''Four, I'm not too sure.''</p>
        <p>Buffalo needed only 57 seconds to regain its two-goal lead. As the Sabres passed the puck around the perimeter, Brière found a spot in front of DiPietro and took three swipes at a bouncing puck until it sailed into the net at 12:56.</p>
        <p>The Islanders say that they are capable of a better effort than Monday's. They played hard and disciplined Saturday in a 3-2 victory in Game 2. Now they have to do it again.</p>
        <p>''We already showed in Game 2 that we can compete,'' Smyth said. ''It's a long series.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
