<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amgen Seeks To Reverse Its Bad News</title>
    <meta content="17place" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/business/17place.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841000"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET PLACE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Anemia</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aranesp (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Epogen (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heart</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labeling and Labels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Amgen Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Food and Drug Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sharer, Kevin W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pollack, Andrew</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Market Place (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Anemia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Heart Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anemia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labeling and Labels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anatomy and Physiology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Amgen Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E0D8113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1633" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amgen Seeks To Reverse Its Bad News</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Amgen Seeks to Reverse Its Bad News</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW POLLACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pollack, Andrew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Market Place column; Amgen faces difficulties amid onslaught of bad news in recent months; Food and Drug Administration puts new warnings on anemia drugs Aranesp and Epogen, citing studies that they may cause heart problems or increase chance of death in cancer patients; revenues are expected to increase only 4 percent annually through 2010, about 20 percent lower than sales growth from 2003 to 2006; chief executive Kevin W Sharer says company can overcome problems; photo; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Until recently, Amgen was still considered one of the biggest success stories of the fast-growing biotechnology industry. Now some analysts are comparing it to a lumbering, stumbling pharmaceutical giant that leans too heavily on an aging product portfolio.</p>
        <p>A series of setbacks, some unexpected and some perhaps self-inflicted, pose the greatest challenge in the company's previously charmed 27-year history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A series of setbacks at the pharmaceutical giant pose the greatest challenge to its previously charmed 27-year history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Until recently, Amgen was still considered one of the biggest success stories of the fast-growing biotechnology industry. Now some analysts are comparing it to a lumbering, stumbling pharmaceutical giant that leans too heavily on an aging product portfolio.</p>
        <p>A series of setbacks, some unexpected and some perhaps self-inflicted, pose the greatest challenge in the company's previously charmed 27-year history.</p>
        <p>And some crucial events in coming weeks could make clearer whether Amgen, based in Thousand Oaks, Calif., has hit some ''choppy water'' -- as its chief executive contends -- or whether, as some analysts say, its best days may be behind it.</p>
        <p>''The barrage of bad news that's come out on Amgen in the past 60 days is absolutely unprecedented in the biotech sector,'' said Mark Schoenebaum, a biotechnology stock analyst at Bear Stearns. Amgen's shares are down about 20 percent since late January, knocking nearly $20 billion off the company's market value.</p>
        <p>But the stock has edged up a bit since its recent low of $55.13 on March 29, as some investors have been tempted by management's view that it is too soon for a fire sale. Yesterday, the shares rose 62 cents, to $59.65, as details of a study were released suggesting that the risks of the company's biggest drug were not as clear cut as recently thought.</p>
        <p>''We are not in a crisis, that's for sure,'' Kevin W. Sharer, Amgen's chairman and chief executive, said in an interview. In a crisis, ''people don't know what to do,'' he said. ''People's hair is on fire. Confidence is challenged. We're not there.''</p>
        <p>At best, though, the company faces plenty of challenges. Several recent studies suggest that its blockbuster anemia drugs, Aranesp and Epogen, might be harming patients, particularly if overused. Those products accounted for $6.6 billion of Amgen's $14.3 billion in revenue last year.</p>
        <p>The Food and Drug Administration put new warnings on the drugs last month, citing studies suggesting that Aranesp and Epogen might cause heart problems or hasten the deaths of cancer patients.</p>
        <p>Last Wednesday, the company said it would briefly delay the reporting of its first-quarter results, originally scheduled for this week, to allow it to include data from a clinical trial of Aranesp. The financial results are now expected next Monday.</p>
        <p>The company also disclosed last week that its chief financial officer, Richard D. Nanula, was resigning to ''pursue other opportunities,'' but would stay on for three months to aid the transition to his successor, Robert Bradway.</p>
        <p>Adding to its woes, Amgen recently reported that patients in a clinical trial combining its new colon cancer drug, Vectibix, with other treatments were more likely to die than patients who got only the other treatments. As a result, Vectibix is likely to remain only a niche drug for now.</p>
        <p>Sizing up Amgen's situation in a report titled ''Looking More Like Large Pharma,'' a Citigroup analyst, Yaron Werber, predicted that Amgen's revenues would grow only 4 percent a year through 2010. That would be well below its 20 percent annual sales growth from 2003 to 2006.</p>
        <p>Geoffrey C. Porges of Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company has asked whether Amgen should start paying a dividend to attract shareholders, an inducement common among big drug companies.</p>
        <p>And some are even starting to raise questions quietly about Amgen's long-vaunted management. Michael Aberman, an analyst at Credit Suisse, said Mr. Sharer's team may have tried to expand the use of its drugs too much, resulting in unsuccessful clinical trials and safety problems that could now endanger sales.</p>
        <p>Amgen executives say that their strategies have been driven by science and sound medical considerations. And so far, Mr. Sharer said, Amgen has not changed its financial guidance for the year, which calls for 8 percent to 12 percent revenue growth, along with 10 percent to 15 percent growth in earnings per share.</p>
        <p>The company has mainly reacted to the mounting uncertainty about future sales by taking cost-control steps, imposing a hiring slowdown and postponing the opening of a new factory in Ireland. If sales drop further, Amgen says, more cuts can be made.</p>
        <p>''We certainly have enormous expense flexibility here,'' Mr. Sharer said. ''And we can deal with any conceivable revenue scenario I can imagine. It'll either be more or less painful to deal with, but we can certainly deal with it.''</p>
        <p>Just how painful should become clearer in the next few weeks. Next Monday, the company is expected to release the results of a crucial study testing Aranesp's effect on the longevity of patients with small-cell lung cancer. Aranesp is approved to treat the anemia caused by cancer chemotherapy.</p>
        <p>If the results from that study indicate that patients taking Aranesp are more likely to die sooner than they might otherwise, ''the tide will turn'' against the drugs, said Dr. John A. Glaspy, a professor of medicine at the University of California, Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>''We will not be able to justify treating lots of patients'' with Aranesp, said Dr. Glaspy, who has received consulting and research fees from Amgen.</p>
        <p>An F.D.A. advisory committee plans to meet on May 10 to discuss the safety of the anemia drugs. And later that month another big drug maker, Roche, might win F.D.A. approval for an anemia drug that would compete with Amgen's products.</p>
        <p>Epogen and Aranesp are both genetically engineered versions of erythropoietin, or EPO, a protein made in the kidneys to stimulate production of oxygen-carrying red blood cells. Johnson &amp; Johnson sells a version of Epogen, marketed as Procrit, under a license from Amgen. The drugs have been shown to reduce the need for blood transfusions in patients with kidney disease and in cancer patients getting chemotherapy.</p>
        <p>But in November, a study found that patients with kidney failure who were treated aggressively with EPO drugs had more deaths and heart problems than patients who took only enough of the drugs to raise their levels of red blood cells by modest amounts.</p>
        <p>Then a number of studies came out suggesting that use of Aranesp by cancer patients could worsen their disease or hasten their deaths. Amgen did not immediately disclose the results of one of the trials, done by Danish researchers, prompting an inquiry by the Securities and Exchange Commission.</p>
        <p>Amgen executives, and some outside scientists, say it is still far from clear if the drugs are truly dangerous.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, new details were released about a clinical trial showing that Aranesp had increased the risk of death in cancer patients with anemia who were not getting chemotherapy. Some 48.5 percent of the patients who received Aranesp, in an off-label use of the drug, had died compared with 46 percent of those getting a placebo.</p>
        <p>While Amgen had announced the negative outcome in January, the new details, presented at the American Association for Cancer Research meeting in Los Angeles, suggested that part of the explanation was that the patients who received Aranesp had been more at risk of death to begin with.</p>
        <p>''I don't think anyone regards this trial as having proven a negative impact on cancer,'' Dr. Glaspy, who presented the results, said in an interview.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, given the uncertainties, doctors and insurers are already cutting back use of Aranesp and Epogen, particularly in cancer patients who are not getting chemotherapy. Analysts generally estimate the decrease in use will be 10 percent to 30 percent.</p>
        <p>This month the big insurer UnitedHealthcare began denying reimbursement for EPO drugs if a patient's red cell volume is above a certain level. Previously, United had never even asked doctors to document patients' red cell levels.</p>
        <p>Whatever happens with sales of its anemia drugs, if Amgen is to remain a fast-growing company it must develop new products. But it has yet to show a particular skill in that area, even though it does have many test drugs in its pipeline.</p>
        <p>To this day, Amgen still largely lives off Epogen, first approved in 1989, and Neupogen, approved in 1991 to prevent infection in patients receiving chemotherapy.</p>
        <p>Its biggest new products since then, Aranesp and Neulasta, were modifications of the original two. And its other big product, the rheumatoid arthritis drug Enbrel, was not homegrown but came as part of the company's $10 billion acquisition of Immunex in 2002.</p>
        <p>After being promoted to chief executive in 2000, Mr. Sharer recruited Roger M. Perlmutter from Merck to run research and development. The research effort has roughly tripled since 2002, to more than 6,000 people and $3.4 billion in spending, and the number of drug candidates under development has similarly soared.</p>
        <p>Denosumab, a drug for osteoporosis and bone cancer, could be a blockbuster, and some investors say that it is now more important than ever to Amgen's future. But it will be two or three years before it is known whether the drug is safe and effective enough to win approval.</p>
        <p>Until then, Amgen's fate might rest on the findings of that Aranesp study due out next Monday. Unlike many of the previous studies, that one was devised specifically to study survival.</p>
        <p>Patients in the trial were treated to raise their red cells to levels somewhat higher than recommended in the drug's label, which could increase the chances of safety problems.</p>
        <p>One factor in Amgen's favor is that a previous Aranesp trial, which raised red cells to even higher levels, showed a survival benefit in the subset of patients with small-cell lung cancer -- the only type of patients in the current trial.</p>
        <p>If the new study shows that Aranesp shortens lives, the company might still be able to argue that the drug is safe if used in the lower amounts recommended on the label. But it is unclear how persuasive that case would now be.</p>
        <p>''Lots of people will argue that,'' Dr. Glaspy said. ''But they will argue as we fold up the chairs and turn off the lights.''</p>
        <p>MARKET PLACE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
