<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nets Could Draw Raptors In Homecoming for Carter</title>
    <meta content="17nets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841048"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Toronto Raptors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E2D7113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="652" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nets Could Draw Raptors In Homecoming for Carter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eligon, John</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The sudden change in Vince Carter's demeanor -- from relaxed to intense -- said it all.</p>
        <p>About 30 minutes after recording the fourth triple-double of his career last night, Carter tightened his jaw and put on a pointed glare when told that Toronto's Chris Bosh had said the Raptors wanted to face Carter and the Nets in the playoffs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The sudden change in Vince Carter's demeanor -- from relaxed to intense -- said it all.</p>
        <p>About 30 minutes after recording the fourth triple-double of his career last night, Carter tightened his jaw and put on a pointed glare when told that Toronto's Chris Bosh had said the Raptors wanted to face Carter and the Nets in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>''One more win and they'll get their wish,'' said Carter, who strutted away, put on his baseball cap and shook his head.</p>
        <p>Carter scored 29 points to go with 12 rebounds and 10 assists in the Nets' 104-95 victory against the Knicks at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>The Nets (40-41) need that victory and for the Washington Wizards to lose at least one of their final two games in order to take over the sixth seed and meet the Raptors in the first round of the playoffs. Carter, of course, spent just over six seasons in Toronto and did not leave on the best of terms.</p>
        <p>His recent play has epitomized the Nets' late-season rejuvenation. Carter has had two triple-doubles in just over a week and could make the Nets a dangerous first-round opponent.</p>
        <p>''That's the goal, to come in playing tough basketball,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Nets, who will complete the regular season against the Chicago Bulls tomorrow night, are guaranteed at least the seventh seed. The Wizards (40-40) play the Orlando Magic tonight and finish their season against the Indiana Pacers tomorrow night.</p>
        <p>Carter, who is averaging 25.2 points, 5.9 rebounds and 4.7 assists, has scored at least 20 points in 13 of the Nets' past 15 games. He has had at least 35 points on three occasions and has found his open teammates when the defense collapses on him.</p>
        <p>''This is the time of the year you want to be playing your best basketball,'' Nets point guard Jason Kidd said.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't say it's his best, but I think it's right up there. He has a lot more to give, that I feel he can give to the team.''</p>
        <p>As a unit, the Nets do not want to have a false sense of security.</p>
        <p>Their longest winning streak of the season has been four games, and they have played their worst just when it seemed they were on the verge of getting it right.</p>
        <p>''It's important for us that we understand that we have to go in playing good,'' forward Cliff Robinson said during a recent interview. ''We've shown this year that we haven't been able to relax and coast to wins. It hasn't been that kind of season for us.''</p>
        <p>The Nets have been a bit more consistent over the past few weeks. Since March 12, they have not had a losing streak longer than two games. They have won 10 of their past 16 games, although they have lost to four of the East's top five teams during that span.</p>
        <p>''We're playing to win these games,'' Coach Lawrence Frank said before last night's game.</p>
        <p>''We're going to do everything we can to try to get the best possible seed we can.''</p>
        <p>CHANGES AT FORWARD -- Forward Cliff Robinson, in his 18th N.B.A. season and going to the playoffs for the 17th time, figures to lose some playing time to the rookie Josh Boone.</p>
        <p>The rotation will probably shorten in the postseason, and Coach Lawrence Frank highlighted the Robinson-Boone spot as one of the difficult decisions he will have to make. He has already shortened Robinson's minutes in favor of Boone.</p>
        <p>''I want him to do well when he's in there and I'm sure he wants me to do well,'' said Robinson, who like Boone played collegiately at Connecticut. ''I don't think it's a situation where we're in competition with one another.''</p>
        <p>Boone, who also said he and Robinson cheered for each other, has used Robinson as a motivator.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, we're both going to push each other,'' Boone said.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
