<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Profit Off 11% At Citigroup On Expenses Of Overhaul</title>
    <meta content="17citi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/business/17citi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841034"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Citigroup Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dash, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Subprime Lending</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Citigroup Incorporated</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Prince, Charles O III</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E4D7113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="597" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Profit Off 11% At Citigroup On Expenses Of Overhaul</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Profit Off 11% at Citigroup on Expenses of Overhaul</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC DASH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dash, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Citigroup says its first-quarter earnings fell 11 percent because of big charge for its recently announced overhaul; over all, bank earned $5.01 billion from $5.64 billion year earlier; profit rose 4.3 percent, to $5.88 billion; revenue rose 15 percent, to $25.5 billion (M)d</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Citigroup said yesterday that its first-quarter earnings fell 11 percent because of a big charge for its recently announced overhaul. But the results showed progress in its expense management and strength in investment banking, and its shares rose 2.6 percent.</p>
        <p>Signs of improvement come at a critical time for Citigroup's chairman and chief executive, Charles O. Prince III. Under pressure from investors, Mr. Prince has vowed to reverse the company's disappointing stock performance and rein in high operating expenses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite the decline, Citigroup showed progress in its expense management and strength in investment banking.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Citigroup said yesterday that its first-quarter earnings fell 11 percent because of a big charge for its recently announced overhaul. But the results showed progress in its expense management and strength in investment banking, and its shares rose 2.6 percent.</p>
        <p>Signs of improvement come at a critical time for Citigroup's chairman and chief executive, Charles O. Prince III. Under pressure from investors, Mr. Prince has vowed to reverse the company's disappointing stock performance and rein in high operating expenses.</p>
        <p>While championing a strategy of internal growth of existing business and international growth through acquisitions and expansion of existing business, Mr. Prince recently made some pivotal changes.</p>
        <p>Over the last three months, he has shaken up his management team, bringing in a new finance chief and head of alternative investments. Last week, he announced the biggest overhaul in Citigroup's nine-year history, streamlining its management ranks and eliminating 17,000 jobs.</p>
        <p>And with the $13.4 billion takeover offer for Nikko Cordial of Japan last month along with a string of smaller deals overseas, Mr. Prince has been putting the company's acquisition engine into gear.</p>
        <p>Now, investors are waiting to see if those changes will pay off in a difficult business environment. Yesterday's results showed signs of some deterioration in the quality of credit, as loss rates in credit cards inched upward, delinquencies in second mortgages increased and credit losses grew in some overseas markets, like Japan.</p>
        <p>Despite its substantial subprime lending business, Citigroup has so far escaped the impact of the subprime mortgage meltdown in the United States.</p>
        <p>Over all, the bank earned $5.01 billion or $1.01 a share, from $5.64 billion, or $1.12 a share, a year earlier. Excluding a $871 million aftertax restructuring charge, Citigroup's profits rose 4.3 percent, to $5.88 billion.</p>
        <p>Revenue rose 15 percent, to $25.5 billion, on strong underwriting and trading results, eclipsing growth in operating expenses for the first time since the third quarter of 2005. But revenue growth in the consumer division remains weak.</p>
        <p>Mr. Prince said he felt ''very good'' about the results, especially since they did not reflect the projected savings from the new cost-cutting program. But he declined to predict if it would last over the next year.</p>
        <p>''It has been quite a challenge in some of our businesses, and it feels very good to me to see that progress,'' Mr. Prince said in a conference call with analysts and investors. ''The plan is working.''</p>
        <p>Citigroup's corporate and investment bank had a strong quarter, as profits rose 36 percent, to $2.6 billion. Trading revenue from the fixed-income and equities groups grew more than 20 percent, showing across-the-board strength. Underwriting and advisory fees were also exceptionally strong. Over all, the investment bank's revenue reached $8.9 billion, up 23 percent.</p>
        <p>The Smith Barney operation posted profit of $324 million, driven by an increase in fee-based revenue and higher customer trading levels. Citigroup's private bank profits of $124 million were up 4 percent.</p>
        <p>The performance of Citigroup's global consumer businesses was more disappointing, dragged down by weaker credit quality and a tough interest rate environment. Profit in its United States consumer division fell 12 percent, to 1.77 billion, in the first quarter with every major business posting declines.</p>
        <p>The division's credit card results were especially weak. Even though revenue increased 6 percent, the bulk of that came from a $161 million pretax gain on the sale of MasterCard shares.</p>
        <p>Profit in the international consumer operation fell 16 percent, reflecting higher credit costs in many countries and a major revenue decline after cutting back the consumer business in Japan last year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
