<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets Keep a Sunny Attitude, Thinking About Miami</title>
    <meta content="17mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/sports/baseball/17mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841016"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Miami</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Miami (Fla)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7D7113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="816" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets Keep a Sunny Attitude, Thinking About Miami</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mets Keep a Sunny Attitude, Thinking About Miami</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shpigel, Ben</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, April 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The end is near, Paul Lo Duca was saying Monday. For the record, he did not mean the end of civilization, although the heavy rain that wiped out the Mets' last two games might have led some to believe that.</p>
        <p>''Come Wednesday, we'll be in Miami,'' Lo Duca said. ''If it rains there, at least it won't last long.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Heavy rain has wiped out the Mets’ last two games, and the team is looking forward to traveling to Florida on Wednesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The end is near, Paul Lo Duca was saying Monday. For the record, he did not mean the end of civilization, although the heavy rain that wiped out the Mets' last two games might have led some to believe that.</p>
        <p>''Come Wednesday, we'll be in Miami,'' Lo Duca said. ''If it rains there, at least it won't last long.''</p>
        <p>With the forecast calling for stray showers and temperatures in the 40s here Tuesday night, the Mets should expect to play one more day in this frigid nonsense before salvation comes Wednesday. According to the Penn State Department of Meteorology, the forecast in Miami calls for temperatures in the mid- to upper 70s, with a nice tropical breeze of four to seven miles an hour.</p>
        <p>''In spring training, you can't wait to get out of Florida,'' David Wright said. ''Now I can't wait to get back.''</p>
        <p>This is baseball in April, when the only teams truly immune from blizzards, hailstorms, downpours and the occasional antelope falling from the sky are those who play in domes.</p>
        <p>So far, the Mets have played in cities that do not have domed stadiums. The average game-time temperature through their first 11 games, in St. Louis, in Atlanta and at Shea Stadium, has been about 49 degrees. Take away the 72- and 58-degree readings in the first two games in St. Louis and that figure drops to 45.8 degrees.</p>
        <p>On Saturday afternoon, when the Mets played the Washington Nationals, they received proof that the thermometer at Shea Stadium could surpass 50 degrees; it hit 55.</p>
        <p>''It felt like 95 compared to what it was like the night before,'' Wright said, referring to Friday's game, when winds of 26 m.p.h. combined with temperatures of 45 and below to make it the coldest night of the season, according to several players.</p>
        <p>The inclement weather, Wright said, has made it difficult to develop any sort of continuity.</p>
        <p>The night before a game, hitters begin thinking about the pitcher they will face the next day and pitchers continue preparing for their start.</p>
        <p>''All these games off now are going to come back and bite you later on,'' Lo Duca said. ''We're all healthy and ready to go now.''</p>
        <p>Like many of his teammates, Wright chose to come here Sunday afternoon on one of the team buses. He turned on the television in his hotel room late Sunday afternoon and saw green all over the radar map, signifying rain.</p>
        <p>He said it was challenging to maintain his focus while realizing that there was a good chance that Monday night's game with the Phillies would be rained out anyway.</p>
        <p>''You get here and it's such a letdown,'' Wright said.</p>
        <p>So by 2:30 p.m. Monday, by which time the game had been postponed, Wright was among a few players milling around, figuring out how to adjust their routines. Wright, like most of the position players who came, worked out or took batting practice in the underground cages.</p>
        <p>A few relievers, including Scott Schoeneweis, went outside briefly to throw. He marched into the clubhouse afterward and said: ''I can't feel my face. I can't feel my face.''</p>
        <p>The starting pitchers waited until the early afternoon, when the rotation was completely revamped. It had already been shuffled after Sunday's rainout.</p>
        <p>Tom Glavine will pitch on schedule Tuesday against Freddy García, but John Maine's start was delayed another day, until Wednesday in Miami. Orlando Hernández, who was scheduled to pitch Saturday, was moved to start Thursday.</p>
        <p>The Mets then return home to face Atlanta, with Mike Pelfrey scheduled to start Friday and Oliver Pérez on Saturday at Shea.</p>
        <p>''We took a look at what's best for all five guys,'' Rick Peterson, the pitching coach, said. ''What's best for all five guys was to do this simply because of the weather.''</p>
        <p>The extra time off benefits Pérez most. It allows him to throw four bullpen sessions between starts in an effort to fix some of the mechanical problems he had in his last start. He walked seven batters in two and two-thirds innings Wednesday against the Phillies.</p>
        <p>''You can do some things that you couldn't have done before because it would be too close before the next game,'' Peterson said.</p>
        <p>Pérez has something else to look forward to. The long-range forecast for New York this weekend calls for blue skies, and temperatures could reach 60.</p>
        <p>''If that's the case, I can't wait,'' Wright said. ''It's about time.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The Mets' game against the Washington Nationals that was postponed Sunday has been rescheduled for July 28, as part of a day-night doubleheader. The first game will begin at 12:10 p.m., with the second at 7:10 p.m.  Monday night's game has been rescheduled for June 29, also as part of a day-night doubleheader. The first game will begin at 1:05 p.m. The second is scheduled to start at 7:05.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
