<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In an Assault Trial, Off the Jury, but Not Off the Hook</title>
    <meta content="17juror" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/nyregion/17juror.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841033"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jury System</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Commission on Judicial Conduct (NYS)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Business Week (Magazine)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mclaughlin, Edward J (Justice)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nussbaum, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hartocollis, Anemona</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Buckle, Dwayne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jury System</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Business Week</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Nussbaum, Bruce</person>
        <person class="online_producer">McLaughlin, Edward J</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E4D7113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="706" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In an Assault Trial, Off the Jury, but Not Off the Hook</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In an Assault Trial, Off the Jury, but Not Off the Hook</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANEMONA HARTOCOLLIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hartocollis, Anemona</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Justice Edward J McLaughlin dismisses Bruce Nussbaum from sitting on jury in trial of four lesbians accused of gang assault but orders him to sit in central jury room of courthouse in Manhattan until end of trial; says he believes Nussbaum, who questioned whether jurors should take precautions against reprisals by gang, was trying to avoid jury duty; Nussbaum, assitant managing editor at Business Week, appeals his confinement, and Appellate Division orders his release after three and a half days, as jury begins deliberating; he also files complaint against McLaughlin with State Commission on Judicial Conduct; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just after Bruce Nussbaum, an assistant managing editor at Business Week, was sworn into a Manhattan jury last week in the trial of four lesbians on charges of gang assault, he asked what some might consider astute questions.</p>
        <p>Just what kind of gang was this, Mr. Nussbaum wanted to know, and should he take precautions to protect his wife, like sending her away to stay with friends?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A juror dismissed from a trial of four lesbians accused of gang assault has taken his own fight to court.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just after Bruce Nussbaum, an assistant managing editor at Business Week, was sworn into a Manhattan jury last week in the trial of four lesbians on charges of gang assault, he asked what some might consider astute questions.</p>
        <p>Just what kind of gang was this, Mr. Nussbaum wanted to know, and should he take precautions to protect his wife, like sending her away to stay with friends?</p>
        <p>The questions, alas, did not endear him to Justice Edward J. McLaughlin of State Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>''So do you honestly feel you're in a position to fairly evaluate this case in view of your mindset that your wife might be in danger from an organized group of violent lesbians?'' Justice McLaughlin asked.</p>
        <p>To which Mr. Nussbaum protested, ''That's not what I'm talking about, Judge.</p>
        <p>''When you use, when one uses, the term 'gay,' it generates a number of connotations,'' Mr. Nussbaum said, according to the official transcript, though yesterday he said he actually used the word ''gang,'' not gay, and that the transcript was incorrect.</p>
        <p>''One of them that crossed my mind was, you know, a nationally organized gang, very powerful, that could reach out and try to influence members of the jury.''</p>
        <p>The judge, who indicated in court papers that he believed Mr. Nussbaum was trying to evade jury duty, said: ''You 'did a bad thing,' as the saying goes. You're off the jury.''</p>
        <p>But the judge not only excused Mr. Nussbaum from the jury, he also found him ''grossly unqualified'' for failing to make his fears known earlier, and ordered him to sit in the central jury room of the courthouse from 9:45 a.m. to 4:45 p.m. for the rest of the trial.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nussbaum, believing the judge was out of line, hired a lawyer, Michael F. Bachner, to appeal his confinement to the Appellate Division.</p>
        <p>''Petitioner, a man ready, willing and able to sit on a jury, has been embarrassed and de facto confined by the court for his honesty,'' Mr. Bachner wrote in his brief.</p>
        <p>The case of Nussbaum v. McLaughlin began innocently enough, the official transcript of the jury selection shows.</p>
        <p>As jury selection began, Justice McLaughlin lectured prospective jurors on the seriousness of carrying out their civic duty. ''The best way to look at this process, folks, is it's 1941 and I am the draft board,'' he said. He went on to urge jurors to think of reservists being called to duty, who could look forward to ''being blown up, shot up.''</p>
        <p>In contrast, he said, ''You folks, of course, get to go home, take a shower in the morning, sleep in your own bed, etc., and you'd be startled at the garbage excuses that people like me hear from prospective jurors.''</p>
        <p>The four women are accused of gang assault, and one is accused of attempted murder, in the stabbing and beating of an independent film director in Greenwich Village last August. They have said they are lesbians who were defending themselves against a homophobic attack. The film director testified that they attacked him after he made an innocently flirtatious remark.</p>
        <p>When prospective jurors were questioned about their backgrounds and potential biases, Mr. Nussbaum said that he had belonged to a gang when he was growing up on the Lower East Side in the early 1960s.</p>
        <p>''So did I,'' Justice McLaughlin chimed in, unimpressed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nussbaum, 60, said in an interview yesterday that he belonged to ''a local street gang'' known as Blubber's Gang, after the leader, nicknamed Blubber, when he was growing up on Eighth Street, between Avenues C and D. ''We only sort of got together defensively because other gangs were coming into our neighborhood,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Appellate Division ordered an end yesterday to Mr. Nussbaum's confinement after three and a half days, as the jury began deliberating. Mr. Nussbaum's lawyer said a complaint against the judge was also filed with the New York State Commission on Judicial Conduct.</p>
        <p>For his part, Justice McLaughlin was unrepentant. He said in a telephone interview yesterday that he had ordered Mr. Nussbaum to show up every day because ''you can't be allowed just to play your trump card and go back to work, take your vacation, go home or whatever.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
