<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Leans On Democrats With Talk of Troops Suffering</title>
    <meta content="17prexy" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/washington/17prexy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841014"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WHITE HOUSE MEMO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E7D7113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="943" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Leans On Democrats With Talk of Troops Suffering</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bush Leans on Democrats With Talk of Troops Suffering</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERYL GAY STOLBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>White House Memo: Pres Bush's appearance in East Room of White House with families of soldiers in Iraq--including some who have died--is part of calculated gamble that he can weaken resolve of Democrats in Congress with frequent and specific warnings that delays in passing war spending bill will hurt American troops and their families; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his confrontation with Congress over war spending, President Bush is calculating that he can weaken the resolve of Democrats with frequent and specific warnings that delays in passing the bill will hurt American troops and their families.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Bush makes his case for a war spending bill with no strings attached, White House aides say that talking about the troops is more compelling than delivering up Mr. Bush's other frequent message, that withdrawal from Iraq would be disastrous for the United States. That is why the president appeared in the East Room of the White House on Monday surrounded by families of soldiers -- including some who have died -- to hammer home his message that further delays may mean unpleasant Pentagon cutbacks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush is calculating that he can weaken the resolve of Democrats with warnings that delays in passing the war spending bill will hurt U.S. troops.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his confrontation with Congress over war spending, President Bush is calculating that he can weaken the resolve of Democrats with frequent and specific warnings that delays in passing the bill will hurt American troops and their families.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Bush makes his case for a war spending bill with no strings attached, White House aides say that talking about the troops is more compelling than delivering up Mr. Bush's other frequent message, that withdrawal from Iraq would be disastrous for the United States. That is why the president appeared in the East Room of the White House on Monday surrounded by families of soldiers -- including some who have died -- to hammer home his message that further delays may mean unpleasant Pentagon cutbacks.</p>
        <p>''The clock is ticking for our troops,'' Mr. Bush said, over the gurgling of babies squirming in their mothers' arms. He went on, ''Congress's failure to fund our troops will mean that the readiness of our forces will suffer.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush and Democrats are at loggerheads over whether the war spending bill should include timetables for a troop withdrawal. The president says he will veto any measure that ties his hands in Iraq; Democrats, who must reconcile the House and Senate versions of the spending bill before sending it to Mr. Bush's desk, insist that the final version will include timetables -- regardless of the veto threat.</p>
        <p>With a showdown looming, Mr. Bush has been using the only real ammunition he has: his presidential platform. In a speech to an American Legion Post last Tuesday, he warned that without the new funds, the Army might be forced to delay the formation of new combat brigade teams, a move that he said could require the Pentagon to extend some soldiers' tours in Iraq and Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>But the next day, the Pentagon announced that it already had plans to extend troops tours in a move unrelated to the war financing issue.</p>
        <p>Then, in a radio address on Saturday, Mr. Bush said the Pentagon would soon ask Congress for permission to shift money between accounts to cover the cost of the war.</p>
        <p>''These actions are only the beginning,'' he said, ''and the longer Congress delays, the worse the impact on the men and women of the Armed Forces will be.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the White House has enlisted the Joint Chiefs of Staff and Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates to press its case. In separate letters to Congress this month, the chiefs and the defense secretary each warned, in Mr. Gates's words, of ''increasingly disruptive and costly measures'' to compensate if a spending bill was not signed into law soon.</p>
        <p>The first of those measures -- a request from the Pentagon to Congress for permission to transfer $1.6 billion from Navy and Air Force pay accounts into the Army's operating account -- is expected Tuesday. The Army issued a news release Monday night detailing plans to ''stretch the money it has'' by instructing commanders to slow the purchase of repair parts and other supplies, and to postpone or cancel nonessential travel, among other steps.</p>
        <p>The White House does not intend to let those measures pass unnoticed. If Mr. Gates, who is scheduled to hold a news conference while traveling in the Middle East, does not mention them, aides to Mr. Bush are likely to. They say they intend to shine a spotlight on every change the Pentagon makes.</p>
        <p>''There will be no question as to why these actions are being taken,'' said Dan Bartlett, counselor to Mr. Bush. ''It will be crystal clear.''</p>
        <p>The White House is betting that Democrats will not like the sight of generals and Army commanders complaining that their operations are being affected by Congressional foot-dragging.</p>
        <p>But Democrats do not seem worried. Senator Harry Reid of Nevada, the majority leader, addressed reporters on Monday with two retired generals by his side.</p>
        <p>''I think the American people have lost confidence in this administration,'' Mr. Reid said. ''We're going to send the president a bill that has a timetable in it.''</p>
        <p>Democrats dismiss Mr. Bush's warnings about training and equipment cutbacks; they note that Mr. Bush made no similar complaints last year when the Republican-controlled Congress waited until June to pass an emergency Iraq war spending bill. What is more, they say, the public is on their side.</p>
        <p>''The status quo that he's talking about, which is basically, 'Just give me the money, I'm going to do what I want to do,' is rejected by an overwhelming number of Americans,'' said Senator Jack Reed, Democrat of Rhode Island and a member of the Armed Services Committee. ''They want to see some change.''</p>
        <p>At least one recent nationwide poll, by CBS News, suggests that Mr. Reed, a former paratrooper, may have a point. The telephone poll conducted last week found that just 29 percent of respondents said that Congress should allow all financing for the war in Iraq, without any limits. A clear majority -- 58 percent -- favored setting time limits, and an additional 9 percent wanted all financing blocked.</p>
        <p>As the fight drags on, the White House sends out daily e-mail reminders of how many days it has been since Mr. Bush first sent his funding request to Congress. On Sunday, Day 69, the e-mail headline quoted Vice President Dick Cheney: ''The process has already run on far too long.'' On Monday, Day 70, the missive said that Mr. Bush looked forward to meeting with Congressional leaders to talk about the war spending bill.</p>
        <p>That will occur on Wednesday, Day 72. Then, on Days 73 and 74, Mr. Bush will travel to Ohio and Michigan, taking his fight with Democrats on the road.</p>
        <p>WHITE HOUSE MEMO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
