<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yanks Hand Ball to Prospect Who Earned His Pinstripes</title>
    <meta content="17yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/sports/baseball/17yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841045"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cleveland Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Cleveland Indians</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3D7113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1058" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yanks Hand Ball to Prospect Who Earned His Pinstripes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Yanks Hand Ball to Prospect Who Earned His Pinstripes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was the middle of March, when spring training drags and teams make the obvious cuts from their rosters. The Yankees were playing the Minnesota Twins at Legends Field, and the right-hander Jeff Karstens had been especially impressive on the mound.</p>
        <p>In the Twins' locker room, while the teams played the final few innings, outfielder Rondell White gathered his things to leave. A reporter asked White about Karstens, and White agreed that he looked good. But Karstens was not the pitcher he wanted to talk about.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After six years in Class A and 14 innings in Class AA, Chase Wright will take the mound for the Yankees on Tuesday against Cleveland.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was the middle of March, when spring training drags and teams make the obvious cuts from their rosters. The Yankees were playing the Minnesota Twins at Legends Field, and the right-hander Jeff Karstens had been especially impressive on the mound.</p>
        <p>In the Twins' locker room, while the teams played the final few innings, outfielder Rondell White gathered his things to leave. A reporter asked White about Karstens, and White agreed that he looked good. But Karstens was not the pitcher he wanted to talk about.</p>
        <p>''That lefty, he could be starting on anybody else's team,'' said White, who did not even know the pitcher's name. ''Anybody that throws that hard from the left side with a cutter, a curveball and a changeup, I think he's got a chance.''</p>
        <p>The pitcher was Chase Wright, who was wearing No. 78 and was sent to the minor league camp after the game. But Wright had shown enough to get the attention of White, a 15-year veteran, and the Yankees noticed, too.</p>
        <p>After six years of failing to advance beyond Class A, Wright, 24, allowed only two hits and a run over six and two-thirds innings during spring training. He joined Class AA Trenton and pitched 14 scoreless innings over two starts, allowing 4 hits and striking out 19.</p>
        <p>Tonight, he makes his major league debut against the Cleveland Indians.</p>
        <p>''Can I guarantee at Yankee Stadium on Tuesday night you're going to see the same type of pitcher? We certainly hope so,'' Manager Joe Torre said Sunday after Oakland's Marco Scutaro ripped a game-winning home run against Mariano Rivera. ''But it's going to be a little bit different situation than he's had before.''</p>
        <p>It was not scripted this way, of course. But the Yankees have four starters on the disabled list -- Chien-Ming Wang, Mike Mussina, Carl Pavano and Karstens, who was supposed to be insurance for the others.</p>
        <p>''We're banged up, that's just all there is to it,'' Andy Pettitte said. ''We're as banged up as you can get.''</p>
        <p>Darrell Rasner is already in the rotation, with Pettitte and Kei Igawa. The Yankees need a starter for Saturday in Boston, a spot that could be filled by Karstens, who threw four shutout innings Monday for Class A Tampa, allowing three hits and a walk while striking out five. Wright got the call tonight because he was pitching the best of any Yankees prospect, and because none of the starters for Class AAA Scranton/Wilkes-Barre were on the 40-man roster.</p>
        <p>''He pitched well in spring training, including his last start over in Lakeland,'' said Mark Newman, the Yankees' senior vice president for baseball operations. ''Against Detroit's A lineup, from the second through the fifth innings, he was really good. You always wish guys had more time than this, but he'll go out there and battle and compete.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees' top prospect, Phil Hughes, 20, has a 6.30 earned run average for Scranton, and the Yankees are closely monitoring his development. But Newman said the decision to take Wright was mostly a roster issue; putting Hughes on the 40-man roster would have required more moves to be made.</p>
        <p>''Chase is on the roster,'' Newman said. ''It's not that we're trying to be more careful with Phil than with Chase.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees drafted Wright out of a Texas high school in the third round of the 2001 draft, and he developed slowly. Through his first four seasons, he was 13-21 with a 4.84 E.R.A. and had not yet reached Tampa, the Yankees' high Class A team.</p>
        <p>But in 2005 at Charleston, a low Class A team, Wright accelerated. He was promoted to Tampa last season and won the Florida State League's pitcher of the year award with a 1.88 E.R.A. Since the start of the 2005 season, he is 23-7 with a 2.76 E.R.A.</p>
        <p>''Stuff happens like that; there's a lot of kids who don't improve incrementally, but something just clicks,'' Newman said. ''With him, he just started throwing more strikes, and his changeup has really improved.''</p>
        <p>The left-hander Sean Henn, who has pitched well out of the Yankees' bullpen this season, made the jump to the majors from Class AA Trenton in 2005. But he seemed overmatched with the Yankees and lost two games before being sent down. Wright, he believes, will do better.</p>
        <p>''Chase has confidence in what he's doing,'' Henn said. ''I think anybody who goes from A ball to Double A would say it's the biggest jump in the minors. For him to dominate the way he's dominated, I think he'll do just fine.''</p>
        <p>Henn said he noticed Wright's numbers and sent him a text message a few days ago. He joked in the message that Wright would take his job if he kept this up.</p>
        <p>''He said, 'I'm throwing out of my mind; I don't know what it is,' '' Henn said. ''I told him: Don't try and figure it out. Just keep doing it.''</p>
        <p>Neither Baseball America nor Baseball Prospectus ranked Wright among the Yankees' top 10 prospects before the season. But Newman said Wright's 89-to-91-mile-an-hour fastball ''is good enough, certainly for a left-hander,'' and his changeup makes it more effective.</p>
        <p>So, ready or not, he is here, with Wang and Mussina nursing hamstring injuries and Pavano out with forearm stiffness. The Yankees have lost three of their past four games, and their overall record is 5-6 as they wait for the wounded to return.</p>
        <p>''We know we're going to get healthy,'' Torre said. ''There's nothing that figures to be debilitating anybody for a long period of time. As long as we can hang around and win our share of games, things are going to get more consistent.''</p>
        <p>Tonight, it is up to Wright to help the Yankees hang around. If he impresses the Indians the way he impressed the Twins' White, he could have a chance to pitch in Fenway Park on Sunday.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Shortstop Derek Jeter said he was not concerned about his fielding this season. Jeter, a three-time Gold Glove winner, has six errors after making three last weekend in Oakland. ''There's been times where I felt bad or uncomfortable in the field and made mistakes and said, I've got to go fix this,'' Jeter said after Sunday's game. ''It may not look it, but I actually feel comfortable out there.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
