<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lightning Stays Step Ahead Of Brodeur and Devils</title>
    <meta content="17devils" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/sports/hockey/17devils.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841042"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Tampa Bay Lightning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Tampa Bay Lightning</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Lecavalier, Vincent</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E3D7113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lightning Stays Step Ahead Of Brodeur and Devils</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lecavalier Outshines Brodeur and Devils</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crouse, Karen</byline>
      <dateline>TAMPA, Fla., April 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Martin Brodeur long has been the Devils' safety net, but in the first three games of the Eastern Conference quarterfinals he has not provided his team with its usual cushion.</p>
        <p>Brodeur, the star goalie, was eclipsed in Game 3 on Monday night by the Lightning's best player, Vincent Lecavalier, who collected a goal and an assist in the Lightning's 3-2 victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vincent Lecavalier collected a goal and an assist to help the Lightning take a 2- 1 lead in the best-of-seven series, which resumes Wednesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Martin Brodeur long has been the Devils' safety net, but in the first three games of the Eastern Conference quarterfinals he has not provided his team with its usual cushion.</p>
        <p>Brodeur, the star goalie, was eclipsed in Game 3 on Monday night by the Lightning's best player, Vincent Lecavalier, who collected a goal and an assist in the Lightning's 3-2 victory.</p>
        <p>The victory gave the Lightning a 2-1 lead in the best-of-seven series, which resumes Wednesday.</p>
        <p>''We've got to find a way to be better, myself big-time included,'' said Brodeur, who made 21 saves.</p>
        <p>It was the third consecutive game in which Brodeur has allowed at least three goals, which does not bode well for the Devils' chances of contending for a fourth Stanley Cup championship. Since their first Cup title run in 1995, the Devils have allowed 3 or more goals in 51 postseason games and their record in those games is 8-43.</p>
        <p>''It's my responsibility to be better,'' said Brodeur, who had all he could handle in Lecavalier and his linemate, Martin St. Louis, who had three assists.</p>
        <p>After receiving a thunderous greeting from the home crowd, the Lightning struck first, with Lecavalier beating Brodeur during a power play on a wrist shot from the near circle with 10 minutes 54 seconds remaining in the first period.</p>
        <p>The puck hit the post, then ricocheted off the left skate of Brodeur, who had anticipated that Lecavalier would pass the puck instead of shooting it. ''When you're hot, the puck stays there,'' Brodeur said with a shrug. ''When you're not, it goes in.''</p>
        <p>It was the fourth goal of the series for Lecavalier, who this season has fully blossomed into a player worthy of the hype that accompanied his selection by the Lightning as the No. 1 overall pick in the 1998 draft.</p>
        <p>Billed as the Michael Jordan of hockey by a former Lightning owner, Lecavalier appeared to be on a career path more like Sam Bowie's, his 37 points in 76 games in his fourth season seeming to cement his underachieving status. Lecavalier was a key cog in the Lightning's Stanley Cup championship run in 2004, but it was not until this season, his eighth, that he averaged more than a point a game, finishing with 108 points in 82 regular-season games.</p>
        <p>The 6-foot-4 Lecavalier gets his shots in even when he does not have the puck; in the first period, he led all players with three hits, his physicality as welcome a sight to Lightning fans as his shooting finesse.</p>
        <p>From beginning to end, Lecavalier was the difference maker. He gave the Lightning the early momentum when the Devils were the ones generating the best scoring chances. The Devils had a two-man advantage for 63 seconds late in the first but had one shot on goal, this after scoring on four of eight power plays in the first two games.</p>
        <p>John Madden tied the score in the second period with his first postseason goal. The Devils' top line of Patrik Elias, Scott Gomez and Brian Gionta put 11 shots on net and came away with nothing but long faces.</p>
        <p>''We were working the puck extremely well,'' said Lou Lamoriello, the Devils' general manager and interim coach. ''Had a lot of energy.'' He added: ''We made a couple of mistakes. Unfortunately they were costly.''</p>
        <p>The slip-ups started with Brodeur. When he is at his best, he moves as if he knows what the skaters are going to do before they themselves have decided. Against the Lightning, he has looked uncharacteristically claustrophobic.</p>
        <p>It is as if Lecavalier and St. Louis have crashed Brodeur's comfort zone and crept into his head. In the second minute of the third period, Brad Richards, who was centering the top line, nearly whiffed on a shot but got enough of the puck to put it on target. An antsy Brodeur overplayed the puck and it ended up rolling past him and settled into the back of the net, giving the Lightning a 2-1 lead.</p>
        <p>The Devils were the recipients of a lucky bounce, tying the score three minutes later on a shot by Zach Parise that was redirected into the net by Lightning defenseman Dan Boyle. Parise's goal, his fourth of the postseason, gave the Devils a glimmer of hope, but it proved short-lived. With 6:29 left, Lecavalier and St. Louis set up Vaclav Prospal on the game-winning goal. Prospal's shot was tipped, but as Brodeur knows only too well, teams in the playoffs tend to make their own luck.</p>
        <p>The Devils created scoring chances but not enough traffic in front of Johan Holmqvist, who made 30 saves.</p>
        <p>''We slugged our way through it,'' Lightning Coach John Tortorella said, adding, ''Fluky goals both ways on both teams, but we just found a way to slug our way through and get a win.''</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>Defenseman Colin White, one of the Devils' alternate captains, did not dress because of a stiff back. Right wing Cam Janssen was the team's other scratch.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
