<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Boston Champions Defeat Elements and Rivals</title>
    <meta content="17marathon" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/sports/othersports/17marathon.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841051"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MARATHON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Boston Marathon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Cheruiyot, Robert</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Grigoryeva, Lidiya</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E0D7113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1018" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Boston Champions Defeat Elements and Rivals</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cheruiyot and Grigoryeva Win Boston Marathon</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, April 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Into the bellowing winds and between the raindrops of a dying northeaster, the runners set out for the 111th Boston Marathon on Monday morning.</p>
        <p>Time would be an afterthought for runners who were forced to trade tactics with nature as much as with one another.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Robert Cheruiyot won his third Boston Marathon on Monday. Lidiya Grigoryeva won the women’s race.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Into the bellowing winds and between the raindrops of a dying northeaster, the runners set out for the 111th Boston Marathon on Monday morning.</p>
        <p>Time would be an afterthought for runners who were forced to trade tactics with nature as much as with one another.</p>
        <p>This was the most dismal day to run the 26.2 miles from Hopkinton east to Boston since the 1970 marathon, which was rain-soaked and colder the entire way. Temperatures Monday hovered in the high 40s, and even as the rain mostly stopped an hour into the race, the headwinds gusted as high as 36 miles an hour, adding resistance that turned many legs to lead.</p>
        <p>Robert K. Cheruiyot and Lidiya Grigoryeva were buffeted but barely bothered. Cheruiyot's tribulations and Grigoryeva's training prepared them for this day, giving each the strength to pull away from their slogging challengers in the final miles and collect a $100,000 prize.</p>
        <p>Cheruiyot, who was destitute and despairing in Kenya before finding refuge in running seven years ago, won his second consecutive Boston title and his third over all here.</p>
        <p>He finished in 2 hours 14 minutes 13 seconds, the slowest time in 30 years and one that was nearly seven minutes off the course record he set last year.</p>
        <p>With a mile and a half remaining, Cheruiyot surged in front of James Kwambai, also of Kenya, finishing 20 seconds ahead. ''When the lion is chasing the antelope, he doesn't look back,'' Cheruiyot said later with a smile. ''He has to eat.''</p>
        <p>This time, he savored his victory upright and not in a hospital. Cheruiyot, 28, blocked out his fall on the slick finish-line logo last October in the Chicago Marathon. In that race, as he was breaking the tape, he slipped and fell, striking his back and head. That left him with a stiff back he felt even through the race Monday.</p>
        <p>''To think about falling down is like telling someone something very bad, telling someone that your mother has died,'' he said, clearly still rattled by the incident. ''If I remember Chicago, falling down, I don't like that.''</p>
        <p>New memories flooded the finish line for Grigoryeva, a Russian who struck an imposing figure barreling down Boylston Street in the final two miles.</p>
        <p>After training in the freezing rain of Kislovodsk, near the Caucasus Mountains in Russia, Grigoryeva, 33, said she was prepared for worse conditions and tougher hills. She pulled away from Jelena Prokopcuka of Latvia, a two-time New York City Marathon winner, right before the 25th mile, and crossed the finish line holding a Russian flag in 2:29:18.</p>
        <p>An accomplished 10,000-meter runner, Grigoryeva overwhelmed her two closest challengers, including Madaí Pérez of Mexico, as they ran three across only two miles before the finish.</p>
        <p>''In the last half of the race, I felt very strong and confident in my ability to win,'' Grigoryeva said. ''I am not surprised. I did a lot of long runs during windy, cold weather.''</p>
        <p>It was Grigoryeva's first major marathon title and her third over all, adding to her victories in Los Angeles in 2006 and Paris in 2005. Still, hers was the slowest winning time in Boston since 1985, when Lisa Larsen-Weidenbach finished in 2:34:06 and was the last woman from the United States to win here.</p>
        <p>The top American woman, Deena Kastor, had stomach cramps just after the halfway point and dropped out of the lead pack. She finished fifth in 2:35:09, which gave her the United States title but no consolation.</p>
        <p>Prokopcuka summarized the tactics of the women's race, which started with a pack of eight. ''Today I tried to make pace, but no one supported me; it was a difficult job,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Last year, she lost by 10 seconds to Rita Jeptoo, who finished fourth this year. Prokopcuka finished 40 seconds behind Grigoryeva, her energy sapped by the place that befalls so many here.</p>
        <p>''Breakheart Hill,'' she called it, a light moment of reversing the name for the section of the course from the 19th through 21st miles. ''I knew the wind would be very strong in my face. When your legs don't have enough strength, it's unbelievably hard.''</p>
        <p>Boston broke from tradition and started the women's and men's races two hours earlier, in part for runners to have cooler temperatures, but the rain stopped by 11.</p>
        <p>''How ironic was that,'' said Guy Morse, the executive director of the Boston Athletic Association, which stages the race. ''If we only have this every 111 years, we'll take it. I'm relieved that it worked out so well.''</p>
        <p>The B.A.A., he said, was ''hemorrhaging money'' to make accommodations for the weather, but cancellation was not a consideration. The weather, Morse said, did not produce an inordinate number of medical problems or no-shows. A total of 23,869 runners registered for the race, and of the 20,638 who started, 20,331 finished.</p>
        <p>Cheruiyot was consumed by the motivation of his past. Less than a decade ago, he did not have enough money to eat in Kenya. His father had left the family, his mother turned mentally unstable, and he and his brother, Stephen Biwott (who finished 11th Monday), were sent to live with relatives. Cheruiyot left after being forced to work long hours in the house of a family member and lived on the street.</p>
        <p>''Without an apartment, a mother, a father, nowhere to sleep, no one to run for, you don't have anybody to support you, you have nothing,'' he said. ''I was supposed to kill myself, and I say no. Because of sport.''</p>
        <p>Eventually, he was directed to a running camp, first with the former Boston winner Moses Tanui of Kenya, then he improved enough to train in Italy in 2001. He first won Boston in 2003, and now he trains with the world-record holder Paul Tergat.</p>
        <p>Cheruiyot is in line for a $500,000 bonus for winning the World Marathon Majors series, having won three major races in the past 12 months.</p>
        <p>''The only way to get this is to work, and it doesn't matter what kind of weather, to make my promise come true,'' he said.</p>
        <p>MARATHON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
