<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Neighbors, a Wall Collapse Occasions More Than Nostalgia</title>
    <meta content="17chumleys" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/nyregion/17chumleys.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841035"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chumley's (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Landlords</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Landlords</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Greenwich Village (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E4D7113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="915" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Neighbors, a Wall Collapse Occasions More Than Nostalgia</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Neighbors, a Wall Collapse Occasions More Than Nostalgia</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Residential tenants of building that shares courtyard and landlord with Chumley's in Greenwich Village say wall collapse that shuttered bar is just another element in long-simmering fight with landlord over slow repairs, questionable construction work and troubling living conditions; worry that work on ceilings in hallways has weakened four-story, red-brick walk-up; fear that what happened at Chumley's could happen to their building; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For people who knew Chumley's as the bar without a sign in Greenwich Village, its temporary closing after part of a wall collapsed this month brought back memories of drinks in a famous setting, memories of the prize-winning writers whose pictures were on the walls, memories of colorful stories about the bar's beginnings as a Depression-era speakeasy.</p>
        <p>For people who knew Chumley's as the bar next door, the neighbors who live in a building that shares a courtyard and a landlord with Chumley's, the wall collapse, following the crumpling of an attached chimney, was frightening.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The temporary closing of Chumley’s in Greenwich Village triggered a mix of reactions from neighbors and patrons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For people who knew Chumley's as the bar without a sign in Greenwich Village, its temporary closing after part of a wall collapsed this month brought back memories of drinks in a famous setting, memories of the prize-winning writers whose pictures were on the walls, memories of colorful stories about the bar's beginnings as a Depression-era speakeasy.</p>
        <p>For people who knew Chumley's as the bar next door, the neighbors who live in a building that shares a courtyard and a landlord with Chumley's, the wall collapse, following the crumpling of an attached chimney, was frightening.</p>
        <p>These neighbors -- whose building, at 56 Barrow Street, is just down the block from Chumley's -- see the problems that shuttered Chumley's as another element in a long-simmering fight with their landlord over slow repairs, questionable construction work and troubling living conditions.</p>
        <p>Their long list of complaints includes hallways that were without lights for several weeks last summer, fireplaces that can no longer be used and apartments where mice are regular visitors.</p>
        <p>Nestor Palacios, who lives in a studio apartment at 56 Barrow, said he and his 6-year-old daughter, Isabella, slept in their coats last week because there was no heat. But he said there was another problem when he turned out the lights: The mice came out.</p>
        <p>''I have a hard time falling asleep, waiting for them to crawl over me,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He said that his kitchenette was unusable because of mouse droppings, and that even though he cleaned the countertop and the sink at least once a day, one afternoon last week he found droppings at the edge of the sink.</p>
        <p>''I have now been living with it for so long that I know, if I look behind my bed, what I'm going to find,'' Mr. Palacios said. ''The smell has alerted me.''</p>
        <p>Once, he found a dead mouse in his daughter's bed. Another time, a friend who stayed on a pullout couch in the apartment left in the middle of the night after mice appeared.</p>
        <p>He said that he got a cat, a mouse-fighting option his neighbors had tried, but that he had to give it away because his daughter turned out to be allergic to it.</p>
        <p>In the hallways of 56 Barrow, Y-shaped wooden supports rise from the floor to the ceiling. Sections of the ceiling have been cut away, exposing old beams. On Thursday, wide cellophane tape was wrapped around the fire extinguisher on one of the landings.</p>
        <p>Tenants worried that the work on the ceilings has weakened the four-story, red-brick walk-up. And because they were told some time ago to stop using their fireplaces, they were concerned that what happened at Chumley's, a 19th-century building at 86 Bedford Street, could happen to their building, too.</p>
        <p>''Are our chimneys going to collapse on us?'' Mr. Palacios asked.</p>
        <p>Records of the city's Buildings Department show that the agency issued a stop work order on 56 Barrow but rescinded it in February.</p>
        <p>An inspector who visited the building in March, responding to a call about possible illegal construction in the hallways in the early-morning hours, reported seeing no such work.</p>
        <p>Mr. Palacios said his rent was $1,265 a month. After a meeting with the landlord, he said, he filed papers with the city's Department of Housing and Community Renewal seeking a reduction in rent, because with no fireplaces, there was a reduction in services. His request is pending.</p>
        <p>Mr. Palacios's building, the Chumley's building and the others that open on a little courtyard off Barrow Street are owned by companies with ties to Margaret Streicker Porres, who controls a number of old buildings in Chelsea and Greenwich Village that the city has designated as landmarks.</p>
        <p>Last year, after taking legal action against tenants in some of her other rent-regulated buildings, she moved to evict two tenants at one of those buildings, saying she needed their apartments for her family.</p>
        <p>The tenants in that eviction dispute took issue with the idea that she needed their apartments for her brother and sister. They noted at the time that her father, John H. Streicker, is the chairman of a real estate company that manages a $5 billion portfolio that includes 50,000 apartments.</p>
        <p>A call to New Castle Realty Services, which manages the Greenwich Village buildings, was transferred to a man who identified himself only as Michael and refused to give his last name or answer questions. A later request for comment that was faxed to New Castle went unanswered.</p>
        <p>At 56 Barrow, Mr. Palacios's cat-owning neighbor Grace Byrd, said problems with her apartment began almost as soon as she moved in last summer, when the ceiling collapsed.</p>
        <p>''The situation we're living in is so awful,'' said Ms. Byrd, an intern at Christie's, the auction house. ''There are the holes in the ceiling, there's no heat and the whole building is basically just crumbling into itself.''</p>
        <p>She and Mr. Palacios said construction crews had worked on one of the adjacent buildings, which is vacant.</p>
        <p>Mr. Palacios said that last summer, his bathroom floor gave way and that while it was being repaired, he was told to go to an apartment in the vacant building to use the toilet or take a shower. Part of that apartment, he said, later collapsed.</p>
        <p>As for Chumley's, whose owner hopes to reopen it in a month or two, a spokeswoman for the Buildings Department said yesterday that no permit had yet been issued for the work needed to shore up the facade.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
