<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Filings on Campaign Finances Offer Glimpses Into Operations of the Candidates</title>
    <meta content="17donate" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/us/politics/17donate.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841010"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HEADING TOWARD 2008"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consultants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Romney, Mitt</person>
        <person class="online_producer">McCain, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Obama, Barack</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Giuliani, Rudolph W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804EED8113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="783" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Filings on Campaign Finances Offer Glimpses Into Operations of the Candidates</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Finance Filings Offer Glimpses of ’08 Candidates</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID D. KIRKPATRICK and ARON PILHOFER; Griff Palmer contributed from New York.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kirkpatrick, David D; Pilhofer, Aron</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The American public has given about $160 million to the 2008 presidential candidates so far this year, more than four times the total contributed to campaigns in the same period four years ago.</p>
        <p>Much of the money went into the pockets of the political class: media, fund-raising and political consultants. But each campaign doled out its contributions differently, often in unexpected ways that provide some insights into the candidates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Presidential candidates have raised more than four times the total contributed in the same period four years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The American public has given about $160 million to the 2008 presidential candidates so far this year, more than four times the total contributed to campaigns in the same period four years ago.</p>
        <p>Much of the money went into the pockets of the political class: media, fund-raising and political consultants. But each campaign doled out its contributions differently, often in unexpected ways that provide some insights into the candidates.</p>
        <p>Mitt Romney, the Republican, who is by far the richest candidate, was stingiest with his staff members' salaries, often having them fly discount airlines and stay in accommodations as humble as a Super 8 Motel in Parsippany, N.J.</p>
        <p>Senator John McCain of Arizona, whose Republican primary campaign spent the highest percentage of income during the quarter, paid nearly $11,000 for photography, $1,700 for decorations and $1,671 for flowers.</p>
        <p>Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton of New York, who irked donors during her last Senate campaign by running up heavy bills for such amenities, spent just $205 for photographs and $89 for flowers, according to the campaign's filings. But her campaign did report a debt of $1,995 to Jack H. Lucky Floral Design in New Market, Va.</p>
        <p>Others drew fine distinctions among donors. Senator Barack Obama, the Illinois Democrat, has talked of running a new kind of campaign that refuses fund-raising help from federal lobbyists. But a list of his top fund-raisers released over the weekend shows that his campaign has defined the term in an exacting way.</p>
        <p>At least two of the donors on his list of 130 top fund-raisers were registered federal lobbyists as recently as last year. One, Tom Reed, works at the law and lobbying firm of K &amp; L Preston Gates and earned about $60,000 from lobbying in 2006.</p>
        <p>Another, Alan Solomont, is one of the best known Democratic donors and helped raise more than $35 million for Senator John Kerry's presidential campaign in 2004.</p>
        <p>Mr. Solomont is the founder of a nursing home company and, during the Clinton administration, news reports suggested that he used his clout as a fund-raiser to argue against tougher regulation of nursing homes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Solomont reported about $90,000 in income last year from lobbying the federal government about Medicare and Medicaid; Mr. Obama has made overhauling health care a focus of his campaign.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Solomont said he had withdrawn his lobbyist registration as soon as he signed on as a fund-raiser. ''When I joined the campaign, I ended that,'' he said.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Mr. Obama said Mr. Reed had stopped lobbying also.</p>
        <p>The spokesman, Bill Burton, said that accepting help from people who had just left lobbying did not breach the campaign's policy.</p>
        <p>''The point of this ban on federal lobbyists' donations,'' Mr. Burton said, ''is that we don't want the fund-raising help of someone who is currently lobbying the federal government.''</p>
        <p>Like its rivals, the Obama campaign has sought financial support from an array of other influence-seekers, including lobbyists at the state level, federal public affairs advocates who are not registered lobbyists, and the chief executives of companies with strong interests in federal policy and legislation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Obama's supporters note that his principal rival, Mrs. Clinton, has enlisted the support of several registered lobbyists among her ''Hillraisers,'' as she calls her biggest fund-raisers.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain's campaign, which trailed its rivals in fund-raising (with about $15 million) but outpaced them in spending (about $11 million), had the highest-paid staff of any campaign in either party.</p>
        <p>Nine of the roughly 150 people listed on his payroll earned more than $25,000 in the first quarter, including the political strategists Michael Dennehy, whose $51,925 earnings made him the highest-paid staff member listed on any campaign, and Terry Nelson, who made $36,173.</p>
        <p>Rudolph W. Giuliani, the Republican former mayor of New York, paid seven staffers more than $25,000. Mike DuHaime, his campaign manager, was the second highest paid aide, earning $44,375.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton paid three staff members more than $25,000; her campaign manager, Patti Solis Doyle, was paid $27,142 in the quarter. But her campaign also reported $154,000 in unpaid bills to her media adviser, Mandy Grunwald, and $277,000 to her main political adviser, Mark Penn.</p>
        <p>The only employee of Mr. Obama's campaign to make more than $25,000 for the quarter was Julianna Smoot, his finance director. She earned $26,099 and oversaw $24.8 million in primary fund-raising.</p>
        <p>None of Mr. Romney's roughly 150 staff members made that much. ''We put a premium on efficiency,'' said Kevin Madden, a spokesman. Recalling a trip for Mr. Romney's campaign announcement in Michigan, he said, ''We tripled up in a hotel suite -- one of those cheaper ones.''</p>
        <p>HEADING TOWARD 2008</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
