<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TODAY IN BUSINESS</title>
    <meta content="17biztoday" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841001"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505EFD8113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="844" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TODAY IN BUSINESS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HIDDEN LOSERS IN HOUSING SLUMP -- Among the lesser-known losers in the downturn in new home construction are immigrant workers -- most of them illegal -- who have ridden the building boom and now find jobs few and far between. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>QUITE A TAX SHELTER -- Because of some structural differences in hedge funds, some managers of the lightly regulated private pools of money have discovered a way to avoid paying taxes on their huge fees for up to 10 years. [A1.]</p>
        <p>FOR SAFE ROAD TRAVEL ABROAD -- Rochelle Sobel founded the Association for Safe International Road Travel after her son died in a bus crash in Turkey two weeks before he was to graduate from medical school. ''It is important to not only know the laws, but the road culture before you go,'' she said. Traffic accidents are the leading cause of nonnatural death for Americans overseas, according to the State Department. [C7.]</p>
        <p>SALLIE MAE SOLD TO PRIVATE FIRMS -- Sallie Mae agreed to be sold for $25 billion to two private equity investors amid calls in Washington to cut federal subsidies for student loans. The deal has the potential not only to change Sallie Mae but also to shake up the entire lending industry. [C1.]</p>
        <p>HOME DEPOT'S GREEN LABEL -- Home Depot, the second-largest retailer in the United States, is introducing the largest green-labeling program -- for 3,000 products -- in retailing today in a move that could persuade its rivals to speed up their own plans. [C1.]</p>
        <p>TROUBLES FOR AMGEN -- Setbacks at Amgen, some unexpected and some perhaps self-inflicted, are posing new challenges in the company's previously charmed 27-year history. [C1.]</p>
        <p>A NEW SOURCE OF ETHANOL -- Because of the great worldwide demand for corn, an alternative method for producing ethanol -- using the cellulose waste from sugar cane -- has been sought by researchers, venture capitalists and government officials as a way to help end America's dependency on foreign oil. A new plant under construction in Louisiana could help in that effort. [C1.]</p>
        <p>AND DIESEL FUEL FROM WHAT? -- Tyson Foods and ConocoPhillips are forming an alliance to produce and market diesel fuel made from pork, poultry and beef fat. [C5.]</p>
        <p>A BANK DEAL IS THREATENED -- A possible bidding war has sent shares of the big Dutch bank ABN Amro soaring, which is threatening the company's takeover by its preferred suitor, Barclays. ABN Amro has also rejected an unusual takeover overture from a group of three European banks. [C1.]</p>
        <p>JUSTICES HEAR WORK-RULE CASE -- In 1975, the Labor Department exempted home care aides from federal minimum wage and overtime protections. Lawyers representing an aide from New York argued before the Supreme Court to get that regulation changed. [B2.]</p>
        <p>CLOUD OVER GUIDANT IS LIFTED -- The Food and Drug Administration erased the cloud it cast in a warning letter sent to the Guidant Corporation in December 2005, a change that should make it easier for its parent, Boston Scientific, to introduce improvements in the unit's heart-regulating implants. [C3.]</p>
        <p>WHAT WAS THAT DOMAIN NAME? -- The House is to vote on legislation that clarifies the law barring for-profit companies from using names that sound like official government agencies -- especially ones that use the letters I, R and S in a row. [C3.]</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T ENDS BID FOR TELECOM ITALIA -- AT&amp;T has withdrawn its offer to buy a stake in the company that controls Telecom Italia, -- perhaps dissuaded by intense political pressure in Italy against a sale to a foreign company. [C3.]</p>
        <p>YAHOO'S NEWSPAPER DEAL -- Yahoo announced a broad deal with publishers representing 264 newspapers to sell national advertising across their Web sites. [C2.]</p>
        <p>RETAIL SALES UP SLIGHTLY IN MARCH -- Retail sales rose a bit more than expected in March, but adjusted February sales were much higher than first estimated, the Commerce Department has said. [C4.]</p>
        <p>A GOOD SIGN FOR CITIGROUP? -- Citigroup's first-quarter earnings declined 11 percent because of a big charge for its recently announced corporate revamping. But the results showed progress in its expense management and strength in investment banking, and its shares rose 2.6 percent, which come at a critical time for Citigroup's chief executive. [C3.]</p>
        <p>WHAT FEMALE TRAVELERS WANT -- American Airlines has tried to tap into the female market with innovations like lie-flat business-class seats on its long-haul flights. But a new Web site for women travelers isn't sitting well. On the Road: Joe Sharkey. [C7.]</p>
        <p>ONLINE</p>
        <p>Business Briefing  Articles on these developments are at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>MICROSOFT IS PREPARING to introduce a suite of design software, called Expression Studio, that will go head to head with Adobe Systems' flagship tools, Photoshop and Illustrator. It also will include a tool for building multimedia programs to bring it in line with Adobe's Flash. (AP)</p>
        <p>MATTEL REPORTED a 60 percent decline in first-quarter profit but beat Wall Street revenue expectations with strong sales, despite a decline in demand for Barbie dolls in the United States. (AP)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HIDDEN LOSERS IN HOUSING SLUMP -- Among the lesser-known losers in the downturn in new home construction are immigrant workers -- most of them illegal -- who have ridden the building boom and now find jobs few and far between. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>QUITE A TAX SHELTER -- Because of some structural differences in hedge funds, some managers of the lightly regulated private pools of money have discovered a way to avoid paying taxes on their huge fees for up to 10 years. [A1.]</p>
        <p>FOR SAFE ROAD TRAVEL ABROAD -- Rochelle Sobel founded the Association for Safe International Road Travel after her son died in a bus crash in Turkey two weeks before he was to graduate from medical school. ''It is important to not only know the laws, but the road culture before you go,'' she said. Traffic accidents are the leading cause of nonnatural death for Americans overseas, according to the State Department. [C7.]</p>
        <p>SALLIE MAE SOLD TO PRIVATE FIRMS -- Sallie Mae agreed to be sold for $25 billion to two private equity investors amid calls in Washington to cut federal subsidies for student loans. The deal has the potential not only to change Sallie Mae but also to shake up the entire lending industry. [C1.]</p>
        <p>HOME DEPOT'S GREEN LABEL -- Home Depot, the second-largest retailer in the United States, is introducing the largest green-labeling program -- for 3,000 products -- in retailing today in a move that could persuade its rivals to speed up their own plans. [C1.]</p>
        <p>TROUBLES FOR AMGEN -- Setbacks at Amgen, some unexpected and some perhaps self-inflicted, are posing new challenges in the company's previously charmed 27-year history. [C1.]</p>
        <p>A NEW SOURCE OF ETHANOL -- Because of the great worldwide demand for corn, an alternative method for producing ethanol -- using the cellulose waste from sugar cane -- has been sought by researchers, venture capitalists and government officials as a way to help end America's dependency on foreign oil. A new plant under construction in Louisiana could help in that effort. [C1.]</p>
        <p>AND DIESEL FUEL FROM WHAT? -- Tyson Foods and ConocoPhillips are forming an alliance to produce and market diesel fuel made from pork, poultry and beef fat. [C5.]</p>
        <p>A BANK DEAL IS THREATENED -- A possible bidding war has sent shares of the big Dutch bank ABN Amro soaring, which is threatening the company's takeover by its preferred suitor, Barclays. ABN Amro has also rejected an unusual takeover overture from a group of three European banks. [C1.]</p>
        <p>JUSTICES HEAR WORK-RULE CASE -- In 1975, the Labor Department exempted home care aides from federal minimum wage and overtime protections. Lawyers representing an aide from New York argued before the Supreme Court to get that regulation changed. [B2.]</p>
        <p>CLOUD OVER GUIDANT IS LIFTED -- The Food and Drug Administration erased the cloud it cast in a warning letter sent to the Guidant Corporation in December 2005, a change that should make it easier for its parent, Boston Scientific, to introduce improvements in the unit's heart-regulating implants. [C3.]</p>
        <p>WHAT WAS THAT DOMAIN NAME? -- The House is to vote on legislation that clarifies the law barring for-profit companies from using names that sound like official government agencies -- especially ones that use the letters I, R and S in a row. [C3.]</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T ENDS BID FOR TELECOM ITALIA -- AT&amp;T has withdrawn its offer to buy a stake in the company that controls Telecom Italia, -- perhaps dissuaded by intense political pressure in Italy against a sale to a foreign company. [C3.]</p>
        <p>YAHOO'S NEWSPAPER DEAL -- Yahoo announced a broad deal with publishers representing 264 newspapers to sell national advertising across their Web sites. [C2.]</p>
        <p>RETAIL SALES UP SLIGHTLY IN MARCH -- Retail sales rose a bit more than expected in March, but adjusted February sales were much higher than first estimated, the Commerce Department has said. [C4.]</p>
        <p>A GOOD SIGN FOR CITIGROUP? -- Citigroup's first-quarter earnings declined 11 percent because of a big charge for its recently announced corporate revamping. But the results showed progress in its expense management and strength in investment banking, and its shares rose 2.6 percent, which come at a critical time for Citigroup's chief executive. [C3.]</p>
        <p>WHAT FEMALE TRAVELERS WANT -- American Airlines has tried to tap into the female market with innovations like lie-flat business-class seats on its long-haul flights. But a new Web site for women travelers isn't sitting well. On the Road: Joe Sharkey. [C7.]</p>
        <p>ONLINE</p>
        <p>Business Briefing  Articles on these developments are at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>MICROSOFT IS PREPARING to introduce a suite of design software, called Expression Studio, that will go head to head with Adobe Systems' flagship tools, Photoshop and Illustrator. It also will include a tool for building multimedia programs to bring it in line with Adobe's Flash. (AP)</p>
        <p>MATTEL REPORTED a 60 percent decline in first-quarter profit but beat Wall Street revenue expectations with strong sales, despite a decline in demand for Barbie dolls in the United States. (AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
