<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>This Postseason, the Rangers' Lundqvist Is Healthy and in Top Form</title>
    <meta content="17rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/sports/hockey/17rangers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841017"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Atlanta Thrashers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Lundqvist, Henrik</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E6D7113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="858" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>This Postseason, the Rangers' Lundqvist Is Healthy and in Top Form</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rangers’ Lundqvist Is Healthy and in Top Form</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinser, Lynn</byline>
      <dateline>GREENBURGH, N.Y., April 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two of the saves that Rangers goaltender Henrik Lundqvist made against Atlanta on Saturday could have filled a small highlight reel. First, Keith Tkachuk skated in alone and veered left, but Lundqvist dashed across his crease, cut off the angle and stopped his shot.</p>
        <p>That left Lundqvist out of position, but he scrambled upright and knocked the follow-up shot by Ilya Kovalchuk high over the crossbar with his blocker.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Henrik Lundqvist’s performance in the last crucial months of the regular season was nothing short of spectacular.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two of the saves that Rangers goaltender Henrik Lundqvist made against Atlanta on Saturday could have filled a small highlight reel. First, Keith Tkachuk skated in alone and veered left, but Lundqvist dashed across his crease, cut off the angle and stopped his shot.</p>
        <p>That left Lundqvist out of position, but he scrambled upright and knocked the follow-up shot by Ilya Kovalchuk high over the crossbar with his blocker.</p>
        <p>It was a display of quickness and determination that was forgotten as soon as Rangers forward Sean Avery raced up ice, bounced the puck off the glass and watched it ricochet into Atlanta's net 8 minutes 8 seconds into Game 2 of their first-round playoff series. Forgotten, except by Lundqvist's teammates, who fully appreciated that Avery's goal would not have occurred without the saves that preceded it.</p>
        <p>''We're not doing what we're doing right now if he hasn't been great,'' Rangers Coach Tom Renney said of Lundqvist. ''We all understand that.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers lead the best-of-seven series, 2-0, and play Game 3 on Tuesday night at Madison Square Garden, where Lundqvist is adored and fans chant his name at every opportunity. So far in this series, he has received far less attention than the Thrashers' goalies. Kari Lehtonen was benched after stopping 34 shots in a 4-3 loss in Game 1 and replaced by Johan Hedberg, who made 37 saves in a 2-1 loss Saturday.</p>
        <p>Lundqvist had a relatively modest combined total of 48 saves, but his value is not measured in quantity.</p>
        <p>''Players in front of him know if there's a breakdown, he's our last line of defense and he's always there for us,'' defenseman Paul Mara said. ''He's done it so many times. It helps you be confident just having him back there.''</p>
        <p>Lundqvist's performance in the last crucial months of the regular season was nothing short of spectacular. In the Rangers' 34 games after the All-Star Game break, Lundqvist led the N.H.L. in goals against average (1.80) and save percentage (.934), and had four shutouts. He started all but one of those games.</p>
        <p>Renney said he monitored Lundqvist for signs that he needed rest, but found that he did not. Lundqvist skips most game-day skates and some practices to stay fresh. He is among the fittest of his teammates, who marvel at his ability.</p>
        <p>''I think the biggest thing about him is his competitiveness, not just wanting to win, but he stays with the puck even when it appears he may be beaten or completely out of the play,'' center Matt Cullen said. ''He battles so hard to get back in position. I think that's probably his best attribute.''</p>
        <p>Lundqvist's performance since the All-Star Game break has been a far cry from the way he finished last season, when he struggled to recover from a hip injury and battled what he later revealed to be migraines. His season also included a break for the Olympics, where Lundqvist led Sweden to a gold medal.</p>
        <p>During a four-game playoff sweep by the Devils, Lundqvist was benched after the first game. He returned for Game 3 but never recovered his top form. He gave up 13 goals in three games.</p>
        <p>''Experience is important,'' Renney said. ''It's a great teacher. You've got to allow yourself to stumble a little bit so you can correct yourself and move forward.''</p>
        <p>Lundqvist, though, said that last season had little effect on him.</p>
        <p>''I don't think about it at all,'' he said. ''I focus on this year. I feel good about my game. I feel healthy. I try to approach the game the same way I've been doing the last couple of months. Even though this is just my second N.H.L. playoffs, I've been playing playoffs for the last six years. You know it's going to be more intense.''</p>
        <p>Lundqvist played for Vastra Frolunda of the Swedish Elite League, winning 12 of 14 playoff games in 2005 and leading his team to the league championship. That convinced the Rangers, who drafted him in the seventh round in 2000, that he was ready for the N.H.L.</p>
        <p>He has another reason to feel proud, watching his twin, Joel, gain playoff experience with the Dallas Stars. Joel Lundqvist is a checking-line forward who spent half the season in the minors before the Stars called him up in late January. He scored in the Stars' victory in Game 2 against Vancouver, with a thrilled brother watching him on television.</p>
        <p>''It's fun to see him play,'' Henrik Lundqvist said. ''I like his style. He has a lot of energy. It's fun to watch. Obviously, he's excited to play for Dallas. He's been working really hard, especially the first half-year down in the minors.''</p>
        <p>The brothers talk as much as they can and watch each other's playoff games intently, although Henrik said he did not stay awake for the four-overtime marathon Dallas and Vancouver played in Game 1.</p>
        <p>''We don't talk every day, but sometimes we just call to see what's going on,'' Henrik Lundqvist said. ''It's good to see. He's where he wants to be right now.''</p>
        <p>And Lundqvist is right where the Rangers want him.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
