<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>More Than a Handshake Deal</title>
    <meta content="17japan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/sports/baseball/17japan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841044"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Japan</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Igawa, Kei</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E3D7113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1368" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>More Than a Handshake Deal</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">More Than a Handshake Deal for Japanese Baseball Players</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID PICKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Picker, David</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If Kei Igawa helps the Yankees defeat the Cleveland Indians tomorrow night at Yankee Stadium, Manager Joe Torre will probably offer him a handshake and some words of encouragement. But Igawa, who pitched for the Hanshin Tigers in his native Japan the previous eight seasons, is accustomed to more tangible rewards.</p>
        <p>After contributing to a Hanshin victory, Igawa's manager would frequently hand him an envelope stuffed with yen, usually the equivalent of about $1,000. Igawa was free to spend the money as he liked. He usually saved it and kept the envelope as a souvenir.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Japan, managers sometimes offer cash for playing a good game, a system that some players refer to as fight money.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If Kei Igawa helps the Yankees defeat the Cleveland Indians tomorrow night at Yankee Stadium, Manager Joe Torre will probably offer him a handshake and some words of encouragement. But Igawa, who pitched for the Hanshin Tigers in his native Japan the previous eight seasons, is accustomed to more tangible rewards.</p>
        <p>After contributing to a Hanshin victory, Igawa's manager would frequently hand him an envelope stuffed with yen, usually the equivalent of about $1,000. Igawa was free to spend the money as he liked. He usually saved it and kept the envelope as a souvenir.</p>
        <p>The financial exchange, which is separate from a player's salary, is common in Japanese baseball and known as kantoku shou, which, translated literally, means manager prize. The foreign players in Nippon Professional Baseball commonly refer to it as fight money.</p>
        <p>The system is simple: When a player shines in the eyes of his manager during a victory -- by doing something like hitting a game-winning home run or pitching eight solid innings or stealing a base during a key moment -- he is later rewarded with cash. Sometimes players are given cash for their cumulative statistics, like having the most victories on the team by the All-Star Game break.</p>
        <p>Not every ball club in the 12-team league gives fight money, and no two teams' systems are identical. But when fight money is used, its purpose is uniform -- to provide extra motivation. ''It's like you're the horse and they put a carrot in front of you and you try to go for it,'' Igawa said through an interpreter last week. ''It's like bait.''</p>
        <p>Fight money, whether it is given to one player or divided among many, usually amounts to no more than $5,000 a victory. In most cases, management supplies the funds. But Igawa said fight money sometimes came directly from his manager's wallet. He added that he once had a manager who, in lieu of money, handed out expensive watches.</p>
        <p>Managers have been to known to withhold fight money in the weeks before a big game. If the team wins the game, the stars receive a windfall. Igawa, who has had two no-decisions for the Yankees in his first two starts of the season, laughed at the idea of Torre's handing him a bucket full of dollars after beating the Boston Red Sox. He said he knew that fight money was not used in the major leagues here and that getting motivated without it would not be a problem.</p>
        <p>Hideki Okajima, a reliever who made his major league debut this season for the Red Sox, received fight money when he played for the Yomiuri Giants but not when he played for the Hokkaido Nippon Ham Fighters.</p>
        <p>''If the system exists and it helps the team's motivation, I think it's better to have it,'' Okajima said through an interpreter. ''The harder you work, the better you perform. And you get to see an actual physical award for that.''</p>
        <p>In Okajima's case, Giants Manager Shigeo Nagashima, a legendary figure in Japanese baseball who is now retired, would distribute fight money during team meetings. After a player received his envelope, his teammates applauded. Okajima noted that since the amount was relatively small, the financial reward paled in comparison to the gratification of being recognized.</p>
        <p>In Major League Baseball, many players have incentive clauses in their contracts that reward them for things like making the All-Star team or playing in a certain number of games. But there is no known day-to-day reward system. Several major leaguers who did not play in Japan said they had not heard of the fight money custom; some wondered why players in Japan, where salaries are much less than they are in Major League Baseball but top players make about $5 million a year, needed extra motivation.</p>
        <p>''It's such an odd concept over here for us,'' Mets pitcher Tom Glavine said. ''My immediate reaction is you're paying guys extra for what they're getting paid to do anyway.''</p>
        <p>Glavine said fight money reminded him of the pay-for-performance system proposed by major league owners in 1990. The system, which was rejected by the players' union and never implemented, would have paid players based on their tenure and their statistics from the previous two seasons.</p>
        <p>Glavine also said fight money could create conflict.</p>
        <p>''If you're a player and you think, 'Hey, I got a chance to go 4 for 4 today and I might get that money at the end of the game,' '' Glavine said. '' 'But, man, we got runners on first and second, or a runner on second, and the better thing for me to do here might be to sacrifice him over. But now I'm going to go 3 for 4 instead of 4 for 4.' You kind of start getting into that gray area.''</p>
        <p>Bobby Valentine, who managed in the majors for 15 seasons and is now the manager of the Chiba Lotte Marines, said in some ways fight money went against Japanese values like group harmony. Superstars are likely to receive the bulk of fight money, setting them apart from their teammates, he said.</p>
        <p>Valentine decided to alter the system. After each victory, his players are awarded points based on their performance. A reliever who tosses a shutout inning might get 1 point; a pinch-runner who scores might get 2 points. Every player who enters a game receives points, and players ultimately receive cash based on how many points they accumulate. The system is so intricate, Valentine said, a computer is needed.</p>
        <p>Valentine, who does not hand money directly to players or pay from his own pocket, takes 10 percent of the management allotment for fight money to give to auxiliary staffers, like bullpen catchers and massage therapists, some of whom make about $60,000 a year.</p>
        <p>''With our team, it's a motivating factor for the guys behind the scenes because it's money they never would see,'' Valentine said during a telephone interview from Fukuoka, Japan. ''I remember talking to one of our veteran guys and asking him if he thought the system was fair that I established when I got here. He said it really didn't matter. That money didn't mean anything to him.''</p>
        <p>Valentine would not discuss how many yen his players received, noting that fight money was taxable and he did not want to get anyone in trouble. The amounts are usually not made public.</p>
        <p>In addition to fight money, players in Japan often receive performance-based gifts from sponsors, sometimes in the form of cash. The gifts can range from the mundane to the luxurious.</p>
        <p>Igawa, when he was a bachelor, received hot plates. In several of his 10 seasons with Yomiuri, Hideki Matsui of the Yankees received an automobile from a car dealership for being, in the opinion of the dealership, the Central League's most valuable player.</p>
        <p>Daisuke Matsuzaka of the Red Sox played the previous eight seasons for the Seibu Lions, who did not use fight money. He often received stuffed animals and sets of towels from sponsors. Sometimes the gifts became burdensome.</p>
        <p>''As the winning pitcher for the Lions, I'd receive a case with two dozen cans of coffee,'' Matsuzaka said through an interpreter. ''I like coffee but not really from a can. I just gave it away to people.''</p>
        <p>Matsuzaka, Igawa and Okajima are still adjusting to life in Major League Baseball, which means no fight money or an abundance of gifts. Thousands of miles away, C. J. Nitkowski, a reliever, is making the transition in the opposite direction.</p>
        <p>Nitkowski played 10 seasons in the majors and then in Class AAA before signing with the Fukuoka SoftBank Hawks this season. Not surprising, he has embraced the concept of fight money.</p>
        <p>''I just look at it as a bonus I was never expecting,'' Nitkowksi said in an e-mail message.</p>
        <p>Nitkowski said he would like fight money to be used in the minor leagues, where players often make a few thousand dollars a month before taxes. But he said he did not think the system would work in the majors, where salaries can reach more than $20 million a season.</p>
        <p>''With salaries where they are right now,'' Nitkowski said, ''it's ashtray change at best.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
