<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knicks Win Back Their Fans, if Not the Game</title>
    <meta content="17knicks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/17/sports/basketball/17knicks.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841047"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Madison Square Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Nets</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E2D7113FF934A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="929" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knicks Win Back Their Fans, if Not the Game</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Knicks Win Back Their Fans, if Not the Game</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beck, Howard</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The national anthem was only halfway over last night, but one giddy fan could not contain his enthusiasm. Right around the time that the bombs were ''bursting in air,'' a shout burst from the end zone at Madison Square Garden: ''Let's go, Rangers!''</p>
        <p>There will be a playoff game here tonight, but it will be played on ice. The wooden floorboards will be safely tucked away for a third consecutive spring.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the Knicks played their final game of the season at Madison Square Garden, the optimism belonged to the Rangers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The national anthem was only halfway over last night, but one giddy fan could not contain his enthusiasm. Right around the time that the bombs were ''bursting in air,'' a shout burst from the end zone at Madison Square Garden: ''Let's go, Rangers!''</p>
        <p>There will be a playoff game here tonight, but it will be played on ice. The wooden floorboards will be safely tucked away for a third consecutive spring.</p>
        <p>As the Knicks prepared for their final home game last night, the optimism belonged to the Rangers, their corporate brothers. And the biggest pregame cheer went to Jason Kidd of the Nets, their cross-Hudson rivals, who sent the Knicks to a 104-95 loss.</p>
        <p>So it goes for the Knicks (32-49), who have made one postseason appearance in the past six years (a sweep by the Nets in 2004). They spent most of the past six months testing their fans' patience and sanity. They acknowledged as much when Stephon Marbury took the microphone before the tipoff.</p>
        <p>''You guys stuck with us throughout the year,'' Marbury, the Coney Island-born guard, said. ''We know it was tough this year, not making the playoffs.'' But, he assured the crowd, ''There are better things to come.''</p>
        <p>It did not come in the next few hours. The Nets (40-41) completed a sweep of the season series and are now 24-4 against the Knicks, counting playoffs, since Kidd arrived in 2001. The Nets clinched at least a seventh-place finish in the Eastern Conference and moved to a half-game behind Washington for the sixth seed.</p>
        <p>Vince Carter led the way with his fourth career triple-double: 29 points, 12 rebounds and 10 assists. Steve Francis had 26 points for the Knicks, and the rookie Mardy Collins, their lone bright spot in April, added 23 points.</p>
        <p>But the Knicks lost their fifth straight game, and their 15th in the last 18.</p>
        <p>Losing has become almost routine in the final month, but Coach Isiah Thomas has continued to praise his team for fighting and competing every night. He took a long time to meet with the news media last night, saying he ''needed to really collect my thoughts.''</p>
        <p>''I really don't like losing,'' Thomas said. ''We compete hard, but at the same time, in competing hard you ask the players for all they can give. And even though they give everything, you're still not satisfied, and you have to have a reality check with yourself before you come in here and really just start going off on people.''</p>
        <p>The Knicks announced a sellout, their 22nd, which is their lowest total in four years. Their season average, 18,805, is the franchise's lowest in 15 years.</p>
        <p>But the Knicks announced sellouts for 19 of their last 25 home games. If that trend is any indication, a sizable percentage of fans believe again. That was not the case a year ago, after the Knicks lost 59 games. The hangover lasted into this season, with fans booing every pratfall as the Knicks lost six of their first seven home games. Marbury and Thomas were the primary targets.</p>
        <p>It became so bad that Thomas openly lamented his team's home-court disadvantage.</p>
        <p>''It was a very hostile environment for us and it's not that anymore,'' Thomas said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Something changed in late December, when the Knicks won a number of thrillers at the Garden, including overtime victories against Utah, Charlotte and Detroit.</p>
        <p>''I knew we were going to win them back,'' Thomas said. ''It's a warm and friendly environment for us now, but it wasn't then. But we fought hard to win them back.''</p>
        <p>Some measure of faith was restored during the middle months, when the Knicks won about half of their games. The emergence of Eddy Curry and David Lee surely helped.</p>
        <p>''Last year, all people were talking about was, 'We're terrible,' '' said Fred Klein, a season-ticket holder since 1960. ''All of a sudden now, we got players.''</p>
        <p>Asked if the beleaguered fan base believed in the Knicks again, Klein said, ''Oh, absolutely.''</p>
        <p>So the Knicks' marketing folks can spend another summer selling hope, if not verifiable success. With one game left, the Knicks are only nine victories better than last season. Only the collapse of the Boston Celtics saved the Knicks from a last-place finish in the Atlantic Division. They will even finish behind the Philadelphia 76ers, who jettisoned their two stars -- Allen Iverson and Chris Webber -- early in the season.</p>
        <p>The Knicks played their Garden finale without Marbury (turf toe), Quentin Richardson (back surgery) and Lee (leg injury). Apropos of their season, the Knicks welcomed back one star (Jamal Crawford) just as they lost another. Curry strained his right hamstring in the first half and did not return. He said he hoped to play in the season finale, tomorrow night at Charlotte.</p>
        <p>Crawford was in uniform for the first time since Feb. 26, the night he was found to have a stress fracture in his right ankle. He made a nominal appearance, to warm cheers, with 30.8 seconds left in the third quarter. He did not touch the ball.</p>
        <p>The fans who stayed until the final buzzer rose and applauded politely.</p>
        <p>''To have them show us that kind of support tonight was a great step moving into next year, knowing that we have their support,'' Lee said.</p>
        <p>If not for late-season injuries to Crawford, Richardson and Lee, the Knicks might have made the playoffs, albeit with a losing record. Apparently, that belief is enough to keep the Garden turnstiles in motion -- even on nights that the Rangers are off.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
