<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Pack Rat Who Supplies the Scenic Illusion</title>
    <meta content="29laferla" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/theater/29laferla.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843600"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">La Ferla, Ruth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Loquasto, Santo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Loquasto, Santo</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E0DB143EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1234" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Pack Rat Who Supplies the Scenic Illusion</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Pack Rat Who Supplies the Scenic Illusion</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RUTH LA FERLA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">La Ferla, Ruth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles theater set designer Santo Loquasto, who currently has three shows running in New York; life, career and philosophy of design described; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SANTO LOQUASTO is canny with a metaphor. In the first half of ''Our Leading Lady,'' Charles Busch's barbed sendup of show business, he framed the stage, a sketchy simulacrum of Ford's Theater in Washington, with a majestic proscenium arch. As the action progressed, that arch shifted position to register the play's ever-shifting perspectives. In the final act, it leaned forlornly against a wall, an eloquent shorthand for the players' thwarted ambitions in the gray hours after Lincoln's assassination.</p>
        <p>''The arch collapsed, and that was meant to send an emotional signal,'' said Mr. Loquasto, who designed the set and for whom such economy of gesture has long been a signature. That migratory arch goes straight to the heart of the play, which closes this weekend. It ''toys with the notion of what theater is,'' said Lynne Meadow, who directed the production at the Manhattan Theater Club, and underscores the show's themes: ''that the essence of theater is illusion; that one fact of performance can have many aspects, like a person.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This month, the designer Santo Loquasto deploys a series of deft conceits in three shows appearing concurrently on the New York stage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SANTO LOQUASTO is canny with a metaphor. In the first half of ''Our Leading Lady,'' Charles Busch's barbed sendup of show business, he framed the stage, a sketchy simulacrum of Ford's Theater in Washington, with a majestic proscenium arch. As the action progressed, that arch shifted position to register the play's ever-shifting perspectives. In the final act, it leaned forlornly against a wall, an eloquent shorthand for the players' thwarted ambitions in the gray hours after Lincoln's assassination.</p>
        <p>''The arch collapsed, and that was meant to send an emotional signal,'' said Mr. Loquasto, who designed the set and for whom such economy of gesture has long been a signature. That migratory arch goes straight to the heart of the play, which closes this weekend. It ''toys with the notion of what theater is,'' said Lynne Meadow, who directed the production at the Manhattan Theater Club, and underscores the show's themes: ''that the essence of theater is illusion; that one fact of performance can have many aspects, like a person.''</p>
        <p>This month, Mr. Loquasto deploys a series of similarly deft conceits in three more shows appearing concurrently on the New York stage. For the Roundabout Theater's revival of the 1990 Craig Lucas romance ''Prelude to a Kiss'' at the American Airlines Theater, for which he created the sets, Mr. Loquasto devised a backdrop of row upon row of SoHo-style factory windows to suggest the bohemia of downtown Manhattan. For ''Inherit the Wind,'' a revival of the 1955 ''monkey trial'' drama at the Lyceum Theater, for which he did both sets and costumes, he recreated a battered courtroom crowded with people in rumpled linens to conjure a small town in turmoil.</p>
        <p>To reinforce the emotional heat of ''110 in the Shade,'' a Roundabout revival of the 1963 musical with songs by Harvey Schmidt and Tom Jones (''The Fantasticks''), for which he also did both sets and costumes, he hung an enormous disc from the ceiling of Studio 54. Depending on how it is lighted and angled, it functions as a moon or, more often, as an implacably brilliant sun.</p>
        <p>The knack for making less say more has established Mr. Loquasto as one of America's foremost stage designers. ''Santo has a great editorial sense,'' said Doug Hughes, the director of ''Inherit the Wind.'' ''Among the battery of props that are all exquisitely chosen, he will recognize during rehearsal weeks that many are superfluous and will happily cut them away.''</p>
        <p>A compact man with close-cropped hair and a salt-and-pepper beard, Mr. Loquasto, 63, combines Zen-like calm with genial self-mockery. Offering a tour of his book-and-bibelot-clotted seven-room apartment on Riverside Drive, he showed none of the flamboyance or bloated self-importance that would betray a more, well, theatrical personality.</p>
        <p>Chiding himself for his incessant shopping, he explained that the playful Greek hunting scene that hangs above his mantel was unearthed during one of his frequent thrifting trips to upstate New York. ''When you shop as part of what you do, it can be deadly,'' he confided.</p>
        <p>An inveterate hunter-gatherer, he nevertheless says he has no trouble sacrificing an acquisitive streak to the requirements of a show. ''Accommodating almost to a fault,'' as he portrays himself, he will also insist that he has no discernible style.</p>
        <p>That point is arguable. It is true, though, that in a career spanning more than four decades, he has glided confidently between the extremes of austerity and clutter. For ''The Cherry Orchard,'' the innovative Andrei Serban production for the Public Theater, he conceived a lyrically white-on-white setting, its spareness relieved by a few sticks of furniture and some spindly trees. In ''American Buffalo'' he conveyed a mood of incipient chaos with a layered, sculptural set built on a dizzying accretion of props.</p>
        <p>His ever-malleable vision has earned him three Tony Awards and 10 nominations, and the allegiance of a few longtime collaborators. ''He has an ability to paint on so many different canvases,'' Ms. Meadow said, ''to bring to life everything from the simple set of 'Inherit the Wind,' to the most incredibly baroque design.''</p>
        <p>A mobile barbecue wheeled onto the stage in ''Prelude to a Kiss'' raises the specter of a rigidly conformist suburbia. In ''Inherit the Wind,'' Mr. Loquasto and Mr. Hughes, the director, filled part of the courtroom with spectators from the audience. ''We thought that would dramatize the idea of a body politic in a few efficient strokes,'' Mr. Hughes explained. ''Some of Santo's most striking ideas are the most simple; that sort of reduction releases power.''</p>
        <p>There are signs of the pack rat in the designer's apartment, where layer upon layer of books, pictures, set models and magazines first overwhelm the eye, then coalesce into a restful whole. Perched on a corner cabinet is a discarded model of a set for ''Faust,'' designed for the Metropolitan Opera. Gathered on a side table are the magazine clippings Mr. Loquasto uses in his research, among them a DKNY jeans advertisement that inspired the hair, makeup and overall mood of ''110 in the Shade.'' Each is arranged against a backdrop of peeling cream-tone walls.</p>
        <p>''I'm somewhat drawn to a dilapidated world,'' Mr. Loquasto acknowledged, ''the re-creation of layers that you find in a place like Rome.'' Years ago, when he first moved in, he simulated the distressed look of age by scraping the walls bare, then just walking away.</p>
        <p>The apartment serves as a depot for assorted cartons, some filled with shoes for one of his myriad projects. ''We load things out of here and have them shipped,'' Mr. Loquasto said, ''so this place becomes more of a way station.''</p>
        <p>Heaped under tables and near the doors, those boxes are evidence of the projects he juggles continually, partly as an outlet for his protean energy, partly out of practical necessity. The need to take on as much work as he can handle is perhaps a remnant of the days when Mr. Loquasto, fresh out of Yale, was forced to take on multiple jobs simultaneously just to pay the bills.</p>
        <p>Hooked on theater growing up in Wilkes Barre, Pa., by the mid-1960s he was designing for the Williamstown Theater Festival, and as early as 1967 he did his first work for American Ballet Theater. After picking up an M.F.A. from Yale in 1969, he joined the New York Shakespeare Festival, then went on to collaborate on theater, film and dance works with thorny mavericks like Twyla Tharp, Woody Allen, Jerome Robbins and Mr. Serban.</p>
        <p>His relationship with Mr. Robbins, who died in 1998, was fraught. ''He was indecisive,'' his point of view vacillating until the 11th hour, Mr. Loquasto recalled. At that stage, the designer had his way by default. ''It was, 'Well, O.K., we'll have to work with what we have,' '' he remembered slyly telling Mr. Robbins.</p>
        <p>Over the years a similarly calculated passivity has helped him cope. Lonny Price, who directed ''110 in the Shade,'' originally asked for a sky drop over the stage, said Mr. Loquasto, who could not convince Mr. Price that such a notion might be overkill. ''It wasn't easy for Lonny to visualize things from a model,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But earlier this month, during technical rehearsals, Mr. Loquasto's vision seemed to have prevailed, his giant sun doubling as an incandescent sky. His battles with Mr. Robbins have taught him to wait.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes,'' he said, ''you have to just let time be your ally.''</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
