<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Derek Walcott</title>
    <meta content="letter.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/books/review/letter.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843536"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Letters"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Walcott, Derek</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Logan, William</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E4D8163EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1118" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Derek Walcott</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Derek Walcott</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor: I'm afraid that William Logan's review of Derek Walcott's ''Selected Poems''(April 8) is shot through within accuracies. For instance, Logan asserts that the poetry Walcott has written since receiving the Nobel Prize in 1992 -- particularly his most recent volume, ''The Prodigal'' (2004) -- is ''haunted by the dissolutions of mortality'' and reads like a ''roll call of the dead''; then Logan cites, as an example, Walcott's ''elegy for Joseph Brodsky'' and quotes the first stanza of ''The Forests of Europe.'' But ''The Forests of Europe'' is neither an example of Walcott's post-Nobel work nor an elegy for Brodsky; the poem was published in ''The Star-Apple Kingdom'' in 1979, some 13 years before Walcott received the Nobel Prize, and some 17 years before Brodsky's death.</p>
        <p>In another instance, Logan asserts that ''the tin-eared poems in island patois have been among Walcott's least successful.'' Then he writes: Walcott's most fluid and achieved work lies in the books from 'Sea Grapes' (1976) through 'The Arkansas Testament' (1987).'' But perhaps the most celebrated poem of that period -- the period</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor: I’m afraid that William Logan’s review of Derek Walcott’s “Selected Poems”(April 8) is shot through within accuracies. For instance, Logan asserts that the poetry Walcott has written since receiving the Nobel Prize in 1992  particularly his most recent volume, “The Prodigal” (2004)  is “haunted by the dissolutions of mortality” and reads like a “roll call of the dead”; then Logan cites, as an example, Walcott’s “elegy for Joseph Brodsky” and quotes the first stanza of “The Forests of Europe.” But “The Forests of Europe” is neither an example of Walcott’s post-Nobel work nor an elegy for Brodsky; the poem was published in “The Star-Apple Kingdom” in 1979, some 13 years before Walcott received the Nobel Prize, and some 17 years before Brodsky’s death.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor: I'm afraid that William Logan's review of Derek Walcott's ''Selected Poems''(April 8) is shot through within accuracies. For instance, Logan asserts that the poetry Walcott has written since receiving the Nobel Prize in 1992 -- particularly his most recent volume, ''The Prodigal'' (2004) -- is ''haunted by the dissolutions of mortality'' and reads like a ''roll call of the dead''; then Logan cites, as an example, Walcott's ''elegy for Joseph Brodsky'' and quotes the first stanza of ''The Forests of Europe.'' But ''The Forests of Europe'' is neither an example of Walcott's post-Nobel work nor an elegy for Brodsky; the poem was published in ''The Star-Apple Kingdom'' in 1979, some 13 years before Walcott received the Nobel Prize, and some 17 years before Brodsky's death.</p>
        <p>In another instance, Logan asserts that ''the tin-eared poems in island patois have been among Walcott's least successful.'' Then he writes: Walcott's most fluid and achieved work lies in the books from 'Sea Grapes' (1976) through 'The Arkansas Testament' (1987).'' But perhaps the most celebrated poem of that period -- the period</p>
        <p>Logan cites as Walcott's best -- is ''The Schooner 'Flight,' '' a long and brilliant poem (also from the ''The Star-Apple Kingdom''), which is written entirely in ''island patois.'' In yet another instance, Logan asserts that ''the rhythms and intonations of English verse were a passport to the elsewhere; but they came with a burden -- the language of the colonial masters was not the one caught in his ear at home.''</p>
        <p>Then, to illustrate his point, Logan quotes from ''A Far Cry From Africa,'' perhaps the greatest poem of Walcott's early period (1948-1960): ''How choose / Between this Africa and the English tongue I love? / Betray them both, or give back what they give?''</p>
        <p>First, anyone with even a cursory knowledge of Walcott's life knows that ''the language of the colonial masters'' was indeed ''the one caught in his ear at home,'' most particularly the language of Shakespeare and the Bible, both of which were read to him as a boy by his mother. Second, and perhaps more important, ''A Far Cry From Africa'' is not a poem concerned, as Logan suggests, with questions of language, but with horrific violence -- the violence of tribal Africans and a ''white child hacked in bed'' on the one hand, and the violence of the colonizing British on the other. While Logan suggests that the poem revolves around the divide within Walcott between his conflicting allegiances to ''island patois'' and to the English language, the divide, as articulated in ''A Far Cry From Africa,'' is demonstrably more profound. It is a divide between England and Africa played out in the larger world, as well as within the very blood of the poet himself.</p>
        <p>''I who am poisoned with the blood of both,'' Walcott writes, ''Where shall I turn, divided to the vein?''</p>
        <p>Logan concludes his review with this observation: ''For more than half a century he has served as our poet of exile -- a man almost without a country  in flight from himself.''</p>
        <p>But for many years now, Walcott has lived the bulk of his days in St. Lucia, the very country in which he was born. I'm afraid that, in this instance, it is evident that Logan has written of matters of which he knows little or nothing.</p>
        <p>JOSEPH CUOMO  Queens</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The compelling authenticity of Derek Walcott's poetry speaks for itself through even the most peevish and befuddled readings. Logan's review of Walcott's ''Selected Poems'' posits the astonishing notion that Walcott is somehow false, presenting an invented persona (shallow, conceited and suspect) corroborated and celebrated by academics who share his agenda. This is a misrepresentation of a poet who explores the conflicted and fragmented places, populations, identities and languages left in the wake of the colonial experience. Logan is a poor reader of Walcott by intent, capacity or both; he reads irony, ambivalence and complexity as deceit, vanity and contrivance.</p>
        <p>Walcott's poems are not just representative of an entire generation's experience of exile -- they comprise, indeed are, that experience. In his work, human beings are made of more than one place. He invented both himself and an entire kind of language, one that incorporates into poetry not only his particular ancestry and tongue, but also those of anyone who has ever felt alienated, bicultural, lost or re-found.</p>
        <p>RACHEL DEWOSKIN  Manhattan</p>
        <p>KIRUN KAPUR  Newburyport, Mass.</p>
        <p>William Logan replies:</p>
        <p>I'm grateful to Joseph Cuomo for reminding me that Joseph Brodsky wasn't among the dead when Walcott wrote ''Forest of Europe.'' I was pursuing a subtler idea that got away from me during editing -- that the poem's elegiac tone is embedded in Walcott's meditation on the belated life that exiles often inhabit. Walcott is uneasy with strong emotion, but in ''Forest of Europe'' (not, as Cuomo has it, ''The Forests of Europe'') he was moved by a familiar sense of displacement. The poem is splendid, not because he grieves prematurely for Brodsky, but because he mourns Brodsky's exile, as he does his own.</p>
        <p>Otherwise, I'm surprised that Cuomo can read prose sentences so badly. If I love Walcott's books from ''Sea Grapes'' through ''The Arkansas Testament,'' that doesn't mean they're free of duff poems, like the one in patois that Cuomo is enamored of. If I say the King's English wasn't caught in Walcott's ear at home, I don't mean in his house -- but all around him, in the streets and the shops. Cuomo has trouble distinguishing a poem's ostensible subject, like the violence in ''A Far Cry From Africa,'' from its theme, Walcott's self-division as a child of both Africa and empire, with the blood of both in his veins. The poet manages to sound like an exile wherever he lives; but mastery of English and immersion in the classics have estranged him from the island of his birth, no matter how often he returns or how long he stays.</p>
        <p>Walcott's conflicts are played out within himself -- his vanities and even his self-pity erode the imperial manner of his verse. Rachel DeWoskin and Kirun Kapur simply deny the flaws are there. I don't think Walcott's ''persona'' is invented -- no, I fear the poet is all too much the man. Walcott has been taken up by academics with no ear for his verse but devout sympathy for his themes, academics who write with just the high-minded, chilling air of words like ''populations'' and ''identities.'' These correspondents, as if fresh from a postcolonial literature class, are uncomfortable with the notion that Walcott might suffer both vanity and ambivalence, might indulge in both conceit and irony; but they're more interested in cleansing his personality than in hearing his complexity.</p>
        <p>Letters</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
