<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinging to Gridiron Hope In Indoor Minor League</title>
    <meta content="29topicnjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/29topicnj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843702"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="INDOOR FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arena Football</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Morris Township (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York/New Jersey Revolution (Arena Football Team)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lehigh Valley Outlawz (Arena Football Team)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Continental Indoor Football League</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mallozzi, Vincent M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06EFD8153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="600" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinging to Gridiron Hope In Indoor Minor League</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Clinging to Gridiron Hope in Indoor Minor League</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VINCENT M. MALLOZZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mallozzi, Vincent M</byline>
      <dateline>MORRIS TOWNSHIP</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scene at Mennen Arena in Morris Township, NJ, described as New York/New Jersey Revolution and Lehigh Valley Outlawz of minor league arena football's Continental Indoor Football League prepare for and play game; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THIRTEEN hours before kickoff last Saturday, Scott Veith walked into the William G. Mennen Sports Arena and began making preparations for a football game between the New York/New Jersey Revolution and the Lehigh Valley Outlawz of the Continental Indoor Football League -- a minor league of arena football.</p>
        <p>Anxiously awaiting the Revolution's first-ever home game, Mr. Veith arrived at 6 a.m. and began rolling extra coats of white paint on each yard line. He fastened white padding around the boards that surround the 50-yard field, taped banners from corporate sponsors to the padding and straightened out thin layers of green carpeting that looked but felt nothing like artificial turf.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>MORRIS TOWNSHIP.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THIRTEEN hours before kickoff last Saturday, Scott Veith walked into the William G. Mennen Sports Arena and began making preparations for a football game between the New York/New Jersey Revolution and the Lehigh Valley Outlawz of the Continental Indoor Football League -- a minor league of arena football.</p>
        <p>Anxiously awaiting the Revolution's first-ever home game, Mr. Veith arrived at 6 a.m. and began rolling extra coats of white paint on each yard line. He fastened white padding around the boards that surround the 50-yard field, taped banners from corporate sponsors to the padding and straightened out thin layers of green carpeting that looked but felt nothing like artificial turf.</p>
        <p>By early afternoon, Mr. Veith was greeting children who had gathered for a birthday party when he bumped into Kevin Hanratty, the Revolution's director of player personnel, player agent and starting quarterback.</p>
        <p>''Hey, Coach,'' Mr. Hanratty said to Mr. Veith.</p>
        <p>Welcome to the minor leagues of minor league football, where coaches like Mr. Veith -- whose day job is as a Y.M.C.A. fitness director -- and players like Mr. Hanratty -- who is studying online for a law degree when he is not studying his playbook -- are wearing as many hard hats as it takes to hang on to a gridiron dream.</p>
        <p>''I would love to climb that football ladder,'' said Mr. Hanratty, 28, a former quarterback at Iona who is in his second year with the Revolution and has negotiated contracts for most of his teammates, players between the ages of 19 and 38 who earn from $100 to $500 a game.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Hanratty and Company, many of whom played at lower-division colleges, the climb is high. The closest rung on the professional ladder is Arena2 football, above that Arena Football and Canadian Football, and then the ultimate step up to the National Football League.</p>
        <p>''I'm probably not going to the N.F.L., but I still want to play at the highest possible level,'' said Benjamin Ford, 24, who played at South Carolina State and plays running back and defensive back and returns kicks for the Revolution. ''Right now, this is the highest level.''</p>
        <p>The Revolution, who were 0-3 heading into last Saturday's clash with the Outlawz, finished 0-10 in 2006, their inaugural season, but every game was on the road. This year, with a home field of their own, players and coaches alike are hoping to fill their 2,500-seat arena with fans.</p>
        <p>''Tonight is huge for the future of our franchise,'' said Mr. Hanratty, already in full uniform two hours before the game. ''We want to play well so that these fans keep coming back.''</p>
        <p>A crowd of about 500 eventually settled in their seats, three of those filled by Doug Del Tufo, a lawyer, and his sons, Jordan, 16, and Brett, 9, who live in Succasunna. Mr. Del Tufo said he spent $12 apiece for tickets and happily noted that parking was free.</p>
        <p>''This is fun and it's affordable,'' he said. ''Win or lose, we're going to support the Revolution.''</p>
        <p>Next to the Del Tufos sat the former New York Giants running back Lee Rouson and his 9-year-old son, Jesse, who live in Flanders. Both families sat in front of the Outlawz bench, where the team owner, Jim DePaul, taped the wrists and ankles of many of his players before the game.</p>
        <p>Although Lehigh Valley won, 46-29, the Del Tufos and many other fans rushed onto the field afterward to greet their new hometown heroes.</p>
        <p>''The good news for us and for our fans,'' Mr. Veith said, ''is that the only way to go from here is up.''</p>
        <p>INDOOR FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
