<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rethinking the Path to Prestige</title>
    <meta content="29towns" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/29towns.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843897"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OUR TOWNS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Our Towns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut/New Haven</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Admissions Standards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Admissions Standards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Haven (Conn)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Yale University</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E2DE133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="892" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rethinking the Path to Prestige</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rethinking the Path to Prestige</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER APPLEBOME</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Applebome, Peter</byline>
      <dateline>NEW HAVEN</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Richard C. Levin, president of Yale University, has a problem: too many applicants, too few slots.</p>
        <p>Of course, this is a problem that defines success in a process in which the biggest rewards go to the universities that attract and then reject the most applicants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Yale University is considering adding two new residential colleges to the 12 existing ones, increasing each class by more than 10 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Richard C. Levin, president of Yale University, has a problem: too many applicants, too few slots.</p>
        <p>Of course, this is a problem that defines success in a process in which the biggest rewards go to the universities that attract and then reject the most applicants.</p>
        <p>But as this year's version of the admissions demolition derby winds down for exhausted high school seniors, two interesting issues are posed by a proposal of Dr. Levin's to add two new undergraduate residential colleges at Yale: Is this a good idea for Yale? And is his larger issue his problem or ours?</p>
        <p>If any place is on safe footing in the admissions arms race, it's Yale, which last year beat out its competitors by accepting only 9 percent of applicants. (This year the rate grew to 9.6 percent as applications dropped, perhaps because some high school seniors saw the futility of applying.) So it's hard to look from afar at the proposal by Dr. Levin and not think, Why aren't others doing this? His plan would add two new residential colleges to the 12 existing ones, which would increase each class by about 150 students, or more than 10 percent.</p>
        <p>As he said in an interview, after Yale expanded to its current size in the 1960s, there were roughly 4,000 to 5,000 applicants a year for 1,300 positions in the freshman class. The size of the freshman class has remained about the same, but now there are some 20,000 applicants, including a growing number of international ones, plus all the other desired niches of minority students, athletes, children of alums and the rest.</p>
        <p>''Expansion could help relieve those pressures and create more opportunities for students who are just ordinary, extremely brilliant and talented students who don't have any of those other connections,'' Dr. Levin said. ''We have astonishing educational resources here. If we can educate more students and give them exposure to the opportunities here, I think we can make an even more substantial contribution to the nation and the world.''</p>
        <p>The proposal is just that, and a decision is likely to come near the end of the year. If expansion is approved, chances are that construction on the two colleges would begin in 2011 and be completed in 2013.</p>
        <p>Adding 150 slots for 20,000 applicants goes only so far, but given the ever-expanding universe of applicants, the idea has an undeniable logic. Princeton, too, is completing an expansion that will take its undergraduate enrollment to 5,200 in 2012, from 4,700 in 2005. The issue is particularly salient at state flagship institutions.</p>
        <p>But making space for more students is no small thing; each of the colleges at Yale would cost $200 million to build, plus other costs for educating the new students. People have understandable worries about changing the intimate culture at Yale. Students say the new colleges might have the feeling of being too far from the heart of the campus. And, perhaps not surprisingly, students who won the admissions game seem focused on protecting their place in the pecking order. ''I don't see any reason not to just keep it selective,'' said Joanna Boyle, a senior from Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Sigh. Which brings us back to the broader questions worth asking. Last week, in one of those ''you can't make it up'' episodes, Marilee Jones, the admissions dean at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, who had been one of the strongest voices for toning down the college hysteria, resigned after admitting she had fabricated her own education credentials.</p>
        <p>BUT high school counselors and admissions experts who aren't invested in the game say there really is a backlash building against the notions that a college's ranking or status is a proxy for educational quality, and that teenagers should spend their high school years in a frenzy of résumé building, the better to get into the college most esteemed by guidebook editors and readers.</p>
        <p>So, most of them agree that if Yale can make it work, getting a few more people into the university is almost certainly a good thing. But convincing a lot more people that there's life beyond the 20 or so colleges on the standard striver's shopping list would be even better.</p>
        <p>Even Dr. Levin says there's something perverse about the current system, where ''prestige and reputation tend to depend on how many students you reject.''</p>
        <p>Lloyd Thacker, a former high school guidance counselor who founded the Education Conservancy, a nonprofit group that has become a persistent voice against admissions hysteria, criticizes what he calls ''driving under the influence of rankings.''</p>
        <p>The question now, he says, is who will take the lead in changing the way the game is played. A few years back it was a fringe question. Now it's one that a lot of people within education, not just high school seniors with tread marks on their backs, are asking -- even if no one has figured out what to do about it.</p>
        <p>''Admissions professionals are engaging in a lot of soul-searching about what we're doing,'' said Barmak Nassirian, a spokesman for the American Association of Collegiate Registrars and Admissions Officers. ''People realize the system as a whole is getting out of hand. They're aware we have set up a system in which rational behavior on the part of each player is contributing to a major national act of irrationality.''</p>
        <p>OUR TOWNS E-mail: peappl@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: peappl@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
