<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rangers' Plan of Attack Is to Keep Thinking Defense First</title>
    <meta content="29rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/sports/hockey/29rangers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843956"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Buffalo Sabres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Jagr, Jaromir</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Zinser, Lynn</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3DD133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="700" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rangers' Plan of Attack Is to Keep Thinking Defense First</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rangers’ Plan of Attack Is to Keep Thinking Defense First</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinser, Lynn</byline>
      <dateline>GREENBURGH, N.Y., April 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is not the prettiest style of play, not exactly what offensively skilled players like Jaromir Jagr would prefer if they had a choice, but the Rangers spent two periods of Game 2 against Buffalo showing why it has become their style.</p>
        <p>Now the Rangers say they have to stick to their lockdown defensive strategy -- despite trailing by two games to none in their second-round playoff series after a 3-2 loss Friday -- and just do it better Sunday in Game 3 at Madison Square Garden.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Rangers say they have to stick to their lockdown defensive strategy  despite trailing by two games to none in their second-round playoff series after a 3-2 loss Friday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is not the prettiest style of play, not exactly what offensively skilled players like Jaromir Jagr would prefer if they had a choice, but the Rangers spent two periods of Game 2 against Buffalo showing why it has become their style.</p>
        <p>Now the Rangers say they have to stick to their lockdown defensive strategy -- despite trailing by two games to none in their second-round playoff series after a 3-2 loss Friday -- and just do it better Sunday in Game 3 at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>''It's the way we need to play against them and, more importantly, it's the way we need to play to be successful regardless of who we are playing,'' center Matt Cullen said.</p>
        <p>''We've sort of cemented that in the last part of the year and in the first round and even last night. That's the way we have to play. That's our style of hockey.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers returned home for a short, simple practice Saturday that was designed mostly to emphasize what Coach Tom Renney believes they can do well against Buffalo.</p>
        <p>The Rangers' strategy is the hockey equivalent of downshifting a sports car to win a race on a hilly course. The Rangers would love to be charging ahead, but their first priority is to contain the speedy Sabres.</p>
        <p>So when the Rangers return home to try to salvage this series, they will fall back on what they learned during their push for a playoff berth: The glamour of scoring must take a back seat. The forechecking must be less pronounced. Protecting the neutral zone will be crucial because that is where they can slow Buffalo's formidable forwards.</p>
        <p>''Playoff time, there's always more concentration on defensive hockey,'' center Michael Nylander said.</p>
        <p>''It's not what you get, it's what you give up most of the time. We have to make sure we don't give up too much and take what's there, capitalize when you have chances.''</p>
        <p>Nylander, who centers a line with Jagr and Marcel Hossa, has seen Buffalo use a similar strategy. The Sabres have countered the Rangers' top line with a tight five-man, defense-first approach, giving up offense to frustrate the potentially explosive Jagr.</p>
        <p>It was a chess match that the Rangers were winning for much of Game 2. They used goals on two power plays -- and gave up one on a Sabres power play -- to take a 2-1 lead into the third.</p>
        <p>It was their own hiccup, a turnover by defenseman Marek Malik, that allowed the Sabres to tie the score. And Buffalo's winning goal came after another stumble, when the dangerous Thomas Vanek was left unchecked in front of the goal.</p>
        <p>''Especially when the games are so tight, every mistake can cost you the game,'' Rangers goaltender Henrik Lundqvist said. ''We just have to limit the mistakes, and we're in good shape. We created chances. We played well. We should feel confident.''</p>
        <p>Aside from turning games into tightrope walks that hinge on the smallest mistakes, the other downside of leaning heavily on this style of play has been its effect on one of the Rangers' biggest weapons, forward Sean Avery.</p>
        <p>Avery has not had a point against Buffalo and has failed to rattle the Sabres with his usual no-holds-barred, straight-ahead approach.</p>
        <p>''There is a balance there,'' Renney said. ''It's the pressure-contain question that you ask yourself based on where the puck is put and what type of quality possession your opponent has.</p>
        <p>''The conclusion that I've drawn is that there is a good time to do both. We still want to push the envelope. We still want to go after these guys as much as we possibly can but be sensible about when we do that.''</p>
        <p>In Game 3, with the home-ice advantage, the Rangers will find out if downshifting will save them.</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>Tom Renney said that defenseman Michal Rozsival, who took another shot to his injured left leg in Game 2, would be evaluated Sunday morning to see if he can play Game 3. Rozsival, the Rangers' top defenseman, did not practice Saturday.  Sabres Coach Lindy Ruff said that he may bench forward Maxim Afinogenov, who has been largely unproductive against the Rangers.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
