<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How YouTube Helped LisaNova Start HerCareer</title>
    <meta content="29wall" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/arts/television/29wall.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843606"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Youtube</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wallenstein, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Donovan, Lisa</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Mad TV (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">YouTube.com</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07EFDB143EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1111" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How YouTube Helped LisaNova Start HerCareer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">How YouTube Helped LisaNova Start HerCareer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW WALLENSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wallenstein, Andrew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles comic actress and writer Lisa Donovan, who has crossed over from amateur Internet productions to network television; beginnings on YouTube, with self-produced vignettes, and adjustment to joining Mad TV cast discussed; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Lisa Donovan shoots a video, the contents of her Hollywood apartment tend to get rearranged. One recent weekday afternoon, the couch had been moved over near the front door. Seemingly every lighting fixture in the apartment had been strategically positioned on the floor, lampshades set aside to allow naked bulbs to illuminate the scene. A microphone was propped up on Ms. Donovan's purse.</p>
        <p>She and her brother, Ben Donovan, took seats on folding chairs where the couch once was, rehearsing their lines for a skit in which they play rival campaigners for presidential candidates (she for Hillary Rodham Clinton, he for Rudolph W. Giuliani). Ms. Donovan's boyfriend, Dan Zappin, set up his camcorder. Just one more adjustment was necessary before he could shoot: he raced into the kitchen and unplugged the refrigerator to silence its hum.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A rare crossover from Web amateur to professional television comedian.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Lisa Donovan shoots a video, the contents of her Hollywood apartment tend to get rearranged. One recent weekday afternoon, the couch had been moved over near the front door. Seemingly every lighting fixture in the apartment had been strategically positioned on the floor, lampshades set aside to allow naked bulbs to illuminate the scene. A microphone was propped up on Ms. Donovan's purse.</p>
        <p>She and her brother, Ben Donovan, took seats on folding chairs where the couch once was, rehearsing their lines for a skit in which they play rival campaigners for presidential candidates (she for Hillary Rodham Clinton, he for Rudolph W. Giuliani). Ms. Donovan's boyfriend, Dan Zappin, set up his camcorder. Just one more adjustment was necessary before he could shoot: he raced into the kitchen and unplugged the refrigerator to silence its hum.</p>
        <p>This production might be just another of Ms. Donovan's YouTube submissions were it not for the presence of a third performer. Jordan Peele, a cast member from the Fox sketch-comedy series ''Mad TV,'' sat next to her, playing a Barack Obama supporter. And their scene was intended not for YouTube but for Fox, which hired Ms. Donovan in February to join the cast for multiple episodes.</p>
        <p>Ms. Donovan, 26, is making a rare crossover from the ranks of amateur Internet production to professional television. It is not an easy transition, but as the relocation of ''Mad TV'' to her apartment attests, the show is willing to play by her rules, too.</p>
        <p>''The idea of dressing up, having fun and acting every week was really appealing,'' Ms. Donovan said. ''I was already doing the poor man's version of it.''</p>
        <p>This time last year, Ms. Donovan was just another struggling actress in Hollywood. She had moved to California four years ago from Scarsdale, N.Y., but never landed an agent or a role. She found more success working in corporate and television production, learning the basics of shooting and editing.</p>
        <p>She put those skills to work on YouTube, where she has carved out a distinct identity under her nom de Internet, LisaNova. She has uploaded more than 30 comedic videos in the last year, ranging from pop-culture commentaries to absurdist riffs, each typically garnering hundreds of thousands of views. Her most popular video, a Britney Spears parody in which she transforms herself into Teenie Weenie, a vacuous pop starlet of her own creation, has drawn more than two million views.</p>
        <p>When she began posting videos, Ms. Donovan regarded YouTube merely as a creative outlet. But to her surprise, phone calls and e-mail messages from entertainment companies began pouring in offering money-making opportunities. ''In no way did I think this was going to be like a career-changing thing,'' she said.</p>
        <p>One of those calls came from Nicole Garcia, casting director for ''Mad TV.'' When a friend of Mrs. Garcia's sent her a link to Ms. Donovan's YouTube work, she realized she had already encountered the performer in an audition for a different show, but had passed.</p>
        <p>Now Mrs. Garcia saw a raw talent with comic timing and writing skills who happened to be fetching enough to pull off imitations of Keira Knightley and Salma Hayek. She suspected that Ms. Donovan had the versatility to withstand the rigors of the ''Mad TV'' audition process, which requires creating three original characters, as well as three celebrity impressions of the actor's choice.</p>
        <p>Ms. Donovan's crossover is not without precedent. ''Saturday Night Live'' hired a current cast member, Andy Samberg, on the strength of his work for the Lonely Island, a collective that produced online videos in which he starred. MTV gave Andy Milonakis a show after he was discovered online by the ABC late-night host Jimmy Kimmel, who is an executive producer of Mr. Milonakis's MTV2 series.</p>
        <p>But Mrs. Garcia also realized Ms. Donovan might invite skepticism from the tight-knit ''Mad TV'' creative team, most of whom were groomed in the same improv-comedy circles. ''When you can't say 'I'm a member of the Groundlings' or Second City and you're this person coming from complete obscurity, that's a challenge,'' Mrs. Garcia said. ''I think YouTube created this perception of her as some kind of stunt that wasn't serious.''</p>
        <p>But Ms. Donovan excelled in several rounds of auditions. And instead of holding her back, her YouTube pedigree attracted interest from several other networks, said her lawyer, Matthew Sugarman. That demand pushed the show to hire her.</p>
        <p>Dick Blasucci, an executive producer of ''Mad TV,'' said, ''I think she is that talented -- that it was nice that we got her on the air first. She did have a lot of heat behind her from YouTube.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Donovan did not get time to ease into her new surroundings. In her first week on the job, she was cast in a sketch that required her to perform in front of a studio audience. She played Ms. Hayek as a guest on a send-up of ''The Ellen DeGeneres Show,'' spoofing the actress's bubbly personality and Mexican accent. ''The first sketch we threw her into was the total opposite of what she does,'' Mr. Blasucci said, referring to the presence of the audience. ''But she did a great job.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Blasucci said he also wanted to play to Ms. Donovan's strengths with self-produced vignettes. Which brings her back to the apartment where she typically shoots her YouTube material. Mr. Peele, who is in his fourth season on ''Mad TV,'' said he enjoyed shooting outside the studio.</p>
        <p>''We rarely get the sort of freedom to produce on our own terms, so this is a nice change of pace,'' said Mr. Peele, who collaborated on the script with Ms. Donovan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blasucci said he was increasingly willing to unleash his cast for segments without the multicamera setup that has been de rigueur for sketch comedy going back to the 1970s. ''Mad TV'' even recently held a contest inviting viewers to send in videos of their own skits.</p>
        <p>''It's nice to let them improvise without worrying about taking a van full of producers with them,'' Mr. Blasucci said of the show's cast members. ''I think our audience likes that grittiness, that guerrilla look.''</p>
        <p>In June, ''Mad TV'' will review the cast roster to determine who will return. In the meantime, Ms. Donovan plans to return to YouTube and continue producing her own work. ''When you're on 'Mad TV,' to get your own sketch done is a hard thing,'' she said. ''Here it's very impulsive. I have an idea, I call two people and we shoot it. You can't do that on a show. I like being in control of it, and I want to continue to do that.''</p>
        <p>TELEVISION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
