<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Document Dispute at Center of Wolfowitz Case</title>
    <meta content="29wolfowitz" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/washington/29wolfowitz.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843906"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Bank</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weisman, Steven R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wolfowitz, Paul D (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riza, Shaha Ali</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">World Bank</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wolfowitz, Paul D</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E1DE133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="635" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Document Dispute at Center of Wolfowitz Case</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Document Dispute at Center of Wolfowitz Case</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN R. WEISMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weisman, Steven R</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>World Bank documents on Pres Paul Wolfowitz's handling of transfer, promotion and salary of his companion Shaha Ali Riza are subject to conflicting interpretations; Wolfowitz is expected to claim documents show he acted on advice of bank's ethics committee to work out fair agreement; committee of bank's board is circulating document indicating Wolfowitz violated bank rules and ethical standards (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Arriving as president of the World Bank in the summer of 2005, Paul D. Wolfowitz told colleagues that he was eager to tackle poverty in Africa and corruption in aid. But almost immediately he became consumed by frustrating negotiations with bank officials over the status of his companion, an employee at the bank, documents released this month show.</p>
        <p>Now these documents are at the center of the World Bank's inquiry into his conduct and Mr. Wolfowitz's defense, both of which will be presented at the World Bank's board of directors on Monday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Instead of offering definitive answers on Paul D. Wolfowitz’s conduct as head of the World Bank, documents have become a matter of conflicting interpretations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Arriving as president of the World Bank in the summer of 2005, Paul D. Wolfowitz told colleagues that he was eager to tackle poverty in Africa and corruption in aid. But almost immediately he became consumed by frustrating negotiations with bank officials over the status of his companion, an employee at the bank, documents released this month show.</p>
        <p>Now these documents are at the center of the World Bank's inquiry into his conduct and Mr. Wolfowitz's defense, both of which will be presented at the World Bank's board of directors on Monday.</p>
        <p>Instead of offering definitive answers on Mr. Wolfowitz's conduct, however, the documents on the handling of the transfer, promotion and salary of Shaha Ali Riza, Mr. Wolfowitz's companion, have become a matter of conflicting interpretations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolfowitz and his lawyer, Robert S. Bennett, are expected to say that the documents back their argument that in handling Ms. Riza's pay raise, promotion and transfer, Mr. Wolfowitz ''acted on the advice of the board's ethics committee to work out an agreement'' fair to her and in compliance with bank rules.</p>
        <p>But a committee of the bank's board looking into the situation is circulating a document indicating that, after he got authorization to handle the matter, Mr. Wolfowitz appears to have violated bank rules and ethical standards of his own employment contract by granting her an outsize pay raise and a major promotion.</p>
        <p>On Monday, board members are expected to ask him what criteria he used in granting the salary increase, why he apparently did not clear the specifics with others and why he allowed, or directed, his aides to spread what they say was a falsehood, namely that the ethics committee had approved the salary.</p>
        <p>Some time in the coming week, the 24-member board may ask for Mr. Wolfowitz's resignation, declare a loss of confidence in his leadership or do nothing in the hope that negotiations with the Bush administration can bring about a voluntary resignation. Few doubt the board's determination to push him out.</p>
        <p>The documents do show that Mr. Wolfowitz in 2005 alerted bank officials to the potential conflict of interest posed by his relationship with Ms. Riza and that he had sought to recuse himself from discussions about how to resolve it.</p>
        <p>When an anonymous whistle-blower complained about the salary increase in early 2006, Ad Melkert, the chairman of the bank's ethics committee, said in a letter on Feb. 28 that the complaint did not warrant ''any further review by the committee.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bennett is expected to argue that Mr. Wolfowitz's actions were in accordance with advice by ethics officials and were subsequently cleared by these same officials. This view is endorsed by many who defend Mr. Wolfowitz.</p>
        <p>''The initial decision on Ms. Riza's salary was reviewed in 2005 and again in 2006,'' said Ruth Wedgwood, an expert in international law and diplomacy and a longtime acquaintance of Mr. Wolfowitz. ''This is a case of what lawyers call 'asked and answered.' Why is it being brought up now?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Melkert declined requests for interviews, but he issued a statement 10 days ago saying that he approved Mr. Wolfowitz's actions in 2005 without knowing about the salary package and that in 2006 he had no authority to reopen it as an ethics matter. ''At no time did Mr. Wolfowitz or anyone else in bank management disclose to the ethics committee the terms and conditions of the external assignment,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Xavier Coll, a vice president for human resources, was the official directed by Mr. Wolfowitz to give Ms. Riza her pay and promotion. He also declined a request for an interview, but an official close to him said Mr. Coll was uneasy about the raise in 2005 and did not formally approve it even while letting it go through.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
