<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tell Them Seth Sent You</title>
    <meta content="29weekend" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/travel/29weekend.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070513T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843586"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEEKEND IN NEW YORK | SPEAKEASIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prohibition Era (1920-1933)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kugel, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EED6173EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tell Them Seth Sent You</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tell Them Seth Sent You</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH KUGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kugel, Seth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Seth Kugel Weekend in New York column offers tour of former speakeasies; list; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON April 4, 1929, nine parched years into Prohibition, New York City's police commissioner, Grover Aloysius Whalen, told a crowd at the Rotary Club in Manhattan that there were a whopping 32,000 speakeasies peddling forbidden hooch in New York City.</p>
        <p>That was one for about every 215 New Yorkers (including children), and those were just the ones the police had documented. Ten days later, The New York Times called speakeasies -- which it also called ''resorts'' -- ''one of the outstanding social institutions of New York.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Spend a weekend visiting the sites of former “resorts” in a city where Prohibition never really caught on.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON April 4, 1929, nine parched years into Prohibition, New York City's police commissioner, Grover Aloysius Whalen, told a crowd at the Rotary Club in Manhattan that there were a whopping 32,000 speakeasies peddling forbidden hooch in New York City.</p>
        <p>That was one for about every 215 New Yorkers (including children), and those were just the ones the police had documented. Ten days later, The New York Times called speakeasies -- which it also called ''resorts'' -- ''one of the outstanding social institutions of New York.''</p>
        <p>In case you couldn't tell, Prohibition never really caught on here.</p>
        <p>Want to spend a weekend visiting the sites of former speakeasies? It's not hard, given the sheer number. The building housing the grilled-cheese purveyor Say Cheese in Hell's Kitchen? Check. The parking lot at 100 Bayard Street in Chinatown? Check. But you want the ones that are still slinging the sauce to this day.</p>
        <p>Though the expensive (and jacket-required) ''21'' Club may be the most famous, what with its secret wine cellar and storied clientele and all, the award for coolest history goes to Onieal's Grand Street, whose predecessor was connected by a secret tunnel to the old Police Headquarters across the street. The tunnel was filled in (they say), but the cellar's stone walls and the barroom's carved-wood ceiling -- said to have been imported from Venice in 1875 -- has been left alone. (More recent history: Onieal's was the location for Scout Bar on ''Sex in the City.'')</p>
        <p>Fanelli Cafe in SoHo still has its pressed-tin ceiling, old hanging light fixtures and the Neolithic neon sign that makes the place seem like a diner, not a bar and restaurant. (That was probably not an accident: serving drinks in teacups was a popular tactic in the time of temperance.) The walls are decorated with black-and-white photos of scrawny and venerable pugilists and liquor licenses that date to 1879. Behind the bar, the pantry doors lead to what was a hush-hush back room; the bartenders use it these days to count their tips.</p>
        <p>Normally, you shouldn't do a speakeasy tour without visiting Chumley's, a beer-drinking, burger-eating place with a literary history (John Steinbeck and F. Scott Fitzgerald were customers). It maintains its 1920s anonymity in part because it doesn't have a sign, and in part because it's buried in the labyrinth of confusing West Village streets. But part of a wall collapsed on April 5, and rebuilding is going on. The manager, Gina Ruiz, said that it is expected to reopen by June 1.</p>
        <p>Midtown had a heck of a lot of speakeasies back when, and flipping through the newspapers of the day, you'd have noticed a marketing nightmare: people were always showing up dead in them. That is no longer a problem. But since most of Midtown has been rebuilt over the decades, finding a former speakeasy could be.</p>
        <p>Here's one: Flute Bar in Midtown sits in the former underground home of the Club Intyme, run by the well-known nightclub hostess Texas Guinan. The place doesn't quite have the same charm as in those days, when Tex popularized the phrase ''Hello, sucker.'' (One time, when asked in court, she defined sucker as ''pal.'') Though Flute Bar's attempts to dress itself up are a bit off -- those empty Champagne bottles lining the ceiling edge toward dorm-room chic -- it does have a great Champagne list and a lot of history.</p>
        <p>If you really want to go back in time, try Bill's Gay Nineties. Though it doesn't actively hide its location, it is still, in a way, a latter-day speakeasy, not listed in some of the major dining and nightlife guides (not Zagat, not Time Out, not Shecky's).</p>
        <p>But lots of people know about the place, which you might call ''retro retro.'' It opened during Prohibition as a tribute to the 1890s, which, in those days, must have seemed gloriously boozy. Through the ancient swinging doors, and past your gracious, storytelling host, Aldo Leone (the 83-year-old nephew of Mama Leone), is the cozy Silver Dollar Bar. It's open very night except Sunday. On weekends starting at 8:30 p.m., a piano player rouses the sometimes startlingly raucous crowd with sing-along tunes that on a recent night ranged from ''Don't Cry for Me Argentina'' to the Prohibition-era ''Carolina in the Morning.''</p>
        <p>The walls are thick with photos, including those of athletes of yore (boxers from the 1890s) and getting-toward-yore (Wade Boggs and Roger Clemens in Red Sox uniforms -- wrong '90s). There are a dining room upstairs and a private party room up from that, but the action is in the bar, where the full menu (try the crab cakes) is served, too.</p>
        <p>One person who probably did not patronize the place was William M. Bennett, who in 1929 ran in the Republican mayoral primary as a dry candidate. One of his campaign promises was that he would close a speakeasy that sat ''in the shadow of Police Headquarters'' -- very possibly Onieal's predecessor -- along with what he estimated were 100,000 speakeasies in the city.</p>
        <p>His threat did not go over well. He lost the nomination to a wet candidate named Fiorello H. La Guardia, 62,894 to 17,100. Which might explain why your flight to New York will not be landing in Bennett Airport, and why you can have a drink at the bar upon arrival.</p>
        <p>PASSWORDS AND A BOOZY PAST</p>
        <p>Bill's Gay Nineties, 57 East 54th Street (between Park and Madison Avenues), (212) 355-0243; www.billsnyc.com.  Chumley's, 86 Bedford Street (Barrow and Grove Street), West Village, (212) 675-4449.  Fanelli Cafe, 94 Prince Street (Mercer Street), SoHo; (212) 226-9412; www.fanellicafe.com.  Flute Bar, 205 West 54th Street (Broadway and Seventh Avenue), Midtown, (212) 265-5169; www.flutebar.com.  Onieal's Grand Street, 174 Grand Street (Mulberry and Lafayette Streets), NoLIta, (212) 941-9119; www.onieals.com.  ''21'' Club, 21 West 52nd Street (Fifth and Sixth Avenues), Midtown, (212) 582-7200; www.21club.com.</p>
        <p>WEEKEND IN NEW YORK | SPEAKEASIES</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 13, 2007, Sunday  The Weekend in New York column on April 29 about former speakeasies referred incorrectly to the attention that one bar, Bill's Gay Nineties, has received from guidebooks. It is included in the Zagat New York City night life guide; it has not been overlooked by Zagat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 13, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>The Weekend in New York column on April 29 about former speakeasies referred incorrectly to the attention that one bar, Bill's Gay Nineties, has received from guidebooks. It is included in the Zagat New York City night life guide; it has not been overlooked by Zagat.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
