<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Asks Florida Graduates To Back Immigration Change</title>
    <meta content="29bush" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/washington/29bush.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843892"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Illegal Immigrants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Dade College</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodnough, Abby</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Illegal Immigrants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E3DE133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="530" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Asks Florida Graduates To Back Immigration Change</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bush Asks Florida Graduates to Back Immigration Change</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY GOODNOUGH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodnough, Abby</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, April 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush, in speech to mostly Hispanic graduates of Miami Dade College, presses for overhaul of immigration law; urges students to join national debate on immigration policy (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush used a speech to mostly Hispanic graduates of Miami Dade College on Saturday to press for an overhaul of immigration law, calling for changes that ''resolve the status of those who are already here without amnesty, and without animosity.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush urged the 1,500 students, many of whom were born in other countries, to join the national debate on immigration policy, saying they ''see every day the values of hard work and family and faith that immigrants bring'' and so should make their voices heard.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At a speech to mostly Hispanic graduates of Miami Dade College on Saturday, President Bush pressed for an overhaul of immigration law.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush used a speech to mostly Hispanic graduates of Miami Dade College on Saturday to press for an overhaul of immigration law, calling for changes that ''resolve the status of those who are already here without amnesty, and without animosity.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush urged the 1,500 students, many of whom were born in other countries, to join the national debate on immigration policy, saying they ''see every day the values of hard work and family and faith that immigrants bring'' and so should make their voices heard.</p>
        <p>Nearly 80 percent of graduates at the college's campus in Kendall, where Mr. Bush spoke, are Hispanic; many are Cuban-American. Mr. Bush got a standing ovation and fervent applause, even as hundreds of protesters waved signs along the perimeter of the suburban campus opposing the war and calling for the president's impeachment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's younger brother, former Gov. Jeb Bush, came to hear him speak, along with Senator Mel Martinez, Republican of Florida, and several Cuban-American members of the state's Congressional delegation.</p>
        <p>Earlier in the day, Mr. Bush discussed immigration in his weekly radio address, calling on Congress to reach agreement on the ''critical challenge'' of improving immigration laws. Administration officials estimate that 12 million illegal immigrants are in the United States, and that the number has been growing by an average of 400,000 a year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush is trying to bring both parties together on immigration legislation, even as he is fighting with Democrats over Iraq. He wants to create a temporary worker program and a way for some illegal immigrants already here to legalize their status, while stepping up border patrol.</p>
        <p>''We need a system where our laws are respected,'' Mr. Bush told the graduates. ''We need a system that meets the legitimate needs of our economy. And we need a system that treats people with dignity and helps newcomers assimilate into our society.</p>
        <p>''We must address all elements of this problem together, or none of them will be solved at all. And we must do it in a way that learns from the mistakes that caused previous reforms to fail.''</p>
        <p>Miami Dade is the largest community college in the nation, and only the second community college where a sitting president has given a commencement address. Christopher Miles, president of the student government association at the Kendall campus, told Mr. Bush the school was nicknamed ''Democracy's College,'' and said more than half the graduates were the first in their families to enter higher education.</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Bush received the warmest of welcomes, some faculty members wore green and white ribbons on their robes to advocate an end to the war.</p>
        <p>Before Mr. Bush spoke, the names of every nation that the graduates hailed from were announced, with Cuba, Colombia, Nicaragua and Venezuela drawing some of the heartiest cheers.</p>
        <p>As he has often done when visiting Miami, Mr. Bush criticized Cuba, where he said ''the opportunity to participate in an open debate does not exist.'' He also alluded to Fidel Castro's recent illness, saying the day is nearing when ''the light of liberty will shine'' on Cuba.</p>
        <p>''The reign of every tyrant comes to an end,'' Mr. Bush said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
