<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Environmental Group to Preserve Estate</title>
    <meta content="29updateliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/29updateli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843670"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="UPDATE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Scully Estate (Islip, NY)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Suffolk County (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Islip (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seatuck Environmental Assn</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Suffolk County Greenways Environmental Interpretive Center</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E2DB153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="425" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Environmental Group to Preserve Estate</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Environmental Group to Preserve Estate</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Seatuck Environmental Assn signs contract with Suffolk County to manage and preserve Scully Estate in Islip, NY; estate will become Suffolk County Greenways Environmental Interpretive Center; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Seatuck Environmental Association, a nonprofit group that promotes the conservation of Long Island wildlife, has signed a contract with Suffolk County to manage and preserve the Scully Estate, one of Long Island's more unusual residences.</p>
        <p>The group's executive director, Enrico G. Nardone, will become the caretaker of the long private but soon to be public estate, which is in Islip near Great South Bay and adjacent to the Seatuck National Wildlife Refuge. The Seatuck group has been operating from temporary offices in Bay Shore since the summer of 2002.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Seatuck Environmental Association, a nonprofit group that promotes the conservation of Long Island wildlife, has signed a contract with Suffolk County to manage and preserve the Scully Estate, one of Long Island’s more unusual residences.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Seatuck Environmental Association, a nonprofit group that promotes the conservation of Long Island wildlife, has signed a contract with Suffolk County to manage and preserve the Scully Estate, one of Long Island's more unusual residences.</p>
        <p>The group's executive director, Enrico G. Nardone, will become the caretaker of the long private but soon to be public estate, which is in Islip near Great South Bay and adjacent to the Seatuck National Wildlife Refuge. The Seatuck group has been operating from temporary offices in Bay Shore since the summer of 2002.</p>
        <p>Grosvenor Atterbury, the architect of Forest Hills Gardens in Queens and the American Wing of the Metropolitan Museum of Art in Manhattan, designed the whimsical yet imposing Scully Estate, a 27-room turreted country estate house. It was built in 1917.</p>
        <p>Suffolk County bought the house and its 70 surrounding acres of woods, streams and saltwater wetlands from the National Audubon Society for $4 million in June 2004. The land purchase was one of the largest ever by the county in western Suffolk.</p>
        <p>The estate will become the Suffolk County Greenways Environmental Interpretive Center. The Seatuck group will run the center's environmental education programs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nardone said he hoped the estate house would be open to the public by next spring. He said boardwalks and observation platforms were planned to accommodate visitors to the grounds, which he hoped would be open as early as this summer. ''The more public the better,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In recent months the county has replaced windows broken by vandals and made other repairs, Mr. Nardone said.</p>
        <p>County Legislator Cameron Alden, a Republican from Islip, first proposed using the estate for a county-sponsored educational and interpretive center. The Legislature approved the plan unanimously in 2004.</p>
        <p>The estate's new use fulfills the wishes of the former owner, Hathaway Weekes Scully. She donated the property to the National Audubon Society in 1968 with a request that it become a public wildlife sanctuary and nature center.</p>
        <p>The Seatuck Environmental Association, a 300-member group, sought unsuccessfully several years ago to open an environmental center in Twyford, a manor house owned by the group's founder, Charles D. Webster, and located in the 196-acre Seatuck National Wildlife Refuge. The United States Fish and Wildlife Service, the refuge manager, evicted the group from an outbuilding it occupied at the refuge and demolished the house over its protests in 2003, five years after Mr. Webster's death.</p>
        <p>The service said the 150-year-old house and surrounding gardens conflicted with the refuge's mission of maintaining uninterrupted open spaces for wildlife.</p>
        <p>UPDATE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
