<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Protecting Industry, Not Workers</title>
    <meta content="l29osha" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843831"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Missouri</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4D7123EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="731" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Protecting Industry, Not Workers</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''OSHA Leaves Worker Safety Largely in Hands of Industry'' (front page, April 25) demonstrates how the voluntary compliance approach favored by business interests and put into effect by the Bush administration fails to protect workers' safety and health.</p>
        <p>Labor's movement for safety and health rights was inspired by the civil rights movement of the 1960s and culminated in the passage of the Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970. For the first time in American history, workers had the right to resist unsafe working conditions, to have OSHA inspect their workplace and to know if the materials they were working with violated OSHA safety standards.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''OSHA Leaves Worker Safety Largely in Hands of Industry'' (front page, April 25) demonstrates how the voluntary compliance approach favored by business interests and put into effect by the Bush administration fails to protect workers' safety and health.</p>
        <p>Labor's movement for safety and health rights was inspired by the civil rights movement of the 1960s and culminated in the passage of the Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970. For the first time in American history, workers had the right to resist unsafe working conditions, to have OSHA inspect their workplace and to know if the materials they were working with violated OSHA safety standards.</p>
        <p>President Bush's voluntary compliance approach is a smokescreen for the evisceration of OSHA. It is tantamount to turning regulatory authority over to business interests, and workers have little choice but to assume the risk of getting injured, ill or killed on the job. Voluntary compliance is nothing more than the rollback of every American's right to safe and healthful working conditions.</p>
        <p>Vernon Mogensen  Brooklyn, April 25, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is an associate professor of political science at Kingsborough Community College.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>OSHA's mission is to assure, as far as possible, safe and healthful working conditions for every worker. Your article shows that this commitment has been degraded.</p>
        <p>OSHA is the primary federal agency for enforcing occupational safety and health standards, yet it devotes a portion of its resources to its Voluntary Protection Programs. While this is not contrary to OSHA's mission, these consultation services are available from private sources like the National Safety Council and insurance companies.</p>
        <p>One aspect of OSHA's work that cannot be performed by the private sector is enforcement. By devoting a portion of its resources to business consulting, the number of OSHA personnel available for safety standards enforcement is reduced.</p>
        <p>Deane Smith  Moorestown, N.J., April 25, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is a safety engineer who provides OSHA training classes in colleges and to businesses.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>OSHA's defense of its inaction on behalf of American workers only confirms its insensitivity to the families of the people it is supposed to ''protect.''</p>
        <p>In modern times, when pro-business administrations occupy the White House, they defang the regulatory bureaucracy by wiping out agencies, appointing heads of agencies in bed with the industries under their authority, cutting their staffs as well as budgets and conducting studies to delay taking action.</p>
        <p>In the mid-1980s, when I was the mayor of University Park, a suburb of Chicago, I once asked the president of our industrial park's largest corporation about the truth of claims that American industries were subjected to excessive governmental regulation. He responded: ''Well, it is not all that bad. When the Democrats are in office we can work it out with them, and when the Republicans are in office, no one comes around.''</p>
        <p>Earl P. Bell  Olympia Fields, Ill., April 25, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Instead of low-wage factory workers getting seriously ill at microwave popcorn plants from exposure to the food-flavoring agent diacetyl, let's imagine a different scenario: business executives getting sick from exposure to some chemical related to golf or computers or cellphones. Three or four incidents and the response would be swift.</p>
        <p>OSHA's inaction and its claim that ''the science is murky'' about the connection between diacetyl and lung disease is another shameful example of this administration's arrogant dismissal of the health and safety of those without power.</p>
        <p>Claudia MonPere McIsaac  Oakland, Calif., April 25, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Industry influence on OSHA standards did not start in the Bush administration. Since its inception in 1970, industry has fought to weaken OSHA. The standards originally adopted by OSHA were heavily influenced by industry lobbyists.</p>
        <p>These original standards have not been substantially updated over the last 37 years to reflect newer scientific understanding of toxic effects. Worse, for 37 years OSHA has consistently ignored recommendations by the National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health to issue new standards or revise existing ones.</p>
        <p>Consequently, millions of working people have been and are currently exposed to levels of toxic substances that are known to cause illnesses like cancer, reproductive problems and other often devastating health conditions.</p>
        <p>Joel Shufro  New York, April 26, 3007</p>
        <p>The writer is executive director of the New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
