<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Park Condos, But the Park Comes Later</title>
    <meta content="29post" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/realestate/29post.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843725"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="POSTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brooklyn Bridge Park (NYC)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vandam, Jeff</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Brooklyn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brooklyn Bridge (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902EFD7153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="682" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Park Condos, But the Park Comes Later</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Park Condos, but the Park Comes Later</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF VANDAM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vandam, Jeff</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Conversion of Brooklyn Heights warehouse at 360 Furman Street to 449-unit condominium building called One Brooklyn Bridge Park is nearing completion; luxury units will range from $550,000 to $7 million; move-in time frame is anticipated by end of year; construction of Brooklyn Bridge Park itself is set to begin in summer; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR years, the yellowish warehouse building at 360 Furman Street, a fast-moving thoroughfare beneath the Brooklyn-Queens Expressway in Brooklyn Heights, served as a distribution center and storage space for the Jehovah's Witnesses, whose headquarters are still nearby. As one of the few remaining commercial structures in operation on the waterfront, 360 Furman often seemed a curiosity to people ambling about on the Brooklyn Heights Promenade a few blocks away.</p>
        <p>Today, giant orange banners advertise the building's new status as a 449-unit condominium called One Brooklyn Bridge Park. Though the park in its title -- or most of it, anyway -- does not yet exist, condo sales are under way, and the development is being described by its marketers as the largest residential conversion of a building in the history of Kings County.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sales at One Brooklyn Bridge Park, the largest residential conversion of a building in the history of Kings County, are under way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR years, the yellowish warehouse building at 360 Furman Street, a fast-moving thoroughfare beneath the Brooklyn-Queens Expressway in Brooklyn Heights, served as a distribution center and storage space for the Jehovah's Witnesses, whose headquarters are still nearby. As one of the few remaining commercial structures in operation on the waterfront, 360 Furman often seemed a curiosity to people ambling about on the Brooklyn Heights Promenade a few blocks away.</p>
        <p>Today, giant orange banners advertise the building's new status as a 449-unit condominium called One Brooklyn Bridge Park. Though the park in its title -- or most of it, anyway -- does not yet exist, condo sales are under way, and the development is being described by its marketers as the largest residential conversion of a building in the history of Kings County.</p>
        <p>''There's nothing like this in New York,'' said Robert A. Levine, the chief operating officer of the RAL Companies &amp; Affiliates, the building's developer, looking out a window facing New York Harbor and the financial district from what will eventually become one of the building's duplex town house units. ''You can step out of your living room and be directly on the water,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The 14-story warehouse was built in an elongated H shape in 1928, and conversion work has been in progress for the last 18 months.</p>
        <p>Though groups of residents in the area who are against current plans for the park sued last year to keep market-rate apartments from being built, a state judge dismissed their lawsuit in November. Today, work is proceeding on condominiums ranging from $550,000 to $7 million. The developer is aiming for a move-in time frame of November or December.</p>
        <p>After corralling his visitors amid puddles and parked trucks in the building's future lobby, which now serves as a garage, Mr. Levine took them up to the seventh floor, where floor-to-ceiling windows in a corner unit offered generous views of Manhattan and Brooklyn. (Corner staircases were removed from the building to create such vistas, with design by CDA Architects; some windows are as much as nine feet high.)</p>
        <p>The building will ultimately have a wide variety of apartment configurations, from high-ceilinged 588-square-foot studios to multibedroom penthouses with up to 4,638 square feet -- as well as those town houses, on the west side, nearest to the water.</p>
        <p>''It was really, in a sense, to create that community feeling, that flexibility for people,'' Mr. Levine said, speaking of the range of layouts. All kitchens will have Dada cabinets, Bosch ovens and Hansgrohe bath fixtures. There will be two parking garages -- one with 132 spaces for sale to One Brooklyn Bridge Park occupants, the other a 500-space lot open to the public, with hourly rates.</p>
        <p>Besides typical luxury condo amenities like a fitness center and a meeting room, the building will also have landscaped gardens and an indoor golf simulator, like the one in regular use by the layabouts on the HBO series ''Entourage.''</p>
        <p>Sales have been open for the last few weeks, but only to those on a waiting list, which Mr. Levine said had reached 4,000 people. General sales will open by the end of April, he said. A sales center with a mural of Brooklyn Bridge Park's eventual layout is already open; the mural depicts the building as surrounded by 85 acres of soccer fields, promenades, docks for boats, bicycle paths, open green areas and playgrounds.</p>
        <p>Despite vocal opposition from community groups -- which object to the building of private apartments in ostensibly public spaces -- construction on it is set to begin this summer, said Errol Cockfield, a spokesman for the Empire State Development Corporation.</p>
        <p>Though the building's views of Manhattan and New York Harbor are a major selling point, some units do face the Brooklyn-Queens Expressway. In fact, a few are almost level with the roadway. Responding to questions about how loud it must be inside these units, Mr. Levine took visitors into an east-facing apartment that had two open windows, both level with the highway.</p>
        <p>Closing the windows, he said: ''See? You can hardly hear it.''</p>
        <p>And he was not incorrect.</p>
        <p>POSTING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
