<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Golf's Culture Of Integrity And Dr. Seuss</title>
    <meta content="29roberts" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/sports/golf/29roberts.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070502T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843943"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Selena Roberts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Finchem, Tim</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE5DD133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1152" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Golf's Culture Of Integrity And Dr. Seuss</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Golf’s Culture of Integrity and Dr. Seuss</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tiger Woods was king of the pond even before the PGA Tour began elevating its leader's power in a Dr. Seussian version of ''Yertle the Turtle.''</p>
        <p>''I'm ruler of all that I see,'' as Yertle proclaims. ''But I don't see enough. That's the trouble with me.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the PGA Tour to empower Tiger Woods above all is to create a petri dish for an abuse of fame, to lose the ability to tell its rock star no, to sanction its own tumble from virtue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tiger Woods was king of the pond even before the PGA Tour began elevating its leader's power in a Dr. Seussian version of ''Yertle the Turtle.''</p>
        <p>''I'm ruler of all that I see,'' as Yertle proclaims. ''But I don't see enough. That's the trouble with me.''</p>
        <p>Commissioner Tim Finchem keeps raising Tiger's vision upon stacked turtles. Not only does Tiger use the Tour's platform in his endorsement race to be the first billionaire athlete, he is also enabled to double dip.</p>
        <p>The Tour announced last month that Woods would play host to the AT&amp;T National in Washington in July, with the Tiger Woods Foundation as its primary beneficiary. At 31, Woods became the youngest player to be a Tour event host, joining Jack and Arnie with a 19th hole of his own.</p>
        <p>Historic day, everyone said. A technical illusion, as it turns out.</p>
        <p>The PGA Tour also co-sanctions the four-year-old Deutsche Bank Championship outside Boston, where, according to the tournament official Eric Baldwin, the Tiger Woods Foundation is its rights-holder and primary beneficiary.</p>
        <p>The only tangible difference is the management group: the D.C. fest will be run by Tiger's foundation; the Boston tournament is operated by Tiger's agent, IMG.</p>
        <p>Either way, Tiger is in charge. How do you please the host with the most? No event is cheap. As it is, the Tour donates about $240,000, according to tax documents, to Tiger's Target World Challenge, an unofficial event. To co-sanction official Tour stops, PGA officials supplement the purses. The AT&amp;T National and Deutsche Bank could run the PGA about $8 million this year, according to industry experts.</p>
        <p>The payoff for Tiger is tucked in the pocket of his charity. Last year, his foundation received an estimated $1.5 million from the Deutsche Bank Championship.</p>
        <p>Is there a money trail to Tiger's heart? What's wrong with buying Tiger's affection, anyway?</p>
        <p>It contradicts every tenet of golf's righteous culture of integrity. ''This is golf,'' Finchem said repeatedly during an interview last week, as if the sport's virtue inoculates it from scrutiny.</p>
        <p>The PGA Tour doesn't drug-test, because that would imply a steroid problem exists. Who knew willful ignorance was a marketing strategy? The Tour applies this see-no-evil approach to glaring conflicts of interest, too.</p>
        <p>Appearance fees are prohibited on Tour, but a deposit into Tiger's foundation is a de facto wink-wink offer because the cash functions as an inducement for him to tee off. Call it Tiger insurance.</p>
        <p>''The chances of him not showing up are zero,'' said Nick Paul, a former tournament director, now vice president and managing director of 361 Sports and Event Marketing, adding: ''It's a creative way to get around the rules. It's not a question of money. It is a question of intent and use of funds.''</p>
        <p>This is about outside motives, not inside Tiger's soul. The foundation provides Woods with a career goal Michael Jordan never developed -- a social legacy. The foundation is a lifeline for children, a nice branding tool for Tiger and catnip to the corporate world. Tiger is all but perched in a carnival kissing booth with companies lined up for a nickel smooch.</p>
        <p>Twenty-seven sponsors are listed on his foundation's Web site. Tiger has endless charity streams without the PGA Tour's complicit role in perceived bribery.</p>
        <p>Neither the AT&amp;T National nor the Deutsche Bank Championship will experience the indignities of the Tiger Duality. With Tiger, a tournament doubles its TV audience. Without him, it turns into a Durham Bulls outing on the schedule.</p>
        <p>''It becomes such a negative that people tune out,'' Paul said.</p>
        <p>Tiger has played only five events in four months. This weekend's Byron Nelson is not among them. For years, Tiger played out of deference to Nelson. Now Nelson is dead and Woods is a no-show.</p>
        <p>Woods is a schedule recluse, the J. D. Salinger of golf. A PGA card requires 15 entries. He will play about 18 -- maybe. The oil tycoon Jack Vickers recently called the PGA ''a one-man show'' as he cited Tiger's absence as a reason for shuttering his International event in Colorado this year.</p>
        <p>Vickers probably flipped his oil can when the International's July spot in the schedule was replaced by Tiger's tourney. The paradox was also not lost on the caretakers of the Kemper-run event that had, for years, been part of the D.C. golfing scene. It, too, recently folded without Tiger.</p>
        <p>Now Woods is a Beltway power broker. He already legislates to the PGA.</p>
        <p>''It's only leverage if you use it as leverage,'' Finchem said, adding, ''I don't have a concern about that.''</p>
        <p>But Tiger does exploit his sway, if passive-aggressively. Other voices are ignored on issues, but a suggestion by Tiger is processed as a demand. In 2000, Tiger complained that the Tour was taking financial advantage of him, that Finchem ignored him. Voilà, Finchem and Woods met and love was in the air.</p>
        <p>Tiger wanted a shortened season. Tiger received a FedEx Cup race that ends in September. Tiger wanted a tournament like Jack's. Tiger received the D.C. gala, which was delivered, as desired, with a reduced field of 120 to enhance its prestige, and, as Woods mentioned, to speed up play.</p>
        <p>Out goes the International, in comes the AT&amp;T National in a field switcheroo that cost about 30 players spots. Rich Beem called it an insult, and Heath Slocum questioned its fairness.</p>
        <p>Wasn't Tiger supposed to bring inclusion to the game? Instead, the Tour is more polarized than ever, between the haves and the have-nots. Several tournament officials say privately that they are tempted to barter for Tiger with a donation, but others refuse to abandon their community aid.</p>
        <p>''You have to ask, how long is Tiger going to be out there?'' said Dave Kaplan, the tournament director for the AT&amp;T Classic in Duluth, Ga. ''Is it till he's 50 or 35? Who knows? If he catches Jack Nicklaus, does he say, 'That's it'? And you'd hate to think it, but Tiger, like anyone, could get hurt tomorrow. Stuff happens.''</p>
        <p>Stuff makes it a lateral hazard for the Tour to wrap itself in one player. The Tiger Boom could vanish as quickly as the dot-com high. Sports wither all the time, from American pro soccer after Pelé, to boxing after corruption, to a National Hockey League with a puny television deal.</p>
        <p>For the Tour to empower Tiger above all is to create a petri dish for an abuse of fame, to lose the ability to tell its rock star no, to sanction its own tumble from virtue.</p>
        <p>This is not Tiger's issue, but a Tour management flaw. What is best for Tiger is not necessarily a 2-foot gimme for those below. It was, after all, a tiny turtle squeezed beneath the pond king that, with a wiggle, toppled Yertle.</p>
        <p>''The great Yertle, the Marvelous he,'' as Dr. Seuss wrote, ''is King of the mud. That is all he can see.''</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: selenasports@nytimes.com</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 2, 2007, Wednesday  A picture caption in some copies on Sunday with a Sports of The Times column about the PGA Tour's handling of Tiger Woods given his support among corporate sponsors misidentified the man shown with Woods. He is AT&amp;T's chairman and chief executive, Edward E. Whitacre Jr. -- not Tim Finchem, the PGA Tour commissioner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 2, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A picture caption in some copies on Sunday with a Sports of The Times column about the PGA Tour's handling of Tiger Woods given his support among corporate sponsors misidentified the man shown with Woods. He is AT&amp;T's chairman and chief executive, Edward E. Whitacre Jr. -- not Tim Finchem, the PGA Tour commissioner.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: selenasports@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
