<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Randolph Loses Cool, Mets Rally for Win</title>
    <meta content="29mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/sports/baseball/29mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843954"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Washington Nationals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Washington Nationals</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Randolph, Willie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E3DD133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="952" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Randolph Loses Cool, Mets Rally for Win</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After Randolph Loses Cool, Mets Rally for Win</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shpigel, Ben</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From his spartan office inside the visiting clubhouse at R.F.K. Stadium, where he waited after being ejected, Willie Randolph could have spent the rest of Saturday's game stewing about everything else that went wrong Saturday.</p>
        <p>That list included the three close calls at first base that went against his team, a knee injury to Jose Valentín and an undeserved no-decision for Tom Glavine in his quest for 300 victories.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>What began poorly ended spectacularly as the Mets, after tying the score with two outs in the ninth, scored four runs in the 12th to defeat the Washington Nationals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From his spartan office inside the visiting clubhouse at R.F.K. Stadium, where he waited after being ejected, Willie Randolph could have spent the rest of Saturday's game stewing about everything else that went wrong Saturday.</p>
        <p>That list included the three close calls at first base that went against his team, a knee injury to Jose Valentín and an undeserved no-decision for Tom Glavine in his quest for 300 victories.</p>
        <p>But what began poorly ended spectacularly as the Mets, after tying the score with two outs in the ninth, scored four runs in the 12th to defeat the Washington Nationals, 6-2, and snap their two-game losing streak. The big hits came from Carlos Beltrán, whose bases-loaded double knocked in two runs, and David Wright, whose two-run single drove in his first runs since April 18, but it was the bench players who sparked the comeback.</p>
        <p>''We're not going to win with the same nine, 10 or 11 guys,'' Glavine said. ''We need everyone to contribute.''</p>
        <p>In Randolph's absence, the bench coach Jerry Manuel handled the roster with the touch of a diamond cutter. He inserted Endy Chávez to pinch-run for Shawn Green in the ninth, and he called on Julio Franco to pinch-hit with two on and two out. Franco delivered a single, and Chávez hustled around third to slide home beneath the tag as the Mets scored the tying run while being down to their last out for the second time in four games.</p>
        <p>''It was almost like two games in one,'' Randolph said.</p>
        <p>The Mets may need one of their key reserves, Damion Easley, to fill in for Valentín, who will fly back to New York on Sunday to have a magnetic resonance imaging exam after he felt a pop on the outside of his right knee while covering second base on Felipe Lopez's steal attempt in the third inning.</p>
        <p>He remained in the game but, after Glavine retired Ronnie Belliard on a comebacker to begin the fourth, Valentín suddenly started walking off the field. He was met in front of the dugout by Randolph and the head trainer Ray Ramirez before shuffling into the clubhouse.</p>
        <p>Valentín said his knee buckled when he moved to his right on Belliard's grounder, and Valentín, who missed three months in 2005 with sprained ligaments in the same knee, did not want to take any chances.</p>
        <p>''Knock on wood, I hope it's nothing serious,'' Valentín said.</p>
        <p>After falling behind, 2-1, in the eighth, on Belliard's two-out double off Aaron Heilman, the Mets rallied against closer Chad Cordero because, of all things, a close play at first that went their way. Green smoked a two-out single off third baseman Ryan Zimmerman's glove, and Easley followed by sending a grounder to deep short. The throw by Lopez popped into Robert Fick's glove as Easley tagged the bag, and he was called safe.</p>
        <p>''Definitely safe,'' Easley said.</p>
        <p>Franco lined a 1-0 pitch into right field for a single. Chávez, pinch-running for Green, barreled toward home. Sensing a throw coming in, Chávez started his slide away from the plate and snuck his foot in just beneath catcher Jesus Flores's tag to score the tying run.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't going to let him tag me,'' Chávez said.</p>
        <p>The trouble at first base started in the fifth when, within a three-batter span, Easley and José Reyes hit tough grounders to third base. Both were called out despite television replays indicating that they were safe. When another close play went in favor of the Nationals the next inning, Randolph had seen enough.</p>
        <p>With one out in the sixth, pitcher Jerome Williams slammed a ball off the left-field fence for a 360-foot single. The next hitter, Lopez, grounded to shortstop for what set up to be a double play. Easley's return throw to first was deemed too late by the first-base umpire, Tony Randazzo, infuriating Randolph. As Glavine threw up his hands in disgust, Randolph ran out of the dugout and proceeded to tell Randazzo, in no uncertain terms, that he blew the call. ''He had a tough night,'' Randolph said of Randazzo. ''We'll just leave it at that.''</p>
        <p>Randolph, not surprisingly, was ejected, but Glavine had to harness his frustration to face Belliard. On a 1-1 pitch, Belliard lined a double into the left-field corner, scoring Lopez with the game's first run.</p>
        <p>Glavine allowed only one run in six strong innings, and the Mets wish they could have managed even that much against Williams. He entered the game 0-4 with a 7.77 earned run average but allowed one hit -- a Beltrán one-out single in the sixth -- before leaving the game in the seventh with a sprained left ankle. With the game turned over to their bullpen, the Nationals let the Mets back in.</p>
        <p>Jesus Colome allowed a two-out single to Green. Easley followed by hitting a grounder to third that Zimmerman bobbled and then threw wide of second base and into right field, setting up second and third for the pinch-hitter David Newhan. A 1-1 pitch scooted past Flores, allowing Green to tie the score at 1-1. Easley advanced to third, but Newhan grounded out.</p>
        <p>If Valentín's injury requires a stay on the disabled list, Easley is the natural choice to replace him in the lineup. To back him up, the Mets would have to delve into their system, where the options are unappealing. The Mets acquired Ruben Gotay, the Class AAA New Orleans second baseman, from Kansas City last July to add infield depth, but he hasn't played in the majors since 2005. Anderson Hernández, last season's opening day starter at second base, is playing shortstop for New Orleans and has not yet proven he can handle major-league pitching.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
