<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Case of Rough Play, or More, That Turned Fatal in Queens</title>
    <meta content="29punch" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/29punch.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843886"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE4DE133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1696" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Case of Rough Play, or More, That Turned Fatal in Queens</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Case of Rough Play, or More, That Turned Fatal in Queens</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELLEN BARRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barry, Ellen</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a recent afternoon behind Public School 127 in East Elmhurst, Queens, two girls in jeans and parkas crouched on the ground, track-and-field-style, and then skipped the length of the basketball court. Boys flung a ball back and forth with maniacal energy. There was no reminder of the moment that passed here a month ago, when one 13-year-old boy struck another on the head and the second sat down, in pain.</p>
        <p>But in two homes in East Elmhurst, that moment goes on and on.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a blow to the head on a Queens playground, one young boy is dead and another is accused of third-degree assault.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a recent afternoon behind Public School 127 in East Elmhurst, Queens, two girls in jeans and parkas crouched on the ground, track-and-field-style, and then skipped the length of the basketball court. Boys flung a ball back and forth with maniacal energy. There was no reminder of the moment that passed here a month ago, when one 13-year-old boy struck another on the head and the second sat down, in pain.</p>
        <p>But in two homes in East Elmhurst, that moment goes on and on.</p>
        <p>On 100th Street, a family is mourning the boy who was hit, Guarionex Montas, who died March 24 of a skull fracture and bleeding in his brain. Miguel Cepeda cannot shake the memory of holding Guarionex, his nephew, that night, when bloody foam began to flow from his nose and mouth so fast that Mr. Cepeda used a roll of Bounty trying to soak it up.</p>
        <p>A cousin remembers quieter things about the boy, known as Guachy (pronounced GWA-chee): How he wanted to be a detective, how he had trouble pronouncing the letter R. He was, she said, ''the loved one out of the whole family.''</p>
        <p>Ten blocks away, another family is frightened for their own boy, a gangly seventh grader who faces a charge of third-degree assault. When he was arrested and taken to a juvenile center, his uncle flew in from Los Angeles, and 20 supporters showed up for hearings in Queens Family Court. Borough President Helen Marshall, a neighbor in East Elmhurst, was so concerned that she offered to supervise him when he was released.</p>
        <p>''Whatever happens, this child has to be cleared of this thing,'' she said in an interview.</p>
        <p>In the coming months, the justice system will struggle to find an appropriate punishment -- if any -- for an act that seems to fall into the murky area between play and violence. Defense attorneys say the boys were engaged in slap-boxing, an ordinary form of adolescent horseplay; prosecutors say the boy hit Guachy in the head with a hard object and then threatened to hurt him and his brother if they reported it. As the case progresses, East Elmhurst is torn along an invisible line, with two large families mobilized in the name of their sons.</p>
        <p>''This is a very tragic case, and also a very difficult case,'' Judge Rhea Friedman said at a hearing earlier this month. ''It is distressing to have to make critical decisions with so little information, frankly.''</p>
        <p>The two boys were friendly, by all accounts. Guachy's mother moved her four children to East Elmhurst from the South Bronx a year ago, hoping to raise them in a safer, more middle-class neighborhood. The family of the other boy -- The New York Times is withholding his name because he is being charged as a juvenile -- has lived in East Elmhurst since the 1950s, when it was one of the few neighborhoods where black families could buy a house.</p>
        <p>He gave the police his account of what happened on March 23. The afternoon began with a trip to McDonald's and a visit to a friend's house to play Xbox 360. After that, he said, the group ''went to the handball court to slap-box.''</p>
        <p>His uncle, a video producer and editor who lives in Los Angeles, said slap-boxing, done with an open hand, is a longstanding and benign tradition in the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>''It's part of how you develop a reputation for being able to stand up for yourself,'' he said. ''It's sort of like an entry into your teen years. It's like cubs fighting. Whoever's the quickest tends to win.''</p>
        <p>In this case, the boy told police, Guachy got hurt. He said he hit Guachy in the temple, and that Guachy sat down, complaining of a headache. Guachy's brother Jose, a 15-year-old who attends the sixth grade at P.S. 127, said it was time to go. When Jose went to fetch their coats, the boy said in the statement, Guachy hit his head a second time, on a pole, but no explanation was offered in the first court appearance as to why he did so. The boy also reported that Guachy had been drinking alcohol.</p>
        <p>Guachy's uncle Casimiro Cepeda said Guachy did not drink, and noted that the blow to the head came just an hour after school had let out.</p>
        <p>Guachy and Jose walked five blocks to their apartment. Neither said anything to their mother or stepfather about what had happened, but Guachy went to bed, saying he felt sick. He woke up complaining of pain and swelling, so his stepfather stepped out to buy Advil. A few hours later, Jose saw blood pouring from his brother's nose and mouth.</p>
        <p>Hours passed in the hospital before the doctors gave the results of a CT scan: Guachy's skull had been fractured and a vein had burst, Mr. Cepeda recalled. He was declared dead at 10 the next morning.</p>
        <p>The family pressed Jose to explain what had happened. At first, he said the injury had happened accidentally -- a flying elbow in a basketball game -- but then he changed his story. Later, when the family was in the Dominican Republic for Guachy's funeral, Jose told authorities that the other boys had threatened that he would be ''stabbed or jumped'' if he told the truth.</p>
        <p>Now, Jose told them, he felt safe enough to say that the boy ''took an object and hit the decedent in the head,'' as the city's lawyer, Theresa Wilson-Campbell, put it in court. Ms. Wilson-Campbell said that when the police executed a search warrant at the boy's home, they found a small black umbrella with a wooden handle that the authorities believe might be the weapon.</p>
        <p>Other boys at the playground gave ''widely different accounts,'' describing the two boys as ''playing,'' said Melanie Shapiro, a defense lawyer, at the hearing. Everyone described them as close friends, she said.</p>
        <p>The boy who hit Guachy was one of the mourners at his wake in Queens on March 27; Guachy's relatives remember that he dropped off a card and a stuffed rabbit. On March 30, he was arrested.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors for the City Law Department, which handles juvenile delinquency cases, are not allowed to discuss pending cases publicly. But a typical investigation would begin by seeking facts, said Laurence Busching, the Law Department's family court division chief: Where were the kids in relationship to each other? How big or small were they? Were these ''two kids who have been playing all along and something just happened, or is there some motive and some reason it changed from play to something else?'' How much harm are they physically capable of inflicting?</p>
        <p>''Even though you have great emotional responses, you still have to put those things aside and focus on what are the facts,'' Mr. Busching said.</p>
        <p>The charge at the boy's arrest was manslaughter -- which could bring a penalty of 18 months in a juvenile center -- and he was detained. When the deadline arrived to file, though, the city could present evidence only for two lesser charges of third-degree assault, a misdemeanor that could bring a maximum penalty of a year in a juvenile center. After a juvenile is placed with the Office of Children and Family Services on a delinquency case, the agency can seek to extend the placement year by year until his 18th birthday.</p>
        <p>Kim McLaurin, the head attorney at the Legal Aid Society's Queens juvenile rights division, said taking the boy from his home could prove particularly damaging.</p>
        <p>''On the one hand, you do appreciate the fact that a child has died,'' she said. ''But you don't want to prejudge, because the stakes are high.''</p>
        <p>In court, Ms. Wilson-Campbell argued that the boy had a history of being aggressive, and said the principal of P.S. 127 was trying to remove him from school because of discipline problems.</p>
        <p>She also quoted from a notebook found in a search of the house, which described him as the leader of a gang of 50 boys, and said that ''they sent out their boys when somebody messes with them.''</p>
        <p>''It seems to be part fiction and part journal,'' she said of the writings.</p>
        <p>Judge Friedman seemed skeptical, and ordered the boy released to his mother, warning him sternly against having contact with members of Guachy's family. She noted that his school records showed good attendance and did not reflect a ''dangerous or aggressive youngster,'' and that he had no juvenile police record. ''I do not see the nexus between any alleged gang activities and, for lack of a better word, dangerousness,'' she said.</p>
        <p>She found probable cause for one count of third-degree assault. ''It is either a terrible accident gone wrong, or it may be something that rises to the level of penal law,'' she said. ''We don't know the answer to that.''</p>
        <p>The Cepedas buried Guachy in Villa Altagracia, a seaside city in the Dominican Republic, where his mother grew up. They were still there when they heard that the boy had not been charged with manslaughter, and it angered them to hear that elected officials like Ms. Marshall had come out in his support.</p>
        <p>Guachy's mother and stepfather met on Friday afternoon with Councilman Hiram Monserrate, who represents East Elmhurst. Edwin Hernandez, 33, a cousin, said they believe the beating ''had something to do with a gang in school, maybe an initiation or something, where they take one of the weakest kids.''</p>
        <p>''It is not justice,'' said Mr. Cepeda, Guachy's uncle . ''You see people working for the city trying to save this guy. You know the thing he did; he didn't break a window.''</p>
        <p>The other boy's family and their supporters are, for their part, fiercely protective.</p>
        <p>''I don't know where he's going in life, but I'm going to make sure that he gets there,'' said Ms. Marshall, who allowed the boy to stay in her office at Borough Hall for two days when he was released. Relatives are particularly angry that prosecutors have said that he was affiliated with a gang. His uncle called that notion ''laughable.''</p>
        <p>''I know the kid,'' he said. ''He doesn't even backtalk. He doesn't have the temperament for that.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
