<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Lineup of 'I Dunnits' With Stylish Stories to Tell</title>
    <meta content="29theaterctCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/29theaterct.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843657"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Theaterworks (Hartford, Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gold, Sylviane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hatcher, Jeffrey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Campo, Steve</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Murderers (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4DB153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="638" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Lineup of 'I Dunnits' With Stylish Stories to Tell</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Lineup of ‘I Dunnits’ With Stylish Stories to Tell</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SYLVIANE GOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gold, Sylviane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sylviane Gold reviews TheaterWorks production of Jeffrey Hatcher play Murderers, directed by Steve Campo; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There's no point wondering whodunit -- Jeffrey Hatcher's new play tells us the answer to that question right off the bat. The fun at TheaterWorks in Hartford is finding out how they dun it, and why.</p>
        <p>''Murderers,'' which runs through May 27, begins with three people announcing, in rapid succession, ''I am a murderer'' -- as if they were on a bizarro episode of ''To Tell the Truth.'' And then, one by one, they step onto the stage, decorated by Jeff Cowie with a palmy tropical vista and wrought-iron patio furniture (including striped umbrella and colorful tumblers), to tell us their stories.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There’s no point wondering whodunit. The fun at TheaterWorks in Hartford is finding out how they dun it, and why.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There's no point wondering whodunit -- Jeffrey Hatcher's new play tells us the answer to that question right off the bat. The fun at TheaterWorks in Hartford is finding out how they dun it, and why.</p>
        <p>''Murderers,'' which runs through May 27, begins with three people announcing, in rapid succession, ''I am a murderer'' -- as if they were on a bizarro episode of ''To Tell the Truth.'' And then, one by one, they step onto the stage, decorated by Jeff Cowie with a palmy tropical vista and wrought-iron patio furniture (including striped umbrella and colorful tumblers), to tell us their stories.</p>
        <p>It doesn't sound as if it would make much of a play. But in the capable hands of Mr. Hatcher, the director Steve Campo and a trio of transfixing actors, this simple formula provides a pleasing evening's entertainment.</p>
        <p>''Murderers'' takes place at the Riddle Key Luxury Senior Retirement Living Center and Golf Course. Its well-off ''seasoned citizens'' may have come for the golf and the retirement living, but somehow, they end up dying -- at a higher-than-statistically probable rate. The three people onstage bear some of the responsibility.</p>
        <p>There's the spoiled loafer Gerald Halverson, whose slick plan for keeping a $5 million estate in the family involves all kinds of nasty business in addition to the two murders at the center of his tale. There's the crafty betrayed wife, Lucy Stickler, who concocts an elaborate ruse that will enmesh her husband and his mistress and punish them once and for all. And there's the cheery Minka Lupino, whose job at Riddle Key allows her a privileged view of the clientele and whose highly evolved sense of justice requires that she dispatch some of them from time to time.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hatcher, who brought a similar triple-pronged structure to his ''Three Viewings,'' can do a lot with a single monologue. Of course, he's primarily spinning a rococo crime scenario. And of course, he's revealing personality traits. But he also manages to fill each character's social circle with well-drawn, recognizable supporting players.</p>
        <p>He is helped immeasurably in this by Mr. Campo and the cast. It shouldn't be surprising that three professional actors would be expert at mimicry. But the gusto with which they tackle these comic mini-portraits makes it seem, sometimes, as if they're not alone onstage.</p>
        <p>Just watch Bill Kux, as Gerald, slide into the upper-crust Midwestern drawl of Spiff, ''one of those gals who studied Vogue for a living.'' Observe Donna Wandrey as her eyes widen, her voice trills and she imitates Lucy's nemesis, serving a super-stiff martini and asking with fake solicitude: ''What's the matter, dear? Drink too strong?''</p>
        <p>Ann Talman's Minka, who quickly reveals herself to be not just a killer but a serial offender as well, gets to show the audience the juiciest of these individuals: a vicious wife decreeing that there will be no memorial service for her just-deceased mother-in-law, since ''she didn't have any friends here anyway''; a cynical nurse plying a widower with sex and drugs in the expectation that ''he can't live forever''; and most ornate of all, a honey-dripping Southerner who writes murder mysteries and seems to have written the one in which Minka is starring.</p>
        <p>As this lineup suggests, Mr. Hatcher hasn't quite made up his mind whether to be amused or angered by the opportunists, schemers and dirty old men -- and women -- he finds at Riddle Key. There are not a lot of innocent bystanders in the pictures his miscreants paint. But they are such a stylish bunch, and they tell their stories with so much charm that we smile at their crimes and enjoy their company -- and hope that one or two of them are lying.</p>
        <p>''Murderers,'' by Jeffrey Hatcher, is at TheaterWorks, 233 Pearl Street, Hartford, through May 27. Information: (860) 527-7838 or www.theaterworkshartford.org.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
