<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rogues' Gallery of Oddballs, A Force to Contend With</title>
    <meta content="29theatnjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/29theatnj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843704"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Repertory Company</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siegel, Naomi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giron, Arthur</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bennett, Peter</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Love and Murder (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Repertory Company</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Giron, Arthur</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EFD8153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="510" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rogues' Gallery of Oddballs, A Force to Contend With</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rogues’ Gallery of Oddballs, a Force to Contend With</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NAOMI SIEGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Siegel, Naomi</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Naomi Siegel reviews New Jersey Repertory Company production of Arthur Giron play Love and Murder, directed by Peter Bennett; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Is it possible to enjoy the four outrageous characters at the center of Arthur Giron's ''Love and Murder'' without finding the play worthwhile? That was the question I struggled to answer at the end of Mr. Giron's issue-stuffed, plot-heavy ''serio-comic murder mystery,'' onstage at the New Jersey Repertory Company in Long Branch. The play is hard to take seriously, as the author demands; perhaps that's the problem.</p>
        <p>In rambling notes published in the program, Mr. Giron, who was born in New York of Guatemalan parents, describes some of his inspiration for the play: the Guatemalan cleaning woman he knew who was cheated out of her wages; the upstate New York town where men joined fraternal organizations but women were discouraged from meeting for coffee, and where the only beauty shop was in a brothel serving the nearby military base. These concerns crowd and confuse this ribald, sexually explicit romp (there are several instances of full frontal nudity) but don't lend much shape or meaning to the exercise.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“Love and Murder” is an issue-stuffed, plot-heavy “serio-comic murder mystery” onstage at the New Jersey Repertory Company in Long Branch.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Is it possible to enjoy the four outrageous characters at the center of Arthur Giron's ''Love and Murder'' without finding the play worthwhile? That was the question I struggled to answer at the end of Mr. Giron's issue-stuffed, plot-heavy ''serio-comic murder mystery,'' onstage at the New Jersey Repertory Company in Long Branch. The play is hard to take seriously, as the author demands; perhaps that's the problem.</p>
        <p>In rambling notes published in the program, Mr. Giron, who was born in New York of Guatemalan parents, describes some of his inspiration for the play: the Guatemalan cleaning woman he knew who was cheated out of her wages; the upstate New York town where men joined fraternal organizations but women were discouraged from meeting for coffee, and where the only beauty shop was in a brothel serving the nearby military base. These concerns crowd and confuse this ribald, sexually explicit romp (there are several instances of full frontal nudity) but don't lend much shape or meaning to the exercise.</p>
        <p>None of this, however, stops Mr. Giron's rogues' gallery of oddballs, performed to manic perfection by a superb cast under Peter Bennett's direction, from engaging and entertaining the audience. Liz Zazzi, her blond hair piled on her head, her silk peignoir opening seductively at the knees, is divinely tacky as Tex, a flamboyant, sex-starved cabaret singer with a lifelong goal of cutting a record. Tex is married to Dr. Tuttle, the obsessive town doctor and alderman, who may or may not be a murderer and a fraud, and whose passion for Tex is unrequited. As unctuously played by John FitzGibbon, he is one creepy dude.</p>
        <p>Thomas (Blackie) Swamp Cree, a young Mohawk Indian law enforcement officer willing to do whatever it takes (including stripping) to land on the cover of Newsweek, is the province of Dan Domingues, a comically gifted young actor with eyes that never stop talking. Blackie would seem to be the lover of Tex and her maid, Helen, a former exchange student from Guatemala whose current illegal status leaves her open to exploitation and blackmail. As played by the exquisite Guenia Lemos, Helen is nevertheless a force to contend with. A mysterious presence -- her fiancé was the victim of a political killing in her native country -- Helen is like a poised alley cat waiting to pounce.</p>
        <p>To try to describe the ultimate unraveling of ''Love and Murder'' would prove more tedious than enlightening. Suffice it to say, sexual liaisons change at a moment's notice (including a suggestion of a lesbian attraction on Tex's part); a woman becomes pregnant (or does she?); a murder is committed (we're not sure by whom); and a suicide-by-hanging leaves lovers free to follow their destiny, whatever that may be.</p>
        <p>Worth spending two hours watching? Not unless prurient tastes dictate your choice of entertainment -- or if you simply want to catch four fine actors doing what they do best.</p>
        <p>''Love and Murder'' is at the New Jersey Repertory Company, 179 Broadway, Long Branch, through May 6. Information: (732) 229-3166 or at www.njrep.org.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
