<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>McCain Tries to Recapture Vigor of His Last Campaign</title>
    <meta content="29mccain" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/us/politics/29mccain.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070501T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843893"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Arizona</location>
        <person class="online_producer">McCain, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E3DE133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="997" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>McCain Tries to Recapture Vigor of His Last Campaign</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">McCain Tries to Recapture Vigor of His Last Campaign</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>TEMPE, Ariz., April 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Republican presidential candidate John McCain has made clear that policy he adopted as candidate in 2004 of speaking freely, frequently and at length to reporters and audiences is sill in place; seeks to recapture spontaneity and energy of last campaign; tends to stop reading speech off prompters and deliver it in his own relaxed and unscripted way; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Several times this week -- while wrapping up a town hall meeting in Des Moines, or a conference call with bloggers from Sioux City, Iowa -- Senator John McCain and his listeners were told that there was time for just one more question. ''Can I do two more?'' Mr. McCain would ask.</p>
        <p>As he toured crucial states this week after announcing his candidacy for president, Mr. McCain, a Republican of Arizona, made it clear that the policy he adopted as a candidate in 2000 of speaking freely, frequently and at length to reporters and audiences was still in place as he struggled to regain front-runner status.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator John McCain is standing by the policy he adopted as a candidate in 2000 of speaking freely, frequently and at length to reporters and audiences.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Several times this week -- while wrapping up a town hall meeting in Des Moines, or a conference call with bloggers from Sioux City, Iowa -- Senator John McCain and his listeners were told that there was time for just one more question. ''Can I do two more?'' Mr. McCain would ask.</p>
        <p>As he toured crucial states this week after announcing his candidacy for president, Mr. McCain, a Republican of Arizona, made it clear that the policy he adopted as a candidate in 2000 of speaking freely, frequently and at length to reporters and audiences was still in place as he struggled to regain front-runner status.</p>
        <p>For a generation of political reporters in an age when direct access even to local candidates can be rare and tightly restricted, it brought to mind an earlier era, along with questions about whether he could recapture some of the spontaneity and energy of the last campaign.</p>
        <p>''I know I can't do it any other way,'' Mr. McCain said as he spoke about the Iraq war, presidential politics, campaign finance and other topics during a bus trip through New Hampshire. ''After a while, after we get through these important and necessary questions, there is a certain banter back and forth, and that makes it enjoyable.''</p>
        <p>Banter, of course, is not without its risks. When Mr. McCain replaced the words of the Beach Boys tune ''Barbara Ann'' with ''Bomb Iran'' this month, he became a curious sensation on YouTube and angered many who are against the war. But the move seemed to appeal to hawkish voters -- as evidenced by the warm reception Mr. McCain's campaign got when it played the original song at several rallies this week.</p>
        <p>Mostly, Mr. McCain addressed a handful of central issues. He explained why he continued to support a heavy troop presence in Iraq, saying that the war would ''follow us home'' if the mission failed -- but always being sure to add that the war had been ''terribly mismanaged.'' And he spoke at length about the wasteful spending in Washington, which he lamented had been continued by Republicans, and invoked President Ronald Reagan's line that Congress spent like a drunken sailor.</p>
        <p>''I never knew a sailor, drunk or sober, that had the imagination of our Congress,'' Mr. McCain said at a town hall meeting in Des Moines. ''I'm not making this up when I tell you a few weeks ago I received an e-mail from a guy who said, 'As a former drunken sailor, I resent being compared to members of Congress.' ''</p>
        <p>During the trip, as he stopped reading his speech off prompters and began to deliver it in his own, relaxed way, he veered into unscripted areas. Several times he expressed reservations about the direction Russia was taking under President Vladimir V. Putin (''if you want to call him 'president,' '' he said in a pointed aside in Charleston, S.C.), saying that the Russian leader had shut down political opposition, had taken control of the news media and was being unhelpful when it came to Iran.</p>
        <p>The crowds in New Hampshire, where the kickoff began, were not terribly big, perhaps kept away from the outdoor rallies by a chill rain. But they grew more enthusiastic in South Carolina and Mr. McCain was received well at two town hall meetings in Iowa. The tour ended here, at Tempe City Hall, before a loud crowd of supporters and antiwar protesters.</p>
        <p>Along the way, Mr. McCain met protesters from the left and right. In Manchester, N.H., antiwar demonstrators held a sign that said, ''Don't bomb bomb bomb bomb bomb Iran'' while a protester who felt Mr. McCain was soft on immigration appeared in a sombrero holding a sign that said, ''Illegals for McCain.'' Throughout the trip there were reminders of Mr. McCain's peculiar mix of candor and humor. Asked how much time he would spend in the Senate during the campaign, he readily acknowledged, ''Not a lot.''</p>
        <p>At a news conference in Columbia, S.C., Mr. McCain made a show of presenting a check to the state Republican Party. ''I'd like to give you this check for $25,000 you extorted from me in order to get on the ballot,'' he joked.</p>
        <p>But his biography -- and the years he spent as a prisoner of war -- had a way of creeping in, even in lighthearted moments. After a long discussion of policy on a bus tour, one reporter asked Mr. McCain if he was superstitious.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain allowed that he was more likely to pick up a penny if it was showing heads than tails. His wife, Cindy, reminded him that he throws a pinch of salt over his shoulder when he knocks over the salt shaker. ''I think all pilots are superstitious to some degree,'' Mr. McCain said.</p>
        <p>Then he launched into an anecdote from his days in the Navy about how he used to have a superstition: each time he went to take off from the aircraft carrier Forrestal, he would hand his helmet to Tom Ott, a petty officer second class from Mississippi on the flight deck who would clean his visor before he taxied out.</p>
        <p>The anecdote turned quickly somber. ''The day of the Forrestal fire, he was standing there and he'd just handed my helmet back to me when the missile hit and he was incinerated in the fire,'' Mr. McCain said, recalling an attack that killed 134 of his shipmates. ''I always remember him with great affection but a little bit of guilt because he was standing there because of my idiosyncrasy.''</p>
        <p>Along the way, voters tried to make up their minds about him. Bob Dastin, a 73-year-old lawyer from Manchester who braved the rain to hear him speak, said he had supported Mr. McCain in 2000, and still did.</p>
        <p>''Oh, I think he's going to have a very difficult time, considering his stance on the war,'' Mr. Dastin said. ''But considering the opposition, I think he's going to have a very good chance.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 1, 2007, Tuesday  An article on Sunday about Senator John McCain's presidential campaign misstated the cause of a fire aboard the aircraft carrier Forrestal, which killed 134 of Mr. McCain's shipmates during his Navy career. It resulted from the explosion of an American rocket on the deck, not an attack.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 1, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article on Sunday about Senator John McCain's presidential campaign misstated the cause of a fire aboard the aircraft carrier Forrestal, which killed 134 of Mr. McCain's shipmates during his Navy career. It resulted from the explosion of an American rocket on the deck, not an attack.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
