<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Materialism, Snobbery And Young Shoppers</title>
    <meta content="l29conn-2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843975"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E0DD133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="446" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Materialism, Snobbery And Young Shoppers</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Lesley Jane Seymour's unabashed reveling in tween shopping habits (''Tweens 'R' Shoppers,'' April 22) proclaims this young group of girls, ages 8 to 15, as a new economic power base in consumer spending. Really this is not new at all -- young girls from wealthy suburban towns have been power shopping for decades, displaying insatiable tastes for designer labels, fueled by parents' seemingly limitless budgets to support such spending.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Lesley Jane Seymour's unabashed reveling in tween shopping habits (''Tweens 'R' Shoppers,'' April 22) proclaims this young group of girls, ages 8 to 15, as a new economic power base in consumer spending. Really this is not new at all -- young girls from wealthy suburban towns have been power shopping for decades, displaying insatiable tastes for designer labels, fueled by parents' seemingly limitless budgets to support such spending.</p>
        <p>What is missing from this lighthearted discussion, though, is the impact of spending habits, not to mention the overriding themes of materialism and overt snobbery perpetuated by a lifestyle of acquisitions nurtured at such a young age.</p>
        <p>Lynn Villency Cohen  Stamford</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>My children at 12 did not even know the name ''Louis Vuitton.'' Presently, their priorities lie in their studies, working, sports, traveling and spending time with friends. Oh, and they have chosen to actually help people in need by doing volunteer work in local hospitals and places such as Costa Rica and Jamaica.</p>
        <p>Still today, when they need clothes, we go shopping and find items that look good, fit well and do not cost a fortune. My children do not like seeing designer logos embellished on their clothing, as they would rather themselves be seen, not the name on their shirts or jeans.</p>
        <p>Many of us have forgotten how to help others or merely claim that we do not have the time to do so. We cannot blame these children; a parent's job is to guide the children and encourage them to grow up to be formidable adults.</p>
        <p>Linda Rowan  Redding</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Lesley Jane Seymour's profile of three shopping tweens was a poignant look at how a new generation of shoppers succumbs to brand names and price-based decisions (the higher the price, the trendier the fashion). We have been lured into paying money to advertise the brand-name logos we willingly flaunt, and buying very expensive pre-ripped jeans.</p>
        <p>As the shopping bags held by the girls in the lead photograph demonstrate, we also allow Abercrombie &amp; Fitch's suggestive advertising and skin-tight jeans inventory to mask the possibility that subtlety and age-appropriate dressing are a faster route to sophisticated style.</p>
        <p>What a gift it would be if the fashion industry spent less time marketing the lowest common style denominator to our youngsters and, rather, helped them learn the meaning of style. Perhaps then our children would notice that the true value of Eve's bracelet mentioned in the article was not its Juicy Couture price tag, but rather that it was a gift of the heart from her mother.</p>
        <p>Jane Bailey  Washington, Conn.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
