<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sallie Permar, Matthew Ferraguto</title>
    <meta content="29PERMAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/fashion/weddings/29PERMAR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843758"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Permar, Dr. Sallie R.</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ferraguto, Matthew P.</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E7DC123EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="447" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sallie Permar, Matthew Ferraguto</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sallie Permar, Matthew Ferraguto</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dr. Sallie R. Permar and Matthew P. Ferraguto were married yesterday at Capon Springs &amp; Farms, a family resort in Capon Springs, W.Va. The Rev. Wayne Ham, a Baptist minister, officiated.</p>
        <p>The bride, 31, is keeping her name. She is a third-year resident in pediatrics at Children's Hospital in Boston and a research fellow in the division of viral pathogenesis at Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center in Boston. She graduated from Davidson College and received a Ph.D. in microbiology and immunology from Johns Hopkins. She also received a medical degree, magna cum laude, from Harvard.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dr. Sallie R. Permar and Matthew P. Ferraguto were married yesterday at Capon Springs &amp; Farms, a family resort in Capon Springs, W.Va. The Rev. Wayne Ham, a Baptist minister, officiated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dr. Sallie R. Permar and Matthew P. Ferraguto were married yesterday at Capon Springs &amp; Farms, a family resort in Capon Springs, W.Va. The Rev. Wayne Ham, a Baptist minister, officiated.</p>
        <p>The bride, 31, is keeping her name. She is a third-year resident in pediatrics at Children's Hospital in Boston and a research fellow in the division of viral pathogenesis at Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center in Boston. She graduated from Davidson College and received a Ph.D. in microbiology and immunology from Johns Hopkins. She also received a medical degree, magna cum laude, from Harvard.</p>
        <p>She is a daughter of Elizabeth Ann Permar and David Hayes Permar III of Raleigh, N.C. Her father is a lawyer at Hatch, Little &amp; Bunn, in Raleigh. Her mother is the coordinator of the Career Development Center at Needham B. Broughton High School, also in Raleigh.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom, 30, is the press secretary in the Boston office of Representative Stephen F. Lynch. The bridegroom graduated cum laude from Duke. He is the son of Marie Catherine Ferraguto of North Andover, Mass., and Philip James Ferraguto of Arlington, Mass.</p>
        <p>His mother is the treasurer of the summer session at Phillips Academy in Andover, Mass. His father is the director of purchasing for Cains Foods, a manufacturer in Ayer, Mass.</p>
        <p>The couple met in Boston on June 17, 2005, after a Red Sox game.</p>
        <p>''It was a lucky night,'' Mr. Ferraguto said. ''The Red Sox beat the Pirates, 6-5.''</p>
        <p>And, in a bar after the game, it was Mr. Ferraguto's turn to make a play. He saw Ms. Permar accidentally bump into one of his friends and seized the opportunity to start a conversation with her.</p>
        <p>He introduced himself and soon learned that she was from North Carolina.</p>
        <p>''I told her I went to school in North Carolina,'' he said.</p>
        <p>That piece of news interested Ms. Permar, whose younger brother and older sister had graduated from the University of North Carolina.</p>
        <p>But her smile quickly faded when she learned Mr. Ferraguto went to Duke, North Carolina's bitter sports rival.</p>
        <p>''Even though he gave the wrong answer,'' Ms. Permar said, ''I stayed in the conversation.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ferraguto admitted that their alma maters were ''a bit of a stumbling block,'' but said they soon got past it when they began discussing their mutual love for the state of North Carolina, former Senator John Edwards and running marathons. Coincidentally, each had run a marathon for the first time in the 1999 Marine Corps Marathon in Washington.</p>
        <p>''He seemed very sincere and was interested in hearing what I had to say,'' Ms. Permar said. ''I found him to be a lovable Duke alumni, which is very rare.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
