<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Normalcy Returns: Rivera Gets First Save</title>
    <meta content="29redsox" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/sports/baseball/29redsox.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843948"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Posada, Jorge</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Torre, Joe</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Steinbrenner, George M 3d</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E4DD133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="711" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Normalcy Returns: Rivera Gets First Save</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Normalcy Returns: Rivera Gets First Save</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAT BORZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Borzi, Pat</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first cut fastball that Mariano Rivera threw yesterday moved as it was supposed to: sharply, late and in to pinch-hitter Jason Varitek, a switch-hitter batting left-handed. That was the surest sign that Rivera's 22-game wait for his first save of the season was about to end.</p>
        <p>Varitek then blooped a single to right, another sign that the life had returned to Rivera's trademark cutter. Rivera retired the next three batters in order, with third baseman Alex Rodriguez contributing a nifty barehand pickup and throw on Julio Lugo's roller.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although it took Mariano Rivera nearly the entire first month of the season to get his first save, he maintained that he never lost confidence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first cut fastball that Mariano Rivera threw yesterday moved as it was supposed to: sharply, late and in to pinch-hitter Jason Varitek, a switch-hitter batting left-handed. That was the surest sign that Rivera's 22-game wait for his first save of the season was about to end.</p>
        <p>Varitek then blooped a single to right, another sign that the life had returned to Rivera's trademark cutter. Rivera retired the next three batters in order, with third baseman Alex Rodriguez contributing a nifty barehand pickup and throw on Julio Lugo's roller.</p>
        <p>It took Rivera 16 pitches to wrap up the Yankees' 3-1 victory against Boston at Yankee Stadium and end a seven-game losing streak that seemed to put Manager Joe Torre's job in jeopardy.</p>
        <p>Rivera, 37, has never been one to admit concern during the rare rough patches in his 12-plus seasons with the Yankees. Although it took Rivera nearly the entire first month of the season to get his first save, he maintained that he never lost confidence, even after being charged with four runs in a startlingly bad third of an inning Friday night.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't down at all,'' Rivera said. ''It has been tough. I'm not going to hide that. You all see that.''</p>
        <p>Before yesterday, Rivera had had only had two save chances this month. He had blown both in spectacular fashion, surrendering a three-run, game-ending homer to Marco Scutaro on April 15 in Oakland, then giving up two runs on three hits to lose again five days later at Boston.</p>
        <p>Rivera's ineffectiveness in Friday's 11-4 loss, when Torre brought him in with the Yankees three runs behind because Rivera needed work, put the ugliest of exclamation points on an awful night. Rivera said that he could not put his pitches where he wanted, and his cutter came in virtually straight. With one out, four consecutive Red Sox hitters reached base, on three singles and a walk, before Torre replaced Rivera with Mike Myers.</p>
        <p>Torre and Rivera insisted Friday that Rivera simply needed more work. The back-to-back appearances did not appear to have hurt his velocity or the movement of his pitches yesterday.</p>
        <p>''Mo was Mo,'' Torre said. ''He's certainly tenacious. You weren't going to take this away from him.''</p>
        <p>Except for the 1998 and 2003 seasons, when strained groin muscles landed Rivera on the disabled list, he had never gone this far into a season without a save. That No. 1 came against the Red Sox, the team that has given him more trouble than any other, was particularly telling.</p>
        <p>Since the 2004 All-Star Game break, Rivera has blown 7 of 21 save chances against the Red Sox and 8 of 89 against all the other teams in baseball, including postseason opponents. His earned run average against Boston is more than double what it is against the rest of baseball (4.65 to 1.80), and the Red Sox hit nearly 100 points higher against him than everyone else does (.291 to .196).</p>
        <p>After Varitek's hit, Rivera challenged Álex Cora, who tapped weakly toward the mound for a force play. Cora still runs well, and shortstop Derek Jeter chose not to risk a bad throw. After Rodriguez's fine play on Lugo, first baseman Kevin Youkilis popped out.</p>
        <p>''If you guys are worried about Mariano Rivera, he throws 94 miles an hour on his cutter,'' '' Youkilis said with equal measures of disbelief and disgust. ''Come on.</p>
        <p>''If we hit him, he's throwing like garbage. You never give the hitters any credit. If we don't hit him, he's Mariano Rivera. But he's one of the best closers in the game. You can't count him out.''</p>
        <p>Jeter said: ''I don't worry about Mo. The only time he gets in trouble is when he doesn't throw strikes. Today, the ball was moving.''</p>
        <p>Rivera made sure to praise Kei Igawa's six scoreless innings in relief of the injured Jeff Karstens. If not for Igawa, Rivera probably would not had this save chance at all.</p>
        <p>It will take months for Rivera to reduce his 10.57 E.R.A. to something less unsightly, but Saturday was a first step.</p>
        <p>''We all needed this, and a close game to win,'' Torre said. ''We needed a number of people to do the job, and we all did.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
