<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Places to Eat And Get Off Your Feet</title>
    <meta content="29dineweWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/29dinewe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843666"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/WHITE PLAINS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Forty Carrots (White Plains, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bloomingdale's Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cafe Nordstrom (White Plains, NY, Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Zodiac, The (White Plains, NY, Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nordstrom Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Neiman Marcus Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Westchester Mall (White Plains, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gabriel, Alice</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DB153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1206" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Places to Eat And Get Off Your Feet</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Places to Eat and Get Off Your Feet</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALICE GABRIEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gabriel, Alice</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alice Gabriel reviews Forty Carrots restaurant in Bloomingdale's, Cafe Nordstrom and The Zodiac restaurant in Nieman Marcus, all at The Westchester mall in White Plains, NY; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LACROSSE and baseball share their opening seasons with another popular sport and pastime: spring shopping. Straw hats and strappy sandals mark new beginnings, and White Plains, with its major department stores, is Westchester's material mecca. A serious shopper can burn a lot of calories walking the length of The Westchester, pulling clothes on and off in tight dressing rooms, parading around the shoe department in one pair of cute flats after another. So shoppers need nourishment, and the self-contained universes of Bloomingdale's, Nordstrom and Neiman Marcus can provide it.</p>
        <p>The Zodiac</p>
        <p>Adjacent to St. John Knits at Neiman Marcus, the Zodiac restaurant is a sleek refuge for pampered shoppers. The chairs are upholstered, the voices hushed. Signs of the zodiac are etched in chlorine-blue glass, and the chic menu covers are patterned with argyle diamonds and stripes. This is a place for grown-ups, with a particularly good selection of still and sparkling wines by the glass. (Try the crisp 2005 Verlegen sauvignon blanc, from the Stellenbosch region of South Africa.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shoppers need nourishment, and the self-contained universes of Bloomingdale’s, Nordstrom and Neiman Marcus can provide it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LACROSSE and baseball share their opening seasons with another popular sport and pastime: spring shopping. Straw hats and strappy sandals mark new beginnings, and White Plains, with its major department stores, is Westchester's material mecca. A serious shopper can burn a lot of calories walking the length of The Westchester, pulling clothes on and off in tight dressing rooms, parading around the shoe department in one pair of cute flats after another. So shoppers need nourishment, and the self-contained universes of Bloomingdale's, Nordstrom and Neiman Marcus can provide it.</p>
        <p>The Zodiac</p>
        <p>Adjacent to St. John Knits at Neiman Marcus, the Zodiac restaurant is a sleek refuge for pampered shoppers. The chairs are upholstered, the voices hushed. Signs of the zodiac are etched in chlorine-blue glass, and the chic menu covers are patterned with argyle diamonds and stripes. This is a place for grown-ups, with a particularly good selection of still and sparkling wines by the glass. (Try the crisp 2005 Verlegen sauvignon blanc, from the Stellenbosch region of South Africa.)</p>
        <p>The menu is broadly appealing, offering composed salads, upscale sandwiches and carefully calculated entrees. Roasted vegetables are layered on toasted ciabatta with fresh mozzarella and balsamic drizzle. Smoked salmon, vine-ripened tomatoes, capers, red onions, cucumber and dilled cream cheese are served on a toasted pumpernickel bagel. Loin of New Zealand lamb is bathed with a whole-grain mustard demi-glace. Desserts include a wonderfully coconutty coconut cake.</p>
        <p>I was charmed by the diminutive white cup of chicken consommé, an amuse bouche. The voluminous trademark popover that followed was dark brown and eggy, with a big marble of strawberry butter on the side. And a smooth, soothing cold mandarin orange soufflé came with a scoop of chicken salad nestled in radicchio, trim slices of carrot nut bread, and an assortment of fresh fruit. The plate was almost a caricature of the lunch upon which ladies lunch, and deeply satisfying.</p>
        <p>Cafe Nordstrom</p>
        <p>On the third floor at Nordstrom, a display of oversize down pillows, and notes drifting from the grand piano on the floor below, seem calculated to induce drowsiness. In fact, the store's gestalt could be described as something bordering on somnambulation.</p>
        <p>It was late afternoon when I visited, and the crowd had thinned at Cafe Nordstrom, where diners place their orders at the front register, pay in advance, and seat themselves. The space has all the charm of an airport restaurant, with stark décor and uninspired music. Once you sit down, expansive views to the north and west are obscured by concrete parapets.</p>
        <p>The cafe is one of four restaurant ''concepts'' trademarked by Nordstrom nationwide, and the menu has a corporate feel. The emphasis is on salads and sandwiches, but the food is dressier than at a diner. A twist on classic niçoise salad features seared salmon, French green beans, Kalamata olives and hard-cooked egg. Sandwiches include blackened chicken with avocado and cilantro lime aioli on jalapeño cheese bread and roast beef with horseradish mayonnaise, caramelized onion and watercress on rustic onion bread.</p>
        <p>I ordered a cup of crab and sweet corn chowder and, on the advice of the woman ahead of me in line, the blue cheese and pear salad. Unbidden, my waitress brought a tall glass of ice water, a nice touch, then later returned with a pallid white roll and the chowder. Lukewarm, with a texture best described as gludgy, the soup appeared to have been brought to a boil at some point in its past, causing the cream to separate. But the salad was in a different league altogether: a perfect mix of crisp romaine, dainty mesclun, juicy Anjou pear, slivered red onion, candied walnuts and a brisk champagne vinaigrette.</p>
        <p>Forty Carrots</p>
        <p>The legendary lunch counter on the fourth floor at Bloomingdale's is a great place to catch a second wind. Whitewashed plaster walls inlaid with rough boards strive for a European farmhouse effect. Most shoppers have at their feet the day's trophies in Bloomingdale's signature Little and Big Brown Bags. The chit-chat flies; even single diners engage their BlackBerries and cellphones.</p>
        <p>Forty Carrots offers healthy soups, salads and sandwiches, as well as light entrees and double-thick milkshakes. The vegetarian chopped salad is a greengrocer's dream: spinach, romaine and baby greens tossed with chopped cucumber, artichokes, red onion, roasted red peppers, shredded carrots, tomatoes and a scattering of Gorgonzola. Other favorites include lively tuna salad sandwiches and egg-white omelets with crisp fries.</p>
        <p>But Bloomie's famous frozen yogurt is queen. When I visited in the early afternoon, a handful of diners poked at salads, but almost everyone else seemed to have ordered a big whorl of snow-white yogurt, served in a glass bowl set on a doily; they rested their elbows on the counter, spoons poised, dreamily sculpting the smooth mounds and sipping hot coffee in a prescribed suburban ritual.</p>
        <p>I happily joined in, ordering a small plain-and-hazelnut twist with a side of strawberries. (Toppings include wildflower honey, walnuts, wheat germ, coconut, granola, melba sauce or sprinkles, but most customers ordered their yogurt straight up, pure and simple.) The plain yogurt had a pleasant zing, reminiscent of lemon extract, and the nonfat hazelnut was surprisingly rich and delicious.</p>
        <p>A few seats to my right, a lone gentleman among the two dozen women at the counter had a different ritual. After ordering, in quick succession, two glasses of pinot grigio, he turned sheepishly to the young woman next to him and said, ''When my wife is shopping, I need two.''</p>
        <p>Shop and Drop</p>
        <p>Located within major department stores in White Plains, these restaurants are busiest at lunch or in the late afternoon. Cafe Nordstrom, with its kids menu and high chairs, is well-suited to children. Forty Carrots, with its tall counter stools, is less so, but I noted many youngsters at La Provence, a more traditional restaurant with a children's menu adjacent to Forty Carrots. The Zodiac is mostly for adults. although it does have a children's menu; toddlers might be better served just beyond Neiman Marcus at the City Limits Diner, with its telltale fleet of strollers parked outside.</p>
        <p>FORTY CARROTS, Bloomingdale's, 175 Bloomingdale Road; (914) 684-6200. Open Monday to Saturday, 11:30 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sunday, noon to 4:30 p.m. All salads, sandwiches and entrees are under $10. Frozen yogurt is $3.75 (small) and $4.50 (large); toppings and fresh fruit are extra. Pinot grigio and pinot noir are available by the glass ($5.50). Major credit cards accepted.</p>
        <p>CAFE NORDSTROM , Nordstrom, 130 Westchester Avenue, (914) 946-1122. Open Monday to Thursday, 10 a.m. to 7 p.m.; Friday and Saturday, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Sunday, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. All salads, sandwiches and entrees are under $10. No alcohol served. Major credit cards accepted.</p>
        <p>THE ZODIAC, Neiman Marcus, Maple and Paulding Avenues, (914) 428-2000. Open Monday to Saturday, 11:30 a.m. to 4 p.m.; closed Sunday. Salads, $13.75 to $18; sandwiches, $11.75 to $14; entrees, $13.50 to $18. (Shoebox lunches, which include the famous Neiman Marcus chocolate chip cookie, can be ordered to go.) Wines by the glass are $8 to $14. Neiman Marcus accepts cash, personal checks and Neiman Marcus, Bergdorf Goodman, American Express and JCB cards only.</p>
        <p>ALICE GABRIEL</p>
        <p>DINING/WHITE PLAINS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
