<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Savings in Cutting Out the Middle Men</title>
    <meta content="29chass" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/sports/baseball/29chass.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843901"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Baltimore Orioles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cleveland Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Schoeneweis, Scott</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Minaya, Omar</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Julio, Jorge</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE2DE133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1694" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Savings in Cutting Out the Middle Men</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">No Savings in Cutting Out the Middle Men</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>More than 10 times in the past week, relief pitchers have given starters reasons to hate them. In fact, it's an interesting dynamic that such feelings don't develop. Pitchers, though, are part of a close-knit fraternity. They understand these things.</p>
        <p>In the past week, these things included unwanted developments in the sixth, seventh, eighth and ninth innings. All resulted in the starters losing leads they had when they left their games and losing their chances for a victory. In the case of Tom Glavine, it cost him his 294th victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Failing to hold leads is not a new development for relief pitchers, but in today’s game of six-inning baseball, the work of relievers has become all the more important.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>More than 10 times in the past week, relief pitchers have given starters reasons to hate them. In fact, it's an interesting dynamic that such feelings don't develop. Pitchers, though, are part of a close-knit fraternity. They understand these things.</p>
        <p>In the past week, these things included unwanted developments in the sixth, seventh, eighth and ninth innings. All resulted in the starters losing leads they had when they left their games and losing their chances for a victory. In the case of Tom Glavine, it cost him his 294th victory.</p>
        <p>Glavine left the Mets' game with a 6-3 lead last Sunday, but Édgar Rentería's three-run home run against Scott Schoeneweis in the seventh inning pulled Atlanta into a 6-6 tie. The same day, James Shields of Tampa Bay and Jon Garland of the Chicago White Sox left after the eighth inning with leads, and Chad Gaudin of Oakland left after the sixth with a lead. Their teams all ended up losing.</p>
        <p>During the next five days, Joe Kennedy of Oakland and Aníbel Sánchez of Florida (after five innings), Carlos Zambrano of the Chicago Cubs (in the sixth), Adam Loewen of Baltimore and Jason Bergmann of Washington (both after six) and Chien-Ming Wang of the Yankees and Clay Hensley of San Diego (in the seventh) left games with leads, only to watch relievers squander them. The same happened to Jake Peavy of San Diego and Zach Duke of Pittsburgh, who left after seven innings.</p>
        <p>Failing to hold leads is not a new development for relief pitchers, but in today's game of six-inning baseball, in which the duration of pitchers' starts has shrunk, the work of relievers has become all the more important.</p>
        <p>Forget closers. The pitchers who come before them, after the starters finish their work, have become more critical to the outcome of a game.</p>
        <p>The shrinking start has not been a sudden development. It has been gradual, but there is no turning back. Figures researched by the Elias Sports Bureau tell the tale.</p>
        <p>Taking the last 15 years into account, Elias found that the average length of a start has dwindled from 6.2 innings in 1992 to 5.9 in 1999 to 5.82 last season.</p>
        <p>Similarly, the percentage of pitchers lasting six innings has shrunk from 65.7 to 60.4 to 59.3. The percentage lasting seven innings has gone from 44 to 34.2 to 31. The percentage making it through eight innings has fallen from 21.7 to 13 to 9.6. The percentage of pitchers throwing complete games has dropped from 9.9 to 4.9 to 3.</p>
        <p>Little wonder that some teams have placed a premium on bolstering their bullpens, signing relievers as free agents, trading for relievers or starting to develop them in their minor league systems.</p>
        <p>''Unless you have four or five guys who are going to be high-quality starters, you need a bullpen,'' said Omar Minaya, the Mets' general manager, who has spent the past two winters fortifying his bullpen.</p>
        <p>Two winters ago, he signed Billy Wagner to be the Mets' closer and traded for Duaner Sánchez and Jorge Julio. Last season, he traded for Roberto Hernández and Guillermo Mota. Over the winter, he traded for Ambiorix Burgos and signed Schoeneweis. Then in the spring, in what could turn into one of the Mets' best long-term moves, they promoted the 23-year-old Joe Smith to the major league roster.</p>
        <p>Other teams have also been busy fortifying their bullpens. In the off-season, Atlanta traded for Rafael Soriano and Mike Gonzalez and re-signed Bob Wickman, whom they traded for last season. Baltimore signed Danys Báez, Chad Bradford, Jamie Walker and Scott Williamson, and Cleveland signed Joe Borowski, Aaron Fultz and Hernández.</p>
        <p>The Indians and the Orioles began the weekend with the third- and fourth-most effective bullpens in the American League. Although their relievers had a tough week, the Mets remained No. 1 in the majors with a 2.27 earned run average, up from 1.59 a week ago.</p>
        <p>The Mets were No. 1 in the National League last season, but in the A.L. the Indians were 11th and the Orioles 13th.</p>
        <p>''We committed significant dollars, but all one-year deals,'' said Mark Shapiro, the Indians' general manager. ''One-year deals give you the ability to react and make adjustments as the season goes along because of injury or lack of performance.''</p>
        <p>Jim Duquette, the Orioles' vice president for baseball operations, has acknowledged following Minaya's model.</p>
        <p>The demand for relief pitchers has forced their price up. It has also placed a premium on the best relievers, because relievers are notorious for their inconsistency from season to season.</p>
        <p>''I still feel the best way to build a good bullpen is to do it internally,'' said Shapiro, who identified three relievers the Indians are developing: Tom Mastny, who is with the team now because of injuries; Edward Mujica; and Tony Sipp.</p>
        <p>Minaya has done well trading for relievers, but his best addition may turn out to be the team's third-round pick in the 2006 amateur draft, the right-handed Smith. He has been so good in his early appearances that he may influence teams to select more relief pitchers in higher rounds during the amateur draft in June.</p>
        <p>''He throws strikes with all his pitches,'' Minaya said. ''It's very rare that you see a young man who can throw strikes with all of his pitches and any time in the count.''</p>
        <p>Smith so impressed the Mets, Minaya added, that when Sánchez was lost for the season last July, ''we considered bringing him up.''</p>
        <p>They didn't, but he is in the team's bullpen now. After a scoreless inning in the Mets' 4-3 loss Friday, he had relieved in 13 games for a total of 12 innings, allowing no runs and seven hits while striking out 13.</p>
        <p>Green Improves Hitting</p>
        <p>When the Mets acquired Shawn Green from Arizona in August, they appeared to be getting a hitter who was beyond his prime. He did nothing with the Mets to alter that perception, batting .257 in 34 games for the Mets.</p>
        <p>But Green, a 34-year-old right fielder, has demonstrated this month that he has plenty of hits left in his bats. After going 2 for 4 Friday night, he was hitting .358, sixth in the National League.</p>
        <p>''I worked a lot in spring training and ironed out a bad kink in my swing,'' said Green, whose only season as a .300 hitter came in 1999 with Toronto. ''I think that work is starting to pay off, I hope. It's early in the year, but I feel really good up there.''</p>
        <p>What did he discover he was doing wrong in his swing? ''My hands were drifting forward too much,'' Green said. ''Now I keep them back. I picked it up during the winter.''</p>
        <p>Now he looks forward to a productive summer.</p>
        <p>April Isn't His Month</p>
        <p>When the Pittsburgh Pirates traded for Adam LaRoche in January, they explained that they needed a solid left-handed hitter to improve their lineup against right-handed pitchers. LaRoche has not disappointed them -- that is, he has performed in the first month of the season exactly the way he has always performed in the first month of the season. He hasn't hit.</p>
        <p>LaRoche was hitting .123 after going 1 for 3 in Friday's game. A year ago, he hit .200 in the first month. In the first three years of his career, he was a .206 first-month hitter.</p>
        <p>The Pirates, however, have good things to look forward to. Once LaRoche got past April last season, he batted .300. For his career, his average outside April is .286.</p>
        <p>April Isn't Their Month Either</p>
        <p>Adam LaRoche is not the only first baseman coping with a lack of hits. Carlos Delgado of the Mets woke up yesterday hitting .195, Richie Sexson of Seattle .148, Doug Mientkiewicz of the Yankees .140, Craig Wilson of Atlanta .174 and Ryan Shealy of Kansas City .096.</p>
        <p>But if first basemen think they are having trouble, they won't receive any sympathy from third basemen: Kevin Kouzmanoff of San Diego was hitting .117, Brandon Inge of Detroit .129, Wilson Betemit of the Los Angeles Dodgers .133, Alex Gordon of Kansas City .153 and Edwin Encarnación of Cincinnati .174.</p>
        <p>Then there are the hit-deprived catchers: Gerald Laird of Texas, .140; David Ross of Cincinnati, .146; Gregg Zaun of Toronto, .186; Brian Schneider of Washington, .194; and Jason Kendall of Oakland, .183.</p>
        <p>It's Too Early to Judge</p>
        <p>It has never been wise to judge players and teams on their April performances, so judgment should be reserved in at least some cases this early in the season.</p>
        <p>The San Francisco Giants are an example. Which are the real Giants? Most so-called experts wrote them off before the season, many predicting that the Giants would finish last in the National League West.</p>
        <p>When the Giants began the season with eight losses in their first 12 games, they were in last place and seemed destined to fulfill the predictions. But after the Giants sustained their eighth loss on April 17 in Colorado, they embarked on an eight-game winning streak and moved briefly into first place. The streak ended Friday night.</p>
        <p>The Philadelphia Phillies -- proclaimed ''the team to beat'' by their shortstop, Jimmy Rollins -- began the season as a team everyone beat, losing 11 of their first 15 games. Just when it seemed they could be written off as an early also-ran, the Phillies won five in a row. They still look like an early also-ran, but give them a little more time to bury themselves.</p>
        <p>Cubs fans expected Lou Piniella to perform feats of magic, but instead Chicago's North Side team has threatened to disappear from contention before the race starts. Milwaukee and Pittsburgh are the teams taking advantage of the weak National League Central, at least temporarily.</p>
        <p>In the American League Central, on the other hand, the Cleveland Indians are showing signs that they might be this year's Detroit Tigers. The Indians were a disappointment last season, playing far below their talent level, so they were poised to take huge strides toward the contending status they were expected to have last year.</p>
        <p>But the season is early for the Indians, too.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
