<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LIVING IN/Pleasant Plains, S.I.; If It Stayed the Same, That Would Be Different</title>
    <meta content="29livi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/realestate/29livi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070429T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843724"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Living In | Pleasant Plains, S.I."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pleasant Plains (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilson, Claire</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Staten Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Staten Island (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500EFD7153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1726" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LIVING IN/Pleasant Plains, S.I.; If It Stayed the Same, That Would Be Different</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">If It Stayed the Same, That Would Be Different</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAIRE WILSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilson, Claire</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Living In article on Pleasant Plains, Staten Island; maps; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHANGE has been the one constant in Pleasant Plains, a small, once sleepy hamlet on Raritan Bay close to the southernmost tip of Staten Island.</p>
        <p>Towering old trees define the hamlet, which in the last census had a population of nearly 5,000, and which is best described as a patchwork of residential pockets scattered among swaths of wetlands, woods and waterfront conservation area.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Change has been the one constant in Pleasant Plains, a small, once sleepy hamlet on Raritan Bay close to the southernmost tip of Staten Island.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CHANGE has been the one constant in Pleasant Plains, a small, once sleepy hamlet on Raritan Bay close to the southernmost tip of Staten Island.</p>
        <p>Towering old trees define the hamlet, which in the last census had a population of nearly 5,000, and which is best described as a patchwork of residential pockets scattered among swaths of wetlands, woods and waterfront conservation area.</p>
        <p>But in the last five years, storm and sanitary sewers and new water mains have been installed, and zoning has been adjusted to protect Pleasant Plains's 1.6 square miles from the building of houses on too-small parcels -- which had been happening with some regularity.</p>
        <p>Modifications like this never occur in a vacuum, of course, and the town has its share of vocal advocates on each side of the zoning question.</p>
        <p>Marie Bodnar, district manager of Community Board 3, comes down on the side of more protective zoning. ''Overdevelopment has been a problem throughout the South Shore,'' she said in a recent interview, during which she expressed satisfaction with the changes. ''Now, a builder can't take down one house and put up three.''</p>
        <p>Randy Lee, chief executive of the Leewood Real Estate Group, the developer of the 22-home Estates at Opal Ridge in Pleasant Plains, takes the opposing stance. He contends that any such zoning restrictions should be deferred until the entire borough is subjected to planners' scrutiny and a comprehensive master plan emerges on judicious development.</p>
        <p>''All downzoning does is increase the minimum size of the lot, making the resulting lots more expensive and the houses that are built on them more expensive,'' said Mr. Lee, who is also chairman of the Staten Island Economic Development Corporation. ''The goal of the proposers is to just have million-dollar houses that only rich people can afford.''</p>
        <p>But anything that preserves open space can only be an asset to Dennis D. Dell'Angelo, an architect who is president of the Pleasant Plains/Princes' Bay/Richmond Valley Civic Association. ''A lot of people move here because of the open space and the feeling you get in those neighborhoods,'' said Mr. Dell'Angelo.</p>
        <p>Although he sings the praises of local schools and emphasizes the safety of Pleasant Plains -- citing its low crime rates -- he acknowledges that it is the closeness to nature and the small-town ambience that residents seem to love the most.</p>
        <p>''It is a small community that people have pride in,'' he said. It is also a homogeneous community, by city standards -- 92 percent white, according to census data.</p>
        <p>What You'll Find</p>
        <p>Pleasant Plains is bordered by the waterfront to the east, the property of the Mission of the Immaculate Virgin-Mount Loretto to the south, the Korean War Veterans Parkway to the north and, to the west, a vague line created by Lemon Creek, Bayview Avenue and Lenevar Avenue, according to Mr. Dell'Angelo. But he and other residents concur that the borders with adjacent communities of Princes' Bay and Richmond Valley are fuzzy at best.</p>
        <p>The houses are a mix of new mansion-style homes on large plots of land, some town homes and many two-family units with studio or one-bedroom rental apartments. Some blocks have clusters of older Victorian-style homes and 1920s side-hall colonials on dead-end streets without curbs or sidewalks.</p>
        <p>Two houses are being considered for landmark status, one a Second Empire structure built in the 1880s and the other an 1850s Greek Revival. If they are named landmarks, they will be the only two buildings in Pleasant Plains to be so designated.</p>
        <p>Jack Chadwick, a sergeant with the Triborough Bridge and Tunnel Authority, bought ''the worst house in the nicest neighborhood'' about eight years ago when he moved in from Mariner's Harbor, also on Staten Island. He tore the house down and built a new one, then acquired adjoining land to ensure that the woodsy environment would be maintained. A collector of Ford Mustangs that he has restored, he enjoys the amenities of being part of the city but without the downside of traffic, pollution and noise. Above all, he said, Pleasant Plains is an excellent place to raise his three daughters, who attend local schools.</p>
        <p>''Everybody knows me and my kids,'' said Mr. Chadwick, whose annual Christmas lights extravaganza, held on his lawn the weekend after Thanksgiving as a neighborhood inaugural of the holiday season, has made him something of a local celebrity. ''It's nice to know that if they're out, somebody is going to be looking out for them.''</p>
        <p>What You'll Pay</p>
        <p>The current inventory of houses for sale is about 18, according to Adam Weintraub, owner of the Berns Agency, a local realty company.</p>
        <p>But with a number of new homes coming to market in the last year, prices have dropped 10 or 15 percent, said Fred Shayewitz, an agent with Richmond Homes/GMAC. ''The tide has turned from an active sellers' market to a soft buyers' market,'' he said. ''Buyers are in command.''</p>
        <p>Adrienne Setbon, a broker with Own-a-Home Realty, is the exclusive representative for a community of 22 one- and two-family detached homes still under construction. Asking prices for a one-family unit with three or four bedrooms and three and a half baths start at $789,000.</p>
        <p>According to Ms. Setbon, new detached homes in Pleasant Plains generally start at $800,000, while semiattached units average around $675,000, and town homes, which zoning no longer allows, typically resell for about $550,000.</p>
        <p>Older homes, often on large parcels, are less expensive. Mr. Weintraub said a 1935 three-bedroom, one-and-a-half-bath colonial on a 75-by-171-foot lot sold recently for $631,000, while another, also a three-bedroom, one-and-a-half-bath, built in 1909, sold for $675,000. Its lot measured 106 by 109 feet.</p>
        <p>Among Mr. Weintraub's current listings is a 70-by-160-foot buildable lot on a dead-end street that backs onto a nature preserve with a small pond. The asking price is $699,000.</p>
        <p>Rental units in the community are most often in newer two-family homes. Studios run about $750 a month, while one-bedroom units are about $900 a month, Mr. Weintraub said. Rentals at the new Opal Ridge are $850 a month for a one-bedroom, according to Ms. Setbon.</p>
        <p>What to Do</p>
        <p>The environs of Pleasant Plains are great for walking and bicycling. There is a public fishing pier at the end of Sharrott Avenue, adjacent to a seaside nature preserve. Five minutes away by car or bus, the 17th-century fieldstone Conference House is famous as the site of a peace conference on Sept. 11, 1776, an ill-fated attempt to avert the Revolutionary War. The park has a gazebo looking out over the Arthur Kill and a busy calendar of events.</p>
        <p>The Catholic Youth Organization center at the Mission of the Immaculate Virgin, also known as Drumgoole Village at Mount Loretto, has programs for young people that include basketball, indoor soccer and summer camp. It also plays host to about 200 seniors a day from the Tottenville and Pleasant Plains Senior Citizens Friendship Clubs, in conjunction with the New York City Department for the Aging.</p>
        <p>Shopping options include small stores near the train station, as well as nearby Amboy Plaza, which has a Waldbaum's supermarket, Eckerd drugstore and Dunkin' Donuts.</p>
        <p>The Staten Island Mall is about seven minutes away by car. Also less than 10 minutes away near the Outerbridge Crossing are Target and Home Depot, among others.</p>
        <p>The Woodbridge Center in Woodbridge, N.J., is also a popular destination. ''You are so close to the Outerbridge you can go shopping in Jersey where there are no taxes,'' said Barbara Corregano, an independent broker.</p>
        <p>The Commute</p>
        <p>The AE7 Atlantic Express bus goes to Midtown Manhattan from a lot at the intersection of the West Shore Expressway and the Korean War Veterans Memorial Parkway. The trip takes about an hour and 20 minutes; monthly tickets are $228.</p>
        <p>Taking the Staten Island Railway to the Staten Island Ferry takes 27 minutes and costs $2. The ferry to Manhattan takes 25 minutes and is free; transfer to the subway is free.</p>
        <p>The rush-hour commute by car can take one hour and 25 minutes. According to David Solowitz, a construction worker who commutes from Pleasant Plains to points around the city by car, the traffic on the Staten Island Expressway ''is really bad, especially at rush hour.''</p>
        <p>The Schools</p>
        <p>Public schools in the area are highly regarded. Public School 3 on South Goff Avenue has about 720 students in prekindergarten through Grade 5. Of fourth graders in the academic year ended in 2006, 85.6 percent scored at or above grade level in English, compared with 60.4 percent of fourth graders citywide. In math, the number was 94 percent, versus 78.3 percent citywide.</p>
        <p>Two schools teach Grades 6 through 8. At Intermediate School 34 on Academy Street, 68.3 percent of eighth graders scored at or above grade level in English in 2006, compared with 32.9 percent citywide. In math, the number was 67.5 percent, versus 40.9 percent citywide. Among eighth graders at Intermediate School 7 on Huguenot Avenue, 71.3 percent scored at or above grade level in English, 72.2 percent in math.</p>
        <p>Tottenville High School on Luten Avenue offers Grades 9 through 12; enrollment is about 3,700. SAT averages in 2005 were 478 on the verbal portion, versus 497 statewide, and 487 on math, versus 511 statewide.</p>
        <p>One private option is the Roman Catholic St. Joseph-St. Thomas School on Maguire Avenue. According to the principal, JoAnn Gaal, 330 are enrolled in prekindergarten through Grade 8. Tuition is $3,200 a year for parishioners. Nearby religious schools for Grades 9 through 12 include the Roman Catholic St. Joseph-by-the-Sea and the boys-only Yeshiva of Staten Island.</p>
        <p>The History</p>
        <p>Pleasant Plains remained largely undeveloped until well into the 20th century. It got its name in 1860, when it was designated a stop on the new railroad, and a commercial hub sprang up around the train station, according to the Encyclopedia of the City of New York.</p>
        <p>It is best known as the site of Mount Loretto, or the Mission of the Immaculate Virgin, a Lower Manhattan orphanage that moved to Pleasant Plains in the early 1880s. Scenes from ''The Godfather'' were shot there.</p>
        <p>A Snapshot</p>
        <p>Large open spaces woven in among the residential pockets help preserve the uncongested and quiet feel of the area, whose many dead-end streets and cul-de-sacs are safe havens for children.</p>
        <p>Living In | Pleasant Plains, S.I.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 29, 2007, Sunday  The ''Living In'' article in the Real Estate section this weekend, about Pleasant Plains, Staten Island, incorrectly describes the borders of the neighborhood. As correctly shown on the map with the article, Pleasant Plains is bordered on the south by the waterfront, on the west by Cunningham Road, on the north by the Korean War Veterans Parkway and on the east by a vague line created by Lemon Creek, Bayview Avenue and Lenevar Avenue.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 28, 2007, Saturday  The ''Living In'' article in the Real Estate section this weekend, about Pleasant Plains, Staten Island, incorrectly describes the borders of the neighborhood. As correctly shown on the map with the article, Pleasant Plains is bordered on the south by the waterfront, on the west by Cunningham Road, on the north by the Korean War Veterans Parkway and on the east by a vague line created by Lemon Creek, Bayview Avenue and Lenevar Avenue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 29, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>The ''Living In'' article in the Real Estate section this weekend, about Pleasant Plains, Staten Island, incorrectly describes the borders of the neighborhood. As correctly shown on the map with the article, Pleasant Plains is bordered on the south by the waterfront, on the west by Cunningham Road, on the north by the Korean War Veterans Parkway and on the east by a vague line created by Lemon Creek, Bayview Avenue and Lenevar Avenue.</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>Correction: April 28, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>The ''Living In'' article in the Real Estate section this weekend, about Pleasant Plains, Staten Island, incorrectly describes the borders of the neighborhood. As correctly shown on the map with the article, Pleasant Plains is bordered on the south by the waterfront, on the west by Cunningham Road, on the north by the Korean War Veterans Parkway and on the east by a vague line created by Lemon Creek, Bayview Avenue and Lenevar Avenue.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
