<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: Questions for Russell Simmons; Hip-Hop Guru</title>
    <meta content="29wwln--Q4.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/magazine/29wwlnQ4.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843569"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Questions for Russell Simmons"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/John Edwards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Rap Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rap Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Def Jam</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Simmons, Russell</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Imus, Don</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Edwards, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Obama, Barack</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Winfrey, Oprah</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Trump, Donald J</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500EED8173EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="662" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: Questions for Russell Simmons; Hip-Hop Guru</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hip-Hop Guru</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Deborah Solomon</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Solomon, Deborah</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the co-founder of Def Jam Recordings and the so-called C.E.O. of hip-hop, do you think the outrage over Don Imus's prickly language and his firing might broaden into a crusade against song lyrics? It already has broadened to lyrics. It's been that way since 1983. They've been yelling at me from Run-D.M.C. and the Beastie Boys till now.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The rap producer and clothing designer talks about whyhe prefers John Edwards to Barack Obama, the importance of meditation and what’s so spiritual about Donald Trump.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the co-founder of Def Jam Recordings and the so-called C.E.O. of hip-hop, do you think the outrage over Don Imus's prickly language and his firing might broaden into a crusade against song lyrics? It already has broadened to lyrics. It's been that way since 1983. They've been yelling at me from Run-D.M.C. and the Beastie Boys till now.</p>
        <p>What do you make of Barack Obama, who recently said that rap musicians should reform their lyrics? What we need to reform is the conditions that create these lyrics. Obama needs to reform the conditions of poverty. I wish he really did raise his money on the Internet, like he said. I wish he really did raise his money independently.</p>
        <p>What are you saying? I think about one-fourth of his campaign contributions came from small donations made over the Internet, even though he collected more than any other Democratic candidate from Wall Street people. So at the end of the day, he's controlled, too. That's my point. He's a mouse, too, like everybody else.</p>
        <p>Are there any presidential candidates who inspire you? I talk to John Edwards more than I talk to anyone. He has said more things about the conditions we need to think about. He went to yoga with me. He did the whole class, an hour and a half. He sweated like crazy. He's in good shape, but it was hard on him.</p>
        <p>You write extensively about your devotion to yoga in your new self-help book, ''Do You!''</p>
        <p>Is the title your own coinage? No. It's an old hip-hop expression: ''Do you!'' It's just something we say all the time. It means do what you want to do. Do what inspires you. Don't be a sheep. Keep it real. The book was originally called ''Russell Simmons' Laws of Success.''</p>
        <p>Really? That's pretty generic. Oprah renamed the book. It was like God calling. She gave me a better title.</p>
        <p>Your book basically advocates for old-fashioned American values -- i.e., work hard, don't give up. The book doesn't say just work hard. It says meditate. That's the most important thing in the book. I go to yoga every day. I meditate every morning. Do you meditate?</p>
        <p>I prefer reading in bed. That for me is meditation. No it's not. It's noise. It's the opposite.</p>
        <p>To be awake is to be fully present, no noise, just you and God. Most of us only have seconds of full consciousness. To live in a state of samadhi -- that's what we're here for.</p>
        <p>Why did you, a self-proclaimed seeker of spiritual truths, ask Donald Trump, of all people, to write the foreword to the book? I think it's all God. I say that all day long. The real process is doing you and having a truth that you live up to. Donald is different than a lot of other very rich people. He has a good time. He is always laughing. He's into doing him.</p>
        <p>In the years since you sold your stake in Def Jam, you've gone into the fashion business and developed clothing lines like Phat Farm and Baby Phat. Do you still run them with your wife, Kimora Lee? We're separated. She works upstairs. People do think it's inspiring the way we handle our partnership.</p>
        <p>You're known for dating models. What do they offer besides flawless skin? They're better than actresses. Actresses are kind of a little crazy.</p>
        <p>There are other women besides models and actresses. Why don't you try dating, say, a professor the next time around? A professor? I can barely read.</p>
        <p>Are you dyslexic? No. I can read. But I can't understand anything. I just read ''The Autobiography of a Yogi,'' by Paramahansa Yogananda, over and over again.</p>
        <p>Do you see a therapist? Why? You think I'm crazy?</p>
        <p>No, but you seem to have a heightened need for stimulation. Unfortunately, I do. My nickname is Rush, but I practice yoga every day so I can rush less.</p>
        <p>Deborah Solomon</p>
        <p>Questions for Russell Simmons</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
