<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Actress With Doubts, But Not About Directing</title>
    <meta content="29osta" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/movies/29osta.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070506T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843608"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Onstad, Katrina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Polley, Sarah</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Away From Her (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals/Sundance Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sundance Film Festival (Park City, Utah)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sundance Film Festival (Park City, Utah)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sundance Film Festival (Park City, Utah)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Polley, Sarah</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Away From Her (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EFDB143EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1874" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Actress With Doubts, But Not About Directing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Actress With Doubts, but Not About Directing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATRINA ONSTAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Onstad, Katrina</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles indie film director Sarah Polley, whose new film Away from Her has just been released; her career as child star in Canada discussed; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF Sarah Polley were a country, she would be on high alert, code orange. The fine-boned veteran actress seemed to hover above the restaurant banquette where she sat, her huge blue eyes apparently unburdened by eyelids. She was expounding on the slippery sensation of being interviewed.</p>
        <p>''I'm actually a really gregarious, loud person who laughs a lot, but if you get me into an interview, I start playing a role of myself instead of myself, and accommodating this image of me that's very serious,'' she said. ''So these days I'm trying to be less precious, less earnest, and not worry about it so much.'' She paused, then burst out laughing. ''Oh, God. I sound earnest about not being earnest!''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Actress Sarah Polley joins the ranks of indie auteurs with the release of her first feature, “Away From Her.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF Sarah Polley were a country, she would be on high alert, code orange. The fine-boned veteran actress seemed to hover above the restaurant banquette where she sat, her huge blue eyes apparently unburdened by eyelids. She was expounding on the slippery sensation of being interviewed.</p>
        <p>''I'm actually a really gregarious, loud person who laughs a lot, but if you get me into an interview, I start playing a role of myself instead of myself, and accommodating this image of me that's very serious,'' she said. ''So these days I'm trying to be less precious, less earnest, and not worry about it so much.'' She paused, then burst out laughing. ''Oh, God. I sound earnest about not being earnest!''</p>
        <p>Earnestness may not be of much use to the average young movie star, but it's a quality befitting a writer-director, which Ms. Polley, at 28, has become. Next month, before sitting on the jury at the Cannes Film Festival, she joins the ranks of indie auteurs with the release of her first feature, ''Away From Her.''</p>
        <p>Over lunch in the heart of the fast-gentrifying downtown neighborhood where she lives, Ms. Polley was reflective, particularly about her struggle to reconcile a social conscience with the narrow expectations Hollywood maintains for beautiful blondes. In 1999, she was the one starlet on the crowded cover of Vanity Fair's Hollywood issue who publicly scolded the magazine for crediting Tommy Hilfiger as her clothier when the overalls she wore actually came from a vintage store in Toronto, purchased by her own hand. With a few exceptions -- dealing ecstasy and hanging with Katie Holmes in ''Go,'' slaying zombies in the remake of ''Dawn of the Dead'' -- Ms. Polley the actress has rarely left the borders of the independent film world. She has worked with a long list of the best studio-free directors around, including Atom Egoyan (on ''Exotica'' and ''The Sweet Hereafter''), Wim Wenders (''Don't Come Knocking'') and David Cronenberg (''eXistenZ'').</p>
        <p>''Away From Her'' keeps her squarely in the independent milieu. An adaptation of the Alice Munro short story ''The Bear Came Over the Mountain,'' it features a rare lead performance from Julie Christie, who stars opposite the pedigreed Canadian actor Gordon Pinsent (''The Shipping News''). The pair play Fiona and Grant, a long-married couple confronting Fiona's Alzheimer's. Fiona enters a nursing home, and Grant watches -- helplessly at first, then furiously -- as his wife becomes inexplicably bonded to another patient, a mute in a wheelchair played by Michael Murphy (''Manhattan'').</p>
        <p>Shot in the bitter cold of rural southern Ontario on a modest budget of $4 million Canadian (Lionsgate has picked up distribution), this thoughtful, measured film about the slow drift of memory and marriage has received excellent notices at a string of film festivals, and opens in New York and Los Angeles on Friday before rolling out across the country later in the month.</p>
        <p>Ms. Polley read the short story in The New Yorker on a plane ride from Iceland in 2001, where she had just finished shooting the Hal Hartley celebrity parable ''No Such Thing.'' She was in the early stages of a relationship with the man who would become her husband, a Toronto film editor named David Wharnsby. By the time she landed, Ms. Polley had conceived the film version of the story in her mind as an investigation into the longevity (and, within that, the cruelty and grace) of love.</p>
        <p>''I think we have a really hard time culturally with what happens to love after the first year. It is difficult, and it is painful, and it is a letdown,'' said Ms. Polley, who married in 2003. ''That first year is so much less profound than what happens when you're actually left with each other and yourself in an honest way. It was interesting to me to make a film about what love looked like after life had gotten in the way, and what remained.''</p>
        <p>High-minded literary adaptations are not the most common conclusion to the child-star story, but Ms. Polley's short life is a narrative of surprising, sometimes brutal swerves. She comes from a creative Toronto family with five children headed by a casting-director mother, Diane, and an actor father, Michael (currently seen on the Sundance Channel's theater satire ''Slings and Arrows,'' on which Sarah Polley makes occasional, uncharacteristically comedic appearances). The family mythology maintains that Sarah was an acting-obsessed toddler who grabbed scripts off the coffee table and demanded auditions, landing her first role at age 5 in the film ''One Magic Christmas.''</p>
        <p>While Ms. Polley does not blame her parents for failing to dissuade her, she said that she would never allow her hypothetical children to perform professionally. ''When an 8-year-old wants to become a fireman, you go, 'Look, go and play with these toys and pretend you're a fireman.' Why do we let kids who want to act become actors?''</p>
        <p>At 8, Ms. Polley played the urchin Sally Salt in Terry Gilliam's ''Adventures of Baron Munchausen,'' which also starred Robin Williams and Uma Thurman in small roles. For her, the experience was traumatic: 18-hour days on a set in Spain, and hospital trips for hypothermia and an irregular heart rate caused by an explosion that went off near her head.</p>
        <p>''Baron Munchausen,'' she said, ''really defined me in terms of never really wanting to be on huge films ever, and really focusing on independent films. There's a real fear in me of never wanting to be in an unsafe environment again.''</p>
        <p>Doug Liman, a good friend of Ms. Polley's who directed her in ''Go,'' is a victim of her wariness. ''I've offered Sarah a part in everything I've made since 'Go,' including the female lead in 'The Bourne Identity,' and she keeps turning me down,'' he said. ''She has a tremendous amount of ambivalence about this profession, but that makes her a better actress. She has no interest in seeing herself in a magazine, but she does have an acute sensitivity to real human beings. Even going out for lunch with her, it's hard to scream, 'Where's my Diet Coke?' when Sarah has just been incredibly kind to the waitress.''</p>
        <p>Post-Gilliam, Ms. Polley hit child stardom in Canada playing the precocious lead in the television series ''Avonlea,'' a prairie period drama that eventually ran in the United States on the Disney Channel. Two days after she turned 11, her mother died of cancer. A few months later, Ms. Polley developed scoliosis, a severe curvature of the spine. Between the ages of 11 and 15, she wore a fiberglass brace for 16 hours a day, enduring painful welts and humiliating costume fittings to accommodate the bulky, corsetlike contraption. Then, at 15, she underwent a 10-hour operation and spent a year in bed recovering (the rods still in her back occasionally set off alarms at airport security checkpoints).</p>
        <p>''The thing about Sarah is, she's only 28 but she's been through quite a lot in her life,'' said Olympia Dukakis, who plays the pragmatic wife of Fiona's mute boyfriend in ''Away From Her.'' ''She seems very sweet, and she is, but she's not frivolous. It's a metaphor: she's got a rod up her back. You can see it in her acting. It's a kind of steeliness.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Polley never finished high school, but she read widely, and to the left. In the early '90s, she joined a growing political movement in Toronto, handing out socialist newsletters and organizing protests against the neoconservative provincial government.</p>
        <p>After several months, Ms. Polley's political obsessions were making her, as she put it, ''boring, dogmatic, narrow.'' When Mr. Egoyan invited her to return to acting with the lead role of the incest-victim narrator in ''The Sweet Hereafter,'' she agreed, but expected to quickly return to her political activities.</p>
        <p>''It seemed like a nice little ending to my acting career to work with Atom, and then it ended up sort of being the beginning of it,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The film was a critical smash, earning Mr. Egoyan a best-director Oscar nomination. In short order, Ms. Polley appeared in ''Go'' and ''Guinevere,'' in which she played the young lover of an older Stephen Rea. Then she won the part of Penny Lane, head ''Band-Aide'' in ''Almost Famous,'' Cameron Crowe's rock 'n' roll crowd pleaser. The part of a flighty, used groupie seems about as far from Ms. Polley, politically and in person, as possible. After weeks of rehearsal, she began to feel as if she'd made a huge mistake.</p>
        <p>''The part didn't fit me. Every day, it felt less and less like something I could pull off,'' she recalled. ''You just knew when you read the script that whoever played that part was going to have a certain kind of life, and it wasn't one I was ready for.'' She walked away, and Kate Hudson became Penny Lane, earning an Oscar nomination and a permanent place in the tabloids.</p>
        <p>After the ''Almost Famous'' incident, Ms. Polley fell into a depression about her future. She continued -- and still does -- to pop up as a player in a multitude of small Canadian films, most of which were never released outside Canada, but she questioned whether she wanted to be an actor. A viewing of the director Terrence Malick's ''Thin Red Line'' sparked an epiphany.</p>
        <p>''It literally lifted and carried me out of this depression, and I had no idea movies could do that,'' she said. So Ms. Polley, at the age of 22, signed up for film school at the Canadian Film Center, where she directed two shorts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Egoyan, an executive producer on ''Away From Her,'' says he finds Ms. Polley's transition to director unsurprising. ''There are two types of actors on a set: those who are very consumed with their performance, and those who are taking advantage of a front-row seat as to how a film is made,'' he said. ''I always saw her spending a lot of time with the crew, watching the way the camera was moving, absorbing composition, movement. I could feel her eyes on me.''</p>
        <p>The film Ms. Polley has made is about emotional endurance, and it stars a cadre of enduring older performers who have managed to navigate the film world with their senses of self intact (she spoke enviously of the fact that Ms. Christie lives modestly in Britain and has a full life without acting). In this way, ''Away From Her'' seems like Ms. Polley's effort to imagine some kind of future happiness for herself: as a married woman, and as a filmmaker in an industry she has known, if not loved, her entire life.</p>
        <p>''For a long time, I felt extremely judgmental of the environment I was working in and the people I was working with,'' she said. ''I don't feel like my politics have softened, but I don't feel like every single thing I do professionally defines me anymore. It's all experience. At this point, I'm open to anything. Even Hollywood doesn't scare me anymore.''</p>
        <p>Of course, Ms. Polley's version of the mainstream isn't exactly a summer franchise: she is preparing for a part in an HBO mini-series about John Adams, produced by Tom Hanks. ''O.K., so maybe it's not that commercial,'' she said, laughing again. ''But for me, it's pretty slick.''</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 6, 2007, Sunday  An article last Sunday about the film actress and director Sarah Polley referred incorrectly to the setting of ''Avonlea,'' the Canadian television series in which she starred. It was set on Prince Edward Island, not the prairie.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 6, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about the film actress and director Sarah Polley referred incorrectly to the setting of ''Avonlea,'' the Canadian television series in which she starred. It was set on Prince Edward Island, not the prairie.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
