<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Locals Critical of Plans to Redraw Air Routes</title>
    <meta content="29weekctCN-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843964"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DD133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="322" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Locals Critical of Plans to Redraw Air Routes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA PETERSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A federal plan to redraw air routes over the coast of Connecticut drew strong criticism at a public hearing in Stamford last Tuesday, with local residents saying they fear a decline in their quality of life and their property values from more planes flying at lower altitudes over their homes.</p>
        <p>The comments came at a public hearing held by the Federal Aviation Administration that drew more than 150 people.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A federal plan to redraw air routes over the coast of Connecticut drew strong criticism at a public hearing in Stamford last Tuesday, with local residents saying they fear a decline in their quality of life and their property values from more planes flying at lower altitudes over their homes.</p>
        <p>The comments came at a public hearing held by the Federal Aviation Administration that drew more than 150 people.</p>
        <p>The session, one of five public forums scheduled to take place around the region, came a month after the F.A.A. revealed its long-awaited plan for coping with airspace congestion. The administration said the plan would reduce delays at area airports like La Guardia by an average of six minutes per flight, for an overall reduction in delays of 32 percent.</p>
        <p>Steven Kelley, the administration's manager of airspace redesign, said that he understood residents' concerns, but that the agency had no control over the airline schedules.</p>
        <p>''What has changed in the past few years is the growth in air traffic,'' he said. ''We must find a way to reduce delays and improve the efficiency of the system.''</p>
        <p>The F.A.A. said that it would accept public comments on the plan until May 11, and that it would come up with a final plan in August, then begin phasing in the route changes over five years.</p>
        <p>Several towns have hired consultants and lawyers to explore the possibility of filing a lawsuit. But several local officials expressed frustration with what they described as a lack of hard information from the F.A.A. on how many planes would pass overhead at altitudes lower than 6,000 feet, which they said would significantly affect the intensity of the noise below.</p>
        <p>Paul Giusti, a selectman from New Canaan, said Thursday that he was told that the F.A.A. was going to release raw data on flight operations, in response to residents' complaints at the hearing about a lack of material.</p>
        <p>THE WEEK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
