<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bronx Students Learn Filmmaking, Tribeca Style</title>
    <meta content="29bronx" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/29bronx.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843896"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals/Tribeca Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tribeca Film Festival (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tribeca Film Festival (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tribeca Film Festival (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Bronx (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E2DE133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="743" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bronx Students Learn Filmmaking, Tribeca Style</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bronx Students Learn Filmmaking, Tribeca Style</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MANNY FERNANDEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fernandez, Manny</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The sixth annual Tribeca Film Festival, which started Wednesday and ends May 6, has had a fair share of star-studded premieres. Yesterday afternoon, about 13 miles north of TriBeCa, a different sort of premiere was under way.</p>
        <p>The concession stand near the red carpet was selling strawberry-flavored Twizzlers (three for a quarter). The theater was not really a theater: It was the gym of a Bronx charter school, lined with gray metal folding chairs, the first few rows of which were labeled ''Reserved'' for the student filmmakers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>About 120 Bronx students learned the basics of filmmaking thanks to a training program overseen by the Tribeca Film Institute.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The sixth annual Tribeca Film Festival, which started Wednesday and ends May 6, has had a fair share of star-studded premieres. Yesterday afternoon, about 13 miles north of TriBeCa, a different sort of premiere was under way.</p>
        <p>The concession stand near the red carpet was selling strawberry-flavored Twizzlers (three for a quarter). The theater was not really a theater: It was the gym of a Bronx charter school, lined with gray metal folding chairs, the first few rows of which were labeled ''Reserved'' for the student filmmakers.</p>
        <p>There was loud applause when several of the young people finally stepped onto the red carpet, strutted into the gym and posed for photographs. Tevon Walker wore a black suit for the occasion. His mother, grandmother and aunt cheered him on.</p>
        <p>This was his first film, after all. Tevon is 11 years old.</p>
        <p>The lights dimmed, and the movie appeared on a screen on a stage decorated with balloons. It was a short documentary, made by and for students of the Bronx Preparatory Charter School. Tevon sang a snippet of a Mary J. Blige song. His classmates danced, rapped and waxed poetic. They talked about who they were and where they were from, but there was no plot, no theme. It was just a 13-minute letter from Bronx Prep to the world.</p>
        <p>''No one can take our identity away from us,'' said Michael Smith-Grant, 17, a Bronx Prep senior. ''It's something we created. It's ours.''</p>
        <p>The students' documentary was created in a five-week filmmaking training program at the school overseen by the Tribeca Film Institute, the nonprofit arm of the film festival. About 120 students from the sixth to the 12th grades learned the basics of filmmaking and shot footage both in and out of the classroom. They brainstormed, roamed the neighborhood doing interviews, drew storyboards, studied other films and met two filmmakers affiliated with the festival.</p>
        <p>The final product was assembled by a professional film editor and shown for the first time at the school yesterday. The training program, called Tribeca Teaches: Films in Motion, seeks to spread the spirit of the festival outside Manhattan to young people not exposed to the art and science of filmmaking, said the institute's president, Sydney Meeks.</p>
        <p>''We can make a film about Bronx Prep that looks very refined,'' Mrs. Meeks said. ''But this is real and showed the students as they are.''</p>
        <p>The institute is considering expanding the program to other schools around the city, state and country, said Jane Rosenthal, a co-founder of the festival and co-chairwoman of the institute.</p>
        <p>The Bronx Prep film, called ''Classroom Snapshot,'' is a kind of video yearbook. There was Pablo Flores, a 13-year-old sixth grader, describing himself: ''I'm Dominican and I like girls.'' There was the girl torn between two careers: ''I am a future lawyer and maybe a future actress.''</p>
        <p>Myles Miller, 13, who walked around the gym with a reporter's notebook, spoke of his love of news reporting. Ashley Hood, 13, and Marissa Charlemagne, 12, pretended they were models in an impromptu fashion show.</p>
        <p>At one point, the camera panning the borough's skyline, students stood on the roof of the school building on Third Avenue a few blocks from the Cross Bronx Expressway. Amid fast-paced shots of high-rise projects and chain-link fences, amid the jokes and the rap songs, one student was asked on a street corner if the Bronx is a safe place for children.</p>
        <p>The boy paused only a moment. He shook his head. ''No,'' he said.</p>
        <p>After the screening, attended by dozens of students, parents, teachers and administrators, a few students stood on stage, taking questions from the audience.</p>
        <p>Someone asked what was the most challenging part of making a movie. Michael Smith-Grant said it was balancing regular schoolwork and the film project. A seventh grader said it was deciding what clothes to wear. Tevon replied: ''The most challenging part for me was watching what I did after I did it.''</p>
        <p>Tevon, a sixth grader who lives near the school, was not the slightest bit nervous. He has a part in a planned school play and has been writing a screenplay, ''Time Wars: A Tale Untold,'' a spinoff of the ''Star Wars'' movies. His grandmother plays a queen; his aunt plays a Jedi.</p>
        <p>A boy asked out of curiosity if anyone had gotten hurt during the making of the film. ''My throat was acting up,'' Tevon explained, ''and I was hitting high notes.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
