<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Miniature Works as the Main Attraction</title>
    <meta content="29artsctCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/29artsct.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843656"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Center for Contemporary Printmaking</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Genocchio, Benjamin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E4DB153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="621" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Miniature Works as the Main Attraction</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Miniature Works as the Main Attraction</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BENJAMIN GENOCCHIO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genocchio, Benjamin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Benjamin Genocchio reviews Sixth International Miniature Print Biennial at Center for Contemporary Printmaking in Norwalk, Conn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The delicate touch and dense composition of the more than 130 works in the Sixth International Miniature Print Biennial at the Center for Contemporary Printmaking in Norwalk make for a smart, stylish exhibition.</p>
        <p>This year's judge is David Kiehl, curator of prints at the Whitney Museum of American Art in New York City. He has done a marvelous job of editing down the 548 entries from 180 artists living in 18 countries to a coherent-looking show. There is a clear emphasis on figurative work, though I suspect this has more to do with the submissions than Mr. Kiehl's own taste.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The more than 130 works in the Sixth International Miniature Print Biennial at the Center for Contemporary Printmaking in Norwalk make for a smart, stylish exhibition.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The delicate touch and dense composition of the more than 130 works in the Sixth International Miniature Print Biennial at the Center for Contemporary Printmaking in Norwalk make for a smart, stylish exhibition.</p>
        <p>This year's judge is David Kiehl, curator of prints at the Whitney Museum of American Art in New York City. He has done a marvelous job of editing down the 548 entries from 180 artists living in 18 countries to a coherent-looking show. There is a clear emphasis on figurative work, though I suspect this has more to do with the submissions than Mr. Kiehl's own taste.</p>
        <p>Entries were restricted to a space of four square inches -- usually a square or a horizontal or vertical rectangle. This can take a little getting used to, for you need to train your eyes to look more intently at the imagery. But whether you use a magnifying glass (available at reception) or just look very closely, you will find a wealth of detail and visual pleasure that is more usually associated with works of art on a larger scale.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Kiehl points out in his introduction to the exhibition brochure, miniature prints were originally made to be printed in books, or viewed in the palm of your hand like postcards, rather than framed and hung on walls. In keeping with this history, the entries to the exhibition have been loosely mounted on cardboard and stuck directly on the wall. The more than 400 unsuccessful submissions are also available for viewing in ring-bound folders at the exhibition's entrance.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kiehl awarded prizes to three of the prints, ''Carpe Diem,'' a lively, atmospheric etching by Ivan Rusachek from Belarus; ''Seascape,'' an abstracted linocut by David McMillan from England; and ''Fantasy Hibiscus,'' a lush, colored photogravure of a flower by Jim Egan from Hawaii. All are terrific works of art, striking a balance between mastery of technique and innovation.</p>
        <p>The most interesting of them is Mr. McMillan's ''Seascape,'' which contains just enough in the way of spare calligraphic marks to permit an enticing glimpse of the sea, clouds and possibly a boat. Here abstraction is used not as an end in itself but to reveal and intensify the subject, the artist melding figurative and abstract elements until the distinction becomes meaningless.</p>
        <p>The rest of the show is a catchall of prints from around the world. Some of them are by artists working in obscurity and isolation; others are by well-known practitioners. In the latter category is Josef Werner, a master printmaker from Munich who is represented by two quality etchings. Not only is his drawing marvelously precise, but each is also expertly printed using a range of techniques.</p>
        <p>Almost 20 artists working at the printmaking center were also selected for inclusion in the exhibition, most of them Connecticut-based. Among them is Sally Frank, who created a dense, enticing image of a gray winter forest using a solarplate intaglio print process, in which an image is transferred to a printing plate using sunlight or an artificial light source. The print has a rare luminosity and richness of tone.</p>
        <p>There is also more traditional work, like Walter Buttrick's black-and-white etchings and aquatints of street scenes. Among them is an image of hipster teenagers hanging out in their car, which is parked at the curb. But it is the spatial ambiguity of the scene that steals the show by forcing us to confront the unusual vantage point from which the image is taken. Perhaps there is a metaphor here for the somewhat disorienting process of viewing miniature prints.</p>
        <p>''Sixth International Miniature Print Biennial,'' Center for Contemporary Printmaking, Mathews Park, 299 West Avenue, Norwalk, through May 12. Information: (203) 899-7999 or www.contemprints.org.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
