<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Third Wheel Isn't Just Along for the Ride</title>
    <meta content="29nets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/sports/basketball/29nets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843881"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Toronto Raptors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Jefferson, Richard</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5DE133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1059" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Third Wheel Isn't Just Along for the Ride</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nets’ Jefferson Is Just Happy to Blend With the Superstars</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Richard Jefferson spent a good portion of Game 3 on Friday night drawing the defense as if he were chaperoning a field trip to the Basketball Hall of Fame.</p>
        <p>From the corner or ahead on the break, he had the best seat in the house to admire Jason Kidd's sleight of hand and Vince Carter's hang time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Finishing with 18 points and 6 rebounds Friday, Richard Jefferson, the Nets’ small forward, is content with his role as third wheel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Richard Jefferson spent a good portion of Game 3 on Friday night drawing the defense as if he were chaperoning a field trip to the Basketball Hall of Fame.</p>
        <p>From the corner or ahead on the break, he had the best seat in the house to admire Jason Kidd's sleight of hand and Vince Carter's hang time.</p>
        <p>When asked to describe Kidd's effortless triple-double and Carter's dynamic 37 points at Continental Arena -- performances that led the Nets to a 102-89 victory and a two-games-to-one series lead against the young Toronto Raptors -- Jefferson gave up on adjectives.</p>
        <p>''It's great to be on their team; there's no other way to describe it,'' Jefferson said.</p>
        <p>Finishing with 18 points and 6 rebounds Friday, and going 8 for 8 from the free-throw line, Jefferson, the Nets' small forward, is content with his role as third wheel. He has played it patiently throughout his five-year career.</p>
        <p>''J and Vince, they're some of the greatest athletes on this planet, they're future Hall of Famers, I'm just enjoying the ride,'' Jefferson said. ''I wouldn't be in the position I'm in if it wasn't for those guys. My basketball I.Q. wouldn't be as high as it is if I didn't have Jason around me.''</p>
        <p>What lessons did Jefferson use from Kidd on Friday when he was struggling to hit his shot? ''The ability to do other things to help the team if you're not going well,'' Jefferson said. ''His ability to pass, to rebound, to get other people involved, that's something a lot of people could learn from.''</p>
        <p>Kidd, who grows more vocal during the playoffs, encouraged Jefferson all game. ''I didn't want frustration to set in with him because he's as important as anybody,'' Kidd said. ''I told him to keep taking it to the basket, the shots will fall, and if not, keep making your free throws.''</p>
        <p>Ah, the free throws. Once a touchy subject for Jefferson, now it is just a good-natured joke for those Nets who were around for Jefferson's ignominious 2002 playoff trip to the free-throw line.</p>
        <p>In Game 5 (then the final game of the first-round series) against the Indiana Pacers, the Nets were ahead by 3 points. Jefferson, a rookie, needed to make at least one free throw with 5.1 seconds left in regulation to secure the Nets' first series victory in 18 seasons. He missed both, and Reggie Miller made a turnaround 39-foot bank shot at the buzzer to send the game into overtime.</p>
        <p>''Oh, I'm sure we kidded him for it, telling him, 'You almost got us knocked out of the first round,' '' the Nets' president, Rod Thorn, said Friday in a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>But Kidd rescued the team in overtime, and the rest is Nets history. ''We've given him a hard time,'' Kidd said. ''But the beauty of his game, growing in the spotlight, when he was thrown in as a rookie, those are the best learning experiences.''</p>
        <p>Jefferson went on to play for the 2004 United States Olympic team and signed a six-year, $78 million contract through the 2009-10 season. That is when the Nets are scheduled to move into the yet-to-be built Barclays Center in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>Jefferson is the only current Net who would be under contract when the team moves. But will he be there?</p>
        <p>The Nets, according to several people with knowledge of the team's plans, will probably shop Jefferson this summer to get another post player to complement the returning Nenad Krstic. Jefferson's contract ($11 million this season) is easier to trade than Kidd's ($18 million). Even though he is still not 100 percent from arthroscopic surgery on his right ankle three months ago, Jefferson may be playing well enough to increase his trade value.</p>
        <p>''You believe in Rod and Bruce Ratner, they're going to do what's best for the team,'' Jefferson said, referring to Thorn and the Nets' owner. ''If they include you, they include you, if not, you move on.''</p>
        <p>The Nets' future depends on whether Carter wants to move on. Set to opt out of his contract and seek free agency, Carter could return to his native Orlando, Fla., even though the Nets could pay him more. With Friday's performance, it is easy to see how Carter sells tickets; Ratner, has already expressed an eagerness to keep him.</p>
        <p>Ratner said the same for Kidd last month. But what about Jefferson?</p>
        <p>''I'd rather not talk about that stuff now,'' Ratner said, beaming, after shaking hands with fans Friday. Later, he congratulated Jefferson in the locker room.</p>
        <p>''I'm just thinking game by game, just like the players,'' Ratner said. ''I love watching our Nets. It's real team play.''</p>
        <p>Jefferson's attitude and personality -- he tries not to take life or the game too seriously -- has made the team work. As when he played alongside the acrobatic Kerry Kittles and Kenyon Martin, Jefferson is still leading the fast break, allowing the slower Carter to trail. ''You have to run for your teammates,'' Jefferson said.</p>
        <p>''We're a close group in the sense we don't care who scores and that does remind me of the teams that went to the finals,'' Kidd said. ''That's what messes up a lot of franchises, people don't want to be the third wheel. R. J. has the personality to be first or second, but in due time. He has patience that he'll be up there.''</p>
        <p>When Jefferson was recovering from surgery, the Nets went 8-13. When he returned for the final 21 games, the Nets went 13-8, helping them avoid a losing record to finish at 41-41. He is still the Nets' most aggressive slasher, who spreads the floor and, when healthy, plays solid defense.</p>
        <p>''He has great intent, he's a winner,'' Nets Coach Lawrence Frank said. ''He's a guy you want out there.''</p>
        <p>Jefferson scored 28 points to lead the Nets to victory in Game 1 when Kidd and Carter were struggling. He stepped aside in Game 3 while Kidd and Carter stirred the crowd.</p>
        <p>Under the Nets' chief executive, Brett Yormark, where everything but the players' sweat has a corporate sponsor, the playoffs carry the motto ''It's a Brand New Season.''</p>
        <p>Jefferson is the link to the old and the new, if not the present bond between superstars. ''I don't think I'm the secret ingredient,'' he said.</p>
        <p>For now, Jefferson is the staple.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
