<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>These Are the Saves To Remember</title>
    <meta content="29hockey" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843880"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY: SUNDAY SHOOTOUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5DE133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1006" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>These Are the Saves To Remember</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF Z. KLEIN and KARL-ERIC REIF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Jeff Z; Reif, Karl-Eric</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the Islanders trailing, 4-3, and only 15 seconds from elimination in Game 5 of their opening-round series against Buffalo, Isles wing Miroslav Satan accepted a pass at the top of the right face-off circle and turned on the afterburners.</p>
        <p>Satan blew past Sabres defenseman Henrik Tallinder and cut in on goal. Ryan Miller, the Sabres' goalie, started to go down at the right post, but Satan did not shoot -- instead he zipped across the crease with the puck.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the Islanders trailing, 4-3, and only 15 seconds from elimination in Game 5 of their opening-round series against Buffalo, Isles wing Miroslav Satan accepted a pass at the top of the right face-off circle and turned on the afterburners.</p>
        <p>Satan blew past Sabres defenseman Henrik Tallinder and cut in on goal. Ryan Miller, the Sabres' goalie, started to go down at the right post, but Satan did not shoot -- instead he zipped across the crease with the puck.</p>
        <p>Miller toppled onto his side, then rolled onto his back, trying desperately to stay in front of Satan as he crossed the goalmouth. Finally, beyond the left post, Satan pivoted and shot. Miller, completing his snow-angel sprawl while flat on the ice and with one leg high over his head, somehow stopped the puck with the back of his glove hand. The rebound skittered to the side of the net and wound up beneath Miller with 10 seconds left.</p>
        <p>Miller's incredible save won the game and clinched the series for the Sabres. It may wind up ranking as one of the greatest stops in Stanley Cup history.</p>
        <p>For a save to qualify as great, it has to turn the tide or come at a truly critical juncture. Here are five candidates for the title of Greatest Save in Playoff History:</p>
        <p>KEN DRYDEN, 1971 FINALS, GAME 7 -- Montreal leads, 3-2, in Chicago with about four minutes to play, and the Blackhawks are storming the Canadiens' end. Suddenly the puck goes to the Hawks' Keith Magnuson to the right of the net. He shoots, and Dryden, Montreal's gangly rookie, makes the save. But the rebound caroms to the opposite side, where Jim Pappin, open and unmarked, is camped at the post. He one-times the redirect perfectly just inside the pipe, but Dryden's leg darts out to toe it away even as Pappin lifts his stick to celebrate. The Canadiens go on to win the Stanley Cup.</p>
        <p>FRANK PIETRANGELO, 1991 FIRST ROUND, GAME 6 -- The Penguins trail the Devils, three games to two, and with Tom Barrasso injured, the Penguins have the backup Pietrangelo in net. Ahead by 2-1 in the first period, Pietrangelo stops a point-blank shot from the Devils' Brendan Shanahan, but the rebound goes to Peter Stastny, who shoots at a gaping net. Pietrangelo somehow dives across the crease and gloves the puck. The Penguins go on to win the game, the series and the Cup. To this day in Pittsburgh, this play is known as the Save.</p>
        <p>KIRK McLEAN, 1994 FIRST ROUND, GAME 7 -- It is overtime and Calgary is on a three-on-two rush. McLean, Vancouver's goalie, comes well out to cut down the angle on Theo Fleury, who is speeding down the right wing. Fleury passes to a wide-open Robert Reichel in full flight in the left circle, and McLean zooms across his crease feet first, pads stacked, to deny Reichel. The Canucks win in double overtime and wind up going to the Cup finals.</p>
        <p>MIKE RICHTER, 1994 FINALS, GAME 4 -- The Rangers lead the series by two games to one, but trail, 2-1, in Vancouver in the second period. The 60-goal scorer Pavel Bure is pulled down on a breakaway and awarded a penalty shot. Bure, known as the Russian Rocket, zooms in and dekes forehand-backhand-forehand. But Richter stabs out with his right pad to thwart him, leading the Rangers to a comeback victory. From there, they hang on to win their first Cup in 54 years.</p>
        <p>CAM WARD, 2006 FINALS, GAME 7 -- Carolina leads, 2-1, but Edmonton is desperate to draw even in the closing minutes. With 3 minutes 40 seconds left, the Oilers burst into the Hurricanes' zone. Raffi Torres races along the left-wing boards and fires from a sharp angle. Ward, a rookie, makes the save, but the puck rebounds to Fernando Pisani alone at the front of the crease. He shovels it at the empty net, but somehow Ward shoots his leg out in a full stretch and smothers the puck. Carolina hangs on the rest of the way and wins the Stanley Cup.</p>
        <p>A Slice of Sweden</p>
        <p>When Vancouver beat Dallas in Game 7 of their opening-round series last Monday, it meant that the Canucks' three stars from Ornskoldsvik, Sweden -- Markus Naslund, and Henrik Sedin and Daniel Sedin -- would continue into the playoff quarterfinals.</p>
        <p>About 55,000 people live in Ornskoldsvik and its environs, yet it has produced a surprising number of N.H.L. players. Among them are Peter Forsberg, and the former Rangers Anders Hedberg and Niklas Sundstrom. Earlier this month, Modo Hockey, Ornskoldsvik's team in the Swedish Elitserien, won its first domestic championship in 28 years. Seven hometown players were on the roster, including Sundstrom and the former N.H.L. players Hans Jonsson, Andreas Salomonsson and Pierre Hedin.</p>
        <p>Notes</p>
        <p>Peter Forsberg may return to Ornskoldsvik sooner rather than later. Nashville General Manager David Poile said last week that he doubted that Forsberg would return to the N.H.L. next season because of the injuries he has had to endure. Forsberg, who joined the Predators at the trade deadline and becomes an unrestricted free agent on July 1, had a nagging foot injury all season. Since 1996, he has missed 269 games while sustaining at least 20 significant injuries, including at least five concussions and a ruptured spleen that had to be removed in an emergency operation during the 2001 playoffs.</p>
        <p>The Anaheim-Vancouver playoff series is only the fifth between West Coast teams, and the first in 14 years. The previous series: Los Angeles over Vancouver in the 1993 quarterfinals and in the 1991 opening round, Vancouver over Los Angeles in the 1982 quarterfinals and Los Angeles over Oakland in the 1969 quarterfinals.</p>
        <p>Further evidence that outhitting your opponent does nothing to increase your chances of winning: In the first playoff round, teams that outhit their opponents by a significant margin (nine or more hits a game) had a record of 7-8.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY: SUNDAY SHOOTOUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
