<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A District Attorney Who Warns but Also Strikes</title>
    <meta content="29peopleweWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/29peoplewe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843671"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="LAW ENFORCEMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drunken and Reckless Driving</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Difiore, Janet (Dist Atty)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gruen, Abby</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">District Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drunken and Reckless Driving</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">District Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">DiFiore, Janet</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E2DB153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="903" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A District Attorney Who Warns but Also Strikes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A District Attorney Who Warns but Also Strikes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY GRUEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gruen, Abby</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on tough stand taken by Westchester County District Attorney Janet DiFiore against drunken driving as well as gun crime and child protection; DiFiore says next big initiative will be creation of countywide crime intelligence center; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GONE are the days when a police officer might be willing to send a tipsy driver home with a warning in Westchester County. Today, there are more random road stops, blood alcohol tests are stricter and plea bargaining has gotten tougher.</p>
        <p>Last month, the Westchester district attorney, Janet DiFiore, announced jail sentences in three recent deaths caused by drunken drivers. Those sentenced included Ann Marie Ciarcia, 47, in the death of her daughter's friend Emily Cornish, 16; Ralph Tarchine III, 19, for two crashes, one of which resulted in the death of his childhood friend Michael Plunkett, 17; and Drew Zottola, 58, for a hit and run that killed Milton Vizhco, 25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>GONE are the days when a police officer might be willing to send a tipsy driver home with a warning in Westchester County. Today, there are more random road stops, blood alcohol tests are stricter and plea bargaining has gotten tougher.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GONE are the days when a police officer might be willing to send a tipsy driver home with a warning in Westchester County. Today, there are more random road stops, blood alcohol tests are stricter and plea bargaining has gotten tougher.</p>
        <p>Last month, the Westchester district attorney, Janet DiFiore, announced jail sentences in three recent deaths caused by drunken drivers. Those sentenced included Ann Marie Ciarcia, 47, in the death of her daughter's friend Emily Cornish, 16; Ralph Tarchine III, 19, for two crashes, one of which resulted in the death of his childhood friend Michael Plunkett, 17; and Drew Zottola, 58, for a hit and run that killed Milton Vizhco, 25.</p>
        <p>''We're about accountability here,'' Ms. DiFiore said, ''and people are going to be held accountable for their actions.''</p>
        <p>Backing up her tough talk, Ms. DiFiore, 51, is out most weeknights speaking to community groups about the dangers of drunken driving, as well as other issues like gun crime and child protection. The public information campaign is part of a new focus on crime prevention that Ms. DiFiore has brought to the district attorney's office since her swearing-in on Jan. 1, 2006.</p>
        <p>Happy to participate in community forums, Ms. DiFiore has otherwise eschewed public attention. With 40,000 prosecutions last year, she has chosen to be low-key about her successes, announcing noteworthy convictions by press release, unlike her predecessor, Jeanine F. Pirro, who was more apt to call a press conference.</p>
        <p>''I don't think it is appropriate for the prosecutor's office to be out there in a very flashy or high-profile sort of way,'' Ms. DiFiore said. ''We do our work in the courtroom, and that is how we speak about our work.''</p>
        <p>Four months after taking office, Ms. DiFiore announced the formation of the Child Fatality Review Team, an independent group of experts that reviews child deaths and makes preventive recommendations. Ms. Pirro and Andrew J. Spano, the county executive, had fought for years over how to establish the team.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spano, who has become one of Ms. DiFiore's biggest boosters, said: ''There is a philosophical difference there. The former district attorney saw herself as the chief law enforcement officer in the county, and the new district attorney sees herself as part of the law enforcement community.''</p>
        <p>Ms. DiFiore says that her next big initiative will be the creation of a countywide crime intelligence center so that all 43 independently run police departments in Westchester can share data daily.</p>
        <p>''Everything she is doing is multijurisdictional,'' said Frank G. Straub, the White Plains police commissioner, who is working on the intelligence center project. ''Her office is excellent in terms of building collaborations across the county.''</p>
        <p>Ms. DiFiore has also earned the respect of colleagues in the criminal justice system by her willingness to review closed cases, most notably the murder convictions of Jeffrey Deskovic, who was released last year after a review of DNA evidence, and Anthony DiSimone, whose case was overturned because it was found that significant evidence had been withheld from the defense.</p>
        <p>''It is extraordinary,'' said Bennett L. Gershman, a professor at Pace University Law School and expert on prosecutorial misconduct. ''This doesn't happen in the United States. When a case is over, you move on, you don't look back.''</p>
        <p>Ms. DiFiore's office has even appointed a commission to find out what happened in the Deskovic case and to make sure it never happens again. ''We are not about winning cases. That is not our goal, and that is not the tone I set in this office,'' she said. ''We are about seeking justice in every single case, and that means seeking the truth in the back end of every case.''</p>
        <p>In a recent interview in her elegantly decorated office overlooking downtown White Plains, Ms. DiFiore discussed her priorities for her second year.</p>
        <p>''The gun violence issue is big,'' she said. ''People maybe don't connect with it because it seems so distant, but it affects all of us because it doesn't stay in one place.''</p>
        <p>She has formed the Gang Violence and Firearms Bureau in her office to track and prosecute gun crimes. The new bureau builds on a community outreach program that Ms. DiFiore and other municipal officials started in November, when a change in the state's gun laws mandated a minimum sentence of three and a half years for illegal possession of a loaded firearm.</p>
        <p>''Having been a judge, and seeing the faces of young people who came through on gun possession charges, I thought it would be remiss of me if I didn't try to do a public awareness campaign on that issue,'' said Ms. DiFiore, who inaugurated the program in front of a packed auditorium of students at her alma mater, Mount Vernon High School.</p>
        <p>Since then, she has spoken at dozens of high schools around the county, including Blind Brook High School in Rye Brook, where last month she participated in a discussion about teenage drinking and drug use before an audience of more than 175 parents and students.</p>
        <p>Ms. DiFiore, the mother of a Bronxville High School senior, a college junior and a first-year law student, switched the topic several times from legal liability to advising the parents to be responsible and involved.</p>
        <p>''Remember, we need to be role models,'' she said. ''Beacons for our kids.'' It is a standard, Ms. DiFiore's admirers say, that she applies to herself as well.</p>
        <p>LAW ENFORCEMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
