<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Here and There Amid the Living, the Dead Call Out</title>
    <meta content="29land" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/us/29land.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843934"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THIS LAND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cemeteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Rhode Island</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Narragansett (Ri)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barry, Dan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Columns/This Land</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Rhode Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Rhode Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cemeteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tombs and Tombstones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cemeteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tombs and Tombstones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Rhode Island</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E6DD133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="933" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Here and There Amid the Living, the Dead Call Out</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Here and There Amid the Living, the Dead Call Out</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN BARRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barry, Dan</byline>
      <dateline>NARRAGANSETT, R.I.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dan Barry This Land column visits Narragansett, RI, to examine some of Rhode Island's estimated remaining 3,300 private burial grounds; reports some local historians believe large number of private burial grounds reflects Rhode Island's origins as place of religious tolerance with few centralized churches; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Perhaps the long-ago dead should have ceded ground by now, considering the premium on land in a state that is, to employ one cliché of measurement, ''about the size of Rhode Island.'' But in stubborn silence, the dead here refuse.</p>
        <p>Wander anywhere, and Rhode Islanders of the distant past all but rise to greet you from one of at least 3,300 family burial grounds still extant in this smallest of states. Their headstones, in clusters of five here or 10 there, often jut from surroundings so thoroughly developed that few of the living ever pay heed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are at least 3,300 family burial grounds still extant in Rhode Island, even though land comes at a premium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Perhaps the long-ago dead should have ceded ground by now, considering the premium on land in a state that is, to employ one cliché of measurement, ''about the size of Rhode Island.'' But in stubborn silence, the dead here refuse.</p>
        <p>Wander anywhere, and Rhode Islanders of the distant past all but rise to greet you from one of at least 3,300 family burial grounds still extant in this smallest of states. Their headstones, in clusters of five here or 10 there, often jut from surroundings so thoroughly developed that few of the living ever pay heed.</p>
        <p>In a tidy subdivision in Narragansett, off Ginger Lane, a weedy mound rises from putting-green lawns. There, just a few yards from a driveway's basketball hoop, rest some Robinsons, including one woman who died under British rule, succumbing to that all-too-familiar ailment, a broken heart.</p>
        <p>A few miles away, across the road from a Moo Moo's ice cream stand, dozens of Kenyons are buried in a grassy plot that seems to have been carved from a Super Stop and Shop parking lot, when of course it was the other way around. Beside the flow of minivans and trucks rest broken headstones, including one for a Kenyon named Welcome.</p>
        <p>And in Cranston, between two houses and behind a third, lie some Watermans and Stones, the calculations upon their tablets speaking to the preciousness of every day. Benjamin Stone, for example, died April 10, 1877, ''aged 33 years, 9 mo. &amp; 15 days.''</p>
        <p>Many of the headstones here have been uprooted or broken, and a vandal has scratched curlicues into a slate stone ''sacred to the memory of Eleanor F. Waterman.'' Judging by the lawn chairs and beer cans about, the place has become a neighborhood hangout. But a single dollop of white among the decaying leaves suggests that at least one child had too much respect, or fear, to retrieve an errant baseball.</p>
        <p>With the present nose-to-nose with the past, it is not hard to imagine the dead, resting against their own headstones and liberated by invisibility, pondering our silly modern ways: being led by dogs on evening walks past that Cranston plot; idly tossing basketballs at that Narragansett hoop; buying milk at that Super Stop and Shop. Pray tell, hast thou no cow?</p>
        <p>And every now and then, you ponder them. You almost feel them peering over your shoulder as you kneel before their graves to picture who they were, based on the bare-bone statistics that time slowly erases from slate: date of birth, length of time above ground, role as husband or wife, son or daughter.</p>
        <p>You move on, but they remain, in circumstances not always reflecting well upon the living.</p>
        <p>Some local historians say that the large number of these private burial grounds -- that is, those not trampled by progress's march -- reflects Rhode Island's origins as a place of religious tolerance, with few centralized churches. It may also reflect a more temporal matter: the distance, say, between rural East Greenwich and the colonial settlement of Providence, some 16 miles away. Might as well set aside a corner of the family farm.</p>
        <p>That is what the Tillinghasts of East Greenwich did. Then the descendants died off or moved away, bequeathing by their absence the family plot to the elements. Now, if Dean Thompson is inclined, and he usually is, he will lead you dozens of yards to the back of his family's greenhouse business, Briarbrook Farm, where Pardon Tillinghast and kin rest.</p>
        <p>There, among gravestones adorned with etchings of angels, the wild rose and bittersweet vines snag your clothing, refusing to let go. ''The stuff'll climb up your leg if you stand long enough,'' Mr. Thompson says, standing amid overgrowth more accustomed to visits by deer.</p>
        <p>Over the years, interest in historic cemeteries rose and fell. Then Evelyn Wheeler, a formidable woman of 67 living in restless retirement in Narragansett, sought permission a few years ago to tidy up a local cemetery, but could find no one in charge, either in town or in the state.</p>
        <p>Faster than you could say Pardon Tillinghast, she pushed the state legislature to resurrect a state commission on historic cemeteries. Dozens of people attended the first meeting, at a senior citizens center in Warwick. Plans were made to have volunteers clean up grave sites, identify long-forgotten burial plots and bolster the efforts of local cemetery commissions.</p>
        <p>Narragansett alone has 15 historic cemeteries still in existence, including one opposite Charlie O's, a tavern known for its ribs. Past stacks of lobster traps rest, among others, Hazard Knowles and his wife, Susan. For anyone wondering about the couple's next intended port of call, their headstones feature carvings of a single hand, pointing up.</p>
        <p>Then there's the old cemetery of Gardners and Slocums. Not long ago, Ms. Wheeler noticed that the plot, which measured about 30 feet by 30 feet, was described in town records as 66 feet by 135 feet. ''So I climbed over a wall and started taking debris out,'' she recalls. ''I kept finding stones and more stones and more stones.''</p>
        <p>Some people believe that it is better to have cemeteries rest under the peaceful blanket of natural growth than to expose them to vandals. But Ms. Wheeler says that daylight coaxes more than periwinkle from the soft earth; that old headstones, even those bearing little more than someone's name, touch us in ways we can hardly articulate.</p>
        <p>One day after the clean-up, she saw sunlight shining again upon the headstone of a Mary Slocum, dead more than 200 years, and who knows why, but she cried.</p>
        <p>THIS LAND</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
