<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Unexpected Find: A Place for Filipino Food</title>
    <meta content="29dinenjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/29dinenj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843694"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/BLOOMFIELD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pandan (Bloomfield, NJ, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corcoran, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E0D8153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="836" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Unexpected Find: A Place for Filipino Food</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Unexpected Find: A Place for Filipino Food</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CORCORAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Corcoran, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Corcoran reviews Pandan restaurant in Bloomfield, NJ; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE name is inviting but unrevealing. Pandan Asian Cuisine: it sounds -- well, pan-Asian, and there are no outward signs that this trim, bright little restaurant in Bloomfield is anything but.</p>
        <p>The menu invites you to ''explore the culinary mysteries of Asia,'' and along with chicken teriyaki and Vietnamese spring rolls it offers a dozen ''Thai specials.'' Only when you examine it closely, and hear the lilting accents of some of the servers, do you realize that you've wandered into one of the few Filipino restaurants in New Jersey.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pandan Asian Cuisine in Bloomfield features the vigorous, self-confident style of Filipino cooking.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE name is inviting but unrevealing. Pandan Asian Cuisine: it sounds -- well, pan-Asian, and there are no outward signs that this trim, bright little restaurant in Bloomfield is anything but.</p>
        <p>The menu invites you to ''explore the culinary mysteries of Asia,'' and along with chicken teriyaki and Vietnamese spring rolls it offers a dozen ''Thai specials.'' Only when you examine it closely, and hear the lilting accents of some of the servers, do you realize that you've wandered into one of the few Filipino restaurants in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>That there are so few (the largest concentration is along Newark Avenue in Jersey City) is curious. The state has a sizable Filipino-American population -- 85,000 as of the 2000 census, far more than the number of Japanese, Korean, Thai or Vietnamese New Jerseyans. Yet as far as I can tell, this page has never given a full-fledged review to a Filipino restaurant. It's time to set that right, for this is a cuisine worth getting to know.</p>
        <p>It's a vigorous, self-confident style of cooking, with an emphasis on headstrong flavors. The Filipino national fish is called bangus (BONG-oos), and Pandan fillets it and fries it whole -- after marinating it in vinegar, garlic and pepper to lend spice and depth to its mild, perchlike flavor. Bangus is said to be a challenge to debone, but I encountered no hazards -- just crisp dark-brown skin, firm milky flesh and a lively topping of chopped mango, cucumber, tomato, onion and dill.</p>
        <p>The owner, Linda de los Reyes, opened Pandan in 2004, 16 years after coming to New Jersey from the Philippines, where her late husband, Rustico, was a politician. (The restaurant is named for a spiky, palmlike South Asian tree whose leaves impart a flavor something like vanilla.) Mrs. de los Reyes says that until three years ago her culinary experience consisted of baking for her family and catering; the restaurant, she told me, ''just popped out.'' She entrusts the cooking to a colleague, Rose Robles, and to two other chefs, one from Thailand (that must explain those specials) and one from Ecuador.</p>
        <p>But the recipes are mostly hers, and so is Pandan's winning ambience. Formerly a corner deli, the space is now as vibrant as mango salsa, its Creamsicle-colored walls trimmed, like the furniture, with wicker. Green votive candles brighten the tables. The congenial, efficient servers wear T-shirts in tropical-fruit colors, with slogans like ''Vitamin P for Pandan.''</p>
        <p>The menu is long, and the prices are so gentle you'll want to come with a group and execute a full-gainer dive into the menu section headed ''Pandan's Specials.'' You'll note that two words figure prominently: grilled and pork. There's pork steak, grilled pork belly, grilled pork chop, grilled spareribs and pork barbecue.</p>
        <p>I loved them all. In particular, the pork belly was thin, well charred and succulent -- a fine fate for a cut of meat usually associated with bacon (and commodity futures). Spareribs were spicy and satisfying. Pork also figured in a wonderfully hearty soup called molo, in which wrinkly pork dumplings vied for attention with shiitake mushrooms, water chestnuts and shredded chicken in a clear, smoky broth.</p>
        <p>The menu offers some concessions to vegetarians and diners watching their cholesterol. Mussels are stir-fried with an energetic combination of black beans, garlic, ginger and scallions. Grilled eggplant is intriguingly flavored with lime juice and fish sauce. Sizzling pusit, or char-grilled squid, is a scary-looking tangle of chewy tentacles served in a smoking cast-iron pan.</p>
        <p>The non-Filipino dishes we tried were skippable: bland, gooey pad thai and curried salmon that was overcooked and as hard as a hockey puck. Likewise the chiffon cakes, which look enticing but taste mainly of sugar and vegetable shortening.</p>
        <p>But ice creams, especially purple yam, enchanted the children at our table. (Hint: tell them it's ''purple ice cream.'') Then there's a dessert that comes in a tall parfait glass, filled with shaved ice, chopped fruit, red and white beans, coconut gelatin, sweet corn, flan, evaporated milk and who knows what else.</p>
        <p>It's called halo-halo. It means ''mix-mix'' in Tagalog. It's as exuberant and unsubtle as the restaurant itself -- and as unexpected.</p>
        <p>Pandan  406 Broad Street  Bloomfield  (973) 748-9997  www.pandanasiancuisine.com</p>
        <p>GOOD</p>
        <p>THE SPACE A bright and inviting corner storefront with about 40 seats. Wheelchair accessible.  THE CROWD Casually dressed but knowledgeable, with a healthy complement of Filipinos in search of authentic home cooking.  THE STAFF Friendly and fluent in English.  THE BAR Bring your own wine or beer.  THE BILL Lunch combinations, $7.50. Dinner entrees, $8 to $17.50. American Express, MasterCard, Visa.  WHAT WE LIKE Savory mussels, molo soup, pork steak, grilled pork belly, grilled pork chop, grilled spareribs, pork barbecue, grilled eggplant, fried bangus (milkfish), sizzling pusit (grilled squid), ice creams, halo-halo.  IF YOU GO  Open Sunday, Tuesday and Wednesday, 11 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Thursday to Saturday, 11 a.m. to 10 p.m. Closed Monday. Reservations recommended on weekends. Parking on the street or in a rear lot.  Reviewed April 29, 2007</p>
        <p>DINING/BLOOMFIELD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
