<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Decline and Fall</title>
    <meta content="Coates.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/books/review/Coates.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843558"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Rome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Rome (Italy)</location>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Day of the Barbarians, The:: The Battle That Led to the Fall of the Roman Empire (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E0D8173EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="688" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Decline and Fall</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Decline and Fall</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE COATES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Coates, Steve</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE DAY OF THE BARBARIANS</p>
        <p>The Battle That Led to the Fall</p>
        <p>of the Roman Empire.</p>
        <p>By Alessandro Barbero.</p>
        <p>Translated by John Cullen.</p>
        <p>180 pp. Walker &amp; Company. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the fourth century, it was the beginning of the end for Rome.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE DAY OF THE BARBARIANS</p>
        <p>The Battle That Led to the Fall</p>
        <p>of the Roman Empire.</p>
        <p>By Alessandro Barbero.</p>
        <p>Translated by John Cullen.</p>
        <p>180 pp. Walker &amp; Company. $24.95.</p>
        <p>On the long hot summer afternoon of Aug. 9, 378, near Adrianople in the Roman province of Thrace, Gothic tribesmen -- Germanic warriors from across the Danube -- annihilated the field army of the Eastern Roman Empire, butchering thousands of soldiers and the unpopular emperor Valens. But only in a narrow sense are those hours of slaughter the point of the title of Alessandro Barbero's ''Day of the Barbarians.'' For as Barbero convincingly maintains, the battle of Adrianople, though little known today, ''changed the course of world history'' and began the chain of events that led to the sack of Rome in 410 and, soon after, to the inexorable eclipse of the West.</p>
        <p>Barbero, a professor of medieval studies at the University of Piemonte Orientale in Vercelli, Italy, strongly suggests that it didn't have to be that way, in no small part because these Goths, the first to enter the empire in force, came not as invaders but as immigrants. Despite the popular notion that it was already tottering in the fourth century, Rome was still mighty, defended by an army of over half a million men. It was also an empire that ''barbarians wanted to join.'' Its ''open and composite'' governing class promoted a universalist ''melting pot'' ideology, and the army, Barbero shows, was an assimilation machine, efficiently melding willing barbarians into its multiethnic, multicultural polity.</p>
        <p>So in many ways it had been natural for Valens to acquiesce when, two years before the fateful battle, a mass of desperate Gothic tribes, already dependent on the Romans economically and terrorized by the Huns, begged to be allowed to cross the Danube and settle within the empire's bounds. The new immigrants would pay taxes, supply recruits for the Roman army and farm the empire's underpopulated northeast corner (Adrianople was in what is now European Turkey). But what might have been a grand opportunity turned into a colossal failure of crisis management, one that exposed the empire's every failing and fissure. Barbero's narrative skillfully exploits the tensions inherent in these events; it is excruciating to watch the scales tilt grain by grain against the Romans.</p>
        <p>The waves of refugees, ferried chaotically over the mile-wide river in an ad hoc flotilla (a scene that gripped the young Edward Gibbon) were far too many to provide for on the spot, or to shift quickly to new settlements. Corrupt officials exploited them monstrously, and Goth mercenaries already serving loyally were needlessly alienated. When the immense multitude turned hostile, the Romans squandered chances for a decisive early strike. Later, with their soldiers tied down on the vast imperial borders, they had difficulty gathering a mobile force large enough for a confrontation, and Valens, vainglorious, refused to wait for Western reinforcements. The result was catastrophe; the Balkans were laid waste, and only Gothic inexperience at siege-works saved the Eastern capital, Constantinople. Valens's successor, Theodosius the Great, eventually made peace on much the same terms under which the Goths had been invited into the empire in the first place -- but not before their power had been revealed in Roman blood, and not before they and the barbarians who came in their wake had effectively overwhelmed Rome's assimilationist machinery.</p>
        <p>Adrianople traumatized the ancient world. For Ammianus Marcellinus, Rome's last great historian and Barbero's main ancient source, the empire's history finished with the battle, ''as if it had come to a full stop.'' But history has devious ways of outliving its declared end. One of the many paradoxes in Barbero's elegant and pleasurable little account -- what a joy it is to read about the ancient world in digestible portions -- is that the Eastern empire learned from its experience and intentionally shifted its barbarians farther and farther toward the West. Despite being the site of the first irreparable crack in the imperial fabric, the East lived on as the Byzantine Empire and remained stable and strong long after the shell of the West had crumbled under the barbarian onslaught.</p>
        <p>Steve Coates is an editor at the Book Review.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Steve Coates is an editor at the Book Review.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
