<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tax Reform and Accountability</title>
    <meta content="CTbudget" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/opinion/nyregionopinions/CTbudget.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843674"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Connecticut"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rell, M Jodi (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Rell, M Jodi</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E1DB153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="610" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tax Reform and Accountability</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tax Reform and Accountability</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial supports both Connecticut Gov M Jodi Rell and Democratic-controlled Legislature's budget proposals; holds that if raising income tax is inevitable this year, Democratic budget takes good first step toward assuring that money is spent responsibly</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the surface, the budget arguments taking place in the State Capitol sound to many citizens a little like the tastes-great-less-filling debate once posed by a famous beer commercial. Gov. M. Jodi Rell says her budget is better than that of the majority Democrats; Democrats, who unveiled their proposal a little less than two weeks ago, say their budget is ''smarter and fairer'' than hers.</p>
        <p>The plans share one thing in common: they both raise taxes. It is unavoidable. Even if government did absolutely nothing new in the next two years, the costs of debt service, which now makes up 11 percent of the $16 billion budget, as well as health care, salaries, raises and other items would still make expenditures rise by about $800 million a year. The state's constitutional cap on spending would have to be broken just to keep the status quo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If raising the income tax is inevitable this year, the least our government should do is to spend the money responsibly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the surface, the budget arguments taking place in the State Capitol sound to many citizens a little like the tastes-great-less-filling debate once posed by a famous beer commercial. Gov. M. Jodi Rell says her budget is better than that of the majority Democrats; Democrats, who unveiled their proposal a little less than two weeks ago, say their budget is ''smarter and fairer'' than hers.</p>
        <p>The plans share one thing in common: they both raise taxes. It is unavoidable. Even if government did absolutely nothing new in the next two years, the costs of debt service, which now makes up 11 percent of the $16 billion budget, as well as health care, salaries, raises and other items would still make expenditures rise by about $800 million a year. The state's constitutional cap on spending would have to be broken just to keep the status quo.</p>
        <p>Knowing that, both sides decided that if they had to raise taxes, they might as well try to tackle some big problems. But they chose differently. The governor picked education. The Democrats focused on health care and reforming the state's income tax.</p>
        <p>Governor Rell's budget pours money into school districts, particularly in the cities. She wants to raise the top rate for the state's income tax to 5.5 percent, from 5 percent She has called for a 3 percent cap on annual increases in local property taxes, a topic on which Democrats have so far refused to even hold a hearing, and an end to levying property taxes on cars, which the Democrats have dismissed. Her proposal to offer health care to the uninsured deserves to be taken more seriously.</p>
        <p>The Democrats focus on health care and reforming the largely flat state income tax -- currently, those who make $50,000 or $500,000 pay the same rate. Democrats propose a tax ranging from 3 percent for the lowest wages to 6.95 percent for couples filing jointly with annual incomes above $250,000.</p>
        <p>The taxes would start with the first dollar a person earns but, as is true today, there would be an exemption for lower income people that in effect would leave them with no tax to pay. In addition, Democrats would double the state's property tax credit to $1,000. Their budget would raise Medicaid rates for doctors and hospitals, increase access to medical and dental care for the poor, and put all municipal employees in a health insurance pool negotiated by the state. Education budgets would get more money, but the increases would not be as generous as in Governor Rell's plan.</p>
        <p>Both sides need each other. The spending cap cannot be broken without the governor's consent, and Democrats hold a veto-proof majority in both houses. In reaching compromise, the Democrats' bid to make the income tax more progressive is long overdue.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, though more money should be aimed at poor districts to address the educational inequities that are Connecticut's disgrace, the Democrats would force all districts to accept state oversight on how they spend the money. That's a plus, because more accountability is needed. The Democrats' budget has by far the best approach in that regard; new programs will have to demonstrate their effectiveness by agreed-upon measures.</p>
        <p>That sounds basic, and it is, but the state rarely does this now. Too often the causes represented by the loudest, most politically connected voices at legislative hearings get the greatest infusions of cash -- whether they should or not, and whether their programs are successes or flops.</p>
        <p>If raising the income tax is inevitable this year, the least our government should do is to spend the money responsibly. The Democratic budget takes a good first step toward assuring that.</p>
        <p>Connecticut</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
