<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Menudo Hopefuls Strut, Preen and Even Try to Sing</title>
    <meta content="29menudo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/29menudo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843890"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Rock Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rock Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Menudo</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E3DE133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Menudo Hopefuls Strut, Preen and Even Try to Sing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Menudo Hopefuls Strut, Preen and Even Try to Sing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY RAMIREZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ramirez, Anthony</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the universe of boy bands of the 1980s, Puerto Rico's Menudo was particularly ruthless.</p>
        <p>If a boy grew too tall, he was gone; when a boy's voice grew too deep, he was gone; and, famously, when he turned 16, he was gone. Replacement singers were plentiful and brought the group back to the regulation strength of five.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>About 50 or so boys auditioned a cappella at the food court at the Queens Center Mall for the final round of selections for the next Menudo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the universe of boy bands of the 1980s, Puerto Rico's Menudo was particularly ruthless.</p>
        <p>If a boy grew too tall, he was gone; when a boy's voice grew too deep, he was gone; and, famously, when he turned 16, he was gone. Replacement singers were plentiful and brought the group back to the regulation strength of five.</p>
        <p>The resulting Menudo incarnations were successful, selling more than 20 million albums of pop music and giving the world a young Ricky Martin. By 1997, however, Menudo (Spanish slang for boy) was gone, the victim of business disputes and the fickle tastes of girls.</p>
        <p>Now Menudo is set to be deployed again, as a musical group and a reality television show for MTV.</p>
        <p>So yesterday, about 50 or so boys, and not a few freshly shaven men, auditioned a cappella in Spanish and English at the food court at the Queens Center Mall in Elmhurst for the final round of selections for the next Menudo.</p>
        <p>It was a typical Queens maelstrom: fathers with shaved heads held toddlers in each arm; Peruvians in hip-hop gear glowered past identically clad Vietnamese. But mostly it was pre-teen Latinas who bounced on the balls of their feet. Screams emerged from them at regular intervals.</p>
        <p>Those who auditioned were unarguably young. Joseph, contestant No. 13, wore blue jeans and a dark blazer at least two sizes too big for his skinny frame. At one point, he seemed distraught before going on stage, but he was consoled by an older woman in a purple jumpsuit who patted his hands.</p>
        <p>A few had the moves, but fewer still had the sound. They closed their eyes, placed their left hands on their hearts, leaned toward the judges, bent their knees, winked at the girls. A few tried movements out of Chippendale's.</p>
        <p>As for the singing, however, showerheads around the country are familiar with the noise. No Marc Anthony singing ''Contra la Corriente,'' one of his signature salsa ballads. More like Rex Harrison, in ''My Fair Lady,'' but talk-singing his way through ''My Girl'' by the Temptations.</p>
        <p>After the first 30 contestants, even the most caffeinated of the pre-teen girls was glum, holding her chin in both hands.</p>
        <p>The judges, however, were in Paula Abdul mode. Johnny Wright, the chief judge and a past manager of the Backstreet Boys and New Kids on the Block, said in an interview, ''There's a lot of kids here with great voices, and I'm going to push a couple of them through.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wright judged Menudo auditions in Los Angeles, Miami and Dallas, which yielded about 10 candidates. With two or three more from Queens, he said, he will have enough to fill a house for the MTV reality show, ''Road to Menudo,'' set to debut May 12. The members of the TV show have not yet been chosen. The final group will have five members.</p>
        <p>Unlike the old Menudo with its Darwinian rules, even the age restriction isn't hard and fast with the new Menudo, said Mr. Wright. Band members must be at least 15 and look 19. (''You can't be 19 looking like 30,'' he quickly noted.)</p>
        <p>And the Menudo sound will change, Mr. Wright said. ''The new Menudo will be eclectic, representing today's sound. It could be hip-hop, could be dance, could be R&amp;B, could be rock, but always maintaining its Latin heritage.''</p>
        <p>David Figueroa, a contestant from Howard Beach, works inventory at Best Buy and is 23. The Menudo application, he noted, said applicants should ''appear to be less than 19 years old.'' He ran a hand over his cheek and said, ''so I shaved it up and been keeping it smooth, make sure I don't look old.''</p>
        <p>The contestants weren't the only ones who were not teenagers. Some of the fans were older, too.</p>
        <p>''I used to go to every Menudo concert,'' said Madeline Cortez, 38, a medical receptionist from Corona, Queens. ''Menudo was so beautiful, the singing, the dancing, the outfits. My favorite was Ricky Martin!''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
