<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At One Elementary School, A Lesson in Real Time</title>
    <meta content="29topicctCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/29topicct.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843662"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ENVIRONMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Plastics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chester (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bannister, Valerie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut/Connecticut River Valley</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DB153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="567" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At One Elementary School, A Lesson in Real Time</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At One Elementary School, a Lesson in Real Time</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VALERIE BANNISTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bannister, Valerie</byline>
      <dateline>CHESTER</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on decision by Chester Elementary School in Chester, Conn, to switch to more environmentally-friendly metal utensils from plastic ones; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SCHOOL cooks not only have to please some picky eaters, but they also have to do it without going over budget. For most schools, that means using plastic utensils.</p>
        <p>But in Chester, concerns over the environment led the elementary school to switch to metal in October, to reduce the waste of throwing out at least a thousand plastic forks, knives and spoons each month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chester.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SCHOOL cooks not only have to please some picky eaters, but they also have to do it without going over budget. For most schools, that means using plastic utensils.</p>
        <p>But in Chester, concerns over the environment led the elementary school to switch to metal in October, to reduce the waste of throwing out at least a thousand plastic forks, knives and spoons each month.</p>
        <p>The school was reluctant to make the change at first, but agreed after the Parent-Teacher Organization offered to buy some 40 dozen metal utensils for about $270. (Plastic utensils cost about $7 per thousand.)</p>
        <p>Karen D'Agostino, the P.T.O. president, said it was the overall waste generated by the cafeteria that had led her to look into washable silverware.</p>
        <p>She said she believed there was an important educational element as well. ''I feel like, as a school, we should be educating the children not just academically, but also environmentally,'' Ms. D'Agostino said. ''It's not enough to talk about it, you have to live it.''</p>
        <p>In addition, she said, ''being environmentally conscious is cheaper in the long run.''</p>
        <p>The cafeteria, which serves lunch daily to about 150 of the school's 330 students, is supposed to pay for itself but has been operating in the red the past few years, the principal, Hank Stockmal, said. This year, the school was allocated an extra $8,000 to cover a past deficit.</p>
        <p>''We're on a very tight budget for school lunch,'' said Barbara Greider, director of food services for Regional School District 4, which also includes the towns of Deep River and Essex.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Greider said that Chester Elementary was the only school in the district to use metal utensils, and officials from districts in the neighboring towns of Killingworth and Madison said that their schools used plastic.</p>
        <p>Tom Murphy, a spokesman for the State Department of Education, said the state did not keep track of how many schools used plastic or metal utensils, calling that a local decision. But he did say that there were about 580,000 public school students in Connecticut -- an indication of how much plastic could be getting thrown away every day.</p>
        <p>In Region 4, Mrs. Greider said, the middle and high schools cannot use metal utensils because they do not have dishwashers.</p>
        <p>The elementary school started using plastic utensils several years ago because they were cheaper and children were throwing away the metal ones. Each month, about 40 metal knives, spoons and forks would end up in the garbage, said Linda Jones, the cafeteria manager. In the first few months of this year, only about 20 pieces of flatware were lost, she said, adding that the P.T.O. promised to replace them.</p>
        <p>A third grader, Dan Lachance, 9, said he liked the change. ''They shouldn't be using all that plastic,'' he said. ''It's not good because it takes a lot of energy to make the plastic and you put it in the garbage. It stays in the ground for like a thousand years.''</p>
        <p>Elesa Palmer, 11, a fourth grader, said that she liked plastic utensils better -- ''The metal is hard, and you can hurt yourself that way'' -- but that she was in favor of reducing waste.</p>
        <p>Jenna Armenia, 10, a fifth grader, said she was glad that the school had switched because metal utensils do not break as easily.</p>
        <p>''The plastic ones,'' she said, ''used to break when we ate ice cream.''</p>
        <p>ENVIRONMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
