<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Warm Reception for an Icelander</title>
    <meta content="29Deal1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/realestate/29Deal1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843732"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BIG DEAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asbestos</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barbanel, Josh</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johannesson, Jon Asgeir</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Palmadottir, Ingibjorg</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Forgette, Simon H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zaga, Yossi</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/The Big Deal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asbestos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D6153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1414" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Warm Reception for an Icelander</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Warm Reception for an Icelander</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSH BARBANEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barbanel, Josh</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jon Asgeir Johannesson, president of Baugur Group, and partner Ingibjorg Palmadottir buy one of most expensive apartments ever sold in Manhattan below 42nd Street, triplex at 50 Gramercy Park North, for more than $24 million; condominium conversion work is halted at Sheffield on West 57th Street when city inspectors discover asbestos in ceiling material on five floors; attorney Simon H Forgette sells town house at 409 East 58th Street to Yossi Zaga for $6.5 million and buys town house at 217 East 61st Street for more than $5 million; photos (Big Deal column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A BUSINESSMAN from Iceland who built an international retailing empire has just acquired one of the most expensive apartments ever sold in Manhattan below 42nd Street, a Gramercy Park triplex costing more than $24 million, brokers say.</p>
        <p>The buyer, Jon Asgeir Johannesson, is president and chief executive of the Baugur Group, which has investments in grocery, fashion, real estate and media, including interests in more than 3,700 stores in Iceland, England and Scandinavia. He is also on trial at home for corruption.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jon Asgeir Johannesson, a businessman from Iceland, has just acquired one of the most expensive apartments ever sold in Manhattan below 42nd Street.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A BUSINESSMAN from Iceland who built an international retailing empire has just acquired one of the most expensive apartments ever sold in Manhattan below 42nd Street, a Gramercy Park triplex costing more than $24 million, brokers say.</p>
        <p>The buyer, Jon Asgeir Johannesson, is president and chief executive of the Baugur Group, which has investments in grocery, fashion, real estate and media, including interests in more than 3,700 stores in Iceland, England and Scandinavia. He is also on trial at home for corruption.</p>
        <p>In January, property records show, Mr. Johannesson, and his partner, Ingibjorg Palmadottir, paid just over $10 million for a floor-through unit on the 16th floor at 50 Gramercy Park North, the new apartment tower created by Ian Schrager at the Gramery Park Hotel.</p>
        <p>The couple liked that apartment and the hotel services in the building so much, brokers say, that they came back and bought the duplex penthouse above it, for $14 million more, including $4 million to acquire another buyer's rights to the apartment.</p>
        <p>The combined space will have 7,000 square feet on three levels, along with a 738-square-foot terrace on the 16th floor and two large terraces, totaling 1,300 square feet, on the 18th floor. That works out to just over $3,400 a square foot, excluding the terraces.</p>
        <p>Affluent Europeans have been significant buyers in new developments that offer hotel services, like 50 Gramercy Park North, brokers say, particularly now that the value of the dollar has declined compared with the euro or the British pound.</p>
        <p>Although there are about as many people in Manhattan below Gramercy Park as there are in all of Iceland (population just over 300,000), Mr. Johannesson may appreciate his new home for the peace and quiet offered by the neighborhood, especially in view of the turmoil he has been facing at home in Iceland.</p>
        <p>Beginning in 1989 with a discount food store in Iceland, Mr. Johannesson has built a large retailing presence throughout the region, and he has been a player in major retail acquisitions and investments in England in recent years.</p>
        <p>In 2005, Mr. Johannesson was charged in a 40-count indictment alleging financial irregularities in his dealing with his company. ''From Popcorn Seller to Jet-Setting Playboy,'' is how The Financial Times described him in a newspaper profile at the time.</p>
        <p>The charges were dropped by the Reykjavik District Court last year and then reinstated after the prosecution appealed, and he is now on trial on some remaining counts in Iceland.</p>
        <p>James Lansill, a senior managing director at the Corcoran Sunshine Marketing Group, which is selling apartments at 50 Gramercy Park North, said that all but two of the 23 units in the building, a co-op with less restrictive condominium rules, had been sold. The sales prices averaged more than $2,600 a square foot, he said, pushing up market values for ''every single neighbor on Gramercy Park.''</p>
        <p>'Popcorn Ceilings' Halt Construction</p>
        <p>THE pounding of hammers, the whine of screw guns and the scratching of scrapers ceased last week at the Sheffield on West 57th Street, as tenants still in the building won a skirmish in the war over its conversion into a luxury condominium.</p>
        <p>What stopped construction, at least for a while, was not the ongoing harassment case brought by the owners against a tenant leader, or the wrangling over the rights of tenants during condo conversions, but the discovery of asbestos by city inspectors in ''popcorn ceilings,'' the rough material troweled or sprayed on concrete ceiling slabs when the project was put up in the late 1970s.</p>
        <p>The findings vindicated tenants who had complained about hazards during renovations in the 48-story building with 853 apartments. Susanne Jansson, a tenant who has lived there for decades, raised concerns about asbestos after reviewing the records of permits filed by the developers, a group led by Kent M. Swig. The tenants did their own tests and found asbestos in five samples.</p>
        <p>At first, nothing was done. A state judge refused to issue an injunction stopping construction. The city's Department of Environmental Protection did tests, and for a time could not confirm the findings. The developer, which had done repeated tests of its own, questioned the integrity of the tenants' tests.</p>
        <p>But then the facts changed. Prodded by tenants and City Councilwoman Gale Brewer, city environmental officials sent inspectors back once more to test locations identified by the tenants, accompanied by the tenant asbestos consultant, Evan Browne. Ian Michaels, a spokesman for the city's Department of Environmental Protection, said that this time, 7 of the 12 ceiling samples tested positive for significant amounts of asbestos, on 5 floors.</p>
        <p>Asbestos, a substance that can cause cancer or lung disease if inhaled, was, according to the industry, last in use in most construction materials in 1978, the year that the Sheffield was completed.</p>
        <p>It was unclear why the asbestos turned up in some samples and not others. Mr. Browne, a division manager at JLC Environmental Consultants, said it was possible the mortar had not been mixed completely so that tiny samples used in testing might have missed the asbestos. Mr. Swig said it was possible that only a few bags of asbestos-containing materials had found their way to the project.</p>
        <p>Regular construction at the Sheffield stopped early last week, as the developers began a cleanup of the entire site by a licensed asbestos contractor under a plan approved by the city. Mr. Swig said construction would resume floor by floor as the cleanup was completed, on two or three floors each day. He said that the air in the building would be monitored regularly throughout the construction.</p>
        <p>The popcorn finish has been removed from about two-thirds of the building, Mr. Swig said, and he expects the remainder to be taken out as well. ''We tested over 180 samples, and all tested negative,'' he said. ''Now we are erring on the side of caution. We are cleaning from the bottom of the building up, every single surface in the building whether it has asbestos or not.''</p>
        <p>Another Closing, Another Show</p>
        <p>BUY or rent? Sell or rent? Sometimes these are difficult decisions to make, requiring spreadsheets, projections and complex calculations. At 409 East 58th Street, an intimate red-brick town house near First Avenue, next to a towering 47-story apartment complex, the decision was easy.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, Simon H. Forgette, a Seattle personal injury lawyer whose hobby is buying and restoring old buildings in Manhattan, where he maintains an apartment, paid just over $2.9 million for the three-story house. He brought in an architect, Joseph A. Cornacchia, and a contractor, Dayne Christian, to turn the building, which had been divided into apartments, back into a single-family house with traditional features but the latest appliances.</p>
        <p>''We really just love turning them back to the way they were or would have been,'' Mr. Forgette said, ''using as much period detail as possible, and a floor plan not based on the use of coal.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Forgette's plan was to rent out the house, and as the project was nearing completion last year, Beth Roberts, a broker with Prudential Douglas Elliman, listed it for lease at $18,500 a month.</p>
        <p>Ilan Bracha, another Elliman broker, brought in Yossi Zaga, an Israeli-born California T-shirt millionaire, to rent it. But Mr. Zaga, an owner of the P and Y T-Shirt Company and its subsidiary, American Printworks, a silk-screening plant with 140 employees in Vernon, Calif., just south of Los Angeles, had another idea.</p>
        <p>Instead of renting, he asked Mr. Forgette to name a price. With the prices of town houses soaring, the property was appraised at $5.8 million. Mr. Forgette took the bait, named a price and earlier this month the house sold for $6.5 million, 8 percent above the appraised value.</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Forgette pocketed a nice profit, he said he still felt dissatisfied. There was no time for the team to sit around and admire what they had created together.</p>
        <p>So last week Mr. Forgette was back in New York for another real estate closing, one of several new Manhattan ventures.</p>
        <p>He said he had paid more than $5 million for an 18-foot-wide town house at 217 East 61st Street, which was purchased in 1960 by Montgomery Clift, the star of ''From Here to Eternity'' and ''A Place in the Sun.'' The house has changed little since it was sold by Clift's estate after his death in 1966. Mr. Forgette said he planned to preserve Clift's bar, gin stains and all.</p>
        <p>BIG DEAL E-mail: bigdeal@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: bigdeal@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
