<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Warriors Lead Mavericks but Cling to Underdog Status</title>
    <meta content="29mavs" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/sports/basketball/29mavs.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843915"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Dallas Mavericks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Golden State Warriors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Dallas Mavericks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Basketball Assn</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Nelson, Don</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E0DE133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="812" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Warriors Lead Mavericks but Cling to Underdog Status</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Warriors Lead Mavericks but Cling to Underdog Status</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <dateline>OAKLAND, Calif., April 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Don Nelson conducted his off-day interview Saturday perched comfortably on a stool, with his dog resting quietly at his feet. The placid pooch was rescued from the pound in Maui. His name is Lucky.</p>
        <p>On practice days, Lucky has the full run of the Golden State Warriors' practice court, which at the moment seems about right. The Warriors, who slipped into the playoffs with a just-happy-to-be-here smile, are running wild and unchecked through the psyche of the Dallas Mavericks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Golden State is two victories from eliminating the Mavericks, who had the N.B.A.’s best record. Yet Warriors coach Don Nelson insists his team has been lucky.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Don Nelson conducted his off-day interview Saturday perched comfortably on a stool, with his dog resting quietly at his feet. The placid pooch was rescued from the pound in Maui. His name is Lucky.</p>
        <p>On practice days, Lucky has the full run of the Golden State Warriors' practice court, which at the moment seems about right. The Warriors, who slipped into the playoffs with a just-happy-to-be-here smile, are running wild and unchecked through the psyche of the Dallas Mavericks.</p>
        <p>On a raucous, ear-splitting Friday night at Oracle Arena, the Warriors stunned the Mavericks with a 109-91 rout and seized a 2-1 advantage in the best-of-seven Western Conference series.</p>
        <p>Golden State, which did not clinch a playoff berth until the final night of the season, is two victories from eliminating the Mavericks, who had the N.B.A.'s best record, 67-15.</p>
        <p>Lucky? Nelson insists that is all his team is.</p>
        <p>''We're not the best team in this series,'' Nelson said, still clinging to the underdog mantra. ''We know that, you guys know that. For us to have a chance, we've got to play over our heads. And we did that last night.''</p>
        <p>They did so much more. In their first home playoff game in 13 years, the Warriors gave credence to the slogan printed on 20,000 yellow T-shirts that filled the arena: ''We believe.'' They made the Mavericks look nervous and disjointed. They made Nelson look falsely modest.</p>
        <p>''It's true, it's true. Would I lie to you?'' Nelson said with a straight face.</p>
        <p>Golden State's performance suggested that he might. Baron Davis, the swaggering point guard, scored 24 points. Jason Richardson, one of the longest-tenured (and thus longest-suffering) Warriors, had 30 points. Golden State shot 52 percent through three quarters, held Dallas to 38.8 percent in the game and stifled Dirk Nowitzki, the presumed favorite for most valuable player.</p>
        <p>Nowitzki had 20 points, 4 after halftime, and looked ordinary. There could be no more ominous sign for the Mavericks and their championship aspirations. In their drive to the N.B.A. finals last year, the Mavericks dispatched with the well-worn cliché about a ''soft'' personality. They are on the verge of making it relevant again.</p>
        <p>Dallas has lost six of its past seven playoff games, including the last four in the 2006 finals. Miami, which beat Dallas for the championship, is down by 3-0 to Chicago and appears headed for a quick exit. The Mavericks, if they cannot solve the Warriors' maddening brand of small ball in Sunday's Game 4, could be next.</p>
        <p>Coach Avery Johnson has refashioned the Mavericks as a defensive team, but they let the Warriors drive at will and score 52 points in the paint. Dallas has thrived on crisp passing and patience but is shooting .407 in the series. The Mavericks are being dismantled by a team that won 42 games in the regular season.</p>
        <p>''We just didn't have the passion and the fire and the intensity and the physicality to win this game,'' Johnson said Friday. ''It's hard to explain at this point in the season. But we got to consistently get our swagger back, and we better get it quickly.''</p>
        <p>Only two teams seeded No. 1 have lost in the first round since the N.B.A. adopted its current playoff format in 1984: Miami (to the Knicks) in 1999 and Seattle (to Denver) in 1994.</p>
        <p>The Warriors could still be regarded as long shots, except that they have beaten Dallas in six of their past seven games. Nelson, the N.B.A.'s master of unconventionality, has confounded Dallas, his former team, and Johnson, his former assistant.</p>
        <p>Golden State started three guards and two small forwards -- with the 6-foot-9 Al Harrington at center -- for Games 1 and 2. Johnson countered by shifting Nowitzki to center to start Game 1, and it backfired in a 97-85 loss.</p>
        <p>For Game 2, Johnson went back to his usual lineup, with Erick Dampier at center, and the Mavericks -- aided in part by the ejections of Davis and Stephen Jackson -- took a 112-99 victory.</p>
        <p>Nelson struck again in Game 3, however, starting the 6-11 Andris Biedrins instead of the slumping Harrington. The Warriors raced to an 11-point lead in the first quarter.</p>
        <p>The Mavericks looked confused and maybe a little tight, though that was not a description Johnson wanted to hear.</p>
        <p>''Why should a team that's been in seven playoff series together, been to the Western Conference semifinals, won some big games last year in the playoffs, been to the finals, why should we be tight?'' Johnson said Saturday.</p>
        <p>His voice was, well, taut -- at least compared with the carefree expressions found in the Warriors' gym.</p>
        <p>''We just want to stay humble and win the series before we start talking crazy,'' Jackson said.</p>
        <p>The silver ink on his shoes suggested something else: ''Shock Da World.'' Jackson scrawled those words before the series started. Some underdogs bark.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
