<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bad Drivers Who Got Bad Driver Retraining</title>
    <meta content="29colctCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/29colct.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843658"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drunken and Reckless Driving</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hirshey, Gerri</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drivers Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drivers Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drunken and Reckless Driving</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E4DB153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="858" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bad Drivers Who Got Bad Driver Retraining</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bad Drivers Who Got Bad Driver Retraining</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERRI HIRSHEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hirshey, Gerri</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gerri Hirshey column on recidivism rate among dangerous and aggressive drivers in Connecticut who are required to take retraining course; suggests listening to gospel-mix CDs while driving; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVERY driver on the state's busy roads can come up with candidates for a Mobile Moron hall of shame. My arch contenders include the woman who twice nudged my rear bumper during a long tie-up; she was busy applying mascara in her rearview mirror. Vying with her for top honors: the business type who floored his BMW past a school bus stopped on a narrow two-lane road with red lights flashing and children boarding. He was a trendsetting offender; a report in this newspaper in 2005 found that passing a stopped school bus with its lights flashing -- a $450 violation -- was on the rise in Connecticut.</p>
        <p>Certainly, the police can't be everywhere. But after the last close call, I resolved to find out just what the consequences are for the road bullies who have been caught repeatedly in moving violations. Not much, it turns out. The state's enforcement policy with dangerous and aggressive drivers can be described as a bumpy road at best. Since 1996, the Department of Motor Vehicles has had a retraining program for drivers caught in the act twice or more. It mandates retraining classes given by driving schools; failure to complete a course within 60 days results in license suspension.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Connecticut, it appears that there are not many consequences for the road bullies who have been caught repeatedly in moving violations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVERY driver on the state's busy roads can come up with candidates for a Mobile Moron hall of shame. My arch contenders include the woman who twice nudged my rear bumper during a long tie-up; she was busy applying mascara in her rearview mirror. Vying with her for top honors: the business type who floored his BMW past a school bus stopped on a narrow two-lane road with red lights flashing and children boarding. He was a trendsetting offender; a report in this newspaper in 2005 found that passing a stopped school bus with its lights flashing -- a $450 violation -- was on the rise in Connecticut.</p>
        <p>Certainly, the police can't be everywhere. But after the last close call, I resolved to find out just what the consequences are for the road bullies who have been caught repeatedly in moving violations. Not much, it turns out. The state's enforcement policy with dangerous and aggressive drivers can be described as a bumpy road at best. Since 1996, the Department of Motor Vehicles has had a retraining program for drivers caught in the act twice or more. It mandates retraining classes given by driving schools; failure to complete a course within 60 days results in license suspension.</p>
        <p>The task of reforming these offenders was granted to two private vendors by the motor vehicle commissioner at the time, Michael Kozlowski, on a no-bid, exclusive and perpetual basis. One was the National Safety Council, which operates out of Syracuse, N.Y., and has no physical presence in the state. The other does business as the Driving School Association of Connecticut and is run by Jack P. Sousa, a friend of former Gov. John G. Rowland's.</p>
        <p>A July 2004 report by the State Office of Legislative Research provoked a public outcry when it revealed that the retraining program was an ineffective wreck on the highway. The report laid bare a scantily monitored operation wherein driving schools grossed $5.4 million in fees from 2000 to 2003 ($60 per driver, with $10 going to the Department of Motor Vehicles). Auditors tracked a series of shifting addresses and principals for the Driving School Association of America, which was not registered as a business with the secretary of state.</p>
        <p>The D.M.V. itself was unable to account for the fees it had collected. And for the 77,200 offending drivers who took the course there was a dismal recidivism rate of 41 percent and higher. Seventeen percent had to take the course four times. Some admitted to sleeping through it. State Senator Bill Finch, a Democrat from Bridgeport, pronounced the classes ''a joke, an absolute joke.''</p>
        <p>In the nearly three years since that report, have there been changes? According to a D.M.V. spokesman, William Seymour, a new, retooled system began operation in February. Over all, he says, ''the D.M.V. has instituted more regulatory oversight,'' including on-site inspections, audits and unannounced visits to private vendors giving the classes. There are now four vendors, selected by competitive bids. Mr. Sousa's organization is still among them.</p>
        <p>Will the new system work any better? The D.M.V. says it will begin collecting data from those classes ''in an attempt to determine causes for recidivism.'' That rate, last measured two years ago, is still about 40 percent. And driver retraining remains quite profitable here; between 2003 and this past March, 97,462 violators have taken the classes, forking over more than $5.8 million in total fees in order to stay on the roads and avoid license suspension.</p>
        <p>Bottom line: The road bullies are still out there. And through my windshield, they appear largely unchecked and unrepentant. How best to cope? Short of paying to learn evasive tactics at the Skip Barber Racing School, I pass on a calming, holistic antidote to the debilitating toxins of victim's road outrage. I discovered it by accident during a hideous siege on I-95.</p>
        <p>To counter the honking, I slipped one of my gospel-mix CDs into the car player. I'm not a churchgoer but I am a connoisseur of classic gospel shouters: Mahalia Jackson, the Blind Boys of Alabama, the Clara Ward Singers, Sam Cooke with the Soul Stirrers. As my shoulders relaxed and even the children stopped bickering, I felt the soothing effect of music first sung to cope with plantation savageries far worse than a tailgating S.U.V. Better still, the beat is lively enough to keep the most stressed commuter awake, alert and defensive.</p>
        <p>Now I keep those CDs close at hand, and pop them in during prime times for stupid drivers: the eternal road work on Route 7, the northbound Merritt anytime after 3 p.m., jammed schoolyard pickups. The song rotation is geared to overcoming gridlock, spiritual and four-lane: ''Twelve Gates Into the City,'' ''How I Got Over,'' ''This Too Shall Pass'' and ''Let Me Go Home.''</p>
        <p>I would like to have faith in the redemptive powers of the D.M.V.'s well-intentioned improvements. But I wonder if the retraining vendors might also try a Hail Mary pass and hand out uplifting CDs on the way out. Even the most habitual vehicular sinner would be hard put to pass a school bus with the magnificent Mahalia singing ''Impatient Heart.''</p>
        <p>E-mail: conn@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: conn@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
