<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bluefish Hoping to Draw More Fans This Season</title>
    <meta content="29mainctCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/29mainct.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843660"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="COMMERCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minor Leagues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bridgeport (Conn)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bridgeport Bluefish (Minor League Team)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moseley, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minor Leagues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Bridgeport (Conn)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Bridgeport Bluefish</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E4DB153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="907" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bluefish Hoping to Draw More Fans This Season</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bluefish Hoping to Draw More Fans This Season</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT MOSELEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Moseley, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>BRIDGEPORT</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Bridgeport Bluefish, Atlantic League baseball team in Bridgeport, Conn, which is hoping to attract more fans as it celebrates its 10th anniversary; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE'S new energy emanating from the Ballpark at Harbor Yard this spring as the Bridgeport Bluefish prepare for their home opener against the York Revolution on May 4. The energy is being generated by a new roster, a new general manager and a new manager -- one with plenty of name recognition. But it's also born from a sense of financial urgency.</p>
        <p>The Bluefish, one of the original members of the Atlantic League, which is celebrating its 10th anniversary this season, have yet to turn a profit. It may not be a sink-or-swim year, said the team's chief executive, Mary-Jane Foster, but the Bluefish clearly need more fans to embrace their marketing slogan, ''Get hooked on the Blues.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>BRIDGEPORT.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE'S new energy emanating from the Ballpark at Harbor Yard this spring as the Bridgeport Bluefish prepare for their home opener against the York Revolution on May 4. The energy is being generated by a new roster, a new general manager and a new manager -- one with plenty of name recognition. But it's also born from a sense of financial urgency.</p>
        <p>The Bluefish, one of the original members of the Atlantic League, which is celebrating its 10th anniversary this season, have yet to turn a profit. It may not be a sink-or-swim year, said the team's chief executive, Mary-Jane Foster, but the Bluefish clearly need more fans to embrace their marketing slogan, ''Get hooked on the Blues.''</p>
        <p>''If it were a year in which we lose a great deal of money, we'd really have to take a hard look at whether baseball can be successful here,'' Ms. Foster, 56, said. ''But it's not going to be that type of year. I think we're going to break even.''</p>
        <p>One team official said twice as many tickets had been sold this preseason as last year, and the team has a marquee name in the dugout with Manager Tommy John, who won 288 games in a 26-year major-league career with six teams, including the Yankees. Besides having a surgical procedure named after him, Mr. John, 63, may be best known for having the most victories of any retired major-league pitcher not in the Hall of Fame.</p>
        <p>Mr. John takes over from Dave LaPoint, 47, another former major-league pitcher, who guided the Bluefish to a 75-49 record last year, best in the Atlantic League. After the team lost to Lancaster in the playoffs, Mr. LaPoint's contract was not renewed, and he was hired by the Long Island Ducks, also of the Atlantic League. Ms. Foster says she was looking for ''sizzle and substance'' in a new manager when Bobby Valentine, the former Mets manager and a native of Stamford, e-mailed one of her investors and suggested Mr. John.</p>
        <p>''Tommy's got a wonderful personality,'' Ms. Foster said.</p>
        <p>''She added: ''He believes the game is at least as much about the fans as it is the baseball. It's a perfect match; we're thrilled.''</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. John says he is excited about coming to Bridgeport.</p>
        <p>''Is it about matching wits with the other managers?'' he asked. ''I don't think it ever is, because the players play and the best managers I've seen stay out of the way of the players. If the players can't play, you can't manage.''</p>
        <p>Last year's team could play, but it was largely disbanded anyway. The Atlantic League is independent, with no major-league affiliations, and it encourages its eight teams to change at least 50 percent of their rosters each year so fans don't see the same recycled ballplayers.</p>
        <p>The new general manager of the Bluefish, Bill Larsen, 62, has nearly 20 years of experience running minor-league teams in Nashville and suburban Chicago. He says he is particularly proud of the success he had in Illinois, since his teams were profitable despite having to compete for fans with the Cubs and the White Sox. That situation is not unlike the one in Bridgeport, where the Bluefish vie for the baseball dollar with the Yankees, the Mets and even the Red Sox, as well as minor-league affiliates in New Britain (the Twins) and Norwich (the Giants) and the independent New Haven County Cutters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Larsen has his work cut out for him. In 1998, their first season, the Bluefish led the league in attendance at the 5,500-seat Harbor Yard, but the average attendance has steadily slipped since 2002, when they drew 3,853 per game. Last season it fell to 2,971.</p>
        <p>Ms. Foster, a co-founder and co-owner of the Bluefish with her husband, Jack E. McGregor, would not say how much the team is losing. But Mr. McGregor, 72, said the Bluefish lost about $500,000 last year.</p>
        <p>But he and Tom Kushner, 42, of New Canaan, who invested in the team a year ago, said the current owners were confident that the team would be as successful in the ledger books as it has been on the field.</p>
        <p>''This is as confident as I've been for 10 years,'' Mr. McGregor said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kushner urged patience. ''These things take time,'' he said. ''Losing money is never fun, but I think we have the right people in place, so there's light at the end of the tunnel.''</p>
        <p>He says there's a sense of urgency to do ''trench-warfare marketing'' throughout the state, especially in lower Fairfield County and New Haven County.</p>
        <p>For fans, the new season holds promise.</p>
        <p>''I'm chomping at the bit,'' said Sheryl Rosen, 43, of Bridgeport, president of the Bluefish booster club. ''I can't wait to meet Tommy John.''</p>
        <p>Ray Wargo, 69, of Bridgeport, said he, too, was excited by the arrival of Mr. John. But Mr. Wargo said traffic had become a problem, especially after games when the Arena at Harbor Yards next door was also booked. ''If people get aggravated too often, they're not going to come,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rosen and Mr. Wargo said they planned to attend more than 30 games this season.</p>
        <p>''It amazes me that they don't sell out every game, because it's so close, so convenient, and it's good baseball,'' Ms. Rosen said. ''I'm worried about how much longer we're going to have the team because of the financial situation.''</p>
        <p>COMMERCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
