<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Muslim Students, a Drive to Deem Holy Days as Holidays</title>
    <meta content="29holi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/thecity/29holi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843786"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK UP CLOSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Id Al-Fitr (Muslim Observance)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Id Al-Adha (Muslim Observance)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Coalition for Muslim School Holidays</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Education Department (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brady, Emily</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E4DA123EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="411" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Muslim Students, a Drive to Deem Holy Days as Holidays</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Muslim Students, a Drive to Deem Holy Days as Holidays</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EMILY BRADY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brady, Emily</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Coalition for Muslim School Holidays is urging New York City Department of Education to include two Muslim holidays, Id al-Adha and Id al-Fitr on city's public school calendar; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE movement began last year when statewide tests for elementary school children were administered on Jan. 10, coinciding with Id al-Adha, a holiday that commemorates the story of Abraham and is a time of prayer and feast for the city's Muslim community.</p>
        <p>Muslim parents were dismayed that they were forced to choose between supporting their children's education and observing one of their holiest days as a family.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An organization is urging the city’s education department to include two Muslim holidays, Id al-Adha and Id al-Fitr, the end of the monthlong Ramadan fast, on the city’s public school calendar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE movement began last year when statewide tests for elementary school children were administered on Jan. 10, coinciding with Id al-Adha, a holiday that commemorates the story of Abraham and is a time of prayer and feast for the city's Muslim community.</p>
        <p>Muslim parents were dismayed that they were forced to choose between supporting their children's education and observing one of their holiest days as a family.</p>
        <p>''We couldn't go to prayer with our children,'' said Bakary Camara, a Gambian father of five who lives in Highbridge in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>Mr. Camara responded to the situation by joining the Coalition for Muslim School Holidays, a group made up of more than 50 labor, community and religious organizations that was formed last April. The organization is urging the city Department of Education to include two Muslim holidays, Id al-Adha and Id al-Fitr, the end of the monthlong Ramadan fast, on the city's public school calendar.</p>
        <p>Exactly how many of the city's students are affected by the situation is unknown. The coalition estimates that 12 percent of public school students are Muslim. The Department of Education does not keep statistics based on students' religion.</p>
        <p>Currently, students who miss a day of school for religious observance receive an excused absence. But despite the efforts of the coalition, which in mid-March released a report setting out their case and two weeks later held a public forum at a West Bronx school attended by about 350 people, the Education Department seems unlikely to change its stance any time soon.</p>
        <p>''We are not adding any more holidays to the school calendar,'' said Dina Paul Parks, a department spokeswoman, adding that the schedule of religious holidays hasn't been altered since the early 1960s.</p>
        <p>But an excused absence isn't good enough for coalition members, or for State Senator John Sabini of Queens and Bronx Assemblyman Ruben Diaz Jr. Although the Education Department turned down the coalition's request last May, both legislators have introduced bills within the past two months to make the holidays official for the city's public schools.</p>
        <p>''There's a lot of parents who take attendance very seriously and they don't want that blemish,'' said Mr. Diaz, whose district includes Soundview, where the Muslim immigrant Amadou Diallo was killed in 1999.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sabini, who represents many South Asian Muslims in Jackson Heights, said: ''Excused absences just alienate students from the rest of their classmates. We don't have excused absences for Christmas or Yom Kippur.''</p>
        <p>EMILY BRADY</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK UP CLOSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
