<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: The Ethicist; Teacher, Jeweler</title>
    <meta content="29wwln--ethicist.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/magazine/29wwlnethicist.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843591"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="The Ethicist"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/The Ethicist</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jewels and Jewelry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jewels and Jewelry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E5DC143EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="554" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: The Ethicist; Teacher, Jeweler</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Teacher, Jeweler</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Randy Cohen</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Randy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A fellow teacher at my elementary school sells jewelry. A student came to deliver $80 worth of merchandise to a woman with whom I share a classroom. She was not in, so I said he could leave the package on her chair. The next day she inquired about her jewelry: she never received it. Someone stole it from our classroom. Who is responsible for the $80?</p>
        <p>Name Withheld, Connecticut</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dilemmas involving thieves and scabs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A fellow teacher at my elementary school sells jewelry. A student came to deliver $80 worth of merchandise to a woman with whom I share a classroom. She was not in, so I said he could leave the package on her chair. The next day she inquired about her jewelry: she never received it. Someone stole it from our classroom. Who is responsible for the $80?</p>
        <p>Name Withheld, Connecticut</p>
        <p>Everyone. Well, not me. And not the nonrecipient. But everyone else who played a part in this sad saga shares responsibility, although not equally.</p>
        <p>The jewelry-selling teacher is most culpable: her tiny minion never actually delivered the jewelry to her customer. Also questionable, why was she running a private business during school hours? Why did she enlist students as her underlings? Assuming she has been fired for abusing her office, it seems heartless to tax her for the $80.</p>
        <p>The delivery kid, too, acted ever so slightly imperfectly. He got the package near, but not to, the customer, exposing it to theft. This is why many delivery companies have recipients sign for a package, and few hire 11-year-olds. The jewelry dealer could, I suppose, demand reimbursement from the child. Fagin would.</p>
        <p>The child could then seek restitution from you. It was reasonable of him to heed the advice of an adult authority figure, advice that proved imprudent.</p>
        <p>Or the thief could have a change of heart and return the swag. I'm going to leave the room now, and when I come back I want to see those gewgaws on my desk.</p>
        <p>Update: There was no theft. It was</p>
        <p>all a merry mix-up. The teacher sells jewelry and candles. The customer ordered both, but the package contained only the latter. The merchant-teacher insisted that the jewelry must have been stolen, but when she got home she found it in her laundry basket. A curious storage system, but inventory control is beyond my purview.</p>
        <p>At a job interview, I learned that the company was seeking replacements for striking workers. I have nearly always sided with workers on strike. We all deserve decent wages and working conditions. Should I accept the job if it is offered?</p>
        <p>D.R., Minneapolis</p>
        <p>You should not casually take the job; your own values forbid it. To scab -- let's call it by its ugly but apt name -- is to undermine people's efforts to join together to better their lot. It is a perilous thing to strike; few employees do so lightly. I would be loath to put my self-interest above that of workers who feel driven to such an extreme step.</p>
        <p>Not every strike is justified, but when lacking information that supports an employer's case, my impulse is to defer to the employees. This is as much a matter of ideology and upbringing as ethics, but sometimes we are compelled to make a quick decision based on not enough knowledge. That is when we refer to our fundamental assumptions about the world, a reasonable place to begin but not to linger: the obligation remains to make informed choices. Fortunately, you have time to do so.</p>
        <p>Update: D.R. was offered the job and accepted it without knowing much about the labor conflict. Before he could learn more and perhaps reconsider, the strike was settled and the offer rescinded. He has since found another job.</p>
        <p>The Ethicist</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
