<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Bid to Keep Young Arms Healthy</title>
    <meta content="29RpitchNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843699"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Little League</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Charkes, Juli Steadman</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Little League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05EFD8153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="997" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Bid to Keep Young Arms Healthy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULI S. CHARKES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Charkes, Juli Steadman</byline>
      <dateline>ARDSLEY, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Little League managers and coaches across New York metropolitan area explain to parents policies and regulations, including new mandate that limits number of pitches thrown and forces pitchers to rest between appearances; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE managers and coaches for Ardsley's Little League teams squeezed into the child-size seats in the Concord Road Elementary School cafeteria late last month to go over the rules and regulations for this season.</p>
        <p>Many of the safety procedures were familiar: catchers' masks need a throat guard; no parents on the field; baseball bats must be regulation size. But this policy was addressed for the first time: mandatory limits on the number of pitches.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE managers and coaches for Ardsley's Little League teams squeezed into the child-size seats in the Concord Road Elementary School cafeteria late last month to go over the rules and regulations for this season.</p>
        <p>Many of the safety procedures were familiar: catchers' masks need a throat guard; no parents on the field; baseball bats must be regulation size. But this policy was addressed for the first time: mandatory limits on the number of pitches.</p>
        <p>''This is as new to me as it is to all of you,'' Mark Weinstein, a Little League administrator and umpire in Westchester, told the crowd. ''I can't think of anything more boring than standing there and counting pitches. But what's at stake is the health and the arms of your children.''</p>
        <p>For the first time, Little League Baseball is requiring its divisions to limit the number of pitches thrown, depending on age, and to force pitchers to rest between appearances. The policy affects 6,200 baseball leagues worldwide (but not the 1,300 softball leagues in Little League).</p>
        <p>Under the program, players 10 and younger can throw 75 pitches; 11- and 12-year-olds are limited to 85; 13- to 16-year-olds can throw 95; and for those 17 and older, the limit is 105.</p>
        <p>The policy also stipulates how many days a pitcher must rest depending on the number of pitches thrown; for example, pitchers aged 7 to 16 who throw 21 to 40 pitches must rest at least one day, and throwing 61 or more pitches requires three days of rest. Pitch counts are slightly higher for older pitchers. (More details can be found on Little League's Web site, www.littleleague.org.)</p>
        <p>The idea, Little League administrators say, is to counter arm injuries from overuse that were once the domain of adult athletes but are increasingly showing up in children and adolescents.</p>
        <p>''We were seeing arm injuries in players as young as 15 and 16 that traditionally you wouldn't see until the mid-20s,'' said Stephen D. Keener, president and chief executive of Little League Baseball and Softball. ''We talked about the contributing factors, particularly at such a young age, and most of the medical experts felt the biggest culprit was the overuse of pitching arms.''</p>
        <p>To develop the pitch counts, Little League consulted the American Sports Medicine Institute in Birmingham, Ala., where Dr. James R. Andrews is a leader in so-called Tommy John surgery, named after the former major league pitcher. In the procedure, surgeons replace the damaged ulnar collateral ligament with another ligament in the arm.</p>
        <p>While the surgery has allowed scores of professional pitchers to resume their careers, the number of high school pitchers undergoing it has steadily risen in the last 12 years, said Glenn S. Fleisig, the institute's research director. From 1995 to 1998, Dr. Andrews performed the surgery on nine high school pitchers (out of 119 total procedures); from 1999 to 2002, 61 high school pitchers (out of 354); and from 2003 to 2006, 148 high school pitchers (out of 619).</p>
        <p>''You definitely see a lot more overuse injury and trauma in young patients nowadays,'' said Dr. Nicholas A. Bavaro, an orthopedic surgeon at hospitals in Westchester and Rockland Counties. ''Things such as elbow problems or torn ligaments -- they used to be fairly uncommon in adolescents and children.''</p>
        <p>Those involved in children's sports blame a modern-day phenomenon for the sharp increase: playing on several teams at once.</p>
        <p>''In the past 10 years or so, there's been an evolution in youth baseball where children who were once only playing on Little League teams are now playing on various travel teams and other elite teams at the same time,'' Mr. Keener said.</p>
        <p>That physical strain takes a toll on young bodies, Dr. Bavaro said.</p>
        <p>Sam Blumenthal, 14, from Dobbs Ferry, broke a bone in his elbow when he was 12, pitching in a game for Ardsley Little League, the only league he plays in, said his father, Dale Blumenthal. The injury did not require surgery but provided a sobering lesson, Mr. Blumenthal said.</p>
        <p>''Yes, I was surprised at how serious these injuries can be,'' he said. Sam continues to pitch, and his father welcomes the pitch count policy.</p>
        <p>John Doherty, a former pitcher for the Detroit Tigers who teaches baseball clinics throughout Westchester County, said, ''Pitching is not a natural movement.'' Avoiding injury, he said, is as much about proper form and mechanics as it is about the number of pitches. He also warned against allowing young pitchers to throw curveballs. ''We always teach the kids to throw the ball straight and to throw strikes, because then it's baseball,'' he said.</p>
        <p>A program was tested last year by 500 leagues, including teams in New Haven. ''I did have two leagues that tried out pitch counts in the survey last year, and the results were outstanding,'' said David Ruotolo, a Little League administrator in Connecticut.</p>
        <p>Some leagues have expanded on the policy. ''I've had a couple of leagues that are limiting the number of innings a child can pitch in one game, in addition to the number of pitches,'' said Joan Bosinius, a Little League coordinator on Long Island.</p>
        <p>Westchester has 35 Little League chapters. Interviews with several coaches pointed to a common belief: while pitch counts are a step in the right direction, it is up to managers, coaches and parents to watch for signs of injury and fatigue.</p>
        <p>''I see what happens with some of these managers and parents,'' said Bill Dinaso, who coaches a Little League team in Ardsley and whose son, Dakota, 14, is a pitcher for it. ''It's push, push, push and throw, throw, throw. But with this pitch count, more kids will have to learn how to pitch now.''</p>
        <p>Tony Richardson, the director for Little League in New Jersey, which has 320 leagues, said making pitch counts mandatory was necessary to educate parents and managers.</p>
        <p>''In a year from now, we'll be asking ourselves why we didn't think of doing this all along,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
